<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:07:30[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>DXplain</title>
<id>10013985</id>
<revision>
<id>240898766</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-25T13:53:32Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Whpq</username>
<id>643450</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Health software</category>
<category>Medical informatics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>DXplain</b> is a <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/2368154.xml">
Clinical decision support system</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
 (CDSS) available through the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
 that assists <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/832314.xml">
clinic</link>ians by generating stratified <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/18507525.xml">
diagnoses</link> based on user input of patient signs and symptoms, laboratory results, and other clinical findings <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. <feeling wordnetid="100026192" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<temper wordnetid="107551052" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/1592807.xml">
Evidential</link></temper>
</state>
</feeling>
 support for each <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/915081.xml">
differential diagnosis</link> is presented, along with recommended follow-up that may be conducted by the clinician to arrive at a more definitive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/18507525.xml">
diagnosis</link>.  The system also serves as a clinician reference with a searchable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> of diseases and clinical manifestations.
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

Designed by the Laboratory of Computer Science at the <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/1149900.xml">
Massachusetts General Hospital</link></hospital>
, work on DXplain began in 1984 with a first version being released in 1986 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.  
DXplain contains a database with crude probabilities for over 4,900 clinical manifestations that are associated with over 2,200 unique diseases, yielding a total of over 230,000 unique finding-disease interconnections <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Educational tool </st>

<p>

Use of DXplain as a tool for medical consultation has been common to some institutions since it fills a gap, particularly for <link>
medical student</link>s in clinical rotations, that is not adequately covered by textbook literature <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. The system's large and accessible knowledge base combined with its ability to formulate diagnostic hypotheses have made it a popular education tool for US-based medical schools; by 2005, <b>DXplain</b> was supporting more than 33,189 total users <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Methodology </st>

<p>

DXplain generates ranked <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/915081.xml">
differential diagnoses</link> using a pseudo-probabilistic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> (<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.  Each clinical finding entered into DXplain is assessed by determining the importance of the finding and how strongly the finding supports a given diagnosis for each disease in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/239497.xml">
knowledge base</link>.  Using this criterion, DXplain generates ranked differential diagnoses with the most likely diseases yielding the lowest rank.  Using stored information regarding each disease’s prevalence and significance, the system differentiates between common and rare diseases.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Accuracy </st>

<p>

Analysis of accuracy has shown promise in DXplain and similar clinical decision support systems.  In a preliminary trial investigation of 46 benchmark cases with a variety of diseases and clinical manifestations, the ranked differential diagnoses generated by DXplain were shown to be in alignment with a panel of five board-certified physicians <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>.  In another study investigating how well decision support systems work at responding to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/4393.xml">
bioterrorism</link> event, an evaluation of 103 consecutive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/205264.xml">
internal medicine</link> cases showed that Dxplain correctly identified the diagnosis in 73% of cases, with the correct diagnosis averaging a rank of 10.7 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Clinical usage </st>

<p>

Despite its usage in clinician training, similar to other clinical decision support systems, DXplain has not expanded beyond the research laboratory or medical training setting, due in part to a lack of support by <link>
clinicians</link> in real-world settings <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Barnett GO, Cimino JJ, Hupp JA, Hoffer EP. DXplain. An evolving diagnostic decision-support system. JAMA. 1987 Jul 3;258(1):67-74.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lcs.mgh.harvard.edu/projects/dxplain.html">
MGH Laboratory of Computer Science – projects – dxplain,” Laboratory of Computer Science, Massachusetts General Hospital. 2007. </weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
London S. DXplain: a Web-based diagnostic decision support system for medical students. Med Ref Serv Q. 1998 Summer;17(2):17-28.</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://groups.csail.mit.edu/medg/courses/6872/2004/DXp%20HST%20Lec%2005.pdf">
Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (CSAIL), MIT. 2005.</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="5">
Detmer WM, Shortliffe EH. Using the Internet to Improve Knowledge Diffusion in Medicine. Communications of the Association of Computing Machinery. 1997; 40(8):101-108. 1997.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Feldman MJ, Barnett GO. An approach to evaluating the accuracy of DXplain. Comput Methods Programs Biomed. 1991 Aug;35(4):261-6.</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/EID/vol10no1/03-0243.htm">
Bravata DM, Sundaram V, McDonald KM, Smith WM, Szeto H, Schleinitz MD, et al. Detection and diagnostic decision support systems for bioterrorism response. Emerg Infect Dis. 2004 Jan. </weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
Coiera E. Guide to Health Informatics: 2nd Edition. Arnold, 2003; 332-343.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lcs.mgh.harvard.edu/projects/dxplain.html">
DXplain at the MGH Lab of Computer Science</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
