<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:18:26[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108058098">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>Cognio</title>
<id>10439522</id>
<revision>
<id>229936204</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-05T07:09:27Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Wilsbadkarma</username>
<id>2426806</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Montgomery County, Maryland</category>
<category>Companies based in Maryland</category>
<category>Radio-frequency identification</category>
<category>Networking companies of the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Cognio, Inc.</b> builds RF (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/42852.xml">
radio frequency</link>) spectrum analysis solutions that find and solve wi-fi channel interference problems on wireless networks and in wireless applications, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/169320.xml">
RFID</link>. Designed for the frequency bands in common use today (802.11a/b/g and RFID), Cognio’s product, Spectrum Expert, helps network engineers analyze, diagnose, and locate sources of 802.11 interference within the enterprise's RF environment. Cognio was acquired by Cisco Systems in 2007.
<sec>
<st>
 Company overview </st>

<p>

Cognio has been shipping the Spectrum Expert <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/63973.xml">
WiFi</link> management software since the spring of 2005 and has built a base of over a thousand customers.  Cognio sells its wireless Internet connectivity solutions directly, through resellers, and through OEM partnerships with companies such as AirMagnet, Fluke Networks, and WildPackets.  
Cognio is headquartered in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/145050.xml">
Germantown</link></village>
, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/18858.xml">
Maryland</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 (near <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/108956.xml">
Washington, D.C.</link></village>
), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
USA</link>, and is privately held with investments from North Bridge Venture Partners, ABS Ventures, and Avansis Ventures. The company currently has 35 employees.
Cognio has been granted 12 patents, and has submitted 172 patent applications for its RF analysis technology.
Cognio’s Market: Spectrum Analysis Software for Enterprise Communications
Cognio sells its WiFi spectrum analyzer products primarily to network engineers and field service engineers responsible for security for wireless networks or applications that run on wireless networks. These engineers need to be able to troubleshoot an RF interference pattern or problems that hamper wireless communications.</p>
<p>

In a wireless network, devices communicate by transmitting radio waves. Each type of network operates in a specific range of radio wave frequencies. This range is called a spectrum.</p>
<p>

<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/14739.xml">
IEEE 802.11</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 wireless networks operate in an unlicensed spectrum. That is, their frequency bands are not licensed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/41145.xml">
FCC</link> or other organizations exclusively for 802.11 traffic. Instead, the spectrum is shared with many other types of devices, such as cordless phones and <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/3742.xml">
Bluetooth</link></system_of_measurement>
</machine>
</device>
</standard>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 devices. Because it was designed for use in a shared spectrum, 802.11 technology checks to see if the airwaves are sufficiently clear before transmitting messages. This means that if the airwaves are crowded with other radio signals, an 802.11 device will shut itself out of communications. </p>
<p>

There are many possible sources of RF interference for 802.11 networks. First, other nearby 802.11 WLANs may cause wi-fi channel interference. Second, other communication devices that share the same spectrum—devices such as Bluetooth headsets—may cause 802.11 interference. Third, interference may originate from the radio energy given off by other electronic devices, such as video cameras and microwave ovens. </p>
<p>

RF interference may result in slow network performance and dropped connections. Devices such as RF jammers and certain types of video cameras can prevent WLANs from communicating at all.</p>
<p>

Most WLAN management tools do not measure or analyze RF interference problems. They monitor only Layers 2 and up in the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/22747.xml">
OSI model</link></system_of_measurement>
</advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
. They might report that performance is slow, but they are typically unable to report that slow performance is caused by WiFi interference. Consequently, WLAN network engineers detecting poor connectivity in wireless internet areas are often left without any WiFi tools for analyzing RF interference, for measuring the effects of RF interference on specific channels of a network, and for identifying the type and location of sources of interference.</p>
<p>

Network engineers could make use of scientific spectrum analyzers. But these tools, which were designed for use in laboratory settings, are often too large and heavy for use by network administrators moving throughout a building during the course of a day. Also, many of these WiFi spectrum analyzers cost tens of thousands of dollars.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Wireless spectrum analyzer products </st>

<p>

Cognio currently sells two products: Spectrum Expert for WiFi and Spectrum Expert for RFID. (In its product naming, Cognio omits the hyphen that normally appears in the word Wi-Fi.)</p>
<p>

Cognio Spectrum Expert for WiFi enables network engineers to identify and locate sources of Wi-Fi channel interference on 802.11 networks. The product consists of a PC CardBus card that includes a built-in antenna and hardware designed to rapidly analyze RF activity. Spectrum Expert for WiFi scans the radio spectrum used for 802.11b and 802.11g networks (2.4 to 2.5 GHz). It can also scan the spectrum used for 802.11a networks (4.9 GHz to 5.9 GHz).</p>
<p>

Cognio Spectrum Expert for RFID is similar to the WiFi product, except that it scans the radio spectrum used for RFID tags (851-870 MHz and 902-960 MHz).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Cognio spectrum expert for WiFi interference monitoring </st>

<p>

Cognio Spectrum Expert for WiFi is a PC-laptop-based solution for RF spectrum analysis. The product consists of a Windows application and a CardBus card that features a built-in antenna and Cognio’s patented RF analysis technology.</p>
<p>

Using Spectrum Expert for WiFi, network engineers can see a list of all the devices transmitting in a WLAN’s spectrum. Spectrum Expert’s bar graphs show how much Wi-Fi channel interference a specific device is causing on a specific channel of a WLAN.</p>
<p>

Once they identify an interfering device, network engineers can use Spectrum Expert’s Device Locator feature, which works like a sort of RF <equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/12984.xml">
Geiger counter</link></equipment>
, to track the signal strength and location of the device, so it can be removed, repositioned, or shielded.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Channels and partners </st>

<p>

Cognio sells its products primarily through OEMs and resellers. OEM partners include AirMagnet, Fluke Networks, and WildPackets. Resellers include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/51746.xml">
Cisco</link>, Advanced Telecom Systems, Cumulus Consulting Group, Elexo, Lumiad, Meritech, The PR Group, Psiber, Streakwave, Tessco, Test Tools Europe Ltd., and Unitronics. </p>
<p>

In addition, Cognio works with training partners to offer training on spectrum analysis for Wi-Fi networks. Cognio’s training partners are Security University and SpectroTech.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Partnership with Cisco </st>

<p>

On October 3, 2006, Cognio and Cisco announced a partnership Cisco Press Release (2006) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://newsroom.cisco.com/dlls/partners/news/2006/pr_prod_10-03.html">
http://newsroom.cisco.com/dlls/partners/news/2006/pr_prod_10-03.html</weblink> <it>Cisco Tackles Enterprise Radio Frequency Challenges</it>  to "...address a significant and growing issue facing pervasive enterprise deployments of Wi-Fi networks - radio frequency (RF) interference.”</p>
<p>

On February 26, 2007, Cisco launched a <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cisco.com/en/US/netsol/ns736/networking_solutions_package.html">
section</weblink> devoted to RF interference which features the Cognio Spectrum Expert solution.</p>
<p>

WiFi Management Software Customers Cognio has sold its wireless spectrum analyzer products to over 500 businesses. Customers include the Chicago Board of Trade, Christiana Care, FedEx, Honda, Microsoft, NetStar Telecommunications, Seven Eleven, Siemens, SkyPilot Networks, and the University of Richmond.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Financials </st>

<p>

Cognio, Inc. has been acquired by Cisco Systems, Inc.</p>
<p>

To learn more about the industry acclaimed Spectrum Expert Wi-Fi, please visit the Cisco Spectrum Expert Product page. </p>
<p>

If you are an existing Cognio customer and wish to contact Cisco to register your Spectrum Expert product, please visit the Cisco Spectrum Expert Registration page.</p>
<p>

Customers with active service contract with Cisco can open a support case by accessing the Cisco Technical Assistance Center website or by calling the TAC Hotline at 1 800 553 2447 (or visit  the worldwide contact list). </p>
<p>

For general information on Cisco products, services and ordering, please visit Cisco.com.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Management team </st>

<p>

Cognio’s management team consists of:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tom McPherson (CEO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Neil Diener (CTO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Elizabeth Hess (CFO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jeff White (Executive Vice President, Business Development)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gary Sugar (Founder and Vice President, Engineering)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

William Flanagan (Vice President, Marketing)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Greg Barone (Vice President, Sales)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


<p>


</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cognio.com/">
Company website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</company>
</article>
