<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:29:12[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<software  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106566077">
<web_site  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="106359193">
<header>
<title>Project Elliott</title>
<id>10912523</id>
<revision>
<id>242545819</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T18:02:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Defunct websites</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Software</name>
<parameters>
<frequently_updated>
yes</frequently_updated>
<genre>
Job Search, Internet</genre>
<operating_system>
Internet</operating_system>
<caption>
Project Elliott logo.</caption>
<released>
?</released>
<name>
Project Elliott</name>
<programming_language>
?</programming_language>
<language>
?</language>
<license>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/11592.xml">
Freeware</link></license>
</parameters>
</template>


Project Elliott was the code name for a Silicon Valley-based global start-up enterprise engaged in next generation web services.  Launched on April 17, 2007, www.ProjectElliott.com was a viral marketing website, whose intent was to create interest in a forthcoming new product within the domain of online job search.  The website contained information about an upcoming new product, the team of global engineering, marketing and design experts running the enterprise, viral videos, founders' blogs, and a beta test subscription program for users.<p>

Viral marketing refers to marketing techniques that use pre-existing social networks to produce increases in brand awareness, through self-replicating viral processes, analogous to the spread of pathological and computer viruses. It can often be word-of-mouth delivered and enhanced online; it can harness the network effect of the Internet and can be very useful in reaching a large number of people rapidly. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Mission </st>
<p>

For the job seeker, the mission of Project Elliott was to remove pain from job search by improving the way job seekers search, negotiate and secure jobs by utilizing the increased power of the internet and people.  For the employer, the mission was to improve the process of finding best-fit candidates.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The Team </st>
<p>

The Project Elliott team consisted of serial entrepreneurs with advanced degrees from Stanford, India Institute of Technology, University of Chicago, Carnegie Mellon, UC Berkeley, and UCLA.  The board of advisors included university researchers and scientists (Ph.D.s from Stanford), venture capitalists, patent attorney, and industry thought leaders.  Functionally, the team consisted of engineers from Silicon Valley and India with marketing and design professionals from the San Francisco Bay Area, the Midwest, and the East Coast of USA.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Availability </st>
<p>

Currently, Project Elliott is a defunct project.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Technology </st>
<p>

Machine learning, a proprietary algorithm and a convergence of other technologies were used to develop the product offering, thus transforming a manual job board paradigm into a dynamic enabler for job candidates and employers.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Timeline </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2006, August 27: The idea of a revolution in job search was born to the founder with the birth of his son, Elliott.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2007, April 17: www.ProjectElliott.com was launched.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2008    ?     : www.ProjectElliott.com is now defunct.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Viral marketing</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>












</sec>
</bdy>
</web_site>
</software>
</article>
