<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:35:17[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Effects on the environment in Czechoslovakia from Soviet influence during the Cold War</title>
<id>10978306</id>
<revision>
<id>219590978</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-16T00:03:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Victormj32</username>
<id>7316242</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Czechoslovakia</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>Wikify from April 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Effects_on_the_environment_in_Czechoslovakia_from_Soviet_influence_during_the_Cold_War&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(April 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<sec>
<st>
Background</st>
<p>

After <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
World War II</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
, the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/26779.xml">
Soviet Union</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 put in place <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/5375054.xml">
five-year plan</link>s in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/37403.xml">
East European</link> countries imitating their own five-year plans in order to recover from the war.  The Soviets believed that the economic policies that helped them recover would similarly help the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/37403.xml">
Eastern European</link> counties recoup.  Countries in the <politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/97477.xml">
Eastern Bloc</link></social_relation>
</politics>
 were instructed to build up the industries present in the Soviet Union – regardless of whether or not they had the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/21675.xml">
natural resource</link>s to support those industries – or to concentrate on developing pre-existing industries which could benefit the Soviet Union. In the case of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/5322.xml">
Czechoslovakia</link></country>
, the state was told to concentrate on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/1608478.xml">
heavy industry</link>.  This concentration on heavy industry depleted the country's natural resources at an extraordinarily fast rate and produced an excessive amount of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollution</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Effects</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollution</link> produced by heavy industry seriously degraded air quality.  The air contained high concentrations of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/50958.xml">
sulfur dioxide</link> because the energy production was largely based on combustion of fuel high in sulfur.  As a result, 50 percent of the forests were either dead or dying.  Cases of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/13629466.xml">
bronchitis</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/44905.xml">
asthma</link> in children almost doubled with the increase in the use of sulfur dioxide.  The water, too, was affected by the excessive pollution, both from industrial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/37401.xml">
fertilizer</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/158705.xml">
oil spill</link>s.  The lack of water <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/588001.xml">
waste treatment</link> meant that a large portion of the water was undrinkable for the population, and some of the water was so bad that it was even unusable by the industry.  Conditions were worst in Northern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/4345.xml">
Bohemia</link>, which was a part of the so-called ‘triangle of death’ that also included South-East <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/13058.xml">
East Germany</link></country>
 and South-West <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/22936.xml">
Poland</link></country>
, but the effects were also felt beyond the region in which the pollution originated.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/7969.xml">
Danube River</link> carried much of the pollution to other areas of the state and other countries, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/3263.xml">
acid rain</link> brought the pollution directly to the cities, where it could eat away at the buildings and statues.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The government's role</st>
<p>

While pollution was increasing, records and information relating to pollution became increasingly inaccessible to the public.  Students who tried to make the public aware of the problems were arrested and detained by the police.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  Often no records were even kept on the industrial effects on the environment.  There were some people involved with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/46539.xml">
non-governmental organizations</link> that tried to correct the situation, but these groups were largely interested in acting as an adversary of the state.  Under the <law wordnetid="106532330" confidence="0.8">
<fundamental_law wordnetid="106533648" confidence="0.8">
<document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<legal_document wordnetid="106479665" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/423968.xml">
constitution of 1960</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</legal_document>
</document>
</fundamental_law>
</law>
, the state was legally required to protect the quality of the environment as far as necessary to protect human health, but in northern Czechoslovakia, pollution reportedly shortened a person’s life by three to four years.  The government even acknowledged these poor living conditions by offering a bonus to people who lived in the area for more than ten years – called burial money by the people in the area.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

The government face problems in trying to solve environmental problems because there was no central branch responsible for environmental safety and protection.  Instead, there were many different branches responsible for different aspects of the environment – one for water, one for land, one for air, etc., and these different branches often had conflicting interests.  Each branch would try to enforce its own environmental priorities without regard to the overall environmental picture.  Furthermore, these branches were in charge not only of the environmental issues in their area, but also of the economic issues, giving each branch a set of conflicting priorities, and economic needs would generally win out.  When the government imposed fines for failures to comply with pollution regulations, it would also help industry pay off the fines, leaving industry with little incentive to change policies.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Adamova, Eva. “Environmental Management in Czecho-Slovakia.” Environmental Action in Eastern Europe. Ed. Barbara Jancar-Webster. Armonk, New York: M.E. Sharpe, 1993. 42-57.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Students Take Word of Protests to Czechoslovak Towns, Villages; Communist Authorities Try to Stop Activists from Spreading the News, The Washington Post, November 24th, 1989.</entry>
<entry id="3">
East Europe: Greening of the Reds, The Washington Post, December 24th, 1989.</entry>
<entry id="4">
The Scars of Pollution; Iron Curtain Rises to Reveal Dirt, Death; POISON IN THE EAST, The Boston Globe, December 17th, 1989.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Furher reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Crampton, R. J. "Eastern Europe in the Twentieth Century – and After." 2nd ed. New York: Routledge, 1997.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
