<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:41:21[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Operating reserve</title>
<id>11068261</id>
<revision>
<id>229968938</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-05T12:08:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cedars</username>
<id>37157</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Power engineering</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="320px" src="Reservepower.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

An idealized representation of the four kinds of reserve power and the time intervals after an unexpected failure that they are in use.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
</caption>
</image>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/38824.xml">
power systems</link>, the <b>operating reserve</b> is the generating capacity available to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/3500178.xml">
system operator</link> within a short interval of time to meet demand in case a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/82330.xml">
generator</link> is lost or there is another disruption to the supply. Most power systems are designed so that, under normal conditions, the operating reserve is always at least the capacity of the largest generator plus a fraction of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/4490333.xml">
peak load</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><p>

The operating reserve can be divided into two kinds of reserve power: the <b>spinning reserve</b> and the <b>non-spinning</b> or <b>supplemental reserve</b>:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The spinning reserve is the extra generating capacity that is available by increasing the power output of generators that are already connected to the power system. For most generators, this increase in power output is achieved by increasing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/30400.xml">
torque</link> applied to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/30848.xml">
turbine's rotor</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The non-spinning or supplemental reserve is the extra generating capacity that is not presently connected to the system but can be brought online after a short delay. In isolated power systems, this typically equates to the power available from fast-start generators.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> However in interconnected power systems, this may include the power available on short notice by importing power from other systems or retracting power that is presently being exported to other systems.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Generators that intend to provide either spinning and non-spinning reserve should be able to reach their promised capacity within ten or so minutes. Most power system guidelines require a significant fraction of their operating reserve to come from spinning reserve.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> This is because the spinning reserve is slightly more reliable (it doesn't suffer from start-up issues) and can respond immediately whereas with non-spinning reserve generators there is a delay as the generator starts-up offline.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

In addition, there are two other kinds of reserve power that are often discussed in combination with the operating reserve: the <b>frequency-response reserve</b> and the <b>replacement reserve</b>:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The frequency-response reserve is provided as an automatic reaction to a loss in supply. It occurs because immediately following a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/164989.xml">
loss of supply</link>, the generators slow down due to the increased load. To combat this slowing, many generators have a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/430361.xml">
governor</link>. By helping the generators to speed up, these governors provide a small boost to both the output frequency and the power of each generator. However because the frequency-response reserve is often small and not at the discretion of the system operator it is not considered part of the operating reserve.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The replacement reserve is reserve power provided by generators that require a longer start-up time (typically thirty to sixty minutes). It is used to relieve the generators providing the spinning or non-spinning reserve and thus restore the operating reserve (confusingly the replacement reserve is sometimes known as the 30 or 60-minute operating reserve).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The time periods over which all four kinds of reserve power operate is illustrated in the diagram that accompanies this article.</p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
B. J. Kirby, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://certs.lbl.gov/pdf/spinning-reserves.pdf">
Spinning Reserve From Responsive Loads</weblink>, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, March 2003.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Jianxue Wang; Xifan Wang and Yang Wu, <it>Operating Reserve Model in the Power Market</it>, IEEE Transactions on Power Systems, Vol. 20, No. 1, February 2005.</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.caiso.com/docs/2003/09/08/2003090815135425649.pdf">
Spinning Reserve and Non-Spinning Reserve</weblink>, California ISO, January 2006.</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wecc.biz/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=Downloads&amp;file=index&amp;req=getit&amp;lid=125">
WSCC Operating Reserve White Paper</weblink>, Western Systems Coordinating Council, July 1998.</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.mit.edu/energylab/www/pubs/el99-005wp.pdf">
The Value of Reliability in Power Systems</weblink>, MIT Energy Laboratory, June 1999.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Eric Hirst, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ksg.harvard.edu/hepg/Papers/Hirst_PRDReliability_04-02.pdf">
Price-Responsive Demand as Reliability Resources</weblink>, April 2002.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
