<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:43:06[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Epsiplus</title>
<id>11254448</id>
<revision>
<id>139250440</id>
<timestamp>2007-06-19T18:13:26Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Gary King</username>
<id>118799</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from May 2007</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles with possible conflicts of interest</category>
<category> Public economics</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Epsiplus&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Epsiplus%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(May 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Unbalanced_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>A major contributor to this article or its creator appears to have a  with its subject.</b>
It may require  to comply with Wikipedia's content policies, particularly . Please discuss further on the . <it>(May 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>ePSIplus</b> is a Thematic Network, funded by the <control wordnetid="105196375" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="105196582" confidence="0.8">
<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/9974.xml">
European Commission</link></power>
</authority>
</control>
's eContentplus programme, to support the implementation of the European Directive on Re-use Public Sector Information (Directive 2003/98/EC of the European parliament and of the Council: 17 November 2003). <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/10890716.xml">
EU Member States</link> were required to implement the Directive into national law by 1 July 2005.</p>
<p>

ePSIPlus uses experts on PSI resources, in order to facilitate re-use of public sector information for the benefit of companies, public administrations and citizens.</p>
<p>

The project focuses on five major themes identified as a result of the ePSINet Accompanying Measure under the eContent Programme:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Legal and regulatory progress and impact (including implementation of the Directive)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Public sector organisation and culture change (including compliance with the Directive)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Encouraging PSI re-use business</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The financial impact of the Directive: pricing and charging (including impact on public sector costs and budget)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Information management, standards and data quality</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The ePSIplus <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/54293.xml">
web portal</link> is in the public domain and provides access to a range of knowledge emerging in the re-use of public sector information (PSI), across all EU member states, for both public and private sector stakeholders. The site also provides a forum for the discussion of key issues. </p>
<p>

ePSIplus provides information on PSI re-use across Europe including news, reports, legal cases, good practices and benchmarking on the progress of legislation by means of a country scorecard, searchable by thematic area, country and free text terms. </p>
<p>

The ePSIplus Network community includes organisations and individuals who are stakeholders from European countries in PSI re-use, from the public and private sector. </p>
<p>

The Network also involves 25 European national representative organisations and a number of European Associations participating in promoting the Network and providing local knowledge. </p>
<p>

The Network co-ordinating team is responsible for planning, development and co-ordination activities and includes expert analysts with backgrounds in the five major themes. </p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epsiplus.net/">
ePSIplus Web Portal</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/activities/econtentplus/index_en.htm">
eContentplus programme</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epsiplus.net/epsiplus/reports/european_directive_on_psi">
European Directive on Public Sector Information (PSI) Re-use (2003/98/EC)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/psi/index_en.htm">
European Commission's Information Society Web Portal on Public Sector Information (Access and Re-use)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
