<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:43:09[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<private_school  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108411170">
<school  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276720">
<educational_institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276342">
<seminary  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108284994">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>San Francisco Theological Seminary</title>
<id>11257824</id>
<revision>
<id>218800552</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-12T06:23:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lukemwills</username>
<id>3555529</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Seminaries and theological colleges in the United States</category>
<category>Education in Marin County, California</category>
<category>Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.) seminaries</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="387px" src="Sfts_hillside_photo.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

 San Francisco Theological Seminary
</caption>
</image>

<p>

San Francisco Theological Seminary is a graduate theological institution in California, with a northern campus in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/102391.xml">
San Anselmo</link> and a southern campus in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/49782.xml">
Pasadena</link>. An institution of the <denomination wordnetid="108146782" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/25031.xml">
Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.)</link></denomination>
, SFTS is devoted to graduate theological education in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/102584.xml">
Reformed tradition</link> through dialogue, inquiry and critical reflection.</p>

<p>

SFTS is a founding member of the <private_school wordnetid="108411170" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<seminary wordnetid="108284994" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/953425.xml">
Graduate Theological Union</link></institution>
</group>
</seminary>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
</private_school>
 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/4860.xml">
Berkeley</link></village>
, the largest consortium of seminaries in the United States. The <private_school wordnetid="108411170" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<seminary wordnetid="108284994" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/953425.xml">
GTU</link></institution>
</group>
</seminary>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
</private_school>
 provides students an ecumenical context to explore diverse religious views and traditions, offering unique opportunities for personal and professional growth.</p>


<sec>
<st>
 Mission Statement: </st>

<p>

SFTS prepares leaders for the Church of Jesus Christ sent by the Holy Spirit in God’s mission to the world. We are committed to the education of students in spiritual formation, critical theological reflection, and the skills and arts of ministry, to serve in congregations, the wider church, the classroom, and public sphere.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History: </st>
<p>

San Francisco pastor William Anderson Scott opened two Presbyterian schools in his churches in the mid-19th century, the second of which became San Francisco Theological Seminary. </p>
<p>

In 1871, SFTS began with four professors and four students meeting for instruction at the Presbyterian City College located in what now is Union Square. Six years later, the Seminary moved to its own building next to the City College building on Haight Street.</p>

<p>

The seminary moved in 1890 to a 14-acre hilltop site in Marin County about 15 miles north of the Golden Gate Bridge. A new charter issued in 1900 gave the Seminary power to grant degrees, and jurisdiction over the Seminary was transferred from the Synod to the General Assembly of the Presbyterian Church in 1913. </p>
<p>

In the post World War II era under President Jesse Hays Baird, SFTS enjoyed unprecedented expansion, with enrollment increasing to more than 300 and new buildings rising all over the San Anselmo campus. </p>
<p>

SFTS joined in 1962 with neighboring theological schools in founding the Graduate Theological Union. The GTU developed joint M.A. and Ph.D. degrees. SFTS continued to offer its own Master of Arts degrees in theological studies. Under its Advanced Pastoral Studies program, the Seminary added the Doctor of the Science of Theology (S.T.D.) and the Doctor of Ministry (D.Min.) degrees.</p>
<p>

In 1990, SFTS opened its second campus in Pasadena, which is housed in Pasadena Presbyterian Church.
Today, the San Anselmo campus has more than 350 master’s and doctoral level students, with about 115 full-time, and the Pasadena campus supports 100 full- and part-time master-level students. More than 20 faculty between the two campuses provide instruction and scholarship.</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Academic information: </st>

<p>

SFTS offers a theological education that is grounded in Scripture as well as in touch with contemporary issues in the church and world. Degree programs between the Northern &amp; Southern California campuses include:
&#8226; <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/647722.xml">
Master of Divinity</link></property>
</degree>
 (San Anselmo &amp; Pasadena)
&#8226; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/4126896.xml">
Master of Arts</link> in Theological Studies (San Anselmo &amp; Pasadena)
&#8226; <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/3152215.xml">
Doctor of Ministry</link></property>
</degree>
 (San Anselmo)
SFTS offers two graduate-level diplomas on the Northern California campus:
&#8226; Diploma in the Art of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../595/3734595.xml">
Spiritual Direction</link>
&#8226; Diploma in Spiritual Formation Studies
In conjunction with the Graduate Theological Union, students can also earn the following degrees:
&#8226; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/4126896.xml">
Master of Arts</link>
&#8226; <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/2065969.xml">
Doctor of Theology</link></property>
</degree>

&#8226; <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/8775.xml">
Doctor of Philosophy</link></property>
</degree>

The Southern California campus also provides a Certificate of Ministry Studies non-diploma program.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 SFTS Programs: </st>
<p>

The Lloyd Center - The Lloyd Center provides a variety of services including counseling &amp; psychotherapy, spiritual direction, clergy and leadership coaching, psychologocial assessements for ministerial candidates. The Lloyd Center also offers a doctor of ministry degree in pastoral care and counseling.
Field Education - The Department of Field Education and Integrative Studies assists M. Div students in finding their place of ministry. From the Introduction to Ministry taught in the first year, through year-long supervised internships, students experience first-hand, practical applications of theoretical learning.
Program in Christian Spirituality – PCS offers diploma programs in spiritual direction and spiritual formation; a doctor of ministry degree in spirituality; a spirituality concentration in the master of divinity program; plus pastoral renewal opportunities.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Seminary Events: </st>

<p>

SFTS sponsors a variety of events for students seeking a choice for graduate theological education, including:
72 Hours of Discernment – Spend three days on the San Anselmo campus learning about the SFTS experience and discerning God’s call for you in study and ministry.
Seminary Saturdays – Join fellow students and faculty in Southern California for a “day in the life” opportunity to experience life as a seminary student in the flexible and diverse Southern California program.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sfts.edu/">
San Francisco Theological Seminary website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</seminary>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</private_school>
</article>
