<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:36:25[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Quantum graph</title>
<id>11264285</id>
<revision>
<id>244401352</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T16:54:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Twri</username>
<id>7976492</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Quantum mechanics</category>
<category>Extensions and generalizations of graphs</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link> and  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/22939.xml">
physics</link>, a <b>quantum graph</b> is a linear, network-shaped structure whose time evolution is described by a system of <link>
schrödinger equation</link>s or, more generally, by a set of evolution equations associated with differential or pseudo-differential operators acting on functions defined  on a metric graph.  Such systems were first studied by Ruedenberg--Scherr as models of free electrons in organic molecules in the 1950s.  They arise in a variety of mathematical contexts, e.g. as model systems in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/313779.xml">
quantum chaos</link>, in the study of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/41863.xml">
waveguides</link>, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/355377.xml">
photonic crystals</link> and in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/2213942.xml">
Anderson localization</link>, or as limit on shrinking thin wires.  Quantum graphs have become prominent models in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/1503271.xml">
mesoscopic physics</link> used to obtain a theoretical understanding of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/21488.xml">
nanotechnology</link>.
<sec>
<st>
 Metric graphs </st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="400px" src="quantumgraph.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A metric graph embedded in the plane 
with three open edges.  The dashed line denotes the metric 
distance between two 
points <math>x</math> and <math>y</math>.
</caption>
</image>

A <b>metric graph</b>
is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/325806.xml">
graph</link> consisting of a set <math>V</math> of vertices and 
a set <math>E</math> of edges where each edge <math>e=(v_1,v_2)\in E</math> has been associated 
with an interval <math>[0,L_e]</math> so that <math>x_e</math> is the coordinate on the 
interval, the vertex <math>v_1</math> corresponds to <math>x_e=0</math> and  
<math>v_2</math> to <math>x_e=L_e</math> or vice versa.  The choice of which vertex lies at zero is 
arbitrary with the alternative corresponding to a change of coordinate on the 
edge.
The graph has a natural metric: for  two 
points <math>x,y</math> on the graph, <math>\rho(x,y)</math> is 
the shortest distance between them
where distance is measured along the edges of the graph.
It is possible to embed a metric 
graph in the plane, <math>{\mathbb R}^2</math>, or space, <math>{\mathbb R}^3</math>, if the lengths are 
chosen appropriately.</p>
<p>

<b>Open graphs:</b> in the combinatorial graph model 
edges always join pairs of vertices however in a quantum graph one may also 
consider semi-infinite edges.  These are edges associated with the interval 
<math>[0,\infty)</math> attached to a single vertex at <math>x_e=0</math>.  
A graph with one or more 
such open edges is referred to as an open graph.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Quantum graphs </st>

<p>

Quantum graphs are metric graphs equipped with a differential 
(or pseudo-differential) operator acting on functions on the graph.  
A function <math>f</math> on a metric graph is defined as the <math>|E|</math>-tuple of functions
<math>f_e(x_e)</math> on the intervals.   
The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/18994167.xml">
Hilbert space</link> of the graph is <math>\bigoplus_{e\in E} L^2([0,L_e])</math>
where the inner product of two functions is </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\langle f,g \rangle = \sum_{e\in E} \int_{0}^{L_e} f_e^{*}(x_e)g_e(x_e) \, dx_e,</math>
</indent>

<math>L_e</math> may be infinite in the case of an open edge.  The simplest example of an operator on a metric graph is the <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<mathematical_relation wordnetid="113783581" confidence="0.8">
<equation wordnetid="106669864" confidence="0.8">
<operator wordnetid="113786413" confidence="0.8">
<mathematical_statement wordnetid="106732169" confidence="0.8">
<function wordnetid="113783816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/174706.xml">
Laplace operator</link></function>
</mathematical_statement>
</operator>
</equation>
</mathematical_relation>
</message>
</statement>
.  The operator on an edge is <math>-\frac{\textrm{d}^2}{\textrm{d} x_e^2}</math> where <math>x_e</math> is the coordinate on the edge.  To make the operator self-adjoint a suitable domain must be specified.  This is typically achieved by taking the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/611964.xml">
Sobolev space</link> <math>H^2</math> of functions on the edges of the graph and specifying matching conditions at the vertices.</p>
<p>

The trivial example of matching conditions that make the operator self-adjoint are the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/423504.xml">
Dirichlet boundary conditions</link>, <math>f_e(0)=f_e(L_e)=0</math> for every edge.  An eigenfunction on a finite edge may be written as </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>f_e(x_e) = \sin \left( \frac{n \pi x_e}{L_e} \right)</math> 
</indent>

for integer <math>n</math>.  If the graph is closed with no infinite edges and the 
lengths of the edges of the graph are rationally independent
then an eigenfunction is supported on a single graph edge 
and the eigenvalues are <math>\frac{n^2\pi^2}{L_e^2}</math>.  The Dirichlet conditions 
don't allow interaction between the intervals so the spectrum is the same as 
that of the set of disconnected edges.</p>
<p>

More interesting self-adjoint matching conditions that allow interaction between edges are the <link>
Neumann</link> or natural matching conditions.  A function <math>f</math> in the domain of the operator is continuous everywhere on the graph and the sum of the outgoing derivatives at a vertex is zero,</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\sum_{e\sim v} f'(v) = 0 \ ,</math>
</indent>

where <math>f'(v)=f'(0)</math> if the vertex <math>v</math> is at <math>x=0</math> and <math>f'(v)=-f'(L_e)</math> if <math>v</math> is at <math>x=L_e</math>.</p>
<p>

The properties of other operators on metric graphs have also been studied.  
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 These include the more general class of Schrŏdinger operators,</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\left( i \frac{\textrm{d}}{\textrm{d} x_e} + A_e(x_e) \right)^2 + V_e(x_e) \ ,</math>
</indent>

where <math>A_e</math> is a "magnetic vector potential" on the edge and <math>V_e</math> is a scalar potential.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Another example is the <mathematical_relation wordnetid="113783581" confidence="0.8">
<operator wordnetid="113786413" confidence="0.8">
<function wordnetid="113783816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/1079448.xml">
Dirac operator</link></function>
</operator>
</mathematical_relation>
 on a graph which is a matrix valued operator acting on vector valued functions that describe the quantum mechanics of particles with an intrinsic angular momentum of one half such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/9476.xml">
electron</link>.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Dirichlet-to-Neumann operator on a graph is a pseudo-differential operator that arises in the  study of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/355377.xml">
photonic crystals</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Theorems </st>

<p>

All <b>self-adjoint matching conditions</b> of the Laplace operator on a graph can be classified according to a scheme of Kostrykin and Schrader, see <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.  Let <math>v</math> be a vertex with <math>d</math> edges emanating from it.  For simplicity we choose the coordinates on the edges so that <math>v</math> lies at <math>x_e=0</math> for each edge meeting at <math>v</math>.  For a function <math>f</math> on the graph let </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\mathbf{f}=(f_{e_1}(0),f_{e_2}(0),\dots,f_{e_{d}}(0))^T , \qquad \mathbf{f}'=(f'_{e_1}(0),f'_{e_2}(0),\dots,f'_{e_{d}}(0))^T.</math>
</indent>

Matching conditions at <math>v</math> can be specified by a pair of matrices 
<math>A</math> and <math>B</math> through the linear equation,</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>A \mathbf{f} +B \mathbf{f}'=\mathbf{0}. </math>
</indent>

The matching conditions define a self-adjoint operator if 
<math>(A, B)</math> has the maximal rank <math>d</math> and <math>AB^{*}=BA^{*}.</math></p>
<p>

The spectrum of the Laplace operator on a finite graph can be conveniently described 
using a <b>scattering matrix</b> approach introduced by Kottos and Smilansky
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.  The eigenvalue problem on an edge is,</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>-\frac{d^2}{dx_e^2} f_e(x_e)=k^2 f_e(x_e).\,</math>
</indent>

So a solution on the edge can be written as a linear combination of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/41559.xml">
plane waves</link>.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>f_e(x_e) = c_e \textrm{e}^{i k x_e} + \hat{c}_e \textrm{e}^{-i k x_e}.\,</math>
</indent>

where in a time-dependent Schrödinger equation <math>c</math> is the coefficient 
of the outgoing plane wave at <math>0</math> and <math>\hat{c}</math> coefficient of the incoming 
plane wave at <math>0</math>.
The matching conditions at <math>v</math> define a scattering matrix</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>S(k)=-(A+i kB)^{-1}(A-ikB).\,</math>
</indent>

The scattering matrix relates the vectors of incoming and outgoing plane-wave 
coefficients  at <math>v</math>, <math>\mathbf{c}=S(k)\hat{\mathbf{c}}</math>.
For self-adjoint matching conditions <math>S</math> is unitary.  An element of 
<math>\sigma_{(uv)(vw)}</math> of <math>S</math> is a complex transition amplitude 
from a directed edge <math>(uv)</math>
to the edge <math>(vw)</math> which in general depends on <math>k</math>.  
However, for a large class of matching conditions 
the S-matrix is independent of <math>k</math>.  
With Neumann matching conditions for example</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>
A=\left( \begin{array}{ccccc}
1&amp; -1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; \dots \\
0 &amp; 1 &amp; -1 &amp; 0 &amp; \dots \\
&amp; &amp; \ddots &amp; \ddots &amp;  \\
0&amp; \dots &amp; 0 &amp;  1 &amp; -1 \\
0 &amp;\dots &amp; 0 &amp; 0&amp; 0 \\
\end{array} \right) , \quad B=\left( \begin{array}{cccc}
0&amp; 0 &amp; \dots &amp; 0 \\
\vdots &amp; \vdots &amp;  &amp; \vdots \\
0&amp; 0 &amp; \dots &amp; 0 \\
1 &amp;1 &amp; \dots &amp; 1 \\
\end{array} \right).
</math>
</indent>

Substituting in the equation for <math>S</math> 
produces <math>k</math>-independent transition amplitudes </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\sigma_{(uv)(vw)}=\frac{2}{d}-\delta_{uw}.\,</math>
</indent>

where <math>\delta_{uw}</math> is the Kronecker delta function that is one if <math>u=w</math> and 
zero otherwise.  From the transition amplitudes we may define a 
<math>2|E|\times 2|E|</math> matrix</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>U_{(uv)(lm)}(k)= \delta_{vl} \sigma_{(uv)(vm)}(k) \textrm{e}^{i kL_{(uv)}}.\,</math>
</indent>

<math>U</math> is called the bond scattering matrix and 
can be thought of as a quantum evolution operator on the graph.  It is
unitary and acts on the vector of <math>2|E|</math> plane-wave coefficients for the 
graph where <math>c_{(uv)}</math> is the coefficient of 
the plane wave traveling from <math>u</math> to <math>v</math>.  
The phase <math>\textrm{e}^{i kL_{(uv)}}</math> is the phase acquired by the plane wave 
when propagating from vertex <math>u</math> to vertex <math>v</math>.</p>
<p>

<b>Quantization condition:</b> An eigenfunction on the graph 
can be defined through its associated its <math>2|E|</math> plane-wave coefficients.
As the eigenfunction is stationary under the quantum evolution a quantization 
condition for the graph can be written using the evolution operator.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>|U(k)-I|=0.\,</math>
</indent>

Eigenvalues <math>k_j</math> occur at values of <math>k</math> where the matrix <math>U(k)</math> has an 
eigenvalue one.  We will order the spectrum with 
<math>0\leqslant k_0 \leqslant k_1 \leqslant \dots</math>. </p>
<p>

The first <b>trace formula</b> for a graph was derived by Roth (1983).
In 1997 Kottos and Smilansky used the quantization condition above to obtain
the following trace formula for the Laplace operator on a graph when the
transition amplitudes are independent of <math>k</math>.
The trace formula links the spectrum with periodic orbits on the graph.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>d(k):=\sum_{j=0}^{\infty} \delta(k-k_j)=\frac{L}{\pi}+\frac{1}{\pi} 
\sum_p \frac{L_p}{r_p} A_p \cos(kL_p).</math>
</indent>

<math>d(k)</math> is called the density of states.  The right hand side of the trace 
formula is made up of two terms, the Weyl 
term <math>\frac{L}{\pi}</math> 
is the mean separation of eigenvalues and the oscillating part is a sum 
over all periodic orbits <math>p=(e_1,e_2,\dots,e_n)</math> on the graph.  
<math>L_p=\sum_{e\in p} L_e</math> is the length of the orbit and 
<math>L=\sum_{e\in E}L_e</math> is
the total length of the graph.  For an orbit generated by repeating a 
shorter primitive orbit, <math>r_p</math> counts the number of repartitions.  
<math>A_p=\sigma_{e_1 e_2} \sigma_{e_2 e_3} \dots \sigma_{e_n e_1}</math> is 
the product of the transition amplitudes at the vertices of the graph around 
the orbit.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Applications </st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="naphthalene2.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Naphthalene molecule
</caption>
</image>

Quantum graphs were first employed in the 1930's 
to model the spectrum of free electrons in organic molecules like 
Naphthalene, see figure.  As a first approximation the 
atoms are taken to be vertices while the 
σ-electrons form bonds that fix a frame
in the shape of the molecule on which the free electrons are confined. </p>
<p>

A similar problem appears when considering quantum waveguides.  These 
are mesoscopic systems - systems built with a width on the scale of
nanometers.  A quantum waveguide can be thought of as a fattened graph 
where the edges
are thin tubes.  The spectrum of the Laplace operator on this domain
converges to the spectrum of the Laplace operator on the graph
under certain conditions.  Understanding mesoscopic systems plays an 
important role in the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/21488.xml">
nanotechnology</link>.</p>
<p>

In 1997 Kottos and Smilansky proposed quantum graphs as a model to study  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/313779.xml">
quantum chaos</link>, the quantum mechanics of systems that 
are classically chaotic.  Classical motion on the graph can be defined as 
a probabilistic <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/60876.xml">
Markov chain</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 where the probability of scattering 
from edge <math>e</math> to edge <math>f</math> is given by the absolute value of the 
quantum transition amplitude squared, <math>|\sigma_{ef}|^2</math>.  For almost all 
finite connected 
quantum graphs the probabilistic dynamics is ergodic and mixing, 
in other words chaotic.</p>
<p>

Quantum graphs embedded in two or three dimensions appear in the study
of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/355377.xml">
photonic crystals</link>.  In two dimensions a simple model of 
a photonic crystal consists of polygonal cells of a dense dielectric with 
narrow interfaces between the cells filled with air.  Studying 
dielectric modes that stay mostly in the dielectric gives rise to a 
pseudo-differential operator on the graph that follows the narrow interfaces.</p>
<p>

Periodic quantum graphs like the lattice in <math>{\mathbb R}^2</math> are common models of
periodic systems and quantum graphs have been applied 
to the study the phenomena of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/2213942.xml">
Anderson localization</link> where localized 
states occur at the edge of spectral bands in the presence of disorder.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
P. Kuchment, Quantum graphs I.  Some basic structures, <it>Waves in Random Media</it> <b>14</b>, S107-S128 (2004)</entry>
<entry id="2">
S. Gnutzman &amp; U. Smilansky, Quantum graphs: applications to quantum chaos and universal spectral statistics, <it>Adv. Phys.</it> <b>55</b> 527-625 (2006)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
