<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:02:31[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<procedure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101023820">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Intrusion detection system</title>
<id>113021</id>
<revision>
<id>243763290</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T23:06:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jclemens</username>
<id>200029</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>System administration</category>
<category>Computer security procedures</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about the computing term.&#32;&#32;For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/1294759.xml">
Burglar alarm</link>.
An <b>Intrusion detection system</b> (<b>IDS</b>) is software and/or hardware designed to detect unwanted attempts at accessing, manipulating, and/or disabling of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer systems</link>, mainly through a network, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>. These attempts may take the form of attacks, as examples, by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/29213.xml">
cracker</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/20901.xml">
malware</link> and/or disgruntled employees. An IDS cannot directly detect attacks within properly encrypted traffic.<p>

An intrusion detection system is used to detect several types of malicious behaviors that can compromise the security and trust of a computer system. This includes network attacks against vulnerable services, data driven attacks on applications, host based attacks such as privilege escalation, unauthorized logins and access to sensitive files, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/20901.xml">
malware</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/18994196.xml">
virus</link>es, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/30056.xml">
trojan horse</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/6010.xml">
worm</link>s).</p>
<p>

An IDS can be composed of several components: <b>Sensors</b>  which generate security events, a <b>Console</b> to monitor events and alerts and control the sensors, and a central <b>Engine</b> that records events logged by the sensors in a database and uses a system of rules to generate alerts from security events received. There are several ways to categorize an IDS depending on the type and location of the sensors and the methodology used by the engine to generate alerts. In many simple IDS implementations all three components are combined in a single device or appliance.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Types of Intrusion-Detection systems </st>
<p>

In a network-based intrusion-detection system (NIDS), the sensors are located at choke points in network to be monitored, often in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/179485.xml">
demilitarized zone</link> (DMZ) or at network borders. The sensor captures all network traffic and analyzes the content of individual packets for malicious traffic. In systems, PIDS and APIDS are used to monitor the transport and protocols illegal or inappropriate traffic or constructs of language (say SQL). In a host-based system, the sensor usually consists of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/430106.xml">
software agent</link>, which monitors all activity of the host on which it is installed. Hybrids of these two systems also exist.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/219307.xml">
network intrusion detection system</link> (NIDS) is an independent platform which identifies intrusions by examining network traffic and monitors multiple hosts.  Network Intrusion Detection Systems gain access to network traffic by connecting to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/1937926.xml">
hub</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/40614.xml">
network switch</link> configured for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/702709.xml">
port mirroring</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/1933660.xml">
network tap</link>.  An example of a NIDS is <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/861864.xml">
Snort</link></software>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/5920030.xml">
protocol-based intrusion detection system</link> (PIDS) consists of a system or agent that would typically sit at the front end of a server, monitoring and analyzing the communication protocol between a connected device (a user/PC or system).  For a web server this would typically monitor the HTTPS protocol stream and understand the HTTP protocol relative to the web server/system it is trying to protect.  Where HTTPS is in use then this system would need to reside in the "shim" or interface between where HTTPS is un-encrypted and immediately prior to it entering the Web  presentation layer.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/5920258.xml">
application protocol-based intrusion detection system</link> (APIDS) consists of a system or agent that would typically sit within a group of servers, monitoring and analyzing the communication on application specific protocols.  For example; in a web server with database this would monitor the SQL protocol specific to the middleware/business-login as it transacts with the database.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/1189224.xml">
host-based intrusion detection system</link> (HIDS) consists of an agent on a host which identifies intrusions by analyzing system calls, application logs, file-system modifications (binaries, password files, capability/acl databases) and other host activities and state. An example of a HIDS is <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/8913472.xml">
OSSEC</link></software>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A hybrid intrusion detection system combines two or more approaches.  Host agent data is combined with network information to form a comprehensive view of the network.  An example of a Hybrid IDS is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/13485881.xml">
Prelude</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<sec>
<st>
 Passive system vs. reactive system </st>
<p>

In a <b>passive system</b>, the intrusion detection system (IDS) sensor detects a potential security breach, logs the information and signals an alert on the console and or owner. In a <b>reactive system</b>, also known as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/269059.xml">
intrusion prevention system</link> (IPS), the IDS responds to the suspicious activity by resetting the connection or by reprogramming the firewall to block network traffic from the suspected malicious source. This can happen automatically or at the command of an operator.</p>
<p>

Though they both relate to network security, an intrusion detection system (IDS) differs from a firewall in that a firewall looks outwardly for intrusions in order to stop them from happening. Firewalls limit access between networks to prevent intrusion and do not signal an attack from inside the network. An IDS evaluates a suspected intrusion once it has taken place and signals an alarm. An IDS also watches for attacks that originate from within a system.</p>
<p>

This is traditionally achieved by examining network communications, identifying heuristics and patterns (often known as signatures) of common computer attacks, and taking action to alert operators.  A system which terminates connections is called an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/269059.xml">
intrusion prevention system</link>, and is another form of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/956499.xml">
application layer firewall</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 IDS evasion techniques</st>

<p>

<accomplishment wordnetid="100035189" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<feat wordnetid="100036762" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/9332320.xml">
Intrusion detection system evasion techniques</link></feat>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</event>
</accomplishment>
 bypass detection by creating different states on the IDS and on the targeted computer. The adversary accomplishes this by manipulating either the attack itself or the network traffic that contains the attack.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Development </st>

<p>

A preliminary concept of an IDS began with James P. Anderson and reviews of audit trails.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  An example of an audit trail would be a log of user access.</p>
<p>

Fred Cohen noted in 1984 (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/2010184.xml">
Intrusion Detection</link>) that it is impossible to detect an intrusion in every case and that the resources needed to detect intrusions grows with the amount of usage.</p>
<p>

Dorothy E. Denning, assisted by Peter Neuman, published a model of an IDS in 1986 that formed the basis for many systems today.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  Her model used statistics for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/8190902.xml">
anomaly detection</link>, and resulted in an early IDS at SRI named the Intrusion detection expert system (IDES), which ran on Sun Workstations and could consider both user and network level data.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  IDES had a dual approach with a rule-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/10136.xml">
Expert System</link> to detect known types of intrusions plus a statistical anomaly detection component based on profiles of users, host systems, and target systems.  Lunt proposed adding an <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
Artificial neural network</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 as a third component.  She said all three components could then report to a resolver.  SRI followed IDES  in 1993 with the Next-generation Intrusion Detection Expert System (NIDES).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

The Multics intrusion detection and alerting system (MIDAS), an expert system using P-BEST and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/18016.xml">
LISP</link>, was developed in 1988 based on the work of Denning and Neuman.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>  Haystack was also developed this year using statistics to reduce audit trails.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

Wisdom &amp; sense (W&amp;S) was a statistics-based anomaly detector developed in 1989 at the Los Alamos National Laboratory.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>  W&amp;S created rules based on statistical analysis, and then used those rules for anomaly detection.</p>
<p>

In 1990, the Time-based inductive machine (TIM) did anomaly detection using inductive learning of sequential user patterns in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/6068.xml">
Common LISP</link> on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/32517.xml">
VAX</link> 3500 computer.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>  The Network Security Monitor (NSM) performed masking on access matrices for anomaly detection on a Sun-3/50 workstation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>  The Information Security Officer's Assistant (ISOA) was a 1990 prototype that considered a variety of strategies including statistics, a profile checker, and an expert system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>  ComputerWatch at AT&amp;T Bell Labs used statistics and rules for audit data reduction and intrusion detection.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

Then, in 1991, researchers at the University of California created a prototype Distributed intrusion detection system (DIDS), which was also an expert system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>  The Network anomaly detection and intrusion reporter (NADIR), also in 1991, was a prototype IDS developed at the Los Alamos National Laboratory's Integrated Computing Network (ICN), and was heavily influenced by the work of Denning and Lunt.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>  NADIR used a statistics-based anomaly detector and an expert system.</p>
<p>

The Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory announced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/5529490.xml">
Bro</link> in 1998 which used its own rule language for packet analysis from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/2475190.xml">
libpcap</link> data.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>  Network Flight Recorder (NFR)in 1999 also used libpcap.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>  APE was developed as a packet sniffer, also using libpcap, in November, 1998, and was renamed <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/861864.xml">
Snort</link></software>
 one month later.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

The Audit data analysis and mining (ADAM) IDS in 2001 used <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/170533.xml">
tcpdump</link> to build profiles of rules for classifications.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/219307.xml">
Network intrusion detection system</link> (NIDS)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/1189224.xml">
Host-based intrusion detection system</link> (HIDS)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/5920030.xml">
Protocol-based intrusion detection system</link> (PIDS)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/5920258.xml">
Application protocol-based intrusion detection system</link> (APIDS)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/1199510.xml">
Anomaly-based intrusion detection system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/269059.xml">
Intrusion prevention system</link> (IPS)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/1589987.xml">
Artificial immune system</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/3320515.xml">
Autonomous Agents for Intrusion Detection</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Free Intrusion Detection Systems </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/861864.xml">
Snort NIDS</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/13425792.xml">
Endian Firewall</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/16090722.xml">
Untangle</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/5529490.xml">
Bro NIDS</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/13485881.xml">
Prelude Hybrid IDS</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/8913472.xml">
OSSEC HIDS</link></software>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Anderson, James P., "Computer Security Threat Monitoring and Surveillance," Washing, PA, James P. Anderson Co., 1980.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Denning, Dorothy E., "An Intrusion Detection Model," Proceedings of the Seventh IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, May 1986, pages 119-131</entry>
<entry id="3">
Lunt, Teresa F., "IDES:  An Intelligent System for Detecting Intruders," Proceedings of the Symposium on Computer Security; Threats, and Countermeasures; Rome, Italy, November 22-23, 1990, pages 110-121.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Lunt, Teresa F., "Detecting Intruders in Computer Systems," 1993 Conference on Auditing and Computer Technology, SRI International</entry>
<entry id="5">
Sebring, Michael M., and Whitehurst, R. Alan., "Expert Systems in Intrusion Detection:  A Case Study," The 11th National Computer Security Conference, October, 1988</entry>
<entry id="6">
Smaha, Stephen E., "Haystack:  An Intrusion Detection System," The Fourth Aerospace Computer Security Applications Conference, Orlando, FL, December, 1988</entry>
<entry id="7">
Vaccaro, H.S., and Liepins, G.E., "Detection of Anomalous Computer Session Activity," The 1989 IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, May, 1989</entry>
<entry id="8">
Teng, Henry S., Chen, Kaihu, and Lu, Stephen C-Y, "Adaptive Real-time Anomaly Detection Using Inductively Generated Sequential Patterns," 1990 IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy</entry>
<entry id="9">
Heberlein, L. Todd, Dias, Gihan V., Levitt, Karl N., Mukherjee, Biswanath, Wood, Jeff, and Wolber, David, "A Network Security Monitor," 1990 Symposium on Research in Security and Privacy, Oakland, CA, pages 296-304</entry>
<entry id="10">
Winkeler, J.R., "A UNIX Prototype for Intrusion and Anomaly Detection in Secure Networks," The Thirteenth National Computer Security Conference, Washington, DC., pages 115-124, 1990</entry>
<entry id="11">
Dowell, Cheri, and Ramstedt, Paul, "The ComputerWatch Data Reduction Tool," Proceedings of the 13th National Computer Security Conference, Washington, D.C., 1990</entry>
<entry id="12">
Snapp, Steven R, Brentano, James, Dias, Gihan V., Goan, Terrance L., Heberlein, L. Todd, Ho, Che-Lin, Levitt, Karl N., Mukherjee, Biswanath, Smaha, Stephen E., Grance, Tim, Teal, Daniel M. and Mansur, Doug, "DIDS (Distributed Intrusion Detection System) -- Motivation, Architecture, and An Early Prototype," The 14th National Computer Security Conference, October, 1991, pages 167-176.</entry>
<entry id="13">
Jackson, Kathleen, DuBois, David H., and Stallings, Cathy A., "A Phased Approach to Network Intrusion Detection," 14th National Computing Security Conference, 1991</entry>
<entry id="14">
Paxson, Vern, "Bro:  A System for Detecting Network Intruders in Real-Time," Proceedings of The 7th USENIX Security Symposium, San Antonio, TX, 1998</entry>
<entry id="15">
Amoroso, Edward, "Intrusion Detection:  An Introduction to Internet Surveillance, Correlation, Trace Back, Traps, and Response," Intrusion.Net Books, Sparta, New Jersey, 1999, ISBN 0-9666700-7-8</entry>
<entry id="17">
Barbara, Daniel, Couto, Julia, Jajodia, Sushil, Popyack, Leonard, and Wu, Ningning, "ADAM:  Detecting Intrusions by Data Mining," Proceedings of the IEEE Workshop on Information Assurance and Security, West Point, NY, June 5-6, 2001</entry>
<entry id="16">
Kohlenberg, Toby (Ed.), Alder, Raven, Carter, Dr. Everett F. (Skip), Jr., Foster, James C., Jonkman Marty, Raffael, and Poor, Mike, "Snort IDS and IPS Toolkit," Syngress, 2007, ISBN 978-1-59749-099-3</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dmoz.org/Computers/Security/Intrusion_Detection_Systems/">
Intrusion Detection Systems category at Open Directory Project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://csrc.ncsl.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-94/SP800-94.pdf">
Guide to Intrusion Detection and Prevention Systems (IDPS)</weblink>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/21888.xml">
NIST</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/3265523.xml">
CSRC</link> special publication SP 800-94, released 02/2007</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.softpanorama.org/Security/intrusion_detection.shtml">
Softpanorama: Intrusion Detection (General Issues)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.securityfocus.com/infocus/1232">
IDS Evasion with Unicode</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/5616">
Linux Journal article</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ipsec.pl/intrusion-detection/prevention-systems-classification-tree.html">
Intrusion Detection/Protection Systems classification tree</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.infiltrated.net/?p=90">
Cross Reference Anomaly Processing: CRAP</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</article>
