<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:44:29[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<hospital  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="103540595">
<header>
<title>California Mission Hospital</title>
<id>11319135</id>
<revision>
<id>175426305</id>
<timestamp>2007-12-03T06:10:11Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>LeoNomis</username>
<id>723195</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Hospitals in California</category>
<category>Orange County, California</category>
<category>Children&apos;s hospitals in the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Hospital</name>
<parameters>
<Beds>
304</Beds>
<Website>
http://www.mission4health.com/</Website>
<HealthCare>
Non-profit</HealthCare>
<Type>
Specialist</Type>
<Speciality>
<happening wordnetid="107283608" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<emergency wordnetid="107417405" confidence="0.8">
<crisis wordnetid="107417644" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<juncture wordnetid="107416714" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/788093.xml">
Trauma</link></juncture>
</psychological_feature>
</crisis>
</emergency>
</event>
</happening>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/36808.xml">
Heart</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/1055005.xml">
Maternity</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/23593.xml">
Pediatric</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/55034.xml">
Spine</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/3717.xml">
Brain</link></Speciality>
<Country>
US</Country>
<Name>
California Mission Hospital</Name>
<Emergency>
Yes</Emergency>
<Region>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/107824.xml">
Mission Viejo, California</link></village>
</Region>
<State>
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/5407.xml">
California</link></country>
</State>
<Founded>
1971</Founded>
</parameters>
</template>


There are other hospitals also named <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/12735878.xml">
Mission Hospital</link>
<p>

<b>Mission Hospital</b> is located in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/107824.xml">
Mission Viejo</link></village>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/5407.xml">
California</link></country>
.</p>
<p>

It is a 304-bed acute care, full-service facility serving all of south <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/45330.xml">
Orange County</link></county>
 and houses the region’s designated trauma center, one of only three in the county.</p>
<p>

Mission Hospital offers a complete array of top-quality healthcare services including:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mission Trauma Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mission Heart Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mission Breast Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mission Maternity Center</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Mission Hospital also offers the highest level of care in orthopedics, rehabilitation, cancer, stroke, spine, vascular and wellness services.</p>
<p>

Mission Hospital is a member of the St. Joseph Health System, sponsored by the Sisters of St. Joseph of Orange. Our mission is to extend the Catholic health care ministry of the Sisters of St. Joseph of Orange, by continually improving the health and quality of life of people in the communities we serve. Our vision is to care for the medically underserved, to create healthier communities, and to alleviate conditions which limit access to basic health services.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

The Mission Hospital opened on August 11, 1971 with 124 patient beds, 330 employees and a medical staff of 41 physicians providing general acute care, including obstetrics, pediatrics, surgery, intensive care and emergency services.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1973, 89 new beds were added to accommodate growing demand.  Designated a paramedic base station.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1974, cardiac rehabilitation opened.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1976 a helipad opened</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1977 oncology services became available.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1980 it became one of the six original Orange County hospitals designated as a regional trauma center.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1981 the Oncology Care Unit opened.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1988 the Heart Surgery and Angioplasty program was introduced.  The Mission Medical Tower and the Center for Rehab/Sports/Wellness opened along with a new four-level parking structure linking the upper and lower medical campuses and hospital services.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1989, the Foundation at Mission Hospital Regional Medical Center was established to support community health education, medical staff research and programs to benefit the community.  Also, the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit opened and the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit was upgraded to a Level II program.  The hospital acquired state-of-the-art MRI and CT scanners.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Mission Surgery Center and the Mission Regional Imaging Center opened.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1992 the five-story patient tower opened, making Mission Hospital the largest medical center in south Orange County with a total of 274 beds.  The Fetal Diagnostic Center  and the Mission Rehabilitation Center opened.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1993 the <b>Children's Hospital at Mission</b>, now known as <b>CHOC at Mission</b>, opened on the fifth floor of Mission Hospital. It was the first and only pediatric hospital in south Orange County.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1994 the Mission Hospital Regional Medical Center became a member of the non-profit <link>
St. Joseph Health System</link> sponsored by the <link>
Sisters of St. Joseph of Orange</link>.  As a non-profit hospital, the Mission Hospital Foundation broadened its scope to include raising funds for capital needs. The Pastoral Care department, later renamed Spiritual Care, was developed to meet the spiritual and emotional needs of patients and their families.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 1996 Mission Hospital collaborated with five other not-for-profit organizations to open the South Orange County Family Resource Center serving as a clearing-house for information and resources available to families. Mission Hospital assumed sponsorship of the South County Community Clinic, in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/107834.xml">
San Juan Capistrano</link></village>
, renaming it Camino Health Center.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 2002 the Edward and Ann Muldoon Cardiac Center opened.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 2003 Mission opened a health center in <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/1330448.xml">
Ladera Ranch</link></group>
</community>
</gathering>
</social_group>
. Along with the Mission Health Center in Rancho Santa Margarita, the urgent care center provides the community service for minor emergencies and basic healthcare needs, ranging from sprains to sore throats.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

For the future Mission Hospital has embarked on an ambitious plan to significantly expand the hospital campus during the next two decades to accommodate the community's growing healthcare needs. This includes an expanded Emergency Department and Mission Regional Trauma Center, as well as the recently completed Mission Conference Center. Major construction in the next few years includes an 80,000-square-foot, 122 bed patient tower, a 140,000-square-foot medical office facility along Crown Valley Parkway, a new chapel, and numerous other expansions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Fact Sheet </st>

<p>

<b>Quick Facts</b>
Bed Size: 304 
Annual Discharges: 15,939 
Outpatient Visits: 102,084 
Avg. Daily Census: 189 
Number of Physicians: 698 
Annual # of Traumas: 940 
Annual # of ER Visits: 53,696 
Annual # of Births: 3,043 </p>
<p>

<b>Mission Hospital Centers of Excellence</b>
Mission Regional Trauma Center 
Mission Heart Center 
Mission Maternity Center 
Mission Vascular Center 
Mission Spine Center 
Mission Cancer Center 
Mission Brain Injury Center </p>
<p>

<b>Mission Hospital Services</b>
Center for Rehab/Sports/Wellness 
Rehabilitation Programs 
Orthopedic Services 
Wellness Programs 
Senior Services 
Spiritual Care Services 
Surgical Services 
Outpatient Testing Services </p>
<p>

<b>Important Notes</b>
• Largest medical center in south Orange County with the area's only designated trauma center. </p>
<p>

• Winner of the 2000 Ernest A. Codman award for excellence in quality healthcare presented by Joint Commission on Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations (JCAHO). </p>
<p>

• Our Patient Care Tower houses CHOC at Mission, the only pediatric hospital in the area and a cooperative effort with Children's Hospital of Orange County. </p>
<p>

• In 1994, the hospital became one of 15 Catholic, not-for-profit hospitals operated by the St. Joseph Health System and sponsored by the Sisters of St. Joseph of Orange. </p>
<p>

• Accredited by the Joint Commission on Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations (JCAHO) and CARF, the Rehabilitation Accreditation Commission. </p>
<p>

• As a non-profit organization, Mission Hospital commits ten percent of its net income to programs benefiting the underserved and 1.5 percent of its operating expenses to programs that benefit the community.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Sister of St. Joseph</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mission4health.com/">
Official hospital website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</hospital>
</article>
