<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:45:43[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<military_unit  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108198398">
<division  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108213205">
<army_unit  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108190754">
<header>
<title>Microsoft Research Asia</title>
<id>11354525</id>
<revision>
<id>241277051</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-27T06:09:43Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Amy.lixiurui</username>
<id>7949389</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Microsoft Research</category>
<category>Articles to be expanded since May 2007</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All articles to be expanded</category>
<category>Microsoft divisions</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Microsoft_Research_Asia&amp;action=edit">
improve this article or section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(May 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<b>Microsoft Research Asia</b>, Microsoft’s fundamental research arm in the Asia Pacific region, was founded on November 5th, 1998. In the past decade, the lab has conducted fundamental, curiosity-driven research with the goal of realizing Microsoft’s vision of future computing. By harnessing the best talent from across Asia and the world, it has grown into a world-class research lab. In 2004, MIT Technology Review named Microsoft Research Asia “the hottest computer lab in the world”.</p>
<p>

Over its ten-year history, Microsoft Research Asia has grown into an organization that employs over 350 researchers and engineers, has welcomed more than 2,500 interns, has awarded over 230 Microsoft fellowships, has published over 1,500 papers for top international journals and conferences, and has achieved many technological breakthroughs. </p>
<p>

Technologies from Microsoft Research Asia have had an influence not only within Microsoft but also on the broader community. Over 200 innovations from the lab have been transferred to Microsoft products, including Office XP, Office System 2003, Windows XP, Windows Server 2003, Windows XP Media Center Edition, Windows XP Tablet PC Edition, Xbox, MSN, Windows Live and our company’s latest releases – Windows Vista and Office 2007. In addition, technologies from the lab have been adopted by international standards bodies such as MPEG4 (error-resilient video transmission), IETF (TCP/IP header compression), and ITU/ISO (video-compression technology).</p>

<p>

<b>Many of these successes are the result of an ambitious research agenda that boils down to five areas central to Microsoft’s long-term vision and strategy:</b> 
■	Natural User Interfaces enable users to interact with a computer using speech, gestures, and expressions. </p>
<p>

■	Next-generation multimedia allows people to search for and to be immersed in interactive online shopping, education, meeting, and entertainment activities.</p>
<p>

■	Data-Intensive Computing explores the new infrastructures, algorithms. Tools, and applications to collect, analyze, and mine results for data-intensive business in both the consumer and enterprise sectors.</p>
<p>

■	Search and Online Ads take Web search and online advertising to the next level by applying data-mining, machine-learning, and knowledge-discovery techniques to information analysis, organization, retrieval, and visualization. </p>
<p>

■	Computer Science Fundamental includes areas such as theoretical computer science (theory), systems, networking, and machine learning that will have an impact on multiple applications and products. </p>



</bdy>
</army_unit>
</division>
</military_unit>
</article>
