<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:47:21[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Agile web development</title>
<id>11412687</id>
<revision>
<id>237750528</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-11T17:29:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>J.delanoy</username>
<id>2372780</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Web 2.0</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from July 2007</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since May 2008</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Agile software development</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
<category>Web development</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="150px" src="Merge-arrows.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrows
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  with . ()</col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Agile_web_development&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Agile+web+development%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(July 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>


Agile <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/611714.xml">
web development</link> is a model for development of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/288311.xml">
web applications</link>. Its concept is similar to <belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<doctrine wordnetid="105943300" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/639009.xml">
Agile software development</link></doctrine>
</belief>
, but is limited to web applications.  It is more efficient and powerful within a short timeline than other models, incorporates face-to-face communication, and includes technical personnel as well as customers as part of the team. Agile web development uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/239050.xml">
project manager</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/1579278.xml">
business analyst</link>s, emphases on clear goals, planning, and iterative delivery. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/11412687.xml">
Agile web development</link> ensures the successful completion of product at the end of each iteration. </p>
<p>

The agile web development model follows planning, requirement analysis, designing, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/40892.xml">
coding</link>, testing, and documentation developing stages parallel.  Successful interaction reaches toward to successful completion of application because of customer involvement hence we never met with the condition where we have to change the product due to changes in requirements, correct decision has to be taken by keeping customers confidence and informed choice, minimizing delays of the product. All the tasks are performed at given period, with just enough documentation to be effective. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Small time line.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Refined Team.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Clear planning.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Short Documentation.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Due to the regular involvement and feedback of the customer, the application tends to be more error free, more requirement oriented, and more user friendly. Also, tasks such as planning, development, design, coding, testing, etc. are done simultaneously, driven by the customer’s demands. It also reduces the development cycle time. The documentation of the application is less formal, to reduce the time taken and to be more human friendly. </p>
<p>

Agile methodology is similar to the iterative, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/263345.xml">
RAD</link> <link>
Prototype model</link>, but it has its own principles for developing a web application and it has introduced concepts that overcome the problems associated with existing models.</p>
<p>

For instance, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/33980.xml">
waterfall model</link> frequently changes requirements during the development life cycle, which means it fails whenever the requirements are changed at the end or not properly understood or implemented according to customers current feedback.  In the iterative incremental model, the development process moves according to the iterations. Requirements analysis, designing, and functional modification must be added at each version or iteration of a system to satisfy the customer feedback, and at last it is integrated into the system. Agile development adopted the key points from an iterative model but differs from iterative in relation to the timeboxes. An agile development life cycle devotes attention to a shorter time duration for completion of the project. With the help of timeboxes, developers can easily estimate the problem and correct it in a given time, so that at the end of each iteration, it is modified.</p>
<p>

Companies are moving towards Agile as it results in more Customer Satisfaction and hence there business - Says Amit Bathla.
</p>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://agilewebdevelopment.com/">
Agile Web Development</weblink>  (ruby on rails oriented)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://agilemanifesto.org/">
Agile Manifesto</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.agilealliance.org/">
Agile Alliance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.agilemodeling.com/essays/agileSoftwareDevelopment.htm">
Definition</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.agileskills.org/">
Agile Skills</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
