<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:49:25[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108058098">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>Robert W. Baird &amp; Co.</title>
<id>11477828</id>
<revision>
<id>210426482</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-05T21:52:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>UtherSRG</username>
<id>33145</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Financial services companies of the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Robert W. Baird &amp; Co.</b> is the principal U.S. operating subsidiary of Baird, an international employee-owned financial services firm, and one of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://money.cnn.com/galleries/2008/fortune/0801/gallery.bestcos_top50.fortune/39.html">
FORTUNE 100 Best Companies to Work For</weblink>.<p>

With more than 2,300 employees, Baird is one of the largest privately held, full-service investment firms in the United States. Baird manages and oversees $77 billion in assets.* </p>
<p>

Baird’s principal operating subsidiary outside the U.S. is Robert W. Baird Group Ltd. in Europe. Baird also has an operating subsidiary in Asia supporting its private equity operations.</p>
<p>

(*All assets are as of December 31, 2007)</p>

<sec>
<st>
Businesses</st>
<p>

Baird is a wealth management, capital markets, private equity and asset management firm that serves individuals, corporations, institutional investors and municipalities as financial advisor, asset manager, investment banker and specialist in equity research, private equity and public finance.</p>
<p>

Baird’s major business units focus on:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/2657389.xml">
Private Wealth Management</link> – Financial Advisors provide comprehensive financial advice and investment solutions. Baird Financial Advisors manage and oversee more than $58 billion in client assets.* </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Asset Management – Equity and fixed-income money managers serve investors including public and private retirement plans, corporations, foundations, other institutional clients and high-net-worth individuals. Combined, Baird Advisors and Baird Investment Management have $15.3 billion under management.* Baird also offers mutual funds through Baird Funds, including fixed income mutual funds managed by Baird Advisors and equity mutual funds managed by Investment Management.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Equity Capital Markets – The transatlantic investment banking team serves primarily middle-market companies and has advised on M&amp;A transactions and corporate financings totaling $94 billion over the last ten years. Additionally, equity sales and trading professionals make Baird’s equity research available to institutional investors in North America and Europe. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fixed Income Capital Markets – Baird has been the No. 1 underwriter in the Midwest for negotiated public finance issues under $20 million since 2002 (Source: Thomson Financial Securities Data). The fixed income sales and trading desk is active in both the primary and secondary markets for taxable and tax-exempt securities. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Private Equity – Partnerships in the U.S. and Europe leverage a global platform to help portfolio companies accelerate growth. Baird Capital Partners provides late-stage growth or change-of-control capital to U.S. middle-market companies in the areas of Business Services and Manufactured Products. Baird Venture Partners invests in early- and expansion-stage, U.S.-based companies in the areas of Business Services and Healthcare/Life Sciences. Baird Capital Partners Europe provides change-of-control and growth capital to mid-size companies in the United Kingdom, with a particular interest in Business Services and Manufactured Products. Granville Baird targets mid-market growth companies in Germany. Since inception, the private equity partnerships have raised and managed $2.4 billion in capital.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

(*All assets are as of December 31, 2007)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Founded in 1919 as the investment arm of the First Wisconsin National Bank, Baird is headquartered in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. In 1934, the firm became an independent entity, called The Securities Company of Milwaukee, Inc. When the firm joined the <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<geographic_point wordnetid="108578706" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<workplace wordnetid="104602044" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<stock_exchange wordnetid="104323026" confidence="0.8">
<exchange wordnetid="103302487" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/21560.xml">
New York Stock Exchange</link></exchange>
</stock_exchange>
</geographical_area>
</workplace>
</tract>
</location>
</geographic_point>
</landmark>
</point>
</position>
</region>
</site>
 in 1948, it took the name of its lead partner since inception, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/12327134.xml">
Robert W. Baird</link></scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
. From 1982 to 2004, Northwestern Mutual Life owned a majority interest in Baird. In 2004, Baird became a fully independent, employee-owned financial services firm.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Industry accolades</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Recognized as one of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://money.cnn.com/galleries/2008/fortune/0801/gallery.bestcos_top50.fortune/39.html">
FORTUNE 100 Best Companies to Work For</weblink> in 2004, 2005, 2006, 2007 &amp; 2008</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Named “Middle Market Investment Bank of the year” in 2008 by <it>Buyouts</it> magazine</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Named “Middle Market Bank of the Year” for 2006 by <it>Investment Dealers’ Digest''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Named 2008 “Manufacturing Sector Adviser of the Year” by <it>Acquisitions Monthly</it> in the UK</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Received “Deal of the Year” recognitions from <it>The M&amp;A Advisor</it> (2005, 2006 &amp; 2007)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Honored as advisor of the “Midwest Regional Deal of the Year” by <it>The Bond Buyer</it> in 2007</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Research analysts recognized repeatedly as “Best on the Street” by <it>The Wall Street Journal</it> (since 1993) and as “Top Equity Analysts” by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.forbes.com/2007/05/01/best-brokers-analysts-pf-07topanalysts-cz-sk_0501starmine_land.html">
Forbes.com/StarMine</weblink> (since 2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Financial Advisors named among the “Top 100 Financial Advisers” (2004, 2006, 2007 &amp; 2008) and the “100 Top Women Financial Advisers” (2006 and 2007) in the industry by <it>Barron’s</it> as well as the “Top-ranked Advisor Teams in America” by <it>Research</it> magazine (2005&ndash;2007), the “Top 100 Wirehouse Advisors” (2007) by <it>Registered Rep</it> magazine and the “Top 100 Wealth Advisors” (2007) by <it>Worth</it> magazine.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Senior executives</st>
<p>

Paul E. Purcell, Chairman, President &amp; Chief Executive Officer</p>
<p>

Steven G. Booth, Director of Investment Banking</p>
<p>

Paul J. Carbone, Director of Baird Private Equity</p>
<p>

Leslie H. Dixon, Chief Human Resources Officer</p>
<p>

Glen F. Hackmann, General Counsel</p>
<p>

Patrick S. Lawton, Director of Fixed Income Capital Markets</p>
<p>

William W. Mahler, Director of Institutional Sales</p>
<p>

Leonard M. Rush, CPA, Chief Financial Officer</p>
<p>

Michael J.  Schroeder, Director of Private Wealth Management</p>
<p>

Russell P. Schwei, CPA, Chief Operations and Information Officer</p>
<p>

Mary Ellen Stanek, CFA, Director of Asset Management</p>
<p>

Robert J. Venable, CFA, Director of Research</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References and external links</st>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rwbaird.com/">
Official Web site</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rwbaird.com/career/ca_index.asp">
Baird careers Web site</weblink></p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</company>
</article>
