<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:52:44[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108435388">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<network  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108434259">
<header>
<title>SDDEM</title>
<id>11483694</id>
<revision>
<id>207801153</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-24T07:06:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>BOTijo</username>
<id>3729068</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Enterprise model</category>
<category>Business theory</category>
<category>Enterprise modelling</category>
<category>Management</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from January 2008</category>
<category>Enterprise networks</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=SDDEM&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22SDDEM%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(January 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<b>Synchronization and Management of Different Distributed Enterprise Models</b> (SDDEM) is a research field related to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1674621.xml">
Business Process Modeling</link>. SDDEM targets at supporting the achievement of the organisational <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/41285.xml">
interoperability</link> between two or more different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organizations</link> by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/28738.xml">
synchronisation</link> of enterprise models.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Background </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Model synchronization </st>

<p>

Model synchronization is used to maintain the same “understandability” on models between independent organizations (model repositories) possible on multiple computing devices. For example, a partial model of a supplier might need to be synchronized with a partial model of its customer aligned with an overall supply chain model.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Enterprise modelling across organizations </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/7466964.xml">
Enterprise modeling</link> can help to achieve organisational interoperability and
can support the implementation of the necessary features for the
interoperability of systems by including interface descriptions and
infrastructure characteristics. Models can be very helpful in handling the
complexity within networks of interacting enterprises.
Provided that the models themselves are interoperable, they can to great extend simplify
tasks like federated analysis and simulation supporting the
identification of the interoperability effects between organisations. Enterprise interoperability is the scope of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
EU</link> supported network of excellence <link>
InterOP</link>, where the SDDEM research topic emerged within.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Interoperability of Models </st>

<p>

How to elaborate models across different organisations and how to deal with
already existing models within such modelling approach, is mainly an activity
of research organisations or consultancies, i.e. external actors. They currently apply proprietary concepts and do not necessarily produce generic interoperability solutions. </p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/41285.xml">
interoperability</link> between distributed and federated models can be
distinguished on three levels:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

. Enterprise <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/346781.xml">
modeling language</link> constructs → single elements of the model</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/7466964.xml">
Enterprise model</link>ing methods and methodologies → rules for the	combination of the single elements</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

. The content of the enterprise models → representation/expressing of information using a modelling language</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 SDDEM: The Understanding-Level interoperability </st>

<p>

The synchronisation and management of different distributed enterprise models
deals especially with this third level of model interoperability to
achieve a support of interoperability across organisations. The main
assumption behind SDDEM is that for the work with models across organisations it is
necessary to understand the <b>content</b> represented within the models. This holds
independently of what the models are destined for: to analyse a supply chain, or to be constantly used to monitor and improve the workflow between companies, etc.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Example Scenario </st>

<p>

The difficulties caused by divergent modeling can be illustrated by the problems of a company, for example a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/155500.xml">
SME</link> supplier, which has to participate into different co-operations and has to be compliant with the enterprise models of its partners. First of all, the modelling language might be considered. The solution for the language aspects could be the use of <link>
UEML</link> approach.</p>
<p>

In the next step, the content of the model needs to be related to the content of the other models. This includes considering the structure, the used constructs, terminology, etc. </p>
<p>

Moreover, for achieving both compatibility in the language and in the content (modelled information), the <b>management</b> of the decentralised models is required. How changes in the SME model are reflected in all network models, in which the SME participates? What are the results and implications of such changes? SDDEM addresses these problems, especially regarding model content and model management, though it does not claim to provide an “ultimate solution”.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Scope and Objectives </st>

<p>

The target of SDDEM is supporting the achievement of the organisational interoperability between two or more different organizations by the synchronisation of enterprise models. It covers the following two subjects and their relations:   
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Enterprise businesses (organisation and management of the cooperation and of the related processes),</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IT systems (requirement definitions on the IT systems, interface descriptions, necessary infrastructure, etc.).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
EU</link> vision of enterprises connected in ecosystems is supported by <link>
 InterOP NoE</link> by discussing the interoperability issue. Within this, SDDEM aims to provide the basis for semi-automatically aligning of models, distributed over various
organizational units, in such a way that consistent model systems are
established, suited for execution, simulation, monitoring and analysis of
workflow processes. 
Furthrmore, this aim supports a fast adaptation to the nowadays rapidly changing
environment. </p>
<p>

SDDEM deals mainly with the <b>content</b> of a model and not with modelling
languages. Consequently, it is related to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/49681.xml">
 ontology</link> issues and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Computer+science%22])">
 semantics</link>. It focuses on the organisational aspects of such models, i.e. the common understanding of modelling structure, constructs or naming of modelling elements to express the model content.</p>
<p>

The other aspect discussed in the context of SDDEM is the <b>management</b> of such distributed enterprise models. An enterprise model associated with different other models requires clear procedures for its evolution.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Related Technologies and Research Fields </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/32170.xml">
UML</link>, <link>
BPMI</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/3015586.xml">
BPMN</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/8725977.xml">
BPDM</link>, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/7284218.xml">
IEM</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 are related to the topic of Modelling across enterprises, but they are more focused on execution and modelling language issues. </p>
<p>

As
described before e.g. the work with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/32170.xml">
UML</link> models could also require mechanisms
to synchronise different models. </p>
<p>

<link>
UEML</link> is another way to allow different models work together using the same
language, provided that they are closely linked.
In the real world, very few enterprises and models are developed under identical 
environment, languages, and tools. In this terms, <link>
UEML</link> is a language, enabling a 
translation between other languages, rather than a model interoperability tool (which
is the aim of SDDEM).  The SDDEM approach takes into account <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/19159508.xml">
cultural</link> and regional differences, both in the enterprise way of working and in the way of developing models.
Nonetheless, with UEML support for the language level interoperability, the SDDEM goals become easier to achieve.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://153.97.93.166/sddem">
SDDEM Portal</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.interop-vlab.eu">
INTEROP-VLAB</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</network>
</group>
</system>
</article>
