<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:14:30[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Service-oriented analysis and design</title>
<id>1155393</id>
<revision>
<id>240885087</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-25T12:26:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>ABF</username>
<id>3048050</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since May 2008</category>
<category>Service-oriented (business computing)</category>
<category>Software design</category>
<category>Enterprise application integration</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Mergefrom.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that  be  into this article or section. ()</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

As <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/666924.xml">
service-oriented architecture</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/666924.xml">
SOA</link>) and the service-oriented computing platform mature more formal approaches and methodologies to building service-oriented solution logic have emerged. These build upon earlier analysis and design processes (including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/2613984.xml">
object-oriented analysis and design</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1674621.xml">
business process modeling</link>) and share in the common goal of promoting an effective means of achieving a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/234273.xml">
separation of concerns</link>.</p>
<p>

A number of common terms have surfaced in association with structured service and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/666924.xml">
SOA</link> delivery processes:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 service-oriented analysis</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 service-oriented design</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 service-oriented analysis and design (SOAD)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 service-modeling</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 service-oriented modeling</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 service-oriented modeling framework (SOMF)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 service-oriented modeling and architecture (SOMA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 business-driven development (BDD)</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
Service-oriented analysis</st>

<p>

This process generally refers to a pre-design effort centered around the definition of conceptual services or a conceptual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/666924.xml">
service-oriented architecture</link>. Much like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/2613984.xml">
object-oriented analysis</link>, the goal is often to achieve an ideal representation. A variation of service-oriented analysis is provided as part of the SOAD framework. The first vendor-agnostic service-oriented analysis process to be published was documented in Thomas Erl’s <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soabooks.com">
"Service-Oriented Architecture: Concepts, Technology, and Design"</weblink> in which the conceptual services were termed "service candidates". Service-oriented analysis is documented as part of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/dwbooks/soacompass.html">
"Service-Oriented Architecture Compass"</weblink>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Service-oriented design</st>
<p>

Generally following the completion of a service-oriented analysis, a service-oriented design process will continue by using the results of the service-oriented analysis as a starting point. This process usually subjects the conceptual services to real world factors and conditions, ultimately resulting in concrete service designs. Thomas Erl was also responsible for publishing the first vendor-agnostic service-oriented design process in his book, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soabooks.com">
"Service-Oriented Architecture: Concepts, Technology, and Design"</weblink>. As part of Erl’s process, service candidates produced by the service-oriented analysis process are used as input for service-oriented design. Coverage of service-oriented design was published in an article titled <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/dwbooks/soacompass.html">
"Service-Oriented Architecture Compass"</weblink>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Service-oriented analysis and design (SOAD)</st>
<p>

Created by IBM (and also referred to as "service-oriented architecture modeling and analysis"), this is an approach to software modeling and development specially designed for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/666924.xml">
service-oriented architecture</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/666924.xml">
SOA</link>). SOAD adds innovations for service repositories, service orchestration, and the enterprise service bus. It also helps design, build, aggregate, and deploy applications as Web services based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/29215.xml">
SOAP</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/4030790.xml">
WSDL</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/158694.xml">
UDDI</link> technologies. The term SOAD first was used in the article <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/webservices/library/ws-soad1/">
"Elements of Service-Oriented Analysis and Design"</weblink>. SOAD is further covered in   <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/dwbooks/soacompass.html">
"Service-Oriented Architecture Compass"</weblink> (by Bieberstein, Bose, Flammante, Jones, and Shah).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Service modeling</st>
<p>

Service modeling refers to a sub-process of the service-oriented analysis process documented in Thomas Erl’s book <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soabooks.com">
"Service-Oriented Architecture: Concepts, Technology, and Design"</weblink>. The service modeling process is responsible for the definition and refinement of service candidates based on various considerations, including a specific subset of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/4953034.xml">
service-orientation</link> principles.
</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Service-oriented modeling – an SOA modeling framework (SOMF)</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/12943175.xml">
Service-oriented modeling</link></it>
</indent>

One approach to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/12943175.xml">
service-oriented modeling</link>, known as service-oriented modeling framework (SOMF), has been created by Michael Bell and is documented in his book <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0470141115/ref=pd_cmp_a_img">
"Service-Oriented Modeling: Service Analysis, Design, and Architecture"</weblink>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The service-oriented modeling framework (SOMF) evocates that all software assets that we have been designing, architecting, constructing, and deploying to production environment are actually Services. 
<image location="right" width="150px" src="SOMF_V_1.1.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Service-Oriented Modeling Framework (SOMF) Version 1.1
</caption>
</image>
 
These entities are regarded as service-oriented assets that should be treated just like any other software piece in our world. The SOMF idea accentuates this notion since it offers a holistic and anthropomorphic modeling language, easy to use, and universal enough that business and technology personnel can jointly collaborate to model software for an organization. So what is the major advantage of this methodology? This approach does not tie SOMF modeling effort with any specific language platform. The SOMF simply deals with three major modeling aspects: structural, behavioral, and relationships of services. </p>
<p>

Thus, SOMF proposes three major service structures that make up a business application: atomic service - an indivisible software entity; composite service – software piece that aggregates other services and forms hierarchical relationship among its contained services; and last, service cluster – a conceptual structure that binds distributed services by their business or technological relationships and context.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.modelingconcepts.com/pdf/SOMF_ANALYSIS_MODELING.pdf">
SOMF Examples</weblink>"&#32;(Softcopy).&#32;  Methodologies Corporation.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.modelingconcepts.com/pages/download.htm">
SOMF Examples &amp; Language Notation</weblink>"&#32;(Softcopy).&#32;  Methodologies Corporation.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Service-oriented modeling and architecture (SOMA)</st>
<p>

SOMA refers to the more general domain of service modeling necessary to design and create SOA. SOMA covers a broader scope and implements service-oriented analysis and design (SOAD) through the identification, specification and realization of services, components that realize those services (a.k.a. "service components"), and flows that can be used to compose services.  </p>
<p>

SOMA includes an analysis and design method that extends traditional object-oriented and component-based analysis and design methods to include concerns relevant to and supporting SOA. It consists of three major phases of identification, specific and realization of the three main elements of SOA, namely, services, components that realize those services (aka service components) and flows that can be used to compose services.</p>
<p>

SOMA is an end-to-end SOA Method for the identification, specification, realization and implementation of services (including information services), components, flows (processes/composition).  SOMA builds on current techniques in areas such as domain analysis, functional areas grouping, variability-oriented analysis (VOA)
process modeling, component-based development, object-oriented analysis and design and use case modeling.  SOMA introduces new techniques such as goal-service modeling, service model creation and a service litmus test to help determine the granularity of a service.</p>
<p>

SOMA identifies services, component boundaries, flows, compositions, and information through complementary techniques which include domain decomposition, goal-service modeling and existing asset analysis.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Arsanjani, Ali&#32;(2004).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/webservices/library/ws-soa-design1/">
Service-Oriented Modeling and Architecture: How to Identify, Specify and Realize Services for your SOA</weblink>"&#32;(Softcopy).&#32;  IBM developerWorks.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bierberstein, Norbert;&#32;Sanjay Bose, Marc Fiammante, Keith Jones, Rawn Shah&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ibmpressbooks.com/bookstore/index.asp?rl=1/">
Service-Oriented Architecture (SOA) Compass: Business Value, Planning, and Enterprise Roadmap</weblink>"&#32;(Hardcover).&#32;  IBM Press (ISBN-13: 978-0-13-187002-4; Published: Oct 25, 2005; 272 pages).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Business-driven development (BDD)</st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/5378877.xml">
Business-driven development</link> is a methodology for developing IT solutions that directly satisfy business requirements. This is achieved by adopting a model-driven approach that starts with the business strategy, requirements and goals and then transforms them into an IT solution. The transformation is typically achieved by applying model transformations. Due to the alignment of the business layer and the IT layer, it is possible to propagate changes of the business (semi-)automatically to the IT systems. This leads to increased flexibility and shorter turnaround times when changing the business and adapting the IT systems. BDD shares these objectives with SOA and SOAD, which makes it one of the candidate methodologies for SOA design. SOMA and BDD can be used in combination.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Michael Bell, Service-Oriented Modeling: Service Analysis, Design, and Architecture, Wiley 2008,
 ISBN 978-0-470-14111-3</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Shan, Tony;&#32;Hua, Winnie&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.idea-group.com/articles/details.asp?id=5523">
A Service-Oriented Solution Framework for Internet Banking</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;  International Journal of Web Services Research, Vol. 3, Issue 1, pp 29-48.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Shan, Tony;&#32;Hua, Winnie&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/SCC.2006.99">
Solution Architecture for N-Tier Applications</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;  In Proc. of the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Services Computing (SCC 2006), pp. 349-356.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Erl, Thomas&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soabooks.com">
Service-Oriented Architecture: Concepts, Technology, and Design</weblink>"&#32;(Hardcover).&#32;  Prentice Hall (ISBN 0131858580, 796 pages).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Wada, Hiroshi;&#32;Suzuki, Junichi&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.umb.edu/~jxs/pub/">
A Service-Oriented Design Framework for Secure Network Applications</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;  In Proc. of the 30th IEEE International Conference on Computer Software and Applications Conference (COMPSAC 2006).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Wada, Hiroshi;&#32;Suzuki, Junichi&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.umb.edu/~jxs/pub/">
A Model-Driven Development Framework for Non-Functional Aspects in Service Oriented Grids</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;  In Proc. of 2nd IEEE International Conference on Autonomic and Autonomous Systems (ICAS 2006).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Zimmermann, Olaf;&#32;Schlimm, Pestel, Waller&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.perspectivesonwebservices.de/download/INF05-ServiceModelingv11.pdf">
Analysis and Design Techniques for Service-Oriented Development and Integration</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;  INFORMATIK 2005 — Informatik LIVE! Band 2, Beiträge der 35. Jahrestagung der Gesellschaft für Informatik e.V. (GI), Bonn, 19. bis 22. September 2005, ISBN 3-88579-396-2).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bell, Michael&#32;(2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0470141115/ref=pd_cmp_a_img">
Service-Oriented Modeling: Service Analysis, Design and Architecture</weblink>".&#32;  John Wiley &amp; Sons 2008, ISBN 978-0-470-14111-3.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/12943175.xml">
Service-oriented modeling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/4953034.xml">
Service-orientation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/928254.xml">
Enterprise service bus</link> (ESB)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
