<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:54:00[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<region  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108630985">
<administrative_district  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108491826">
<location  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100027167">
<district  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108552138">
<country  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108544813">
<header>
<title>Nordic model</title>
<id>11595783</id>
<revision>
<id>244448873</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T21:22:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jeff79</username>
<id>3491839</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All pages needing cleanup</category>
<category>Cleanup from April 2008</category>
<category>Economic systems</category>
<category>Articles lacking sources from June 2007</category>
<category>Economic policy</category>
<category>Articles that may contain original research since November 2007</category>
<category>All articles lacking sources</category>
<category>Economywide country studies</category>
<category>Nordic countries</category>
<category>Articles with weasel words</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <p>

This article or section has multiple issues. Please help <b><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Nordic_model&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink></b> or discuss these issues on the .
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It does not <b>cite any </b>. Please help improve it by citing . Tagged since June 2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It may contain  or . Tagged since October 2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Its  or factuality may be compromised by . Tagged since July 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It may require general  to meet Wikipedia's . Tagged since April 2008.</entry>
</list>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
<p>

The <b>Nordic model</b> refers to the economic and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/4735888.xml">
social model</link>s of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/153481.xml">
Nordic countries</link> (<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/76972.xml">
Denmark</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/10577.xml">
Finland</link></country>
, <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/5058739.xml">
Sweden</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</autocracy>
 and <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/21241.xml">
Norway</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
). This particular adaptation of the mixed market economy is characterized by more generous welfare states (relative to other developed countries), which are aimed specifically at enhacing individual autonomy through providing public sector employment opportunities (especially to women), ensuring the universal provision of basic human rights and stablizing the economy. It is distinguished from other welfare states with similar goals by its emphasis on maximizing labor force pariticipation, promoting gender equality, egalitiarian and extensive benefit levels, large magnitude of redistribution, and liberal use of expansionary fiscal policy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

On the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/345414.xml">
Index of Economic Freedom</link> 2008, Denmark's rating is 11th highest of 162 countries (4th in Europe), Finland's 16th, and Sweden's 27th.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>
<p>

Economic publications, such as the <it>"The Nordic Model - Embracing globalization and sharing risks"</it>, characterize the system as follows:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Strong property rights, contract enforcement, and overall ease of doing business.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Little barriers to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/59212.xml">
free trade</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Little <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/17020599.xml">
product market</link> regulation. Nordic countries rank very high in product market freedom according to OECD rankings.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Little <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/41916.xml">
financial market</link> regulation. Denmark and Finland have the lowest regulation burden in <link>
EU-15</link> according to OECD rankings.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 All Nordics have been pioneers in privatization. For instance, Sweden successfully privatized education with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/9750.xml">
education voucher</link>s in 1992.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Pension systems are privatized. Systems have higher pension funding rates than in most European countries. They still have deficits, however.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sweden has decentralized wage coordination, while Finland is ranked the least flexible.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Like in other European countries, the powerful labor unions tend to block reform attempts.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Reforms and favorable economic development seem to have reduced unemployment, which has traditionally been higher. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Denmark's social democrats managed to push reforms in 1994 and 1996. Denmark's flexible market differs radically from other Nordics (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/2726617.xml">
Flexicurity</link>). According to World Bank data, Denmark has almost no labor market regulation, ranking the first European country in labor freedom.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sweden at 56.6% of GDP, Denmark at 51.7%, and Finland at 48.6% reflects very high public spending, compared to 46.9% in Germany, 39.3% in Canada, and 33.5% in <island wordnetid="109316454" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/147575.xml">
Ireland</link></island>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A key reason for public spending is the very large number of bureaucrats. They often have jobs-for-life and make up around a third of the workforce (more than 38% in Denmark). The public sector's low productivity growth has been compensated by Europe's pioneering privatization and outsourcing programs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Public spending in social transfers such as unemployment benefits and early-retired programs is high. In 2001, the wage-based unemployment benefits were around 90% of wage in Denmark and 80% in Sweden, compared to 75% in Holland and 60% in Germany. Unemployed were also able to receive benefits several years before reductions, compared to quick benefit reduction in other countries. Public spending in areas such as education or health is not far from the OECD median.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Overall tax burden are among the world's highest; 51.1% of GDP in Sweden, and 43.3% in Finland, compared to 34.7% in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
, 33.5% in <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
, and 30.5% in <island wordnetid="109316454" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/147575.xml">
Ireland</link></island>
. Median employee's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/1632834.xml">
tax wedge</link>s is between 57%-65%. All income groups suffer from high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/15728486.xml">
effective marginal tax rate</link>s<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../067/217067.xml">
Value-added tax</link> rates are over 20% and corporate tax rates around the OECD median at around 26%. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/373814.xml">
Property tax</link>es are low or non-existent. The tax burden is particularly heavy on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/14551.xml">
service sector</link>s. Karlson, Johansson &amp; Johnsson estimates that the percentage of the buyer’s income entering the service vendor’s wallet (inverted tax wedge) is around 15% in Nordic countries, compared to 10% in Belgium, 15% in Germany, 25% in France, 30% in Ireland and 50% in the United States. Some taxation is avoided by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/2378247.xml">
self-service</link> and in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/18618063.xml">
black market</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Labor market</st>
<p>

In the Nordic countries, social regulations do not come from the law, like in southern Europe, but are defined in collective agreement. Thus, for example, minimum wages do not exist in Norway, Sweden, Finland or Denmark; each branch determines its own rules.  The high unionization rate (more of 85%) is partly coming from a historic tradition following violent conflicts in the 30s, partly from the importance of Nordic Trade Unions in the political life of the countries, and also by the services provided (unemployment insurance, support for the negotiation of individual salaries, bank and insurance services, holidays, etc.). The importance and influence of the Trade Unions is very high in the Nordic countries.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Education and research </st>
<p>

The Nordic countries are the highest spenders in Europe, both through the government training schemes and private sector, for education, training and research:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 According to the OECD, Denmark spends each year more than 7% of its GDP on education, Sweden 6,5% and Finland 6%, as opposed to 5,5% in United Kingdom. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 More than 80% of the Swedes are following a training each year, which is twice the European average</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sweden and Finland spend each year more than 4% of their GDP on research, Denmark 2,6% and the UK less than 2%. The Nordic countries, including Norway and Iceland, protected in 2002 more patents that France or United Kingdom, with less than 25 millions of inhabitants.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Public sector</st>
<p>

Sweden and Denmark were in 2004 the countries of the European union where the expenses of the public administrations were the highest, with respectively 57,2 and 56,3%, Finland a little on this side with 50,7%. The Nordic countries are quite near France (53,8%) and very distant from the British model, where taxes and public expenditure in general are much lower, but where people are generally expected to manage more of their own affairs for themselves.</p>
<p>

The Nordic countries are spending a large amount on social protection, as much as France and the UK: between 26,4% and 32,5% of the GDP for 30,6% in France and 27,6% in United Kingdom in 2004. The social benefits are high, with a high level social net: the welfare system payments are higher than anywhere else in Europe, including Germany, Italy, Spain or France. Such a level can cause problems: Finland reviewed its social and fiscal system because, for some groups, the fact of leaving unemployment for a job was too expensive.  This last point is considered a major issue by many in all of the Nordic countries.</p>
<p>

Almost all residents have access to a very comprehensive health system and social protection. Some Nordic economists believe that high social contributions put a positive weight on national production, when VAT is paid also on imported products.</p>
<p>

2004 health cost in Finland was 7.5% of GDP, 15.3% in the US, 10.5% in France and 8.1% in the UK. Management costs of social programs were, in 2005 according to Eurostat, 4% in France and 2.9% to Denmark.</p>
<p>

The crisis of the Nordic model in Sweden and Finland at the end of the 1980s and in the beginning of the 1990s pushed them to search for ways of making their welfare system more efficient. This was partly in an effort to install in the citizens’ minds a clear link between the taxes and the services they received, but also because the old systems were too costly to maintain. This decentralization has been in some countries quite extreme: in Finland, the whole sanitary and social system is under the responsibility of municipalities, which are sometimes quite small.</p>
<p>

Denmark recently reviewed the number of municipalities, dividing their number by 3 from 300 to 99, partly in order to oblige them to provide services to at least 30 000 inhabitants, and also to try and improve local government efficiency. Finland, Sweden, Norway are going in the same direction, but slowly.</p>
<p>

Sweden invented a labor market activation policy in the 1950s, when it decided to oblige unemployed people either to actively look for a job in support groups, or to train with a specific objective, or to participate as a trainee in the private or public sector. These activation schemes cost a lot: in 2003, Denmark dedicated 1.529% of  its GDP to active employment measures, Sweden 1.042% and Finland 0.748%, the EU average  being below 0.7%.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Other features</st>
<p>

Denmark is adopting heavy use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/277289.xml">
wind energy</link>, mainly through its national champion in this field, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/2377378.xml">
Vestas</link></company>
.  This is  currently meeting 20% of the country's energy requirements.</p>
<p>

Sweden is attempting to adopt a policy of being energy self-dependent by 2020 with an <politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../124/7112124.xml">
Oil phase-out in Sweden</link></social_relation>
</politics>
.</p>
<p>

Nordic countries generally have very high rates of gender equality by most measurements.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Performance</st>
<p>

We could sum up our description of the Nordic models: the productive private sector needs to be efficient and generate exports due to the small indigenous populations.  the workforce is highly unionised and therefore the unions have a major say in both the running of business and that of government.  The Governments ultimately have the biggest say in the management and development of the economy. Salaries (and taxes) are high,  and there is a comprehensive social security system open to all.</p>
<p>

There has been an overall strong economic recovery since the extreme economic malaise in the Nordic countries, especially Denmark and Sweden, suffered up to the 1990s when their currencies came under attack when members of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/335543.xml">
European Exchange Rate Mechanism</link>.  </p>
<p>

In recent years the following official figures have been reported:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Between 1984 and 2002, Sweden's GDP growth was 36% compared to 111% in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/14560.xml">
Ireland</link></country>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 High growth in the last years, (10,05 percent for the EU to 15 on 2000-2004, 15% for Finland 12,3% for Sweden, 4,4% for Sweden and 5,5% for Finland in 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Low unemployment, the lowest of the European union for Denmark (3,4% in March 2007…) after having known high levels 10 years ago (9,1% in Sweden, 9,6% to Denmark and 16,3% in Finland for 1993 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Po Official Official poverty risk rate are 9% in Sweden, 10% in Denmark, 11% in Finland, 13%in France and 19% in United Kingdom.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 According to libertarian think tank Timbo, when measured by wealth, the poor have less wealth than in the United States. For instance, they live in smaller apartments, have lower <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../963/373963.xml">
home ownership</link>, and have less household equipment. These findings are however contradicted by a peer-reviewed study in the American Economic Review by American economist Lane Kenworthy who found that the percentage of household living on less than 40% of U.S. median household income (adjusted for household size) was lowest in the Nordic countries, and much lower than in the U.S.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Governments have committed to fiscal responsibility. In 2004, Sweden, Finland and Denmark presented an excess of the public accounts (respectively of 1,2%, 1,9% and 2,6% of the GDP), whereas France presented a deficit of 3,7% and United Kingdom a deficit of 3,1%.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Flight of Capital, as is often seen in any country where taxes are significantly higher than their neighbors, incentive to move ones financial dealings outside of the country to avoid taxation can become a problem. As a result, some Danes and Swedes have emigrated or based their financial affairs outside of their home countries. Examples of this include <entrepreneur wordnetid="110060352" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<celebrity wordnetid="109903153" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/136763.xml">
Ingvar Kamprad</link></person>
</celebrity>
</entrepreneur>
, the Swede who founded furniture retail chain <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/14751.xml">
IKEA</link></company>
, who has lived in Switzerland for the past 30 years, while the Ikea business operates through a Netherlands-based holding company.  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/428379.xml">
Janus Friis</link></person>
, the co-founder of <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/424589.xml">
Skype</link></software>
, is now based in the UK and another very recent Danish example is the boxer <boxer wordnetid="109870208" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/2688815.xml">
Mikkel Kessler</link></boxer>
, who rebased to Monaco in 2007. Stephen Kinnock, son of former UK <party wordnetid="108256968" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/19279158.xml">
Labour Party</link></party>
 leader <politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/21978.xml">
Neil Kinnock</link></politician>
, and the husband of the Danish Socialist party leader <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/1728975.xml">
Helle Thorning Schmidt</link> also doesn't base himself in Denmark.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The extensive social services network can potentially lead to situations where a statistically significant amount of people live exclusively on unemployment benefits, without seeking employment. The magnitude of this problem is not certain, but it is worth noting that the countries following the Nordic model have very low unemployment.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 As <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/46313.xml">
globalisation</link> becomes a more accepted part of business and personal life, many companies are becoming more aware of international opportunities to cut costs, as with the high taxes and high cost of living, they are finding they can recruit employees cheaper abroad. Thus <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/235890.xml">
outsourcing</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/529536.xml">
offshoring</link> are becoming very common, especially in sectors such as IT and manufacturing, and many building construction companies are importing labour from the new Eastern European members of the <economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
European Union</link></economy>
, rather than recruit internally and pay Nordic salary levels.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Esping-Andersen, G. (1991). <it>The three worlds of welfare capitalism</it>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.etla.fi/files/1892_the_nordic_model_complete.pdf">
The Nordic Model</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spectator.co.uk/the-magazine/features/526631/made-in-sweden-the-new-tory-education-revolution.thtml">
Made in Sweden: the new Tory education revolution</weblink>, <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/64051.xml">
The Spectator</link></publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</press>
</creation>
</print_media>
</magazine>
</product>
</work>
</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.heritage.org/research/features/index/countries.cfm">
Index of Economic Freedom</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.etla.fi/files/1892_the_nordic_model_complete.pdf">
The Nordic Model</weblink> - Analysis of the Nordic Model</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scandinavian-social-model.tk">
 THE MYTH OF THE SCANDINAVIAN MODEL - An economic Critique of the Scandinavian Social Model</weblink> An analysis based on facts and figures</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</article>
