<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:47:28[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Not-To-Exceed (NTE)</title>
<id>11652270</id>
<revision>
<id>235322677</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-31T05:14:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Eastlaw</username>
<id>1046972</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>United States environmental law</category>
<category>Emissions reduction</category>
<category>Energy in the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<it>This article deals with an emissions standard for Heavy-Duty Diesel Engines which was created by the United States Environmental Protection Agency.</it>
<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Portal.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Energy&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Portal.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Ecology&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

The <b>Not-To-Exceed (NTE)</b> standard recently promulgated by the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
United States Environmental Protection Agency</link></agency>
 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
USEPA</link>) ensures that heavy-duty engine emissions are controlled over the full range of speed and load combinations commonly experienced in use. NTE establishes an area (the “NTE zone”) under the torque curve of an engine where emissions must not exceed a specified value for any of the regulated pollutants.  The NTE test procedure does not involve a specific driving cycle of any specific length (mileage or time). Rather it involves driving of any type that could occur within the bounds of the NTE control area, including operation under steady-state or transient conditions and under varying ambient conditions. Emissions are averaged over a minimum time of thirty seconds and then compared to the applicable NTE emission limits <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Creation of NTE</st>
<p>

NTE standards were created by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
USEPA</link> as a result of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/994191.xml">
consent decree</link> between the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
EPA</link> and several major diesel engine manufacturers.  These manufacturers included <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/668125.xml">
Caterpillar</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/1064863.xml">
Cummins</link></company>
, <manufacturer wordnetid="108060446" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/1041935.xml">
Detroit Diesel</link></institution>
</business>
</enterprise>
</company>
</manufacturer>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/5273296.xml">
Mack</link>, Mack's parent company <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/162292.xml">
Renault</link></company>
 Vehicles Industriels, and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/32412.xml">
Volvo</link></company>
 Truck Corp.  These manufacturers were accused of violating the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/697291.xml">
Clean Air Act</link> by installing devices that defeat emission controls. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.  As part of the resulting consent decree settlement with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
EPA</link>, these manufacturers were assessed heavy fines and were subjected to new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/652195.xml">
emissions standards</link> which included NTE.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Current requirements to achieve engine operation in the "NTE Zone"</st>
<p>

When all of the following conditions are simultaneously met for at least 30 seconds, and engine is considered to be operating in the NTE zone.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/9640.xml">
Engine</link> speed must be greater than 15% above idle speed  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Engine <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/30400.xml">
torque</link> must be greater than or equal to 30% of maximum torque. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Engine power must be greater than or equal to 30% of maximum <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/24236.xml">
power</link></concept>
</idea>
. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Vehicle <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/59211.xml">
altitude</link> must be less than or equal to 5,500&nbsp;feet (1,700&nbsp;m). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Ambient temperature must be less than or equal to 100&nbsp;°F (38&nbsp;°C) at sea level to 86°F at 5,500&nbsp;feet (1,700&nbsp;m). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/1047277.xml">
Brake specific fuel consumption</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/930457.xml">
BSFC</link>) must be less than or equal to 105% of the minimum BSFC if an engine is not coupled to a multi-speed manual or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/334940.xml">
automatic transmission</link>. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Engine operation must be outside of any manufacturer petitioned exclusion zone. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Engine operation must be outside of any NTE region in which a manufacturer states that less than 5% of in-use time will be spent.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

For <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/158740.xml">
Exhaust gas recirculation</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/158740.xml">
EGR</link>) equipped engines, the <link>
intake manifold</link> temperature must be greater than or equal to 86-100 degrees <unit_of_measurement wordnetid="113583724" confidence="0.8">
<definite_quantity wordnetid="113576101" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/11524.xml">
Fahrenheit</link></definite_quantity>
</unit_of_measurement>
, depending upon intake manifold pressure. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

For EGR-equipped engines, the engine coolant temperature must be greater than or equal to 125-140 degrees Fahrenheit, depending on intake manifold pressure. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Engine after treatment systems’ temperature must be greater than or equal to 250 degrees <unit_of_measurement wordnetid="113583724" confidence="0.8">
<definite_quantity wordnetid="113576101" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/19593040.xml">
Celsius</link></definite_quantity>
</unit_of_measurement>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Visual representations of NTE Zone</st>
<p>

<image location="center" width="380px" src="NTE_Zone_graphic_2.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Example NTE Control Area for Heavy-Duty Diesel Engine With 100% Operational Engine Speed Less Than 2400 rpm
</caption>
</image>
<image location="center" width="380px" src="NTE_Zone_graphic.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Example NTE Control Area for HeavyDuty Diesel Engine With 100% Operational Engine Speed Greater Than 2400 rpm
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Description</st>
<p>

The NTE test, as defined in CFR 86.1370-2007, establishes an area (NTE control area) under the torque curve of an engine where emissions must not exceed a specified emission cap for a given pollutant.  The NTE cap is set at 1.25 times the FTP emission limit as described in the subsection above.  For 2005 model year heavy-duty engines, the NTE emission cap for NMHC plus NOx is 1.25 times 2.5 grams per brake horsepower-hour, or 3.125 grams per <link>
brake horsepower</link>-hour.  The basic NTE control area for diesel engines has three basic boundaries on the engine’s torque and speed map.  The first is the upper boundary that is represented by an engine’s maximum torque at a given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/28748.xml">
speed</link>.  The second boundary is 30 percent of maximum torque.  Only operation above this boundary is included in the NTE control area.  The third boundary is determined based on the lowest engine speed at 50 percent of maximum power and highest engine speed at 70 percent of maximum power. This engine speed is considered the “15 percent operational engine speed”.  The fourth boundary is 30% of maximum power <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controversy and deficiency regarding NTE standards</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Controversy</st>
<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/7283.xml">
controversial</link> issue is the applicability of the NTE <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/18012.xml">
limits</link> to the real-world driving. In order for NTE standards to apply, the engine needs to remain within the NTE zone (limits include operation at a minimum of 30% of rated power) for at least 30 seconds. Concerns arose that performing this action could prove to be difficult, as each time the driver removes the foot from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/87920.xml">
accelerator</link> pedal, or shifts gears on vehicles with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/622145.xml">
manual transmission</link>, the engine leaves the NTE zone. </p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/764593.xml">
urban</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/28908.xml">
suburban</link> driving, this happens relatively often, to the point that NTE standards are applicable only a very small portion of the operation <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>
or, in some cases, not at all. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/22934.xml">
probability</link> of the engine remaining within the NTE zone for over 30 seconds also decreases with the advent of high-power engines. For example, if the power required to maintain a motorcoach or an over-the-road truck at highway cruising speed is somewhere around 150&nbsp;hp (110&nbsp;kW), the probability that a 475&nbsp;hp (354&nbsp;kW) engine will consistently operate at loads above 30%, without “dips” to lower power levels, can be relatively small.   </p>
<p>

These concerns were confirmed by studies carried out by <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/185979.xml">
West Virginia University</link></university>
 (WVU) under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/994191.xml">
Consent Decree</link>s. WVU found that “remaining for 30 seconds within the NTE zone can be quite difficult.  The resulting low NTE availability poses a problem as many measurements within the NTE area have to be rejected along with those from outside the NTE area.  The question arises if in this way all real-life emissions are sufficiently ‘well reflected’ in the NTE test results”<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

A second issue of concern in the same vein is a case when an engine is compliant within the NTE zone, but exhibits elevated NOx at power levels just outside the NTE zone, or at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/1211612.xml">
idle</link>.  For reasons such as this the Working Group On Off Cycle Emissions is studying whether an extension of the NTE zone is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/61032.xml">
rational</link> as they ponder if there are spots on the engine map (outside of the NTE zone) that have a significant contribution in real life <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/10181.xml">
emissions</link>.  Their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/5212692.xml">
preliminary</link> findings echo those of WVU as they found that the time of engine operation in the NTE zone is rather low. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
EPA admitted deficiencies</st>
<p>

According to the US EPA there are technical limitations of NTE under limited operating conditions which have caused the EPA to “carve-out” (see graphs above) certain portions of the NTE zone to allow for these <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/321847.xml">
deficiencies</link>. Excerpts as follows:</p>
<p>

<it>“NTE zone was defined by a desire to have a homogeneous emissions limit. Carve-outs within that zone exclude certain areas of operation from NTE consideration or limit how much emissions from that operation can contribute to an NTE result, deficiencies allow temporary exceedences of the NTE standards due to technical limitations under limited operating conditions. The idea is not to hold the manufacturer responsible for NTE compliance during modes where the engine is not capable of operating or where it is not technically feasible to meet the NTE standards.”</it> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Regarding the particulate matter “carve-out”</st>
<p>

<it>"<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/286688.xml">
PM</link>-specific region is “carved out” of the NTE control area. The PM specific
area of exclusion is generally in the area under the torque curve, where engine
speeds are high and engine torque is low, and can vary in shape depending upon several
speed-related criteria and calculations detailed in the regulations. Controlling PM in this
range of operation presents fundamental technical challenges which we believe can not be overcome in the 2004 time frame. Specifically, the cylinder pressures created under these high speed and low load conditions are often insufficient to prevent lube oil from being ingested into the combustion chamber. High levels of PM emissions are the result.
Furthermore, we do not believe that these engines spend a significant portion of their
operating time in this limited speed and torque range"</it> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Lawsuits and settlement</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Lawsuits</st>
<p>

In 2001, five separate lawsuits were filed against the US <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
EPA</link> by the Engine Manufacturers Association (EMA) and several individual trucking industry entities (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/1506903.xml">
International Truck and Engine Corporation</link>). Each of those lawsuits challenged the
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/1144105.xml">
legality</link> and technological <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/4832472.xml">
feasibility</link> of certain engine emission control standards in EPA
regulations now referred to as NTE requirements.  In their challenge, EMA stated that to determine whether an engine meets a primary emission standard, engines are tested and assessed using a standardized 20-minute emissions laboratory test known as the Federal Test Procedure. The NTE, by contrast, has no specified test procedure and potentially could apply over an almost infinite number of test conditions. This, in the manufacturers’ view, made it virtually impossible to ensure total compliance with the NTE—since there is no real or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/95170.xml">
practical</link> way to test an engine under all conceivable conditions—and so made the NTE both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
unlawful</link> (the CAA authorizes EPA to adopt engine standards AND accompanying test procedures) and technically infeasible.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Settlement</st>
<p>

On June 3, 2003, the parties finalized a settlement of their disputes pertaining to the NTE standards. The parties agreed upon a detailed outline for a future regulation that would require a manufacturer-run heavy-duty in-use NTE testing (“HDIUT”) program for diesel-fueled engines and vehicles. One section of the outline stated: </p>
<p>

<it>“The NTE Threshold will be the NTE standard, including the margins built into the existing regulations, plus additional margin to account for in-use measurement accuracy. This additional margin shall be determined by the measurement processes and methodologies to be developed and approved by EPA/CARB/EMA. This margin will be structured to encourage instrument manufacturers to develop more and more accurate instruments in the future.”</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
HDIUT and Portable Emissions Measurement Systems (PEMS)</st>
<p>

The ultimate objective of the new HDIUT program is to allow for a significant streamlining of engine certification if a truly robust in-use emissions testing program proves feasible and cost effective.  Time-consuming and expensive laboratory assessments of engines could then give way to real-world, real-time emissions assessments that efficiently provides more relevant data.</p>
<p>

Basically, the HDIUT is an industry agreed to manufacturer run, in-use, on-road testing program.  It builds upon the original NTE standard.  It is designed to focus on compliance in the real world, and relies on emissions testing, utilizing <control wordnetid="103096960" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<regulator wordnetid="104072193" confidence="0.8">
<mechanism wordnetid="103738472" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/11108817.xml">
Portable Emissions Measurement System</link></mechanism>
</regulator>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</control>
s (PEMS) with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/286685.xml">
NOx</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/426169.xml">
HC</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/234610.xml">
CO</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/286688.xml">
PM</link> being the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollutants</link> to be measured. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>  Measurement Accuracy Margins are being established to account for the emissions measurement variability associated with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/11108817.xml">
PEMS</link> in-use. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/697291.xml">
Clean Air Act</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<plan wordnetid="105898568" confidence="0.8">
<plan_of_action wordnetid="105902545" confidence="0.8">
<policy wordnetid="105901508" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/11058555.xml">
Mobile Emission Reduction Credit (MERC)</link></policy>
</plan_of_action>
</plan>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<legislative_act wordnetid="106564387" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<plan wordnetid="105898568" confidence="0.8">
<legal_document wordnetid="106479665" confidence="0.8">
<plan_of_action wordnetid="105902545" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<policy wordnetid="105901508" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="106532095" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/7186486.xml">
Global Warming Solutions Act of 2006</link></act>
</policy>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</social_relation>
</plan_of_action>
</legal_document>
</plan>
</document>
</idea>
</legislative_act>
</politics>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/643401.xml">
Clear Skies Act of 2003</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/10934212.xml">
Air pollution</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/3752162.xml">
Atmospheric dispersion modeling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/652195.xml">
Emission standard</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<plan wordnetid="105898568" confidence="0.8">
<plan_of_action wordnetid="105902545" confidence="0.8">
<policy wordnetid="105901508" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/2780146.xml">
European emission standards</link></system_of_measurement>
</policy>
</plan_of_action>
</plan>
</standard>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/9506027.xml">
Criteria air contaminants</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/7332857.xml">
Pollutant Standards Index</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/627819.xml">
Automobile emissions control</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/1621705.xml">
National Ambient Air Quality Standards</link> (USA EPA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/3201.xml">
Attribution of recent climate change</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/9742791.xml">
Western Regional Climate Action Initiative</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<control wordnetid="103096960" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<regulator wordnetid="104072193" confidence="0.8">
<mechanism wordnetid="103738472" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/11108817.xml">
Portable Emissions Measurement System</link></mechanism>
</regulator>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</control>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.epa.gov</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.enginemanufacturers.org/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dieselnet.com/standards/">
Dieselnet pages on vehicle emission standards</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/enviro_scores.pdf">
US EPA Vehicle Environmental Performance Score Specifications</weblink><message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link></format>
</language>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;(26.5&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/149755.xml">
KiB</link>).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/nvfel/">
EPA National Vehicle and Fuel Emissions Laboratory</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/ttn/catc/">
EPA Clean Air Technology Center</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/otaq/cert/hd-cert/stds-eng.pdf">
Emission Standards Reference Guide</weblink><message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link></format>
</language>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;(141&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/149755.xml">
KiB</link>) for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/182436.xml">
heavy</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/183749.xml">
duty</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/25897.xml">
nonroad</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/9640.xml">
engine</link>s. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.fueleconomy.gov/ </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fueleconomy.gov/feg/tax_hybrid_new.shtml">
Federal Income Tax Credits for Hybrids placed in service</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.epa.gov/globalwarming</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.environmentalhealthnews.org/">
Environmental health news</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ucsusa.org/clean_vehicles/vehicles_health/automaker-rankings-2007.html">
Automaker Rankings 2007: The Environmental Performance of Car Companies</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 Dieselnet,"Applicability and Test Cycles", Emission Standards » United States Heavy-Duty Truck and http://www.dieselnet.com/standards/us/hd.html</entry>
<entry id="2">
 Mike Osenga, "Diesel industry confronts the emission settlement EPA enforcement of the Clean Air Act affects entire diesel engine industry)(Industry Overview)", <it>Diesel Progress North American Edition</it>, (Published 12/1/98) http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-53919838.html</entry>
<entry id="3">
 US EPA Office of Transportation and Air Quality, "In-Use Testing Program for Heavy-Duty Diesel Engines and Vehicles, Technical Support Document" <it>Document EPA420-R-05-006</it> (Published June 2005) http://epa.gov/otaq/regs/hd-hwy/inuse/420r05006.pdf</entry>
<entry id="4">
 State of California AIR RESOURCES BOARD, "PUBLIC HEARING TO CONSIDER AMENDMENTS TO ADOPT 
NOT-TO-EXCEED AND EURO III EUROPEAN STATIONARY CYCLE EMISSION TEST PROCEDURES FOR THE 2005 AND SUBSEQUENT MODEL YEAR HEAVY-DUTY DIESEL ENGINES", <it>STAFF REPORT: INITIAL STATEMENT OF REASONS</it> (Date of Release: October 20, 2000) http://www.arb.ca.gov/regact/ntetest/isor.doc</entry>
<entry id="5">
 </entry>
<entry id="6">
Study on Emission Control Technology For Heavy Duty Vehicles, "In-use Conformity Testing of Emissions Control Devices", Study Prepared for the European Comissiom - DG ENTR (Enterprise), (May 2002) http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/automotive/pagesbackground/emission_control/vol_5-in-use_conformity_testing.pdf</entry>
<entry id="7">
Riemersma, Iddo. "WNTE Control Area Evaluation With Respect to The Real-World Engine Operation Envelope", Prepared for the 13th meeting of the Working Group on Off-Cycle Emission, (Presented 5-7 April 2006). http://www.oica.net/htdocs/WWH/Off%20cycle/13th%20meeting/Informal%20Doc%20No%20%2042%20-%20Presentatie%20OCE-NTE%20meeting%20final.pdf</entry>
<entry id="8">
United States Environmental Protection Agency, "Control of Emissions of Air Pollution from 2004 and Later Model Year Heavy-Duty Highway Engines and Vehicles; Revision of Light-duty Truck Definition", 40 CFR Parts 85 and 86 (1999) http://www.epa.gov/otaq/regs/hd-hwy/1999nprm/nprm-4c.pdf</entry>
<entry id="9">
 Engine Manufacturers Association,"Questions and Answers Regarding the EMA-EPA
Heavy-duty NTE Settlement", (June 11, 2003)http://www.enginemanufacturers.org/admin/library/upload/371.pdf</entry>
<entry id="10">
United States Environmental Protection Agency, "Test Plan to Determine PEMS Measurement
Allowances for the Gaseous Emissions Regulated under the Manufacturer-Run Heavy-Duty Diesel Engine In-Use Testing", Docket #OAR-2004-0072-0069, (May 20, 2005)
Programhttp://www.epa.gov/otaq/highway-diesel/regs/testplan.pdf</entry>
<entry id="11">
Spears, Matt (of the USEPA), "U.S. EPA PEMS Measurement Allowance Program", Presentation for 2007 JRC Conference on Mar 19, 2007. http://transportenv07.jrc.it/pdf/C/C_2_20_Spears_M_US%20Measurement%20Allowance%20Program.pdf</entry>
<entry id="12">
Shimpi,Shirish A. (of Cummins) "US Engine Manufacturer Views on In-Use Testing", Presentation for 2007 JRC Conference on Mar 19, 2007. http://transportenv07.jrc.it/pdf/C/C_1_19_Shimpi_S_US%20Manufacturer%20Views%20on%20In-Use%20Emissions.pdf</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
