<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:55:36[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<computer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103082979">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<device  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103183080">
<machine  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103699975">
<web_site  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106359193">
<header>
<title>Knowledge community</title>
<id>11679632</id>
<revision>
<id>214073655</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-22T00:07:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Iridescent</username>
<id>937705</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles that may contain original research</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from January 2008</category>
<category>Community websites</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
<category>Articles that may contain original research since January 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Knowledge_community&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Knowledge+community%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(January 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section may contain  or .</b>
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Knowledge_community&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink> by adding . See the for details. <it>(January 2008)</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

A knowledge community is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/5695.xml">
community</link> construct, stemming from the convergence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/72896.xml">
knowledge management</link> as a field of study and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/850579.xml">
social exchange theory</link>. Formerly known as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/1978984.xml">
discourse community</link> and having evolved from forums and web forums, knowledge communities are now often referred to as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/10115122.xml">
community of practice</link> or virtual community of practice.  As with any field of study, there are various points of view on the motivations, organizing principles and subsequent structure of knowledge communities.  </p>
<p>

<b>Perspectives</b></p>
<p>

As a web or virtual construct, knowledge communities can be said to have evolved from bulletin board systems, web forums and online discourse communities through the 80s and 90s.  When framed with the scores of social networking sites coming online at the turn of the millennia, knowledge communities can be described as another form of social media.  The biggest difference between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link> sites and knowledge communities is, social network sites typically lack moderation or an outcome orientation.</p>
<p>

Stemming from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/850579.xml">
social exchange theory</link>, a well-established perspective is to view knowledge communities as a type of exchange. The motivations for participating in the exchange vary. The exchange remains open based on the perceived value (e.g., return on time investment) to knowledge community members. </p>
<p>

Knowledge communities can also be viewed as a method by which to do organizational or process <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/118450.xml">
innovation</link>. KCs are often founded to introduce change to a system, an organizational or societal by identifying, creating, representing and/or distributing data, information and/or knowledge in and via a community context on the pretext that more significant value will be created via a knowledge value chain.</p>
<p>

From an organizational perspective, knowledge communities serve to maintain the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/7273911.xml">
strong ties</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/7273911.xml">
weak ties</link> of the organization with many diverse publics; they help feed quality back into the organization (via more timely feedback and narrative analysis of discussions), drive organization credibility (via more rich exposure and building public trust by incorporating diverse opinion) and speed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/230647.xml">
knowledge transfer</link> and knowledge utilization, as well as do <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/12362106.xml">
Knowledge Mobilization</link> (e.g., by providing a conversation space to bridge gaps between research and practice). </p>
<p>

Common across perspectives is, knowledge communities can be employed to identify, create, represent, and/or distribute knowledge within and/or between populations</p>
<p>

<b>Organizational Behavior and Structure</b></p>
<p>

Knowledge communities nurture and facilitate ongoing relationships and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/9037547.xml">
Knowledge Ecosystem</link> where ideas are exchanged on an ongoing basis. Knowledge value is generated (derived, realized) during the transactional nature of the exchange.  Existing knowledge can be synthesized (e.g. research fused with ideas from the field or other research) or new knowledge created via exchanges.  KCs use a variety of two-way communication tools (e.g., via discussion board, article commenting, rating, poll, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/1558384.xml">
webinar</link> ) to foster discussion and the exchange of ideas.  </p>
<p>

The organizational structure of knowledge communities varies significantly based on sponsorship and purpose.  Contribution, moderation and content governance within knowledge communities is typically distributed amongst a core set of community members who become community moderator\facilitators.  At a minimum, members of knowledge communities typically include a mix of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/1958462.xml">
subject matter expert</link>s, moderators,  facilitators and the general public or a target population.</p>
<p>

While information within a knowledge community is usually promoted to be open and public, persons are able to keep information private as well. Public information within knowledge communities is sometimes covered by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/245719.xml">
Creative Commons Licenses</link> and is given credit to the creators. Knowledge communities are seen as a bridge between traditional publishing models and an open access systems.</p>
<p>

<b>Pitfalls</b></p>
<p>

Knowledge communities and communities or practice suffer from the same pitfalls of all communities.  To some, the mission driven orientation can be a detractor to creativity.  To others, the exchange aspects of reek of the over commodification of culture and by pooling experts or like-minded persons, KCs and CoPs can often be less diverse than traditional communities.  Perhaps the societal response has been the emergence of social networks.  Again, however, it is important to point out social networks and knowledge communities are related, but not the same.  </p>
<p>

<b>See Also</b></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/303330.xml">
Collaboration</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/10115122.xml">
Community of Practice</link> (CoP)</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/118450.xml">
Innovation</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/8071599.xml">
Knowledge building communities</link> (KBC)</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/5118075.xml">
Knowledge value chain</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/9037547.xml">
Knowledge Ecosystem</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/12362106.xml">
Knowledge Mobilization</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/4223528.xml">
Learning Community</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/1392681.xml">
Learning organization</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/15870253.xml">
Professional Learning Community</link> (PLC)</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/1091610.xml">
Virtual Community of Practice</link> (VCoP)</p>
<p>

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/1070215.xml">
Virtual team</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/1614337.xml">
Value Network</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/5303055.xml">
Value Network Analysis</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/176320.xml">
Virtual Community</link> (VC)</p>

</bdy>
</web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</article>
