<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:02:38[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Knowledge space</title>
<id>11851855</id>
<revision>
<id>204093095</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-07T22:51:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>American Eagle</username>
<id>6584471</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Knowledge representation</category>
<category>Cognition</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/2081516.xml">
mathematical psychology</link>, a <b>knowledge space</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/5170.xml">
combinatorial structure</link> describing the possible states of knowledge of a human learner.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
To form a knowledge space, one models a domain of knowledge as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/454886.xml">
set</link> of concepts, and a feasible state of knowledge as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/27631.xml">
subset</link> of that set containing the concepts known or knowable by some individual. Typically, not all subsets are feasible, due to prerequisite relations among the concepts. The knowledge space is the family of all the feasible subsets. Knowledge spaces were introduced in 1985 by <link>
Jean-Paul Doignon</link> and <link>
Jean-Claude Falmagne</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> and have since been studied by many other researchers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> They also form the basis for two computerized tutoring systems, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wundt.kfunigraz.ac.at/rath/">
RATH</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aleks.com/">
ALEKS</weblink>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><p>

It is possible to interpret a knowledge space as a special form of a restricted latent class model<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.</p>
<p>

<b>Knowledge space</b> is also a term used with a different meaning in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/13692155.xml">
philosophy</link> by <link>
Pierre Lévy</link> in his 1997 book <it>Collective Intelligence</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Definitions</st>
<p>

Some basic definitions used in the knowledge space approach:
A tuple <math>(Q, K)</math> consisting of a non-empty set <math>Q</math> and a set <math>K</math> of subsets from <math>Q</math> is called a <it>knowledge structure</it> if <math>K</math> contains the empty set and <math>Q</math>.
A knowledge structure is called a <it>knowledge space</it> if it is closed under union, i.e. if <math>S, T \in Q</math> implies <math>S\cup T</math>.
A knowledge space is called a <it>quasi-ordinal knowledge space</it> if it is in addition closed under intersection, i.e. if <math>S, T \in Q</math> implies <math>S\cap T</math>.
The well-known Birkhoff Theorem shows that there is a one-to-one correspondence between the set of all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/23582.xml">
quasiorders</link> on Q and the set of all quasi-ordinal knowledge spaces on Q, i.e. each quasi-ordinal knowledge space can be represented by a quasi-order and vice versa.</p>
<p>

An important subclass of knowledge spaces, the <it>well-graded knowledge spaces</it> or <it>learning spaces</it>, can be defined as satisfying two mathematical axioms:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 If <math>S</math> and <math>T</math> are both feasible subsets of concepts, then <math>S\cup T</math> is also feasible. In educational terms: if it is possible for someone to know all the concepts in <it>S</it>, and someone else to know all the concepts in <it>T</it>, then we can posit the potential existence of a third person who combines the knowledge of both people.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 If <math>S</math> is a nonempty feasible subset of concepts, then there is some concept <it>x</it> in <it>S</it> such that <math>S\setminus\{x\}</math> is also feasible. In educational terms: any feasible state of knowledge can be reached by learning one concept at a time.</entry>
</list>

A set family satisfying these two axioms forms a mathematical structure known as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/667063.xml">
antimatroid</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Construction</st>
<p>

In practice there exist several methods to construct knowledge spaces. The most frequently used method is querying experts. There exists several querying algorithms which allow one or several experts to construct a knowledge space by answering a sequence of simple questions<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>.
Another method is to construct the knowledge space by explorative data analysis (for example by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/16569923.xml">
Item tree analysis</link>) from data
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>.</p>
<p>

A third method is to derive the knowledge space from an analysis of the problem solving processes in the corresponding domain<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite id="CITEREFDoignonFalmagne1999" style="font-style:normal">Doignon, J.-P.&#32;&amp;&#32;Falmagne, J.-Cl.&#32;(1999),&#32;<it>Knowledge Spaces</it>, Springer-Verlag, ISBN 3-540-64501-2</cite>&nbsp;.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite id="CITEREFDoignonFalmagne1985" style="font-style:normal">Doignon, J.-P.&#32;&amp;&#32;Falmagne, J.-Cl.&#32;(1985),&#32;"Spaces for the assessment of knowledge",&#32;<it>International Journal of Man-Machine Studies</it>&#32;<b>23</b>:  175–196</cite>&nbsp;.</entry>
<entry id="3">
A <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wundt.uni-graz.at/kst.php">
bibliography on knowledge spaces</weblink> maintained by Cord Hockemeyer contains over 300 publications on the subject.</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wundt.uni-graz.at/MathPsych/cda/overview_sokrates.htm">
Introduction to Knowledge Spaces: Theory and Applications</weblink>, Christof Körner, Gudrun Wesiak, and Cord Hockemeyer, 1999 and 2001.</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite id="CITEREFSchrepp2005" style="font-style:normal">Schrepp, M.&#32;(2005),&#32;<it>About the connection between knowledge structures and latent class models.</it>, Methodology, 1 (3) ,92-102.</cite>&nbsp;.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Jillian Dellit, <it>Education (and EdNA) in the knowledge age</it>, available at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csu.edu.au/special/online99/proceedings99/206b.htm">
http://www.csu.edu.au/special/online99/proceedings99/206b.htm</weblink> accessed 19 July 2007</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite id="CITEREFKoppen1993" style="font-style:normal">Koppen, M.&#32;(1993),&#32;<it>Extracting human expertise for constructing knowledge spaces: An algorithm.</it>, Journal of Mathematical Psychology, 37 ,1-20</cite>&nbsp;.</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite id="CITEREFKoppenDoignon1990" style="font-style:normal">Koppen, M.&#32;&amp;&#32;Doignon, J.-P.&#32;(1990),&#32;<it>How to build a knowledge space by querying an expert.</it>, Journal of Mathematical Psychology, 34 ,311-331</cite>&nbsp;.</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite id="CITEREFSchrepp1999" style="font-style:normal">Schrepp, M.&#32;(1999),&#32;<it>Extracting knowledge structures from observed data.</it>, British Journal of Mathematical and Statistical Psychology, 52 ,213-224</cite>&nbsp;.</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite id="CITEREFSchrepp2003" style="font-style:normal">Schrepp, M.&#32;(2003),&#32;<it>A method for the analysis of hierarchical dependencies between items of a questionnaire.</it>, Methods of Psychological Research --- Online, 19 ,43-79</cite>&nbsp;.</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite id="CITEREFAlbertLukas1999" style="font-style:normal">Albert, D.&#32;&amp;&#32;Lukas, J.&#32;(1999),&#32;<it>Knowledge Spaces: Theories, Empirical Research, Applications.</it>, Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Mahwah, NJ</cite>&nbsp;.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
