<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:04:15[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Model of hierarchical complexity</title>
<id>11911464</id>
<revision>
<id>210781900</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-07T11:29:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mdd</username>
<id>113850</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>behavior</category>
<category>Complex systems theory</category>
<category>cognition</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>model of hierarchical complexity,</b> is a framework for scoring how complex a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/4805.xml">
behavior</link> is. It quantifies the order of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/13998.xml">
hierarchical</link> complexity of a task based on mathematical principles of how the information is organized and of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/149354.xml">
information science</link>. This model is developed by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<journalist wordnetid="110224578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/12669356.xml">
Michael Commons</link></journalist>
</writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 and others since the 1980s.
<sec>
<st>
  Overview </st>
<p>

The Model of Hierarchical Complexity, which has been presented as a formal theory <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, is a framework for scoring how complex a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/4805.xml">
behavior</link> is. Developed by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<journalist wordnetid="110224578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/12669356.xml">
Michael Commons</link></journalist>
</writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, it quantifies the order of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/13998.xml">
hierarchical</link> complexity of a task based on mathematical principles of how the information is organized <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>, and of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/149354.xml">
information science</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. Its forerunner was the <link>
General Stage Model</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>. It is a model in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/2081516.xml">
mathematical psychology</link>.</p>
<p>

Behaviors that may be scored include those of individual humans or their social groupings (e.g., organizations, governments, societies), animals, or machines. It enables scoring the complexity of human reasoning in any domain. It is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/1486561.xml">
cross-cultural</link>ly valid. The reason it applies cross-culturally is that the scoring is based on the mathematical complexity of the hierarchical organization of information. Scoring does not depend upon the content of the information (e.g., what is done, said, written, or analyzed) but upon how the information is organized.</p>
<p>

The MHC is a non-mentalistic model of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/1058840.xml">
developmental stages</link>. It specifies 14 orders of hierarchical complexity and their corresponding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/1058840.xml">
stages</link>. It is different from previous proposals about developmental stage applied to humans <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>. Instead of attributing behavioral changes across a person’s age to the development of mental structures or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/48031.xml">
schema</link>, this model posits that task sequences form hierarchies that become increasingly complex. Because less complex tasks must be completed and practiced before more complex tasks can be acquired, this accounts for the developmental changes seen, for example, in individual persons’ performance of tasks. (For example, a person cannot perform <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../118/3118.xml">
arithmetic</link> until the numeral representations of numbers are learned. A person cannot multiply numbers until addition is learned). Furthermore, previous theories of stage have confounded the stimulus and response in assessing stage by simply scoring responses and ignoring the task or stimulus. The Model of Hierarchical Complexity separates the task or stimulus from the performance. The participant’s performance on a task of a given complexity represents the stage of developmental complexity.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Vertical complexity of tasks performed </st>
<p>

One major basis for this developmental theory is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/1225101.xml">
task analysis</link>. The study of ideal tasks, including their instantiation in the real world, has been the basis of the branch of stimulus control called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/438004.xml">
psychophysics</link>. Tasks are defined as sequences of contingencies, each presenting stimuli and each requiring a behavior or a sequence of behaviors that must occur in some non-arbitrary fashion. The complexity of behaviors necessary to complete a task can be specified using the horizontal complexity and vertical complexity definitions described below. Behavior is examined with respect to the analytically-known complexity of the task.</p>
<p>

Tasks are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/19595649.xml">
quantal</link> in nature. They are either completed correctly or not completed at all. There is no intermediate state. For this reason, the Model characterizes all stages as hard and distinct.  The orders of hierarchical complexity are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/19595649.xml">
quantized</link> like the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/9476.xml">
electron</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/1206.xml">
atomic orbitals</link> around the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/54411.xml">
nucleus</link>. Each task difficulty has an order of hierarchical complexity required to complete it correctly. Since tasks of a given order of hierarchical complexity require actions of a given order of hierarchical complexity to perform them, the stage of the participant’s performance is equivalent to the order of complexity of the successfully completed task. The quantal feature of tasks is thus particularly instrumental in stage assessment because the scores obtained for stages are likewise discrete.</p>
<p>

Every task contains a multitude of subtasks (Overton, 1990). When the subtasks are carried out by the participant in a required order, the task in question is successfully completed. Therefore, the model asserts that all tasks fit in some sequence of tasks, making it possible to precisely determine the hierarchical order of task complexity. Tasks vary in complexity in two ways: either as **horizontal** (involving classical information); or as **vertical** (involving hierarchical information).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Horizontal complexity </st>
<p>

Classical information describes the number of “yes-no” questions it takes to do a task. For example, if one asked a person across the room whether a penny came up heads when they flipped it, their saying “heads” would transmit 1 bit of “horizontal” information. If there were 2 pennies, one would have to ask at least two questions, one about each penny. Hence, each additional 1-bit question would add another bit. Let us say they had a four-faced top with the faces numbered 1, 2, 3, and 4. Instead of spinning it, they tossed it against a backboard as one does with dice in a game of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/6062.xml">
craps</link>.  Again, there would be 2 bits. One could ask them whether the face had an even number. If it did, one would then ask if it were a 2. Horizontal complexity, then, is the sum of bits required by just such tasks as these.               </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Vertical complexity </st>
<p>

Hierarchical complexity refers to the number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/25407.xml">
recursion</link>s that the coordinating actions must perform on a set of primary elements. Actions at a higher order of hierarchical complexity: (a) are defined in terms of actions at the next lower order of hierarchical complexity; (b) organize and transform the lower-order actions (see Figure 2); (c) produce organizations of lower-order actions that are new and not arbitrary, and cannot be accomplished by those lower-order actions alone. Once these conditions have been met, we say the higher-order action coordinates the actions of the next lower order.</p>
<p>

To illustrate how lower actions get organized into more hierarchically complex actions, let us turn to a simple example.  Completing the entire operation 3 x (4 + 1) constitutes a task requiring the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../118/103118.xml">
distributive</link> act. That act non-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/3019808.xml">
arbitrarily</link> orders adding and multiplying to coordinate them. The distributive act is therefore one order more hierarchically complex than the acts of adding and multiplying alone; it indicates the singular proper sequence of the simpler actions. Although simply adding results in the same answer, people who can do both display a greater freedom of mental functioning. Thus, the order of complexity of the task is determined through analyzing the demands of each task by breaking it down into its constituent parts. </p>
<p>

The hierarchical complexity of a task refers to the number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/19616384.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22An+example%22])">
concatenation</link> operations it contains, that is, the number of recursions that the coordinating actions must perform. An order-three task has three concatenation operations. A task of order three operates on a task of order two and a task of order two operates on a task of order one (a simple task).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Stages of development </st>
<p>

The notion of stages is fundamental in the description of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/10326.xml">
human</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/19653842.xml">
organism</link>ic, and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.computing.dcu.ie/~humphrys/Notes/GA/advanced.topics.html">
http://www.computing.dcu.ie/~humphrys/Notes/GA/advanced.topics.html</weblink> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/1174964.xml">
machine</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/3533357.xml">
evolution</link>.  Previously it has been defined in some ad hoc ways.  Here, it is described formally in terms of the Model of Hierarchical Complexity (MHC). </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Formal definition of stage</st>
<p>

Since actions are defined inductively, so is the function <it>h</it>, known as the order of the hierarchical complexity. To each action <it>A</it>, we wish to associate a notion of that action's hierarchical complexity, <it>h(A)</it>. Given a collection of actions <b>A</b> and a participant <it>S</it> performing <b>A</b>, the <it>stage of performance</it> of <it>S</it> on <b>A</b> is the highest order of the actions in <b>A</b> completed successfully at least once, i.e., it is
stage (<it>S</it>, <b>A</b>) = max{<it>h(A)</it> | <it>A</it> (epsilon) <b>A</b> and <it>A</it> completed successfully by <it>S</it>}. Thus, the notion of stage is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/2661487.xml">
discontinuous</link>, having the same gaps as the orders of hierarchical complexity. This is in agreement with previous definitions (Commons et al., 1998; Commons &amp; Miller, 2001; Commons &amp; Pekker, 2007).</p>
<p>

Because MHC stages are conceptualized in terms of the hierarchical complexity of tasks rather than in terms of mental representations (as in Piaget’s stages), the highest stage represents successful performances on the most hierarchically complex tasks rather than intellectual maturity. Table 1 gives descriptions of each stage.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Stages of hierarchical complexity</st>
<p>

Table 1. Stages described in the Model of Hierarchical Complexity
<indent level="1">

| class="wikitable"
</indent>
|-
! Order or Stage
! What they do
! How they do it
! End result
|-
| 0 - calculatory
| Exact –- no <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/12746.xml">
generalization</link>, computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/5926.xml">
computation</link>s (computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/5213.xml">
computing</link> computations)
| Human-made programs manipulate 0, 1, not 2 or 3.
| None
|-
| 1 - sensory or motor
| Discriminate in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/217914.xml">
rote</link> fashion, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/569399.xml">
stimuli</link> generalization, move  
| Move limbs, lips, toes, eyes, elbows, head  View objects or move
| <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/364332.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Philosophical+basis+of+behavioral+research%22])">
Discriminative</link> establishing and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/188540.xml">
conditioned</link> reinforcing stimuli
|-
| 2 - circular sensory-motor
| Form open-ended <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/20696.xml">
proper classes</link> 
| Reach, touch, grab, shake objects, circular babble 
| Open ended proper classes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/22980.xml">
phoneme</link>s, archiphonemes
|-
| 3 - sensory-motor
| Form <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/6978.xml">
concept</link>s
| Respond to stimuli in a class successfully 
| <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/18852.xml">
Morpheme</link>s, concepts
|-
| 4 - nominal
| Find <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/38227.xml">
relation</link>s among concepts.  Use names
| Find relations among concepts  Use names
| Single words: ejaculatives &amp; exclamations, verbs, nouns, number names, letter names
|-
| 5 - sentential
| <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/577858.xml">
Imitate</link> and acquire sequences  Follows short sequential acts
| Generalize match-dependent task actions.  Chain words
| Pronouns: my, mine, I, me, myself; yours, you, yourself, yourselves; we, ours, us, ourselves, our; they, them; myself, ourselves, yourself, yourselves; thou, thee, thyself, thine; youse, youse guys, you-uns, yis, yinz; he, him, himself, his; she, her, herself, hers; it, itself, its; themselves, their, theirs
|-
| 6 - preoperational
| Make simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/61093.xml">
deduction</link>s. Follow lists of sequential acts.  Tell stories.
| Count <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/60931.xml">
event</link> events and objects  Connect the dots  Combine numbers and simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../094/81094.xml">
proposition</link>s
| Connectives: as, when, then, why, before; products of simple operations
|-
| 7 - primary
| Simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/3729225.xml">
logic</link>al deduction and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/307139.xml">
empirical</link> rules involving time sequence  Simple arithmetic
| Adds, subtracts, multiplies, divides, counts, proves, does series of tasks on own
| Times, places, counts acts, actors, arithmetic outcome, sequence from calculation
|-
| 8 - concrete
| Carry out full <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../118/3118.xml">
arithmetic</link>, form <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/1267764.xml">
clique</link>s, plan deals
| Does <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/313384.xml">
long division</link>, short division, follows complex <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/7830.xml">
social rules</link>, ignores simple social rules, takes and coordinates <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/480711.xml">
perspective</link> of other and self	
| Interrelations, social events, what happened among others, reasonable deals, history, geography
|-
| 9 - abstract
| Discriminate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/32818.xml">
variable</link>s such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/18956166.xml">
stereotype</link>s; logical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/228806.xml">
quantification</link>; (none, some, all)
| Form variables out of finite classes  Make and quantify propositions
| Variable time, place, act, actor, state, type; quantifiers  (all, none, some); <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/2418429.xml">
categorical assertions</link> (e.g., “We all die")
|-
| 10 - formal
| Argue using empirical or logical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/5236854.xml">
evidence</link>  Logic is linear, 1 dimensional
| Solve problems with one unknown using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/18716923.xml">
algebra</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/3729225.xml">
logic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/10174.xml">
empiricism</link>
| Relationships (for example: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/37196.xml">
causality</link>) are formed out of variables; words: linear, logical, one dimensional, if then, thus, therefore, because; correct <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/26700.xml">
scientific</link> solutions
|-
| 11- systematic
| Construct multivariate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19008728.xml">
matrices</link>
| Coordinates more than one variable as input.  Consider relationships in contexts.    
| <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/60931.xml">
Event</link>s and concepts situated in a multivariate context; systems are formed out of relations; systems: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
legal</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/37235.xml">
societal</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/7485.xml">
corporate</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/6639133.xml">
economic</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/21754.xml">
nation</link>al
|-
| 12 - metasystematic
| Construct multi-systems and metasystems out of disparate systems
| Create metasystems out of systems Compare systems and perspectives Name properties of systems: e.g. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/13564.xml">
homomorphic</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../828/14828.xml">
isomorphic</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/56054.xml">
complete</link>, consistent (such as tested by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/75802.xml">
consistency proof</link>s), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/2615477.xml">
commensurable</link>
| Metasystems and supersystems are formed out of systems of relationships
|-
| 13 - paradigmatic  
| Fit metasystems together to form new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/175308.xml">
paradigm</link>s
| Synthesize metasystems
| Paradigms are formed out of multiple metasystems
|-
| 14 - cross-paradigmatic
| Fit paradigms together to form new fields
| Form new fields by crossing paradigms
| New fields are formed out of multiple paradigms
|}</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Relationship with Piaget’s theory </st>
<p>

There are some commonalities between the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/1058599.xml">
Piagetian</link> and Commons’ notions of stage and many more things that are different.  In both, one finds: </p>
<p>

1. Higher order actions defined in terms of lower order actions. This forces the hierarchical nature of the relations and makes the higher order tasks include the lower ones and requires that lower order actions are hierarchically contained within the relative definitions of the higher order tasks.</p>
<p>

2. Higher order of complexity actions organize those lower order actions. This makes them more powerful. Lower order actions are organized by the actions with a higher order of complexity, i.e., the more complex tasks.</p>
<p>

What Commons et al. (1998) have added includes:</p>
<p>

3. Higher order of complexity actions organize those lower order actions in a non-arbitrary way.</p>
<p>

This makes it possible for the Model’s application to meet real world requirements, including the empirical and analytic. Arbitrary organization of lower order of complexity actions, possible in the Piagetian theory, despite the hierarchical definition structure, leaves the functional correlates of the interrelationships of tasks of differential complexity formulations ill-defined. The following dimensions are inherent in the application:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Task and performance are separated	</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 All tasks have an order of hierarchical complexity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 There is only one sequence of orders of hierarchical complexity.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Hence, there is structure of the whole for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/13028195.xml">
ideal tasks</link> and actions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 There are gaps between the orders of hierarchical complexity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Stage is defined as the most hierarchically complex task solved. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 There are gaps in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/2161615.xml">
Rasch</link> Scaled Stage of Performance.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Performance stage is different task area to task area.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 There is no structure of the whole—horizontal decaláge—for performance. It is not inconsistency in thinking within a developmental stage. Decaláge is the normal modal state of affairs.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Orders and corresponding stages </st>
<p>

The MHC specifies 15 orders of hierarchical complexity and their corresponding stages, showing that each of Piaget’s substages, in fact, are hard stages. Commons also adds four postformal stages: Systematic stage 11, Metasystematic stage 12, Paradigmatic stage 13, and Crossparadigmatic stage 14.  It may be the Piaget's consolidate formal stage is the same as the systematic stage.  There is one other difference in the orders and stages.  At the suggestion of Biggs and Biggs, the sentential stage 5 was added.  The sequence is as follows: (0) computory, (1) sensory &amp; motor, (2) circular sensory-motor, (3) sensory-motor, (4) nominal, the new (5) sentential, (6) preoperational, (7) primary, (8) concrete, (9) abstract, (10) formal, and the four postformal: (11) systematic, (12) metasystematic, (13) paradigmatic, and (14) cross-paradigmatic.  The first four stages (0-3) correspond to Piaget’s sensorimotor stage at which infants and very young children perform.  The sentential stage was added at Fischer’s suggestion (1981, personal communication) citing Biggs &amp; Collis (1982).  Adolescents and adults can perform at any of the subsequent stages.  MHC stages 4 through 5 correspond to Piaget’s pre-operational stage; 6 through 8 correspond to his concrete operational stage; and 9 through 11 correspond to his formal operational stage. </p>
<p>

The three highest stages in the MHC are not represented in Piaget’s model.  These stages from the Model of Hierarchical Complexity have extensively influenced the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/12108792.xml">
Positive Adult Development</link>.  Few individuals perform at stages above formal operations. More complex behaviors characterize multiple system models (Kallio, 1995; Kallio &amp; Helkama, 1991). Some adults are said to develop alternatives to, and perspectives on, formal operations. They use formal operations within a “higher” system of operations and transcend the limitations of formal operations. In any case, these are all ways in which these theories argue for and present converging evidence that adults are using forms of reasoning that are more complex than formal operations with which Piaget’s model ended.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Empirical research using the model </st>
<p>

The MHC has a broad range of applicability.  The mathematical foundation of the model makes it an excellent research tool to be used by anyone examining performance that is organized into stages.  It is designed to assess development based on the order of complexity which the individual utilizes to organize information.  The MHC offers a singular mathematical method of measuring stages in any domain because the tasks presented can contain any kind of information. The model thus allows for a standard quantitative analysis of developmental complexity in any cultural setting.  Other advantages of this model include its avoidance of mentalistic or contextual explanations, as well as its use of purely quantitative principles which are universally applicable in any context. </p>
<p>

The following can use the Model of Hierarchical Complexity to quantitatively assess developmental stages: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/1486561.xml">
Cross-cultural</link> developmentalists;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Animal developmentalists; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<branch wordnetid="108401248" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/9703.xml">
Evolutionary psychologists</link></geographical_area>
</branch>
</tract>
</location>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</field>
</region>
;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/15450.xml">
Organizational psychologists</link>;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Developmental political psychologists; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Learning theorists;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/25140.xml">
Perception</link> researchers;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/14400.xml">
History of science</link> historians;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Educators;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Therapists;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/569.xml">
Anthropologists</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The following list shows the large range of domains to which the Model has been applied.  In one representative study, Commons, Goodheart, and Dawson (1997) found, using Rasch (1980) analysis, that hierarchical complexity of a given task predicts stage of a performance, the correlation being r = .92. Correlations of similar magnitude have been found in a number of the studies.  </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 List of examples </st>
<p>

List of examples of tasks studied using the Model of Hierarchical Complexity or <it>Fischer’s Skill Theory</it> (1980):
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Algebra (Commons, in preparation) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Animal stages (Commons &amp; Miller, 2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Atheism (Commons-Miller, 2005) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Attachment and Loss (Commons, 1991; Miller &amp; Lee, 2000)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Balance beam and pendulum (Commons, Goodheart, &amp; Bresette, 1995; Commons, Pekker, et al, 2007)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Contingencies of reinforcement (Commons, in preparation) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Counselor stages (Lovell, 2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Empathy of Hominids (Commons &amp; Wolfsont, 2002)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Epistemology (Kitchener &amp; King, 1990; Kitchener &amp; Fischer, 1990)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Evaluative reasoning (Dawson, 2000)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Four Story problem (Commons, Richards &amp; Kuhn, 1982; Kallio &amp; Helkama, 1991)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Good Education (Dawson-Tunik, 2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Good Interpersonal (Armon, 1989)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Good Work (Armon, 1993)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Honesty and Kindness (Lamborn, Fischer &amp; Pipp, 1994) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Informed consent (Commons &amp; Rodriguez, 1990, 1993; Commons, Goodheart, Rodriguez, &amp; Gutheil, 2006; Commons, Rodriguez, Adams, Goodheart, Gutheil, &amp; Cyr, 2007).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Language stages (Commons, et al., 2007)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Leadership before and after crises (Oliver, 2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Loevinger's Sentence Completion task (Cook-Greuter, 1990) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Moral Judgment, (Armon &amp; Dawson, 1997; Dawson, 2000)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Music (Beethoven) (Funk, 1989)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Orienteering (Commons, in preparation) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Physics tasks (Inhelder &amp; Piaget, 1958)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Political development (Sonnert &amp; Commons, 1994)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Relationships (Armon, 1984a, 1984b)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Report patient's prior crimes (Commons, Lee, Gutheil, et al., 1995)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Social perspective-taking (Commons &amp; Rodriguez, 1990; 1993)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Spirituality (Miller &amp; Cook-Greuter, 2000)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tool Making of Hominids (Commons &amp; Miller 2002)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Views of the Agood life@ (Armon, 1984c; Danaher, 1993; Dawson, 2000; Lam, 1995)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Workplace culture (Commons, Krause, Fayer, &amp; Meaney, 1993)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Workplace organization (Bowman, 1996a, 1996b)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Writing (Commons &amp; DeVos, 1985)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Commons &amp; Pekker, 2007 </entry>
<entry id="2">
(Commons, Trudeau, Stein, Richards, &amp; Krause, 1998)</entry>
<entry id="3">
(Coombs, Dawes, &amp; Tversky, 1970)</entry>
<entry id="4">
 (Commons &amp; Richards, 1984a, 1984b;  Lindsay &amp; Norman, 1977;  Commons &amp; Rodriguez,  1990,  1993)</entry>
<entry id="5">
(Commons &amp; Richards, 1984a, 1984b)</entry>
<entry id="6">
(e.g., Inhelder &amp; Piaget, 1958)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Copyright permissions</entry>
</list>

Portions of this article are from “Applying the Model of Hierarchical Complexity” by  Commons, M. L., Miller, P. M., Goodheart, E. A., Danaher-Gilpin, D., Locicero, A., Ross, S. N. Unpublished manuscript. Copyright 2007 by Dare Association, Inc. Available from Dare Institute, commons@tiac.net. Reproduced and adapted with permission of the publisher. Portions of this article are also from “Introduction to the Model of Hierarchical Complexity” by M. L. Commons, in the Behavioral Development Bulletin, 13, 1-6 (http://www.behavioral-development-bulletin.com/).  Copyright 2007 Martha Pelaez. Reproduced with permission of the publisher.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Literature </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Armon, C. (1984a). Ideals of the good life and moral judgment: Ethical reasoning across the life span. In M. L. Commons, F. A. Richards, &amp; C. Armon (Eds.), <it>Beyond formal operations: Vol. 1. Late adolescent and adult cognitive development</it> (pp. 357-380).  New York: Praeger.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Armon, C. (1984c). Ideals of the good life and moral judgment:  Evaluative reasoning in children and adults. <it>Moral Education Forum</it>, 9(2).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Armon, C. (1989). Individuality and autonomy in adult ethical reasoning.  In M. L. Commons, J. D. Sinnott, F. A. Richards, &amp; C. Armon (Eds.), <it>Adult development, Vol. 1. Comparisons and applications of adolescent and adult developmental models</it>, (pp. 179-196). New York: Praeger.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Armon, C. (1993). The nature of good work: A longitudinal study. In J. Demick &amp; P. M. Miller (Eds.), <it>Development in the workplace</it> (pp. 21-38). Hillsdale, NJ: Erlbaum.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Armon, C. &amp; Dawson, T. L. (1997).  Developmental trajectories in moral reasoning across the life-span. <it>Journal of Moral Education</it>, 26, 433-453. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Biggs, J. &amp; Collis, K.  (1982).  A system for evaluating learning outomes:  The SOLO Taxonomy. New York: Academic Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bowman, A. K. (1996b). Examples of task and relationship 4b, 5a, 5b statements for task performance, atmosphere, and preferred atmosphere.  In M. L. Commons, E. A. Goodheart, T. L. Dawson, P. M. Miller, &amp; D. L. Danaher, (Eds.) <it>The general stage scoring system (GSSS)</it>. Presented at the Society for Research in Adult Development, Amherst, MA. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L. (1991). A comparison and synthesis of Kohlberg's cognitive-developmental and Gewirtz's learning-developmental attachment theories.  In J. L. Gewirtz &amp; W. M. Kurtines (Eds.), Intersections with attachment (pp. 257-291).  Hillsdale, NJ: Erlbaum.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Goodheart, E. A., &amp; Bresette, L. M. with Bauer, N. F., Farrell, E. W., McCarthy, K. G., Danaher, D. L., Richards, F. A., Ellis, J. B., O'Brien, A. M., Rodriguez, J. A., and Schraeder, D. (1995). Formal, systematic, and metasystematic operations with a balance-beam task series: A reply to Kallio's claim of no distinct systematic stage.  <it>Adult Development</it>, 2 (3), 193-199.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Goodheart, E. A., &amp; Dawson T. L. (1997). <it>Psychophysics of Stage: Task Complexity and Statistical Models</it>. Paper presented at the International Objective Measurement Workshop at the Annual Conference of the American Educational Research Association, Chicago, IL.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Goodheart, E. A., Pekker, A., Dawson, T. L., Draney, K., &amp; Adams, K. M. (2007).  Using Rasch scaled stage scores to validate orders of hierarchical complexity of balance beam task sequences. In E. V. Smith, Jr. &amp; R. M. Smith (Eds.).  <it>Rasch measurement: Advanced and specialized applications</it> (pp. 121-147). Maple Grove, MN: JAM Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Goodheart, E. A., Rodriguez, J. A., Gutheil, T. G.  (2006). Informed Consent:  Do you know it when you see it?  <it>Psychiatric Annals</it>, June, 430-435.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Krause, S. R., Fayer, G. A., &amp; Meaney, M. (1993). Atmosphere and stage development in the workplace. In J. Demick &amp; P. M. Miller (Eds.). <it>Development in the workplace</it> (pp. 199-220). Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Lee, P., Gutheil, T. G., Goldman, M., Rubin, E. &amp; Appelbaum, P. S. (1995). Moral stage of reasoning and the misperceived "duty" to report past crimes (misprision).  <it>International Journal of Law and Psychiatry</it>, 18(4), 415-424.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., &amp; Miller, P. A.  (2001).  A quantitative behavioral model of developmental stage based upon hierarchical complexity theory.  <it>Behavior Analyst Today</it>, 2(3), 222-240.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Miller, P. M.  (2002). A complete theory of human evolution of intelligence must consider stage changes: A commentary on Thomas Wynn’s Archeology and Cognitive Evolution. Behavioral and Brain Sciences. 25(3), 404-405. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M.  L., &amp; Miller, P.  M. (2004). Development of behavioral stages in animals.  In Marc Bekoff (Ed.).  <it>Encyclopedia of animal behavior</it>. (pp. 484-487). Westport, CT: Greenwood Publishing Group.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., &amp; Pekker, A. (2007).  Hierarchical Complexity: A Formal Theory. Manuscript submitted for publication.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., &amp; Richards, F. A. (1984a).  A general model of stage theory. In M. L. Commons, F. A. Richards, &amp; C. Armon (Eds.), <it>Beyond formal operations: Vol. 1.  Late adolescent and adult cognitive development</it> (pp. 120-140). New York: Praeger.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., &amp; Richards, F. A. (1984b). Applying the general stage model. In M. L. Commons, F. A. Richards, &amp; C. Armon (Eds.), <it>Beyond formal operations: Vol. 1.  Late adolescent and adult cognitive development</it> (pp. 141-157). New York: Praeger.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Richards, F. A., &amp; Kuhn, D. (1982).  Systematic and metasystematic reasoning: A case for a level of reasoning beyond Piaget's formal operations.  <it>Child Development</it>, 53, 1058-1069.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Rodriguez, J. A. (1990).  AEqual access" without "establishing" religion: The necessity for assessing social perspective-taking skills and institutional atmosphere. <it>Developmental Review</it>, 10, 323-340.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Rodriguez, J. A. (1993). The development of hierarchically complex equivalence classes. <it>Psychological Record</it>, 43, 667-697.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Rodriguez, J. A.  (1990).  "Equal access" without "establishing" religion:  The necessity for assessing social perspective-taking skills and institutional atmosphere.  <it>Developmental Review</it>, 10, 323-340.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., Trudeau, E. J., Stein, S. A., Richards, F. A., &amp; Krause, S. R. (1998).  The existence of developmental stages as shown by the hierarchical complexity of tasks.  <it>Developmental Review</it>, 8(3), 237-278.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons, M. L., &amp; De Vos, I. B.  (1985). <it>How researchers help writers</it>. Unpublished manuscript available from Commons@tiac.net.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commons-Miller, N. H. K.  (2005). <it>The stages of atheism</it>.  Paper presented at the Society for Research in Adult Development, Atlanta, GA.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cook-Greuter, S. R. (1990). Maps for living: Ego-development theory from symbiosis to conscious universal embeddedness. In M. L. Commons, J. D. Sinnott, F. A. Richards, &amp; C. Armon (Eds.). <it>Adult Development: Vol. 2, Comparisons and applications of adolescent and adult developmental models</it> (pp. 79-104). New York: Praeger.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Coombs, C. H., Dawes, R. M., &amp; Tversky, A.  (1970). <it>Mathematical psychology:  An elementary introduction</it>. Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey:  Prentice-Hall.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Danaher, D.  (1993). <it>Sex role differences in ego and moral development: Mitigation with maturity</it>.  Unpublished dissertation, Harvard Graduate School of Education.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dawson, T. L. (2000). Moral reasoning and evaluative reasoning about the good life. <it>Journal of Applied Measurement, 1 (372-397). </it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dawson Tunik, T. L. (2004). "A good education is" The development of evaluative thought across the life span. <it>Genetic, Social, and General Psychology Monographs</it>, 130, 4 112.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fischer, K. W. (1980). A theory of cognitive development: The control and construction of hierarchies of skills. <it>Psychological Review</it>, 87(6), 477-531.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Funk, J. D.  (1989). Postformal cognitive theory and developmental stages of musical composition.  In M. L. Commons, J. D. Sinnott, F. A. Richards &amp; C. Armon (Eds.), <it>Adult Development: (Vol. 1) Comparisons and applications of developmental models</it> (pp. 3-30).  Westport, CT: Praeger. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Inhelder, B., &amp; Piaget, J.  (1958). <it>The growth of logical thinking from childhood to  adolescence: An essay on the development of formal operational structures</it>. (A. Parsons, &amp; S. Seagrim, Trans.). New York: Basic Books (originally published 1955).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kallio, E.  (1995).  Systematic Reasoning: Formal or postformal cognition? <it>Journal of Adult Development</it>, 2, 187 192.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kallio, E., &amp; Helkama, K.  (1991).  Formal operations and postformal reasoning: A replication. <it>Scandinavian Journal of Psychology</it>.  32(1), 18 21. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kitchener, K. S., &amp; King, P. M. (1990). Reflective judgement: Ten years of research.  In M. L. Commons, C. Armon, L. Kohlberg, F. A. Richards, T. A. Grotzer, &amp; J. D. Sinnott (Eds.), <it>Beyond formal operations: Vol. 2.  Models and methods in the study of adolescent and adult thought</it> (pp. 63-78).  New York: Praeger.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kitchener, K. S. &amp; Fischer, K. W. (1990). A skill approach to the development of reflective thinking. In D. Kuhn (Ed.), Developmental perspectives on teaching and learning thinking skills . <it>Contributions to Human Development</it>: Vol. 21 (pp. 48-62).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lam, M. S. (1995).  <it>Women and men scientists' notions of the good life:  A developmental approach</it>. Unpublished doctoral dissertation, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lamborn, S., Fischer, K.W., &amp; Pipp, S.L. (1994). Constructive criticism and social lies: A developmental sequence for understanding honesty and kindness in social relationships. <it>Developmental Psychology</it>, 30, 495 508.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lindsay, P. H., &amp; Norman, D. A. (1977). <it>Human information processing: An introduction to psychology</it>, (2nd Edition), New York: Academic Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lovell, C. W.  (1999). Development and disequilibration: Predicting counselor trainee gain and loss scores on the Supervisee Levels Questionnaire.  <it>Journal of Adult Development</it>.	</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Miller, M. &amp; Cook Greuter, S. (Eds.). (1994). <it>Transcendence and mature thought in adulthood</it>. Lanham: MN: Rowman &amp; Littlefield.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Miller, P. M., &amp;. Lee, S. T. (June, 2000).  <it>Stages and transitions in child and adult narratives about losses of attachment objects</it>.  Paper presented at the Jean Piaget Society.  Montreal, Québec, Canada. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Overton, W. F. (1990). <it>Reasoning, necessity, and logic:  Developmental perspectives</it>. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oliver, C. R.  (2004). <it>Impact of catastrophe on pivotal national leaders' vision statements: Correspondences and discrepancies in moral reasoning, explanatory style, and rumination</it>. Unpublished doctoral dissertation, Fielding Graduate Institute.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rasch, G.  (1980). <it>Probabilistic model for some intelligence and attainment tests</it>.  Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sonnert, G., &amp; Commons, M. L.  (1994). Society and the highest stages of moral development. <it>Politics and the Individual</it>, 4(1), 31-55.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dareassociation.org">
Dare Association, Inc.</weblink> display text.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.behavioral-development-bulletin.com">
Behavioral Development Bulletin</weblink> display text. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adultdevelopment.org">
Society for Research in Adult Development</weblink> display text</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
