<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:16:45[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<computer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103082979">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<device  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103183080">
<machine  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103699975">
<web_site  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106359193">
<header>
<title>Electoral-vote.com</title>
<id>1192840</id>
<revision>
<id>244636272</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T20:27:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Interwebs</username>
<id>7038006</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>United States presidential election, 2004</category>
<category>American political websites</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox weblog</name>
<parameters>

<image width="150px" src="">
</image>
<website>
http://www.electoral-vote.com</website>
<name>
Electoral-vote.com</name>
</parameters>
</template>


<p>

<b>Electoral-Vote.com</b> (formally, <b>Electoral Vote Predictor</b>) is a website that analyzes state polls to predict the outcome of U.S. elections.  Well known for its color-coded electoral map of the United States, the site was created during the lead-up to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/1297662.xml">
2004 U.S. Presidential election</link> to predict the winner.  The site tries to improve on national polls usually reported in the media by predicting which way each state's electoral vote will go based on statewide polls.  U.S. presidents are in fact elected by separate popular elections in each state, rather than direct popular vote of the entire country.  The winner of each election receives the state's electoral votes equal to its members of Congress (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/85533.xml">
Electoral College</link> for details).  EV.com's method thus simulates the actual process.  Updated throughout the campaign, visitors can see who is "ahead" at any time.</p>
<p>

The creator of the website is <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<professor wordnetid="110480730" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/3110.xml">
Andrew S. Tanenbaum</link></professor>
</person>
, an American computer science professor living and teaching in the Netherlands who goes by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/40594.xml">
pseudonym</link> "The Votemaster".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
2004 Presidential election </st>
<p>

The site began operating on May 24, 2004 with a simple map and a few links to other pages.  The information available grew over time, though.
During the months leading up to the 2004 U.S. Presidential election, the site was updated daily to reflect new state polls.  The site was immensely popular, attracting nearly 700,000 daily visitors as election day neared and was the most popular election site in the country, in the top 1,000 Web sites in the world, and in the top 10 blogs in the world.</p>
<p>

The main page consisted of a map of the United States with the individual states colored varying degrees of red or blue, based on the polls for that state.  For instance, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/14849.xml">
Illinois</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, a state that was polling strongly for Democrat <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/5122699.xml">
John Kerry</link> was colored dark blue, whereas <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/18859.xml">
Michigan</link></country>
 where Kerry's lead polled by a small margin was colored light blue.  Analogously, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/29810.xml">
Texas</link></causal_agent>
</physical_entity>
 was dark red during the whole campaign, indicating Bush's strong lead there.  All of the polling data were provided in multiple formats, including <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/20268.xml">
Excel</link></format>
</software>
, and <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/2084645.xml">
.csv</link></format>
</information>
</message>
 for downloading.  Other features included historical data on previous elections, charts and animations showing the polls over the course of time, cartograms and links to hundreds of other pages and external Websites with tables, charts, graphs, and other election data and information.</p>
<p>

The main algorithm just used the most recent poll(s) in every state.  If two polls came out on the same day, they were averaged.  This algorithm used all published polls, including those by partisan pollsters such as Strategic Vision (R) and Hart Research (D).  A second algorithm used only nonpartisan polls and averaged all polls during the past three days. A third algorithm used historical data to predict how undecided voters would break. Maps for each of the algorithms were given every day, but the first one got most of the publicity since it was on the main page.</p>
<p>

The site's final tracking using algorithm 1 posted on <link>
Election Day</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/21461.xml">
November 2</link> gave 262 electoral votes to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/5122699.xml">
John Kerry</link> and 261 to <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/3414021.xml">
George W. Bush</link></businessperson>
</person>
</president>
, with 15 tossups.  The
second algorithm (averaging 3 days worth of nonpartisan polls) gave Kerry 245 and Bush 278 with
15 tossups. The third algorithm (predicting the undecideds) predicted 281 for Kerry and 257 for Bush.
The actual vote gave Kerry 252 to Bush's 286. Clearly using nonpartisan polls and averaging a few days worth of polls did best. This algorithm got 47 states plus D.C. right, 1 state (Iowa) wrong, and said New Mexico and Wisconsin were too close to call. The most-recent-poll wins algorithm got 46 right, 4 wrong, and one too close to call.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
2006 Midterm election</st>
<p>

On September 6, 2006, the site began tracking the 2006 Congressional elections in the <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/19592407.xml">
Senate</link></legislature>
.  Shortly thereafter, the House of Representatives was added. The map on the site's front page displayed polling for the 2006 Senate races.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  For <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/19468510.xml">
House</link></legislature>
 races, the site featured a "Hot House Races" page with links to <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/5043734.xml">
Wikipedia</link></web_site>
 articles on the candidates, links to the candidates' official websites, and notes on the races.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  The relatively small number of House election polls as well as 2004's House vote totals were used to project the makeup of the House on the site's front page.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. The site correctly predicted the winners in all 33 Senate races.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
2008 Presidential, Senate, and House elections</st>

<p>

As of late December 2006, the site began its 2008 coverage, which includes the presidential race, all 33 Senate races, and about 40 House races that were close in 2006 and are expected to be highly contested in 2008. For each of the known presidential, senatorial and House candidates, a photo is given, linked to the candidate's Wikipedia entry, along with a brief description of the candidate and race. The site also has four prototype maps, one showing the 2004 presidential election, one showing the governors by state, one showing the senate by state and finally one showing the House delegations by state. No polling data was presented until December 2007 when data on the primaries was presented.</p>
<p>

Polling data has been constantly presented each day and analysis given on the likely outcome of the upcoming primaries as well as upcoming trends.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://electoral-vote.com/">
electoral-vote.com</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Poll Crazy" http://www.guardian.co.uk/salon/story/0,,1331599,00.html 2004-10-20</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://electoral-vote.com/">
Electoral-vote.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.electoral-vote.com/evp2006/Info/hothouse.html">
The Hot House Races</weblink> at electoral-vote.com</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://media.www.thewestgeorgian.com/media/storage/paper523/news/2008/01/16/Opinion/Its-Going.To.Be.A.Photo.Finish-3152991.shtml">
It's going to be a photo finish</weblink>", <it><link>
The West Georgian</link></it>&#32;(<link>
2008-01-16</link>).&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</article>
