<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:16:54[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108435388">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<network  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108434259">
<header>
<title>Influence diagram</title>
<id>1194259</id>
<revision>
<id>220259654</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-19T00:31:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Modify</username>
<id>380367</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Bayesian networks</category>
<category>Decision theory</category>
<category>Diagrams</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

An <b>influence diagram (ID)</b> (also called a <b>decision network</b>) is a compact graphical and mathematical representation of a decision situation.  It is a generalization of a <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/203996.xml">
Bayesian network</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, in which not only <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/49571.xml">
probabilistic inference</link> problems but also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/265752.xml">
decision making</link> problems (following <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/736803.xml">
maximum expected utility</link> criterion) can be modeled and solved.<p>

ID was first developed in mid-1970s within the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/1190842.xml">
decision analysis</link> community with an intuitive semantic that is easy to understand. It is now adopted widely and becoming an alternative to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/232602.xml">
decision tree</link> which typically suffers from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/191933.xml">
exponential growth</link> in number of branches with each variable modeled.  ID is directly applicable in <link>
team decision analysis</link>, since it allows incomplete sharing of information among team members to be modeled and solved explicitly.  Extension of ID also find its use in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/11924.xml">
game theory</link> as an alternative representation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/267355.xml">
game tree</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Semantics</st>

<p>

An ID is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/204002.xml">
directed acyclic graph</link> with three types (plus one subtype) of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/325806.xml">
node</link> and three types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/19721986.xml">
arc</link> (or arrow) between nodes.</p>
<p>

Nodes;
<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/1196827.xml">
Decision</link> node</it> (corresponding to each decision to be made) is drawn as a rectangle.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/63778.xml">
Uncertainty</link> node</it> (corresponding to each uncertainty to be modeled) is drawn as an oval.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

<it>Deterministic node</it> (corresponding to special kind of uncertainty that its outcome is deterministically known whenever the outcome of some other uncertainties are also known) is drawn as a double oval.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>Value node</it> (corresponding to each component of additively separable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/736803.xml">
von Neumann-Morgenstern utility</link> function) is drawn as an octagon (or diamond).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Arcs;
<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>Functional arcs</it> (ending in value node) indicate that one of the components of additively separable utility function is a function of all the nodes at their tails.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>Conditional arcs</it> (ending in uncertainty node) indicate that the uncertainty at their heads is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/5791.xml">
probabilistically conditioned</link> on all the nodes at their tails.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

<it>Conditional arcs</it> (ending in deterministic node) indicate that the uncertainty at their heads is deterministically conditioned on all the nodes at their tails.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>Informational arcs</it> (ending in decision node) indicate that the decision at their heads is made with the outcome of all the nodes at their tails known beforehand.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Given a properly structured ID;
<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Decision nodes and incoming information arcs collectively state the <it>alternatives</it> (what can be done when the outcome of certain decisions and/or uncertainties are known beforehand)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Uncertainty/deterministic nodes and incoming conditional arcs collectively model the <it>information</it> (what are known and their probabilistic/deterministic relationships)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Value nodes and incoming functional arcs collectively quantify the <it>preference</it> (how things are preferred over one another).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<it>Alternative, information, and preference</it> are termed <it>decision basis</it> in decision analysis, they represent three required components of any valid decision situation.</p>
<p>

Formally, the semantic of influence diagram is based on sequential construction of nodes and arcs, which implies a specification of all conditional independencies in the diagram.  The specification is defined by the <math>d</math>-separation criterion of Bayesian network.  According to this semantic, every node is probabilistically 
independent on its non-successor nodes given the outcome of its immediate predecessor nodes.  Likewise, a missing arc between non-value node <math>X</math> and non-value node <math>Y</math> implies that there exists a set of non-value nodes <math>Z</math>, e.g., the parents of <math>Y</math>, that renders <math>Y</math> independent of <math>X</math> given the outcome of the nodes in <math>Z</math>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Example</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Figure22.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Simple influence diagram for making decision about vacation activity
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Consider the simple influence diagram representing a situation where a decision-maker is planning on her vacation.
<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

There are 1 decision node (<it>Vacation Activity</it>), 2 uncertainty nodes (<it>Weather Condition, Weather Forecast</it>), and 1 value node (<it>Satisfaction</it>).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

There are 2 functional arcs (ending in <it>Satisfaction</it>), 1 conditional arc (ending in <it>Weather Forecast</it>), and 1 informational arc (ending in <it>Vacation Activity</it>).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Functional arcs ending in <it>Satisfaction</it> indicate that <it>Satisfaction</it> is a utility function of <it>Weather Condition</it> and <it>Vacation Activity</it>.  In other words, her satisfaction can be quantified if she knows what the weather is like and what her choice of activity is.  (Note that she does not value <it>Weather Forecast</it> directly)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Conditional arc ending in <it>Weather Forecast</it> indicates her belief that <it>Weather Forecast</it> and <it>Weather Condition</it> can be dependent.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Informational arc ending in <it>Vacation Activity</it> indicates that she will only know <it>Weather Forecast</it>, not <it>Weather Condition</it>, when making her choice.  In other words, actual weather will be known after she makes her choice, and only forecast is what she can count on at this stage.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

It also follows semantically, for example, that <it>Vacation Activity</it> is independent on (irrelevant to) <it>Weather Condition</it> given <it>Weather Forecast</it> is known.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applicability in value of information</st>

<p>

The above example highlights the power of influence diagram in representing an extremely important concept in decision analysis known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/1194470.xml">
value of information</link>.  Consider the following three scenarios;
<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Scenario 1: The decision-maker could make her <it>Vacation Activity</it> decision while knowing what <it>Weather Condition</it> will be like.  This corresponds to adding extra informational arc from <it>Weather Condition</it> to <it>Vacation Activity</it> in the above influence diagram.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Scenario 2: The original influence diagram as shown above.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Scenario 3: The decision-maker makes her decision without even knowing the <it>Weather Forecast</it>.  This corresponds to removing informational arc from <it>Weather Forecast</it> to <it>Vacation Activity</it> in the above influence diagram.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Scenario 1 is the best possible scenario for this decision situation since there is no longer any uncertainty on what she cares about (<it>Weather Condition</it>) when making her decision.  Scenario 3, however, is the worst possible scenario for this decision situation since she needs to make her decision without any hint (<it>Weather Forecast</it>) on what she cares about (<it>Weather Condition</it>) will turn out to be.</p>
<p>

The decision-maker is usually better off (definitely no worse off) to move from scenario 3 to scenario 2 through the acquisition of new information.  The most she should be willing to pay for such move is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/1194470.xml">
value of information</link> on <it>Weather Forecast</it>, which is essentially <link>
value of imperfect information</link> on <it>Weather Condition</it>.</p>
<p>

Likewise, it is the best for the decision-maker to move from scenario 3 to scenario 1.  The most she should be willing to pay for such move is called <link>
value of perfect information</link> on <it>Weather Condition</it>.</p>
<p>

The applicability of this simple ID and the value of information concept is tremendous, especially in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/265752.xml">
medical decision making</link> when most decisions have to be made with imperfect information about patients, diseases, etc.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

Influence diagrams are hierarchical and can be defined either in terms of their structure or in greater detail in terms of the functional and numerical relation between diagram elements.  An ID that is consistently defined at all levels&mdash;structure, function, and number&mdash;is a well-defined mathematical representation and is referred to as a <it>well-formed influence diagram</it> (WFID).  WFIDs can be evaluated using <link>
reversal</link> and <link>
removal</link> operations to yield answers to a large class of probabilistic, inferential, and decision questions.  More recent techniques have been developed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link> community with their works around <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/49571.xml">
Bayesian network inference</link> (<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/800010.xml">
Belief propagation</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
).</p>
<p>

Influence diagram having only uncertainty nodes (i.e., Bayesian network) is also called <b>relevance diagram</b>.  This is perhaps a better use of language than <it>influence diagram</it>.  An arc connecting node <it>A</it> to <it>B</it> implies not only that "<it>A</it> is relevant to <it>B</it>", but also that "<it>B</it> is relevant to <it>A</it>" (i.e., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/442688.xml">
relevance</link> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/53741.xml">
symmetric</link> relationship).  The word <it>influence</it> implies more of a one-way relationship, which is reinforced by the arc having a defined direction.  Since some arcs are easily reversed, this "one-way" thinking that somehow "<it>A</it> influences <it>B</it>" is incorrect (the causality could be the other way around).  However, the term <it>relevance diagram</it> is never adopted in larger community, and the world continues to refer to <it>influence diagram</it>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Bibliography</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Detwarasiti, A. and R.D. Shachter. (2005). Influence diagrams for team decision analysis. Decision Analysis 2(4): 207-228.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Holtzman, Samuel, <it>Intelligent Decision Systems</it> (1989), Addison-Wesley.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Howard, R.A. and J.E. Matheson, "Influence diagrams" (1981), in <it>Readings on the Principles and Applications of Decision Analysis</it>, eds. R.A. Howard and J.E. Matheson, Vol. II (1984), Menlo Park CA: Strategic Decisions Group.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Koller, D. and B. Milch. (2003). Multi-agent influence diagrams for representing and solving games. Games and Economic Behaviors, 45: 181-221.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pearl, J. (1988).  <it>Probabilistic Reasoning in Intelligent Systems:  Networks of Plausible Inference,</it> San Mateo, CA:  Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, Inc.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Shachter, R.D. (1986). Evaluating influence diagrams. Operations Research, 34: 871-882.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Shachter, R.D. (1988). Probabilistic inference and influence diagrams. Operations Research 36: 589-604.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lev Virine and Michael Trumper. <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.projectdecisions.org">
Project Decisions: The Art and Science</weblink></it>, Vienna, VA: Management Concepts, 2008. ISBN 978-1567262179</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/203996.xml">
Bayesian network</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/232602.xml">
Decision tree</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/15623038.xml">
Morphological Analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Node removal</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Node reversal</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lumina.com/software/influencediagrams.html">
What are influence diagrams?</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ftp.cs.ucla.edu/pub/stat_ser/r326.pdf">
J. Pearl, "Influence Diagrams - Historical and Personal Perspectives," <it>Decision Analysis,</it> Vol. 2(4): 232-234, December 2005.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</network>
</group>
</system>
</article>
