<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:05:05[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Multimedia Web Ontology Language</title>
<id>11988917</id>
<revision>
<id>220275535</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-19T02:13:27Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Earle Martin</username>
<id>9867</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Multimedia</category>
<category>Semantic Web</category>
<category>Ontology (computer science)</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Multimedia Web Ontology Language (MOWL)</b> has been designed to facilitate semantic interactions with multimedia contents. It supports perceptual modeling of concepts using expected media properties. While the reasoning in traditional ontology languages, e.g. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/248001.xml">
Web Ontology Language</link> (OWL), is based on <link>
Description Logics</link>, MOWL supports a probabilistic reasoning framework based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/203996.xml">
Bayesian Network</link>.
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

W3C forum has undertaken the initiative of standardizing the ontology representation for web-based applications. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/248001.xml">
Web Ontology Language</link> (OWL), standardized in 2004 after maturing through <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
XML</link></format>
(S), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/19522034.xml">
RDF</link>(S) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/1768517.xml">
DAML+OIL</link> is a result of that effort. Ontology in OWL (and some of its predecessor languages) has been successfully used in establishing semantics of text in specific application contexts. </p>
<p>

The concepts and properties in these traditional ontology languages are expressed as text, making an ontology readily usable for semantic analysis of textual documents. Semantic processing of media data calls for perceptual modeling of domain concepts with their media properties. Such modeling was first proposed in a Ph.D. Thesis by Hiranmay Ghosh (Electrical Engineering Department, IIT Delhi, 2002) in the form of <it>Knowledge Description Language</it> (KDL). With the standardization of OWL by W3C, KDL was merged with OWL to form Multimedia Web Ontology Language (MOWL).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Key Features </st>

<p>

Syntactically, MOWL is an extension of OWL. These extensions enable 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Definition of media properties following <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/185224.xml">
MPEG-7</link> media description model.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Probabilistic association of media properties with the domain concepts.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Formal semantics to the media properties to enable reasoning.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Formal semantics for spatio-temporal relations across media objects and events.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

MOWL is accompanied with reasoning tools that support
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Construction of model of observation for a concept in multimedia documents with expected media properties.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Probabilistic (Bayesian) reasoning for concept recognition with the model of observation.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 H.Ghosh, S. Chaudhury, K. Kashyap and B. Maiti. Ontology Specification and Integration for Multimedia Applications. <b>Ontologies in the Context of Information Systems</b>, Springer, 2007</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 H.Ghosh, G. Harit and S. Chaudhury. <b>Ontology based interaction with multimedia collections.</b> <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.teriin.org/event">
International Conference on Digital Libraries<it>, New Delhi, 2006</it></weblink>.</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 G. Harit, S. Chaudhury and H. Ghosh. <b>Using Multimedia Ontology for generating conceptual annotations and hyperlinks in video collections</b>. <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.comp.hkbu.edu.hk/iwi06/wi/">
International conference on Web Intelligence<it>, Hong Kong, 2006</it></weblink>.</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 T. Karthik, S. Chaudhury and H. Ghosh. <b>Specifying Spatio-Temporal Relations in Multimedia Ontologies.</b> <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.isical.ac.in/~premi05/">
International Conference of Pattern Recognition and Machine Intelligence<it>, Kolkata 2005</it></weblink>.</it></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
