<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:05:48[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<town  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108665504">
<zone  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108688247">
<city  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108524735">
<header>
<title>Jazan Economic City</title>
<id>12015965</id>
<revision>
<id>243805964</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T02:47:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Saudi Arabia articles missing geocoordinate data</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Cities, towns and villages in Saudi Arabia</category>
<category>Special Economic Zones</category>
<category>Economy of Saudi Arabia</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from October 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox City</name>
<parameters>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jazancity.com/">
Jazan Economic City</weblink></website>
<map_caption>
Location of Jazan Economic City</map_caption>
<mapsize>
250px</mapsize>
<subdivision_type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/468738.xml">
Province</link></subdivision_type>
<image_caption>
Projected Skyline of Jazan Economic City</image_caption>
<population_as_of>
Projected</population_as_of>
<utc_offset>
+3</utc_offset>
<population_total>
1500000</population_total>
<subdivision_name>
<link>
Jazan Province</link></subdivision_name>
<official_name>
Jazan Economic City  مدينة جيزان الاقتصادية</official_name>
</parameters>
</template>


<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="45px" src="Ambox_PR.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section reads like 
, or is otherwise written in an overly promotional tone.</b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Jazan_Economic_City&amp;action=edit">
rewrite this article</weblink> from a  to be less promotional.Where appropriate,  may be marked for speedy deletion with . <it>(October 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

<b>Jazan Economic City</b> (<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/803.xml">
Arabic</link></language>
: مدينة جيزان الاقتصادية&amp;lrm;) The Province of Jazan lies in the south west section of the Kingdom of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/349303.xml">
Saudi Arabia</link></country>
. It has a population of approximately 1.2 million and covers an area of 40,000 sqkm including some 5,000 villages and cities.</p>
<p>

Its major city, Jizan, is home to the Port of Jizan, Saudi Arabia’s third most important port on the Red Sea.</p>
<p>

It is ideally situated on the southern Red Sea coast with a coastline of almost 300km and is very close to the main east and west sea trade routes to Europe, the Far East and Persian Gulf. The Farasan Islands, Saudi Arabia’s first protected wildlife area, is home to the endangered Arabian gazelle and, in winter, receives migratory birds from Europe.</p>
<p>

Its plains are noted for the production of coffee beans and grain crops, like barley millet and wheat; and fruits, such as apples, bananas, grapes, mangoes, papayas, plums and citrus varieties.
__TOC__</p>

<sec>
<st>
Location</st>
<p>

Jazan Economic City will be located along the Red Sea, 60 km northwest of Jizan City. It will occupy an area of 103 km² with a coastline of 11.5 km. The nearest town, Baysh Town, is 23 km east of the proposed future city (latitude: 17 19’ 16”;</p>
<p>

longitude: 42 21’ 43”).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Site Connectivity Plan</st>
<p>

Jazan Economic City will not only be located at the confluence of available raw materials and abundant labour source, but also sit along the main Red Sea shipping route. Facilitating its high connectivity and accessibility will be its proximity to the new International Airport located 60 km south; a new proposed road running east; as well as the future rail connection to Jeddah, situated approximately 600km northwest.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Site Analysis</st>
<p>

The proposed site for Jazan Economic City is bounded by the Red Sea waterfront on the west, a new proposed road on the east that leads to Jizan City, and an existing road on the north that leads to the neighbouring Baysh Town 23 km away. Further up north is the nature park reserve - Baysh Park - that provides a contrasting landscape amidst the uniform desert environment. This beautiful green park along the coastline is a protected area of importance for the preservation of native wildlife, flora, and fauna. Its mature vegetation serves as an ideal green lung for borrowed views from the masterplan as well as a natural playground for many activities. Measuring approximately 12km x 8km (excluding proposed land reclamation works over an existing swamp, thus yielding a final site of 103 sqkm), the site is generally level with wind coming in a north-westerly, south-easterly direction.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Masterplan Proposal</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Heavy Industries</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
1. Power Plant</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
2. Port</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
3. Aluminium Smelter</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
4. Refinery</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
5. Steel</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Secondary Industries</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
1. Fisheries</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
2. Tech Park / Agri-Tech</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
3. Pharmaceuticals</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
4. Chemicals &amp; Plastics</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Human Capital</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
1. Specialized training</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
2. On-job training</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
3. Exchange program</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
4. 500,000 job opportunities</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Lifestyle</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
1. 1. Recreational</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
2. Residential</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
3. Services</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Jazan Economic City focuses on four areas: Heavy Industries, Secondary Industries, Human Capital and Lifestyle. The proposed city will provide a high-quality environment for key industries, technology exchanges, commerce and trade, employment opportunities, education and training, housing and a broad spectrum of socio-economic activities for a projected population</p>
<p>

of 300,000 people.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Landuse</st>
<p>

Commercial, Residential, Community and Industrial components are arranged in graduating concentric circles with the Regional Business Hub – Commercial Business District (CBD) Centre - forming the core of the city.</p>
<p>

The commercial component is ringed by residential, community and industrial components respectively in graduating circular</p>
<p>

belts.</p>
<p>

The Primary industries are situated southwards with an internal utility corridor connecting the proposed road to Jazan city.</p>
<p>

The Secondary industries are located between the primary industry and high-tech industry in proximity to the workers housing.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Heavy Industries</st>
<p>

Local Energy, World Class Industries</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Power Plant</st>
<p>

The power and desalination plant will be located next to the coastline on the South side, consisting of the main power plant, desalination plant, associated balance-of-plant, electrical substation and fuel oil storage facilities.</p>
<p>

Using a steam cycle technology firing on Arabian crude oil, the power plant will be built with sufficient capacity to provide for the power needs of the Economic City with excess capacity to be sold to the grid.</p>
<p>

The desalination plant will be able to provide about 500,000 cubic meters per day of potable water to cater to the internal requirements of the Economic City as well as to supply to the distribution network.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Port</st>
<p>

The establishment of the Port is fundamental to the establishment of Jazan Economic City. The Port provides a vital link to the surrounding region for the importation of raw materials and the export of value-added and processed materials and</p>
<p>

products.</p>
<p>

The Port at the mouth of the Red Sea provides easy access to the world’s shipping lanes with direct access to Europe, East Africa, Asia and Australasia.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Aluminium Smelter</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/249474.xml">
Raw Materials</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Industrial Streaming</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/181586.xml">
Services</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Symbiotic Relationships and Waste Minimization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Industrial Components</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Secondary Industries</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Silicon Processing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/4502.xml">
Biotechnology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Agritechnology</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Refinery</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Dry Dock</st>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Secondary Industries</st>
<p>

Local Materials, World Class Produce</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Silicon Processing</st>
<p>

Silicon processing in Jazan is ideal as it can be found in abundance and is crucial for future technology. With a market demand of approximately 1,200,000 tpa, and a projected growth rate of more than 5% per annum, silicon processing will be an advantageous industrial mix forJazan Economic City.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Textile</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Food Processing</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Tech Park / Agri-Tech</st>
<p>

The Tech Park is focused on implementing and manufacturing, drawing on research and development from a wide range of public and commercial sources. The agri-tech industry is looking to add value to the regional agricultural industry, livestock and crops, improvement and management. Hydroponic development is a current and future technology that will also add value to the Jazan region.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Pharmaceuticals</st>
<p>

Pharmaceuticals are a strong down stream industry of the oil industry and will be enhanced in the future by the development of nutraceuticals and health food products drawing on agricultural resources in the region, implementing new technologies and supplying a growing market in the immediate region.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Chemicals and Plastics</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Secondary Manufacturing</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Construction Materials</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Metal Fabrication</st>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Human Capital</st>
<p>

Local Manpower, World Class Prowess</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Commercial Business District</st>
<p>

An island strategically located at the heart of the development, the business district of Jazan Economic City embodies the main arteries of the commercial businesses.</p>
<p>

Modern offices with state of the art IT infrastructure opens up a wide range of business opportunities, bringing the City to new heights in the region.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Education</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Recreational &amp; Sports</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Commercial / Residentia</st>
<p>

Surrounded by water, the Grand Mosque, located at the promontory, is a resplendent sight to behold for both religious congregations and non-Muslims alike. With elaborate dome and minarets, the Mosque will serve as a core for the precinct’s religious and cultural milieu.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Convention and Exhibition</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Civic Administration</st>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Lifestyle</st>
<p>

Local Lifestyle, World Class Leisure</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Bird’s eye view of Waterfront Villa</st>
<p>

Capitalizing on the vantage view of the Red Sea, the western coast waterfront villas on the crescent shaped and extended horizontal fingers landform command excellent views of the sea, providing an exciting and prestigious lifestyle. Residents will be able to indulge in a luxurious living environment where every exquisite seaside villa comes with its own private marina. The northwest villas located along the tributaries are immersed amongst the surrounding lush green and narrow waterways, offering a quaint and quiet living environment.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hotels and Leisure</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Marina</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Apartments</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Residential</st>
<p>

Located at the marine cove, a variety of low rise residential developments complement the surroundings, combining accessible and contemporary living in a tranquil natural setting. Residents will be able to enjoy the stunning sea views and breeze in their sea front apartments.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Conclusion</st>
<p>

Jazan Economic City will be developed with the philosophy of symbiotic development incorporating co-existing uses to the benefit of each of the components and the environment. Industries would be chosen to enhance the relationship rather than be developed in isolation.</p>
<p>

The primary anchors of Port, Power and desalination, Oil, Aluminium, Steel and Copper provide strong downstream opportunities with industries as diverse as pharmaceuticals, food processing and high value agritech producers within a growing regional environment.</p>
<p>

Jazan Economic City is ideally placed at the mouth of the Red Sea to service markets in Europe, Asia and East Africa as well as to receive raw materials from the surrounding countries that are currently not well served with processing and manufacturing facilities.</p>
<p>

The establishment of an international airport for the region would complete a strong logistics hub also serving those</p>
<p>

markets.</p>
<p>

Jazan Economic City is also central to a booming population. The populations in the immediate regions of KSA, Yemen, Sudan, Ethiopia and Eritrea are expected to nearly double in the next 25 years while the population of Europe is projected to decline. Future markets in Africa and Asia are expected to expand while they are contracting in Europe and America.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Development</st>
<p>

Construction has started on Jazan Economic City, with the main developers as follows
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/11942876.xml">
MMC Corporation Berhad</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/2261514.xml">
Saudi Binladin Group</link></company>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/349303.xml">
Saudi Arabia</link></country>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<sovereign wordnetid="110628644" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/19186951.xml">
King Abdullah bin Abdulaziz</link></person>
</sovereign>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jazancity.com/">
Jazan Economic City Official Website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.jazancity.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jazannews.com/">
Jazan Economic City News Company</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://krwetatnt.net/vb/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jazansecurity.com/">
Jazan Economic City Security</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/479200.xml">
Main Saudi Arabian cities</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/3962121.xml">
Afif</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</village>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/1275983.xml">
Arar</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <b><city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/2451017.xml">
Abha</link></city>
</b>&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/2355897.xml">
Abqaiq</link></urban_area>
</district>
</group>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</community>
</gathering>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</social_group>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/468698.xml">
Al-Bahah</link>&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/3959907.xml">
Bisha</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/1134389.xml">
Buraydah</link></b>&nbsp;·  <b><city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/479214.xml">
Dammam</link></city>
</b>&nbsp;·  <b><city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/6838977.xml">
Dhahran</link></city>
</b>&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/494778.xml">
Diriyah</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</village>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/3932036.xml">
Duba</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/2466792.xml">
Ha'il</link></city>
&nbsp;·  <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/13632366.xml">
Hafar Al-Batin</link></city>
&nbsp;·  <b><region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/2357257.xml">
Hofuf</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</b>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/3932002.xml">
Al Jawf</link>&nbsp;·  <b><city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/277718.xml">
Jeddah</link></city>
</b>&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/1907222.xml">
Jizan</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/632008.xml">
Jubail</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/60978.xml">
Khamis Mushait</link></village>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/3962003.xml">
Al-Kharj</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <b><city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/690043.xml">
Khobar</link></city>
</b>&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/3962935.xml">
Al Majma'ah</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</village>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/21021.xml">
Mecca</link></b> (Makkah)&nbsp;·  <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/36636.xml">
Medina</link></b>&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/1907226.xml">
Najran</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <b><city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/1581754.xml">
Qatif</link></city>
</b>&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/1719051.xml">
Ras Tanura</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/2381985.xml">
Khafji</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <b><city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/51554.xml">
Riyadh</link></city>
</b> (capital)&nbsp;·  <link>
Ta’if</link>&nbsp;·  <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/900737.xml">
Tabuk</link></village>
&nbsp;·  <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/1829378.xml">
Unaizah</link></city>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/629638.xml">
Yanbu' al Bahr</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

Coordinates needed: </p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</city>
</zone>
</town>
</article>
