<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:09:59[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Computer compatibility</title>
<id>12075392</id>
<revision>
<id>214391576</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-23T10:07:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ssmit</username>
<id>4497770</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Interoperability</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A family of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link> models is said to be <b>compatible</b> if certain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> that runs on one of the models can also be run on all other models of the family.  The computer models may differ in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/224515.xml">
performance</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/41651.xml">
reliability</link> or some other characteristic.  Any difference may affect the outcome of the running of the software. 

<sec>
<st>
 Software compatibility </st>

<p>

Software compatibility can refer to the compatibility that a particular software has running on a particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/7597.xml">
CPU architecture</link> such as Intel or PowerPC. Software compatibility can also refer to ability for the software to run on a particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>. Very rarely is a compiled software compatible with multiple different CPU architectures. Normally, an application is compiled for different CPU architectures and operating systems to allow it to be compatible with the different system. <link>
Interpreted software</link>, on the other hand, can normally run on many different CPU architectures and operating systems if the interpreter is available for the architecture or operating system. Software incompatibility occurs many times for new software released for a newer version of an operating system which is incompatible with the older version of the operating system because it may miss some of the features and functionality that the software depends on. Software that does work on older versions of an operating system is said to be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/4459.xml">
backwards compatible</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Hardware compatibility </st>

<p>

Hardware compatibility can refer to the compatibility that computer hardware components have with a particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/7597.xml">
CPU architecture</link>, bus, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/19945.xml">
motherboard</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>. Hardware that is compatible may not always run at its highest stated performance, but it can nevertheless work with legacy components. An example of this is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/25847.xml">
RAM</link>, where some can run at a <link>
clock-speed</link> lower (or sometimes higher) than that which they are rated for. Also, hardware that was designated for one operating system may not work for another, unless available device or kernel drivers are available. For example, much of the hardware for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link> is proprietary hardware <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>with drivers unavailable for use in operating systems such as <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Mac OS X hardware compatibility - http://www.stepwise.com/MacOSXServer/HardwareSupport/index.html</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/305972.xml">
Forward compatibility</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/4459.xml">
Backward compatibility</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Software compatibility</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Cross compatibility</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../335/8400335.xml">
Portability</link></entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
