<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:03:19[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<ingredient  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103570709">
<header>
<title>Fruit preserves</title>
<id>12143913</id>
<revision>
<id>244465218</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T22:56:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Warrington</username>
<id>5253460</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Gels</category>
<category>Condiments</category>
<category>Food ingredients</category>
<category>Food preservation</category>
<category>Spreads</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

"Jam" redirects here. For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/638271.xml">
Jam (disambiguation)</link>.
<image location="right" width="270px" src="Marmeladesorten.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Three varieties of fruit preserves: strawberry, 
quince, and red plum
</caption>
</image>

<image width="250px" src="Ribotroshhashana.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Five varieties of fruit preserves (clockwise): apple, quince, plum, squash, orange (in the middle)
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Fruit preserves</b> refers to fruits or vegetables that have been prepared and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/198153.xml">
canned</link> for long term storage. The preparation of <b>fruit preserves</b> traditionally involves the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/159750.xml">
pectin</link> as a gelling agent, although sugar or honey may be used as well. There are various types of <b>fruit preserves</b> made globally, and they can be made from sweet or savory ingredients.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Variations </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Confit </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/2583479.xml">
Confit</link></it>
</indent>
<b>Confit</b>, which is the past participle form of the French verb "confire" or "to preserve", is most often applied to preservation of meats, especially poultry and pork, by cooking them in their own fat or oils and allowing the fats to set.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> However the term can also refer to fruit or vegetables which have been seasoned and cooked with honey or sugar until it has reached a jam-like consistency.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Savory confits, such as ones made with garlic or tomatoes, may call for a savory oil such as virgin olive oil as the preserving agent.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Conserves </st>
<p>

<b>Conserves</b> are preserves made from a mixture of fruits and/or vegetables. Conserves may also include dried fruit or nuts.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Fruit butter </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/2846163.xml">
Fruit butter</link></it>
</indent>
<b>Fruit butter</b>, is used in this context to refer to a process where the whole fruit is forced through a sieve or blended after the heating process.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

"<it>Fruit butters are generally made from larger fruits, such as apples, plums peaches or grapes. Cook until softened and run through a sieve to give a smooth consistency. After sieving, cook the pulp...add sugar and cook as rapidly as possible with constant stirring... The finished product should mound up when dropped from a spoon, but should not cut like jelly. Neither should there be any free liquid.</it>" - Berolzheimer R (ed) et al (1959)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>
</indent>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Fruit curd </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/3741471.xml">
Fruit curd</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Fruit curd</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/7976.xml">
dessert</link> topping and spread usually made with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/38437.xml">
lemon</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/4984440.xml">
orange</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/276409.xml">
raspberry</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> The basic ingredients are beaten egg yolks, sugar, fruit juice and <component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<ingredient wordnetid="103570709" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/4430416.xml">
zest</link></part>
</ingredient>
</component>
 which are gently cooked together until thick and then allowed to cool, forming a soft, smooth, intensely-flavored spread. Some recipes also include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/355802.xml">
egg whites</link> and/or butter.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Fruit spread </st>
<p>

<b>Fruit spread</b> refers to a jam or preserve with no added sugar.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Marmalade </st>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wiktionary-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wiktionary
</caption>
</image>

Look up  in <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/156658.xml">
Wiktionary</link></web_site>
, the free dictionary.</p>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/145232.xml">
Marmalade</link></it>
</indent>
British-style <b>marmalade</b> is a sweet <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/12143913.xml">
preserve</link> with a bitter tang made from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/10843.xml">
fruit</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/27712.xml">
sugar</link>, water, and (in some commercial brands) a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../094/2909094.xml">
gelling agent</link>. American-style marmalade is sweet, not bitter. In English-speaking usage "marmalade" almost always refers to a preserve derived from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/52136.xml">
citrus fruit</link>, most commonly oranges. The recipe includes sliced or chopped <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/4740907.xml">
fruit peel</link>, which is simmered in fruit juice and water until soft; indeed marmalade is sometimes described as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/12143913.xml">
jam</link> with fruit peel (although perversely many manufacturers now also produce peel-free marmalade). Such marmalade is most often consumed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/19009244.xml">
toast</link>ed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/36969.xml">
bread</link> for breakfast. The favoured citrus fruit for marmalade production in the UK is the "<link>
Seville orange</link>", <it>Citrus aurantium</it> var. <it>aurantium</it>, thus called because it was originally imported from <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/37770.xml">
Seville</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</tract>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</site>
 in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
; it is higher in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/159750.xml">
pectin</link> than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/4984440.xml">
sweet oranges</link>, and therefore gives a good set. Marmalade can also be made from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/38437.xml">
lemon</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/261456.xml">
limes</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/67401.xml">
grapefruit</link>s, strawberries or a combination.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Jam </st>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wiktionary-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wiktionary
</caption>
</image>

Look up  in <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/156658.xml">
Wiktionary</link></web_site>
, the free dictionary.</p>
<p>

<b>Jam</b> contains both fruit juice and pieces of the fruit's (or vegetable's) flesh, however some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/246991.xml">
cookbook</link>s define Jam as cooked and gelled fruit (or vegetable) purees.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

Properly, the term <it>jam</it> refers to a product made with whole fruit, cut into pieces or crushed. The fruit is heated with water and sugar to activate the pectin in the fruit. The mixture is then put into containers. The following extract from a US cookbook describes the process.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

"<it>Jams are usually made from pulp and juice of one fruit, rather than a combination of several fruits. Berries and other small fruits are most frequently used, though larger fruits such as apricots, peaches, or plums cut into small pieces or crushed are also used for jams. Good jam has a soft even consistency without distinct pieces of fruit, a bright color, a good fruit flavor and a semi-jellied texture that is easy to spread but has no free liquid.</it>" - Berolzheimer R (ed) et al (1959)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>
</indent>

<b>Examples</b>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/2455842.xml">
Strawberry</link> jam (sweet, fruit)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mint jam (savory)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Jalapeño</link> pepper jam</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Variations</b></p>
<p>

Uncooked or minimally cooked (less than 5 minutes) jams, called <it>freezer jam</it>, because they are stored frozen, are popular in parts of <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/21139.xml">
North America</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 for their very fresh taste.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Jelly </st>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wiktionary-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wiktionary
</caption>
</image>

Look up  in <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/156658.xml">
Wiktionary</link></web_site>
, the free dictionary.</p>
<p>

In the U.S. and Canada, the term <it>jelly</it> refers to a type of clear fruit spread consisting of firmed fruit (or vegetable) juice made with pectin. In British English, these products are commonly referred to by the terms <it>fruit spread</it> or <it>preserves</it>, although <it>jelly</it> is also used in some instances, for example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/18955.xml">
mint</link> jelly. Jelly can be made from sweet, savory or hot ingredients. <it>Jelly</it> is made by a similar process to jam, with the additional step of filtering out the fruit pulp after the initial heating. A cloth "jelly bag" is traditionally used as a filter.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

"<it>Good jelly is clear and sparkling and has a fresh flavor of the fruit from which it is made. It is tender enough to quiver when moved, but holds angles when cut.</it>
</indent>
:<it>EXTRACTING JUICE - Pectin is best extracted from the fruit by heat, therefore cook the fruit until soft before straining to obtain the juice&nbsp;... Pour cooked fruit into a jelly bag which has been wrung out of cold water. Hang up and let drain. When dripping has ceased the bag may be squeezed to remove remaining juice, but this may cause cloudy jelly.</it>" - Berolzheimer R (ed) et al (1959)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

<b>Examples</b>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/12436.xml">
Grape</link> jelly (sweet fruit)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/18955.xml">
Mint</link> jelly (savory)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Jalapeño</link> pepper jelly (hot)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Preserves </st>
<p>

The term <b>Preserves</b> is usually interchangeable with <b>Jam</b>, however some cookbooks define <b>Preserves</b> as cooked and gelled whole fruit (or vegetable), which includes a significant portion of the fruit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

<image width="250px" src="Jams,_Jellies,_Honeys-Minnesota_State_Fair.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Jams, jellies and honeys, <festival wordnetid="115162388" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/920679.xml">
Minnesota State Fair</link></festival>

</caption>
</image>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Regional terminology</st>
<p>

The terms <it>jam</it> and <it>jelly</it> are used in different parts of the English speaking world in different ways.</p>
<p>

Although both terms exist in North America, the UK and Australia; in the USA most jams are often popularly referred to as "jelly" in a generic way. Meanwhile in the UK, Canada, and Australia the two terms are more strictly differentiated, although the term <it>jam</it> is more popularly used in Australia and South Africa as a generic term.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> To further confuse the issue, the term <it>jelly</it> is also used in the UK and Australia to refer to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/13162.xml">
gelatin dessert</link>, whereas in North America the brand name <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.8">
<hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/16585.xml">
Jell-O</link></language_unit>
</characteristic>
</part>
</signal>
</trade_name>
</hallmark>
</name>
</symbol>
 is used as a generic term for gelatin desserts and is strictly differentiated from clear fruit preserves.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Production</st>
<p>

This section of the article will use the generic term <it>jam</it> unless otherwise noted.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Bubbling_Jam.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Allowing jam to 'boil over' creates a hazard in the kitchen.
</caption>
</image>

In general jam is produced by taking mashed or chopped fruit or vegetable pulp and boiling it with sugar and water. The proportion of sugar and fruit varies according to the type of fruit and its ripeness, but a rough starting point is equal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/33931.xml">
weight</link>s of each. When the mixture reaches a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/19572300.xml">
temperature</link> of 104&nbsp;<unit_of_measurement wordnetid="113583724" confidence="0.8">
<definite_quantity wordnetid="113576101" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/19593040.xml">
°C</link></definite_quantity>
</unit_of_measurement>
 (219&nbsp;<unit_of_measurement wordnetid="113583724" confidence="0.8">
<definite_quantity wordnetid="113576101" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/11524.xml">
°F</link></definite_quantity>
</unit_of_measurement>
), the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/656.xml">
acid</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/159750.xml">
pectin</link> in the fruit react with the sugar, and the jam will set on cooling. However, most cooks work by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/245733.xml">
trial and error</link>, bringing the mixture to a "fast rolling <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/52636.xml">
boil</link>", watching to see if the seething mass changes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/3874132.xml">
texture</link>, and dropping small samples on a plate to see if they run or set.</p>
<p>

Commercially produced jams are usually produced using one of two methods. The first is the open pan method, which is essentially a larger scale version of the method a home jam maker would use. This gives a traditional flavor, with some caramelization of the sugars. The second commercial process, involves the use of a vacuum vessel, where the jam is placed under a vacuum, which has the effect of reducing it's boiling temperature to anywhere between 65-80&nbsp;°C depending on the recipe and the end result desired. The lower boiling temperature enables the water to be driven off as it would be when using the traditional open pan method, but with the added benefit of retaining more of the volatile flavor compounds from the fruit, preventing caramelization of the sugars, and of course reducing the overall energy required to make the product. However, the vacuum pan method does not kill off all micro-organisms which may be present in the jam, therefore once the desired amount of water has been driven off, the jam still needs to be heated briefly to 95-100&nbsp;°C to kill off any micro-organisms that may be present. During the commercial filling of the jam into jars, it is common to use a flame to sterilize the rim of the jar and the lid to destroy any yeasts &amp; molds which may cause spoilage during storage. It is also common practice to inject steam into the head space at the top of the jar immediately prior to the fitting of the lid, in order to create a vacuum. Not only does this vacuum help prevent the growth of spoilage organisms, it also pulls down the tamper evident safety button when lids of this type are employed.
<image location="left" width="150px" src="Raspberry_Jam.PNG" type="thumb">
<caption>

An open jar of raspberry jam
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

How easily a jam sets depends on the pectin content of the fruit. Some fruits, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/172081.xml">
gooseberries</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/709548.xml">
redcurrant</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/172161.xml">
blackcurrant</link>s, citrus fruits, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18978754.xml">
apples</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/276409.xml">
raspberries</link>, set very well; others, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/2455842.xml">
strawberries</link> and ripe <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/72339.xml">
blackberries</link>, often need to have pectin added. There are commercial pectin products on the market, and most industrially-produced jams use them. Home jam-makers sometimes rely on adding a pectin-rich fruit to a poor setter; for example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/72339.xml">
blackberry</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18978754.xml">
apple</link>. Other tricks include extracting juice from redcurrants or gooseberries. Making jam at home is a popular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/49690.xml">
handicraft</link> activity, and many take part in this. Homemade jam may be made for personal consumption, or as part of a <link>
cottage industry</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Legal definitions</st>

<ss1>
<st>
USDA definitions</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/70896.xml">
USDA</link> treats <it>jam</it> and <it>preserves</it> as synonymous, but distinguishes <it>jelly</it> from jams and preserves. All of these are cooked and pectin-gelled fruit products, but jellies are based entirely on fruit juice or other liquids, while jams and preserves are gelled fruit that includes the seeds and pulp.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
European Union directives on 'jam'</st>
<p>

In the <economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
European Union</link></economy>
, the jam <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/410654.xml">
directive</link> (Council Directive 79/693/EEC, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/15888.xml">
24 July</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/34754.xml">
1979</link>) set minimum standards for the amount of "fruit" in jam, but the definition of fruit was expanded to take account of several unusual kinds of jam made in the EU. For this purpose, "fruit" is considered to include fruits that are not usually treated in a culinary sense as fruits, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/9940234.xml">
tomato</link>es; fruits that are not normally made into jams; and vegetables that are sometimes made into jams, such as: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/56277.xml">
rhubarb</link> (the edible part of the stalks), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/5985739.xml">
carrot</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/51628.xml">
sweet potato</link>es, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/164491.xml">
cucumber</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/18581150.xml">
pumpkin</link>s. This definition continues to apply in the new directive, Council Directive 2001/113/EC (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/8849.xml">
20 December</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Jelly worldwide</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/439894.xml">
Mayhaw jelly</link> is a delicacy in parts of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/179553.xml">
American South</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/2381892.xml">
Grass jelly</link>, a food from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5042862.xml">
China</link> and <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/28741.xml">
Southeast Asia</link></location>
</region>
, often served in drinks</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/9061286.xml">
Almond jelly</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
, a sweet dessert from <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/13404.xml">
Hong Kong</link></country>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/724786.xml">
Nata de coco</link></food>
</substance>
, jelly made from coconuts originating from the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/23440.xml">
Philippines</link></country>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Yōkan</link>, a sweet pasty jelly dessert from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/15573.xml">
Japan</link> often made with beans, sweet potato or squash</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/10134698.xml">
Muk</link></it>, a variety of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/16749.xml">
Korea</link></country>
n jelly, seasoned and eaten as a cold salad</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/797031.xml">
Konjac</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
 (also called <it>konnyaku</it>), a variety of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/15573.xml">
Japan</link>ese jelly</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/19721214.xml">
Quince cheese</link> a French quince jelly</entry>
</list>

There are a variety of jellies in the cuisines of East and Southeast Asia. Depending on the type, they may be sweet or unsweetened, or neither.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/1765551.xml">
Lekvar</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/142312.xml">
Peanut butter and jelly sandwich</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2000/sep/29/features11.g22">
On the menu: confit</weblink>".&#32;  <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/19344515.xml">
The Guardian</link></newspaper>
&#32;(2008-9-29).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.&nbsp;"Usually duck, pork or goose, although you can use other meats."</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/confit">
Definition: Confit</weblink>".&#32;<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/255353.xml">
American Heritage Dictionary</link></it>.&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/1298400.xml">
Dictionary.com</link>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.&nbsp;"A condiment made by cooking seasoned fruit or vegetables, usually to a jamlike consistency"</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epicurious.com/recipes/food/views/TOMATO-CONFIT-AND-MARINATED-TOMATOES-SERVED-ON-A-CRISPY-TART-108547">
Tomato Confit recipe</weblink>".&#32;<it><link>
Bon Appétit</link></it>.&#32;  <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/7286857.xml">
Epicurious</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
&#32;(September 2003).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epicurious.com/recipes/food/views/GARLIC-CONFIT-241125">
Garlic Confit recipe</weblink>".&#32;<it><link>
Bon Appétit</link></it>.&#32;  <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/7286857.xml">
Epicurious</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
&#32;(January 2008).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.&nbsp;"Can be made 1 month ahead. Keep chilled and completely covered in oil. Always use clean spoon to remove garlic."</entry>
<entry id="5">
Isabel D. Wolf;&#32;William Schafer&#32;(1990).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.extension.umn.edu/distribution/nutrition/DJ1088.html">
Making Jams, Marmalades, Preserves, and Conserves</weblink>".&#32;  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/416813.xml">
University of Minnesota</link></university>
 extension school.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Ruth Berolzheimer (ed) et al&#32;(1969). Culinary arts institute encyclopedic cookbook (revised),.&#32;Chicago USA.:&#32;Culinary arts institute,&#32;p. 830.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=20050629&amp;slug=caketerms29">
Cake Talk: What the terms mean</weblink>".&#32;<it><book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/1045951.xml">
The Joy of Cooking</link></book>
</it>.&#32;  <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/432610.xml">
The Seattle Times</link></newspaper>
&#32;(2005-06-29).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-02</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<cook wordnetid="109963320" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.8">
<contestant wordnetid="109613191" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<football_player wordnetid="110101634" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<chef wordnetid="109963574" confidence="0.8">
<athlete wordnetid="109820263" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/636344.xml">
Gordon Ramsay</link></athlete>
</chef>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</football_player>
</military_officer>
</serviceman>
</contestant>
</player>
</person>
</cook>
</skilled_worker>
</physical_entity>
&#32;(2007-06-20).&#32;"Lemon and Poppy Seed Scones with Homemade Lemon Curd", <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/39127.xml">
The Times of London</link>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-13</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(1975) <book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/1045951.xml">
The Joy of Cooking</link></book>
.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
<b>Berolzheimer</b>, pp. 831-832</entry>
<entry id="11">
<b>Berolzheimer</b>, pp. 826-829</entry>
<entry id="12">
Howard L &amp; Patten M (eds), 1960, The Australian Women's Weekly - Cookery in colour, Paul Hamlin LTD, London UK, sections956-971</entry>
<entry id="13">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_lexical_differences_in_South_African_English#F-J">
en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_lexical_differences_in_South_African_English#F-J</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="14">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ams.usda.gov/fv/ppbweb/manuals/jelly.pdf">
Grading Manual for Fruit Jelly Fruit Preserves</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).</entry>
<entry id="15">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://europa.eu.int/smartapi/cgi/sga_doc?smartapi!celexapi!prod!CELEXnumdoc&amp;lg=EN&amp;numdoc=32001L0113&amp;model=guichett">
Council Directive 2001/113/EC (20 December 2001)</weblink>".</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Notes </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2000/sep/29/features11.g22">
On the menu: confit</weblink>".&#32;  <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/19344515.xml">
The Guardian</link></newspaper>
&#32;(2008-9-29).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.&nbsp;"Usually duck, pork or goose, although you can use other meats."</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/confit">
Definition: Confit</weblink>".&#32;<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/255353.xml">
American Heritage Dictionary</link></it>.&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/1298400.xml">
Dictionary.com</link>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.&nbsp;"A condiment made by cooking seasoned fruit or vegetables, usually to a jamlike consistency"</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epicurious.com/recipes/food/views/TOMATO-CONFIT-AND-MARINATED-TOMATOES-SERVED-ON-A-CRISPY-TART-108547">
Tomato Confit recipe</weblink>".&#32;<it><link>
Bon Appétit</link></it>.&#32;  <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/7286857.xml">
Epicurious</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
&#32;(September 2003).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epicurious.com/recipes/food/views/GARLIC-CONFIT-241125">
Garlic Confit recipe</weblink>".&#32;<it><link>
Bon Appétit</link></it>.&#32;  <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/7286857.xml">
Epicurious</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
&#32;(January 2008).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.&nbsp;"Can be made 1 month ahead. Keep chilled and completely covered in oil. Always use clean spoon to remove garlic."</entry>
<entry id="5">
Isabel D. Wolf;&#32;William Schafer&#32;(1990).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.extension.umn.edu/distribution/nutrition/DJ1088.html">
Making Jams, Marmalades, Preserves, and Conserves</weblink>".&#32;  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/416813.xml">
University of Minnesota</link></university>
 extension school.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-20</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Ruth Berolzheimer (ed) et al&#32;(1969). Culinary arts institute encyclopedic cookbook (revised),.&#32;Chicago USA.:&#32;Culinary arts institute,&#32;p. 830.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=20050629&amp;slug=caketerms29">
Cake Talk: What the terms mean</weblink>".&#32;<it><book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/1045951.xml">
The Joy of Cooking</link></book>
</it>.&#32;  <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/432610.xml">
The Seattle Times</link></newspaper>
&#32;(2005-06-29).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-02</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<cook wordnetid="109963320" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.8">
<contestant wordnetid="109613191" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<football_player wordnetid="110101634" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<chef wordnetid="109963574" confidence="0.8">
<athlete wordnetid="109820263" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/636344.xml">
Gordon Ramsay</link></athlete>
</chef>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</football_player>
</military_officer>
</serviceman>
</contestant>
</player>
</person>
</cook>
</skilled_worker>
</physical_entity>
&#32;(2007-06-20).&#32;"Lemon and Poppy Seed Scones with Homemade Lemon Curd", <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/39127.xml">
The Times of London</link>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-13</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(1975) <book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/1045951.xml">
The Joy of Cooking</link></book>
.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
<b>Berolzheimer</b>, pp. 831-832</entry>
<entry id="11">
<b>Berolzheimer</b>, pp. 826-829</entry>
<entry id="12">
Howard L &amp; Patten M (eds), 1960, The Australian Women's Weekly - Cookery in colour, Paul Hamlin LTD, London UK, sections956-971</entry>
<entry id="13">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_lexical_differences_in_South_African_English#F-J">
en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_lexical_differences_in_South_African_English#F-J</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="14">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ams.usda.gov/fv/ppbweb/manuals/jelly.pdf">
Grading Manual for Fruit Jelly Fruit Preserves</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).</entry>
<entry id="15">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://europa.eu.int/smartapi/cgi/sga_doc?smartapi!celexapi!prod!CELEXnumdoc&amp;lg=EN&amp;numdoc=32001L0113&amp;model=guichett">
Council Directive 2001/113/EC (20 December 2001)</weblink>".</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uga.edu/nchfp/how/can7_jam_jelly.html">
Making Jams and Jellies</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.extension.umn.edu/distribution/nutrition/DJ1088.html">
Making Jams, Marmalades, Preserves, and Conserves</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.persiancity.com/recipes/search.asp?key=Morabaa">
Varies Jam Recipes (Black Cherry, Carrot, Quince and Apple jams)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nolacuisine.com/2008/10/01/pepper-jelly-recipe">
Pepper Jelly Recipe at Nola Cuisine</weblink></entry>
</list>





</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</ingredient>
</article>
