<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:15:26[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<financial_institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108054721">
<foundation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108406486">
<charity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108406619">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>Liverpool Personal Service Society</title>
<id>12201020</id>
<revision>
<id>237317784</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-09T16:54:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Vendeka</username>
<id>5762788</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Charities based in the United Kingdom</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="pss_blueorange.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

The <it>PSS</it> logo
</caption>
</image>

<b>Liverpool Personal Service Society Incorporated</b>, (PSS) was established on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
1 January</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/34665.xml">
1919</link>, yet still remains an "innovative, empowering charity… with the ethos of pioneering new ways of delivering services".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

The charity provides a range of community based social and healthcare services across north west England, central Scotland and North Wales, enabling people of all ages and needs to live independently within a community setting.  Some of these services include:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

Shared Living - providing discreet housing and support in community settings for those who can benefit from additional support due to their mental health, learning or physical disabilities.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Community Services - a variety of councelling, support and care for all levels of need, both in clients' own homes, and within the wider community. Children and families, are also caterd for. 
</indent>

Whether in their own homes, or in a PCC centre, services are individually tailored around each clients specific needs.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

Adult Placement - supporting vulnerable people in the homes of specially recruited families. The success of the scheme depends upon the needs of the people supported being carefully matched with the opportunities offered by carers.
</indent>

Adult Placement may provide day care, short breaks, intermediate care or long term placements in a carer's home and carers receive training and continuous support to carry out their role.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History of innovation</st>

<p>

PSS services are delivered at neighbourhood level but using innovative models and practice that have been taken up around the world. One of the founders of PSS was <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<advocate wordnetid="109774783" confidence="0.8">
<suffragist wordnetid="110672908" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../205/782205.xml">
Eleanor Rathbone</link></suffragist>
</advocate>
</causal_agent>
</leader>
</person>
</politician>
</physical_entity>
, who was also instrumental in the founding of what was later to become <financial_institution wordnetid="108054721" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="108406486" confidence="0.8">
<charity wordnetid="108406619" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/179332.xml">
Age Concern</link></institution>
</charity>
</foundation>
</financial_institution>
. Other ground-breaking PSS projects include social housing, community legal services and marriage guidance. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Innovation and development </st>

<p>

PSS has developed specialist knowledge and expertise in the provision of:</p>
<p>

•	services for people with dementia and their carers ; 
•	extra care housing which incorporates assistive technology and environmental design ; 
•	services for children, young people and their families including young carers, children whose parent use drugs, vulnerable young people in transition and women with post natal depression;
•	services for offenders and their families.</p>
<p>

The charity is funded mainly through legacies and donations, and this money directly funds new innovations to support future generations.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Dementia</st>

<p>

Alzheimer's disease and other forms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/38390.xml">
dementia</link> are a huge worldwide problem. In Britain alone some 750,000 people are affected - and this number is set to double in the next 25 years.</p>
<p>

Due to the huge impact of this issue, PSS has a special initiative and is dedicated to finding new ways to help carers to care and help support people with dementia to cope better with the effects of their illness.</p>
<p>

The challenge of PSS is to listen and respond to what carers and people with dementia themselves say about their needs and wishes, enabling them to have as much control over their lives as possible.</p>
<p>

Innovation, co-operation, assistive technology - PSS dementia support services today provide a wide range of help to people with dementia and those who care for them.</p>
<p>

PSS provides a wide range of services and assistive technology, helping those sufering from dementia and their carers.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Postnatal depression</st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/175357.xml">
Postnatal depression</link> (PND) occurs in some women after the birth of a child. It affects women world wide, of all ages, of all cultures and from all backgrounds. Any new mother can experience PND however, in areas where there is greater socio-economic deprivation new mothers are more a risk.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

The incidence of post natal depression on Merseyside is 8 times higher than the national average but appropriate service provision is sparse and does not fully meet the level of need.</p>
<p>

It is recognised by health professionals and voluntary sector frontline staff that there is insufficient provision of specialised services in Liverpool offering support to mothers with PND and their families.</p>
<p>

The most common treatments for women with symptoms of postnatal depression is GP prescribed antidepressants. The focus of the PSS, PND Project is to enhance and complement current service delivery with the development of an early intervention strategy.  The Project’s approach to PND is holistic, supporting women and their families. This Project works on the premise that the earlier that postnatal depression is identified the better.  It makes recovery easier and means that mother and baby will be less affected. This approach is complementary to the medical model and is successful at reducing the demand on mainstream mental health services.</p>
<p>

The project adopts a holistic approach to service delivery and the programme of activities includes:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

parent skills training</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

creche provision</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

activities to support Dads</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

outreach -home visits  &amp; play  worker support</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

access to counselling</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

complementary therapies</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

post Natal Depression awareness raising events</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

access to mainstream services inc; Welfare Benefit  Advice [delivered sessionally at centres]</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

direct access to wider  community resources and activities programme</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

delivered in non stigmatised and fully accessible community settings</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This model will enable the service to be delivered across all areas.  The service is unique in that it provides enhanced listening at home and access to qualifoed Counsellors in local community settings with childcare facilities.</p>
<p>

The service will provide the following inputs:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Home visits offering one-to-one support to women and their families</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

PND can be a very isolating experience. The Mum’s support Group enables women to engage in discussion about their issues and gain support from their peers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Childcare available.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The service is unique in that it provides qualified counselling at home to mums who are unable to attend outside appointments.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The service will achieve the following outcome:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Relationships between mother and child are improved using play therapy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Supporting Mums whilst at work to allow them to stay in post. Encouraging mums to enter employment / education</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cost effectiveness plus the added value from access to other support in the mental health resources</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Speedy response and reduction on the demand for crisis interventions</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Ultimately this project will support Liverpool to meet local and national government targets in relation to sustaining and supporting families.  It will also contribute to the development of strong local partnerships with non-statutory organisations.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Charity Commission Report. Crown</entry>
<entry id="2">
The Mental Health Foundation, 2003</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

PSS in the United Kingdom:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pss.org.uk/">
PSS</weblink> (Main PSS web site) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dementiacafe.com/">
PSS Dementia Cafe</weblink> The Innovative PSS Dementia cafe and chat rooms</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.charitycommission.gov.uk/ShowCharity/RegisterOfCharities/CharityWithPartB.aspx?RegisteredCharityNumber=224469&amp;SubsidiaryNumber=0">
Liverpool Personal Service Society, Registered Charity no. 224469</weblink> at the <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<financial_institution wordnetid="108054721" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="108406486" confidence="0.8">
<charity wordnetid="108406619" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/179914.xml">
Charity Commission</link></institution>
</charity>
</foundation>
</financial_institution>
</department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</charity>
</foundation>
</financial_institution>
</article>
