<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:18:04[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Scott Brave</title>
<id>12240764</id>
<revision>
<id>210561583</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-06T13:28:01Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bhadani</username>
<id>219828</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking reliable references from October 2007</category>
<category>Articles with topics of unclear notability from October 2007</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All articles lacking sources</category>
<category>Businesspeople</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Scott Brave</b> is a founder and CTO of Baynote, Inc. Prior to Baynote, Brave was a postdoctoral scholar at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/26977.xml">
Stanford University</link></university>
 and served as lab manager for the CHIMe (Communication between Humans and Interactive Media) Lab. Brave is an inventor of six patents and co-author of over 25 publications in the areas of human-computer interaction and artificial intelligence. He is also an Editor of the "International Journal of Human-Computer Studies" (Amsterdam: Elsevier) and co-author of "Wired for speech: How voice activates and advances the human-computer relationship" (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press). Brave received his Ph.D. in Human-Computer Interaction, and B.S. in Computer Systems Engineering from Stanford University, and his Master's from the MIT Media Lab.
<sec>
<st>
 <b>PUBLICATIONS (Books, Book Chapters, and Journal Articles):</b> </st>
<p>

http://libra.msra.cn/AuthorDetail.aspx?name=scott+brave
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bailenson, J.N., Yee, N., Brave, S., Merget, D., &amp; Koslow, D. (2006, in press). Virtual Interpersonal Touch: Expressing and Recognizing Emotions through Haptic Devices. Human-Computer Interaction.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Jong-Eun Roselyn Lee, Cliff Nass, Scott Brave, Yasunori Morishima, Hiroshi Nakajima, Ryota Yamada. (2006, in press) "The case for caring co-learners: The effects of a computer-mediated co-learner agent on Trust and Learning", Journal of Communication.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Nass, C., Takayama, L, &amp; Brave, S. (2006, in press). Socializing consistency: From technical homogeneity to human epitome. In P. Zhang &amp; D. Galletta (Eds.), Human-computer interaction in management information systems: Foundations. Armonk, NY: M. E. Sharpe.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Nass, C., Brave, S., (2005). Wired for Speech: How Voice Activates and Enhances the Human-Computer Relationship. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S., Nass, C., Hutchinson, K. (2005). Computers that care: investigating the effects of orientation of emotion exhibited by an embodied computer agent. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies. 62(2): 161-178.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Nakajima, H., Morishima, Y., Yamada, R., Brave, S., Maldonado, H., Nass, C., Kawaji, S. (2004). Social intelligence in a human-machine collaboration system: Social responses to agents with mind model and personality. Journal of the Japanese Society for Artificial Intelligence, 19(3): pp. 184&ndash;196.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S., Nass, C. (2003). Emotion in human-computer interaction. In J. Jacko &amp; A. Sears (Eds.), The Human-Computer Interaction Handbook: Fundamentals, Evolving Technologies and Emerging Applications (chap. 4). Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ito, H., Nakanishi, H., Ishida, T., Brave, S., &amp; Nass, C. (2003). A virtual space environment for social psychological experiments. Journal of the Information Processing Society of Japan, 44(2).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 John Koza, Forrest Bennett, David Andre, Martin Keane, Scott Brave. (1999) Genetic Programming III: Darwinian Invention and Problem Solving (Video). Morgan Kaufmann Publishers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S. (1996). Evolving recursive programs for tree search. In P.J. Angeline &amp; K. E. Kinnear,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rosenberg, L. &amp; Brave, S. (1996). The use of force feedback to enhance graphical user interfaces. SPIE Proceedings, Stereoscopic Displays and Virtual Reality Systems III, 2653(36). 243-248.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Witkin, J., Brave, S., French, D. &amp; Geter-Douglass, B. (1996). Discriminative stimulus effects of R-(+)-3-amino-1-hydroxypyrolid-2-one, [(+)-HA-966], a partial agonist of the strychnine-insensitive modulatory site of the N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor. The Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics, 275(3), 1267&ndash;1273.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 <b>PUBLICATIONS (Conference Proceedings):</b> </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ryota Yamada, Hiroshi Nakajima, Scott Brenner Brave, Heidy Maldonado, Jong-Eun Roselyn Lee, Clifford Ivar Nass, Yasunori Morishima (in press) "An Implementation of Socially Intelligent Agents for Emotional Support and its Application", Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man &amp; Cybernetics 2006 (IEEE SMC2006), Taipei, Taiwan, Oct., 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hiroshi Nakajima, Yasunori Morishima, Ryota Yamada, Scott Brave, Clifford Nass, Masaki Arao, Shigeyasu Kawaji (2005) "Mind Model and Social Intelligence in Human-Machine Collaborative Systems", Proceedings of the 16th IFAC World Congress in Prague (IFAC2005), Jul. 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Heidy Maldonado, Jong-Eun Roselyn Lee, Scott Brave, Cliff Nass, Hiroshi Nakajima, Ryota Yamada, Kimihiko Iwamura, Yasunori Morishima, "We Learn Better Together: Enhancing eLearning with Emotional Characters", Proceedings of the Computer Supported Collaborative Learning 2005 (CSCL2005), Taipei, Taiwan, May 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Jong-Eun Roselyn Lee, Heidy Maldonado, Clifford I. Nass, Scott B. Brave, Ryota Yamada, Hiroshi Nakajima, Kimihiko Iwamura, "Can "Cooperative" Agents Enhance Learning and User-Interface Relationship in Computer-based Learning Environment?", Proceedings of the 2005 International Communication Association Conference (ICA2005), New York, US, May. 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Clifford Nass, Ing-Marie Jonsson, Helen Harris, Ben Reaves, Jack Endo, Scott Brave, Leila Takayama: Improving automotive safety by pairing driver emotion and car voice emotion. CHI Extended Abstracts 2005: 1973&ndash;1976.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Morishima, Y., Nakajima, H., Nass, C., Brave, S. B., Maldonado, H., &amp; Yamada, R. (2004). The role of affect and sociality in an agent-based collaborative learning system. Proceedings of the Tutorial and Research Workshop on Affective Dialogue Systems (ADS04). New York: Springer-Verlag. 265-275.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hiroshi Nakajima, Yasunori Morishima, Scott Brave, Ryota Yamada, Heidy Maldonado, Clifford Nass, Shigeyasu Kawaji, "Toward an Actualization of Social Intelligence in Human and Robot Collaborative Systems", Proceedings of the 2004 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS2004), Sendai, Japan, Oct. 2004.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Nakajima, H., Brave, S., Nass, C. Yamada, R., Morishima, Y., &amp; Kawaji, S. (2003). The functionality of human-machine collaboration systems ¬ Mind model and social behavior. Proceedings * Tan, G., Takechi, M., Brave, S., &amp; Nass, C. (2003). Effects of voice vs. remote on U.S. and Japanese user satisfaction with interactive HDTV systems. Extended Abstracts of CHI'03: Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. 714-715.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S., Nass, C., &amp; Sirinian, E. (2001). Force-feedback in computer-mediated communication. Proceedings of UAHCI'01: Universal Access in Human-Computer Interaction (part of HCI 2001). 145-149</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Nass, C., Foehr, U., Brave, S.,&amp; Somoza, M. (2001). The effects of emotion of voice in synthesized and recorded speech. Proceedings of Emotional and Intelligent II: The Tangled Knot of Social Cognition, 91-96.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lee, E., Nass, C., &amp; Brave, S. (2000). Can computer-generated speech have gender? An experimental test of gender stereotype. Extended Abstracts of CHI'00: Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 289-290.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S., Ishii, H., &amp; Dahley, A. (1998). Tangible interfaces for remote collaboration and communication. Proceedings of CSCW '98: Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work, 169-178.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ishii, H., Wisneski, C., Brave, S., Dahley, A., Gorbet, M., Ullmer, B. &amp; Yarin, P. (1998). ambientROOM: Integrating ambient media with architectural space (video). Extended Abstracts of CHI'98: Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 173-174.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Wisneski, C, Ishii, H., Dahley, A., Gorbet, M., Brave, S., Ullmer, B. &amp; Yarin, P. (1998). Ambient displays: Turning architectural space into an interface between people and digital information. Proceedings of CoBuild'98: First International Workshop on Cooperative Buildings, 22-32.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S. &amp; Dahley, A. MiLOs. (1997). FleshFactor: Informationsmacschine mensch: 1997 (Ars Electronica Festival Catalog), 278-279.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S. &amp; Dahley, A. (1997). inTouch: A medium for haptic interpersonal communication. Extended Abstracts of CHI'97: Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 363-364.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S. (1996). Evolving deterministic finite automata using cellular encoding. Genetic Programming 1996: Proceedings of the First Annual Conference, 39-44.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S. (1996). The evolution of memory and mental models using genetic programming. Genetic Programming 1996: Proceedings of the First Annual Conference, 261-266.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rosenberg, L. &amp; Brave, S. (1996). Using force feedback to enhance human performance in graphical user interfaces. Extended Abstracts of CHI'96: Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 291-292.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S. (1995). Using genetic programming to evolve mental models. Proceedings of the Golden West Conference on Intelligent Systems (GWICS), Fourth International Conference, 91-96.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brave, S. (1995). Using genetic programming to evolve recursive programs for tree search. Proceedings of the Golden West Conference on Intelligent Systems (GWICS), Fourth International Conference, 60-65.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 <b>PATENTS:</b> </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Patent Pending (2005). Method and Apparatus for Identifying, Extracting, Capturing, and Leveraging Expertise and Knowledge.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 U.S. Patent # 6,366,272 (2002). Providing interactions between simulated objects using force feedback.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 U.S. Patent # 6,219,032 (2001). Method for providing force feedback to a user of an interface device based on interactions of a controlled cursor with graphical elements in a graphical user interface.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 U.S. Patent # 6,078,876 (2000). Method and apparatus for tracking the position and orientation of a stylus and for digitizing a 3-D object.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 U.S. Patent # 6,028,593 (2000). Method and apparatus for providing simulated physical interactions within computer generated environments.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 U.S. Patent # 6,015,473 (2000). Method for producing a precision 3-D measuring apparatus.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article lacks information on the  of the subject matter.</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Scott_Brave&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by providing context for a general audience, especially in the . <it>(October 2007)</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  that appear in reliable, third-party publications.</b>
s and sources affiliated with the subject of the article are generally not sufficient for a Wikipedia article. Please include more appropriate  from , or discuss the issue on the talk page. <it>(October 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
