<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:19:23[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Internet privacy</title>
<id>1228060</id>
<revision>
<id>244087424</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T08:16:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Hmains</username>
<id>508734</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles needing copy edit</category>
<category>All NPOV disputes</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing copy edit from June 2008</category>
<category>NPOV disputes from February 2008</category>
<category>Internet</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Unbalanced_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  of this article is .</b> 
Please see the discussion on the . <it>(February 2008)</it>Please do not remove this message until the </col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Internet privacy</b> consists of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/25009.xml">
privacy</link> over the media of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>: the ability to control what information one reveals about oneself over the Internet, and to control who can access that information. Many people use the term to mean universal Internet privacy: <it>every</it> user of the Internet possessing Internet privacy. </p>
<p>

Internet privacy forms a subset of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/237536.xml">
computer privacy</link>. Experts in the field of Internet privacy have a consensus that Internet privacy does not really exist.  Privacy advocates believe that it should exist.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Scope of this article</st>
<p>

This article discusses Internet privacy. Readers should understand the general topics of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/25009.xml">
privacy</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/1845896.xml">
personally-identifiable information</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Levels of privacy</st>
<p>

People with only a casual concern for Internet privacy need not achieve total <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/181382.xml">
anonymity</link>. Internet users may achieve an adequate level of privacy through controlled disclosure of personal information. The revelation of IP addresses, non-personally-identifiable profiling, and similar information might become acceptable trade-offs for the convenience that users could otherwise lose using the workarounds needed to suppress such details rigorously. On the other hand, some people desire much stronger privacy. In that case, they may try to achieve <b>Internet anonymity</b> to ensure privacy &mdash; use of the Internet without giving any third parties the ability to link the Internet activities to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/1845896.xml">
personally-identifiable information</link> of the Internet user.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Risks to Internet privacy</st>
<p>

Those concerned about Internet privacy often cite a number of <b>privacy risks</b> &mdash; events that can compromise privacy &mdash; which may be encountered through Internet use. These methods of compromise can range from the gathering of statistics on users, to more malicious acts such as the spreading of spyware and various forms of bug exploitation.</p>
<p>

Privacy measures are provided on several social networking sites to try to provide their users with protection for their personal information.  On Facebook for example privacy settings are available for all registered users.  The settings available on Facebook include the ability to block certain individuals from seeing your profile, the ability to choose your "friends," and the ability to limit who has access to your pictures and videos.  Privacy settings are also available on other social networking sites such as E-harmony and MySpace.  It is the user's prerogative to apply such settings when providing personal information on the internet.
</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Cookies</st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See main article, <text wordnetid="106387980" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<line wordnetid="107012534" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<heading wordnetid="106343971" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/5068415.xml">
HTTP cookie</link></heading>
</method>
</line>
</know-how>
</text>
</it>
</indent>

<text wordnetid="106387980" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<line wordnetid="107012534" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<heading wordnetid="106343971" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/5068415.xml">
Cookie</link></heading>
</method>
</line>
</know-how>
</text>
s are tools which are sometimes used for user-tracking, a common concern in the field of privacy. As a result, some types of cookies are classified as a <it>tracking cookie</it>. Although HTML-writers most commonly use cookies for legitimate purposes, cases of abuse can and do occur.</p>
<p>

An HTTP cookie consists of a piece of information stored on a user's computer to add <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/285512.xml">
statefulness</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 to <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
web</link></invention>
-browsing. Systems do not generally make the user explicitly aware of the storing of a cookie. (Although some users object to that, it does not properly relate to Internet privacy. It does however have implications for computer privacy, and specifically for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/615799.xml">
computer forensics</link>).</p>
<p>

The original developers of cookies intended that only the website that originally distributed cookies to users could retrieve them, therefore returning only data already possessed by the website. However, in practice programmers can circumvent this restriction. Possible consequences include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the placing of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/1845896.xml">
personally-identifiable</link> tag in a browser to facilitate <link>
web profiling</link> (see below), or,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/241154.xml">
cross-site scripting</link> or other techniques to steal information from a user's cookies.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Some users choose to disable cookies in their web browsers - as of 2000 a Pew survey estimated the proportion of users at 4%<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. Such an action eliminates the potential privacy risks, but may severely limit or prevent the functionality of many websites. All significant web browsers have this disabling ability built-in, with no external program required. As an alternative, users may frequently delete any stored cookies. Some browsers (such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<browser wordnetid="106571301" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/210892.xml">
Mozilla Firefox</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</browser>
</program>
</application>
</software>
 and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/18996620.xml">
Opera</link></software>
) offer the option to clear cookies automatically whenever the user closes the browser. A third option involves allowing cookies in general, but preventing their abuse. There are also a host of wrapper applications that will redirect cookies and cache data to some other location.</p>
<p>

The process of <b>profiling</b> (also known as "tracking") assembles and analyzes several events, each attributable to a single originating entity, in order to gain information (especially patterns of activity) relating to the originating entity. Some organizations engage in the profiling of people's web browsing, collecting the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link>s of sites visited. The resulting profiles can potentially link with information that personally identifies the individual who did the browsing.</p>
<p>

Some web-oriented marketing-research organizations may use this practice legitimately, for example: in order to construct profiles of 'typical Internet users'. Such profiles, which describe average trends of large groups of Internet users rather than of actual individuals, can then prove useful for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/8837930.xml">
market analysis</link>. Although the aggregate data does not constitute a privacy violation, some people believe that the initial profiling does.</p>
<p>

Profiling becomes a more contentious privacy issue when data-matching associates the profile of an individual with personally-identifiable information of the individual.</p>

<p>

Governments and organizations may set up <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/287952.xml">
honeypot</link> websites - featuring controversial topics - with the purpose of attracting and tracking unwary people. This constitutes a potential danger for individuals. </p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
ISPs</st>
<p>

Consumers obtain Internet access through an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/100245.xml">
Internet Service Provider</link> (ISP). All Internet data to and from the consumer must pass through the consumer's ISP. Given this, any ISP has the <it>capability</it> to observe everything about the consumer's (unencrypted) Internet activities; however, ISPs are usually prevented from participating in such activities due to legal, ethical, business, or technical issues.</p>
<p>

Despite these legal and ethical issues, some ISPs, such as <commercial_enterprise wordnetid="108065093" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<industry wordnetid="108065234" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/1313323.xml">
British Telecom</link></industry>
</enterprise>
</commercial_enterprise>
 (BT), are planning to use deep packet inspection technology provided by companies such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/16180725.xml">
Phorm</link></company>
 in order to examine the contents of the pages which people visit.  By doing so, they can build up a profile of a person's web surfing habits, which can then be sold on to advertisers in order to provide targeted advertising.  BT's attempt at doing this will be marketed under the name 'Webwise'.</p>
<p>

Normally ISPs do collect at least <it>some</it> information about the consumers using their services. From a privacy standpoint, ISPs would ideally collect only as much information as they require in order to provide Internet connectivity (IP address, billing information if applicable, etc).</p>
<p>

What information an ISP collects, what it does with that information, and whether it informs its consumers, pose significant privacy issues. Beyond the usage of collected information typical of third parties, ISPs sometimes state that they will make their information available to government authorities upon request. In the US and other countries, such a request does not necessarily require a warrant.</p>
<p>

An ISP cannot know the contents of properly-encrypted data passing between its consumers and the Internet. For encrypting <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
web</link></invention>
 traffic, <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/13586.xml">
https</link></b> has become the most popular and best-supported standard. Note however, that even if users encrypt the data, the ISP still knows the IP addresses of the sender and of the recipient. (However, see the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22IP+addresses%22])">
IP addresses</link> section for workarounds.)</p>
<p>

General concerns regarding internet user privacy have become enough of a concern for a UN agency to issue a report on the dangers of identity fraud<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Data logging</st>
<p>

Many programs and operating systems are set up to perform <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/70098.xml">
data logging</link> of usage. This may include recording times when the computer is in use, or which web sites are visited. If a third party has sufficient access to the computer, legitimately or not, the user's privacy may be compromised. This could be avoided by disabling logging, or by clearing logs regularly.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other potential Internet privacy risks</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/28951.xml">
Spyware</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/1157430.xml">
Web bug</link> (HTML-enabled email)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/730243.xml">
Social engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <accomplishment wordnetid="100035189" confidence="0.8">
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<transgression wordnetid="100745005" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<crime wordnetid="100766234" confidence="0.8">
<wrongdoing wordnetid="100732746" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<feat wordnetid="100036762" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/428364.xml">
Phishing</link></activity>
</feat>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</wrongdoing>
</crime>
</event>
</transgression>
</occupation>
</accomplishment>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/78768.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Risks_of_using_anonymous_proxy_servers%22])">
Malicious proxy server</link> (or other "anonymity" services)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Anonymous Internet usage</st>

<p>

For anonymous browsing of websites, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/12590864.xml">
anonymizer</link>. For anonymous email, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/54666.xml">
anonymous remailer</link>.</p>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Further information: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/181382.xml">
anonymity</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Specific cases</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="30px" src="Acap.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  for  grammar, style, cohesion, tone or spelling.</b>
You can assist by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Internet_privacy&amp;action=edit">
editing it</weblink> now. A how-to is available.<it>&nbsp;(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Jason Fortuny and Craigslist</st>
<p>

In early September 2006, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/6940191.xml">
Jason Fortuny</link>, a <area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/737237.xml">
Seattle</link></area>
-area freelance graphic designer and network administrator, posed as a woman and posted an ad to <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/19375754.xml">
Craigslist</link></company>
 Seattle seeking a casual sexual encounter with men in that area. On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/27765.xml">
September 4</link>, he posted to the wiki website <link>
Encyclopædia Dramatica</link> all 178 of the responses, complete with photographs and personal contact details, describing this as the Craigslist Experiment and encouraging others to further identify the respondents.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Although some online exposures of personal information have been seen as justified as exposing malfeasance, many commentators on the Fortuny case saw no such justification here. "The men who replied to Fortuny's posting did not appear to be doing anything illegal, so the outing has no social value other than to prove that someone could ruin lives online", said law professor <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<professor wordnetid="110480730" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/213197.xml">
Jonathan Zittrain</link></professor>
</person>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
, while <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/65411.xml">
Wired</link></it> writer <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<blogger wordnetid="109860415" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<journalist wordnetid="110224578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/6020192.xml">
Ryan Singel</link></journalist>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</blogger>
</physical_entity>
 described Fortuny as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/436194.xml">
sociopathic</link>".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

The <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/18949836.xml">
Electronic Frontier Foundation</link></company>
 indicated that it thought Fortuny might be liable under <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/13015878.xml">
Washington</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 State Law, and that this would depend on whether the information he disclosed was of legitimate public concern. <link>
Kurt Opsahl</link>, the EFF's staff attorney, said "As far as I know, they (the respondents) are not public figures, so it would be challenging to show that this was something of public concern."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

In April 2008, it came to light that Fortuny was sued by a "John Doe" plaintiff who was exposed by his project. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Fortuny initially bragged about the lawsuit on his blog, dubbing it the "Battle in Seattle", but mysteriously and quickly removed any and all references to the suit. </p>
<p>

According to Fortuny, two people lost their jobs as a result of his Craigslist Experiment and another "has filed an invasion-of-privacy lawsuit against Fortuny in an Illinois court." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Search engine data and law enforcement</st>

<p>

Data from major Internet companies, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo</link>! and <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/185041.xml">
MSN</link></web_site>
 (<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
) have already been subpoenaed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/195149.xml">
United States</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> and China<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>. <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/1397.xml">
AOL</link></company>
 even provided a chunk of its own search data online<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>, allowing reporters to track the online behaviour of private individuals<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>. </p>
<p>

In 2006, a wireless hacker pled guilty when his <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 searches were used as evidence against him. The defendant ran a <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 search over the network using the following search terms: "how to broadcast interference over wifi 2.4 GHZ," "interference over wifi 2.4 Ghz," "wireless networks 2.4 interference," and "make device interfere wireless network." While court papers did not describe how the FBI obtained his searches (e.g. through a seized hard-drive or directly from the search-engine), <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 has indicated that it can provide search terms to law enforcement if given an Internet address or Web cookie.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 US v. Zeigler </st>

<p>

Many cases discuss whether a private employee (i.e., not a government employee) who stores incriminating evidence in workplace computers is protected by the Fourth Amendment's reasonable expectation of privacy standard in a criminal proceeding.</p>
<p>

Most case law holds that employees do not have a reasonable expectation of privacy when it comes to their work related electronic communications. See, e.g. US v. Simons, 206 F.3d 392, 398 (4th Cir., Feb. 28, 2000).</p>
<p>

However, one federal court held that employees can assert that the attorney-client privilege with respect to certain communications on company laptops. See Curto v. Medical World Comm., No. 03CV6327, 2006 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 29387 (E.D.N.Y. May 15, 2006).</p>
<p>

Another recent federal case discussed this topic. On January 30, 2007, the Ninth Circuit court in US v. Ziegler, reversed its earlier August 2006 decision upon a petition for rehearing. In contrast to the earlier decision, the Court acknowledged that an employee has a right to privacy in his workplace computer. However, the Court also found that an employer can consent to any illegal searches and seizures. See US v. Ziegler, ___F.3d 1077 (9th Cir. Jan. 30, 2007, No. 05-30177). [1] Cf. US v. Ziegler, 456 F.3d 1138 (9th Cir. 2006).</p>
<p>

In Ziegler, an employee had accessed child pornography websites from his workplace. His employer noticed his activities, made copies of the hard drive, and gave the FBI the employee's computer. At his criminal trial, Ziegler filed a motion to suppress the evidence because he argued that the government violated his Fourth Amendment rights.</p>
<p>

The Ninth Circuit allowed the lower court to admit the child pornography as evidence. After reviewing relevant Supreme Court opinions on a reasonable expectation of privacy, the Court acknowledged that Ziegler had a reasonable expectation of privacy at his office and on his computer. That Court also found that his employer could consent to a government search of the computer and that, therefore, the search did not violate Ziegler's Fourth Amendment rights.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 State v. Reid </st>

<p>

A New Jersey appellate court has also issued an opinion on the privacy rights of computer users. That court held that computer users can expect that the personal information they give their internet service providers are considered private. State v. Reid 2007 N.J. Super. LEXIS 11 (January 22, 2007). [2].</p>
<p>

In that case, prosecutors asserted that Shirley Reid broke into her employer’s computer system and changed its shipping address and password for suppliers. The police discovered her identity after getting a subpoena to the internet provider, Comcast Internet Service.</p>
<p>

The lower court suppressed information from the internet service provider that linked Reid with the crime. The New Jersey appellate court agreed with this decision. As a result, New Jersey offers greater privacy rights to computer users than most federal courts. Although this case does not directly discuss the Fourth amendment, it illustrates that some states are providing more privacy protection to computer users than the federal courts. It also illustrates that caselaw on privacy in workplace computers is still evolving.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Teachers and MySpace</st>
<p>

Teachers’ privacy on MySpace has created controversy across the world. They are forewarned by The Ohio News Association <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> that if they have a MySpace account, it should be deleted.  Eschool News warns, “Teachers watch what you post online.” <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> The ONA also posted a memo advising teachers not to join these sites. Teachers can face consequences of license revocations, suspensions, and written reprimands.</p>
<p>

The Chronicle of Higher Education wrote an article on April 27, 2007 entitled "A MySpace Photo Costs a Student a Teaching Certificate" about Stacy Snyder<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>.  She was a student of Millersville University of Pennsylvania who was denied her teaching degree because of an unprofessional photo posted on MySpace, which involved her drinking with a pirates’ hat on and a caption of “Drunken Pirate".  Due to this, she was given an English degree.  </p>
<p>

John Bush, a 52 year old physical education teacher from St. Augustine, was fired over an inappropriate, not pornographic, picture that was posted on MySpace.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>  What is considered inappropriate is up to the discretion of the school board.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pewinternet.org/report_display.asp?r=19">
Trust and Privacy Online: Why Americans Want to Rewrite the Rules. Pew Internet &amp; American Life Project. Released Aug. 20, 2000</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/6199372.stm">
UN warns on password 'explosion'</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
Neva Chonin&#32;(2006-09-17).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/09/17/PKG6BKQQA41.DTL">
Sex and the City</weblink>".&#32;  <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/319442.xml">
San Francisco Chronicle</link></newspaper>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/15798.xml">
2007-06-17</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Anick Jesdanun&#32;(12 September 2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/14791788/">
Prankster posts sex ad replies online</weblink>".&#32;  <commercial_enterprise wordnetid="108065093" confidence="0.8">
<cooperative wordnetid="101100877" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/18935732.xml">
AP</link></enterprise>
</cooperative>
</commercial_enterprise>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-06-27</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<blogger wordnetid="109860415" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<journalist wordnetid="110224578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/6020192.xml">
Ryan Singel</link></journalist>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</blogger>
</physical_entity>
&#32;(2006-09-08).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blog.wired.com/27BStroke6/index.blog?entry_id=1553329">
Craigslist</weblink>".&#32;  Wired Blogs.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-09-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
 Michael Crook&#32;(<link>
2008-04-17</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.michaelcrook.org/blog/2008/04/17/lawsuit-over-the-craigslist-drama">
Lawsuit Over Craigslist Drama?</weblink>".&#32;  Michael Crook.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-27</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Schwartz, Mattathias.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/03/magazine/03trolls-t.html?ex=1375329600&amp;en=b5085d50ee5c65e5&amp;ei=5124&amp;partner=permalink&amp;exprod=permalink">
Malwebolence</weblink>".&#32;  New York Times.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-01</link>.&nbsp;"After receiving death threats, Fortuny meticulously scrubbed his real address and phone number from the Internet. “Anyone who knows who and where you are is a security hole,” he told me. “I own a gun. I have an escape route. If someone comes, I’m ready.”"</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blog.searchenginewatch.com/blog/060119-060352">
Bush Administration Demands Search Data; Google Says No; AOL, MSN &amp; Yahoo Said Yes</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blog.wired.com/27bstroke6/2007/07/yahoo-knew-more.html">
Yahoo Knew More About China Journalist Subpoena Than It Told Congress It Did</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20060807/0219238.shtml">
Forget The Government, AOL Exposes Search Queries To Everyone</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://technology.guardian.co.uk/online/search/story/0,,1859785,00.html">
They know all about you</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
Tim Wafa&#32;(January 2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://works.bepress.com/tim_wafa/">
Internet Privacy Rights - A Pragmatic Legal Perspective</weblink>".&#32;  <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/13430545.xml">
Berkeley Electronic Press</link></publication>
</periodical>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-17</link>.</entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blogs.sun.com/learningcurve/tags/myspace">
Learning Curve</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eschoolnews.com/news/top-news/related-top-news/?i=50557;_hbguid=49a1babb-b469-4a85-a273-292a0514d91d">
Related Top News - Teachers warned about MySpace profiles</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://chronicle.com/wiredcampus/index.php?id=2029">
Wired Campus: A MySpace Photo Costs a Student a Teaching Certificate - Chronicle.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.news4jax.com/education/10835756/detail.html">
Teacher Fights Firing Over MySpace Page - Education News Story - WJXT Jacksonville</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/5724494.xml">
Anonymous web browsing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/2148229.xml">
Crimeware</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/11056603.xml">
FLAIM</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/10997.xml">
Freenet</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/1185274.xml">
Friend-to-friend</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 (F2F) networks</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/293685.xml">
GNUnet</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/1134243.xml">
Identity Commons</link> (organization)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/11056386.xml">
Internet censorship</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/1879457.xml">
JAP</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 / <link>
AN.ON</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <canine wordnetid="102083346" confidence="0.8">
<carnivore wordnetid="102075296" confidence="0.8">
<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<domestic_animal wordnetid="101317541" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<placental wordnetid="101886756" confidence="0.8">
<dog wordnetid="102084071" confidence="0.8">
<mammal wordnetid="101861778" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/13532651.xml">
On the Internet, nobody knows you're a dog</link></animal>
</mammal>
</dog>
</placental>
</vertebrate>
</domestic_animal>
</chordate>
</carnivore>
</canine>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/245025.xml">
Proxomitron</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/18582150.xml">
Tor</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 [https://www.privacycom.org Privacy Commission]</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/privacy">
Google 'Privacy'</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.internet-online-privacy.com">
Unbiased advice on safeguarding your personal and business privacy online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lawdex.com/docs/Bourke_v_Nissan.pdf">
Expectation of privacy for company email not deemed objectively reasonable - Bourke v. Nissan</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
