<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:19:59[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Matthews Correlation Coefficient</title>
<id>12306500</id>
<revision>
<id>217512148</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-06T10:53:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Андрей Романенко</username>
<id>2513239</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Information_retrieval</category>
<category>Machine learning</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Matthews Correlation Coefficient</b> is used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link> as a measure of the quality of binary (two class) classifications. It takes into account true and false positives and negatives and is generally regarded as a balanced measure which can be used even if the classes are of very different sizes. It returns a value between -1 and +1. A coefficient of +1 represents a perfect prediction, 0 an average random prediction and -1 an inverse prediction.<p>

While there is no perfect way of describing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/847558.xml">
confusion matrix</link> of true and false positives and negatives by a single number, the Matthews Correlation Coefficient is generally regarded as being one of the best such measures.</p>
<p>

Other measures, such as the proportion of correct predictions (also termed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/41932.xml">
Accuracy</link>), are not useful when the two classes are of very different sizes. For example, assigning every object to the larger set achieves a high proportion of correct predictions, but is not generally a useful classification.</p>

<p>

<math>
MCC = \frac{ TP \times TN - FP \times FN } {\sqrt{ (TP + FP) ( TP + FN ) ( TN + FP ) ( TN + FN ) } }
</math></p>

<p>

In this equation, TP is the number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/5657877.xml">
true positives</link>, TN the number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/5657877.xml">
true negatives</link>, FP the number of <link>
false positives</link> and FN the number of <link>
false negatives</link>. If any of the four sums in the denominator is zero, the denominator can be arbitrarily set to one; this results in a Matthews Correlation Coefficient of zero, which can be shown to be the correct limiting value.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Baldi, P; Brunak, S.; Chauvin, Y.; Andersen, C. A. F.; Nielsen, H. Assessing the accuracy of prediction algorithms for classification: an overview. Bioinformatics 2000, 16, 412-424.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Matthews, B.W., Comparison of the predicted and observed secondary structure of T4 phage lysozyme. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1975, 405, 442-451</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</bdy>
</article>
