<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:11:50[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Tech Edge</title>
<id>12310290</id>
<revision>
<id>202943650</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-03T01:23:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>C++</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<b>Tech Edge</b> (Tech-Edge) is the annual computer fest organized by Birla Vidya Niketan as a part of their Cultural Fiesta "UTSAV".
The fest lasts 1 day and usually takes place during July.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Events </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/34035.xml">
Web Design</link>ing</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/72038.xml">
C++</link></programming_language>
 Programming</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Multimedia Presentation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Collage (<hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Photoshop</link></characteristic>
</hallmark>
)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Events like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/18984281.xml">
gaming</link> were held in the past but are now discontinued</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Techedge1.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Tech Edge 2007 wallpaper
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 C++ Programming </st>
<p>

Two rounds are held for this event. In the first round , the Prelims, each team comprising of 2 students is to clear an objective paper. The paper may also contain simple subjective questions. The top 10 teams to clear the prelims would compete in a 2 hour round. Some questions require intense thinking while others just require speed. Scoring is done taking into account the number of attempt calls, and the time taken.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Web Designing </st>
<p>

Web Designing is held as a presentation event. Each team is to bring there pre-prepared websites on CDs and present there concept to the judges. The original files are also required to ensure that the work is their own.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Collage Making </st>
<p>

One student from each school is to produce a collage from the images given to them. The topic is given on the spot and relevant images are provided. The software provided was <hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Photoshop</link></characteristic>
</hallmark>
7.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Multimedia Presentation </st>
<p>

In this event, the skills and creativity of students in forming multimedia presentations is tested. The students have to prepare a presentation in PowerPoint and also present it to the judges.</p>
<p>

More information is available from the school.</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
