<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:26:38[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="104377057">
<header>
<title>Geographic information system</title>
<id>12398</id>
<revision>
<id>244291207</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T03:24:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Topology Expert</username>
<id>6756471</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with limited geographic scope</category>
<category>Geographic information systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

"GIS" redirects here. For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../953/1535953.xml">
GIS (disambiguation)</link>.    
A <b>geographic information system (GIS)</b>, also known as a <b>geographical information system</b>, is an information system for capturing, storing, analyzing, managing and presenting data which is spatially referenced (linked to location).<p>

In the strictest sense, it is any <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/237495.xml">
information system</link> capable of integrating, storing, editing, analyzing, sharing, and displaying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/4951472.xml">
geographically referenced</link> information.  In a more generic sense, GIS applications are tools that allow users to create interactive queries (user created searches), analyze <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/27667.xml">
spatial</link> information, edit data, maps, and present the results of all these operations. <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/1913728.xml">
Geographic information science</link></b> is the science underlying the geographic concepts, applications and systems, taught in degree and GIS Certificate programs at many universities.</p>
<p>

Geographic information system technology can be used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/26700.xml">
scientific investigation</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1044927.xml">
resource management</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/1557851.xml">
asset management</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/18951655.xml">
archaeology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/2364800.xml">
environmental impact assessment</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/45346.xml">
urban planning</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/7294.xml">
cartography</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/19278960.xml">
criminology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/8979002.xml">
geographic history</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/59252.xml">
marketing</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/77547.xml">
logistics</link> to name a few. For example, GIS might allow emergency planners to easily calculate emergency response times in the event of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/58921.xml">
natural disaster</link>, GIS might be used to find <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/102024.xml">
wetland</link>s that need protection from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollution</link>, or GIS can be used by a company to site a new business location to take advantage of a previously under-served <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/3736784.xml">
market</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History of development</st>
<p>

About 15,500 years ago <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, on the walls of caves near <geological_formation wordnetid="109287968" confidence="0.8">
<cave wordnetid="109238926" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/18594.xml">
Lascaux</link></cave>
</geological_formation>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
, <chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<hominid wordnetid="102471762" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<placental wordnetid="101886756" confidence="0.8">
<primate wordnetid="102469914" confidence="0.8">
<mammal wordnetid="101861778" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../335/225335.xml">
Cro-Magnon</link></animal>
</mammal>
</primate>
</placental>
</vertebrate>
</hominid>
</chordate>
 hunters drew pictures of the animals they hunted.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Associated with the animal drawings are track lines and tallies thought to depict migration routes. While simplistic in comparison to modern technologies, these early records mimic the two-element structure of modern geographic information systems, an image associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/40738.xml">
attribute</link> information.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>
In 1854, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/1160623.xml">
John Snow</link> depicted a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/7591.xml">
cholera</link> outbreak in London using points to represent the locations of some individual cases, possibly the earliest use of the geographic method.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> His study of the distribution of cholera led to the source of the disease, a contaminated water pump (the Broad Street Pump, whose handle he disconnected terminating the outbreak) within the heart of the cholera outbreak. <image location="right" width="300px" src="Snow-cholera-map.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/17225836.xml">
E. W. Gilbert</link>'s version (1958) of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/1160623.xml">
John Snow</link>'s 1855 map of the Soho cholera outbreak showing the clusters of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/7591.xml">
cholera</link> cases in the <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/17867.xml">
London</link></village>
 epidemic of 1854
</caption>
</image>
 While the basic elements of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/29954.xml">
topology</link> and theme existed previously in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/7294.xml">
cartography</link>, the John Snow map was unique, using cartographic methods not only to depict but also to analyze clusters of geographically dependent phenomena for the first time.</p>
<p>

The early 20th century saw the development of "photo lithography" where maps were separated into layers. Computer hardware development spurred by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/21785.xml">
nuclear weapon</link> research would lead to general purpose computer "mapping" applications by the early 1960s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

The year 1962 saw the development of the world's first true operational GIS in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/22219.xml">
Ottawa, Ontario</link>, Canada by the federal Department of Forestry and Rural Development. Developed by Dr. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<geographer wordnetid="110127555" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/4061593.xml">
Roger Tomlinson</link></scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</geographer>
</intellectual>
</person>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
, it was called the "<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/1256197.xml">
Canada Geographic Information System</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
" (CGIS) and was used to store, analyze, and manipulate data collected for the <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/4243331.xml">
Canada Land Inventory</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
 (CLI)—an initiative to determine the land capability for rural Canada by mapping information about soils, agriculture, recreation, wildlife, waterfowl, forestry, and land use at a scale of 1:50,000. A rating classification factor was also added to permit analysis.</p>
<p>

CGIS was the world's first "system" and was an improvement over "mapping" applications as it provided capabilities for overlay, measurement, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/386407.xml">
digitizing</link>/scanning.  It supported a national coordinate system that spanned the continent, coded lines as "arcs" having a true embedded topology, and it stored the attribute and locational information in separate files. As a result of this, Tomlinson has become known as the "father of GIS," particularly for his use of overlays in promoting the spatial analysis of convergent geographic data.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  CGIS lasted into the 1990s and built the largest digital land resource database in Canada. It was developed as a mainframe based system in support of federal and provincial resource planning and management. Its strength was continent-wide analysis of complex <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/8495.xml">
dataset</link>s. The CGIS was never available in a commercial form.</p>
<p>

In 1964, Howard T Fisher formed the  Laboratory for Computer Graphics and Spatial Analysis at the Harvard Graduate School of Design (LCGSA 1965-1991), where a number of important theoretical concepts in spatial data handling were developed, and which by the 1970s had distributed seminal software code and systems, such as 'SYMAP', 'GRID', and 'ODYSSEY' -- which served as literal and inspirational sources for subsequent commercial development -- to universities, research centers, and corporations worldwide.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

By the early 1980s,  M&amp;S Computing (later <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/1769437.xml">
Intergraph</link></company>
), Environmental Systems Research Institute (<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/141435.xml">
ESRI</link></company>
) and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/631060.xml">
CARIS</link></institution>
</company>
 (Computer Aided Resource Information System) emerged as commercial vendors of GIS software, successfully incorporating many of the CGIS features, combining the first generation approach to separation of spatial and attribute information with a second generation approach to organizing attribute data into database structures. 
In parallel, the development of two public domain systems began in the late 1970s and early 1980s. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/19348017.xml">
MOSS</link>, the Map Overlay and Statistical System project started in 1977 in Fort Collins, Colorado under the auspices of the Western Energy and Land Use Team (WELUT) and the US Fish and Wildlife Service. <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/549892.xml">
GIS</link></software>
 was begun in 1982 by the U.S. Army Corp of Engineering Research Laboratory (USA-CERL) in Champaign, Illinois, a branch of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers to meet the need of the United States military for software for land management and environmental planning. The later 1980s and 1990s industry growth were spurred on by the growing use of GIS on <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
 workstations and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18457137.xml">
personal computer</link>. By the end of the 20th century, the rapid growth in various systems had been consolidated and standardized on relatively few platforms and users were beginning to export the concept of viewing GIS data over the Internet, requiring data format and transfer standards. More recently, there are a growing number of free, open source GIS packages which run on a range of operating systems and can be customized to perform specific tasks.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Techniques used in GIS</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Data creation</st>
<p>

Modern GIS technologies use digital information, for which various digitized data creation methods are used. The most common method of data creation is digitization, where a hard copy map or survey plan is transferred into a digital medium through the use of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/37315.xml">
computer-aided design</link> (CAD) program, and geo-referencing capabilities.  With the wide availability of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/595704.xml">
ortho-rectified imagery</link> (both from satellite and aerial sources), heads-up digitizing is becoming the main avenue through which geographic data is extracted.  Heads-up digitizing involves the tracing of geographic data directly on top of the aerial imagery instead of through the traditional method of tracing the geographic form on a separate digitizing tablet.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Relating information from different sources</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="46px" src="Globe_important.svg">
<caption>

Globe icon
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The examples and perspective in this article or section may not represent a  of the subject.
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Geographic_information_system&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> or discuss the issue on the .</col>
</row>
</table>


If you could relate information about the rainfall of your <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/28151.xml">
state</link> to aerial photographs of your <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/36656.xml">
county</link>, you might be able to tell which wetlands dry up at certain times of the year. A GIS, which can use information from many different sources in many different forms, can help with such analyses. The primary requirement for the source data consists of knowing the locations for the variables. Location may be annotated by x, y, and z coordinates of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/17617.xml">
longitude</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/17616.xml">
latitude</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/1765158.xml">
elevation</link>, or by other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/517305.xml">
geocode</link> systems like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/51550.xml">
ZIP Code</link>s or by highway <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/285728.xml">
mile marker</link>s. Any variable that can be located spatially can be fed into a GIS. Several computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link>s that can be directly entered into a GIS are being produced by government agencies and non-government organizations. Different kinds of data in map form can be entered into a GIS.</p>
<p>

A GIS can also convert existing digital information, which may not yet be in map form, into forms it can recognize and use. For example, digital <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/1184557.xml">
satellite images</link> generated through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/228148.xml">
remote sensing</link> can be analyzed to produce a map-like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/41310.xml">
layer</link> of digital information about vegetative covers. Another fairly developed resource for naming GIS objects is the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<wordbook wordnetid="106418693" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<dictionary wordnetid="106418901" confidence="0.8">
<reference_book wordnetid="106417598" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/2295995.xml">
Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</link></publication>
</reference_book>
</dictionary>
</book>
</wordbook>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/2295995.xml">
GTGN</link>), which is a structured vocabulary containing around 1,000,000 names and other information about places<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gis.ednet.ns.ca/gis_uses_in_US.htm">
http://gis.ednet.ns.ca/gis_uses_in_US.htm</weblink>.</p>
<p>

Likewise, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/6889.xml">
census</link> or hydrologic tabular data can be converted to map-like form, serving as layers of thematic information in a GIS.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Data representation</st>
<p>

GIS data represents real world objects (roads, land use, elevation) with digital <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/18985040.xml">
data</link>. Real world objects can be divided into two abstractions: discrete objects (a house) and continuous fields (rain fall amount or elevation). There are two broad methods used to store data in a GIS for both abstractions: Raster and Vector.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Raster</st>
<p>

A raster data type is, in essence, any type of digital image represented in grids. Anyone who is familiar with digital photography will recognize the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/25742.xml">
pixel</link></format>
</artifact>
</structure>
</information>
</message>
 as the smallest individual unit of an image. A combination of these pixels will create an image, distinct from the commonly used <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/27751.xml">
scalable vector graphics</link> which are the basis of the vector model. While a digital image is concerned with the output as representation of reality, in a photograph or art transferred to computer, the raster data type will reflect an abstraction of reality. Aerial photos are one commonly used form of raster data, with only one purpose, to display a detailed image on a map or for the purposes of digitization. Other raster data sets will contain information regarding elevation, a <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/78442.xml">
DEM</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
, or reflectance of a particular wavelength of light, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/387175.xml">
LANDSAT</link>.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="geabios3d.jpg">
<caption>

Digital elevation model, map (image), and vector data
</caption>
</image>

<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/1189937.xml">
Raster</link></artifact>
</structure>
 data type consists of rows and columns of cells, with each cell storing a single value. Raster data can be images (<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/25742.xml">
raster</link></format>
</artifact>
</structure>
</information>
</message>
 images) with each pixel (or cell) containing a color value.  Additional values recorded for each cell may be a discrete value, such as land use, a continuous value, such as temperature, or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/3009807.xml">
null</link> value if no data is available. While a raster cell stores a single value, it can be extended by using raster bands to represent RGB (red, green, blue) colors, colormaps (a mapping between a thematic code and RGB value), or an extended attribute table with one row for each unique cell value. The resolution of the raster data set is its cell width in ground units. </p>
<p>

Raster data is stored in various formats; from a standard file-based structure of TIF, JPEG, etc. to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/313755.xml">
binary large object</link> (BLOB) data stored directly in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/98743.xml">
relational database management system</link> (RDBMS) similar to other vector-based feature classes.  Database storage, when properly indexed, typically allows for quicker retrieval of the raster data but can require storage of millions of significantly-sized records.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Vector</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Simple_vector_map.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A simple vector map, using each of the vector elements: points for wells, lines for rivers, and a polygon for the lake.
</caption>
</image>

In a GIS, geographical features are often expressed as vectors, by considering those features as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/18973446.xml">
geometrical</link> shapes.    Different geographical features are expressed by different types of geometry:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/593693.xml">
Points</link>: Zero-dimensional points are used for geographical features that can best be expressed by a single point reference; in other words, simple location.  For example, the locations of wells, peak elevations, features of interest or trailheads. Points convey the least amount of information of these file types. Points can also be used to represent areas when displayed at a small scale.  For example, cities on a map of the world would be represented by points rather than polygons.  No measurements are possible with point features.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/76323.xml">
Line</link>s or polylines: One-dimensional lines or polylines are used for linear features such as rivers, roads, railroads, trails, and topographic lines. Again, as with point features, linear features displayed at a small scale will be represented as linear features rather than as a polygon. Line features can measure distance.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/23621.xml">
Polygon</link>s: Two-dimensional polygons are used for geographical features that cover a particular area of the earth's surface.  Such features may include lakes, park boundaries, buildings, city boundaries, or land uses.  Polygons convey the most amount of information of the file types.  Polygon features can measure perimeter and area.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Each of these geometries is linked to a row in a database that describes their attributes.  For example, a database that describes lakes may contain a lake's depth, water quality, pollution level.  This information can be used to make a map to describe a particular attribute of the dataset.  For example, lakes could be coloured depending on level of pollution.  Different geometries can also be compared.  For example, the GIS could be used to identify all wells (point geometry) that are within 1-mile (1.6&nbsp;km) of a lake (polygon geometry) that has a high level of pollution.</p>
<p>

Vector features can be made to respect spatial integrity through the application of topology rules such as 'polygons must not overlap'. Vector data can also be used to represent continuously varying phenomena. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/650086.xml">
Contour line</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/2857072.xml">
triangulated irregular network</link>s (TIN) are used to represent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/1765158.xml">
elevation</link> or other continuously changing values. TINs record values at point locations, which are connected by lines to form an irregular mesh of triangles. The face of the triangles represent the terrain surface.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Advantages and disadvantages</st>
<p>

There are advantages and disadvantages to using a raster or vector data model to represent reality. Raster datasets record a value for all points in the area covered which may require more storage space than representing data in a vector format that can store data only where needed. Raster data also allows easy implementation of overlay operations, which are more difficult with vector data. Vector data can be displayed as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/32499.xml">
vector graphics</link> used on traditional maps, whereas raster data will appear as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/71925.xml">
image</link> that, depending on the resolution of the raster file, may have a blocky appearance for object boundaries. Vector data can be easier to register, scale, and re-project. This can simplify combining vector layers from different sources. Vector data is more compatible with relational database environments. They can be part of a relational table as a normal column and processed using a multitude of operators.</p>
<p>

The file size for vector data is usually much smaller for storage and sharing than raster data.  Image or raster data can be 10 to 100 times larger than vector data depending on the resolution.  Another advantage of vector data is that it is easy to update and maintain.  For example, a new highway is added.  The raster image will have to be completely reproduced, but the vector data, "roads," can be easily updated by adding the missing road segment.  In addition, vector data allows much more analysis capability, especially for "networks" such as roads, power, rail, telecommunications, etc.  For example, with vector data attributed with the characteristics of roads, ports, and airfields, allows the analyst to query for the best route or method of transportation.  In the vector data, the analyst can query the data for the largest port with an airfield within 60 miles and a connecting road that is at least two lane highway. Raster data will not have all the characteristics of the features it displays.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Non-spatial data</st>
<p>

Additional non-spatial data can also be stored along with the spatial data represented by the coordinates of a vector geometry or the position of a raster cell. In vector data, the additional data contains attributes of the feature. For example, a forest inventory polygon may also have an identifier value and information about tree species. In raster data the cell value can store attribute information, but it can also be used as an identifier that can relate to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/492295.xml">
records</link> in another table.</p>
<p>

There is also software being developed to support spatial and non-spatial decision-making. In this software, the solutions to spatial problems are integrated with solutions to non-spatial problems. The end result it is hoped with these Flexible Spatial Decision-Making Support Systems (FSDSS)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> will be that non experts can use GIS and spatial criteria with their other non spatial criteria to view solutions to multi-criteria problems that will support decision making.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Data capture</st>
<p>

Data capture—entering information into the system—consumes much of the time of GIS practitioners. There are a variety of methods used to enter data into a GIS where it is stored in a digital format. </p>
<p>

Existing data printed on paper or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/172928.xml">
PET film</link> maps can be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/386407.xml">
digitized</link> or scanned to produce digital data. A digitizer produces vector data as an operator traces points, lines, and polygon boundaries from a map. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/317625.xml">
Scanning</link> a map results in raster data that could be further processed to produce vector data.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/60891.xml">
Survey</link> data can be directly entered into a GIS from digital data collection systems on survey instruments using a technique called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
Coordinate Geometry (COGO)</link>. Positions from a <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
Global Positioning System</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 (GPS), another survey tool, can also be directly entered into a GIS.</p>
<p>

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/228148.xml">
Remotely sensed</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
 data also plays an important role in data collection and consist of sensors attached to a platform. Sensors include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/52648.xml">
camera</link>s, digital scanners and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/41958.xml">
LIDAR</link>, while platforms usually consist of aircraft and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/27683.xml">
satellite</link>s.</p>
<p>

The majority of digital data currently comes from photo interpretation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/326279.xml">
aerial photographs</link>. <link>
Soft copy workstation</link>s are used to digitize features directly from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/201460.xml">
stereo pairs</link> of digital photographs. These systems allow data to be captured in two and three dimensions, with elevations measured directly from a stereo pair using principles of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/552840.xml">
photogrammetry</link>. Currently, analog aerial photos are scanned before being entered into a soft copy system, but as high quality digital cameras become cheaper this step will be skipped.</p>
<p>

Satellite remote sensing provides another important source of spatial data. Here satellites use different sensor packages to passively measure the reflectance from parts of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/10134.xml">
electromagnetic spectrum</link> or radio waves that were sent out from an active sensor such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/25676.xml">
radar</link>. Remote sensing collects raster data that can be further processed using different bands to identify objects and classes of interest, such as land cover.</p>
<p>

When data is captured, the user should consider if the data should be captured with either a relative accuracy or absolute accuracy, since this could not only influence how information will be interpreted but also the cost of data capture.</p>
<p>

In addition to collecting and entering spatial data, attribute data is also entered into a GIS. For vector data, this includes additional information about the objects represented in the system.</p>
<p>

After entering data into a GIS, the data usually requires editing, to remove errors, or further processing. For vector data it must be made "topologically correct" before it can be used for some advanced analysis. For example, in a road network, lines must connect with nodes at an intersection. Errors such as undershoots and overshoots must also be removed. For scanned maps, blemishes on the source map may need to be removed from the resulting raster. For example, a fleck of dirt might connect two lines that should not be connected.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Raster-to-vector translation</st>
<p>

Data restructuring can be performed by a GIS to convert data into different formats. For example, a GIS may be used to convert a satellite image map to a vector structure by generating lines around all cells with the same classification, while determining the cell spatial relationships, such as adjacency or inclusion.</p>
<p>

More advanced data processing can occur with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/76332.xml">
image processing</link>, a technique developed in the late 1960s by <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/18426568.xml">
NASA</link></agency>
 and the private sector to provide <link>
contrast enhancement</link>, false colour rendering and a variety of other techniques including use of two dimensional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/52247.xml">
Fourier transforms</link>.  </p>
<p>

Since digital data is collected and stored in various ways, the two data sources may not be entirely compatible. So a GIS must be able to convert <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/1096526.xml">
geographic data</link> from one structure to another.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Projections, coordinate systems and registration</st>
<p>

A property ownership <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/19877.xml">
map</link> and a soils map might show data at different scales. Map information in a GIS must be manipulated so that it registers, or fits, with information gathered from other maps. Before the digital data can be analyzed, they may have to undergo other manipulations—projection and coordinate conversions, for example—that integrate them into a GIS.</p>
<p>

The earth can be represented by various models, each of which may provide a different set of coordinates (e.g., latitude, longitude, elevation) for any given point on the earth's surface. The simplest model is to assume the earth is a perfect sphere. As more measurements of the earth have accumulated, the models of the earth have become more sophisticated and more accurate. In fact, there are models that apply to different areas of the earth to provide increased accuracy (e.g., North American Datum, 1927 - NAD27 - works well in North America, but not in Europe). See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/67153.xml">
datum (geodesy)</link> for more information.</p>
<p>

<it>Projection</it> is a fundamental component of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/7294.xml">
map making</link>. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/51784.xml">
projection</link> is a mathematical means of transferring information from a model of the Earth, which represents a three-dimensional curved surface, to a two-dimensional medium—paper or a computer screen. Different projections are used for different types of maps because each projection particularly suits certain uses. For example, a projection that accurately represents the shapes of the continents will distort their relative sizes. See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/51784.xml">
Map projection</link> for more information.</p>
<p>

Since much of the information in a GIS comes from existing maps, a GIS uses the processing power of the computer to transform digital information, gathered from sources with different projections and/or different coordinate systems, to a common projection and coordinate system. For images, this process is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/9871405.xml">
rectification</link>.</p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Spatial analysis with GIS</st>
<p>

Given the vast range of spatial analysis techniques that have been developed over the past half century, any summary or review can only cover the subject to a limited depth. This is a rapidly changing field, and GIS packages are increasingly including analytical tools as standard built-in facilities or as optional toolsets, add-ins or 'analysts'. In many instances such facilities are provided by the original software suppliers (commercial vendors or collaborative non commercial development teams), whilst in other cases facilities have been developed and are provided by third parties. Furthermore, many products offer software development kits (SDKs), programming languages and language support, scripting facilities and/or special interfaces for developing one’s own analytical tools or variants. The website Geospatial Analysis and associated book/ebook attempt to provide a reasonably comprehensive guide to the subject <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/output/">
http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/output/</weblink>. </p>

<ss2>
<st>
Data modeling</st>
<p>

It is difficult to relate wetlands maps to rainfall amounts recorded at different points such as airports, television stations, and high schools. A GIS, however, can be used to depict two- and three-dimensional characteristics of the Earth's surface, subsurface, and atmosphere from information points. For example, a GIS can quickly generate a map with isopleth or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/650086.xml">
contour line</link>s that indicate differing amounts of rainfall.</p>
<p>

Such a map can be thought of as a rainfall contour map. Many sophisticated methods can estimate the characteristics of surfaces from a limited number of point measurements. A two-dimensional contour map created from the surface modeling of rainfall point measurements may be overlaid and analyzed with any other map in a GIS covering the same area.</p>
<p>

Additionally, from a series of three-dimensional points, or digital elevation model, isopleth lines representing elevation contours can be generated, along with slope analysis, shaded relief, and other elevation products. Watersheds can be easily defined for any given reach, by computing all of the areas contiguous and uphill from any given point of interest. Similarly, an expected <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/744639.xml">
thalweg</link> of where surface water would want to travel in intermittent and permanent streams can be computed from elevation data in the GIS.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Topological modeling</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link>
 Geospatial topology</link></it>
</indent>

In the past years, were there any gas stations or factories operating next to the swamp? Any within two miles (3 km) and uphill from the swamp? A GIS can recognize and analyze the spatial relationships that exist within digitally stored spatial data. These topological relationships allow complex spatial modelling and analysis to be performed. Topological relationships between geometric entities traditionally include adjacency (what adjoins what), containment (what encloses what), and proximity (how close something is to something else).</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Networks</st>
<p>

If all the factories near a wetland were accidentally to release chemicals into the river at the same time, how long would it take for a damaging amount of pollutant to enter the wetland reserve? A GIS can simulate the routing of materials along a linear network. Values such as slope, speed limit, or pipe diameter can be incorporated into network modeling in order to represent the flow of the phenomenon more accurately. Network modelling is commonly employed in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/75472.xml">
transportation planning</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/13435.xml">
hydrology</link> modeling, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/174521.xml">
infrastructure</link> modeling.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Cartographic modeling</st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="500px" src="gislayers.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

 An example of use of layers in a GIS application.  In this example, the forest cover layer (light green) is at the bottom, with the topographic layer over it.  Next up is the stream layer, then the boundary layer, then the road layer.  The order is very important in order to properly display the final result.  Note that the pond layer was located just below the stream layer, so that a stream line can be seen overlying one of the ponds.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The term "cartographic modeling" was (probably) coined by Dana Tomlin in his PhD dissertation and later in his book which has the term in the title. Cartographic modeling refers to a process where several thematic layers of the same area are produced, processed, and analyzed. Tomlin used raster layers, but the overlay method (see below) can be used more generally. Operations on map layers can be combined into algorithms, and eventually into simulation or optimization models.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Map overlay</st>
<p>

The combination of several spatial datasets (points, lines or polygons) creates a new output vector dataset, visually similar to stacking several maps of the same region. These overlays are similar to mathematical <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<chart wordnetid="106999802" confidence="0.8">
<visual_communication wordnetid="106873252" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/61701.xml">
Venn diagram</link></visual_communication>
</chart>
</concept>
</idea>
 overlays. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/47949.xml">
union</link> overlay combines the geographic features and attribute tables of both inputs into a single new output. An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/48157.xml">
intersect</link> overlay defines the area where both inputs overlap and retains a set of attribute fields for each. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/262288.xml">
symmetric difference</link> overlay defines an output area that includes the total area of both inputs except for the overlapping area. </p>
<p>

Data extraction is a GIS process similar to vector overlay, though it can be used in either vector or raster data analysis. Rather than combining the properties and features of both datasets, data extraction involves using a "clip" or "mask" to extract the features of one data set that fall within the spatial extent of another dataset. </p>
<p>

In raster data analysis, the overlay of datasets is accomplished through a process known as "local operation on multiple rasters" or "map algebra," through a function that combines the values of each raster's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19008728.xml">
matrix</link>. This function may weigh some inputs more than others through use of an "index model" that reflects the influence of various factors upon a geographic phenomenon.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Automated cartography</st>
<p>

Digital cartography and GIS both encode spatial relationships in structured formal representations. GIS is used in digital cartography modeling as a (semi)automated process of making maps, so called Automated Cartography. In practice, it can be a subset of a GIS, within which it is equivalent to the stage of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/73362.xml">
visualization</link>, since in most cases not all of the GIS functionality is used. Cartographic products can be either in a digital or in a hardcopy format. Powerful analysis techniques with different data representation can produce high-quality maps within a short time period. The main problem in Automated Cartography is to use a single set of data to produce multiple products at a variety of scales, a technique known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/12746.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Generalization+of+geo-spatial+data%22])">
Generalization</link>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Geostatistics</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link>
 Geostatistics</link></it>
</indent>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/51531.xml">
Geostatistics</link> is a point-pattern analysis that produces field predictions from data points.  It is a way of looking at the statistical properties of those special data.  It is different from general applications of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistics</link> because it employs the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
graph theory</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19008728.xml">
matrix algebra</link> to reduce the number of parameters in the data.  Only the second-order properties of the GIS data are analyzed.</p>
<p>

When phenomena are measured, the observation methods dictate the accuracy of any subsequent analysis.  Due to the nature of the data (e.g. traffic patterns in an urban environment; weather patterns over the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/23070.xml">
Pacific Ocean</link>), a constant or dynamic degree of precision is always lost in the measurement.  This loss of precision is determined from the scale and distribution of the data collection.</p>
<p>

To determine the statistical relevance of the analysis, an average is determined so that points (gradients) outside of any immediate measurement can be included to determine their predicted behavior.  This is due to the limitations of the applied statistic and data collection methods, and interpolation is required in order to predict the behavior of particles, points, and locations that are not directly measurable.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="Dem.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Hillshade model derived from a Digital Elevation Model (DEM) of the Valestra area in the northern Apennines (Italy)
</caption>
</image>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/14569.xml">
Interpolation</link> is the process by which a surface is created, usually a raster dataset, through the input of data collected at a number of sample points. There are several forms of interpolation, each which treats the data differently, depending on the properties of the data set. In comparing interpolation methods, the first consideration should be whether or not the source data will change (exact or approximate). Next is whether the method is subjective, a human interpretation, or objective. Then there is the nature of transitions between points: are they abrupt or gradual. Finally, there is whether a method is global (it uses the entire data set to form the model), or local where an algorithm is repeated for a small section of terrain.</p>
<p>

Interpolation is a justified measurement because of a Spatial Autocorrelation Principle that recognizes that data collected at any position will have a great similarity to, or influence of those locations within its immediate vicinity.</p>
<p>

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/78442.xml">
Digital elevation model</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
s (DEM), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/2857072.xml">
triangulated irregular network</link>s (TIN), Edge finding algorithms, Theissen Polygons, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/11659.xml">
Fourier analysis</link>, <link>
Weighted moving average</link>s, Inverse Distance Weighted, Moving averages, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/477026.xml">
Kriging</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/457680.xml">
Spline</link>, and Trend surface analysis are all mathematical methods to produce interpolative data.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Address Geocoding</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/1876018.xml">
Geocoding</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</it>
</indent>
Geocoding is interpolating spatial locations (X,Y coordinates) from street addresses or any other spatially referenced data such as ZIP Codes, parcel lots and address locations. A reference theme is required to <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/1876018.xml">
geocode</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 individual addresses, such as a road centerline file with address ranges. The individual address locations are interpolated, or estimated, by examining address ranges along a road segment. These are usually provided in the form of a table or database. The GIS will then place a dot approximately where that address belongs along the segment of centerline. For example, an address point of 500 will be at the midpoint of a line segment that starts with address 1 and ends with address 1000. Geocoding can also be applied against actual parcel data, typically from municipal tax maps. In this case, the result of the geocoding will be an actually positioned space as opposed to an interpolated point.</p>
<p>

It should be noted that there are several (potentially dangerous) caveats that are often overlooked when using interpolation. See the full entry for <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/1876018.xml">
Geocoding</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 for more information.</p>
<p>

Various algorithms are used to help with address matching when the spellings of addresses differ. Address information that a particular entity or organization has data on, such as the post office, may not entirely match the reference theme. There could be variations in street name spelling, community name, etc. Consequently, the user generally has the ability to make matching criteria more stringent, or to relax those parameters so that more addresses will be mapped. Care must be taken to review the results so as not to map addresses incorrectly due to overzealous matching parameters.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Reverse geocoding</st>
<p>

Reverse geocoding is the process of returning an estimated street address number as it relates to a given coordinate. For example, a user can click on a road centerline theme (thus providing a coordinate) and have information returned that reflects the estimated house number. This house number is interpolated from a range assigned to that road segment. If the user clicks at the midpoint of a segment that starts with address 1 and ends with 100, the returned value will be somewhere near 50. Note that reverse geocoding does not return actual addresses, only estimates of what should be there based on the predetermined range.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Data output and cartography</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/7294.xml">
Cartography</link> is the design and production of maps, or visual representations of spatial data. The vast majority of modern cartography is done with the help of computers, usually using a GIS but production quality cartography is also achieve by importing layers into a design program to refine it. Most GIS software gives the user substantial control over the appearance of the data.</p>
<p>

Cartographic work serves two major functions:</p>
<p>

First, it produces graphics on the screen or on paper that convey the results of analysis to the people who make decisions about resources. Wall maps and other graphics can be generated, allowing the viewer to visualize and thereby understand the results of analyses or simulations of potential events. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/2414293.xml">
Web Map Server</link>s facilitate distribution of generated maps through web browsers using various implementations of web-based application programming interfaces (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/1610950.xml">
AJAX</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link>, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/20947.xml">
Flash</link></software>
, etc).</p>
<p>

Second, other database information can be generated for further analysis or use.  An example would be a list of all addresses within one mile (1.6 km) of a toxic spill.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Graphic display techniques</st>
<p>

Traditional maps are abstractions of the real world, a sampling of important elements portrayed on a sheet of paper with symbols to represent physical objects. People who use maps must interpret these symbols. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/70713.xml">
Topographic map</link>s show the shape of land surface with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/650086.xml">
contour line</link>s or with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/7963618.xml">
shaded relief</link>.  </p>
<p>

Today, graphic display techniques such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/250304.xml">
shading</link> based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/59211.xml">
altitude</link> in a GIS can make relationships among map elements visible, heightening one's ability to extract and analyze information. For example, two types of data were combined in a GIS to produce a perspective view of a portion of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/82063.xml">
San Mateo County</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/5407.xml">
California</link></country>
. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/78442.xml">
digital elevation model</link>, consisting of surface elevations recorded on a 30-meter horizontal grid, shows high elevations as white and low elevation as black.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The accompanying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/387175.xml">
Landsat</link> Thematic Mapper image shows a false-color infrared image looking down at the same area in 30-meter pixels, or picture elements, for the same coordinate points, pixel by pixel, as the elevation information.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A GIS was used to register and combine the two images to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/25775.xml">
render</link> the three-dimensional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/380405.xml">
perspective view</link> looking down the <position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<mistake wordnetid="100070965" confidence="0.8">
<nonaccomplishment wordnetid="100066216" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/64460.xml">
San Andreas Fault</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</location>
</nonaccomplishment>
</mistake>
</landmark>
</point>
</position>
, using the Thematic Mapper image pixels, but shaded using the elevation of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/250515.xml">
landform</link>s. The GIS display depends on the viewing point of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/22649.xml">
observer</link> and time of day of the display, to properly render the shadows created by the sun's rays at that latitude, longitude, and time of day.</p>
<p>

An archeochrome is a new way of displaying spatial data. It is a thematic on a 3D map that is applied to a specific building or a part of a building. It is suited to the visual display of heat loss data.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Spatial ETL</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/6173472.xml">
Spatial ETL</link> tools provide the data processing functionality of traditional <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<tool wordnetid="104451818" confidence="0.8">
<implement wordnetid="103563967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/239516.xml">
Extract, Transform, Load</link></implement>
</tool>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 (ETL) software, but with a primary focus on the ability to manage spatial data. They provide GIS users with the ability to translate data between different standards and proprietary formats, whilst geometrically transforming the data en-route.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
GIS software</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/1877442.xml">
List of GIS software</link></it>
</indent>

Geographic information can be accessed, transferred, transformed, overlaid, processed and displayed using numerous software applications.  Within industry, commercial offerings from companies such as <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/2973309.xml">
Smallworld</link></institution>
</company>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/141435.xml">
ESRI</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/1769437.xml">
Intergraph</link></company>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/1894018.xml">
Mapinfo</link> and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/180584.xml">
Autodesk</link></company>
 dominate, offering an entire suite of tools.  Government and military departments often use custom software, open source products, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/549892.xml">
GRASS</link>, or more specialized products that meet a well defined need.  Although free tools exist to view GIS datasets, public access to geographic information is dominated by online resources such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/2126501.xml">
Google Earth</link></software>
 and interactive web mapping.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Background </st>
<p>

Originally up to the late 1990s, when GIS data was mostly based on large computers and used to maintain internal records, software was a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/17946878.xml">
stand-alone</link> product. However with increased access to the internet and networks and demand for distributed geographic data grew, GIS software gradually changed its entire outlook to the delivery of data over a network. GIS software is now usually marketed as combination of various interoperable applications and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
API</link>s.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Data creation </st>

<p>

GIS processing software is used for the task of preparing data for use within a GIS. This transforms the raw or legacy geographic data into a format usable by GIS products. For example an aerial photograph may need to be stretched (orthorectified) using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/552840.xml">
photogrammetry</link> so that its pixels align with longitude and latitude gradations (or whatever grid is needed). This can be distinguished from the transformations done within GIS analysis software by the fact that these changes are permanent, more complex and time consuming. Thus, a specialized high-end type of software is generally used by a person skilled in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/228148.xml">
Remote Sensing</link> and / or GIS processing aspects of computer science. In addition, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/2753.xml">
AutoCAD</link></software>
, normally used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/171414.xml">
drafts</link> of engineering projects, can be configured for the editing of vector maps, and has some products that have migrated towards GIS use. It is especially useful as it has strong support for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/386407.xml">
digitization</link>. Raw geographic data can be edited in many standard database and spreadsheet applications and in some cases a text editor may be used as long as care is taken to properly format data.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Geodatabases </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/1404391.xml">
Geodatabase</link></format>
</information>
</message>
</it>
</indent>

A geodatabase is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> with extensions for storing, indexing, querying, and manipulating geographic information and spatial data. While some geodatabases have functions built in to allow geoprocessing, the primary benefit of a geodatabase is in the "database type" capabilities that it gives to spatial data.  Some of these capabilities include easy access using standard database drivers such as ODBC, the ability to easily link or join data tables, also indexing and grouping of spatial datasets independent of software platform.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Management and analysis </st>

<p>

GIS analysis software takes GIS data and overlays or otherwise combines it so that the data can be visually analysed. It can output a detailed map, image or movie used to communicate an idea or concept with respect to a region of interest. This is usually used by persons who are trained in cartography, geography or a GIS professional as this type of application is complex and takes some time to master. The software performs transformation on raster and vector data sometimes of differing datums, grid system, or reference system, into one coherent image. It can also analyse changes over time within a region. This software is central to the professional analysis and presentation of GIS data. Examples include the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/2783580.xml">
ArcGIS</link></software>
 family of ESRI GIS applications (which replaced ESRI's older <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/4071206.xml">
Arc/INFO</link></software>
), <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/2973309.xml">
Smallworld</link></institution>
</company>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/15998393.xml">
Civil Designer</link>, <link>
XMap</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/549892.xml">
GRASS</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Statistical </st>

<p>

GIS statistical software uses standard database queries to retrieve and analyse data for decision making. For example, if one has geographic data that includes detailed demographic information, one can determine how many individuals of a certain age, income, and ethnicity live in a given street block. The data is sometimes referenced with postal codes or street locations rather than with geodetic data. This can be used by computer scientists and statisticians with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link> skills, with an objective of characterizing an area to aid in decisions regarding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/59252.xml">
marketing</link>, social services, emergency planning, etc. Standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/8513.xml">
DBMS</link> can be used or specialized GIS statistical software. These are often housed on servers so that they can be queried with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/33173.xml">
web browser</link>s. Examples are <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/19545.xml">
MySQL</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 or <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/2544228.xml">
ArcSDE</link></software>
.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Readers </st>
<p>

GIS readers are computer applications that are designed to allow users to easily view digital maps as well as view and query GIS-managed data. By definition, they usually allow very little if any editing of the map or underlying map data. Readers can be normal standalone applications that need to be installed locally, though they are often designed to connect to data servers over the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> to access the relevant information. Readers can also be included as an embedded application within a web page, obviating the need for local installation. Readers are designed to be relatively simple and easy to use as well as free.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Web API </st>
<p>

This is the evolution of the scripts that were common with most early GIS systems. An application programming interface (API) is a set of subroutines (organized as object oriented programming) designed to perform a specific task. GIS APIs are designed to manage GIS data for its delivery to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/33173.xml">
web browser</link> client from a GIS server. They are accessed with commonly used scripting language such as <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/32778.xml">
VBA</link></programming_language>
 or <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/9845.xml">
JavaScript</link></programming_language>
. They are used to build a server system for the delivery of GIS that is to made available over an intranet or publicly over the Internet.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Mobile GIS </st>

<p>

GIS has seen many implementations on mobile devices.  With the widespread adoption of GPS, GIS has been used to capture and integrate data in the field.  In the past, gathering GIS in the field was done through marking geographic information onto a paper map and then translating that information into digital format back at the computer.  Now, through the use of mobile devices, geographic data can be directly captured out in the field.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Free and Open-source GIS software</st>
<p>

Many GIS tasks can be accomplished with free or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/277663.xml">
open-source software</link>. </p>
<p>

With the broad use of non-proprietary and open data formats such as the Shape File format for vector data and the Geotiff format for raster data, as well as the adoption of OGC standards for networked servers, development of open source software continues to evolve, especially for web and web service oriented applications. Well-known open source GIS software includes <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/549892.xml">
GRASS GIS</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/4902158.xml">
Quantum GIS</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/6826346.xml">
MapServer</link></software>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4532510.xml">
uDig</link>, <link>
OpenJUMP</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/3500995.xml">
gvSIG</link> and many others (e.g., see <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.osgeo.org">
OSGeo</weblink> or <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.maptools.org">
MapTools</weblink>). </p>
<p>

Much open source GIS development has focused on the creation of libraries that provide functionality for third party applications. Such libraries include <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/5257130.xml">
GDAL/OGR</link></software>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/1803916.xml">
GeoTools</link>. These libraries are used by open source and commercial software alike to provide basic functionality.</p>
<p>

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../963/99963.xml">
PostGIS</link></software>
 provides an open source alternative to geodatabases such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/5776985.xml">
Oracle Spatial</link></software>
, and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/2544228.xml">
ArcSDE</link></software>
.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Vehicle navigation</st>
<p>

A database model of a network of roads and related features is a form of GIS data that is used for vehicle navigation systems. Such a map database is a vector representation of a given road network including road geometry (segment shape), network topology (connectivity) and related attributes (addresses, road class, etc). <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/925715.xml">
Geographic Data Files</link></format>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</information>
</message>
 (GDF) is an <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/14934.xml">
 ISO</link></organization>
 standard for formulating map databases for navigation. An <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/1445706.xml">
Automotive navigation system</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 will combine map-matching, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
GPS</link> coordinates, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/133345.xml">
Dead reckoning</link> to estimate the position of the vehicle.  The map database is also used for route planning and guidance, and possibly advanced functions involving active safety, driver assistance and location-based services. Maintenance of databases for vehicle navigation is discussed in the article <b><know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/10971939.xml">
Map database management</link></method>
</know-how>
</b>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The future of GIS</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="400px" src="GeaBiosOpenLaszloSatelliteMappingApplication2.PNG" type="thumb">
</image>

Many disciplines can benefit from GIS technology. An active GIS market has resulted in lower costs and continual improvements in the hardware and software components of GIS. These developments will, in turn, result in a much wider use of the technology throughout science, government, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
business</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/14543.xml">
industry</link>, with applications including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/63089.xml">
real estate</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/463734.xml">
public health</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/1386551.xml">
crime mapping</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/215337.xml">
national defense</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/29501.xml">
sustainable development</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/21675.xml">
natural resources</link>, landscape architecture, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/18951655.xml">
archaeology</link>, regional and community planning, transportation and logistics. GIS is also diverging into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/62392.xml">
location-based service</link>s (LBS).  LBS allows GPS enabled mobile devices to display their location in relation to fixed assets (nearest restaurant, gas station, fire hydrant),  mobile assets (friends, children, police car)  or to relay their position back to a central server for display or other processing. These services continue to develop with the increased integration of GPS functionality with increasingly powerful mobile electronics (cell phones, PDAs, laptops).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Distributed GIS</st>
<p>

<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/14449501.xml">
Distributed GIS</link></format>
 concerns itself with GI Systems that do not have all of the system components in the same physical location.  This could be the processing, the database, the rendering or the user interface.  Examples of distributed systems are web-based GIS, Mobile GIS, Corporate GIS and GRID computing.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
OGC standards</st>
<p>

<image width="347px" src="Geoservices_server_with_apps.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

OGC standards help GIS tools communicate.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/1043855.xml">
Open Geospatial Consortium</link></it>
</indent>
The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/1043855.xml">
Open Geospatial Consortium</link> (OGC) is an international industry consortium of 334 companies, government agencies and universities participating in a consensus process to develop publicly available geoprocessing specifications. Open interfaces and protocols defined by OpenGIS Specifications support interoperable solutions that "geo-enable" the Web, wireless and location-based services, and mainstream IT, and empower technology developers to make complex spatial information and services accessible and useful with all kinds of applications.  Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) protocols include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/2414293.xml">
Web Map Service</link> (WMS) and <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/405742.xml">
Web Feature Service</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 (WFS).</p>
<p>

GIS products are broken down by the OGC into two categories, based on how completely and accurately the software follows the OGC specifications.</p>
<p>

<it>Compliant Products</it> are software products that comply to OGC's OpenGIS Specifications. When a product has been tested and certified as compliant through the OGC Testing Program, the product is automatically registered as "compliant" on this site.</p>
<p>

<it>Implementing Products</it> are software products that implement OpenGIS Specifications but have not yet passed a compliance test. Compliance tests are not available for all specifications. Developers can register their products as implementing draft or approved specifications, though OGC reserves the right to review and verify each entry.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Web mapping</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/8561200.xml">
Web mapping</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</work>
</it>
</indent>

In recent years there has been an explosion of mapping applications on the web such as <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/1494648.xml">
Google Maps</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/3444247.xml">
Live Maps</link>.  These websites give the public access to huge amounts of geographic data.</p>
<p>

Some of them, like Google Maps and <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/7985488.xml">
OpenLayers</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
, expose an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
API</link> that enable users to create custom applications.  These toolkits commonly offer street maps, aerial/satellite imagery, geocoding, searches, and routing functionality.</p>
<p>

Other applications for publishing geographic information on the web include MapInfo's MapXtreme, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/1769437.xml">
Intergraph</link></company>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/17588500.xml">
GeoMedia</link> WebMap (TM), <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/141435.xml">
ESRI</link></company>
's <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/962855.xml">
ArcIMS</link></software>
, ArcGIS Server, AutoDesk's Mapguide, SeaTrails' AtlasAlive, and the open source <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/6826346.xml">
MapServer</link></software>
.</p>
<p>

In recent years web mapping services have begun to adopt features more common in GIS. Services such as <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/1494648.xml">
Google Maps</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/3444247.xml">
Live Maps</link> allow users to annotate maps and share the maps with others. Conversely, GIS vendors have also created web mapping systems such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/141435.xml">
ESRI</link></company>
's <link>
WebADF</link> that adopt much of the usability and speed of consumer web mapping web sites.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Global change, climate history program and prediction its impact</st>
<p>

Maps have traditionally been used to explore the Earth and to exploit its resources. GIS technology, as an expansion of cartographic science, has enhanced the efficiency and analytic power of traditional mapping. Now, as the scientific community recognizes the environmental consequences of human activity, GIS technology is becoming an essential tool in the effort to understand the process of global change. Various map and satellite information sources can combine in modes that simulate the interactions of complex natural systems.</p>
<p>

Through a function known as visualization, a GIS can be used to produce images - not just maps, but drawings, animations, and other cartographic products. These images allow researchers to view their subjects in ways that literally never have been seen before. The images are often invaluable for conveying the technical concepts of GIS study subjects to non-scientists.</p>
<p>

Prediction of the impact of climate change inheretly involved in many uncertainties sterm from data and model. GIS has been used to in corporated with uncertainty theory to model the coastal impact of climate change, including inudation due to sea-level rise and storm erosion, such as in the east coast of Australia.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Adding the dimension of time</st>
<p>

The condition of the Earth's surface, atmosphere, and subsurface can be examined by feeding satellite data into a GIS. GIS technology gives researchers the ability to examine the variations in Earth processes over days, months, and years. </p>
<p>

As an example, the changes in vegetation vigor through a growing season can be animated to determine when drought was most extensive in a particular region. The resulting graphic, known as a normalized vegetation index, represents a rough measure of plant health. Working with two variables over time would then allow researchers to detect regional differences in the lag between a decline in rainfall and its effect on vegetation.</p>
<p>

GIS technology and the availability of digital data on regional and global scales enable such analyses. The satellite sensor output used to generate a vegetation graphic is produced by the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/5050389.xml">
Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer</link></instrument>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 (AVHRR). This sensor system detects the amounts of energy reflected from the Earth's surface across various bands of the spectrum for surface areas of about 1 square kilometer. The satellite sensor produces images of a particular location on the Earth twice a day. AVHRR is only one of many sensor systems used for Earth surface analysis. More sensors will follow, generating ever greater amounts of data.</p>
<p>

GIS and related technology will help greatly in the management and analysis of these large volumes of data, allowing for better understanding of terrestrial processes and better management of human activities to maintain world economic vitality and environmental quality.</p>
<p>

In addition to the integration of time in environmental studies, GIS is also being explored for its ability to track and model the progress of humans throughout their daily routines. A concrete example of progress in this area is the recent release of time-specific population data by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/447689.xml">
US Census</link>. In this data set, the populations of cities are shown for daytime and evening hours highlighting the pattern of concentration and dispersion generated by North American commuting patterns. The manipulation and generation of data required to produce this data would not have been possible without GIS.</p>
<p>

Using models to project the data held by a GIS forward in time have enabled planners to test policy decisions.  These systems are known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/9072691.xml">
Spatial Decision Support System</link>s.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Semantics and GIS</st>
<p>

Tools and technologies emerging from the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/33149.xml">
 W3C's</link></company>
 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
 Semantic Web Activity</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 are proving useful for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/4780372.xml">
data integration</link> problems in information systems. Correspondingly, such technologies have been proposed as a means to facilitate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/41285.xml">
interoperability</link> and data reuse among GIS applications <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> and also to enable new analysis mechanisms <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>. </p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/49681.xml">
 Ontologies</link> are a key component of this semantic approach as they allow a formal, machine-readable specification of the concepts and relationships in a given domain. This in turn allows a GIS to focus on the meaning of data rather than its syntax or structure. For example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/89755.xml">
reasoning</link> that a land cover type classified as <it>Deciduous Needleleaf Trees</it> in one dataset is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/28592.xml">
specialization</link> of land cover type <it>Forest</it> in another more roughly-classified dataset can help a GIS automatically merge the two datasets under the more general land cover classification. Very deep and comprehensive ontologies have been developed in areas related to GIS applications, for example the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/oswebsite/ontology/">
Hydrology Ontology</weblink> developed by the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<executive_agency wordnetid="108123696" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/19344100.xml">
Ordnance Survey</link></executive_agency>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
 in the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sweet.jpl.nasa.gov/ontology/">
SWEET ontologies</weblink> developed by <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/18426568.xml">
NASA</link></agency>
's <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/16459.xml">
Jet Propulsion Laboratory</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</area>
</landmark>
</point>
</center>
</position>
</region>
</site>
. Also, simpler ontologies and semantic metadata standards are being proposed by the W3C <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/2005/Incubator/geo/">
Geo Incubator Group</weblink> to represent geospatial data on the web. </p>
<p>

Recent research results in this area can be seen in the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geosco.org/">
International Conference on Geospatial Semantics</weblink> and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/oswebsite/partnerships/research/research/terracognita.html">
Terra Cognita -- Directions to the Geospatial Semantic Web</weblink> workshop at the International Semantic Web Conference.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
GIS and Society</st>


<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/12613171.xml">
Neogeography</link></it>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../074/18908074.xml">
Public Participation GIS</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</examination>
</system>
</work>
</it>
</indent>
With the popularization of GIS in decision making, scholars have began to scrutinize the social implications of GIS. It has been argued that the production, distribution, utilization, and representation of geographic information are largely related with the social context. For example, some scholars are concerned that GIS may turn into a tool of omni-surveillance for dictatorship. Other related topics include discussion on copyright, privacy, and censorship. A more optimistic social approach to GIS adoption is to use it as a tool for public participation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="65x28px" src="BlankMap-World.png">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Atlas&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/12433876.xml">
AM/FM/GIS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/7294.xml">
Cartography</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/1386551.xml">
Crime Mapping</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/665259.xml">
Digital raster graphic</link></format>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/14449501.xml">
Distributed GIS</link></format>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/12608.xml">
Geodesy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/1404353.xml">
Geoinformatics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/1913728.xml">
Geographic information science</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1015518.xml">
Geoinformation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/510905.xml">
Geomatics</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/3691948.xml">
Geo (marketing)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/16266129.xml">
GIS applications</link></method>
</know-how>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/7097945.xml">
GIS Day</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/1877442.xml">
List of GIS software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/4855110.xml">
Comparison of GIS software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/5116052.xml">
Open Source Geospatial Foundation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/1043855.xml">
Open GIS Consortium</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../074/18908074.xml">
Public Participation GIS</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</examination>
</system>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/3710051.xml">
Pictometry</link></institution>
</company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/228148.xml">
Remote sensing</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/16870228.xml">
TerraLook</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/14573421.xml">
Traditional knowledge GIS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/2555331.xml">
UNIGIS</link></administration>
</group>
</social_group>
</body>
, international university collaboration on GIS education</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/2265543.xml">
Virtual globe</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/685383.xml">
Topologically Integrated Geographic Encoding and Referencing</link> (TIGER), a US standard for GIS data</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/3059155.xml">
At-location mapping</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/3350640.xml">
GIS in archaeology</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/8979002.xml">
Historical GIS</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/1445706.xml">
Automotive navigation system</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/10971939.xml">
Map database management</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/925715.xml">
Geographic Data Files</link></format>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/51550.xml">
ZIP code</link></characteristic>
</hallmark>
s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/17785064.xml">
Institute of Geoinformatics &amp; Remote Sensing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.giswiki.net/wiki/Education">
Wiki List of Educational Institutions Supporting GIS</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/19395056.xml">
The National States Geographic Information Council</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.culture.fr/culture/arcnat/lascaux/en/">
Lascaux Cave</weblink>".&#32;  French Ministry of Culture.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Curtis, Gregory. The Cave Painters: Probing the Mysteries of the World's First Artists.&#32;NY, USA:&#32;Knopf. ISBN 1-4000-4348-4.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
Dr David Whitehouse.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/871930.stm">
Ice Age star map discovered</weblink>".&#32;  BBC.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-06-09</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.york.ac.uk/depts/maths/histstat/snow_map.htm">
John Snow's Cholera Map</weblink>".&#32;  York University.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-06-09</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Joseph H. Fitzgerald.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.broward.org/library/bienes/lii14009.htm">
Map Printing Methods</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-06-09</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.urisa.org/node/395">
GIS Hall of Fame - Roger Tomlinson</weblink>".&#32;  URISA.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-06-09</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Lucia Lovison-Golob.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gis.dce.harvard.edu/fisher/HTFisher.htm">
Howard T. Fisher</weblink>".&#32;  Harvard University.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-06-09</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Gao, Shan. Paynter, John. &amp; David Sundaram, (2004) "Flexible Support for Spatial Decision-Making" <it>Proc. of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences</it> 5-8 pp. 10]</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite id="CITEREFFonsecaSheth2002" style="font-style:normal">Fonseca, Frederico&#32;&amp;&#32;Sheth, Amit&#32;(2002),&#32;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.personal.psu.edu/faculty/f/u/fuf1/Fonseca-Sheth.pdf">
"The Geospatial Semantic Web"</weblink>&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link>),&#32;<it>UCGIS White Paper</it></cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite id="CITEREFFonsecaEgenhofer1999" style="font-style:normal">Fonseca, Frederico&#32;&amp;&#32;Egenhofer, Max&#32;(1999),&#32;"Ontology-Driven Geographic Information Systems",&#32;<it>Proc. ACM International Symposium on Geographic Information Systems</it>, pp. 14-19</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite id="CITEREFPerryHakimpourSheth2006" style="font-style:normal">Perry, Matthew; Hakimpour, Farshad&#32;&amp;&#32;Sheth, Amit&#32;(2006),&#32;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://knoesis.wright.edu/library/download/ACM-GIS_06_Perry.pdf">
"Analyzing Theme, Space and Time: an Ontology-based Approach"</weblink>&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link>),&#32;<it>Proc. ACM International Symposium on Geographic Information Systems</it>, pp. 147-154</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
</reflist>

IGRS-GIS Institute of Geoinformatics &amp; Remote Sensing</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Berry, J.K. (1993) <it>Beyond Mapping: Concepts, Algorithms and Issues in GIS</it>. Fort Collins, CO: GIS World Books.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bolstad, P. (2005) <it>GIS Fundamentals: A first text on Geographic Information Systems, Second Edition</it>.  White Bear Lake, MN: Eider Press, 543 pp.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Burrough, P.A. and McDonnell, R.A. (1998) <it>Principles of geographical information systems</it>. Oxford University Press, Oxford, 327 pp.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Chang, K. (2007) <it>Introduction to Geographic Information System, 4th Edition</it>. McGraw Hill.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Coulman, Ross (2001 - present) Numerous GIS White Papers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

de Smith M J, Goodchild M F, Longley P A (2007) Geospatial analysis: A comprehensive guide to principles, techniques and software tools", 2nd edition, Troubador, UK available free online at: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com">
http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Elangovan,K (2006)"GIS: Fundamentals, Applications and Implementations", New India Publishing Agency, New Delhi"208 pp.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harvey, Francis(2008) <it>A Primer of GIS, Fundamental geographic and cartographic concepts.</it> The Guilford Press, 31 pp.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Heywood, I., Cornelius, S., and Carver, S. (2006) <it>An Introduction to Geographical Information Systems</it>. Prentice Hall. 3rd edition.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Longley, P.A., <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<geographer wordnetid="110127555" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/1912699.xml">
Goodchild, M.F.</link></educator>
</scholar>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</geographer>
</intellectual>
</person>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
, Maguire, D.J. and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/12161530.xml">
Rhind, D.W.</link></associate>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 (2005) <it>Geographic Information Systems and Science</it>. Chichester: Wiley. 2nd edition.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Maguire, D.J., Goodchild M.F., Rhind D.W. (1997) "Geographic Information Systems: principles, and applications" Longman Scientific and Technical, Harlow.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ott, T. and Swiaczny, F. (2001) <it>Time-integrative GIS. Management and analysis of spatio-temporal data</it>, Berlin / Heidelberg / New York: Springer.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Thurston, J., Poiker, T.K. and J. Patrick Moore. (2003) <it>Integrated Geospatial Technologies: A Guide to GPS, GIS, and Data Logging</it>. Hoboken, New Jersey: Wiley.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tomlinson, R.F., (2005) <it>Thinking About GIS: Geographic Information System Planning for Managers</it>. ESRI Press. 328 pp.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wise, S. (2002) <it>GIS Basics</it>. London: Taylor &amp; Francis.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Worboys, Michael, and Matt Duckham. (2004) <it>GIS: a computing perspective</it>. Boca Raton: CRC Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wheatley, David and Gillings, Mark (2002) <it>Spatial Technology and Archaeology. The Archaeological Application of GIS</it>. London, New York, Taylor &amp; Francis.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fgdc.gov/">
Federal Geographic Data Committee</weblink> — United States federal government standards agency.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ccdmd.qc.ca/en/gis/">
Geographic Information System (GIS) Educational website</weblink> — Educational site with PDF lessons and videos to accompany free GIS software.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gislounge.com">
GIS Lounge</weblink> - Information site for GIS.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gita.org">
GITA</weblink> - Geospatial Information &amp; Technology Association.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.giswiki.net/">
GISWiki.NEWS.Reader</weblink> - Searchable feed aggregator for a large collection of GIS news, mostly in English.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nsgic.org/">
National States Geographic Information Council (NSGIC)</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/">
Open Geospatial Consortium, Inc.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://planetgs.com/">
Planet Geospatial</weblink> - feed aggregator for GIS related blogs.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://erg.usgs.gov/isb/pubs/gis_poster/">
USGS GIS Poster</weblink> — Frequently cited "What is GIS" poster.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible collapsed " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/18963910.xml">
Geography</link>topics</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/18963910.xml">
Geography</link>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/1727031.xml">
History of geography</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Branches</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;background:#f7f7f7;;background:transparent;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;background:transparent;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/13372.xml">
Human</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/1923817.xml">
Behavioral</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/2678329.xml">
Cultural</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/45642.xml">
Demography</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/2149045.xml">
Development</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/177512.xml">
Economic</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/850705.xml">
Feminist</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/2596739.xml">
Health</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/1923965.xml">
Historical</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/1845092.xml">
Political</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/711230.xml">
Regional</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/341029.xml">
Urban</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;background:transparent;;background:#f7f7f7;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/23263.xml">
Physical</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/99358.xml">
Biogeography</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/142440.xml">
Climatology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/2160676.xml">
Coastal</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/71627.xml">
Environmental</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/12608.xml">
Geodesy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/78534.xml">
Geomorphology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/231504.xml">
Glaciology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/13435.xml">
Hydrology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/252582.xml">
Landscape ecology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/145243.xml">
Limnology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/44044.xml">
Oceanography</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/349868.xml">
Palaeogeography</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/59408.xml">
Pedology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/12591925.xml">
Quaternary science</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Techniques</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;background:transparent;;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/7294.xml">
Cartography</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
Geographic Information Systems (GIS)</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/51531.xml">
Geostatistics</link>&nbsp;·  <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
Global Positioning System (GPS)</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
&nbsp;·  <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/228148.xml">
Remote sensing</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/3190431.xml">
Spatial data analysis</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/371299.xml">
Qualitative methods</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Societies</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;background:#f7f7f7;;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/1817321.xml">
American Geographical Society</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
&nbsp;·  <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/4792371.xml">
Association of American Geographers</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
&nbsp;·  <alliance wordnetid="108293982" confidence="0.8">
<world_organization wordnetid="108294696" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/19156768.xml">
European Geography Association</link></world_organization>
</alliance>
&nbsp;·  <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/1224402.xml">
Geographical Association</link></administration>
</group>
</social_group>
</body>
&nbsp;·  <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../046/1371046.xml">
Hong Kong Geographical Association</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
&nbsp;·  <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/2929619.xml">
International Geographical Union</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
&nbsp;·  <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/21550.xml">
National Geographic Society</link></institution>
</group>
</company>
</society>
</social_group>
&nbsp;·  <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/1854772.xml">
Royal Canadian Geographical Society</link></administration>
</group>
</society>
</social_group>
</body>
&nbsp;·  <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/395918.xml">
Royal Geographical Society</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
&nbsp;·  <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<financial_institution wordnetid="108054721" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="108406486" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<charity wordnetid="108406619" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/3984364.xml">
Royal Scottish Geographical Society</link></institution>
</administration>
</charity>
</group>
</foundation>
</financial_institution>
</society>
</social_group>
</body>
&nbsp;·  <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/4627684.xml">
Russian Geographical Society</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
&nbsp;·  <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/11604083.xml">
Saudi Geographical Society</link></administration>
</group>
</society>
</social_group>
</body>
&nbsp;·  <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/2891761.xml">
Society of Woman Geographers</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
&nbsp;·  <link>
Société de Géographie</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Lists</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;background:transparent;;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/12770.xml">
Basic topics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../124/223124.xml">
Geographers</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/699798.xml">
Geography of countries</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</system>
</article>
