<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:25:52[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<software  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106566077">
<header>
<title>SASS-C</title>
<id>12416046</id>
<revision>
<id>242502675</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T14:35:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from September 2008</category>
<category>ATC Software</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Software</name>
<parameters>
<genre>
Air Traffic Management Surveillance sensor performance assessment and trajectory reconstruction (tracker)</genre>
<logo>
<image width="150px" src="SASS-C_logo.jpg">
</image>
</logo>
<screenshot>
<image width="300px" src="ScreenCaptureTR1559.JPG">
</image>
</screenshot>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eurocontrol.int/sass">
http://www.eurocontrol.int/sass</weblink></website>
<latest_release_version>
6.5</latest_release_version>
<developer>
Eurocontrol</developer>
<name>
SASS-C</name>
<latest_release_date>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/19635.xml">
March 15</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link></latest_release_date>
<caption>
SASS-C running Plot Accuracy Analysis.</caption>
<license>
Eurocontrol Licence</license>
<operating_system>
<O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
</operating_system>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=SASS-C&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22SASS-C%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



<p>

Source: Eurocontrol Web site</p>
<p>

SASS-C is an acronym for "Surveillance Analysis Support System for ATC-Centre". It is an ATC-centre based Surveillance Analysis workbench for ATC Radar Plot Analysis and Tracker Performance Measurements. If you are new with the tool, go to the overview page to find out more about it.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Introduction </st>
<p>

SASS-C (Surveillance Analysis Support System for ATC Centre) is a software toolbox developed by EUROCONTROL to provide standardised methods and tools for assessing the performance of Surveillance infrastructures.</p>
<p>

Now widely distributed to civil and military Air Navigation Service Providers, R&amp;D organisations and industrial partners in most of the states of the European Civil Aviation Conference (ECAC), SASS-C is typically used for:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Monitoring the compliance of operational radar and trackers to nominal performance, and in particular those defined in the EUROCONTROL Surveillance Standard for En-Route and Major TMA.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Supporting the periodical (daily/weekly/monthly) monitoring of the ATC Centre surveillance systems efficiency.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Supporting air incident investigation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Supporting the development of radar and tracking systems.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The development of SASS-C is co-ordinated by EUROCONTROL under the guidance and assistance of the European National Administrations, outsourcing most of the life cycle activities to Industry and Research Institutes. This collaborative environment and the general independence from major ATC system suppliers brought required qualities for SASS-C to become rapidly a de-facto standard within ECAC states for the analysis of classical Radars.</p>
<p>

At present, SASS-C is designed to handle surveillance data from Radar sensors (PSR, SSR, Mode S elementary surveillance) in both a Mono- and Multiradar environment, and Trackers. In the future, extensions for handling ADS-B and multilateration data in addition to Radar data are foreseen.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 System Concept </st>
<p>
 
The assessment of the input surveillance data is done by comparing it against a reference. The core concept of SASS-C is that such a reference is built from data provided by the surveillance infrastructure itself i.e. from the infrastructure to be analysed. The advantage of the method is that the evaluation can be done from opportunity traffic, which is a cheap way to perform evaluations (cheaper than e.g. running GPS test flights).</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 SASS-C Architecture </st>
<p>
 
SASS-C is organised into a number of complementary Modules:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 On top, the System Control Module controls data acquisition and execution of the evaluation sessions,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 At the heart, the Input Reconstruction Module creates the reference trajectories from recorded input data,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Then, the Evaluation Module offers the user means to perform the required performance measurements.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Simulator can be used to generate realistic plot data by sampling realistic simulated aircraft trajectories.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Radar Coverage Module is used to draw MultiRadar coverage maps at various flight levels.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</software>
</article>
