<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:20:06[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Exaptation</title>
<id>1242211</id>
<revision>
<id>241593217</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-28T19:23:07Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Muro Bot</username>
<id>5849026</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Evolutionary biology</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since August 2007</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Mergefrom.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that  be  into this article or section. ()</col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Exaptation</b>, <b>cooption</b>, and <b>preadaptation</b> are related terms referring to shifts in the function of a trait during <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/9236.xml">
evolution</link>.  For example, a trait can evolve because it served one particular function, but subsequently it may come to serve another.  Exaptations are common in both anatomy and behavior. Bird feathers are a classic example: initially these evolved for temperature regulation, but later were adapted for flight.  Interest in exaptation relates to both the process and product of evolution: the process that creates complex traits and the product that may be imperfectly designed.
<sec>
<st>
History and definitions</st>
<p>

The idea that the function of a trait might shift during its evolutionary history originated with <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/8145410.xml">
Charles Darwin</link></scientist>
</person>
 (1859, ch. 6).  For many years the phenomenon was labeled “preadaptation.”  Unfortunately, the term suggests forethought, which is contrary to a basic principle of natural selection.</p>
<p>

The idea had been explored by several scholars<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> when in 1982 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/27875.xml">
Gould</link></scientist>
</person>
 and Vrba introduced the term “exaptation”.  Unfortunately for subsequent discussions, this definition had two categories with different implications for the role of adaptation.  
(1) A character, previously shaped by natural selection for a particular function (an adaptation), is coopted for a new use—cooptation.
(2) A character whose origin cannot be ascribed to the direct action of natural selection (a nonaptation), is coopted for a current use—cooptation.  Gould and Vrba (1982, Table 1)
The definitions are silent as to whether exaptations had been shaped by natural selection after cooption, although Gould and Vrba cite examples (e.g., feathers) of traits shaped after cooption.</p>
<p>

To avoid these ambiguities, Buss, et al. (1998) suggested the term “co-opted adaptation,” which is limited to traits that evolved after cooption.  However, the commonly-used terms of ”exaptation” and “cooption” are ambiguous in this regard.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Examples</st>
<p>

Of the many examples of exaptations, here are two involving familiar traits.  A multi-stage example involves human hands, which evolved to facilitate tool use and which are an exaptation of primate hands that were used for grasping tree branches.  Those primate hands, in turn, were an exaptation of front legs that were used for locomotion on the ground, and those legs were an exaptation of the fins of fish, which were used for locomotion in the water.  As this lineage exploited different niches—water, land, trees, and tool-use on the ground—natural selection reshaped its limbs.</p>
<p>

A behavioral example pertains to subdominant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/33702.xml">
wolves</link> licking the mouths of alpha wolves as a sign of submissiveness.  (Similarly, dogs, which are domesticated wolves, lick the faces of their human owners.)  This trait can be explained as an exaptation of wolf pups licking the faces of adults to encourage them to regurgitate food.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Implications</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Evolution of complex traits</st>
<p>

One of the challenges to Darwin’s theory of evolution was explaining how complex structures could evolve gradually,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> given that their incipient forms may have been inadequate to serve any function.  As <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/251057.xml">
Mivart</link> (a critic of Darwin) pointed out, 5 percent of a bird wing would not be functional.  The incipient form of complex traits would not have survived long enough to evolve to a useful form.</p>
<p>

As Darwin elaborated on in the last edition of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/29932.xml">
The Origin of Species</link></it>, many complex traits evolved from earlier traits that had served different functions.   By trapping air, primitive wings would have enabled birds to efficiently regulate their temperature, in part, by lifting up their feathers when too warm. Individual animals with more of this functionality would have left more offspring, resulting in the spread of this trait. </p>
<p>

Eventually, feathers became sufficiently large that they enabled some individuals to glide.  These individuals would leave more offspring, resulting in the spread of this trait because it served a second function, that of locomotion.  Hence, the evolution of bird wings can be explained by a shifting in function from the regulation of temperature to flight.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Jury-rigged design</st>
<p>

Darwin explained how the traits of living organisms are well-designed for their environment, but he also recognized that many traits are imperfectly designed.  They appear to have been made from available material, that is, jury-rigged.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  Understanding exaptations may suggest hypotheses regarding subtleties in the adaptation.  For instance, that feathers evolved initially for thermal regulation may help to explain some of their features unrelated to flight (Buss et al., 1998).</p>
<p>

Some of the chemical pathways for physical pain and pain from social exclusion overlap (MacDonald and Leary, 2005).  The physical pain system may have been co-opted to motivate social animals to respond to threats to their inclusion in the group.  The physical-social pain overlap helps to explain the paradox that people who are threatened with social exclusion sometimes react with physical violence.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
See Jacob (1977) and Mayr (1982) for references.</entry>
<entry id="2">
http://www.wolf.org/wolves/learn/basic/biology/communication.asp, accessed May 16, 2008.</entry>
<entry id="3">
The development of complex structures (i.e., evolution of novelties) occur either by intensification of an existing function or by a switch in functions.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Jacob (1977) sees much of evolution as “tinkering,” that is, working with available traits.  “Tinkering” includes (but is not limited to) shifts in function.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Buss, David M., Martie G. Haselton, Todd K. Shackelford, et al. (1998) “Adaptations, Exaptations, and Spandrels,” <it><periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/3433814.xml">
American Psychologist</link></periodical>
</it>, 53 (May):533&ndash;548. http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/comm/haselton/webdocs/spandrels.html</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Darwin, Charles (1859) <it>The Origin of Species</it>, London, ch. 6, section “Modes of Transition.” http://www.infidels.org/library/historical/charles_darwin/origin_of_species/Chapter6.html.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ehrlich, Paul, and Marcus Feldman (2003) “Genes and Culture: What Creates Our Behavioral Phenome?,” <it>Current Anthropology</it>, 44 (February):87&ndash;107.  Included are comments and a reply.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gould, Stephen Jay, and Elizabeth S. Vrba (1982), "Exaptation &mdash; a missing term in the science of form," <it>Paleobiology</it> 8 (1): 4&ndash;15.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gould, Stephen Jay (1991) “Exaptation: A Crucial tool for Evolutionary Psychology,” <it>Journal of Social Issues</it> 47: 43&ndash;65.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Jacob, Francois (1977) “Evolution and Tinkering,” <it>Science</it> 196 (June 10): 1161&ndash;1166. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 MacDonald, Geoff, and Mark R. Leary (2005) “Why Does Social Exclusion Hurt? The Relationship between Social and Physical Pain,” <it>Psychological Bulletin</it> 131 (2): 202&ndash;223.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mayr, Ernst (1982) <it>The Growth of Biological Thought: Diversity, Evolution, and Inheritance, </it> Harvard University Press, ISBN 0-674-36445-7.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/178870.xml">
Atavism</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/308981.xml">
Vestigiality</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/7335684.xml">
Spandrel (biology)</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://wiki.cotch.net/index.php/Citations_of_cooption, which points to additional webpages.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Major subfields of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biology</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/674.xml">
Anatomy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/2787.xml">
Astrobiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/3954.xml">
Biochemistry</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/3878.xml">
Biostatistics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/4183.xml">
Botany</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/6339.xml">
Cell biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/56566.xml">
Chronobiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/8449.xml">
Developmental biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/9630.xml">
Ecology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/66997.xml">
Epidemiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/418101.xml">
Evolutionary biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/12266.xml">
Genetics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/55170.xml">
Genomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/411951.xml">
Human biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/14959.xml">
Immunology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/20021.xml">
Marine biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/19909.xml">
Microbiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/19200.xml">
Molecular biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/21245.xml">
Neuroscience</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
Nutrition</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/19179706.xml">
Origin of life</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/23084.xml">
Paleontology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/383854.xml">
Parasitology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/48791.xml">
Pathology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/23597.xml">
Physiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/467899.xml">
Systems biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/3036154.xml">
Taxonomy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/34413.xml">
Zoology</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
