<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:20:32[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Pharmacovigilance</title>
<id>1243554</id>
<revision>
<id>244531425</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T07:57:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DiverseMentality</username>
<id>4842600</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Pharmacology</category>
<category>Pharmacy</category>
<category>Healthcare quality</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Pharmacovigilance</b> (PV) is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/24354.xml">
pharmacological</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/26700.xml">
science</link> relating to the detection, assessment, understanding and prevention of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/1474961.xml">
adverse effects</link>, particularly long term and short term side effects of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medicine</link>s<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. Generally speaking, pharmacovigilance is the science of collecting, monitoring, researching, assessing and evaluating information from healthcare providers and patients on the adverse effects of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/180121.xml">
medication</link>s, <link>
biological product</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/439973.xml">
herbalism</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/457857.xml">
traditional medicine</link>s with a view to: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 identifying new information about hazards associated with medicines</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 preventing harm to patients.</entry>
</list>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/888207.xml">
etymological</link> roots are: <it>pharmakon</it> (Greek), “drug;” and <it>vigilare</it> (Latin), “to keep awake or alert, to keep watch.”</p>
<p>

Pharmacovigilance is particularly concerned with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/1274833.xml">
adverse drug reaction</link>s, or ADRs, which are officially described as: "A response to a drug which is noxious and unintended, and which occurs at doses normally used… for the prophylaxis, diagnosis or therapy of disease, or for the modification of physiological function."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Pharmacovigilance is gaining importance for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/23315.xml">
doctor</link>s and scientists as the number of stories in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/19641.xml">
mass media</link> of drug recalls increases. </p>
<p>

Because clinical trials involve several thousand patients at most; less common side effects and ADRs are often unknown at the time a drug enters the market.  Even very severe ADRs, such as liver damage, are often undetected because study populations are small. Postmarketing pharmacovigilance uses tools such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/42253.xml">
data mining</link> and investigation of case reports to identify the relationships between drugs and ADRs.</p>



<sec>
<st>
Risk in medicine</st>
<p>

Medicines have helped to bring improved health and longer life to human beings. Medicines affect the lives of hundreds of millions of people every day. But they are not without risk, and have caused, do cause and will continue to cause harm to many people. There are also large numbers of people who experience no evident effect at all from the drugs they take. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Risks of medical treatment</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

While medicines have led to major improvement in the treatment and control of diseases, they also produce adverse effects on the human body from time to time</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

While many drugs are precisely targeted to the causes and mechanisms of disease, they may also have minor or distressing effects on other parts of the body, or interact negatively with the systems of the particular individual or with other drugs or substances they are taking, or, not work well or at all for some, many or all of those who take them</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is no such thing as a safe drug. There are risks in any intrusion into the human body, whether chemical or surgical. Nothing in this field is entirely predictable - except that the interaction between science and the human body may produce surprises.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Terms commonly used in drug safety</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/1726470.xml">
Benefit</link>s</it> are commonly expressed as the proven therapeutic good of a product, but should also include the patient’s subjective assessment of its effects</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/25617.xml">
Risk</link></it> is the probability of harm being caused, usually expressed as a percent or ratio of the treated population; the probability of an occurrence</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/574234.xml">
Harm</link></it> is the nature and extent of the actual damage that could be caused. It should not be confused with risk</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/1982403.xml">
Effectiveness</link></it> is used to express the extent to which a drug works under real world circumstances, i.e., clinical practice (not clinical trials).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/896469.xml">
Efficacy</link></it> is used to express the extent to which a drug works under ideal circumstances (i.e., in clinical trials)</entry>
</list>
</p>



</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Finding the risks of drugs</st>

<p>

Pharmaceutical companies are required by law in all countries to perform <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/241717.xml">
clinical trials</link>, testing new drugs on people before they are made generally available. The manufacturers or their agents usually select a representative sample of patients for whom the drug is designed — at most a few thousand — along with a comparable control group. The control group may receive a placebo and/or another drug that is already marketed for the disease.</p>
<p>

The purpose of clinical trials is to discover:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 if a drug works and how well</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 if it has any harmful effects, and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 its benefit-harm-risk profile - does it do more good than harm, and how much more? If it has a potential for harm, how probable and how serious is the harm?</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Clinical trials do, in general, tell us a good deal about how well a drug works and what potential harm it may cause. They provide information which should be reliable for larger populations with the same characteristics as the trial group - age, gender, state of health, ethnic origin, and so on.</p>
<p>

The variables in a clinical trial are specified and controlled and the results relate only to the population of which the trial group is a representative sample. A clinical trial can never tell you the whole story of the effects of a drug in all situations. In fact, there is nothing that could tell you the whole story, but a clinical trial must tell you enough; "enough" being determined by legislation and by contemporary judgements about the acceptable balance of benefit and harm.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Spontaneous reporting</st>
<p>

Spontaneous reporting is the core data-generating system of international pharmacovigilance, relying on healthcare professionals (and in some places consumers) to identify and report any suspected <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/1274833.xml">
adverse drug reaction</link> to their national pharmacovigilance centre or to the manufacturer. Spontaneous reports are almost always submitted voluntarily.</p>
<p>

One of this system’s major weaknesses is under-reporting, though the figures vary greatly between countries and in relation to minor and serious ADRs.</p>
<p>

Another problem is that overworked medical personnel do not always see reporting as a priority. If the symptoms are not serious, they may not notice them at all. And even if the symptoms are serious, they may not be recognised as the effect of a particular drug. </p>
<p>

Even so, spontaneous reports are a crucial element in the worldwide enterprise of pharmacovigilance and form the core of the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/33583.xml">
World Health Organization</link></organization>
 Database, which includes around 3.7 million reports (September 2006), growing annually by about 250,000. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Other reporting methods </st>
<p>

Some countries legally oblige spontaneous reporting by physicians. In most countries, manufacturers are required to submit reports they receive from healthcare providers to the national authority. Others have intensive, focused programmes concentrating on new drugs, or on controversial drugs, or on the prescribing habits of groups of doctors, or involving pharmacists in reporting. All of these generate potentially useful information. Such intensive schemes, however, tend to be the exception.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 International collaboration </st>
<p>

The principle of international collaboration in the field of pharmacovigilance is the principal basis for the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who-umc.org/DynPage.aspx?id=13140&amp;mn=1514">
WHO International Drug Monitoring Programme</weblink>, through which over 80 member nations have systems in place which encourage healthcare personnel to record and report adverse effects of drugs in their patients. These reports are assessed locally and may lead to action within the country. Through membership of the WHO Programme one country can know if similar reports are being made elsewhere. (The <economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
European Union</link></economy>
 also has its own scheme.)</p>
<p>

Member countries send their reports to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/6750473.xml">
Uppsala Monitoring Centre</link> where they are processed, evaluated and entered into the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who-umc.org/graphics/4789.pdf">
 WHO International Database</weblink>. When there are several reports of adverse reactions to a particular drug this process may lead to the detection of a signal — an alert about a possible hazard communicated to members countries. This happens only after detailed evaluation and expert review.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Pharmacovigilance in Europe</st>

<p>

The pharmacovigilance effort in Europe is coordinated by the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/1427054.xml">
European Medicines Agency</link></agency>
 (EMEA) and conducted by the national competent medicines authorities (NCA). The main responsibility of the EMEA is to maintain and develop the pharmacovigilance database consisting of all suspected serious adverse reactions to medicines observed in the <alliance wordnetid="108293982" confidence="0.8">
<bloc wordnetid="108171094" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/9576.xml">
European Community</link></bloc>
</alliance>
. The system is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/7437427.xml">
EudraVigilance</link> and contains separate but similar databases of human and veterinary reactions.</p>
<p>

Europe requires the individual marketing authorisation holders (drug companies), to submit all received adverse reactions in electronic form (save in exceptional circumstances). The reporting obligations of the various stakeholders are defined in the Community legislation, in particular:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/153149.xml">
Regulation</link> (EC) No 726/2004</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 for human medicines, <economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
European Union</link></economy>
 <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<pronouncement wordnetid="106727616" confidence="0.8">
<declaration wordnetid="106725877" confidence="0.8">
<directive wordnetid="107170080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/7458065.xml">
Directive 2001/83/EC</link></directive>
</declaration>
</pronouncement>
</message>
</statement>
 as amended and <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<pronouncement wordnetid="106727616" confidence="0.8">
<declaration wordnetid="106725877" confidence="0.8">
<directive wordnetid="107170080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/7467736.xml">
Directive 2001/20/EC</link></directive>
</declaration>
</pronouncement>
</message>
</statement>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 for veterinary medicines, Directive 2001/82/EC as amended.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Reporting can be done with commercial software developed for the purpose or with a web utility called EVWEB accessible through the EudraVigilance homepage. Registration for use of EVWEB is necessary.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Pharmacovigilance in the United States </st>

<p>

<table style="width:210px; float: right; clear: right; text-align:center; margin-top:1em; " class="infobox">
<row style="font-size:90%; background:#DCF0FF">
<col>
 <b><link>
U.S. drug regulation</link></b></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<image width="160px" src="Ritalin-SR-20mg-1000x1000.jpg">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row style="font-size: 90%; line-height: 150%;">
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/359238.xml">
Prescription drugs</link>  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/192042.xml">
Over-the-counter drugs</link><table width="100%" class="collapsible collapsed">
<header style=" text-align: left; background: #DCF0FF; font-size: 90%;">
Law</header>
<row style="font-size: 90%; line-height: 150%;">
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/1271173.xml">
Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/2912632.xml">
Comprehensive Drug Abuse Prevention and Control Act of 1970</link>  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/7727.xml">
Controlled Substances Act</link><legislation wordnetid="106535222" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/6159258.xml">
Prescription Drug Marketing Act</link></legislation>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/3663417.xml">
Drug Price Competition and Patent Term Restoration Act</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/2056907.xml">
Hatch-Waxman exemption</link></col>
</row>
</table>
<table width="100%" class="collapsible collapsed">
<header style=" text-align: left; background: #DCF0FF; font-size: 90%;">
Government agencies</header>
<row style="font-size: 90%; line-height: 150%;">
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/58250.xml">
United States Department of Health and Human Services</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/11632.xml">
Food and Drug Administration</link><law_enforcement_agency wordnetid="108348815" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/146720.xml">
Drug Enforcement Administration</link></law_enforcement_agency>
 <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/46174.xml">
National Institutes of Health</link></association>
</institute>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/8338259.xml">
Center for Drug Evaluation and Research</link></col>
</row>
</table>
<table width="100%" class="collapsible collapsed">
<header style=" text-align: left; background: #DCF0FF; font-size: 90%;">
Process</header>
<row style="font-size: 90%; line-height: 150%;">
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/3218783.xml">
Drug development</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/1340774.xml">
New drug application</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/1487123.xml">
Investigational new drug</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/241717.xml">
Clinical trial</link> (Phase I, II, III, IV)<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/163180.xml">
Randomized controlled trial</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/1243554.xml">
Pharmacovigilance</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/6109226.xml">
Abbreviated New Drug Application</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/12326459.xml">
Fast track approval</link></col>
</row>
</table>
<table width="100%" class="collapsible collapsed">
<header style=" text-align: left; background: #DCF0FF; font-size: 90%;">
International coordination</header>
<row style="font-size: 90%; line-height: 150%;">
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/1616138.xml">
International Conference on Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Registration of Pharmaceuticals for Human Use</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/6750473.xml">
Uppsala Monitoring Centre</link><organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/33583.xml">
World Health Organization</link></organization>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/2939687.xml">
Council for International Organizations of Medical Sciences</link><statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<legal_document wordnetid="106479665" confidence="0.8">
<treaty wordnetid="106773434" confidence="0.8">
<agreement wordnetid="106770275" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<written_agreement wordnetid="106771653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/1476908.xml">
Single Convention on Narcotic Drugs</link></written_agreement>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</agreement>
</treaty>
</legal_document>
</document>
</message>
</statement>
</col>
</row>
</table>
<table width="100%" class="collapsible collapsed">
<header style=" text-align: left; background: #DCF0FF; font-size: 90%;">
Non-governmental organizations</header>
<row style="font-size: 90%; line-height: 150%;">
<col>
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<academy wordnetid="108279298" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/431259.xml">
Institute of Medicine</link></academy>
</institution>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/12667794.xml">
Research on Adverse Drug events And Reports</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
<row style=" text-align: center; font-size: 90%;">

</row>
</table>

Three primary branches of pharmacovigilance in the U.S. include the FDA, the pharmaceutical manufacturers, and the academic/non-profit organizations (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/12667794.xml">
RADAR</link> and <group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/195977.xml">
Public Citizen</link></group>
).  </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Risk management</st>

<p>

In 2002 Heads of Medicines Agencies<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://heads.medagencies.org/">
http://heads.medagencies.org/</weblink> agreed on a mandate for an ad hoc Working Group on establishing a European risk management strategy. The Working Group considered the conduct of a high level survey of EU pharmacovigilance resources to promote the utilisation of expertise and encourage collaborative working.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Source: The Importance of Pharmacovigilance, WHO 2002</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who-umc.org/graphics/9277.pdf">
WHO Technical Report No 498 (1972)</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/1274833.xml">
Adverse drug reaction</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<treatment wordnetid="100658082" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<care wordnetid="100654885" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/1474961.xml">
Adverse effect (medicine)</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</care>
</event>
</treatment>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/4489970.xml">
American Society of Consultant Pharmacists</link></association>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/5594699.xml">
American Society of Medication Safety Officers</link></university>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/6751229.xml">
Boston Collaborative Drug Surveillance Program</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/3135786.xml">
Consultant pharmacist</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/7580709.xml">
COSTART</link> - Coding Symbols for a Thesaurus of Adverse Reaction Terms</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/7437427.xml">
EudraVigilance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/15232178.xml">
International Society for Pharmacoepidemiology</link></institution>
</company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/1200971.xml">
MedDRA</link> - Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<financial_institution wordnetid="108054721" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="108406486" confidence="0.8">
<charity wordnetid="108406619" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/3030020.xml">
National Drug &amp; Safety League</link></institution>
</charity>
</foundation>
</financial_institution>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/463734.xml">
Public health</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/17986913.xml">
Pharmacoepidemiology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/180121.xml">
Pharmacotherapy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/6751304.xml">
The International Society of Pharmacovigilance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

[Therapeutic risk management]]</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/6750473.xml">
Uppsala Monitoring Centre</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Unicus Regulatory Services</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/7580648.xml">
WHOART</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/6883215.xml">
Yellow Card Scheme</link> (UK)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/18029417.xml">
DrugLogic</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
MetricStream</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mhra.gov.uk/home/idcplg?IdcService=SS_GET_PAGE&amp;nodeId=368">
Current Problems in Pharmacovigilance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/Cder/guidance/6359OCC.htm">
United States FDA Guidance on Good Pharmacovigilance Practices</weblink></entry>
</list>



</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
