<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:27:52[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Free Spirits Rowing</title>
<id>12460021</id>
<revision>
<id>211316398</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-09T19:18:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Hbprinter</username>
<id>7917875</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Rowing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Free Spirits</b> is a club for users of the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/1175584.xml">
Concept2</link></institution>
</company>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/15077.xml">
indoor rower</link>.  The club has members from all over the world.  The aim of the club is to promote indoor rowing in order to improve peoples' health and fitness, as described on their web site:  "Free (as in liberated and gratis) Spirits is a fairly random grouping of people of all ages who train using the concept 2 rowing machine.  Being part of the team is motivational.  Noone tells you what to do, but there is a wide variety of activities to choose from if you are so inclined.  The aim of Free Spirits is to have fun, no more than that.  You are free to join and free to leave.  All we ask of members is that they respect the other members whether they row 100 seconds a month or 100+ hours."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>

<sec>
<st>
 Background </st>
<p>

Free Spirits was born from a disagreement with the W.I.S.E. (Welsh, Irish, Scottish, English) indoor rowing team.  Initially there were very few members.  The web site was set up in July 2006 and from this grew the "meter board" <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, a web site that tracks an individual's distance rowed each day.  Free Spirits quickly became the largest indoor rowing club registered with the Concept 2 ranking, and ended the 2006-2007 season with more than 300 members, having rowed the equivalent distance of the Earth to the Moon <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.freespiritsrowing.com/">
freespiritsrowing.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.meterboard.com/">
Free Spirits Rowing - Track your progress thanks to Jonathan Lemon</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.concept2.com/sranking03/challenge/univStandings2007.asp">
University Standings 2007 Page</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
