<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:18:23[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104377057">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<header>
<title>Dataverse</title>
<id>12468027</id>
<revision>
<id>155331969</id>
<timestamp>2007-09-03T02:42:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>RichardVeryard</username>
<id>1516303</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Network file systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Dataverse</b> is a virtual archive where you can list your data sets and create collections of data. Archiving with the dataverse extends the useful life of data, preserving it in perpetuity against the failure of computers systems and the obsolescence of data formats. And, the dataverse makes it easy for students and other researchers to find, use, and cite your data, and provides dedicated archival services.
<sec>
<st>
 The Dataverse Network Project </st>
<p>

The Dataverse Network Project includes integrated developments in web application software, networking, data citation standards, and statistical methods designed to put some of the universe of data and data sharing practices on firmer ground. It facilitates the public preservation and distribution of persistent, authorized, and verifiable research data, with powerful but easy-to-use technology, whether or not the data are in the public domain. The project increases scholarly recognition (including formal scholarly citations to articles and to data sets) and distributed control for authors, journals, and others who make data available, facilitates data access and analysis by the scholarly community, and still enables professional archives to seamlessly provide extensive preservation and other services.   The project site can be found at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://TheData.org[http://TheData.org]">
http://TheData.org<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://TheData.org">
http://TheData.org</weblink></weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The Dataverse Network </st>
<p>

The Dataverse Network is a new project housed at the Institute for Quantitative Social Science (IQSS), with its software written from scratch beginning in 2006.  The team benefited considerably from their experiences with their earlier Virtual Data Center (VDC) project, which spanned 1999-2006 and was organized by Micah Altman, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_King_%28political_scientist%29[Gary">
King</weblink>], and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/8183424.xml">
Sidney Verba</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 as a collaboration between the Harvard-MIT Data Center (now part of IQSS) and the <library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/1828266.xml">
Harvard University Library</link></library>
. Precursors to the VDC date to 1987, and ranged from a stand-alone software guide to local data up to and including pre-web software to ftp cataloging information automatically to other sites across campus at designated times. 
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</article>
