<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:28:42[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<information  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106634376">
<electronic_database  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106588511">
<lexical_database  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106638868">
<wordnet  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106639428">
<database  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106637824">
<header>
<title>Symobi</title>
<id>12479744</id>
<revision>
<id>217799758</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-07T19:03:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ghettoblaster</username>
<id>6603820</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from December 2007</category>
<category>Operating systems</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Symobi&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Symobi%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<b>Symobi</b> (System for mobile applications) is a modern and mobile <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/26123.xml">
real-time operating system</link>. It was and is developed by the German company Miray Software, since 2002 partly in cooperation with the research team of  Prof. Dr. Uwe Baumgarten at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/349679.xml">
Technical University of Munich</link></university>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The graphical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> is designed for the area of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/46630.xml">
embedded</link> and mobile systems. It is also often used on PCs for end users and in the field of industry. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Design</st>

<p>

The basis of Symobi is the message-oriented operating system µnOS, which is on its part based on the real-time <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/20023.xml">
microkernel</link>  Sphere. µnOS offers communication through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/1324867.xml">
message passing</link> between all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/4746766.xml">
processes</link> (from basic operating system service processes to application processes) using the integrated process manager. On the lowest level, the responsibility of the Sphere microkernel is to implement and enforce security mechanisms and resource management in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/25767.xml">
real-time</link>. Symobi itself additionally offers a complete graphical operating system environment with system services, a consistent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
graphical user interface</link>, as well as standard programs and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/197404.xml">
drivers</link>. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Classification</st>

<p>

Symobi combines features from different fields of application in one operating system. As a modern operating system it offers separated, isolated processes, light-weight <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/31629.xml">
threads</link>, and dynamic libraries, like Windows, Linux, and Unix for example. In the area of mobile embedded operating systems, through its low resource requirement and the support of mobile devices it resembles systems like Windows CE, SymbianOS or Palm OS. With conventional real-time operating systems like QNX or VxWorks it shares the real-time ability and the support of different processor architectures.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<p>

The development of Sphere, µnOS and Symobi is based on the ideas and work of Konrad Foikis and Michael Haunreiter (founders of the company Miray Software), initiated during their schooldays, even before they started studying computer science. The basic concept was to combine useful and necessary features (like real-time and portability) with modern characteristics (like microkernel and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/152106.xml">
inter-process communication</link> etc.) to form a stable and reliable operating system. Originally, it was only supposed to serve as a basis for the different application programs developed by Foikis and Haunreiter during their studies. In 2000, Konrad Foikis and Michael Haunreiter founded the company Miray Software when they realised that µnOS was suited for far more than their own use. The cooperation with the TU Munich already evolved two years later. In 2006, the first official version of Symobi was completed, and in autumn of the same year it was introduced in professional circles on the Systems exhibition.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Support</st>

<p>

<b><it>Single-Core</it></b>:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Intel: 80386, 80486, Pentium, Pentium Pro, Pentium II, Pentium III, Pentium 4, Core Solo, Core 2 Solo</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

AMD: Élan SC410, Élan SC520, K6, K6-2, K6-III, Duron, Sempron, Athlon, Opteron</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

VIA: Cyrix Mark II, Cyrix III, C3, C7, Eden</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Rise: mP6</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Marvell / Intel: PXA-250, PXA-255, PXA-270, IXP-420</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Motorola / Freescale: G2, G3, G4</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b><it>Multi-Core</it></b>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Intel: Pentium 4, Core Duo, Core 2 Duo</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

AMD: Athlon X2, Opteron</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Application areas</st>

<p>

Symobi is suited for hand-held products (portable communicators, internet appliances), as well as for consumer applicances (set-top boxes, home gateways, games, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/6447.xml">
consoles</link>). Furthermore it is used in the areas of automotive (control and infotainment systems), industrial control systems (motion control, process control), and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/220633.xml">
point of sale</link>
(cashier systems, ticket machines, information terminals).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Advantages and disadvantages</st>

<p>

The operating system stands out through its real-time microkernel and its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/64020.xml">
multi-processor</link> ability. Furthermore, it is portable and therefore not bound to specific hardware platforms. Symobi's inter-process communication guarantees security and flexibility. It has a modern architecture and runs with only low resource requirements (processor, system memory). The system offers a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/32353.xml">
Java-VM</link>. In the area of standard appliances the operating system it not yet widely spread. It does not support POSIX and has restricted hardware support through drivers. In addition, Symobi is not an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link> operating system and at present does not offer office applications, email functions, or a web browser.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Miray Software: Introducing Symobi, a modern embeddable RTOS, 2006</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://www13.informatik.tu-muenchen.de/personen/baumgarten/index.shtml</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.symobi.com">
Symobi</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www13.cs.tum.edu/">
Operating Systems</weblink> at the Technical University of Munich</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.miray.de/home/index.html">
Miray Software</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</article>
