<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:29:19[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network motif</title>
<id>12499410</id>
<revision>
<id>243661754</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T14:43:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Sabedon</username>
<id>2083035</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Gene expression</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing context</category>
<category>Networks</category>
<category>Wikipedia introduction cleanup</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The introduction to this article provides <b>insufficient context</b> for those unfamiliar with the subject.
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Network_motif&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink> with a .</col>
</row>
</table>



<sec>
<st>
Introduction</st>

<p>

Network motifs are patterns (sub-graphs) that recur within a network much more often than expected at random. Most networks studied in biology, ecology and other fields have been found to show a small set of network motifs; surprisingly, in most cases the networks seem to be largely composed of these network motifs, occuring again and again. Each type of network seems to display its own set of characteristic motifs (ecological networks have differetn motifs than gene regulation networks, etc). These small circuits can be considered as simple building blocks from which the network is composed. This idea was first presented by Uri Alon and his group <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> when network motifs were discovered in the gene regulation (transcription) network of the bacteria <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> and then in a large set of natural networks <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. In following work, the network motifs found in <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it> were discovered in the transcription networks of other bacteria <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> as well as yeast <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> and higher organisms <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>. A distinct set of network motifs were identified in other types of biological networks such as neuronal networks and protein interaction networks <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Network motifs in gene regulation networks</st>

<p>

Much experimental work has been devoted to understanding network motifs in gene regulation networks. These networks control which genes are expressed in the cell in response to biological signals. The network is defined such that genes are nodes, and directed edges represent the control of one gene by a transcription factor (regulatory protein that binds DNA) encoded by another gene. Thus, network motifs are patterns of genes regulating each others transcription rate. When analyzing transcription networks, it is seen that the same network motifs apear again and again in diverse organisms from bacteria to human. The transcriptnio0 network of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it> and yeats, for example, is made of three main motif families, that make up almost the entire network. The leading hypothesis is that the network motif were independently selected by evolutionary processes in a converging manner <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>, since the creation or elimination of regulatory interactions is fast on evolutionary time scale, relative tho the rate at which genes change <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>, Furthermore, experiments on the dynamics generated by network motifs in living cells indicate that they have characteristic dynamical functions. This suggests that the network motif serve as building blocks in gene regulatory networks that are beneficial to the organism.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The function of network motifs</st>

<p>

The functions associated with common network motifs in transcription networks were explored and demonstarted by several research projects both theoreticaly and experimentaly. Below are some of the most common network motifs and their associated function.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Negative autoregulation (NAR)</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Autoregulation_motif.GIF" type="thumb">
<caption>

Schematic representation of an Autoregulation motif
</caption>
</image>

One of simplest and most abundant network motifs in <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it> is negative auto-regulation in which a transcription factor (TF) represses its own transcription. This motif was shown to perform two important functions. The first function is response acceleration. NAR was shown to speed-up the response to signals both theoreticaly and experimentaly. This was first shown in a synthetic transcription network <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> and later on in the natural context in the SOS DNA repair system of E .coli <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>  The second function is increased stability of the auto-regulated gene product concentration against stochastic noise, thus reducing variations in protein levels between different cells <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>. </p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Positive autoregulation (PAR)</st>

<p>

Positive autoregulation (PAR) occurs when a transcription factor enhances its own rate of production. Opposite to the NAR motif this motif slows the response time compared to simple regulation <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref>. In the case of a strong PAR the motif may lead to a bimodal distribution of protein levels in cell populations. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Feedforward loops (FFL)</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Feed-forward_motif.GIF" type="thumb">
<caption>

Schematic representation of a Feed-forward motif
</caption>
</image>

This motif is commonly found in many gene systems and organisms. The motif conssists of three genes and three regulatory interactions. The traget gene Z is regulated by 2 TFs X and Y and in addition TF Y  is alos regulated TF X . Since each of the regulatory interactions may either be positive or negative there are possibly eight types of FFL motifs <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> .Two of those eight types: the coherent type 1 FFL (C1-FFL) (where all interactions are positive) and the incoherent type 1 FFL (I1-FFL) (X activates Z and also activates Y which represses Z) are found much more frequently in the transcription netweork of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it> and yeats than the other six types <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> In addition to the structure of the circuitry the way in which the signals from X and Y are integrate by the Z promoter should also be considered. In most of the cases the FFL is either an  AND gate (X and Y are required for Z activation) or OR gate (either X or Y are suffcient for Z activation) but other input function are also possible.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Coherent type 1 FFL (C1-FFL)</st>

<p>

The C1-FFL with an AND gate was shown to have a function of a ‘sign-sensitive delay’ element and a persistence detector both theoretically <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> and experimentaly <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> with the arabiniose system of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it> . This means that this motif can provide pulse filteration in which short pulsses of signal will not generate a response but persisten signals will generate a response after short delay. The shut off of the output when a persistent puls is ended will be fast.The oposite behavior emerges in the case of a sum gate with fast response and delayed shut off as was demonstrated in the in the flagella system of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref>. </p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Incoherent type 1 FFL (I1-FFL)</st>

<p>

The I1-FFL is a pulse generator and response accelerator. The two signal pathways of the I1-FFL acts in opposite directions where one pathway activates Z and the other represses it. When the repression is complete this leads to a puls like dynamics. It was also demonstrated experimentaly that the I1-FFL can serve as response accelarator in a way which is similar to the NAR motif. The difference is that the I1-FFL can speed-up the response of any gene and not necessarilty a trancription factor gene <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref>. Recently additional function was assigned to the I1-FFL network motif: it was shown both teoretically and experimentaly the I1-FFL can generate non-monotonic input function in both a synthetic <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref>  and native systems <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref>. </p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Multi-output FFLs</st>

<p>

In some cases the same regulators X and Y regulates several Z genes of the same system. By adjusting the strength of the interactions this motif was shown to determine the temporal order of gene activation. This was demonstrated experimentaly in the flagella system of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it>  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Single-input modules (SIM)</st>

<p>

This motif occurs when a single regulator regulates a set of genes with no additional regulation. This is useful when the genes are cooperativly carry out a specific function and therefore need to always be activated in a synchronized manner. By adjusting the strength of the interactions it can creat temporal expression program of the genes it regulates <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref>. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Dense overlapping regulons (DOR)</st>

<p>

This motif occurs in the case that several regulators combinatorialy control a set of genes  with diverse regulatory combinations. This motif was found in <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it> in various systems such as carbon utilization, anarobic growth, stress response and others <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>. In order to better understand the function of this motif one has to obtain more information about the way the multiple inputs are integrated by the genes. Kaplan et al <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref> has mapped the input functions of the sugar utilization genes in <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it>, showing diverse shapes. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Detection of network motifs</st>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weizmann.ac.il/mcb/UriAlon/groupNetworkMotifSW.html">
A software tool that can detect network motifs</weblink></p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>
<p>

An assumption (sometimes more sometimes less implicit) behind the preservation of a topological sub-structure is that it is of a particular functional importance. This assumption has recently been questioned. Some authors have argued that some motifs, like <it>bi-fan motifs</it>, might show a variety depending on the conditions, and therefore<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref>, structure of the motif does not necessarily determine function. Network structure certainly doesn't always indicate function, this is an idea that has been around for some time, for an example see the Sin operon<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref>. Recent research<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref> provides good evidence that network context, i.e. the connections of the motif to the rest of the network, are too important to draw inferences on function from local structure only - the paper also reviews the criticisms and alternative explanations for the observed data.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Alon, U., An Introduction to Systems Biology: Design Principles of Biological Circuits. 2006, Boca Raton: CRC.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Alon, U., Network motifs: theory and experimental approaches. Nat Rev Genet, 2007. 8(6): p. 450-61.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Shen-Orr, S.S., R. Milo, S. Mangan, and U. Alon, Network motifs in the transcriptional regulation network of Escherichia coli. Nat Genet, 2002. 31(1): p. 64-8.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Milo, R., S. Shen-Orr, S. Itzkovitz, N. Kashtan, D. Chklovskii, and U. Alon, Network motifs: simple building blocks of complex networks. Science, 2002. 298(5594): p. 824-7.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Eichenberger, P., M. Fujita, S.T. Jensen, E.M. Conlon, D.Z. Rudner, S.T. Wang, C. Ferguson, K. Haga, T. Sato, J.S. Liu, and R. Losick, The program of gene transcription for a single differentiating cell type during sporulation in Bacillus subtilis. PLoS Biol, 2004. 2(10): p. e328.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Lee, T.I., N.J. Rinaldi, F. Robert, D.T. Odom, Z. Bar-Joseph, G.K. Gerber, N.M. Hannett, C.T. Harbison, C.M. Thompson, I. Simon, J. Zeitlinger, E.G. Jennings, H.L. Murray, D.B. Gordon, B. Ren, J.J. Wyrick, J.B. Tagne, T.L. Volkert, E. Fraenkel, D.K. Gifford, and R.A. Young, Transcriptional regulatory networks in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Science, 2002. 298(5594): p. 799-804.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Odom, D.T., N. Zizlsperger, D.B. Gordon, G.W. Bell, N.J. Rinaldi, H.L. Murray, T.L. Volkert, J. Schreiber, P.A.Rolfe, D.K. Gifford, E. Fraenkel, G.I. Bell, and R.A. Young, Control of pancreas and liver gene expression by HNF transcription factors. Science, 2004. 303(5662): p. 1378-81.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Boyer, L.A., T.I. Lee, M.F. Cole, S.E. Johnstone, S.S. Levine, J.P. Zucker, M.G. Guenther, R.M. Kumar, H.L. Murray,R.G. Jenner, D.K. Gifford, D.A. Melton, R. Jaenisch, and R.A. Young, Core transcriptional regulatory circuitry in human embryonic stem cells. Cell, 2005. 122(6): p. 947-56.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Iranfar, N., D. Fuller, and W.F. Loomis, Transcriptional regulation of post-aggregation genes in Dictyostelium by a feed-forward loop involving GBF and LagC. Dev Biol, 2006. 290(2): p. 460-9.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Milo, R., S. Itzkovitz, N. Kashtan, R. Levitt, S. Shen-Orr, I. Ayzenshtat, M. Sheffer, and U. Alon,Superfamilies of evolved and designed networks. Science, 2004. 303(5663): p. 1538-42.</entry>
<entry id="11">
Ma'ayan, A., S.L. Jenkins, S. Neves, A. Hasseldine, E. Grace, B. Dubin-Thaler, N.J. Eungdamrong, G. Weng, P.T. Ram,J.J. Rice, A. Kershenbaum, G.A. Stolovitzky, R.D. Blitzer, and R. Iyengar, Formation of regulatory patterns during signal propagation in a Mammalian cellular network. Science, 2005. 309(5737): p. 1078-83.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Ptacek, J., G. Devgan, G. Michaud, H. Zhu, X. Zhu, J. Fasolo, H. Guo, G. Jona, A. Breitkreutz, R. Sopko, R.R.McCartney, M.C. Schmidt, N. Rachidi, S.J. Lee, A.S. Mah, L. Meng, M.J. Stark, D.F. Stern, C. De Virgilio, M. Tyers, B.Andrews, M. Gerstein, B. Schweitzer, P.F. Predki, and M. Snyder, Global analysis of protein phosphorylation in yeast. Nature,2005. 438(7068): p. 679-84.</entry>
<entry id="13">
Babu, M.M., N.M. Luscombe, L. Aravind, M. Gerstein, and S.A. Teichmann, Structure and evolution of transcriptional regulatory networks. Curr Opin Struct Biol, 2004. 14(3): p. 283-91.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Conant, G.C. and A. Wagner, Convergent evolution of gene circuits. Nat Genet, 2003. 34(3): p. 264-6.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Dekel, E. and U. Alon, Optimality and evolutionary tuning of the expression level of a protein. in press, 2005.</entry>
<entry id="17">
Camas, F.M., J. Blazquez, and J.F. Poyatos, Autogenous and nonautogenous control of response in a genetic network.Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 2006. 103(34): p. 12718-23.</entry>
<entry id="16">
Rosenfeld, N., M.B. Elowitz, and U. Alon, Negative autoregulation speeds the response times of transcription networks. J Mol Biol, 2002. 323(5): p. 785-93.</entry>
<entry id="19">
Dublanche, Y., K. Michalodimitrakis, N. Kummerer, M. Foglierini, and L. Serrano, Noise in transcription negative feedback loops: simulation and experimental analysis. Mol Syst Biol, 2006. 2: p. 41.</entry>
<entry id="18">
Becskei, A. and L. Serrano, Engineering stability in gene networks by autoregulation. Nature, 2000. 405(6786): p.590-3.</entry>
<entry id="21">
Becskei, A., B. Seraphin, and L. Serrano, Positive feedback in eukaryotic gene networks: cell differentiation by graded to binary response conversion. Embo J, 2001. 20(10): p. 2528-35.</entry>
<entry id="20">
Maeda, Y.T. and M. Sano, Regulatory dynamics of synthetic gene networks with positive feedback. J Mol Biol, 2006.359(4): p. 1107-24.</entry>
<entry id="23">
Ma, H.W., B. Kumar, U. Ditges, F. Gunzer, J. Buer, and A.P. Zeng, An extended transcriptional regulatory network of Escherichia coli and analysis of its hierarchical structure and network motifs. Nucleic Acids Res, 2004. 32(22): p. 6643-9.</entry>
<entry id="22">
Mangan, S. and U. Alon, Structure and function of the feed-forward loop network motif. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A,2003. 100(21): p. 11980-5.</entry>
<entry id="25">
Kalir, S., S. Mangan, and A. U., The coherent feed-forward loop with a SUM input function protects flagella production in Escherichia coli. Molecular Systems Biology, 2005.</entry>
<entry id="24">
Mangan, S., A. Zaslaver, and U. Alon, The coherent feedforward loop serves as a sign-sensitive delay element in transcription networks. J Mol Biol, 2003. 334(2): p. 197-204.</entry>
<entry id="27">
Entus, R., B. Aufderheide, M. Herbert, and M.H. Sauro, Design and implementation of three incoherent feed-forward motif based biological concentration sensors. Systems and Synthetic Biology, 2007. Published on line.</entry>
<entry id="26">
Mangan, S., A. Zaslaver, and U. Alon, The incohorent feedforward loop accelerates response time in the gal system of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. Coli</link></it>. J. Mol. Biol., 2006.</entry>
<entry id="29">
Kalir, S., J. McClure, K. Pabbaraju, C. Southward, M. Ronen, S. Leibler, M.G. Surette, and U. Alon, Ordering genes in a flagella pathway by analysis of expression kinetics from living bacteria. Science, 2001. 292(5524): p. 2080-3.</entry>
<entry id="28">
Kaplan, S., A. Bren, E. Dekel, and U. Alon, The incoherent feed-forward loop can generate non-monotonic input functions for genes. Mol Syst Biol, 2008. 4: p. 203.</entry>
<entry id="31">
Kaplan, S., A. Bren, A. Zaslaver, E. Dekel, and U. Alon, Diverse Two-Dimensional Input-Functions Control Bacterial Sugar Genes. Mol. Cell, 2008.</entry>
<entry id="30">
Zaslaver, A., A.E. Mayo, R. Rosenberg, P. Bashkin, H. Sberro, M. Tsalyuk, M.G. Surette, and U. Alon, Just-in-time transcription program in metabolic pathways. Nat Genet, 2004. 36(5): p. 486-91.</entry>
<entry id="34">
Knabe, J. F., Nehaniv, C. L. and Schilstra, M. J. Do Motifs Reflect Evolved Function? - No Convergent Evolution of Genetic Regulatory Network Subgraph Topologies. In BioSystems, 2008. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biosystems.2008.05.012</entry>
<entry id="32">
Ingram P.J., Stumpf M.P., Stark J. Network motifs: structure does not determine function. BMC Genomics. 2006; 7: 108.<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16677373">
 16677373</weblink></entry>
<entry id="33">
Voigt, Wolf and Arkin in "The B. subtilis SIN Operon: An Evolvable Network Motif", Genetics, 169, 1187-1202 (2005)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weizmann.ac.il/mcb/UriAlon/">
Uri Alon's web page</weblink></p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
