<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:31:13[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<fundamental_quantity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113575869">
<time_period  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="115113229">
<festival  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="115162388">
<header>
<title>San Diego Bay Wine &amp; Food Festival</title>
<id>12585876</id>
<revision>
<id>229612479</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-03T17:22:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Myasuda</username>
<id>1187538</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Food festivals in the United States</category>
<category>Festivals</category>
<category>Culture of San Diego, California</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is written like .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=San_Diego_Bay_Wine_%26_Food_Festival&amp;action=edit">
rewrite this article</weblink> from a . For <b>blatant</b> advertising that would require a fundamental rewrite to become encyclopedic, use  to mark for .&nbsp;<it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


The <b>San Diego Bay Wine &amp; Food Festival</b> is an international showcase of the world's premier wine and spirits producers, chefs and culinary personalities, and gourmet foods. Held in downtown <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/28504.xml">
San Diego</link>, the event benefits the American Institute of Wine &amp; Food culinary arts scholarship program. Over 700 wines, 60 of San Diego’s fine dining restaurants and 30 gourmet food companies and exhibitors take part in the week-long activities. Now in its fourth year, the San Diego Bay Wine &amp; Food Festival features wine tasting seminars, cooking classes by award- winning chefs, and an elegant Reserve Tasting. The festival culminates on Saturday at the Grand Tasting Event and Fine Wine/Lifestyle Auction with the Chef of the Fest competition, celebrity cookbook signing tents, Cost Plus entertainment tent, Olive Oil Tasting Tent and others.
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

The San Diego Bay Wine &amp; Food Festival was created four years ago by co-producers Ken Loyst and Michelle Metter.  "San Diego is a hot bed of activity now with more top name chefs opening fine dining restaurants and a number of our young talent moving up in the culinary world to make big names for themselves," said Metter.  "Wineries from around the world are looking at San Diego as an up and coming market and the demand for this type of event in our city was overwhelming.  What we've found is that the event has become much more significant than a city-centric Festival but rather a luxury food and wine festival catering to 'foodies' across the country."</p>
<p>

While the event has become much talked about in culinary circles, and among food and wine media, Metter adds that,"The attention is fantastic, and we love the reputation we have gained.  Our focus continues to be our auctions and the scholarships we are able to provide from funds raised through them."</p>
<p>

Proceeds from the auctions benefit the American Institute of Wine &amp; Food Culinary Arts Scholarship programs for students in San Diego.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worldofwineevents.com/">
Official San Diego Bay Wine &amp; Food Festival website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</festival>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
</article>
