<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:22:01[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Metapopulation</title>
<id>1260217</id>
<revision>
<id>228321446</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-28T04:12:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jon Nevill</username>
<id>608366</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Population ecology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>metapopulation</b> consists of a group of spatially separated populations of the same <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/28023.xml">
species</link> which interact at some level.  The term metapopulation was coined by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/3010875.xml">
Richard Levins</link></writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biologist>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/34610.xml">
1969</link> to describe a model of population dynamics of insect pests in agricultural fields, but the idea has been most broadly applied to species in naturally or artificially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/1259241.xml">
fragmented habitats</link>. In Levins' own words, it consists of "a population of populations". <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

A metapopulation is generally considered to consist of several distinct populations together with areas of suitable habitat which are currently unoccupied. In classical metapopulation theory, each population cycles in relative independence of the other populations and eventually goes extinct as a consequence of <link>
demographic stochasticity</link> (fluctuations in population size due to random demographic events); the smaller the population, the more prone it is to extinction.  </p>
<p>

Although individual populations have finite life-spans, the metapopulation as a whole is often stable because immigrants from one population (which may, for example, be experiencing a population boom) are likely to re-colonize habitat which has been left open by the extinction of another population.  They may also emigrate to a small population and rescue that population from extinction (called the <it>rescue effect</it>).  </p>
<p>

The development of metapopulation theory, in conjunction with the development of <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/10606078.xml">
source-sink dynamics</link></b>, emphasised the importance of connectivity between seemingly isolated populations.  Although no single population may be able to guarantee the long-term survival of a given species, the combined effect of <it>many</it> populations may be able to do this.</p>
<p>

Metapopulation theory was first developed for terrestrial ecosystems, and subsequently applied to the marine realm (Kritzer &amp; Sale 2006). In fisheries science, the term "sub-population" is equivalent to the metapopulation science term "local population".  Most marine examples are provided by relatively sedentary species occupying discrete patches of habitat, with both local recruitment and recruitment from other local populations in the larger metapopulation. Kritzer &amp; Sale have argued against strict application of the metapopulation definitional criteria that extinction risks to local populations must be non-negligible (K &amp; S 2006:32).</p>
<p>

The most important contributor to metapopulation theory is the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/10577.xml">
Finnish</link></country>
 biologist, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<ecologist wordnetid="110043163" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/6749235.xml">
Ilkka Hanski</link></associate>
</ecologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</biologist>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.helsinki.fi/~ihanski/">
http://www.helsinki.fi/~ihanski/</weblink>, of the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/220548.xml">
University of Helsinki</link></university>
.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Predation and Oscillations</st>
<p>

The first experiments with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/57559.xml">
predation</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/10930438.xml">
spatial heterogeneity</link> were conducted by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/1290178.xml">
G.F. Gause</link></person>
 in the 1930's, based on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/462534.xml">
Lotka-Volterra equation</link>, which was formulated in the mid-1920s, but no further application had been conducted <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. The Lotka-Volterra equation suggested that the relationship between predators and their prey would result in population <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/22522.xml">
oscillations</link> over time based on the initial densities of predator and prey. Gause's early experiments to prove the predicted oscillations of this theory failed because the predator-prey interactions were not influenced by immigration. However, once immigration was introduced, the population cycles accurately depicted the oscillations predicted by the Lotka-Volterra equation, with the peaks in prey abundance shifted slightly to the left of the peaks of the predator densities. Huffaker's experiments expanded on those of Gause by examining how both the factors of migration and spatial heterogeneity lead to predator-prey oscillations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Huffaker's experiments on predator-prey interactions (1958)</st>
<p>
 
In order to study predation and population oscillations, Huffaker used mite species, one being the predator and the other being the prey. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> He set up a controlled experiment using oranges, which the prey fed on, as the spatially structured habitat in which the predator and prey would interact.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> At first, Huffaker experienced difficulties similar to those of Gause in creating a stable predator-prey interaction. By using oranges only, the prey species quickly went extinct followed consequently with predator extinction. However, he discovered that by modifying the spatial structure of the habitat, he could manipulate the population dynamics and allow the overall survival rate for both species to increase. He did this by altering the distance between the prey and oranges (their food), establishing barriers to predator movement, and creating corridors for the prey to disperse.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> These changes resulted in increased habitat patches and in turn provided more areas for the prey to seek temporary protection. When the prey would go extinct locally at one habitat patch, they were able to reestablish by migrating to new patches before being attacked by predators. This habitat spatial structure of patches allowed for coexistence between the predator and prey species and promoted a stable population oscillation model.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Although the term metapopulation had not yet been coined, the environmental factors of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/10930438.xml">
spatial heterogeneity</link> and habitat patchiness would later describe the conditions of a metapopulation relating to how groups of spatially separated populations of species interact with one another. Huffaker's experiment is significant because it showed how metapopulations can directly affect the predator-prey interactions and in turn influence population dynamics.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Aggregation effect and stability of predator-prey interactions</st>
<p>

The stability of predator-prey interactions in patchy environments is reinforced when an aggregation effect occurs. Aggregation effect is when predators are more greatly attracted to habitat patches with high prey densities, therefore, areas with low prey densities are relieved from the pressure of predation and are able to generate a larger population and avoid extinction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> </p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The Levins model</st>
<p>

Levins' original model applied to a metapopulation distributed over many patches of suitable habitat with significantly less interaction between patches than within a patch.  Population dynamics within a patch were simplified to the point where only presence and absence were considered.  Each patch in his model is either populated or not.  </p>
<p>

Let <it>N</it> be the fraction of patches occupied at a given time.  During a time step, each occupied patch can become unoccupied with an extinction probability <it>e</it>.  Additionally, 1&nbsp;−&nbsp;<it>N</it> of the patches are unoccupied.  Each of these may become populated by colonization.  Let <it>c</it> be a constant rate of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/3450872.xml">
propagule</link> generation for each of the <it>N</it> occupied patches.  This yields a probability of <it>cN</it> for each unoccupied patch to be colonized.  So for each time step, the change in the proportion of occupied patches, <it>dN/dt</it>, is</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\frac{dN}{dt} = (1-N)cN - eN.\,</math>
</indent>

This takes on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/87210.xml">
sigmoid</link> shape similar to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18137.xml">
logistic model</link>.  The equilibrium value of <it>N</it> can be calculated by setting <it>dN</it> to be equal to zero.  Solving for <it>N</it> gives either <it>N</it> = 0 or</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math> N = 1 - \frac{e}{c}.\,</math>
</indent>

This result, that <b>N</b> is always less than one, implies that some fraction of a species habitat will always be unoccupied.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Stochastic patch occupancy models (SPOMs)</st>
<p>

One major drawback of the Levins model is that it is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/47922.xml">
deterministic</link>, whereas the fundamental metapopulation processes are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/292222.xml">
stochastic</link>. Metapopulations are particularly useful when discussing species in disturbed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/1596317.xml">
habitats</link>, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/1550259.xml">
viability of their populations</link>, i.e., how likely they are to become <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/49417.xml">
extinct</link> in a given time interval. The Levins model cannot address this issue.</p>
<p>

For <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/216216.xml">
conservation biology</link> purposes, metapopulation models must include (a) the finite nature of metapopulations (how many patches are suitable for habitat), and (b) the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/23542.xml">
probabilistic</link> nature of extinction and colonisation.  Also, note that in order to apply these models, the extinctions and colonisations of the patches must be asynchronous.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Stochasticity and Metapopulations</st>
<p>

Huffaker's studies of spatial structure and species interactions are an example of early experimentation in metapopulation dynamics. Since the experiments of Huffaker and Levins, models have been created which integrate stochastic factors. These models have proven that the combination of environmental variability (stochascity) and relatively small migration rates cause indefinite or unpredictable persistence. However, Huffaker's experiment almost guaranteed infinite persistence because of the controlled immigration variable.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/252582.xml">
Landscape ecology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/216216.xml">
Conservation biology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/826478.xml">
Population viability analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/10930438.xml">
Spatial heterogeneity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/57559.xml">
Predation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/22522.xml">
Oscillation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/462534.xml">
Lotka-Volterra equation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<interaction wordnetid="100039021" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/4715998.xml">
Competition (biology)</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</interaction>
</action>
</event>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Levins, R. 1969. "Some demographic and genetic consequences of environmental heterogeneity for biological control." Bulletin of the Entomological Society of America, 15, 237-240</entry>
<entry id="2">
Real, Leslie A. and Brown, James H. 1991. Foundations of Ecology: Classic papers with commentaries. The University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Huffaker, C.B. 1958. Experimental Studies on Predation: Dispersion factors and predator-prey oscillations. Hilgardia. 27: 343, p. 83</entry>
<entry id="4">
Legendre, P. and Fortin, M.J. 1989. Spatial pattern and ecological analysis. Plant Ecology. 80:2, p.107.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Real, Leslie A. and Brown, James H. 1991. Foundations of Ecology: Classic papers with commentaries. The University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Kareiva, P. 1987. Habitat Fragmentation and the Stability of Predator-Prey Interactions. Nature. 326:6111, p. 388.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Janssen, A. et al. 1997. Metapopulation Dynamics of a Persisting Predator-Prey system.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Real, Leslie A. and Brown, James H. 1991. Foundations of Ecology: Classic papers with commentaries. The University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Real, Leslie A. and Brown, James H. 1991. Foundations of Ecology: Classic papers with commentaries. The University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hanski, I.  <it>Metapopulation Ecology</it>  Oxford University Press.  1999.  ISBN 0-19-854065-5</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Huffaker, C.B. 1958. Experimental Studies on Predation: Dispersion factors and predator-prey oscillations. Hilgardia. 27: 343, p. 83</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fahrig, L. 2003. Effects of Habitat Fragmentation on Biodiversity.  Annual Review of ecology, evolution, and systematics. 34:1, p.487.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Janssen, A. et al. 1997. Metapopulation Dynamics of a Persisting Predator-Prey system. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kareiva, P. 1987. Habitat Fragmentation and the Stability of Predator-Prey Interactions. Nature. 326:6111, p. 388.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kritzer, JP &amp; Sale, PF (eds) (2006) Marine metapopulations, Academic Press, New York.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Legendre, P. and Fortin, M.J. 1989. Spatial pattern and ecological analysis. Plant Ecology. 80:2, p.107.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Levins, R. 1969. "Some demographic and genetic consequences of environmental heterogeneity for biological control."  <it>Bulletin of the Entomological Society of America</it>, <b>15</b>, 237-240</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Levin, S.A. 1974. Dispersion and Population Interactions. The American Naturalist. 108:960, p.207.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Real, Leslie A. and Brown, James H. 1991. Foundations of Ecology: Classic papers with commentaries. The University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.helsinki.fi/science/metapop/</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
