<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:22:21[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<work  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100575741">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<service  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100577525">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Web Services Discovery</title>
<id>1268013</id>
<revision>
<id>221304740</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-23T23:04:57Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ghettoblaster</username>
<id>6603820</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
<category>Web services</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Ambox_?.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>All or part of this article may be .</b>
Please help . Suggestions may be on the . <it>(December 2007)</it></col>
</row>
</table>



<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/93483.xml">
Web services</link> provide access  to software systems over the Internet using standard protocols. In a minimalistic scenario there exists at least a Web service provider that publishes some service such as a weather service and a Web service consumer that uses this service. Web service discovery is the process of finding a suitable Web service for given task.</p>
<p>

Publishing a Web service involves at the bare minimum to create the software artifact and make it accessible to potential consumers. In order that a consumer can use a service, providers usually augment a Web service endpoint with an interface description using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/4030790.xml">
Web Services Description Language</link> (WSDL). </p>
<p>

Optionally a provider can explicitly register a service with a Web services registry such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/158694.xml">
UDDI</link> or publish additional documents intended to facilitate discovery such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/1268030.xml">
Web Services Inspection Language</link> (WSIL) documents. The service users or consumers need to search Web services manually or automatically.  The implementation of UDDI servers and WSIL engines should provide simple search APIs or web-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
GUI</link> to help find Web services. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Federated Discovery </st>

<p>

However, the current UDDI search mechanism can only focus on a single search criterion, such as business name, business location, business category, or service type by name, business identifier, or discovery URL. In fact, in a business solution, it is very normal to search multiple UDDI registries or WSIL documents and then aggregate the returned result by using filtering and ranking techniques, which are used in <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 today.  IBM modularized this federated Web services discovery engine in 2001. The released technology from IBM is <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alphaWorks.ibm.com/tech/be4ws">
Business Explorer for Web Services (BE4WS)</weblink>, which was the first released technology to target on federated Web services discovery. More visionary articles and research papers can be found from the external links.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Research Paper: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www2008.org/papers/fp389.html">
Investigating Web Services on the World Wide Web</weblink>, 2008</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

IBM Article: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/webservices/library/ws-be4ws/">
Aggregate UDDI searches with Business Explorer for Web services</weblink>, 01 Mar 2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Web Services Journal Article: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sys-con.com/story/?storyid=39555&amp;DE=1">
Next-Generation Web Services Discovery</weblink>, August 27, 2002 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Research Paper: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lsdis.cs.uga.edu/lib/download/MWSDI-ICWS04-final.pdf">
Discovery of Web Services in a Federated Registry Environment</weblink>, 2004</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Survey Paper: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mmlab.ceid.upatras.gr/people/sakkopoulos/conf/ht04.pdf">
Web Service Discovery Mechanisms: Looking for a Needle in a Haystack?</weblink>, 2004 </entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</article>
