<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:31:56[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<institute  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108407330">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<association  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108049401">
<lab  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103629986">
<header>
<title>Research Institute for Advanced Computer Science</title>
<id>12685352</id>
<revision>
<id>181468851</id>
<timestamp>2008-01-01T23:13:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Gantuya eng</username>
<id>4783883</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Space organizations</category>
<category>Artificial intelligence laboratories</category>
<category>Computer science institutes</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="60 px" src="riacslogo.png" type="frame">
<caption>

USRA-RIACS Logo
</caption>
</image>
 
<ss2>
<st>
 Overview </st>

<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
Research Institute for Advanced Computer Science (RIACS)</weblink> was founded June 1, 1983 as a joint collaboration between the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/7708517.xml">
 Universities Space Research Association</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
 (USRA) and the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<science_museum wordnetid="104147364" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<depository wordnetid="103177349" confidence="0.8">
<museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/47477.xml">
 NASA Ames Research Center</link></museum>
</depository>
</facility>
</science_museum>
</artifact>
. The Institute was created to conduct basic and applied research in computer science, covering a broad range of research topics of interest to the aerospace community including supercomputing, computational fluid dynamics, computational chemistry, high performance networking, and artificial intelligence. </p>
<p>

Since its inception, a goal of the Institute’s research has been to support scientific research and engineering from problem formulation to results dissemination, combining concurrent processing systems with intelligent systems to allow users to interact in the language of their discipline.  This goal has since expanded to support a broad range of activities associated with space exploration and science, including mission operations and innovative information systems for technology research and development.</p>
<p>

An underlying philosophy and approach of the Institute is that successful research is interdisciplinary, and that challenging applications associated with NASA’s mission provide a driving force for developing innovative information systems and advancing computer science. To implement this approach, research staff undertakes collaborative projects with research groups at NASA, integrating computer science with other disciplines to support NASA’s mission. </p>
<p>

Over its nearly twenty five year history, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
RIACS</weblink> has acted as a bridge between academia and government research, engaging talented researchers from around the world to collaborate with NASA on challenging research topics. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
RIACS</weblink> has also acted as a bridge between industry and the government to mature information technologies for infusion into NASA operations, enabling broader public benefit from research results.</p>
<p>

For  NASA, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
RIACS</weblink> has collaborated most closely with the Intelligent Systems Division and the <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/2208120.xml">
 NASA Advanced Supercomputing Division</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</facility>
</artifact>
</region>
</site>
 (NAS) at the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<science_museum wordnetid="104147364" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<depository wordnetid="103177349" confidence="0.8">
<museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/47477.xml">
 NASA Ames Research Center</link></museum>
</depository>
</facility>
</science_museum>
</artifact>
 – NASA’s Center for Excellence in Information Technology. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
RIACS</weblink>, which was formed the same year as the NAS, worked closely with the division in its early years to develop a strong competency in supercomputing and computational fluid dynamics at NASA.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
RIACS</weblink> helped establish the Intelligent Systems Division, and has since collaborated closely with the division to develop and infuse a number of software innovations in the areas of autonomous systems; intelligent information management and data understanding; and human-centered computing.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Historical Contributions to NASA </st>

<p>

Examples of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
RIACS</weblink> contributions to NASA Ames as part of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ti.arc.nasa.gov">
Intelligent Systems Divisions</weblink> include leadership roles in developing and infusing: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Autoclass Bayesian discovery system – used probabilistic techniques to discover new classes of infra-red stars in the Low Resolution Spectral catalogue from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/301728.xml">
 NASA IRAS mission</link> as the first artificial intelligence program to make an astronomical discovery; also used to discover new classes proteins, introns, and other patterns in DNA/protein sequence data, and others; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Livingstone model-based diagnostic system – flown on <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<probe wordnetid="105800611" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/9070.xml">
 Deep Space One</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</probe>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 as part of Remote Agent and on Earth Observing Mission EO-1 as the first artificial intelligence control system to control a spacecraft without human supervision; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu/research/projects/mapgen">
MAPGEN</weblink> tactical activity planner – a constraint-based planning system used everyday during the <mission wordnetid="108403225" confidence="0.8">
<nongovernmental_organization wordnetid="108009834" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/252908.xml">
 Mars Exploration Rover mission</link></nongovernmental_organization>
</mission>
  resulting in an estimated 20% increase in scientific return; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Clarissa voice-operated procedure browser – used on the <voyage wordnetid="100312553" confidence="0.8">
<spaceflight wordnetid="100313502" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<journey wordnetid="100306426" confidence="0.8">
<travel wordnetid="100295701" confidence="0.8">
<motion wordnetid="100279835" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/15043.xml">
 International Space Station</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</motion>
</travel>
</journey>
</action>
</change>
</event>
</spaceflight>
</voyage>
 as the first spoken- dialogue system used in space; and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu/research/projects/pmt">
Program Management Tool</weblink> – used to manage billions of dollars of <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/18426568.xml">
 NASA</link></agency>
 programs and projects with case studies showing 85% reduction in financial reporting time, elimination of 40% discrepancy rates in non-advocate review milestone data, and elimination of 30% error rates in baseline project plans.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Purpose and Charter </st>

<p>

The stated purpose of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
RIACS</weblink> since its formation is to:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Provide an interface between the NASA Ames Research Center and the academic community and serve as a center of cooperation for activities conducted in areas of advanced computer science and engineering, applied mathematics, and the application of computers to NASA’s scientific and engineering challenges. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Conduct independent research activities with the objective of developing concepts, techniques, or prototypes in computationally related disciplines to enhance problem-solving capabilities in scientific and engineering fields of interest to the aerospace community.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Improve cooperative research efforts of government, industry, and academia toward the solution of problems requiring advanced computational facilities.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Enhance technology transfer between universities, industry and other government agencies by conventional means, including encouragement of the rapid dissemination of preprint reports by institute personnel, presentations at symposia and publications in appropriate journals.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Strengthen ties between the general academic and industrial communities and  NASA’s Ames Research Center to further develop in-house programmatic activities in computer science and technology.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Carry out a variety of additional activities, including lecture programs and visiting scientist programs,  as well as provide consultation and collaboration with NASA Ames on topics in the fields of computer science and applied mathematics.  RIACS personnel may lend support to local universities through the direction of dissertations, service on research committees, and participation in research seminars.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Engage and leverage an eminent Science Council appointed by USRA to review progress of RIACS, including its research, reports, publications, and other matters that would affect or influence the purpose of the Institute. The Science Council also advises the RIACS Director on research projects, priorities, and resource requirements, and reports to USRA on the scientific activity of the Institute.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riacs.edu">
RIACS</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.usra.edu">
USRA</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.arc.nasa.gov">
NASA Ames Research Center</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ti.arc.nasa.gov">
NASA Intelligent Systems Division</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nas.nasa.gov">
NASA Supercomputing Division</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nas.nasa.gov">
NASA</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
</bdy>
</lab>
</association>
</organization>
</institute>
</article>
