<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:37:32[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<cabaret  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="102931417">
<structure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104341686">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<place_of_business  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103953020">
<establishment  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103297735">
<spot  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104286128">
<header>
<title>Discowhip</title>
<id>12772180</id>
<revision>
<id>164030327</id>
<timestamp>2007-10-12T12:13:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>タチコマ robot</username>
<id>421426</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Nightclubs in the United Kingdom</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Discowhip</b> is an event/club night run by Wiltshire based DJs Owen James, Jamie Roxx and Phatcamp (Alex Cargill).  <p>

The music policy is based around a core of house music although the specific sound changes with the times. The Discowhip sound and subsequently the acts and djs change with “what is current” in the UK house scene. Discowhip decided not to associate with any particular genre or style, opting alternatively to stay with what is current in the more general house scene. This policy has been accredited with allowing the event to keep it’s originality.</p>
<p>

The idea was formed in 2005 when two of the promoters were patrons of the Notting Hill Carnival. A chance meeting with Brandon Block, followed by an “off the cuff” remark by one of the wouldbe promoters left the founders with a DJ booked but no venue and no experience.</p>
<p>

The team soon got to work – securing a council venue. They then had to find a name for the event. Originally "Pussy Whipped" was the desired name – however Kennet Council were not happy having a name with the “wrong sort of connotations” thus Discowhip was born.</p>
<p>

5 events on, they have acquired a host of new local talent. The regulars now include...</p>
<p>

•	Dave Moules
•	Micky P
•	Jamie Roxx
•	GH1
•	Phatcamp 
•	Owen James</p>

<p>

The promise from the organisers for regular venues and stability is yet to materialise. It has been said, however, that the lack of strict organisation has only helped to preserve its underground feel.</p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.discowhip.com/">
Discowhip Website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</spot>
</establishment>
</place_of_business>
</artifact>
</structure>
</cabaret>
</article>
