<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:36:13[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Power system simulation</title>
<id>12825821</id>
<revision>
<id>242488041</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T13:12:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Electric power</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Power system simulation</b> models are a class of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/375416.xml">
computer simulation</link> programs that focus on the operation of electrical power systems. These computer programs are used in a wide range of planning and operational situations including:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Long-term generation and transmission expansion planning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Short-term operational simulations</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Market analysis (e.g. price forecasting)</entry>
</list>
<p>

These programs typically make use of <link>
mathematical optimization</link> techniques such <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/43730.xml">
linear programming</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/40324.xml">
quadratic programming</link>, and <link>
mixed integer programming</link>.</p>
<p>

Key elements of power systems that are modeled include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Load flow (<link>
Load Flow Calculation</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Short circuit (<link>
Short Circuit Analysis</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Transient stability (<link>
Transient Stability Simulation</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Optimal dispatch of generating units (<link>
unit commitment</link>).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Transmission <link>
optimal power flow</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Layered on top if this physical framework are models of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/181592.xml">
competition</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/1079244.xml">
Cournot</link>, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/1462677.xml">
Bertrand competition</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, and <link>
Supply Function Equilibrium</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Load Flow Calculation</st>
<p>

The load-flow calculation is the most common network analysis tool for examining the undisturbed and disturbed network within the scope of operational and strategical planning.
On the basis of the network topology with the impedances of all devices as well as with the infeeds and the consumers, the load-flow calculation can provide voltage profiles for all nodes and loading of network components, such as cables and transformers. With this information, the compliance of the operating conditions relating to permissible voltage ranges and maximum loads, or the violation of these conditions, can be examined. This is, for example, important for determining the transmission capacity of underground cables, where the influence of cable bundling on the load capability of each cable has to be taken also into account.
Due of its ability to determine losses and reactive-power allocation, load-flow calculation also supports the planning engineer in the investigation of the most economical operation mode of the network.
When changing over from single and/or multi-phase infeed low-voltage meshed networks to isolated networks, load-flow calculation is essential for operational and economical reasons.
Load-flow calculation is also the basis of all further network studies, such as motor start-up or investigation of scheduled or unschedulded outages of equipment within the outage simulation.
Especially when inevstigating motor start-up, the load-flow calculation results give helpful hints, for example, of whether the motor can be started in spite of the voltage drop caused by the start-up current.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Short Circuit Analysis</st>
<p>

Short Circuitr Analysis is analyze the power flow after fault occurs in power network. The faults maybe are three-phase short circuit, one-phase grounded, two-phase short circuit, two-phase grounded, one-phase break, two-phase break or complex faults.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Transient Stability Simulation</st>
<p>

(todo ...)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Unit Commitment</st>

<p>

The problem of unit commitment involves finding the least-cost dispatch of available generation resources to meet the electrical load.</p>
<p>

Generating resources can include a wide range of types:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/22153.xml">
Nuclear</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/354370.xml">
Thermal</link> (using coal, gas, or other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/48146.xml">
fossil fuels</link>])</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/25784.xml">
Renewables</link> (including hydro, wind, wave-power, and solar)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The key decision variables that are decided by the computer program are:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Generation level (in megawatts)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Number of generating units <it>on''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The latter decisions are binary (0,1), which means the mathematical problem is not continuous.</p>
<p>

In addition, generating plant are subject to a number of complex technical constraints, including:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Minimum stable operating level</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Maximum rate of ramping up or down</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Minimum time period the unit is <it>up</it> and/or <it>down''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

These constraints are amenable to mathematical programming as linear or mixed-integer constraints.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Optimal Power Flow</st>

<p>

Electricity flows through an AC network according to <link>
Kirchhoff's Laws</link>.  Transmission lines are subject to thermal limits (simple megawatt limits on flow), as well as voltage and <link>
electrical stability</link> constraints.</p>
<p>

The simulator must calculate the flows in the AC network that result from any given combination of unit commitment and generator megawatt dispatch, and ensure that AC line flows are within both the thermal limits and the voltage and stability constraints.  This may include contingencies such as the loss of any one transmission or generation element - a so-called security-constrained optimal power flow (SCOPF), and if the unit commitment is optimized inside this framework we have a security-constrained unit commitment (SCUC).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Models of Competitive Behavior</st>

<p>

The cost of producing a megawatt of electrical energy is a function of:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

fuel price</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

generation efficiency (the rate at which potential energy in the fuel is converted to electrical energy)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

operations and maintenance costs</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In addition to this, generating plant incur fixed costs including:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

plant construction costs, and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

fixed operations and maintenance costs</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Assuming <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/23002.xml">
perfect competition</link>, the market-based price of electricity would be based purely on the cost of producing the <it>next</it> megawatt of power, the so-called <it>short-run marginal cost</it> (SRMC).  This price however might not be sufficient to cover the fixed costs of generation, and thus power market prices rarely show purely SRMC pricing.  In most established power markets, generators are <it>free</it> to offer their generation capacity at prices of their choosing.  Competition and use of financial contracts keeps these prices close to SRMC, but inevitably offers price above SRMC do occur (for example during the <link>
California Energy Crisis</link> of 2001).</p>
<p>

In the context of power system simulation, a number of techniques have been applied to simulate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/45445.xml">
imperfect competition</link> in electrical power markets:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Cournot competition</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Bertrand competition</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Supply function equilibrium</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Residual Supply Index analysis</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristics</link> have also been applied to this problem.  The aim is to provide <it>realistic</it> forecasts of power market prices, given the forecast supply-demand situation.</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
