<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:37:03[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Social Franchising</title>
<id>12846801</id>
<revision>
<id>223483585</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-04T07:33:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Loukinho</username>
<id>461336</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> Franchises</category>
<category>Wikify from August 2007</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Social_Franchising&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(August 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Social franchising</b> is defined as a system of contractual relationships “usually run by a non-governmental organization which uses the structure of a commercial franchise to achieve social goals” <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. The definition can further be expanded to mean:<p>

The social franchise is an adaptation of a commercial franchise in which the  developer of a successfully tested social concept (franchiser) enables others (franchisees) to replicate the model using the tested system and brand name to achieve a social benefit. </p>
<p>

One essential element is to belong to a network of franchises and in this network the coordinator (franchiser) is responsible for bringing harmony and concordance to the network and ensure consistency among the health service providers <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. Often in social franchising the services are subsidized so that the recipient of services has a lower out-of-pocket payment. The elements that typify a social franchising package are:  Training, Protocolized management, Standardization of supplies and services, Branding, Monitoring, and Network membership.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Franchising Model </st>
<p>

Franchising for clinical services can be further categorized according to model and the strength of the network: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Stand-alone model: provides exclusively franchised supported services or commodities</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fractional model: services are added to a  practice that existed before the franchising operation and only a portion of the services are from the franchise</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

First generation franchising where the franchiser offer a territory and use of franchising within the guidelines. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Second generation franchising includes first part and active monitoring and control (creating a tighter, more structured, more regulated network)  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Montagu D (2002) Franchising of health services in developing countries. Health Policy and Planning, 17(2): 121-130.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Prata N, Monagu D, Jeffrys E (2005) Private sector, human resources and health franchising in Africa, Bulletin of the World Health Organization, 83(4): 274-279.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Perrot J (2006) Different approaches to contracting in health systems. Bulletin of the World Health Organization, 84(11): 859-866.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Stephenson R, Ong Tsui A, Sulzbach S, Bardsley P, Bekele G, Giday T, Ahmed R, Gopalkrishnan G, Feyesitan B (2004) Franchising Reproductive Health Services. Health Services Research, 39(6 Pt 2): 2053–2080</entry>
</reflist>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
