<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:23:42[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<parlance  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107081177">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<formulation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107069948">
<expressive_style  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107066659">
<header>
<title>Reinventing the wheel</title>
<id>1291336</id>
<revision>
<id>244080876</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T07:03:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Fubar Obfusco</username>
<id>1200</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since May 2008</category>
<category>English idioms</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Anti-patterns</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Mergefrom.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that  be  into this article or section. ()</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations .</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>Reinventing the wheel</b> (aka. <it>"Not built here"</it>) is a phrase that means a generally accepted technique or solution is ignored in favor of a locally invented solution. To "reinvent the wheel" is to duplicate a basic method that has long since been accepted and even taken for granted.</p>
<p>

The inspiration for this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/47563.xml">
idiom</link>atic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/20518.xml">
metaphor</link> lies in the fact that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/33555.xml">
wheel</link> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/53917.xml">
archetype</link> of human ingenuity, both by virtue of the added power and flexibility it affords its users, and also in the ancient origins which allow it to underlie much, if not all, of modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/29816.xml">
technology</link>.  As it is not considered to have operational flaws, an attempt to reinvent it would be pointless and add no value to the object, and would be a waste of time, diverting the investigator's resources from possibly more worthy goals which his or her skills could advance more substantially.</p>
<p>

At the same time, however, "reinventing the wheel" is an important tool in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/228679.xml">
instruction</link> of complex ideas.  Rather than providing students simply with a list of known facts and techniques and expecting them to incorporate these ideas perfectly and rapidly, the instructor instead will build up the material anew, leaving the student to work out those key steps which embody the reasoning characteristic of the field.</p>
<p>

The phrase is sometimes used without derision, especially when the user applies it reflexively, possibly to indicate that although his or her activities might be perceived as merely reinventing the wheel, they actually possess additional value.  This added value may work around <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/803810.xml">
software licensing</link> incompatibilities or around technical limitations present in parts or modules provided by third-parties.  An example would be to implement a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/3268249.xml">
quicksort</link> for a script written in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/9845.xml">
Javascript</link> and destined to be embedded in a web page.  The quicksort algorithm is well known and readily available from <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/106421.xml">
libraries</link></room>
</format>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
</information>
</message>
 for software developers writing general-purpose applications in <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/72038.xml">
C++</link></programming_language>
 or <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
 but Javascript by default provides no such sorting algorithm.  Hence, if a developer wants to use quicksort on his web page, he must "reinvent the wheel" by reimplementing the algorithm.  He could conceivably copy it from another web page but then he could run into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/5278.xml">
copyright</link> and software licensing issues.  Reinventing the wheel in this case provides the missing functionality and also avoids copyright issues.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Related phrases</st>
<p>

"Reinventing the square wheel" is the practice of unnecessarily engineering artifacts that provide functionality already provided by existing standard artifacts (reinventing the wheel) and ending up with a worse result than the standard (a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/742349.xml">
square wheel</link>).  This is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/233956.xml">
anti-pattern</link> which occurs when the engineer is unaware or contemptuous of the standard solution or does not understand the problem or the standard solution sufficiently to avoid problems overcome by the standard.  It is mostly an affliction of inexperienced engineers.</p>
<p>

Many problems contain subtleties which were resolved long ago in mainstream engineering (such as the importance of a wheel's rim being smooth).  Anyone starting from scratch, ignoring the prior art, will naturally face these problems afresh, and to produce a satisfactory result they will have to spend time developing solutions for them (most likely the same solutions that are already well known).  However, when reinventing the wheel is undertaken as a subtask of a bigger engineering project, rather than as a project in its own right hoping to produce a better wheel, the engineer often does not anticipate spending much time on it.  The result is that an underdeveloped, poorly performing version of the wheel is used, when using a standard wheel would have been quicker and easier, and would have given better results.</p>
<p>

Also, "preinventing the wheel", which means to hold off undertaking a task if it is expected to be undertaken at a later date and rolled out. An example would be, "We don't want to preinvent the wheel" when discussing a solution to a problem when it is known that the solution is being developed elsewhere. Referenced in "Change Leadership Project" P Brandt 2003</p>
<p>

"Reinventing the wheel" may be an ironic cliche - it is not clear when the wheel itself was actually invented.  The modern "invention" of wheel might actually be a "re-invention" of an old age invention. Additionally, many different wheels featuring enhancements on existing wheels (such as the many types of available tires) are regularly developed and marketed. The metaphor emphasizes understanding existing solutions, but not necessarily settling for them.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Steve Kemper</link>: <it>A Story of Genius, Innovation, and Grand Ambition</it>, Harper Business, ISBN 0-06-076138-5</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Peter D. Hershock</link>: <it>A Buddhist Response to the Information Age</it>, State University of New York Press, ISBN 0-7914-4232-2</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Peter Brandt</link>: <it> Change Leadership Project</it>, Unpublished 2003</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/1656760.xml">
Custom made</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <entreaty wordnetid="107186828" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="107185325" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/60102.xml">
Not Invented Here</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</request>
</event>
</entreaty>
</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</expressive_style>
</formulation>
</entity>
</parlance>
</article>
