<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:40:25[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Online video analytics</title>
<id>12938501</id>
<revision>
<id>243692868</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T17:22:37Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bluemask</username>
<id>74414</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from September 2008</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
<category>World Wide Web</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Online_video_analytics&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Online+video+analytics%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<it>Online video analytics,</it> also known as web video analytics, is way of measuring what viewers do when they watch an online video. A video is any length of video stream, such as a movie clip, video advertisement, movie trailer, television show or full-length video. Companies that provide web video analytics are able to answer such questions as:
- How long did the viewer watch a particular video?
- Did they pass it along to a friend? embed it in their home page? bounce out as soon as they clicked, play?
- If there was an ad overlay with the video, did they watch it? if so, for how long? Did they click through to complete a sale proposed by the ad?
- Where do the viewers come from that watch videos on a particular site?
These and scores of other questions can be answered with web video analytics.</p>
<p>

Online video is expected to grow at nearly 40% annually through 2011<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, while viewership on traditional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/29831.xml">
television</link> is falling <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.  </p>
<p>

This growing market requires audience information analysis for videos to be monetized through advertisements, much in the way <group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<competition wordnetid="101168569" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/236591.xml">
Nielsen Ratings</link></competition>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</group_action>
 does for traditional television. In May 2008, according to comScore, viewers watched 12 billion videos online <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>
<p>

The most-often recognized leader in the video analysis market is currently <link>
Visible Measures</link>, which offers the most comprehensive platform for understanding how users interact with video content and how that video content spreads online.  Other companies offering related services include firms like Divinity Metrics and Tubemogul.  They distribute videos to the distribution sites, then provide analysis about which sites are most effective in gathering viewers.  They also show where viewership drops off or where most users rewind during the clip, allowing ad placement to be most effective.  </p>
<p>

Online video analytics differs from that for traditional television because you are able to use census-based methods, in contrast to panel-based metrics. Every event that a viewer does while watching a video online can be captured and analyzed, for precise measurement. Reports on usage can show Average Viewing time, Beginning to End Views, and overall Engagement Scores. A leading vendor in this area is GlanceGuide of Palo Alto.</p>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 Reuters <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/internetNews/idUSN2544002420070725?feedType=RSS">
http://www.reuters.com/article/internetNews/idUSN2544002420070725?feedType=RSS</weblink>, Wed Jul 25, 2007 </entry>
<entry id="2">
 David Bauder, Associated Press, May 7, 2007 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4188/is_20070509/ai_n19065572">
http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4188/is_20070509/ai_n19065572</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
 comScore <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.comscore.com/press/release.asp?press=2324">
http://www.comscore.com/press/release.asp?press=2324</weblink>, Jul 14, 2008 </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</bdy>
</article>
