<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:39:33[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<statement  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106722453">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<equation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106669864">
<mathematical_statement  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106732169">
<header>
<title>Parallel mesh generation</title>
<id>13089880</id>
<revision>
<id>239734728</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-20T05:31:41Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DinoBot2</username>
<id>7128788</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Wikify from September 2007</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>Numerical differential equations</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Parallel_mesh_generation&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(September 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Parallel mesh generation</b> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/21506.xml">
numerical analysis</link> is a new research area between the boundaries  of  two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/1181008.xml">
scientific computing</link>  disciplines:  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/176927.xml">
computational geometry</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/145162.xml">
parallel computing</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. Parallel mesh generation methods decompose the original <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/3050716.xml">
mesh generation</link> problem into smaller subproblems which are solved (meshed) in parallel using multiple processors or threads. The existing parallel mesh generation methods can be classified in terms of two basic attributes: (1) the sequential technique used for meshing the individual subproblems and (2) the degree of coupling between the subproblems. One of the challenges in parallel mesh generation is to develop parallel meshing software using off-the-shelf sequential meshing codes.
<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>
<p>

Parallel mesh generation procedures in general decompose the original 2-dimensional (2D) or 3-dimensional  (3D) mesh generation problem into N smaller subproblems which are solved (i.e., meshed) concurrently using P processors or threads<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. The subproblems  can be formulated to be either tightly coupled<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>, partially coupled<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> or even decoupled<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>. The coupling of the subproblems determines the intensity of the communication and the amount/type of synchronization required between the subproblems.</p>
<p>

The challenges in parallel mesh generation methods are: to maintain stability of the parallel mesher (i.e., retain the quality of finite elements generated by state-of-the-art sequential codes) and at the same time  achieve 100% code re-use (i.e., leverage the continuously evolving and fully functional off-the-shelf sequential meshers) without substantial deterioration of the scalability of the parallel mesher.</p>
<p>

There is a difference between parallel mesh generation and parallel triangulation. In parallel triangulation a pre-defined set of points is used to generate in parallel triangles that cover the convex hull of the set of points. A very efficient algorithm for parallel Delaunay triangulations appears in Blelloch et al.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. This algorithm is extended in Clemens and Walkington<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> for parallel mesh generation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Parallel mesh generation software</st>


<p>

While many solvers have been ported to parallel machines, grid generators have left behind. Still the preprocessing step of mesh generation remains a sequential bottleneck in the simulation cycle. That is why the need for developing of stable 3D parallel grid generator is well-justified. Work in this direction is carried out by several institutions <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>. <b>parTgen</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> - partitioner and parallel tetrahedral mesh generator is an example of decoupled method developed and implemented by Evgeny Ivanov et al.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>




<p>

----
Another parallel mesh generator is <b>D3D</b> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> was developed by Daniel Rypl<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> at Czech Technical University in Prague. <b>D3D</b> is a mesh generator capable to discretize in parallel (or sequentially) 3D domains into mixed meshes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Challenges in parallel mesh generation </st>
<p>

It takes about ten to fifteen years to develop the algorithmic and software infrastructure for sequential industrial strength mesh generation libraries. Moreover, improvements in terms of quality, speed, and functionality are open
ended and permanent which makes the task of delivering state-of-the-art parallel mesh generation codes even more difficult.</p>
<p>

An area with immediate high benefits to parallel mesh generation is domain decomposition. The DD problem as it is posed in <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>is still open for 3D geometries and its solution will help to deliver stable and scalable methods that rely on off-the-shelf mesh generation codes for Delaunay and Advancing Front Techniques.</p>
<p>

Finally, a long term investment to parallel mesh generation is to attract the attention of mathematicians with open problems in mesh generation and broader impact in mathematics.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Nikos Chrisochoides, Parallel Mesh Generation, Chapter in Numerical Solution of Partial Differential Equations on Parallel Computers, (Eds. Are  Magnus Bruaset, Aslak Tveito), Springer-Verlag, pp 237-259, 2005.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Nikos Chrisochoides and Demian Nave. Parallel <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../006/9617006.xml">
Delaunay</link> mesh generation kernel. Int. J. Numer. Meth. Engng., 58:161--176, 2003</entry>
<entry id="3">
Lohner, J.Camberos, and M.Marshal. Parallel Unstructured Grid
Generation. Chapter in Unstructured Scientific Computation on Scalable Multiprocessors. (Eds. Piyush Mehrotra and Joel Saltz), pp 31--64, MIT Press, 1990.</entry>
<entry id="4">
H. de Cougny and M.Shephard. Parallel volume meshing using face removals and hierarchical repartitioning. Comp. Meth. Appl. Mech. Engng., 
174(3-4):275--298, 1999.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Andrey Chernikov and Nikos Chrisochoides. Parallel Guaranteed Quality Planar Delaunay  Mesh Refinement Concurrent Point Insertion. SIAM Journal for Scientific Computing, Vol. 28, No. 5, pp 1907-1926, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="6">
J. Galtier and P. L. George. Prepartitioning as a way to mesh 
subdomains in parallel. Special Symposium on Trends in Unstructured Mesh Generation, pp 107--122. ASME/ASCE/SES, 1997.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Leonidas Linardakis and Nikos Chrisochoides. Delaunay Decoupling Method for Parallel  Guaranteed Quality Planar Mesh Generation. SIAM Journal for Scientific Computing, Vol. 27, No. 4, pp 1394-1423, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="8">
G. E. Blelloch, J.C. Hardwick, G.~L. Miller, and D. Talmor, Design and implementation of a practical parallel Delaunay algorithm, Algorithmica, 24 (1999), pp. 243--269.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Clemens Kadow and Noel Walkington. Design of a projection-based parallel Delaunay mesh generation and refinement algorithm. In proceedings of Fourth Symposium on Trends in Unstructured Mesh Generation, 2003.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Fraunhofer Institute for Industrial Mathematics, http://www.itwm.fhg.de</entry>
<entry id="11">
parTgen - partitioner and parallel tetrahedral mesh generator, http://www.itwm.fhg.de/en/hpc__partgen/partgen/</entry>
<entry id="12">
E.G. Ivanov, H. Andrae and A.N. Kudryavtsev, Domain Decomposition Approach for Automatic Parallel Generation of Tetrahedral Grids, International Mathematical Journal Computational Methods in Applied Mathematics, Vol.6(2), 2006, pp. 178--193. </entry>
<entry id="13">
H. Andrae, E. Ivanov, O. Gluchshenko, A. Kudryavtsev, Automatic Parallel Generation of Tetrahedral Grids by Using a Domain Decomposition Approach, Journal of Computational Mathematics and Mathematical Physics, Vol. 48(8), 2008, pp. 1448-1457 </entry>
<entry id="14">
D3D Mesh Generator Web page, http://mech.fsv.cvut.cz/~dr/d3d.html</entry>
<entry id="15">
University Web page of Daniel Rypl, http://mech.fsv.cvut.cz/~dr/</entry>
<entry id="16">
Chrisochoides N., A Survey of Parallel Mesh Generation Methods, Brown University, Providence RI - 2005.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</mathematical_statement>
</equation>
</message>
</statement>
</article>
