<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:45:45[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108058098">
<header>
<title>Coradiant</title>
<id>13096031</id>
<revision>
<id>196659594</id>
<timestamp>2008-03-08T00:59:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Antmusic</username>
<id>2024167</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Companies established in 2000</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Company</name>
<parameters>
<name>
Coradiant, Inc.</name>
<foundation>
2000</foundation>
<location_country>
USA</location_country>
<location_city>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/108055.xml">
Poway, CA</link></location_city>
<type>
Private</type>
<products>
End-User Experience Management</products>
<homepage>
http://www.coradiant.com/</homepage>
<key_people>
Brett Helm (CEO and Chairman)</key_people>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>Coradiant</b> provides End-User Experience Management products which enable organizations to better manage and troubleshoot Web Applications. </p>


<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

Coradiant was founded in 2000 to develop user performance management products to give IT organizations the ability to quickly find and fix web performance problems. Coradiant recognized that monitoring real-users activity on websites was a good way to manage web application performance and developed solutions for End-User Experience Management.</p>
<p>

A June 2007 Forrester Research "Wave" report rated Coradiant as a leader in the Web application performance analysis subsegment and stated that "Coradiant’s End User Experience Monitoring Solution Shines In Web Application Analysis."</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Garbani, Jean-Pierre; Mendel, Thomas Ph.D.; Iqbal, Reedwan, "Coradiant’s End User Experience Monitoring Solution Shines In Web Application Analysis" Forrester Research, Inc., June 21, 2007.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Products </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
TrueSight IM</link> </b> (Incident Management) &mdash; a transparent/secure HW appliance that collects detailed, real-time information on every aspect of the online customer experience and quality from every user.  IT and web operations teams gain complete information used to find and fix web performance problems. TrueSight is delivered as a turn-key, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/4639929.xml">
passive monitoring</link> appliance.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
TrueSight AIM</link></b> (Automated Incident Management):  a transparent/secure HW appliance that enables automated incident management.  TrueSight IM understands hundreds of error conditions.  It automatically converts all user incidents into a summary of those most important to web health, grouped by type, duration, severity, and user impact.   It can then automatically localize web problems, and provide all the tools and detailed data necessary to efficiently root cause and correct them.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
TrueSight BI</link></b> (Business Intelligence): a HW appliance that gathers and transforms user activity collected from one or more TrueSight IM/AIM products to provide comprehensive and detailed analytical reports on end-user service quality.  TrueSight BI combines a leading database with a built-in powerful Business Intelligence (BI) package. Up to 15 months of data can be stored in user, application, and infrastructure performance cubes for turnkey reporting and dashboards. Data can also be easily exported using the turnkey ETL engine to a data warehouse or to individual files for easy access.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Competition </st>

<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/13708079.xml">
Tealeaf</link></company>
 CX Solutions capture every customer's visit with a patented play-back technology to replay and analyze customer behavior.  </p>
<p>

Quest Software Foglight Experience Viewer (from Quest's Xaffire acquisition). Quest's product focuses primarily on visual replay and provides searching capabilities.</p>
<p>

Hewlett-Packard's RUM (from H-P's Mercury Interactive acquisition via Mercury's BeatBox acquisition) captures traffic at the network level.</p>
<p>

Computer Associates (from its Wily acquisition via its TimeStock acquisition) takes a similar approach.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.coradiant.com/">
Coradiant Home Page</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</company>
</article>
