<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:45:34[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<senior_high_school  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108409617">
<header>
<title>New Vista High School</title>
<id>13092714</id>
<revision>
<id>233329415</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-21T14:20:37Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Discospinster</username>
<id>82432</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>High schools in Colorado</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox School2</name>
<parameters>
<mascot>
Phoenix, Aussie Dog</mascot>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://schools.bvsd.org/nvhs/">
New Vista High School</weblink></website>
<state>
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/5399.xml">
Colorado</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</state>
<established>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/34598.xml">
1993</link></established>
<type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/471603.xml">
Public</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/42556.xml">
high school</link></type>
<head_name>
Principal</head_name>
<city>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../341/94341.xml">
Boulder</link></city>
<country>
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
</country>
<school_colors>
black and teal</school_colors>
<name>
New Vista High School</name>
<student_enrollment>
335
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.bvsd.org/scripts/profilepage.asp?numsch310&amp;levelhigh">
http://content.bvsd.org/scripts/profilepage.asp?numsch310&amp;levelhigh</weblink></student_enrollment>
<grades>
9-12</grades>
<head>
Rona Wilensky</head>
</parameters>
</template>


<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>




<sec>
<st>
About New Vista High School</st>
<p>

<b>New Vista</b> is a small school located on the corner of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.bvsd.org/schools_admin/maps/new_vista.gif">
20th and Baseline</weblink> in Boulder Colorado. It was created in 1993 by principal Rona Wilensky, who continues in position as of 2007. New Vista prides itself on its non-traditional format and forward-thinking approach to education.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

New Vista High School opened its doors in the Fall of 1993. </p>
<p>

The 2001 School Accountability Reports issued by the State of Colorado awarded it the second highest performance rating. In the rank ordering of schools, New Vista students scores earned them a 32nd place out of 355 in public high schools.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Academics </st>
<p>

NVHS runs on a quarter system; every nine weeks the schedule changes. There are no Advanced Placement classes, IB Program, or weighted grades. Anything below a B-(80%) is a failing grade. Class subjects are varied, allowing students to learn about things that interest them. New Vista is within close proximity to the University of Colorado and both of the major high schools so students have the option to take classes there if the class doesn't exist at NVHS. Credit is reduced, but accepted, if one receives a C from any of these schools. New Vista is a diverse school; classes are formatted very differently than conventional high schools, are much smaller, approximately 15-30 students per class, and consist of mixed grades.                                          </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Culminating Projects</st>
<p>

Each New Vista student must complete a Culminating Project to graduate.  Students must spend at least 120 hours on a self created project, pursuing a passion, or exploring a new interest.  Every student forms a committee of a younger student, a peer also working on a culminating project, their adviser, a mentor, and an adult who knows them well.  The committee is in place to offer their ideas and thoughts towards creating a successful and enjoyable culminating project. The committee meets during the final year to evaluate the progress a project is making.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Block Schedule</st>
<p>

Yet another unique feature about New Vista is the block schedule. Most students take a total of three or four classes a quarter: AM block, seminar, and PM block or two one hour long PM blocks—along with advisory. AM and PM blocks are worth one credit and seminar classes are worth half a credit. First periods are optional and offer a chance to catch up or get ahead on credit. By allowing students to choose their classes, they determine the difficulty of the next quarter.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Advisory</st>
<p>

Every student at New Vista is assigned to a mixed-grade advisory class; which they attend all four years of their career at New Vista.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Community Gatherings</st>
<p>

Community Gatherings are a weekly, mandatory opportunity for students and teachers to gather as a whole and announce recent/upcoming events such as problems that have recently occurred, programs that are being offered in or around New Vista.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Other Learning Opportunities</st>
<p>

New Vista is unique in the fact that it gives students the chance to explore the community and get credit for their work in out of school activities. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Community Experience</st>
<p>

Every Wednesday, students finish classes at mid-day to serve the community. Students then have the rest of the day to volunteer or help with something they are interested in. CEs vary from an internship with a local architect or artist, to working at a local restaurant or skate shop, to helping in a classroom at another school.  It is up to the student how long he/she would like to continue volunteering.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Workshops</st>
<p>

Some students choose not to participate in Community Experiences but workshops instead. Workshops are classes taught at New Vista by people who are not necessarily teachers.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Learning Unit Contract (LUC)</st>
<p>

New Vista students can earn extra credit for off-campus learning experiences outside the school day and year that are supervised and evaluated by qualified community experts. Examples include: team sports, fitness programs, language study, music, or other private lessons.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Four Days in May</st>
<p>

Every year, for a week in May, students take a break from the regular school curriculum to go out in the community and give back through service learning.  Groups of students, led by staff members, go and volunteer for local non-profit organizations. Four Days in May teaches students leadership skills and provides different ways to get involved in the community.  Projects include: videos for non-profits, maintenance help for seniors, building trails, and working with the GLBTQ (Gay, Lesbian, Bi-sexual, Trans-sexual, and Questioning) group.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Extracurricular activities</st>
<p>

There are many opportunities for extracurricular activities at New Vista, such as clubs and sports. Students are given the chance to go to other schools, such as <link>
The September School</link> to participate in after school activities that they provide.</p>
<p>

There are also activities that New Vista Offers:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Theater</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Restorative Justice</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yearbook</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Equity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Pepquity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 After School Band</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Athletics</st>

<p>

Athletics at New Vista are limited, so many students participate in other school's sports teams such as: wrestling, tennis, cross country, track, football, soccer, and swimming teams. Or they can start a club directed towards a certain sport.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Volleyball</st>
<p>

New Vista has the only co-ed volleyball team in the state. NVHS plays in the 3A and 5A boys league. The team was resurrected in 2001, after a two year hiatus.</p>
<p>

New Vista was the 2007 state champions in 3A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/32558.xml">
volleyball</link></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Clubs</st>
<p>

All clubs at New Vista are formed and organized by students. Students are able to apply for clubs and if enough people are interested in joining, a club will be formed.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bvsd.org/">
BVSD</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://schools.bvsd.org/nvhs/">
New Vista High School</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</senior_high_school>
</article>
