<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:25:49[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Priego de Córdoba</title>
<id>1323169</id>
<revision>
<id>239646929</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-19T20:36:10Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>The Anomebot2</username>
<id>1979668</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Municipalities in Córdoba</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Priego de Córdoba</b> is a town and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/19038.xml">
municipality</link> of southern <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 in the extreme southeastern portion of the province of <link>
Córdoba</link>, near the headwater of the <link>
Guadajoz River</link>, and on the northern slope of the <link>
Sierra de Priego</link>. Pop. (2002) 22,558, in 1900 it was 16,902.<p>

The district abounds in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/5307.xml">
cattle</link> (by 2007 there were almost no cattle in the area) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/50505.xml">
mule</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/13645.xml">
horse</link>s and agricultural products, especially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/32961.xml">
wine</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link> and, according to local people, late <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/23501.xml">
potato</link>es. The local industries also included <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/140990.xml">
tanning</link> and manufactures of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/490147.xml">
esparto</link> fabrics, rugs and cotton goods. The oldest church was built in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/34633.xml">
13th century</link> and subsequently restored; it has a fine chapel. There are ruins of an, originally Moorish, castle (currently (2006) under restoration) having been a fortified city of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/45127.xml">
Moors</link> (with the Hispano-Arabic name Baguh) which was captured by the Christians under Ferdinand III in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/36261.xml">
1225</link>, lost again in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/39967.xml">
1327</link>, and finally retaken in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/39517.xml">
1340</link> by Alfonso XI.</p>
<p>

Some of the best examples of the Spanish Baroque are found in the numerous churches in Priego.
The olive oil from Priego has been given its own denominational tag. The olive oils have recently garnered many of the most prestigious prizes in international competitions.
The first President of the Second Spanish Republic, Niceto Alcala-Zamora, was from Priego.</p>
<p>

Priego is a village found in the 'Ruta de la Califata' (trade route of the Califa).</p>
<p>

The religious brotherhoods of Priego have a long and interesting history, some dating back to before the 1500's. The traditional displays of these brotherhoods in the religious processions of Holy Week (Semana Santa) are renowned for their grandeur and beauty.</p>
<p>

The procession on Holy Thursday (Jueves Santo) of the Brotherhood of the Column (Jesus de la Columna), which is the oldest and most prestigious of the towns brotherhoods, and on Holy Friday (Viernes Santo) the Brotherhood of the Nazarenos, in which the procession is of a hand carried float with Christ carrying the cross. 
The Nazareno is carried from a church in the center of Priego to a mountain top that overlooks Priego known as the Calavario. Once there a priest comes out of the hermitage  there and delivers a benediction. The population holds up pastreys, in the form of roosters or pigs, with a hard boiled egg in the center, known as 'hornazos'. After the benediction it is considered good luck for the coming year to eat the pastrey.</p>
<p>

The oldest section of Priego is its Barrio de la Villa. It is bordered on one side by the town's natural fortress, a high cliff. The alleys that wind through this part of the town are moorish in stle, decorated proudly by the populace with flower pots and religious icons. Some homes retain the ancient tunnel system that went from their cellars (bodegas) to the castle. 
The view from the cliff, known as the "Adarve", is breathtakingly beautiful. It is a favorite subject for paintings. From the "Adarve" one sees an over 180° degree expanse of valley and olive grove speckled mountains known as the "Subetica". </p>


<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>This article incorporates text from the</it> <link>
Encyclopædia Britannica <it>Eleventh Edition''</it></link><it>, a publication now in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link>.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/48361.xml">
Coordinates</link>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stable.toolserver.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Priego_de_C%C3%B3rdoba&amp;params=37_26_N_4_11_W_region:ES_type:city">
37°26′N 4°11′W﻿ / ﻿37.433, -4.183</weblink></p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
