<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:51:34[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>News monitoring</title>
<id>13241675</id>
<revision>
<id>228691816</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-29T22:14:05Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dna13</username>
<id>7558591</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Wikify from September 2007</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>News</category>
<category>Articles to be merged since September 2007</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=News_monitoring&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(September 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Merge-arrow.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrow
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  into . ()</col>
</row>
</table>


<b>News monitoring</b>, or the <b>news monitoring industry</b>, provides government agencies, corporations, public relations professionals, and other organizations access to news information created by the media. Generally monitoring print, broadcast, and internet content for any mention of specific subjects of interest, a news monitoring company will analyze and provide feedback to their client in the form of press clippings, monitoring reports, and media analysis. </p>
<p>

Organizations from the US Government to most of the Fortune 500 companies, and everything in between, use news monitoring' companies to track their presence or the competitors presence in the media. News monitoring clients may also use a news monitoring service to track industry specific trends or legislation. City, State, and Federal agencies use news monitoring services to stay informed in regions they otherwise would not be able to monitor themselves. Some monitoring services specialize in one or more areas of press clipping, TV and radio monitoring, or internet tracking. Media analysis is also offered by the larger news monitoring services.</p>
<p>

The concept of watching media outlet websites using automated technology was pioneered by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.webclipping.com">
WebClipping.com</weblink> in 1998.  Since then, there has been a growing market of companies focused on tracking and monitoring online news, blog and social media content.  As more news content is available online, this has become an increasingly popular solution.</p>
<p>

Industry trade associations include the North American Conference of Press Clipping Services and the International Association of Broadcast Monitors.</p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dna13.com/products/monitor.jsp">
Web-based news monitoring software</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.newsdirectservices.com/">
Example of a television news monitoring company</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.burrellesluce.com/">
Print, web and broadcast news monitoring</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.utahnewsclips.com/">
Broadcast News Tracking &amp; Retrieval</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.webclipping.com">
Internet based news monitoring</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
