<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:47:25[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Conversation Theory</title>
<id>13314050</id>
<revision>
<id>238786358</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-16T11:21:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Nick Green</username>
<id>751036</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cybernetics</category>
<category>Oral communication</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Conversation Theory</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/5904.xml">
cybernetic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/52813.xml">
dialectic</link> framework that offers a scientific theory to explain how interactions lead to "construction of knowledge", or, "knowing": wishing to preserve both the dynamic/kinetic quality, and the necessity for there to be a "knower". <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> This work is proposed by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/4848621.xml">
Gordon Pask</link></educator>
</psychologist>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 in the 1970s.  
<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>
 
Conversation Theory  regards <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/634444.xml">
social system</link>s as symbolic, language-oriented systems where responses depend on one person's interpretation of another person's behavior, and where meanings are agreed through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/228569.xml">
conversation</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> But since meanings are agreed, and the agreements can be illusory and transient, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/26833.xml">
scientific research</link> requires stable reference points in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/682482.xml">
human</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/234240.xml">
transactions</link> to allow for reproducible results. Pask found these points to be the understandings which arise in the conversations between two participating individuals, and which he defined rigorously.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Conversation Theory describes interaction between two or more cognitive systems, such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/205075.xml">
teacher</link> and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/155526.xml">
student</link> or distinct perspectives within one individual, and how they engage in a dialog over a given concept and identify differences in how they understand it. </p>
<p>

Conversation Theory came out of the work of <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/4848621.xml">
Gordon Pask</link></educator>
</psychologist>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 on instructional design and models of individual learning styles. In regard to learning styles, he identified conditions required for concept sharing and described the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/1005416.xml">
learning styles</link> <it>holist</it>, <it>serialist</it>, and their optimal mixture <it>versatile</it>. He proposed a rigorous model of analogy relations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Topics </st>
<p>

Conversation Theory as developed by Pask originated from this cybernetics framework and attempts to explain learning in both living organisms and machines.  The fundamental idea of the theory was that learning occurs through conversations about a subject matter which serves to make knowledge explicit. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Levels of conversation </st>
<p>

Conversations can be conducted at a number of different levels:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Natural language (general discussion)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Object languages (for discussing the subject matter)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Metalanguages (for talking about learning/language) </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Conversation </st>
<p>

Through recursive interactions called "Conversation" their differences may be reduced until agreement--that is, agreement up to a point which Pask called "agreement over an understanding"--may be reached. A residue of the interaction may be captured as an "entailment mesh", an organized and publicly available collection of resultant knowledge, itself a major product of the theory as devotees argue they afford many advantages over <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/29109.xml">
semantic networks</link> and other, less formalized and non-experimentally based "representations of knowledge".</p>

<p>

<table>
<row>
<col>
<image location="left" width="150px" src="deriv.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

The Derivation of a concept from at least two concurrently existing topics or concepts
</caption>
</image>
</col>
<col>
<image width="150px" src="disjunctive.GIF" type="thumb">
<caption>

Alternative derivations may be shown with conjunctive (AND) and disjunctive pathways (OR). This is logically equivalent to T1 = (T2 AND T3) OR (T4 AND T5)
</caption>
</image>
</col>
<col>
<image width="150px" src="cycl.gif" type="thumb">
<caption>

Any two concepts can produce the third, shown as the cyclic form of three concepts --- note that the arrows should show that BOTH T1 and T2 are required to produce T3; similarly for generating T1 or T2 from the others.
</caption>
</image>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<p>

<table>
<row>
<col>
Lastly  a formal analogy is shown where the derivations of the concept triples are indicated. The diamond shape denotes analogy and can exist between any three topics because of the shared meanings and differences.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<image width="150px" src="analogy.png">
<caption>

Analogy
</caption>
</image>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

The relation of one topic to another by an analogy can also be seen as a restriction on a mapping and a distinction to produce the second topic or concept.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Cognitive Reflector </st>
<p>

From Conversation Theory Pask developed what he called a "Cognitive Reflector". This is a virtual machine for selecting and executing concepts or topics from an entailment mesh shared by at least a pair of participants. It features an external modelling facility on which agreement between, say, a teacher and pupil may be shown by reproducing public descriptions of behaviour. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> We see this in essay and report writing or the "practicals" of science teaching. </p>
<p>

Lp was Pask's protolanguage which produced operators like <b>Ap</b> which concurrently executes, <b>Con</b>, the concept of a Topic, <b>T</b> to produce a Description,  <b>D</b>. Thus:</p>
<p>

<b>Ap(Con(T)=&amp;gt; D(T)</b>,  where <b>=&amp;gt;</b> stands for produces. </p>
<p>

A succinct account of these operators is presented in Pask <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Amongst many fascinating insights he points out three indexes are required for concurrent execution, two for parallel and one to designate a serial process. He subsumes this complexity by designating participants A, B etc.</p>
<p>

In Commentary toward the end of Pask <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> he states: </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 The form not the content of the theories (conversation theory and interactions of actors theory) return to and is congruent with the forms of physical theories; such as wave particle duality (the set theoretic unfoldment part of conversation theory is a radiation and its reception is the interpretation by the recipient of the descriptions so exchanged, and vice versa). The particle aspect is the recompilation by the listener of what a speaker is saying. Theories of many universes, one at least for each participant A and one to participant B- are bridged by analogy. As before this is the <it>truth value of any interaction; the metaphor for which is culture itself</it>. 
</indent>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Learning strategies </st>
<p>

In order to facilitate learning, Pask argued that subject matter should be represented in the form of  structures which show what is to be learned.  These structures exist in a variety of different levels depending upon the extent of the relationships displayed.  The critical method of learning according to Conversation Theory is "teachback" in which one person teaches another what they have learned.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> </p>
<p>

Pask identified two different types of learning strategies:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Serialists – Progress through a structure in a sequential fashion </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Holists - Look for higher order relations </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Integrated learning</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 Pask, 1975.</entry>
<entry id="2">
(Pask 1975, 1976)</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thehope.org/convtheo.htm">
Conversation Theory developed by the cybernetician Gordon Pask</weblink> in <it>Realizing the heavenly Jerusalem</it>, Yitzhak I. Hayut, March 1995.</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.cortland.edu/andersmd/learning/Pask.htm">
Conversation Theory - Gordon Pask</weblink> overview from web.cortland.edu.</entry>
<entry id="5">
 See Pask 1975.</entry>
<entry id="6">
 Gordon Pask, <it>Heinz von Foerster's Self-Organisation, the Progenitor of Conversation and Interaction Theories</it>, 1996. </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ranulph Glanville and Karl H. Muller (eds.), <it>Gordon Pask, Philosopher Mechanic- An Introduction to the Cybernetician's Cybernetician</it> edition echoraum 2007 ISBN 9783901941153 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Aleksej Heinze, Chris Procter, Bernard Scott, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://inderscience.metapress.com/media/3duf6u8jtgdqpn9fkp6j/contributions/6/5/8/0/6580506370347k73.pdf">
of conversation theory to underpin blended learning"</weblink>, in: <it>International Journal of Teaching and Case Studies</it> (2007) - Vol. 1, No.1/2  pp. 108 - 120</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 W. R. Klemm, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cvm.tamu.edu/wklemm/Files/ConversationTheory.pdf">
<it>Software Issues for Applying Conversation Theory For Effective Collaboration Via the Internet''</it></weblink>, Manuscript 2002. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gordon Pask, <it>Conversation, cognition and learning</it>. New York: Elsevier, 1975.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gordon Pask, <it>The Cybernetics of Human Learning and Performance</it>, Hutchinson. 1975</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gordon Pask, <it>Conversation Theory, Applications in Education and Epistemology</it>, Elsevier, 1976.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gordon Pask, <it>Heinz von Foerster's Self-Organisation, the Progenitor of Conversation and Interaction Theories</it>, 1996.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.cortland.edu/andersmd/learning/Pask.htm">
Conversation Theory - Gordon Pask</weblink> overview from web.cortland.edu.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pangaro.com/published/cyb-and-con.html">
Cybernetics And Conversation</weblink> by Paul Pangaro, 1994-2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.campus.ncl.ac.uk/unbs/sbi/emad/conversation1.htm">
Conversation Theory: Reasoning about significance and mutuality</weblink> by Mike Martin and John Dobson, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thehope.org/convtheo.htm">
Conversation Theory developed by the cybernetician Gordon Pask </weblink> by Yitzhak I. Hayut-Man ea, 1995.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
