<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:52:04[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Naturalistic Education Theory (NET)</title>
<id>13476571</id>
<revision>
<id>176640415</id>
<timestamp>2007-12-08T21:38:59Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Fabrictramp</username>
<id>1997572</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Education theory</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Naturalistic Education Theory (NET)</b> is a strategy to develop an <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/15201.xml">
interdisciplinary</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</field>
</region>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/479983.xml">
curriculum</link> in the sciences that is a developmentally-appropriate, pedagogical guide for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/9251.xml">
engineering</link> and assessing the construction of a horizontally and vertically aligned and integrated concept sequence.<p>

NET proposes that instruction be based on the understandings of the physical mechanisms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/3717.xml">
the brain</link>. It is a natural curriculum sequencing theory, historically developed, that infers that information consists of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/3365.xml">
byte</link>s which should be arranged and taught in the same manner in which they were originally discovered, disregarding artificial categorization into traditional academic disciplines. The historical-based sequence sets up an interdisciplinary learning spiral around the continuity of information bytes and their systematic linking together, web-style, for a meaningful, four-dimensional concept map structure with continuous associations. This instructional process produces a mental construct fueled by natural curiosity through a developmentally-based need to know. The structure and functional relationship of the resulting curriculum and instruction flows naturally as if the discoveries were their own <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/1170.xml">
architect</link>s and their revelation engineered by their own processes of evolution.</p>
<p>

The NET provides an integrated, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/206358.xml">
holistic</link> explanation of the research, filing, retrieval and processing mechanisms of the brain insofar as they relate to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/419686.xml">
pedagogy</link>. Based on mechanistic premises, it provides a theoretical foundation on which sound instructional engineering can begin.</p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Journal of Thought</it>, Volume 31, Number 2, pp. 85-96, 1996.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>http://www.umsl.edu/~sep/net.htm''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
