<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:27:47[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<substance  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100019613">
<part  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113809207">
<material  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114580897">
<header>
<title>Oil pastel</title>
<id>1356108</id>
<revision>
<id>242944504</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-04T11:38:05Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>RussBot</username>
<id>279219</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Art materials</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Oil pastel</b> (also called <b>wax oil crayon</b>) is a painting and drawing medium with characteristics similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/24533.xml">
pastel</link>s and wax <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/46415.xml">
crayon</link>s. Unlike "soft" or "French" pastel sticks, which are made with a gum or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/3572030.xml">
methyl cellulose</link> binder, oil pastels consist of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/49598.xml">
pigment</link> mixed with a non-drying oil and wax binder. The surface of an oil pastel painting is therefore less powdery, but more difficult to protect with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/155449.xml">
fixative</link>. 
<sec>
<st>
Use</st>
<p>

Oil pastels can be used directly in Darcy form; when done lightly, the resulting effects are similar to pastel chalks. Heavy build-ups can create an almost <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/171211.xml">
impasto</link> effect. Once applied to a surface, the oil pastel pigment can be manipulated with a brush moistened in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/869868.xml">
white spirit</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/151183.xml">
turpentine</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/295711.xml">
linseed oil</link>, or another type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/192331.xml">
vegetable oil</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/37431.xml">
solvent</link>. Alternatively, the drawing surface can be oiled before drawing or the pastel itself can be dipped in oil. It should be noted that some of these solvents pose serious health concerns. </p>
<p>

Oil pastels are considered a fast medium because they are easy to paint with and convenient to carry; for this reason they are often used for sketching, but can also be used for sustained works. Because oil pastels never dry out completely, they need to be protected somehow, often by applying a special <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/155449.xml">
fixative</link> to the painting or placing the painting in a sleeve and then inside a frame. There are some known <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/482602.xml">
durability</link> problems: firstly, as the oil doesn't dry it keeps permeating the paper. This process degrades both the paper and the colour layer as it reduces the flexibility of the latter. 
<image location="left" width="250px" src="1_015.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

An oil pastel drawing by <link>
Arthur Chan</link>
</caption>
</image>
 A second problem is that the stearic acid makes the paper brittle. Lastly both the stearic acid and the wax will be prone to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/1378800.xml">
efflorescence</link> or "wax bloom", the building-up of fatty acids and wax on the surface into an opaque white layer. This is easily made transparent again by gentle polishing with a woolen cloth; but the three effects together result in a colour and contrast layer consisting mainly of brittle stearic acid on top of brittle paper, a combination that will crumble easily. A long term concern is simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/10303.xml">
evaporation</link>: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/542488.xml">
palmitic acid</link> is often present and half of it will have evaporated within 40 years; within 140 years half of the stearic acid will have disappeared. Impregnation of the entire art work by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/43536.xml">
beeswax</link> has been evaluated as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
conservation</link> measure.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Surface and techniques</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Example_Scraping_Oil_pastel.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

An example of the <it>scraping down</it> technique.
</caption>
</image>
The surface chosen for oil pastels can have a very dramatic effect on the final painting. Paper is a common surface but this medium can be used on other surfaces including wood, metal, hardboard (often known as "masonite", a defunct namebrand), canvas and glass. Many companies make papers specifically for pastels that are suitable for use with oil pastels.</p>
<p>

Building up layers of color with the oil pastel, called <it><link>
layering</link></it>, is a very common technique. Other techniques include <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/960256.xml">
underpainting</link></it> and <it>scraping down</it> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/1990690.xml">
sgraffito</link>. Turpentine, or similar liquids such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/2937253.xml">
mineral spirits</link>, are often used as a blending tool to create a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/33813.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Painting%22])">
wash</link> effect similar to some watercolor paintings.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Brands</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Blended_Oil_pastel.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A blended picture using mineral spirits and oil pastels.
</caption>
</image>
There are a number of types of oil pastels, each of which can be classified as either <it>scholastic</it>, <it>student</it> or <it>professional</it> grade.</p>
<p>

<it>Scholastic grade</it>, for example the Loew Cornell brand, is the lowest grade: generally the oil pastels are harder.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

http://www.oilpastelsociety.com/</p>
<p>

http://www.studioarts.co.uk/links/hintsandtips/pastelsinformationhintsandtips.htm</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Elliot, John.  <it>Oil Pastel: for the Serious Beginner,</it> Watson-Guptill Publications, 2002. ISBN 0-8230-3311-2.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oilpastelsociety.com/">
The Oil Pastel Society</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://palimpsest.stanford.edu/waac/wn/wn21/wn21-1/wn21-106.html for a discussion of the evaporation and efflorescence.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wetcanvas.com/forums/forumdisplay.php?s=&amp;forumid=390">
 WetCanvas! Oil Pastel Channel Forums</weblink></entry>
</list>

</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</material>
</part>
</substance>
</article>
