<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:54:34[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<school  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108276720">
<header>
<title>Canberra Secondary School</title>
<id>13562686</id>
<revision>
<id>240845012</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-25T06:58:11Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Xwingfighter2002</username>
<id>1423512</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Secondary schools in Singapore</category>
<category>Sembawang</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Singapore School</name>
<parameters>

<image width="150px" src="">

</image>
<principal>
Mr Tan Keng Joo</principal>
<school_code>
3621</school_code>
<session>
Single session</session>
<name>
Canberra Secondary School</name>
<established>
January <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link></established>
<enrollment>
??</enrollment>
<city_town>
<site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/651591.xml">
Sembawang</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</region>
</site>
</city_town>
<motto>
Challenge, Conquer, Contribute</motto>
<type>
Government School</type>
<homepage>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.canberrasec.net">
Canberra Sec Homepage</weblink></homepage>
<colours>
Blue, Green, Red</colours>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>Canberra Secondary School</b> (Abbreviation: CSS) is a government <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/554992.xml">
secondary school</link> in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/651591.xml">
Sembawang</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</region>
</site>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/27318.xml">
Singapore</link></country>
. The school was established in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link> and it is located at 51 <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/651591.xml">
Sembawang</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</region>
</site>
 Road.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Canberra Secondary was among the 13 new secondary schools which opened on 3 January 2000 with Mr Puvan Ariaratnam as the pioneer principal. The school was housed in <link>
Sembawang Secondary School</link>'s premises at Sembawang Crescent before it moved to its own school at 51 Sembawang Road in June 2000. The astute principal, Mr. Puvan Ariaratnam, has guided the school towards carving a niche of excellence in Information Technology (IT) and multimedia which is pervasive in the school's distinctive educational strategies and infrastructure. Before his appointment to the school, he taught in a junior college, was the Vice-Principal of a secondary school and also served stints in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Ministry of Education. He has been instrumental in the rise of Canberra’s prominence in its initial years of administration. He was succeeded by Mr Tan Keng Joo in 2006 who is currently the prime mover for the school's excellence.</p>
<p>

The school gain popularity in various programs but notably in Video Production. The school had a CCA club call The Arts and Innovation Club or AI for short. It was run by Mr. Adrian Lim who trained, supervised and nurtured a group of dedicated students to conceive, produce and execute video projects. They participated in the Schools Video Awards from 2000 to 2005 winning a record of 4 Gold, 1 platinum and 1 Silver award. They also swept awards at the Panasonic KWN competition and represented Singapore in the world competition on august 2005 coming in third place with the best award for news presentation, a feat that has yet to be surpassed.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mission and Vision</st>

<p>

<b>Mission</b>:</p>
<p>

Inspiring Canberrans to <it>challenge</it> their potential, <it>conquer</it> their aspirations and <it>contribute</it> to society</p>
<p>

<b>Vision</b>:</p>
<p>

A global institution of learning</p>

<p>

<b>School Values</b></p>
<p>

Living with Integrity,</p>
<p>

Learning with Passion,</p>
<p>

Serving with Distinction.</p>

<p>

<b>Strategic Thrust</b></p>
<p>

Inspiring Passionate Learners</p>
<p>

Developing Exemplary Learners</p>
<p>

Building an Immersive Community</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
School Identity</st>

<p>

<b>School Logo</b></p>
<p>

The school logo consists of the 3 Cs:-
Challenge, Conquer and Contribute</p>
<p>

There's also the letter 'i' which stands for Information Technology and Innovation (being a millennium school).</p>
<p>

The pupil (red dot) is going through different paths (3 Cs) to reach for global achievement (green dot).</p>

<p>

<b>School Song</b></p>
<p>

A new day brings us faith to face the challenge</p>
<p>

Let the seeds of knowledge set our minds aglow</p>
<p>

A new day brings us strength to persevere</p>
<p>

Let the will to give show our hearts of gold</p>
<p>

We will challenge conquer and contribute</p>
<p>

with our thoughts and actions we will reach our goals</p>
<p>

The hopes and future are in our hands</p>
<p>

we will never stop aspiring never stop believing</p>
<p>

For we take pride in Canberra Secondary School</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
School Achievements</st>

<ss2>
<st>
School Awards</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

CHERISH Award ['''Gold'''] (2001 – 2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

CHERISH Award ['''Platinum'''] (2005 – 2007)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sustained Achievement Award [Physical Fitness] (2003- 2006)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Academic Value-Added Achievement Award(2005)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Green Audit Award</b> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

2002              - <b>Hibiscus</b></p>
<p>

2003              - <b>Hibiscus</b></p>
<p>

2004              - <b>Orchid</b></p>
<p>

2005 – 2007       - <b>Lotus</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

People Developer Standard (2005)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

IT Incubator School Award (2005)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

National Inter School new Media Challenge- <b>Third</b> [Secondary School Category] (2005)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

National Inter School new Media Challenge- <b>Champions</b> [Secondary School Category] (2006)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

COMPASS PARTNERS ['''Merit Award''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Singapore Family Award [MCYS, SNEF]</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

----</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
CCA Achievements</st>
<p>

<b>Uniform groups</b></p>
<p>

<b>2002</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

St John Ambulance Brigade ['''Silver Award''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2004</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NCC ['''Bronze Award''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NPCC ['''Bronze Award''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

St John Ambulance Brigade ['''Silver''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2005</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NCC Girls ['''Silver Award''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NCC Boys ['''Bronze Award''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NPCC ['''Silver Award''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

St John ['''Gold Award''']</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<b>2006</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NPCC ['''Silver Award''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2007</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NPCC ['''Gold Award''']</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<b>Clubs and Media</b></p>
<p>

<b>2001</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

School Video Award ['''Gold''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2002</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

School Video Award ['''Gold''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2003</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

School Video Award ['''Platinum''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2004</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Animania 2004 Computer 3D Animation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

School Video Award ['''Gold &amp; Merit''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYFC Inter School Aeromodelling Competition ['''Champions''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kids Witness News (Singapore)  -['''Champions''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2005</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

School Video Award ['''Gold''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYFC Inter School Aeromodelling Competition ['''Champions''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kids Witness News (South East Asia)-['''Champions''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kids Witness News (World Championships)- ['''3rd place''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2005 – 2007</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

“Elementz” National Science Competition ['''Bronze''']</entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

<b>Performing Arts</b></p>
<p>

<b>2001</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Drama ['''Bronze''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2002</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Drama ['''Bronze''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2003</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Modern Dance ['''Silver''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2005</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Concert Band ['''Bronze''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Malay Dance ['''Silver''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Modern Dance ['''Bronze''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Drama ['''Bronze''']</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>2007</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Malay Dance ['''Silver''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Concert Band ['''Bronze''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Modern Dance ['''Bronze''']</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SYF Guzheng ['''Bronze''']</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Achievements by Teaching Staff</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mr. S.B. Sivaganesh was crowned the Singapore's Brainiest Teacher in 2003 in a Television game show.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ms. Joyce Lee was awarded the Outstanding History Teacher Award in 2005.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Internal School Programmes</st>

<p>

<b>Academic</b></p>
<p>

<b>Own Your Learning Programme (OYL)</b> is carried out to acquire students with a motivational, good studying practice towards a results-oriented goal. Personal reflections are carried out weekly to monitor their own progress with the guidance of their home-tutors in ensuring every day of the week has been effectively utilized. In addition, students are facilitated with useful advice on their multi-disciplinary and inter-personal conduct towards school-life balance. </p>
<p>

<b>Excellence Programme</b> is a preparatory after-school program for the Singapore Cambridge (UCLES) N/O-Levels, catering to upper secondary students with the agenda of covering the topics in the syllabus at an accelerated pace and developing their content knowledge and relevant skills. The program is integral in the curriculum.  The degree of flexibility of the program lies in the choice and teaching style of the teachers whereby various needs of most students has to be fulfilled. This was inaugurated in the academic year of 2007. The 'O' level results proved the effectiveness of this system with the proliferation of more students with better scores and eligibility for admission into Junior College.</p>
<p>

<b>Non-academic</b></p>
<p>

Apart from the Co-curricular Activities, the students, especially student leaders, are actively involved in activities leadership camps and internal school activities organized by the student councilors. Sports and Arts Festival are held yearly at the CCAB where sports tournament are held annually. These efforts constantly seek to foster a vibrant environment and enthusiastic spirit  within the students. Successes of these activities are indicated in the proliferation of student participation. In the long run, the extrinsic nature of the activities has became an intrinsic part in the student population - worthy of mention would be the popular Ultimate Frisbee culture in the school. </p>

<p>

<b>Winning HEARTS</b></p>
<p>

This programme is inaugurated by the Craft and Technology (C&amp;T) department working on a joint service project with the Handicaps Welfare Association (HWA) which involved upper secondary Home Economics (HE), Art (AR) Design and Technology (T) pupils. The initials of these three subjects, when joined together, form the word, “HEART”, thus the project name, “Winning Hearts” whereby we inspire to win hearts, as a team.</p>
<p>

It serves to infuse students’ project assignments into an Integrated Project Work (IPW) for the department. It also provides opportunities for pupils to undergo experiential learning and provides real-life situations for them to work on in their coursework. Pupils can also help to improve the quality of the lives of the handicapped. As such, this collaboration can be deemed as a community involvement project whereby the students undergo holistic service learning.</p>

<p>

<b>Exchange Programmes</b></p>
<p>

Global Canberrans Programme</p>
<p>

The school believes in providing a holistic education for pupils and this is evident in our holistic character development that builds our pupils’ character. In line with the school’s vision of “A Global Institution of Learning”, the pupils are given every opportunity to engage in learning with the community as well as collaboration with local and international institutions. This is to enable students to be creative and innovative thinkers, ready to face the challenges and demands of the 21st century. As part of the school's academic and character development, Global Canberrans Programme was initiated for pupils to facilitate this internationalisation process. The objectives of this programme are to:</p>
<p>

1. develop pupils to be culturally savvy;
2. expose pupils to the world and sensitive them to the place of Singapore in relation to its global context; and
3. deepen pupils’ commitment and rootedness to Singapore. </p>
<p>

For this year, the school has planned a list of overseas learning programmes to cater to the different needs of our students. The following are the Global Canberrans programmes being planned for end-Oct/Nov timeframe.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Beijing No.80 High School - Beijing, China</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Srinagarindra the Princess Mother School - Chiang Mai, Thailand</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ITAPON Foundation - Nongwai Village, Chiang Mai,Thailand</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Prem Centre, Thailand - Chiang Mai, Thailand</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Olympic Education Programme - Beijing, China</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Publishing</st>
<p>

Canberra Secondary School also published it's inaugural issue of yearbook on Year 2008. The yearbook contained some of the school's achievements and interesting happenings, it was also made mandatory for all students including graduates to purchase it. The yearbook was only given to the school graduating year of 2007</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.canberrasec.net">
Official site</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</school>
</article>
