<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:04:31[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<conveyance  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103100490">
<vessel  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104530566">
<craft  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103125870">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<vehicle  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104524313">
<boat  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="102858304">
<header>
<title>Similitude of ship models</title>
<id>13685099</id>
<revision>
<id>211112914</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-08T21:00:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Thijs!bot</username>
<id>1392310</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>hydraulic engineering</category>
<category>model boats</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="Captvision.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Captain's view from the bridge of a <conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<vessel wordnetid="104530566" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<craft wordnetid="103125870" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<boat wordnetid="102858304" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/13684522.xml">
Port Revel</link></boat>
</vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</building>
</craft>
</structure>
</vessel>
</conveyance>
 supertanker model
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Tugindirect.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Emergency stop of a supertanker model with an escort tug
</caption>
</image>


<sec>
<st>
 Manned models </st>
<p>

Many research workers, hydraulics specialists and engineers have used scale models for over a century, in particular in towing tanks. Manned models are small scale <conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<vessel wordnetid="104530566" confidence="0.8">
<craft wordnetid="103125870" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<boat wordnetid="102858304" confidence="0.8">
<link>
models</link></boat>
</vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</craft>
</vessel>
</conveyance>
 that can carry and be handled by at least one person on an open expanse of water. They must behave just like real ships, giving the shiphandler the same sensations. Physical conditions such as wind, currents, waves, water depths, channels and berths must be reproduced realistically.</p>
<p>

Manned models are used for research (e.g. ship behaviour), engineering (e.g. port layout) and for training in shiphandling (e.g. maritime pilots, masters and officers). They are usually at 1:25 scale.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Similitude of manned models </st>
<p>

<conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<vessel wordnetid="104530566" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<craft wordnetid="103125870" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<boat wordnetid="102858304" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Port Revel</link></boat>
</vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</building>
</craft>
</structure>
</vessel>
</conveyance>
 has chosen to apply the similitude law of <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<architect wordnetid="109805475" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link>
William Froude</link></associate>
</creator>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</engineer>
</person>
</architect>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 (1810-1879) for its manned models. This means that gravity is considered to be preponderant over the other forces acting on the hull (viscosity, capillarity, cavitation, compressibility, etc.).</p>
<p>

The different aspects of similitude may thus be defined as follows:</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Physical similitude </st>
<p>

<b>Similitude of shape:</b> The model has exactly the same geometric shape as the real ship. This means that all the dimensions of the real ship are divided by the same factor, the scale factor. The designers of Port Revel chose a scale of 1:25, so:</p>
<p>

S(L) = 25</p>
<p>

In this similitude, the proportions are kept (the ratios between the various dimensions of the ship are identical). This is also the case with the block coefficient. Furthermore, the angles are a length ratio, so they are also identical to the original ones. The scale factors of the areas and volumes are deduced from this, i.e.:</p>
<p>

S2(L) =  252 = 625</p>
<p>

S3(L) =  253 = 15 625</p>
<p>

<b>Similitude of mass:</b> The model used for shiphandling training must not only resemble the original but also move in the same way as the original when subjected to similar forces. Moreover, the density of the lake water is almost the same as the density of sea water. Consequently, the scale factor for the mass and displacement is the same as that for the volumes, i.e.:</p>
<p>

S(M) = S3(L)  =  253 = 15 625</p>
<p>

<b>Similitude of forces:</b> If the external forces on the model are in similitude, like the shapes, masses and inertia, the model's movement will be in similitude. It can thus be shown that the forces must be at the same scale as the masses and weights, so:</p>
<p>

S(F) =  S(M) =  253 = 15 625</p>
<p>

<b>Similitude of time:</b> In agreement with <amount wordnetid="105107765" confidence="0.8">
<magnitude wordnetid="105090441" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<number wordnetid="105121418" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/395167.xml">
Froude</link></number>
</property>
</magnitude>
</amount>
's law, the time scale is the square root of the length scale, so:</p>
<p>

S(T) =  S1/2(L) =   sqrt(25)  =  5</p>
<p>

<b>Similitude of power:</b> Similarly, it can be shown that:</p>
<p>

S(P) =  S7/2(L) =  257/2 = 78 125</p>
<p>

In conclusion, by choosing a scale of 1:25 for the lengths and by complying with Froude's law, the engineers at Sogreah – Port Revel built models 25 times smaller, operating 5 times more slowly, but as the distances are 25 times less, things occur 5 times faster. The ships are 78125 times less powerful.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Similitude of manoeuvres </st>
<p>
 
While the models must be in correct similitude, this is not enough. Other factors can affect the correct reproduction of the manoeuvres, such as the field of vision, on-board equipment and wind.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 First, manoeuvres on a model require the same pilot's orders as those on a real ship. The only difference is that they are executed five times faster on the model, so there is no time to discuss them. In fact, the rate of operation is such that the captain and helmsman swap roles every hour to avoid fatigue. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The captain's position gives him a true field of vision from the bridge. He gives his orders to the helmsman, who is seated in front of him and operates the wheel and engine.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Control panels show the usual information (engine speed, rudder angle, heading, log, wind speed and direction, shackles of chain lowered). This information is shown in real-life values to help the trainee forget as far as possible that he is on a scale model.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The ships are fitted with bow and stern thrusters and perfectly operational anchors. They behave like real ships from this point of view as well.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tugs are under the captain's orders via remote control, and are handled by a real tug captain.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 As far as the wind is concerned, it should be recalled that as the speed scale factor is 1 in 5, a wind of 10 knots on the lake is equivalent to a 50 knot squall in reality. Ripples on the surface of the water and the movement of leaves on the trees are therefore unreliable indicators. The wind and ship speeds displayed on the control panel are therefore very important for trainees. However, the lake is situated in a forest in a region with little wind, so that uncontrollable wind effects are minimised.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<it>40 years' experience have shown that students quickly learn how to control the models just as they do the real ships that they are used to manoeuvring.</it></p>
<p>

Those who have trained on both claim that scale models are complementary to electronic simulators. While manoeuvres with currents, waves, tugs, anchors, bank effects, etc. are reproduced more accurately on scale models, numerical simulators are more realistic when it comes to the bridge environment.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dominic Reeve et al. (2004) - Coastal engineering processes-Theory and design practice (pp300-310)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Steven A. Hughes (1993) - Physical models and laboratory techniques in coastal engineering.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rui Martins (Lisboa, 1988) - Recent advances in hydraulic physical modelling.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Robert A. Dalrymple (1985) - Physical modelling in coastal engineering.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 US Bureau of Reclamation (1981) - Hydraulic laboratory techniques (pp37-55)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.fr/books?id=wFKUcovQnt4C&amp;pg=PA523&amp;dq=similitude+froude+maritime&amp;sig=5ok3a0il-RebYFy0QeEYacWVsT8#PPA523,M1">
Google Books</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.fr/books?id=1khslZ-jbgEC&amp;pg=PA22&amp;dq=similitude+froude+maritime&amp;sig=u99nNsDiBmPh48VHzLY_9_wazts">
Google Books</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.fr/books?id=3OaD5V5wVYsC&amp;pg=PA300&amp;dq=SCALE+MODEL+coastal&amp;sig=b3qcox5SuHljBbJ7fbJkq_10w_M#PPA300,M1">
Google Books</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.portrevel.com/">
Port Revel</weblink> website</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.afcan.org/dossiers_techniques/port_revel2_gb.html">
AFCAN</weblink> website</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marine-marchande.net/groupe%20mar-mar/Documents/F.Massard/Port-Revel_Marine-marchande/Port-Revel_GB_1_Marine-marchande.htm">
Marine-Marchande.net</weblink> website</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</boat>
</vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</craft>
</vessel>
</conveyance>
</article>
