<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:10:08[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108058098">
<header>
<title>Nielsen Online</title>
<id>13757830</id>
<revision>
<id>242465972</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T10:29:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Marketing research companies of the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Company</name>
<parameters>
<location>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/645042.xml">
New York, New York</link></location>
<company_logo>
<image width="150px" src="Nielsen_Online_logo.gif">
<caption>

Nielsen Online logo.gif
</caption>
</image>
</company_logo>
<company_name>
Nielsen Online</company_name>
<company_type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/1499655.xml">
Private</link></company_type>
<foundation>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link></foundation>
<homepage>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nielsen-online.com/">
www.nielsen-online.com</weblink></homepage>
<key_people>
Itzhak Fisher</key_people>
</parameters>
</template>


Nielsen Online, a service of The <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/1074435.xml">
Nielsen Company</link></company>
, provides measurement and analysis of online audiences, advertising, video, consumer-generated media, word of mouth, commerce and consumer behavior. Previously a majority investor in both companies, Nielsen purchased NetRatings and BuzzMetrics in the spring of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>, combining them to form Nielsen Online. Outside of the U.S., Nielsen Online operates in 16 countries across Europe, Latin America and Asia Pacific.
<sec>
<st>
Products</st>
<p>

Products include: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NetView: An Internet audience measurement service that provides measurement and demographic data on Internet audiences. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

AdRelevance: A service that captures advertising activity across all major industries, channels and ad formats and across most ad types, including all major forms of rich media, on the Web. The service also contains specific ad buyer contacts, and rate card information.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

@Plan: A target-marketing platform for Internet media planning, buying and selling. It reports demographics, in-depth lifestyle and brand preference data. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

VideoCensus: Audience measurement and analysis of online video usage.   </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SiteCensus: A site-centric reporting system uses server-side-visit reports. It provides media companies and publishers third-party measurement for Web site analysis, newsletter and email conversion tracking, ad and keyword measurement and audience assessment. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Market Intelligence: Census-based measurement of audited Web sites within specific markets. The service provides business effectiveness metrics, including unique browsers, page impressions, frequency and session duration.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

BuzzMetrics: A service that helps companies measure, analyze and leverage the power of online consumers who share experiences, advice, opinions on everything from corporate crises to customer service and product performance. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

BuzzTracker: Ongoing tracking studies to help clients understand the online conversation around a brand, issue, campaign, category, event or influence.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

BuzzAudit: A study to deliver analysis and insight into online discussion related to a specific brand, issue, campaign, category, event or influence. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Buzz ThreatTracker: A text-mining technology that captures blog, message board, online forums and other social media venues to help clients identify and analyze threats to brand equity and corporate reputation. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Brand Association Map: A text analysis tool that provides visualization of how consumers talk about a brand or issue in unaided conversations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Research and Analytics: Custom client work based on client needs and using Nielsen Online’s data, analytics and vertical intelligence.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Syndicated Studies include measurement and analysis of Internet activity – including audiences, advertising, video and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/2678120.xml">
CGM</link> – around major events and topical issues including the <playoff wordnetid="107465290" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/27718.xml">
Super Bowl</link></psychological_feature>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</playoff>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/22576.xml">
Olympics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
Nutrition</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/18413531.xml">
Sustainability</link>. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

MegaPanel®:  A market research solution based on a sample of more than 500,000 Internet users measured worldwide, offering insight into Web user behavior. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Homescan Online, in partnership with Nielsen’s, measures both consumers’ offline purchasing behavior and online surfing activity.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Digital Strategic Services Delivers consulting and advisory services.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nielsen-online.com/">
Nielsen Online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nielsen-netratings.com/">
Nielsen//NetRatings</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nielsenbuzzmetrics.com/">
Nielsen BuzzMetrics</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</company>
</article>
