<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:07:45[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<school  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276720">
<public_school  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108410282">
<educational_institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276342">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>The Grange P-12 College</title>
<id>13805229</id>
<revision>
<id>243404793</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T11:23:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Wongm</username>
<id>245841</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Schools in Wyndham</category>
<category>Public schools in Victoria (Australia)</category>
<category>High schools in Victoria (Australia)</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>The Grange P-12 College</b> is a Prep to Year 12 government school located in the outer western suburb of <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/17306237.xml">
Melbourne</link></site>
, Australia, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/615317.xml">
Hoppers Crossing</link>. <p>

The Grange P-12 College has a student population of about 1400, offering a curriculum for years P-12 split over two campuses, Callistemon (P-6) and Deloraine (7-12). Both the <qualification wordnetid="104717139" confidence="0.8">
<fitness wordnetid="104716864" confidence="0.8">
<suitability wordnetid="104715487" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/399324.xml">
Victorian Certificate of Education</link></suitability>
</fitness>
</qualification>
 (VCE) and the <qualification wordnetid="104717139" confidence="0.8">
<fitness wordnetid="104716864" confidence="0.8">
<suitability wordnetid="104715487" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/6122857.xml">
Victorian Certificate of Applied Learning</link></suitability>
</fitness>
</qualification>
 (VCAL) programme are offered to students in years 11 and 12. The Secondary campus (Deloraine) is split into two other subsections, Middle School and Senior School, though both sections are integrated into the one campus.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Facilities </st>
<p>

The Grange provides an enriching education that commences with preps and continues through the secondary years to VCE.  The continuity of curriculum and a seamless transition through primary to secondary years benefits the students both academically and socially.  The two campus structure provides an intimacy which allows all students and staff to know each other.  This creates a sense of belonging and community, one which empowers the entire school.</p>
<p>

The Primary Campus in Callistemon Drive provides a secure, easily supervised and welcoming environment for the Primary students.  Children are kept fully engaged and challenged in wonderfully bright and stimulating learning areas with classes led by a young and effervescent team of teaching professionals.</p>
<p>

The Secondary Campus in Deloraine Drive provides a superbly resourced and mature learning environment. It extends the experiences of Junior School in a positive educational climate which encourages a spirit of enquiry and a life long love of learning.</p>
<p>

The academic and co-curricular programs at The Grange are designed to encourage the highest standard of achievement in everything the students undertake.  The friendly and supportive atmosphere which permeates the entire College is underpinned by a strong code of conduct, a distinctive uniform policy, firm structures and clear expectations.</p>
<p>

All teaching and support staff take pride in equipping each boy and girl with the essential skills required for life long learning and the breadth of outlook they will need to be confident of their ability to successfully shape their futures in a rapidly changing world.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thegrange.vic.edu.au">
The Grange P-12 College</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</educational_institution>
</public_school>
</school>
</article>
