<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:29:33[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Mean Shortest Distance</title>
<id>1386416</id>
<revision>
<id>172140477</id>
<timestamp>2007-11-17T20:16:59Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Railwayfan2005</username>
<id>2785623</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>PGP</category>
<category>Cryptographic software</category>
<category>Cryptography</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In statistical analysis of the <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/23080.xml">
PGP</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/38809.xml">
GnuPG</link>/<link>
OpenPGP</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/296356.xml">
Web of trust</link> the <b>mean shortest distance (MSD)</b> is one measurement of how "trusted" a given PGP key is within the "strongly connected" set of PGP keys that make up the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/296356.xml">
Web of trust</link>.<p>

Drew Streib wrote the following in his explanation of keyring analysis<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dtype.org/keyanalyze/explanation.php">
http://dtype.org/keyanalyze/explanation.php</weblink>:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>There are a variety of metrics one could apply to this set, but I've chosen initially to measure the "mean shortest distance" (MSD) to each key. Since every key is reachable from every other in the strong set, it is possible to find out the shortest distance (number of hops) to any given key from any other key. Averaging these distances gives the MSD to that key from every other key in the strong set.</it>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

<it>It is desirable to have as short as possible an MSD to your key, as that means that on average, people can reach your key quickly through signatures, and thus your key is relatively more trusted than a key with a higher MSD.</it>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

<it>NOTE: This does not mean that you should universally trust keys with a low MSD. This is merely a relative measurement for statistical purposes.</it>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

<it>The MSD has the property of being no more than 1 higher than your lowest signature. In the worst case, every key in the strong set could reach you by getting to that key, plus 1 hop to get to you. It also encourages the joining of keys that are separated by great distances in the graph, as it will make you a highway of sorts for shortest paths between keys in those groups. In the end, it encourages an overall tightening of the world graph, shortening distances between key owners. </it>
</indent>

MSD has become a common metric for analysis of sets of PGP keys.  Very often you will see the MSD being calculated for a given subset of keys and compared with the <it>global MSD</it> which generally refers to the keys ranking within one of the larger key analyses of the global <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/296356.xml">
Web of trust</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dtype.org/keyanalyze/explanation.php">
An explanation of keyring analysis</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
