<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:10:21[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Microinsurance scheme</title>
<id>13888203</id>
<revision>
<id>178382321</id>
<timestamp>2007-12-16T22:38:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cerebellum</username>
<id>3381536</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles to be merged since November 2007</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Insurance</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Merge-arrow.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrow
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  into . ()</col>
</row>
</table>

 
A microinsurance scheme is a scheme that uses, among others, an insurance mechanism whose beneficiaries are (at least in part) people excluded from formal social protection schemes, in particular informal economy workers and their families. The scheme differs from others created to provide legal social protection to formal economy workers. Membership is not compulsory (but can be automatic), and members pay, at least in part, the necessary contributions in order to cover benefits. <p>

<b>The expression "microinsurance scheme" designates</b> either the institution that provides insurance (e.g., a health mutual benefit association) or the set of institutions (in the case of linkages) that provide insurance or the insurance service itself provided by an institution that also handles other activities (e.g., a micro-finance institution).</p>
<p>

<b>The use of the mechanism of insurance implies:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Prepayment and resource-pooling: the regular prepayment of contributions (before the insured risks occur) that are pooled together.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Risk-sharing: the pooled contributions are used to pay a financial compensation to</entry>
</list>

those who are affected by predetermined risks, and those who are not exposed to these
risks do not get their contributions back.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Guarantee of coverage: a financial compensation for a number of risks, in line with a pre-defined benefits package.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Microinsurance schemes may cover various risks</b> (health, life, etc.); the most frequent microinsurance products are: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Life microinsurance (and retirement savings plans) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Health microinsurance (hospitalisation, primary health care, maternity, etc.) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Disability microinsurance </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Property microinsurance – assets, livestock, housing </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Crop microinsurance</entry>
</list>
</p>



</bdy>
</article>
