<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:30:21[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Quality-adjusted life years</title>
<id>1393169</id>
<revision>
<id>207421881</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-22T18:57:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mojomama</username>
<id>6785901</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>medical ethics</category>
<category>Health economics</category>
<category>Quality</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Quality-adjusted life years</b>, or <b>QALYs</b>, is a way of measuring <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/7257968.xml">
disease burden</link>, including both the quality and the quantity of life lived, as a means of quantifying in benefit of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medical</link> intervention. The QALY model requires <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/45479.xml">
utility independent</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/432375.xml">
risk neutral</link>, and <link>
constant proportional tradeoff</link> behaviour.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

They are based on the number of years of life that would be added by the intervention. Each year in perfect health is assigned the value of 1.0 down to a value of 0 for death. If the extra years would not be lived in full health, for example if the  patient would lose a limb, or be blind or be confined to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/106369.xml">
wheelchair</link>, then the extra life-years are given a value between 0 and 1 to account for this.</p>
<p>

The meaning and usefulness of QALY is debated. Perfect health is hard, if not impossible, to define. Some argue that there are health states worse than death, and that therefore there should be negative values possible on the health spectrum (indeed, some health economists have incorporated negative values into calculations). Determining the level of health depends on measures that some argue place disproportionate importance on physical pain or disability over mental health. The effects of a patient's health on the quality of life of others - caregivers, family etc. also does not figure into these calculations.</p>
<p>

The "weight" values between 0 and 1 are usually determined by methods such as:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/9528195.xml">
Time-trade-off</link> (TTO) - In this method, respondents are asked to choose between remaining in a state of ill health for a period of time, or being restored to perfect health but having a shorter life expectancy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Standard gamble</link> (SG) - In this method, respondents are asked to choose between remaining in a state of ill health for a period of time, or choosing a medical intervention which has a chance of either restoring them to perfect health, or killing them.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Visual analogue scale</link> (VAS) - In this method, respondents are asked to rate a state of ill health on a scale from 0 to 100, with 0 representing death and 100 representing perfect health. This method has the advantage of being the easiest to ask, but is the most subjective.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Another way of determining the weight associated with a particular health state is to use standard descriptive systems such as the <link>
EuroQol</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/16989012.xml">
EQ-5D</link> questionnaire, which categorise health states according to the following dimensions: mobility, self-care, usual activities (e.g. work, study, homework or leisure activities), pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. </p>
<p>

However, the weight assigned to a particular condition can vary greatly, depending on the population being surveyed. Those who do not suffer from the affliction in question will, on average, overestimate the detrimental effect on quality of life, compared to those who are afflicted. </p>
<p>

QALYs are used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/1393154.xml">
cost-utility analyses</link> to calculate the ratio of cost to QALYs saved for a particular health care intervention. This is then used to allocate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/261925.xml">
healthcare</link> resources, with an intervention with a lower cost to QALY saved ratio being preferred over an intervention with a higher ratio. This method is controversial because it means that some people will not receive treatment as it is calculated that cost of the intervention is not warranted by the benefit to their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/47789.xml">
quality of life</link>. However, its supporters argue that since health care resources are inevitably limited, this method enables them to be allocated in the way that is most beneficial to society.</p>

<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/1393154.xml">
Cost-utility analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/47789.xml">
Quality of life</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/4144577.xml">
Disability-adjusted life years</link> (DALY)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Euroqol</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../341/3992341.xml">
Case Mix Index</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/429680.xml">
NICE</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Pliskin, Shepard and Weinstein (1980, Operations Research)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cearegistry.com">
CEA Registry Website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jr2.ox.ac.uk/bandolier/booth/glossary/QALY.html">
QALY</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.evidence-based-medicine.co.uk/ebmfiles/WhatisaQALY.pdf">
What is a QALY? (Hayward Medical Communications)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.euroqol.org/">
Euroqo</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Problems and solutions in calculating quality-adjusted life</entry>
</list>

years (QALYs)<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=317370&amp;tools=bot">
http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=317370&amp;tools=bot</weblink>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Over-Reliance on QALYs Might Be Dangerous <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.michaelschlander.com/pnp/presentations_en/Schlander-QALY-Overreliance-iHEA-Copenhagen-070709r.pdf">
http://www.michaelschlander.com/pnp/presentations_en/Schlander-QALY-Overreliance-iHEA-Copenhagen-070709r.pdf</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Comparing the incomparable? A systematic review of competing techniques for converting descriptive measures of health status into QALY-weights </entry>
</list>



</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
