<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:30:29[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<disease  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="114070360">
<ailment  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="114055408">
<header>
<title>Baby colic</title>
<id>1402262</id>
<revision>
<id>244233346</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T22:04:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Enviroboy</username>
<id>3689445</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Pediatrics</category>
<category>Ailments of unknown etiology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Disease</name>
<parameters>
<MeshID>
D003085</MeshID>
<eMedicineTopic>
434</eMedicineTopic>
<Name>
Baby colic</Name>
<MedlinePlus>
000978</MedlinePlus>
<ICD10>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/3530366.xml">
R</link><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/classifications/apps/icd/icd10online/?gr10.htm+r104">
10.4</weblink></ICD10>
<Caption>
Crying newborn</Caption>
<eMedicineSubj>
ped</eMedicineSubj>
<Image>
Crying newborn.jpg</Image>
<ICD9>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.icd9data.com/getICD9Code.ashx?icd9789.0">
789.0</weblink></ICD9>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>Infant colic</b> (also known as <b>baby colic</b>, <b>three month colic</b>, and <b>Infantile colic</b>) is a condition in which an otherwise healthy <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/73165.xml">
baby</link> cries or screams frequently and for extended periods without any discernible reason.<p>

The condition typically appears within the first two weeks of life and almost invariably disappears, often very suddenly, before the baby is three to four months old.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> It is more common in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/216631.xml">
bottle-fed</link> babies, but also occurs in <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<right wordnetid="105174653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/19347033.xml">
breast-fed</link></right>
</relationship>
 infants. The crying frequently occurs during a specific period of the day, often in the early evening.</p>
<p>

Since the cause is not conclusively established (see below) and the amount of crying differs between babies, there is no general consensus on the definition of "colic". Having ruled out other causes of crying, a common rule of thumb is to consider a baby "colicky" if it cries intensely more than three days a week, for more than three hours, for more than three weeks in a month.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Causes</st>
<p>

There is no commonly accepted explanation for colic.  Traditionally, colic was ascribed to abdominal pain resulting from trapped gas in the digestive tract. This theory is not yet discredited, and some recent scientific evidence seems to support it, yet it is no longer universally accepted as the general cause.</p>
<p>

There is solid and mounting evidence that the causes are related to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/3135637.xml">
gut flora</link>, from multiple studies which have shown that colicky babies have different gut flora patterns, which includes a lack of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/965861.xml">
Lactobacillus acidophilus</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Some of these studies suggest the administering of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/731740.xml">
probiotic</link>, such as Lactobacillus acidophilus or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/6030185.xml">
Lactobacillus reuteri</link>, will improve the condition.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Probiotics have been shown to improve other conditions associated with colic, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/56873.xml">
lactose intolerance</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/2183811.xml">
necrotizing enterocolitis</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>, and gastric <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/70425.xml">
inflammation</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>  In addition to that probiotics have been shown to generally improve the health of children who take them.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

It is worth noting, probiotics occur naturally in breastmilk and furthermore a breastfed baby and a formula fed baby have very different gut floras.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

Some doctors claim that it is a combination of a baby's sensitive temperament, the environment, and its immature <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../944/21944.xml">
nervous system</link> that makes him/her cry easily and without control. Others believe that it originates in problems in the baby's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/165423.xml">
digestive system</link>, specifically because of the buildup of gas which cannot be released. New studies at the Colic Clinic at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/4157.xml">
Brown University</link></university>
 demonstrate that nearly half of babies with colic have mild <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/196991.xml">
gastroesophageal reflux</link>. Some cases may be the result of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/56873.xml">
lactose intolerance</link> or lactose overload (the latter when accompanied by green stools).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

Recent research raises a number of hypotheses including the onset of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/285157.xml">
melatonin</link> production by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/285152.xml">
pineal gland</link> (which does not begin until 12 weeks of age, about the time colic seems to disappear),<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/56565.xml">
circadian rhythms</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/73298.xml">
smoking</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/146072.xml">
stress</link> of the mother in the third <link>
trimester</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>
<p>

Many parents have also discovered a link between food and colic - and if the child is breastfed, it could include the food ingested by the mother.  Dairy products seem to top the list as possibly problematic.  It has been suggested that the mother eliminate all sources of dairy from her diet for a week and note any changes in her baby's condition. If it is dairy (or another, less common food relation such as wheat, acid based foods, etc), it will be clearly evidenced within a week.  Mothers then can choose to add back to their diets small samples of the suspected offending food a little bit at a time, and note if there are any unfavorable symptoms that reappear in the baby - and go from there.  Some babies can tolerate absolutely no dairy (including whey, lactose, etc) - some only are bothered by straight and large concentrations of dairy - such as milk, cheese, etc.  The only way to determine this is on an individual basis with the process of elimination and then eventual retrying as the baby ages.  Most will begin to become much more tolerant of mother's diet by about 3 months - but some can continue with problems for much longer.</p>
<p>

Because of the links between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/18333977.xml">
prenatal stress</link>, birth trauma, maternal stress etc, and colic, it has also been suggested that some 'colic', or excessive crying may actually be a healthy stress release requiring support and facilitation rather than suppression or 'cure'.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Treatment</st>
<p>

There is currently no generally-accepted medical treatment for colic, and the approach taken by medical professionals varies substantially from country to country and indeed from doctor to doctor. Many believe that the condition is currently untreatable, and is best left to run its course. Other doctors prescribe <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/1098265.xml">
simethicone</link>, which treats trapped gas; some parents report that this is effective, but for many others it is not, and research suggests that it is not useful.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

One study showed a moderate success when infants with colic were treated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/748049.xml">
dicyclomine</link>, an anti-spasmotic drug commonly found in some anti-diarrheal medications.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

However, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/748049.xml">
dicyclomine</link> has about a 5 percent rate of minor side effects, and a non-zero mortality rate.</p>
<p>

Alternative therapies, particularly those that include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/173548.xml">
Fennel</link>, along with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/7985.xml">
dill</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/166716.xml">
chamomile</link>, and other herbs with purported digestive health benefits, have been applied.  These are primary ingredients in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/5972660.xml">
gripe water</link>, which is believed by some to relieve the symptoms associated with baby colic, teething and baby's gas.  No major scientific study has proven any level of success with these solutions and the United States Food and Drug Administration does not currently advocate their use.  </p>
<p>

Other studies have found success with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/731740.xml">
probiotic</link>s such as <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/6030185.xml">
Lactobacillus reuteri</link></it>, which were intended to reduce gas.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>
<p>

In addition to herbal teas it is believed that the organoleptic effects of certain herbs can help calm and relieve colic symptoms. </p>
<p>

Scientists warn that further studies are necessary before any specific cure should be recommended.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>
<p>

There is general agreement that soothing measures, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/996964.xml">
pacifier</link>s, listening to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/46182.xml">
white noise</link> and rocking, are often effective in calming the baby during crying periods.  Also known as the "cuddle cure",<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> the five S's are known as <b>Swaddling</b>, placing the baby on their <b>Side</b> or <b>Stomach</b>, <b>Swinging</b> the baby, making a <b>Shhh sound</b> in the baby's ear, and giving the baby something to <b>Suck</b> on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thehappiestbaby.com">
http://www.thehappiestbaby.com</weblink>.  Some parents take turns holding the baby upright (which may reduce the pain and crying) to enable the other parent to catch up on sleep. Babies with lactose intolerance or reflux cry harder and longer when left to lie on their backs, but parents are not advised to put the baby to sleep on their front as it is considered a risk factor for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/65344.xml">
Sudden Infant Death Syndrome</link>, or SIDS.</p>
<p>

Various tactics, such as changes in diet or routine, an increase in fresh air or certain herbal teas, are popularly believed to cure colic. There is also the theory that rubbing warm olive oil on the hands and feet, then rubbing the stomach with olive oil in a clockwise motion will cure colic. While some of these may help in certain cases, none of them is known to be universally effective. The widespread belief in them may be partly due to the suddenness with which colic naturally resolves itself. Many parents keep trying different approaches until the colic suddenly stops, at which point they presume that the last thing they tried was the cure.</p>
<p>

Some breastfed babies have problems digesting milk proteins, or have a milk protein sensitivity(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/5558520.xml">
milk allergy</link>) due to the mother's diet.  The proteins from cow's milk are able to pass through the mother's milk to the baby.  Because baby's intestines are still developing this sensitivity causes gas that is extremely painful.  It can also cause the excessive spitting up and reflux.  It can be helped with reflux medication, but not cured.  The only cure is to have the mother completely avoid all milk products, even foods with traces of milk.  Although this has been documented, it is still under debate.  This is because <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/1613569.xml">
La Leche League</link> experts agree that there is already enough stress on a new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/19347033.xml">
breastfeeding</link> relationship without having to deal with radical diet changes as well, and blaming the mother's milk for baby's malady puts pressure on mother to wean unnecessarily.  Formula may actually be more harmful than helpful in this situation, and will not cure the colic.  Some parents attribute colic to "lactose overload" and find that requiring the baby to completely empty one breast before moving on the next helps the problem, or "block feeding" (staying on one breast for 2-3 hours before switching).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>.</p>
<p>

In cases where 'colic' or excessive crying is possibly the infants innate healing mechanism helping them to recover from birth trauma or other past or current stress, appropriate holding and facilitation techniques may be able to increase the effectiveness of the release process and reduce the overall amount of crying time needed. In any case parents may benefit from learning these techniques, as this can help them to cope better psychologically with their child's distress, and to feel more empowered in the midst of an extremely trying situation. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>
<p>

When choosing caregivers for a colicky infant parents should consider the risk of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/398943.xml">
shaken baby syndrome</link>, a form of severe <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/2955547.xml">
child abuse</link>, at the hands of inexperienced sitters who respond violently under the stress of a continuously crying baby.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Effect on the family</st>
<p>

Colic can place an enormous strain on parents and other family members. The feeling that they are not providing something their child desperately wants or needs can induce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/146072.xml">
stress</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/840273.xml">
depression</link>, feelings of helplessness, and low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/150497.xml">
self-esteem</link>. If crying is prevalent during nighttime hours then these problems can be aggravated by the resulting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/18597893.xml">
sleep deprivation</link> or interruption to sleep patterns; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/235562.xml">
exhaustion</link> may also result. Where people live in dense housing such as apartment blocks, persistent crying can also strain relationships with neighbors and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/538368.xml">
landlord</link>s.</p>
<p>

The stress on parents is often compounded by well-meaning but misguided people who believe that the parents must be doing something wrong. This attitude is quite common among people who have raised colic-free children themselves. Even those who have had children who suffered from colic, and who found a "cure" (see above), can be reluctant to believe their own suggested approach does not work for somebody else.</p>
<p>

In some areas, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/153499.xml">
support group</link>s have been set up for parents of children with colic.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Boyd, D &amp; Bee, H (2006). <it>Lifespan Development</it> 4th ed. London: Pearson</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=15693915&amp;dopt=Citation">
Bacterial counts of intestinal Lactobacillus species in infants with colic.</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=15244234&amp;dopt=Citation">
Intestinal microflora in breastfed colicky and non-colicky infants.</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;list_uids=14749232&amp;dopt=Citation">
Long-term consumption of infant formulas containing live probiotic bacteria: tolerance and safety.</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
Francesco Savino, et al: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/119/1/e124">
Lactobacillus reuteri (American Type Culture Collection Strain 55730) versus Simethicone in the treatment of infantile colic: a prospective randomized study</weblink>. PEDIATRICS, Vol. 119, No. 1, January 2007, pp. e124-e130 (doi:10.1542/peds.2006-1222)</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=6409948&amp;dopt=Citation">
Lactobacillus acidophilus as a dietary adjunct for milk to aid lactose digestion in humans.</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adc.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/90/5/544">
Probiotics for infants: two studies, two successes</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jn.nutrition.org/cgi/content/abstract/137/3/812S">
Supplement: Effects of Probiotics and Prebiotics</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
Marsha Walker, RN, IBCLC, just one bottle won't hurt. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.drjaygordon.com/development/bf/supplement.asp"></weblink>  </entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.health-e-learning.com/articles/Lactose.pdf">
Colic and lactose intolerance</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
Sivan, Yakov; Laudon, Moshe; Tauman, Rivi; and Zisapel, Nava. 2001. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pedresearch.org/pt/re/pedresearch/abstract.00006450-200101000-00015.htm">
Melatonin production in healthy infants: evidence for seasonal variations. </weblink> <it>Pediatric Research</it> 49(1): 63-68. </entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=1513278&amp;query_hl=7&amp;itool=pubmed_docsum">
Colic and circadian rhythms</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15811501&amp;query_hl=8&amp;itool=pubmed_docsum">
Colic and maternal stress</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
 Solter.1998 </entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.med.umich.edu/pediatrics/ebm/cats/colic.htm">
University of Michigan clinical trial for simethicone used for colic</weblink></entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=7238059">
Study Offers Hope for Treating Colic</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=6374085&amp;query_hl=12&amp;itool=pubmed_docsum">
Colic and anti-diarrheal medication</weblink></entry>
<entry id="19">
http://www.sdgp.com.au/client_images/18177.pdf</entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/lifestyle/80970_cry.shtml">
Colic and the 'cuddle cure'</weblink></entry>
<entry id="21">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://breastfeeding.hypermart.net/toomuchmilk.html">
Too Much Milk</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.babycareadvice.com/babycare/general_help/article.php?id=18">
BabycareAdvice.com Articles: Lactose overload</weblink></entry>
<entry id="22">
Aletha J. Solter, Ph.D "Tears and Tantrums: what to do when babies and children cry" Shining Star Press (1998)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.citizendium.org/wiki/Infant_colic">
Infant colic</weblink> - article at <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/7005690.xml">
Citizendium</link></web_site>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foodreactions.org/colic/index.html">
Baby colic and treatment with lactase enzyme</weblink> from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foodreactions.org/">
FoodReactions.org</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://my.webmd.com/hw/raising_a_family/hw31506.asp">
WebMd on colic</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lpch.org/HealthLibrary/ParentCareTopics/NewbornQuestions/CryingBabyLessThan3MonthsOldIncludesColic.html">
Baby Colic Advice</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pedresearch.org/cgi/content/full/49/1/63">
 Melatonin Production in Healthy Infants: Evidence for Seasonal Variations</weblink> Pediatric Research</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=1513278&amp;query_hl=7&amp;itool=pubmed_docsum">
Colic, sleep inertia, melatonin and circannual rhythms</weblink> on PubMed.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fussybaby.ca/colictreatments.html">
Review of Treatments for Colic</weblink> Article from Fussy Baby</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15811501&amp;query_hl=8&amp;itool=pubmed_docsum">
Do pregnancy and childbirth adversities predict infant crying and colic?</weblink> on PubMed.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colichelp.com/forums/">
Colic Support Message Boards</weblink> from ColicHelp.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colicbabyshop.com/colicarticles1.htmlHelpfull">
Colic articles,Videos</weblink> from colicbabyshop.com</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</ailment>
</disease>
</article>
