<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:19:50[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<device  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103183080">
<instrument  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103574816">
<header>
<title>XDAIS algorithms</title>
<id>14102480</id>
<revision>
<id>191675617</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-15T17:10:59Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Warut</username>
<id>2676502</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from December 2007</category>
<category>Texas Instruments</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=XDAIS_algorithms&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22XDAIS+algorithms%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<b>XDAIS</b> or <b>eXpressDsp Algorithm Interoperability Standard</b> is a standard for algorithm development by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/47768.xml">
Texas Instruments</link></company>
 for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/2542355.xml">
TMS320</link> DSP family.  The standard was first introduced in 1999 and was created to facilitate integration of DSP algorithm into systems without re-engineering cost. The XDAIS standard address the issues of algorithm resource allocation and consumption on a DSP.  Algorithms that comply with the standard are tested and awarded an "eXpressDSP-compliant" mark upon successful completion of the test</p>
<p>

The standard is comprised of a set of general rules and guidelines that should be applied to all algorithms.  For instance, all XDAIS compliant algorithms must implement an Algorithm Interface, called IALG.  For those algorithms utilizing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/8496.xml">
DMA</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/4793036.xml">
IDMA</link> interface must be implemented.  Further, specific rules are provide for each family of TI DSP.</p>
<p>

Problems are often caused in algorithm by hard-coding access to system resources that are used by other algorithms.  DAIS probits the use of this type of hard-coding.  Instead, DAIS requires a standard API for the application to call a particular algorithm class.  This API is defined in the <link>
xDM standard</link>, also referred to as the <link>
VISA API</link>s (video, imaging, speech and audio).</p>
<p>

A XDAIS developer's kit provides the standard itself, example code, and a demonstration. </p>
<p>

Benefits of XDAIS over non-standardize approach include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Significant reduction in integration time as algorithms do trash each others resources</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Easy comparison of algorithms from multiple different sources in the same application</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Access to broad range of compliant algorithms available from multiple TI DSP Third Parties eliminates need to custom develop complex algorithms</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Algorithms work out-of-the-box with eXpressDSP Multimedia Framework Products, such as <link>
Codec Engine (TI)</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://focus.ti.com/docs/toolsw/folders/print/tmdxdaisxdm.html#technicaldocuments">
XpressDSP Algorithm Standard – xDAIS Developer’s Kit and xDM</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://focus.ti.com/lit/ug/spru424c/spru424c.pdf">
TMS320 DSP Algorithm Standard Developer’s Guide</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</instrument>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</article>
