<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:10:34[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<university  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108286163">
<header>
<title>Barcelona Graduate School of Economics</title>
<id>14123792</id>
<revision>
<id>228545830</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-29T05:23:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Anthony Appleyard</username>
<id>119438</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from December 2007</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
<category>Universities in Catalonia</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Barcelona_Graduate_School_of_Economics&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Barcelona+Graduate+School+of+Economics%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

The <b>Barcelona Graduate School of Economics</b>, commonly referred to as <b>Barcelona GSE</b>, is an independent institution of graduate education located in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/4443.xml">
Barcelona</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</tract>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</site>
, in Catalonia, Spain. It was founded in July 2006 by four academic institutions (<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/63872.xml">
Universitat Pompeu Fabra</link></university>
, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/61407.xml">
Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona</link></university>
, IAE-CSIC and CREI) whose reputations, faculty, and resources underpin the Barcelona GSE master programs. The School is also supported by five private institutions: The Agbar Group, Banc Sabadell, Caixa de Catalunya savings bank, "la Caixa" savings bank, and the FemCAT Foundation. It also receives significant funding from the "Consolider-Ingenio 2010" initiative of the Spanish Government, launched to promote research excellence.</p>
<p>

The School was legally recognized by the government of Catalonia in October 2006 as a Foundation dedicated to higher education. The Barcelona GSE’s unique combination of public and private support provides the School with deep roots in Barcelona’s academic and business communities and guarantees the future success of its master programs.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Mission</st>

<p>

To give graduates the knowledge and skills to contribute to vital areas of tomorrow's economy and society. They aim to achieve this goal by offering students:</p>
<p>

• Academic Excellence</p>
<p>

-Renowned world-class faculty
-Collaborative institutional approach offering academic innovation</p>
<p>

• Rigorous, Innovative Programs</p>
<p>

-Master specializations oriented toward exciting new careers
-Demanding, relevant curricula designed by faculty experts</p>
<p>

• International Outlook</p>
<p>

-Geographic and cultural diversity of students and faculty
-Academic emphasis on the challenges faced by the global economy</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The Barcelona Economics Community</st>

<p>

Although the Barcelona GSE is a young school, it draws on the strengths and noteworthy reputations of its founding academic institutions, and enjoys close collaboration with them in teaching and research as well as in the shared use of resources. This combination of innovation and accumulated experience is one of the unique features of the Barcelona GSE.</p>
<p>

• <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.econ.upf.edu/en/">
The Universitat Pompeu Fabra - Economics and Business Dept.</weblink></p>
<p>

• <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://selene.uab.es/_cs_u_fonaments/ingles/index.htm">
The Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona - Unit of Economic Analysis</weblink></p>
<p>

• <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iae-csic.uab.es/pagines/conpag/tot.htm">
The Institute for Economic Analysis</weblink></p>
<p>

• <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.crei.cat/">
The Center for Research in International Economics</weblink></p>
<p>

Barcelona's Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF) was founded in 1990 as a public university committed to research and excellence. It enrolls over 9,000 students and has a teaching staff of approximately 1,000. It was recently ranked first among Spanish Economics Departments according to a study published in the Spanish Economic Review. In just 16 years, the department has reached the milestone of 1,000 working papers published.</p>
<p>

The Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona - Unit of Economic Analysis (UAB) was created in 1968. With over 50,000 students, 3,000 academic and research staff and 100 postgraduate programs, the UAB is a research powerhouse. The Unit of Economic Analysis is generally considered to be one of Spain's top three Economics Departments.</p>
<p>

The Institute for Economic Analysis (IAE), is part of the Spanish Research Council (CSIC) and was created in the UAB campus in 1985. Its aim is to promote research in Economics at the highest scientific level.</p>
<p>

The Centre for Research in International Economics (CREI) is a research institute created in 1993 by the UPF and the Government of Catalonia. Its research activities focus on international economics and macroeconomics.</p>
<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.barcelonaeconomics.org/">
Reference Network in Analytic Economics</weblink> (CREA) is a research network promoted by the Government of Catalonia to foster excellence in economics research in Barcelona and support top research groups in the field. Three of the founding institutions of the Barcelona GSE compose CREA: the Unit of Economic Analysis of the UAB, the Department of Economics and Business of the UPF, and the Institute of Economic Analysis (IAE-CSIC).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Campuses</st>

<p>

The Barcelona GSE has two campuses: the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://maps.google.es/maps?f=q&amp;hl=es&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Ramon+Trias+Fargas,+25,+08005+Barcelona&amp;sll=40.396764,-3.713379&amp;sspn=11.556158,18.764648&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;z=16&amp;om=1">
Ciutadella campus</weblink> and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://maps.google.es/maps?f=q&amp;hl=es&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Universitat+Aut%C3%B2noma+de+Barcelona,+Bellaterra&amp;sll=41.504336,2.100031&amp;sspn=0.355333,0.586395&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=41.504336,2.100031&amp;spn=0.022208,0.03665&amp;z=15&amp;om=1">
Bellaterra campus</weblink>. At present, three of the programs are based at the Ciutadella campus, at Pompeu Fabra University in central Barcelona. The campus is within walking distance of both the beach and the city's financial, cultural and governmental centers.</p>
<p>

The MSc in the Economics of Science and Innovation is located at the Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona (UAB) campus at Bellaterra. The UAB's self-contained campus offers students all of the services they need in their day-to-day lives and is an easy half-hour train ride from the city center.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.barcelonagse.eu">
Barcelona GSE website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</university>
</article>
