<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:21:40[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>History of wireless mesh networking</title>
<id>14236107</id>
<revision>
<id>243799636</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T02:08:41Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wireless networking</category>
<category>Networks</category>
<category>Network topology</category>
<category>Articles which may be unencyclopedic</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section may contain material .</b>
Please discuss this issue on the .</col>
</row>
</table>


<image width="150px" src="Self-form-self-heal.gif‎" type="thumb">
<caption>

Fig 1:Self-Healing Mesh
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="WIKIthreegenerationslg.gif‎" type="thumb">
<caption>

Fig 2:Three generations of Mesh
</caption>
</image>
 
<image width="150px" src="Single-radio-mesh.gif‎" type="thumb">
<caption>

Fig 3: Single Radio Mesh Cycle
</caption>
</image>
 
<image width="150px" src="Third-Generation-mesh-hop.gif‎" type="thumb">
<caption>

Fig 4:Third Generation Cycle
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The core advantage of wireless <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/912687.xml">
mesh network</link>s is their inherent ability to form a network on power up.  Watch what happens in Fig 1, when the mesh nodes power up (green LED on box turns on). The nodes hear each other's broadcast and a network is self-formed. Also watch what happens when a node fails and how the nodes re-discover an alternate routing path. Network connectivity is thus preserved automatically.  </p>
<p>

Over the years, wireless mesh networking has seen three unique deployments based on radio technology, each incorporating iterative improvements allowing for greater <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/185529.xml">
scalability</link> and higher network performance - both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/30932.xml">
throughput</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/568329.xml">
latency</link>. This early stage of technological development or innovation in wireless mesh is pre IEEE standard and is known a first Generation of Wireless Mesh.  The following deployments are briefly described of various configuration of first generation Wireless Mesh Networking: </p>
<p>

1.<b>First Configuration</b>: 1-Radio Mesh. As shown in Fig 2, this configuration uses one radio channel both to service clients and to provide the mesh backhaul. The single mesh radio, provides both services - client access and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/4624565.xml">
backhaul</link>. Comparative performance analysis indicates this architecture provides the worst services of all the options , as expected- both backhaul and service compete for bandwidth. Also all single radio mesh architectures suffer from the send-receive-wait cycle shown in Fig 3. Since there is only radio, the mesh node has to listen, then send, then listen again. This intermittent stop-and-go behavior adversely affects network performance especially if the destination is far away and the traffic has to be re-transmitted ("hop") across many intermediate nodes first.  </p>
<p>

2. <b>Second Configuration</b>: Dual-Radio with a 1-Radio backhaul mesh. This configuration can also be referred to as a "1+1" network, since each node contains two radios, one to provide service to the clients, and one to create the mesh network for backhaul. The "1+1" appellation indicates that these radios are separate from each other - the radio providing service does not participate in the backhaul, and the radio participating in the backhaul does not provide service to the clients. These two radios can operate in different bands. For example, a 2.4 GHz <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/14739.xml">
802.11</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 b/g radio can be used for service and an 802.11a (5 GHz) radio can be used exclusively for backhaul. </p>
<p>

Most mesh products available today fall into this category. Separating the service from the backhaul improves performance when compared with conventional ad hoc mesh networks. But since a single radio mesh is still servicing the backhaul, packets traveling toward the Internet share bandwidth at each hop along the backhaul path with other interfering mesh backhaul nodes - all-operating on the same channel. This leads to throughput degradations as shown in Fig 3, which are not as severe as for the single radio mesh, but which are sizeable nevertheless. Second generation mesh products are best employed in 1 or 2 hop configurations.  </p>
<p>

3. <b>Third Configuration</b>: 2 radio backhauls. The last architecture shown (far right in Fig 2) is one that provides separate backhaul and service functionality and dynamically manages channels of all of the radios so that all radios are on non-interfering channels. Performance analysis indicates that this provides the best performance of any of the methods considered here. Note that the two backhaul radios for the 3-radio configuration shown in Fig 2 right are of the same type - not to be confused with 1+1 so-called dual radio meshes where one radio is typically of type 802.11 A (backhaul) and the other of type 802.11 B/G (service). In the 3-radio configuration, 2 radios provide up link and down link backhaul functionality, and the other radio provides service to clients. Fig 4 shows how the two radios of the backhaul transmit traffic, with both radios operating independently and on separate channels.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Examples </st>


<p>

The <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/827618.xml">
Naval Postgraduate School</link></university>
, Monterey CA, demonstrated a third configuration multi-radio wireless mesh network for border security.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> In a pilot system, aerial cameras kept aloft by balloons relayed real time high resolution video to ground personnel via a mesh network.</p>
<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/386540.xml">
MIT Media Lab</link> project has developed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/11778236.xml">
XO-1</link> single radio laptop or "OLPC" which is intended for under-privileged schools in developing nations and uses mesh networking (based on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/2727429.xml">
IEEE 802.11s</link> standard) to create a robust and inexpensive infrastructure.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The instantaneous connections made by the laptops are claimed by the project to reduce the need for an external infrastructure such as the internet to reach all areas, because a connected node could share the connection with nodes nearby. A similar concept has also been implemented by Greenpacket with its application called SONbuddy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> </p>
<p>

SMesh is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/14739.xml">
802.11</link> multi-hop single radio wireless mesh network developed by the Distributed System and Networks Lab at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/38420.xml">
Johns Hopkins University</link></university>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> A fast <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/41228.xml">
handoff</link> scheme allows mobile clients to roam in the network without interruption in connectivity, a feature suitable for real-time applications, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
VoIP</link>.</p>
<p>

Many mesh networks operate across multiple radio bands. For example Firetide and Wave Relay second configuration dual radio mesh networks have the option to communicate node to node on 5.2 GHz or 5.8 GHz, but communicate node to client on 2.4 GHz (802.11).  This is accomplished using SDR (Software Defined Radio.)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/912687.xml">
Mesh networking</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/713497.xml">
Wireless mesh network</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.8">
<capitalist wordnetid="109609232" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<supplier wordnetid="110677271" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/60144.xml">
Wireless community network</link></supplier>
</causal_agent>
</capitalist>
</businessperson>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/142569.xml">
Mobile ad-hoc network</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://csrc.nist.gov/manet/">
NIST MANET and Sensor Network Security project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dailywireless.org/2004/07/15/the-mesh-debate/">
The Mesh Debate</weblink>Dailywireless Article on Structured mesh network scalability.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.meshdynamics.com/documents/Mesh_Mining_July08.pdf">
Miners Give a Nod to Nodes</weblink> Artivle reprint from Mission Critical Magazine on Mesh in underground mining</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.meshdynamics.com/MiningAppln.html">
Robust Wireless Mesh Communications inside mines</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.meshdynamics.com/documents/MD_MILITARY_MESH.pdf">
Military Mesh Networks</weblink> What makes military mesh requirements distinctive</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pdos.lcs.mit.edu/roofnet/">
MIT Roofnet</weblink> A research project at MIT that forms the basis of roofnet / <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/12327314.xml">
Meraki</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 mesh networks</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ivolve.com/products/nexis/pdfs/NetworkWhitePaper.pdf">
Wireless Mesh Networks</weblink> Advantages and applications for Industrial and Mobile Solutions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.meshdynamics.com/MiningAppln.html">
Robust Wireless Mesh Communications inside mines - successful pilots</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Robert Lee Lounsbury, Jr..&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://theses.nps.navy.mil/07Sep_Lounsbury.pdf">
OPTIMUM ANTENNA CONFIGURATION FOR MAXIMIZING ACCESS POINT RANGE OF AN IEEE 802.11 WIRELESS MESH NETWORK IN SUPPORT OF MULTIMISSION OPERATIONS RELATIVE TO HASTILY FORMED SCALABLE DEPLOYMENTS</weblink></it>". &#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-23</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wiki.laptop.org/go/Mesh_Network_Details">
XO-1 Mesh Network Details</weblink>".&#32;  laptop.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-23</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sonbuddy.com">
SONbuddy : Network without Network</weblink>".&#32;  sonbuddy.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-23</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://smesh.org">
SMesh</weblink>".&#32;  smesh.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-23</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
