<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:15:05[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<hospital  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="103540595">
<header>
<title>Asan Medical Center</title>
<id>14254950</id>
<revision>
<id>234485405</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-27T02:31:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Trewhelas</username>
<id>67788</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Hospitals in South Korea</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Hospital</name>
<parameters>
<Beds>
2189</Beds>
<Website>
http://www.amc.seoul.kr/eng/index.jsp</Website>
<Type>
Tertiary referral hospital</Type>
<Location>
388-1, Poongnap-2dong, Songpa-gu</Location>
<Country>
South Korea</Country>
<Name>
Asan Medical Center</Name>
<Region>
Seoul</Region>
<Founded>
1989</Founded>
<Image>
Asan_medical_center_front.jpg</Image>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>Asan Medical Center</b>(서울아산병원) Korea’s largest tertiary referral hospital with 2,189 beds, was founded in 1989 by the late Chairman Ju-Yung Chung of Asan Foundation, with the philanthropic principles of meeting the growing demand for specialized treatments to the under privileged in society. Since then, this patient-oriented hospital has been caring more than 8,300 outpatients, 2,080 inpatients, and 180 emergency patients, while successfully performing 195 complex surgical operations on a daily basis. When AMC opens a 20-story new building in 2008, this hospital will be equipped with 3,000 beds and could offer upgraded health care services.    




<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>
<p>
   
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Average number of outpatients per day: 8,300 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Number of hospital admissions: 759,000 yearly / 2,080 daily</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Emergency department registrations: 66,200 yearly</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Surgical cases: 46,200 yearly</entry>
</list>
</p>








</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Medical</st>
<p>
   
<image location="left" width="150px" src="Asan_medical_center_medical.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Medical
</caption>
</image>
   
AMC runs 40 clinical examination departments and 16 specialty care centers for cancers, cardiovascular disease, and diabetes, and specialized clinics for each medical specialty.  In particular, AMC shows an outstanding medical performance on cancer treatments and organ transplants. In February 2006, AMC was ranked number one in the number of operations performed for 9 out of top 10 major cancers among Koreans by the National Health Insurance and Health Insurance Review Agency. According to the 2006 annual report issued by the Korean Network for Organ Sharing of the Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, the number of organ transplants conducted by AMC was 581 out of 2,236, accounted for 24.9% of the 2006 total. AMC has been also operating the Quality Improvement team since 1993, and has electronic systems such as Order Communication System (OCS), Picture Archiving and Communications System (PACS) which were developed by its own technology, and medical equipment such as gamma knife, MRI, CT and so on.   </p>






</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Research and Study</st>
<p>
   
<image width="150px" src="Asan_medical_center_education2.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Research and Study
</caption>
</image>
   
In various areas of clinical and basic medicine, AMC published 567 and 825 research papers in 2005 and 2006 respectively to domestic and international medical fields, and provides integrated courses by affiliating with University of Ulsan College of Medicine. AMC offers medical students with clinical experiences by operating a pre-internship program twice a year as well. As an affiliate medical center of Harvard Medical School, AMC runs a mutual patient advisory and referral system with Harvard Medical School and collaborates in the areas of medical treatment, education, health technology planning through the exchange of doctors, nurses, health technicians, and administrative staff with Harvard Medical School.
Through the partnership contracted with Imperial College London in February 2007, AMC pursues an active clinical exchange and joint research for the areas of clinical and basic medicine.</p>




</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Culture Activity</st>
<p>
   
<image width="150px" src="Asan_medical_center_culture.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Culture Activity
</caption>
</image>
   
AMC provides visitors with a chance to meet the world of art by exhibiting artworks in the lobby. A concert called ‘Asan Medical Center Love Concert’ which is performed by volunteering professional musicians and music majored students is held in the main hall every month. As other endeavors to provide patient friendly environment, AMC plays a movie and offers a reading room to patients and visitors. </p>












</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History/Milestones</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 2008  Opened the Asthma Center and the Pediatric Asthma/Atopy Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 2008  Opened the new 772-bed hospital building, strengthening advanced medical system, environment-friendly medical services</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 2008  Won the Grand Prize of the Korea Social Contribution Award in ‘The Company of Korea 2008’ organized by the Korea Consumer Forum</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2008  Successfully transplanted a heart to a 100-day-old baby for the first time</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2008  The Medical Team of Cardiology led by Professor Park Seong Jeong published their dissertation in the NEJM, one of the most prestigious academic journals in the world</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 2008  Selected as the most respected hospital for two consecutive years by KMAC</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 2008  Publicly recognized as a hospital with the highest number of surgery cases</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 2008  Exceeded 300 cases of liver transplantation annually</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 2008  Seoul Asan Hospital recorded 200 cases of heart transplantation, for the first time in Korea</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 2007  Obtained the certificate for HON Code of the homepage of Seoul Asan Medical Center (a prestigious international certificate allowed to medical information websites that comply with the 8 Code of Ethics suggested by the HON)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 2007  Celebration for marking 10,000 cases of colon cancer surgery</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 2007  Held a symposium to celebrate the 1,000th prostate cancer surgery</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 2007  Held a working meeting with Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, the most prominent cancer research institute in the world</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 2007  Designated as the Good Productivity Enhancement Company in 2007</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

August 2007  Yanghyun Foundation offered the donations to foster cancel specialists</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

July 2007  Held the 1st Asan International Digestive Disease Symposium</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2007  Implementation of in house-developed EMR system</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2007  Selected as the most respected hospital by KMAC</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2007  Selected as “Korea’s Most Admired Hospital” by KMA Consultants, Inc. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 2007  Partnership with the Imperial College in London, UK</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 2006  IRB officially recognized at the Forum for Ethical Review Committees in Asia and the Western Pacific (FERCAP)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

October 2006  Ranked 1st in the National Brand Competitiveness Index (NBCI) by the Korea Productivity Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

July 2006  World’s fist discovery of the production element of appetite control</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 2006  AMC physicians perform Korea’s 1st simultaneous kidney-pancreas transplants living donors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 2005  Prime Minister Award as acknowledgement of free medical services to the survivors of the tsunami</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 2005  The groundbreaking ceremony of the new building</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 2005  Selected as Korea’s best hospital in performance measurement by the Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 2004  Awarded the Minister of Government Administration and Home Affairs Prize</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 2004  Fastest ever achievement of 1,000th liver transplant milestone</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 2004  Won Presidential Prize in the Safety Management Awards</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 2004  Open the Asan Research Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2004  First successful cardiac surgery using a robot conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 2004  1,500th kidney transplant surgery conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 2003  Awarded Grand Prize in the Korea Management Awards</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 2003  World’s first discovery of cardiac valve replacement surgery using Ring</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 2003  World’s first successful liver exchange transplant between four adults</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 2003  Awarded Grand Prize for ‘Customer satisfaction’ at the National Productivity Awards</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 2002  Awarded Presidential Prize for consumer protection services</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

July 2002  First hospital in the nation to succeed in an open-heart surgery on a premature infant</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

June 2002  Awarded Grand Prize in the Digital Awards 2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2002  First hospital certified ‘Korea Best Service’ </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2002  Change the CI of Asan Medical Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 2002  Liver transplantation exceeds 500 cases - Organ Transplantation Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 2001  100th  successful heart transplant surgery </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 2001  Korea’s fist operation in Drug-Eluting Stent on a patient with angina pectoris</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 2001  Successful heart transplantation on the youngest recipient in Korean history</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 2000  AMC surgeons successfully transplant livers from two people into one patient for the first time in history</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 2000  Department of Clinical Laboratory receives CAP certification for blood bank</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 1999  Awarded Grand Prize &amp; Best Entrepreneur Prize in the Customer Satisfaction (CS) Awards 1999 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

July 1999  Selected a certificate company to solve the Y2K problem</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

October 1998  Awarded Grand Prize for Customer Satisfaction from the Korea Management Association</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 1998  Found the cause and treatment for intractable pulmonary hypertension</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 1997  Interventricular septal defect cardiovascular Angiography and Intervention using 100% alcohol conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

July 1996  World’s first lacrimal obstruction intervention using Stent conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 1996  Implantable cardioverter-defibrillator (ICD) surgery for preventing heart stroke conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 1995  Awarded in the 2nd Korea Business Cultural Awards</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 1994  First blood-relation liver transplant conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 1993  First bone marrow transplant using hematogenesis hair cells conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 1992  Heart transplant conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

June 1992  Fist simultaneous pancreas and kidney transplant conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 1991  World’s first coronary angioplasty using Stent conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 1990  Cerebral artery operation using extracorporeal circulation conducted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

June 1989  Open Seoul Joong-Ang Hospital of the Asan Foundation</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Affiliates</st>
<p>
   
<image location="right" width="150px" src="Asan_medical_center_foundation.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Asan Foundation
</caption>
</image>
   </p>


<ss1>
<st>
Asan Foundation</st>
<p>
   
The <link>
Asan Foundation</link> was established by the late Chairman, Ju-Yung Chung, as one of the commemoration works for the 30th anniversary of Hyundai Engineering and Construction, the parent company of Hyundai Group. The Asan Foundation has focused on medical treatment and welfare business following the foundation’s purpose, “Helping the least privileged member of our society”. From the early stage, the Asan Foundation established 8 regional hospitals in rural areas such as Jeongeup, Bosung, Youngdeok , Hongcheon , Gangneung, where there were very few hospitals existed at the time, and has provided medical benefits through the hospitals.     </p>




</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
University of Ulsan College of Medicine</st>
<p>
   
<image location="right" width="150px" src="Asan_medical_center_ulsan.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

University of Ulsan College of Medicine
</caption>
</image>
   
Since founded in 1988, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/10458246.xml">
University of Ulsan</link></university>
 College of Medicine has been operated in the unifications of clinical and basic medicine and runs programs to raise the student’s problem-solving ability. In December 2004, the university’s Seoul campus was moved in the Asan education Research Center of AMC, and AMC, Ulsan University Hospital, and Gangneung Asan Hospital are its teaching hospitals. There are 450 professors working at the University and 358 undergraduate, 797 master, and 275 doctor graduates since it has been founded.  </p>











</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Asan Research Center</st>
<p>
   
<image location="right" width="150px" src="Asan_medical_center_science.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Asan Research Center
</caption>
</image>
   
<link>
Asan Research Center</link> has an affiliation with AMC and University of Ulsan College of Medicine and performs researches in the areas of clinical medicine, basic medicine, and related fields. </p>




</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Asan Health Network</st>
<p>
   
<link>
Gangneung Asan Hospital</link>, <link>
Keumkang Asan Hospital</link>, <link>
Bosung Asan Hospital</link>, <link>
Boryeong Asan Hospital</link>, <link>
Youngdeok Asan Hospital</link>, <link>
Jeongeup Asan Hospital</link>, <link>
Hongcheon Asan Hospital</link></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</hospital>
</article>
