<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:28:15[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<header>
<title>Mosaic: The Prince of Wales&apos;s Muslim Mentoring Project</title>
<id>14337235</id>
<revision>
<id>239905284</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-21T01:28:46Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Islamic organizations</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from December 2007</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from September 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Mosaic:_The_Prince_of_Wales%27s_Muslim_Mentoring_Project&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Mosaic%3A+The+Prince+of+Wales%26%2339%3Bs+Muslim+Mentoring+Project%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="45px" src="Ambox_PR.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section reads like 
, or is otherwise written in an overly promotional tone.</b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Mosaic:_The_Prince_of_Wales%27s_Muslim_Mentoring_Project&amp;action=edit">
rewrite this article</weblink> from a  to be less promotional.Where appropriate,  may be marked for speedy deletion with . <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>Background</b>
At the behest of <link>
His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/17973218.xml">
Business in the Community</link></company>
, one of his major charitable initiatives and <link>
The Prince’s Seeing is Believing</link> Programme have worked in association with a number of individuals to develop a unique alliance of moderate Muslim individuals and organizations with the aim of promoting  tolerance and understanding across society. </p>
<p>

The Prince’s charities group have, alongside other key partners, identified certain specific areas of activity which they believe working collaboratively can have a profoundly positive effect upon U.K social cohesion and Muslim community leadership in particular.  </p>
<p>

The aim of  Mosaic is therefore to establish the means through which both individuals and organizations can have a collaborative positive impact in this area of concern.</p>
<p>

<b>Focus Areas of Action</b>
Mosaic has identified the following initiatives:</p>
<p>

1. Mosaic Muslim Mentoring Network: This network will contain successful young Muslims from across the corporate and public sectors in, for example Investment Banks, Law firms, and Government departments. They will utilize their skills and experiences by mentoring young Muslims from between the ages of 12 and 25 in some of our most deprived areas starting in Burnley, Bradford and Tower Hamlets.  Their aim is to see more young Muslims maximising their opportunities and with experiences and similar cultural/religious backgrounds, the mentors are well suited to become role-models for the young target audience.   
Their focus will be on:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Recruiting 500 mentors across the country by the end of 2008</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Develop a programme of e-mentoring and advice exchange via the Mosaic web presence</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Organize a minimum of 50 “world of Work” visits taking classes of Pupils into work environments by end of 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mosaic wishes to expand the geographical reach of the programme to cover towns in E.Lancs &amp; the Midlands.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This Group is chaired jointly by young professionals from Lovells and HSBC &amp; supported by CLG, SJ Berwin, Deutsche Bank, Fortune Group, Fenchurch partners and a  variety of private Muslim individuals.  </p>
<p>

2. Mosaic Muslim Media Network: This network is exclusively for Muslims working in the media and will focus on the following:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Be a source of information to the Muslim community with regards to the workings of Mainstream media </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Be a source of information about dominant Muslim media attitudes to HMG policy makers, journalists and broadcasters in the UK  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To promote positive Muslim role models in order to act as a catalyst for increased Muslim representation in the Media</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To provide a platform for Media professionals to network, exchange ideas and develop partnerships.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To provide media literacy education to increase critical analysis and understanding of how information is presented across the mediums. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This group is chaired by a senior Muslim professional at <channel wordnetid="106259898" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/6321.xml">
Channel 4</link></channel>
 with representation from individuals across the Media. </p>
<p>

3. Mosaic Muslim Business Bridge: This project will support the capacity of community leaders in deprived Muslim areas to better develop and operate their own operations whilst at the same time increase their ability to present community leadership issues and represent their specific customers, stakeholders and communities.</p>
<p>

This project will focus on the following:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Establish three such bridges between business and local communities in Bradford, Burnley &amp; Leicester</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Each Bridge will recruit a minimum of 12 local leaders and through the bridge process of regular meetings broker in appropriate capacity building support from local businesses via Business in the Community.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

4. Mosaic Muslim Speakers Bureau: A key concern for moderate Muslims is the apparent lack of speakers and role models available to talk as successful mainstream Muslims across all manner of areas from School presentations, through to national media programmes. 
This  Circle will focus on the following:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Developing a range of competent moderate Muslim speakers who by utilizing training provided by the Muslim Media Network will be available for comment, participation and interview as and when required.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Establish a group available for approaches from Government &amp; other agencies for active involvement in initiatives. 	Build an awareness of emerging young Muslims who can be developed to become ambassadors for moderation by being supported themselves from within the network.</entry>
</list>

The lead initiators on this development are a variety of individuals from various sectors alongside prominent individuals who are prepared to act in this role.</p>
<p>

5. Mosaic Muslim Finance Initiative: This initiative will focus on some of the issues surrounding the provision of Islamic financial solutions to those in most challenging circumstances within the U.K.  It will work with legal and financial experts to undertake a  review of what might be required to produce products and services which are acceptable &amp; accessible, make recommendations in order to see if such gaps in provision can be addressed.</p>
<p>

6.The  Mosaic Alliance: This initiative aims to build a major cross sector partnership alliance of moderate Muslim organizations willing top tackle the concerns surrounding Muslims in Britain by sharing experience, resource, knowledge etc.  by developing a Mosaic alliance of associated partners it is perceived that collaboration , the sharing of resources, knowledge &amp; connections will increase the positive impact of partner initiatives.
It aims to achieve this by focusing on the following:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Develop a network communication channel to support the capacity of smaller groups, transfer experiences and build collaborative responses to emerging needs.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hold a major Mosaic gala evening in the Autumn of 2008.  This event will celebrate the very best of Muslim activity in Britain from the Arts to Business, from Community leadership to Public sector delivery.  It is envisaged that this will be the largest such event of its kind in the U.K.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Summary</b>
The Mosaic initiatives set out above provide a set of collaborative, mutually supportive programmes with an unrivalled breadth of engagement.  Mosaic itself will provide a rallying point for the very many moderate Muslims and community led initiatives who wish to counter the negative influences in our society and the effect that such influences have in feeding anti Islamic sentiment within the wider community.</p>
<p>

The management of this ambitious alliance will be maintained by a representative advisory board of prominent Muslim individuals from the public, private and not for profit sectors.  This board will continue to be supported and inspired by His Royal Highness The Prince of Wales who has acted as the catalyst and motivator behind the initiative to date.</p>
<p>

Others actively involved with this project include: <link>
Baroness Pola Uddin</link>, <link>
Princess Badiya of Jordon</link>, <link>
Baroness Kishwer Falconer</link>, <link>
Baroness Sayeed Warsi</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/9550379.xml">
Lord Hameed</link>.  The Project is led by John O'Brien the Director responsible for The Prince of Wales's programmes.</p>

</bdy>
</organization>
</article>
