<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:17:54[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Neural backpropagation</title>
<id>14338608</id>
<revision>
<id>234388748</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-26T17:14:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dmitry Brant</username>
<id>156068</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Neural networks</category>
<category>Neuroscience</category>
<category>Computational neuroscience</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about the biological process.&#32;&#32;For the computer algorithm, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/1360091.xml">
Backpropagation</link>.&#32;&#32;<p>

<b>Neural backpropagation</b> is the phenomenon in which the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/156998.xml">
action potential</link> of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/21120.xml">
neuron</link> creates a voltage spike both at the end of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/958.xml">
axon</link> (normal propagation) and back through to the dendritic arbor or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/8131.xml">
dendrites</link>, from which much of the original input current originated. It has been shown that this simple process can be used in a manner similar to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/1360091.xml">
backpropagation</link> algorithm used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/2266644.xml">
multilayer perceptrons</link>, a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
artificial neural network</link>. In addition to active backpropagation the action potential, there is also passive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/1267442.xml">
electrotonic</link> spread.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Since the 1950s, evidence has existed that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/21120.xml">
neurons</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/7251.xml">
central nervous system</link> generate an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/156998.xml">
action potential</link>, or voltage spike, the travels both through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/958.xml">
axon</link> to signal the next neuron and backpropagates through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/8131.xml">
dendrites</link> sending a retrograde signal to its presynaptic signaling neurons. This current decays significantly with travel length along the dendrites, so effects are predicted to be more significant for neurons whose synapses are near the postsynaptic cell body, with magnitude depending mainly on sodium-channel density in the dendrite. It is also dependent on the shape of the dendritic tree and, more importantly, on the rate of signal currents to the neuron. On average, a backpropagating spike loses about half its voltage after traveling nearly 500 micrometres.</p>
<p>

Backpropagation occurs actively in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/487922.xml">
neocortex</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml">
hippocampus</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/46425.xml">
substantia nigra</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/37070.xml">
spinal cord</link>, while in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/50397.xml">
cerebellum</link> it occurs relatively passively. This is consistent with observations that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/423771.xml">
synaptic plasticity</link> is much more apparent in areas like the hippocampus, which controls memory, than the cerebellum, which controls more unconscious and vegetative functions.</p>
<p>

The backpropagating current also causes a voltage change that increases the concentration of Ca2+ in the dendrites, an event which coincides with certain models of synaptic plasticity. This change also affects future integration of signals, leading to at least a short-term response difference between the presynaptic signals and the postsynaptic spike<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Functions</st>
<p>

There are a number of hypotheses regarding the function of backpropagation of action potentials. In addition to synaptic plasticity, it is also hypothesized to be involved in dendrodendritic inhibition, boosting synaptic responses, resetting membrane potential, retrograde actions at synapses and conditional axonal output.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Algorithm</st>
<p>

While a backpropagating action potential can presumably cause changes in the weight of the presynaptic connections, there is no simple mechanism for an error signal to propagate through multiple layers of neurons, as in the computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/1360091.xml">
backpropagation</link> algorithm. However, simple linear topologies have shown that effective computation is possible through signal backpropagation in this biological sense<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Stuart, Greg; Nelson Spruston, Bert Sakmann, Michael Häusser&#32;(1997).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.neuron.org/content/issue?volume=22&amp;issue=4">
Action potential initiation and backpropagation in neurons of the mammalian CNS</weblink>". <it>TINS</it>&#32;<b>20</b>&#32;(3). Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-13</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal"><link>
Bogacz, Rafal</link>; Malcolm W. Brown, Christophe Giraud-Carrier&#32;(2000).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.math.princeton.edu/%7Erbogacz/papers/Como00.pdf">
Frequency-based Error Back-propagation in a Cortical Network</weblink>". <it>Proceedings of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/56938.xml">
IEEE</link>-<link>
INNS</link>-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/19172663.xml">
ENNS</link> International Joint Conference on Neural Networks, Como (Italy)</it>&#32;<b>2</b>: 211–216. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109%2FIJCNN.2000.857899">
10.1109/IJCNN.2000.857899</weblink>. 0-7695-0619-4. Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-18</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Buzsáki G, Kandel A. Somadendritic backpropagation of action potentials in cortical pyramidal cells of the awake rat. J Neurophysiol. 1998 Mar;79(3):1587-91. PMID 9497436</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Bereshpolova Y, Amitai Y, Gusev AG, Stoelzel CR, Swadlow HA. Dendritic backpropagation and the state of the awake neocortex. J Neurosci. 2007 Aug 29;27(35):9392-9. PMID 17728452 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Rózsa B, Katona G, Kaszás A, Szipöcs R, Vizi ES. Dendritic nicotinic receptors modulate backpropagating action potentials and long-term plasticity of interneurons. Eur J Neurosci. 2008 Jan;27(2):364-77. PMID 18215234 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Waters J, Schaefer A, Sakmann B. Backpropagating action potentials in neurones: measurement, mechanisms and potential functions. Prog Biophys Mol Biol. 2005 Jan;87(1):145-70. Review. PMID 15471594 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Bender VA, Feldman DE. A dynamic spatial gradient of Hebbian learning in dendrites. Neuron. 2006 Jul 20;51(2):153-5. Review. PMID 16846850</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Migliore M, Shepherd GM. Dendritic action potentials connect distributed dendrodendritic microcircuits. J Comput Neurosci. 2007 Aug 3; PMID 17674173 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Lowe G. Inhibition of backpropagating action potentials in mitral cell secondary dendrites. J Neurophysiol. 2002 Jul;88(1):64-85. PMID 12091533</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
