<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:29:17[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<scientist  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110560637">
<header>
<title>Keith Marzullo</title>
<id>14411862</id>
<revision>
<id>188016132</id>
<timestamp>2008-01-30T22:21:57Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Oddharmonic</username>
<id>37486</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>University of California, San Diego faculty</category>
<category>American computer scientists</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Keith Marzullo</b> is the inventor of <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/776615.xml">
Marzullo's algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
, which is part of the basis of the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/159886.xml">
Network Time Protocol</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 and the <link>
Windows Time Service</link>.<p>

Currently he is Professor and Chair, Department of Computer Science and Engineering at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/31927.xml">
University of California, San Diego</link></ranking>
</university>
.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Research</st>
<p>

RAMP (reliable adaptive multipath networks)</p>
<p>

GriPhyN ( Master-worker computation in a wide-area network.)</p>
<p>

MURI (Dependent failure models &amp; Collaborative backup for withstanding network catastrophes.)</p>
<p>

Mobility ( Fault-tolerance for mobile agents. &amp; Personal computational grids.)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Publications</st>
<p>

2003
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Flavio Junqueira, Ranjita Bhagwan, Keith Marzullo, Geoff Voelker and Stefan Savage, The Phoenix recovery system: Rebuilding from the ashes of an Internet catastrophe. Proceedings of the Ninth Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems, May 18-21, 2003, Lihue, HI, to appear.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Karan Bhatia, Keith Marzullo and Lorenzo Alvisi, Scalable causal message logging for wide-area environments. Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, 2003, to appear.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kjetil Jacobsen, Xianan Zhang and Keith Marzullo. Group Membership and Wide-Area Master Worker Computations. ICDCS 2003, to appear.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Flavio Junqueira and Keith Marzullo. Synchronous Consensus for Dependent Process Failures. ICDCS 2003, to appear.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dmitrii Zagorodnov, Keith Marzullo, Lorenzo Alvisi and Thomas Bressoud. Engineering fault-tolerant TCP/IP services using FT-TCP. IEEE Dependable Computing and Communications Symposium (DSN-2003), to appear.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jeremy Sussman and Keith Marzullo. The Bancomat Problem: An Example of Resource Allocation in a Partitionable Asynchronous System. <it>Journal of Theoretical Computer Science</it> 291(1), January 2003.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

2002
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lorenzo Alvisi, Karan Bhatia, and Keith Marzullo, Causality tracking in causal message-logging protocols, <it>Distributed Computing</it>, 15(1):1-15, February 2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Idit Keidar, Jeremy B. Sussman, Keith Marzullo, and Danny Dolev, Moshe: A group membership service for WANs, <it>ACM Transactions on Computer Systems</it>, 20(3): 191-238, February 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dag Johansen D, Kåre Lauvset, and Keith Marzullo. An extensible software architecture for mobile components. Proceedings Ninth Annual IEEE International Conference and Workshop on the Engineering of Computer-Based Systems. IEEE Computer Society. 2002, pp.231-237. Los Alamitos, CA, USA.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kåre Lauvset, Dag Johansen, and Keith Marzullo. Factoring mobile agents. Proceedings Ninth Annual IEEE International Conference and Workshop on the Engineering of Computer-Based Systems. IEEE Computer Society 2002, pp.253-257. Los Alamitos, CA, USA.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

2001
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lorenzo Alvisi, Thomas Bressoud, Amr El-Khasab, Keith Marzullo, and Dmitrii Zagorodnov. Wrapping Server-Side to Mask Connection Failures. INFOCOMM 2001, Anchorage, Alaska, 22-26 April 2001, pp. 329-337 Vol.1.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kåre J. Lauvset, Dag Johansen and Keith Marzullo, TOS: Kernel Support for Distributed Systems Management, Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), Las Vegas, NV, March 2001.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Karan Bhatia, Keith Marzullo, and Lorenzo Alvisi, Scalable Causal Message Logging for Wide-Area Environments, European conference on Parallel Computing (Euro-Par), Manchester, UK, August 2001.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

2000
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Meng-Jang Lin, Keith Marzullo and Stefano Massini. Gossip versus deterministically constrained flooding on small networks. In 14th International Conference on Distributed Computing (DISC 2000), Toledo, Spain, 4-6 Oct. 2000),  pp. 253-267.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jeremy Sussman, Keith Marzullo and Idit Keidar. Optimistic Virtual Synchrony. In Proceedings 19th IEEE Symposium on Reliable Distributed Systems (SRDS-2000), Nürnberg, Germany, 16-18 Oct. 2000, pp. 42-51.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Idit Keidar, Jeremy Sussman, Keith Marzullo and Danny Dolev. A client-server oriented algorithm for virtually synchronous group membership in WANs. In Proceedings 20th IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems, Taipei, Taiwan, 10-13 April 2000, pp. 356-365.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

1999
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Walfredo Cirne and Keith Marzullo. The computational Co-op: Gathering clusters into a metacomputer. Proceedings 13th International Parallel Processing Symposium and 10th Symposium on Parallel and Distributed Processing (IPPS/SPDP 1999). IEEE Computer Society 1999, pp.160-6. Los Alamitos, CA, USA.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Meng-Jang Lin and Keith Marzullo. Directional gossip: gossip in a wide area network. Dependable Computing - EDDC-3. Third European Dependable Computing Conference. Proceedings (Lecture Notes in Computer Science Vol.1667). Springer-Verlag. 1999, pp.364-79. Berlin, Germany.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Chanathip Namprempre, Jeremy Sussman, and Keith Marzullo. Implementing causal logging using OrbixWeb interception. Proceedings of the Fifth USENIX Conference on Object-Oriented Technologies and Systems (COOTS'99). USENIX Assoc. 1999, pp.57-67. Berkeley, CA, USA.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dag Johansen, Keith Marzullo, and Kåre Lauvset. An approach towards an agent computing environment. Proceedings. 19th IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems. Workshops on Electronic Commerce and Web-based Applications. Middleware. IEEE Computer Society 1999,  pp.78-83. Los Alamitos, CA, USA.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dag Johansen, Keith Marzullo, Fred B. Schneider, Kjetil Jacobsen, and Dmitrii Zagorodnov. NAP: practical fault-tolerance for itinerant computations. Proceedings. 19th IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (Cat. No.99CB37003). IEEE Computer Society 1999, pp.180-9. Los Alamitos, CA, USA.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.cs.ucsd.edu/~marzullo/</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
