<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:22:39[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Methods of website linking</title>
<id>14489292</id>
<revision>
<id>242294552</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T17:51:32Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Thingg</username>
<id>5924818</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with Alice and Bob explanations</category>
<category>Internet</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article pertains to methods of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/49547.xml">
hyperlinking</link> to/of different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link>s, often used in regard to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/187946.xml">
search engine optimization</link> (SEO).
<sec>
<st>
 Reciprocal link </st>
<p>

A <b>reciprocal link</b> is a mutual link between two objects, commonly between two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
websites</link> to ensure mutual traffic. Example: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/679079.xml">
Alice and Bob</link> have websites. If Bob's website links to Alice's website, and Alice's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link> links to Bob's website, the websites are reciprocally linked. Website owners often submit their sites to reciprocal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/1395433.xml">
link exchange</link> directories, in order to achieve higher rankings in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engines</link>. Reciprocal linking between websites is an important part of the search engine optimization process because Google uses link popularity algorithms (defined as the number of links that led to a particular page and the anchor text of the link) to rank websites for relevancy.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Three way linking </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/714684.xml">
Webring</link></it>
</indent>

Three way linking (siteA ⇒ siteB ⇒ siteC ⇒ siteA) is a special type of reciprocal linking. The attempt of this link building method is to create more "natural" links in the eyes of search engines. The value of links by three-way linking can then be better than normal reciprocal links, which are usually done between two domains.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Automated linking </st>
<p>

In order to take advantage of the need for inbound links to rank well in the search engines, a number of <b>automatic link</b> exchange services</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Link exchange </st>
<p>

An alternative to the automated linking above is a <b>link exchange</b> forum, in which members will advertise the sites that they want to get links to, and will in turn offer reciprocal or three way links back to the sites that link to them.  The links generated through such services are subject to editorial review.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 One-way linking </st>
<p>

<b>One-way link</b> is a term used among webmasters for link building methods. It is a hyperlink that points to a website without any reciprocal link; thus the link goes "one-way" in direction. It is suspected by many industry <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/542306.xml">
consultants</link> that this type of link would be considered more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/21830.xml">
natural</link> in the eyes of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engines</link>. One-way links are also called Incoming Links or Inbound Links.</p>
<p>

An effective way to build this type of one-way linking is by distributing articles through content sites and article directories. These articles generally contain an <b>About The Author</b> box that contains a one-way link back to the author's URL. When publishers use these articles, those one-way links help authors increase their page rank.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Multi-way linking </st>
<p>

<b>Multi-way linking</b> is a technique used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/398604.xml">
website promotion</link> whereby websites may create similar one-way links that each involves 3 or more partner sites. This provides each website with a one-way non-reciprocal link. This technique has evolved from reciprocal linking. According to <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo</link>, the latest <link>
search algorithms</link> have evolved to hold less favor towards websites that contain a high percentage of reciprocated links, and a higher favor towards websites that maintain a high level of incoming non-reciprocated (one-way) links.</p>
<p>

The term <it>multi-way</it> simply refers to the fact that the link exchange is between 3 or more websites, however each link is singular by only pointing to one other website. Other means of linking that may increase your web presence may also include other indirect methods such as loading images, videos, content or <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/93489.xml">
RSS</link></format>
 feeds from a third partners website.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Link campaign </st>
<p>

<b>Link campaigns</b> are a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/1618177.xml">
online marketing</link> and SEO. A business seeking to increase the number of visitors to its web site can ask its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/1552839.xml">
strategic partner</link>s, professional organizations, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/305503.xml">
 chambers of commerce</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/6884101.xml">
supplier</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/234206.xml">
customer</link>s to add links from their web sites.  A link campaign may involve mutual links back and forth between related sites, but it doesn't have to require the reciprocation of links.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Incestuous linking </st>
<p>

<b>Incestuous linking</b> is an SEO strategy used by a webmaster to promote a collection of their own web sites, or those of close friends. </p>
<p>

Due to the domination of the search engine market by Google, and its underlying PageRank technology, sites are deemed to be more important if they have large numbers of inbound links. If those inbound links are also from highly ranked web sites, they will boost the web site further. With the take-up of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/33645.xml">
blogging</link> and social networking sites such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/1270655.xml">
MySpace</link></company>
, this has resulted in lots of web sites that are inter-linked and can artificially improve the ranking of a web site without merit, i.e. without valuable or unique content.</p>
<p>

When the sites are not directly owned, this is referred to as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/714684.xml">
web clique</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Overlinking </st>
<p>

<b>Overlinking</b> in a webpage or another hyperlinked text is the characteristic of having too many hyperlinks.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

It is characterized by:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A large proportion of the words in each sentence being rendered as links.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Links that have little information content, such as linking on specific years like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/34658.xml">
1995</link>, or unnecessary linking of common words used in the common way, for which the reader can be expected to understand the word's full meaning in context, without any hyperlink help.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A link for any single term is excessively repeated in the same article. "Excessive" is usually more than one link for the same term in a line or a paragraph, since in this case one or more duplicate links will almost certainly then appear needlessly on the viewer's screen.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Underlinking </st>
<p>

The opposites of overlinking are <b>null linking</b> and <b>underlinking</b>, which are phenomena in which hyperlinks are reduced to such a degree as to remove all pointers to a likely-needed context of an unusual term, in the text-area where the term occurs. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Underlinking results whenever a reader encounters an odd term in an article (perhaps not even for the first time), and wants to briefly browse more deeply at that point, but he or she cannot without an extensive search of the article for a (possibly non-existent) instance of the linked term.</p>
<p>

The extreme case of underlinking is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/4335151.xml">
dead-end page</link>, a page with no links at all.
Usability experts discourage making dead-end pages.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Link doping </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/286747.xml">
Google bomb</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</it>
</indent>

<b>Link doping</b> refers to the practice and effects of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/52119.xml">
embedding</link> a large number of gratuitous hyperlinks on a website, in exchange for reciprocal links. Mainly used when describing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/33645.xml">
blog</link>s, link doping usually implies that a person hyperlinks to sites he or she has never visited, in return for a place on the website's <link>
blogroll</link>, for the sole purpose of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/38286.xml">
inflating</link> the apparent popularity of his or her website. Since the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/28249.xml">
search algorithm</link>s of many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/142799.xml">
web directories</link> and search engines rely on the number of hyperlinks to a website to determine its importance or influence, link doping can result in a high placement or ranking for the offending website.</p>
<p>

Originally used in an essay published in <link>
Sobriquet Magazine</link> and on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blogcritics.org/archives/2005/06/19/011301.php">
Blogcritics.org</weblink>, link doping has been confused with the related practice of excessive hyperlinking, also known as "link whoring". While the two phrases may be used interchangeably to describe gratuitous linking, link doping carries the additional connotation of deliberately striving to attain a certain level of success for one's website without having earned it through hard work (as an average athlete on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/141922.xml">
steroids</link> might perform better than a naturally gifted athlete not on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/7214191.xml">
performance-enhancing drugs</link>).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Free for all linking </st>
<p>

A <b>free for all</b> (FFA) link page is a web page set up ostensibly to improve the search engine placement of a particular web site. Webmasters typically will use  software to place a link to their site on hundreds of FFA sites, hoping that the resulting incoming links will increase the ranking of their site in search engines. Experts in SEO techniques do not place much value on FFAs. First, most FFAs only maintain a small number of links for a short time, too short for most search engines to pick up. Second, the high "human" traffic to FFA sites is almost completely other webmasters visiting the site to place their own links manually. Finally, search engine algorithms count more than link numbers, they also check relevancy which the unrelated links on FFA sites do not have. Another drawback to FFAs is the amount of spam e-mail webmasters will receive from members of the FFA. Using an FFA can be considered a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/43651.xml">
spamdexing</link></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Link popularity </st>
<p>

<b>Link popularity</b> is a measure of the quantity and quality of other web sites that link to a specific site on the World Wide Web. It is an example of the move by search engines towards off-the-page-criteria to determine quality content. In theory, off-the-page-criteria adds the aspect of impartiality to search engine rankings. Link popularity plays an important role in the visibility of a web site among the top of the search results. Indeed, some search engines require at least one or more links coming to a web site, otherwise they will drop it from their index.</p>
<p>

Search engines such as Google use a special link analysis system to rank web pages. Citations from other WWW authors help to define a site's reputation. The philosophy of link popularity is that important sites will attract many links. Content-poor sites will have difficulty attracting any links. Link popularity assumes that not all incoming links are equal, as an inbound link from a major <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/5515053.xml">
directory</link> carries more weight than an inbound link from an obscure personal home page. In other words, the quality of incoming links counts more than sheer numbers of them.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Link bait </st>
<p>

<b>Link bait</b> is any content or feature within a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link> that somehow baits viewers to place links to it from other websites. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<employee wordnetid="110053808" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/3453130.xml">
Matt Cutts</link></employee>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 defines link bait as anything "interesting enough to catch people's attention."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Link bait can be an extremely powerful form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/59252.xml">
marketing</link> as it is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/351039.xml">
viral</link> in nature.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Link bait in search engine optimization </st>
<p>

The quantity and quality of inbound links are two of the many metrics used by a search engine ranking <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> to rank a website. Link bait creation falls under the task of link building, and aims to increase the quantity of high-quality, relevant links to a website. Part of successful linkbaiting is devising a mini-PR campaign around the release of a link bait article so that bloggers and social media users are made aware and can help promote the piece in tandem. Social media traffic can generate a substantial amount of links to a single web page. Sustainable link bait is rooted in quality content.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Types of link bait </st>
<p>

Although there are no clear-cut subdivisions within link bait, many attempt to divide them into types of hooks.  This is a short list of some of the most common approaches with brief descriptions:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Informational hooks</b> - Provide information that a reader may find very useful. Some rare tips and tricks or any personal experience through which readers can benefit.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>News hooks</b> - Provide fresh information and obtain citations and links as the news spreads.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Humor hooks</b> - Tell a funny story or a joke. A bizarre picture of your subject or mocking <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/7165.xml">
cartoons</link> can also prove to be link bait.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Evil hooks</b> - Saying something unpopular or mean may also yield a lot of attention. Writing about something that is not appealing about a product or a popular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/33645.xml">
blogger</link>. Provide strong reasons for it.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Tool hooks</b> - Create some sort of tool that is useful enough that people link to it.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Widgets hooks</b> - A badge or tool, that can be placed or embedded on other websites, with a link included.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Forum signature linking </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/294813.xml">
Forum</link> signature linking is a technique used to build backlinks to a website. This is the process of using forum communities that allow outbound hyperlinks in their member's signature. This can be a fast method to build up inbound links to a website; it can also produce some targeted traffic if the website is relevant to the forum topic. It should be stated that forums using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/3766084.xml">
nofollow</link> attribute will have no actual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/187946.xml">
Search Engine Optimization</link> value.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Link broker </st>
<p>

A <b>link broker</b> is a company that allows you to buy or rent links. Link brokerages function in a few different ways but all offer the same service: selling or renting you links.  The quality of the sites, the links they sell and the prices vary greatly, as do the effects those links can have at the search engines.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Blind link </st>
<p>

Some links are created to intentionally hide the ultimate destination of a link until the user has clicked on it.  It's accomplished via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/636686.xml">
redirection</link> (possibly a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/9432908.xml">
URL shortening service</link>) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/1866859.xml">
client-side JavaScript</link>.  Blind links are usually used for deceptive or advertising reasons, and are most associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/435549.xml">
TGPs</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/13998098.xml">
Rickrolling</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Blog Comments </st>
<p>

Leaving a comment on a blog can result in a relevant do follow link to the individual's website.  Most of the time however leaving a comment on a blog turns into a no follow link, which is almost useless in the eyes of search engines such as Google and Yahoo.  On the other hand, most blog comments get clicked on by the readers of the blog if the comment is well thought out and pertains to the discussion of the other commenters and the post on the blog.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/580494.xml">
Backlink</link>: incoming links</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/202325.xml">
Deep linking</link>: linking directly to a page within another website.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/326762.xml">
Inline linking</link>: linking directly to content within another website.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/43218.xml">
Zipf's law</link></distribution>
</group>
</collection>
</arrangement>
</structure>
</law>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/7065490.xml">
Off-page optimization</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pcmag.com/encyclopedia_term/0,2542,t=overlinking&amp;i=48688,00.asp">
PCMag.com Encyclopedia</weblink>".&#32;  <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/1467304.xml">
PC Magazine</link></magazine>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-19</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<celebrity wordnetid="109903153" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/256152.xml">
Dvorak, John C.</link></celebrity>
&#32;(April 2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_zdpcm/is_200204/ai_ziff25363">
Missing Links</weblink>", <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/1467304.xml">
PC Magazine</link></magazine>
.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netmechanic.com/news/vol4/design_no9.htm">
Design Tip: Avoid Dead End Pages</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wiep.net/link-value-factors/">
Factors influencing link value</weblink>"&#32;(web).&#32;<it>Wiep.net</it>&#32;(December 2007).</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mattcutts.com/blog/seo-advice-linkbait-and-linkbaiting/">
SEO Advice: linkbait and linkbaiting</weblink>"&#32;(web).&#32;<it>Matt Cutts: Gadgets, Google, and SEO</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-09-16</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.webdesignbeach.com/beachbar/how-to-increase-website-traffic-complete-css-gallery-list">
Complete CSS Gallery for websites submission</weblink> <it>web design beach</it>, August 31, 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.searchenginejournal.com/all-wikipedia-links-are-now-nofollow/4288/">
All Wikipedia Links Are Now NOFOLLOW</weblink> <it>Search Engine Journal</it>, January 21, 2007.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
