<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:33:12[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108058098">
<header>
<title>Benecaid</title>
<id>14501434</id>
<revision>
<id>191987770</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-17T03:21:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Owch</username>
<id>3490784</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> Insurance</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Company</name>
<parameters>
<location>
<image width="22x20px" src="Flag_of_Canada.svg">
<caption>

Flag of Canada
</caption>
</image>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/64646.xml">
Toronto, Ontario</link>, <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
</location>
<company_logo>
<image width="150px" src="Benecaid.com_logo.jpg‎">
<caption>

 Benecaid.com_logo.jpg‎
</caption>
</image>
</company_logo>
<company_name>
Benecaid</company_name>
<company_slogan>
"Health Benefits. Simplified."</company_slogan>
<company_type>
Private</company_type>
<foundation>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link></foundation>
<industry>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/433425.xml">
Financial Services</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
Insurance</link>)</industry>
<products>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/14507951.xml">
Health spending accounts</link> - both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/14528159.xml">
Health and Welfare Trust</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/14539602.xml">
Private Health Services Plan</link> ,<link>
Administrative Services Only</link>,</products>
<homepage>
http://www.benecaid.com/</homepage>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>Benecaid</b> is a Canadian financial services company focused on the delivery and administration of employee health benefit solutions. They focus on the administration of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/14507951.xml">
health spending accounts</link> (HSAs) - in the form of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/14528159.xml">
Health and Welfare Trust</link> (HWT) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/14539602.xml">
Private Health Services Plan</link> (PHSPs).  They also provide Administrative Services Only (ASO) plans for group health benefits. Benecaid has over 1,800 clients across <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
 and is based in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/64646.xml">
Toronto</link></village>
.
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

Founded in 2000, the company was created by small business owners frustrated with the group health benefits options available to Canadian employers.  With a team of Chartered Accountants and Lawyers, they researched the IT bulletins released by <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/518062.xml">
Canada Revenue Agency</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
 (CRA), specifically those related to HSAs (IT-85R2)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.  They have since developed a suite of financial products for small to medium sized busiensses focused on cost-containment and employee appreciation.  They are a strong supporter of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/7304558.xml">
Consumer driven health care</link> where employers provide employees with greater involvement and control in their day-to-day healthcare spending - particularly through an HSA.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Third-Party Administration </st>
<p>

The company is a third-party administrator or TPA.  In recent years, the Canadian health benefits market has seen a significant increase in the number of TPAs entering the market.  Today, according to a recent article in Benefits Canada, TPAs represent around 10% of the group health insurance market in Canada.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Branding </st>
<p>

In addition to their products, the company is known for their unique branding initiative within the Canadian Insurance industry.  Launched in 2006, the company's new brand features a bright green rectangle logo with the slogan "Health Benefits.  Simplified".  The goal of Benecaid's marketing team was to create an identity differentiating themselves from the traditional and conservative insurers dominating the Canadian economy.  Their "Food for Thought" campaign uses minimalist ads featuring fruits and vegetables with witty tag-lines linking the image to an issue being faced by small-medium sized employers.  For example, in one ad, a picture of an onion appears with the tag-line "Insurance Premiums can make you want to cry.  Stop crying.  Start Saving." </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Technology </st>
<p>

Given the company's recent entry into the market, technology has been easier to implement versus many of the traditional carriers with multiple systems.  The third-pary administration and insurance services industry is very manual requiring a large investment in human capital. Benecaid has been able to build their platform from scratch, allowing for many of the manual processes to be automated.  With automation of the services to support their products, the company has promoted themselves as a lower cost alternative to other carriers.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
IT-85R2 - Health &amp; Welfare Trusts for Employees, Revenue Canada, July 31, 1986.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Health Trusts Can Help Keep the Bottom Line Fit, Libby Znaimer, Financial Post,  
Published: Saturday, November 04, 2006</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</company>
</article>
