<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:34:20[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Jumpstart (Solaris)</title>
<id>14562589</id>
<revision>
<id>195174800</id>
<timestamp>2008-03-01T20:11:05Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Unix software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Jumpstart</b> is a computer network installation tool set used by the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/46145.xml">
Solaris (operating system)</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
.
<sec>
<st>
 Usage </st>
<p>

Jumpstart is used to manage operating system installation in many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
Information technology</link> environments (corporate and otherwise) where Solaris operating system computers are widely used.  It can provide easier installation (minor setup on central server, then one command on an installation "client" system to start it installing).  It also allows completely consistent system installation on many systems over time - each install can have the exact same system configuration and software tools.  Alternatively, different types of systems can be installed for different purposes, in each case with consistent installations for a given defined type.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Structure </st>
<p>

Jumpstart consists of two main parts: network booting of a system, and then network installation.</p>
<p>

Network booting proceeds similarly to Solaris' standard network booting capabilities.  A Jumpstart and network booting server is set up on the same local network as the system(s) to be installed.  Technically, the network boot and install servers can be separate functions, but they are typically the same system.</p>
<p>

Once a client system begins the Jumpstart process, it then accesses the operating system component software packages stored on the Jumpstart server, usually but not exclusively using <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/51252.xml">
Network File System</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 or <b>NFS</b>.</p>
<p>

Those packages, and optionally additional tools or applications, are automatically installed, and then the system is rebooted.  Some additional configuration may be manually performed, or the system's configuration may be set up completely automatically.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dlc.sun.com/pdf/820-0177/820-0177.pdf">
Solaris 10 8/07 Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</weblink>, accessed Dec 4, 2007</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
JumpStart Enterprise Toolkit</link> - JET, a JumpStart Framework that can deliver Solaris and other OSes.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/14562757.xml">
Kickstart (Linux)</link> - a similar, newer tool used on some <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 distributions, primarily but not exclusively <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/556778.xml">
Red Hat Enterprise Linux</link></O>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
