<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:34:51[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<body  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107965085">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<social_group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107950920">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<administration  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108164585">
<header>
<title>Akshara network</title>
<id>14584210</id>
<revision>
<id>226612917</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-19T11:18:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cydebot</username>
<id>1215485</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Non-governmental organizations</category>
<category>Non-governmental organisations based in India</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>infobox software</name>
<parameters>
<screenshot>
<image width="102px" src="Akshara_Network_Logo.png‎">
</image>
</screenshot>
<website>
http://www.aksharakriti.org/</website>
<name>
Akshara Network</name>
<caption>
Akshara Network's logo</caption>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>Akshara Network</b> (known as <b>Akshara</b> or <b>Akshara Network for Development Support Services</b>) is a not-for-profit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/385745.xml">
development</link> support organization working in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
, is initiated by practicing development management professionals to fulfill the need for affordable and timely professional support to individuals and organizations in livelihoods<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> development sector.</p>
<p>

Akshara has contributed to the development sector the <link>
LEAP Process</link> which is a methodical and complete process for development project evaluations and the <link>
Livelihood Framework</link> that explains how development process must function in order to succeed.  </p>
<p>

Akshara's head quarters is located in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/37534.xml">
Hyderabad</link>, <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
Andhra Pradesh</link></legal_power>
 <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
, but operates through out India.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Mission</st>
<p>

To promote, support, sustain and offer appropriate support services to development organizations/ groups/individuals and government organizations for the purpose of contributing to professionalism in the development sector, integrated human development and ecological integrity/security.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Core Philosophy</st>
<p>

Application of management concepts, tools and techniques to development in general and Livelihoods Enhancement for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/126191.xml">
Poor</link>, in particular and working towards <b>Livelihoods Management</b> as an independent discipline.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Focus &amp; Values</st>
<p>

Our focus and Values can best be summarized as follows:</p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<row>
<header>
Thematic Focus</header>
<header>
Guiding Values</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Micro-finance</col>
<col>
Hope that poverty can be eradicated</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Tribal Issues</col>
<col>
Team work/learning</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Watershed Management</col>
<col>
Faith in the capacity of people</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Poverty Reduction</col>
<col>
Significance</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Rural Livelihoods: Four Arrows</col>
<col>
People’s collective effort</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Rural-Urban Continuum</col>
<col>
Excellence</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Eco-fragile and Marginalized Areas</col>
<col>
Learning Organization</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Cooperation and People’s Institutions</col>
<col>
Integrity</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Organization</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Composed of Four Units</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Akshara Gurukulam</b> is a school that offers various programs on Livelihoods Management.  It aims at sourcing, creating, nurturing and developing the development management professionals with clear bias towards the poor to improve their livelihoods and livelihoods options. The curriculum comprises classroom segment + field work.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Akshara Livelihoods Private Limited</b> is a Consulting arm of Akshara Network. Its consulting focus areas include Visioning, Strategic Planning, Project Design for Poverty Reduction and Livelihoods Enhancements Projects, Custom-made trainings, Module Development, Handholding Support, etc.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Akshara Jobs</b> focus is to offer job/employment to rural youth by linking up with various employment opportunities. This happens by matching employers' job specifications and the individual's capabilities, skill -building for the individual where required, matching employer’s need with individuals’ collective/ organization etc.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Akshara Books</b> is a new initiative with focus on Livelihoods Framework, livelihoods concepts and trends, application of management concepts in livelihoods and poverty reduction efforts.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Mentoring and Facilitating Roles</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Akshara Sakthi</b> is a campaign to mobilize livelihoods volunteer force comprising various individuals and organizations into livelihoods management agenda to contribute towards enhancing the livelihoods of the poor in their own way. Currently 1000 volunteers are part of Akshara Sakthi.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Chelama LPC</b> (Livelihoods Professionals Collective) provides a platform for solidarity, security and learning for the livelihoods professionals/workers. This organisation offers services like savings, mutual aid, e-mail, web space, refresher trainings and sourcing work for professionals etc.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Endogenous Tourism at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/12682149.xml">
Pochampally</link></b> in partnership with GOI, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/82256.xml">
UNDP</link>, Andhra Pradesh Tourism and Nalgonda District Administration. As a software implementing partner Akshara is promoting weaving and tourism based livelihoods. Chenetha Gurukulam is also coming up.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Community Livelihoods Facilitators Forum</b> is an organisation of community level animators with livelihoods facilitation/support skills in general and at the grassroots level in particular. The Community Livelihoods Facilitators (CLFs) offer livelihood support services to required programs/organizations.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Magazines</b> - Jeevanopadulu (Telugu) / Livelihoods (English) - is aimed to fulfill the need for authentic knowledge, inputs and updates in livelihoods domain in particular and development sector in general. The magazine features case studies, livelihoods concepts, issues, options, interventions, current/changing trends and impact on livelihoods, interviews from social entrepreneurs, activists, career options etc</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Livelihoods Support Organizations</b> (LSOs) receive visioning, institution building, strategic planning, capacity building, project evaluation and monitoring and other mentoring support from Akshara Mentors. LSO franchisee arrangements are supported. LSO networks with shared livelihoods vision are facilitated. Of the 10 LSOs that received support three became self-reliant.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Field Projects/Partnerships</b> are established with <b>community based organizations</b> (CBOs), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/3742142.xml">
Non-Government Organizations</link> (NGOs) and PRIs for experimentation, shared learning and praxis.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Livelihood Framework</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Akshara-livelihoods-framework.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Framework Diagram
</caption>
</image>
Akshara Network interventions focus on improving the livelihoods of the poor by increasing their stock of and access to Six Capitals natural, physical, social, human, financial and spiritual and by bringing appropriate changes in the Four Contexts ecological, techno-economic, distribution, and income-expenditure pattern that result in Four Arrows- Increased income, Decreased expenditure (cost, time, energy), Increased Employment and Opportunities, Decreased/ diversified risk(s).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
LEAP Process</st>
<p>

<b>Livelihoods Enhancement Action Plan</b> (LEAP)
A livelihoods intervention must be based on the appreciation of the current reality with respect to the four arrows, six capitals and four contexts of the households, the community, village and surrounding areas. This needs to be done in a participatory manner so that the assessment, analysis and planning is done by the villagers. The process also should lead to the identification of the knowledge/skill/resources that are outside the community and need to be explored further. Where required, the process should also lead to the identification of the community organization required. To achieve this, the first step in the LEAP processes is general discussion with the community about the existing socioeconomic and physical environment of a village. This also includes a transect walk and appreciating the techno-economic context, including the markets and their access. For deeper understanding of the available assets and resources of the community, the following participatory exercises (often called LEAP tools) are used:
Social map, Livelihoods analysis and prioritization, Resource map, Value-chain analysis, Traded-in &amp; traded-out, Income &amp; Expenditure pattern</p>
<p>

In addition to the above, farming systems analysis, local market analysis, analysis of emerging opportunity in wider markets, institutional analysis, etc., are also undertaken. </p>
<p>

The analysis would point to various gaps and opportunities, which would have to be prioritized for further study. The interventions would then be a set of simultaneous, supplementary and complementary interventions at individual, household, sub-habitation, habitation, supra-habitation, cluster or policy level. The institutional arrangements for the interventions need to be worked out and the acquisition of resources planned. Resource may be required even at the planning stage and a case may have to be made to acquire the same. Of particular importance would be the access to technical and professional
services during the planning stage, to make the process truly community driven. The emphasis needs to be on process and building the capacities of the target communities. Moreover, the processes need to build an environment congenial for cooperation between the target community with those others present in the village and around.</p>
<p>

Among LEAP tools, resource map, traded-in &amp; traded-out, value-chain analysis, livelihoods analysis and farming systems analysis can provide insights into the natural capital and the environmental and ecological context.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Activities So Far</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Working with National Organizations such as <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/33309.xml">
World Bank</link></association>
</institute>
 and CARE India<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Working with 100 organizations - CBOs, PRIs, Development Organizations, Donors, Govt Organizations/Projects throughout 12 states</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Inducted over 10000 + individuals (professionals, community leaders, resource persons) into Livelihoods Thought</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Outreach of influence  20 + million poor families though support of various projects</entry>
</list>
</p>


<ss1>
<st>
Visioning</st>
<p>

Akshara helps organizations to develop visions and their long-term future plans. The organizations supported range from CBOs, NGOs, Networks of NGOs, organizations implementing large Government projects and movements. Akshara has also visioning for <politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<party wordnetid="108256968" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/3938040.xml">
Lok Satta</link></party>
</social_relation>
</politics>
.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Project Design for Poverty Reduction Projects</st>
<p>

Akshara provides support for multi-lateral and bi-lateral large scale poverty reduction and livelihoods projects including design and preparation of project implementation plans. Support so far includes projects in 7 states (<legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
Andhra Pradesh</link></legal_power>
, <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/29918.xml">
Tamil Nadu</link></city>
, <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/442482.xml">
Bihar</link></legal_power>
, <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/14190.xml">
Himachal Pradesh</link></legal_power>
, <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/47945.xml">
Madhya Pradesh</link></legal_power>
, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/34040.xml">
West Bengal</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</region>
, <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/26291.xml">
Rajasthan</link></legal_power>
) and inducting key staff into the project process in these projects.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Project Design for Livelihood Support Projects</st>
<p>

This includes support for MP Local Area Development Schemes, Watershed Development Projects, multi sectoral Drought Proofing Projects, Artisanal Clusters Development Programs, district level livelihoods plans, livelihoods scoping, support for collectives in various sub-sectors/livelihoods etc.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Long Term Support</st>
<p>

SERP (<b>Velugu</b>) - Managing Livelihoods Framework and 12 Billion <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/228246.xml">
Rupee</link> Community Investment Fund
<b>UNIFEM-WEEM-IGK</b>, <b>UNDP-ETP</b>, <b>IWMI-Water Sector Analysis</b> in Andhra Pradesh - Handholding Support
HelpAge India<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/31161.xml">
Tsunami</link> Project for Elders developing institutional networks for the care of the elderly
<b>Shristi Baitharini</b> river-basin project understanding and supporting livelihoods around river-basin
Livelihoods and NRM support consortium of <b>APRLP</b> Member
NREGA-APREGS Technical support partnership
PRIs, CBOs, field partner NGOs, etc.. Long term partnerships</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Consulting</st>
<p>

Country Report (with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/532257.xml">
IIMA</link>) Changing Business Environment and <b>Dairy Cooperatives</b> in India
Monitoring/Evaluation/Impact Assessment of livelihoods, watersheds, micro-finance, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/3667854.xml">
micro-enterprise</link>,
tsunami and migration projects; and social assessment
Livelihoods Assessment and Scoping, LEAPs, Value-chain Analyses and Sub-sector Analyses
Participatory Poverty Analysis contribution to World Development Report 2000/01<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Trainings and Module Development</st>
<p>

Modules in various aspects of livelihoods including institutions, marketing, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/167854.xml">
micro-credit</link> planning, subsectors,
value-chains etc., and training
Training in applying management concept to livelihoods and development domain
Livelihoods learning programs for community coordinators, livelihoods associates, project managers,
resource persons, NGO leaders, community facilitators and community leaders
Foundation programs in livelihoods analysis, planning, tools and interventions; Sector/sub-sector training
Training in Planning, Monitoring &amp; Learning, Project Management, Enterprise Promotion etc.
Training to Capacity Building Organizations of Poverty Reduction and Livelihoods Projects
Induction to Poverty Reduction and Livelihoods Project Staff</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Milestones</st>
<p>

1998 - Akshara came into being on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/22527.xml">
October 2</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/34647.xml">
1998</link>
1999 - Akshara Formally registered on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/20223.xml">
March 17</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link> (Registration # 1720/99 under Public Societies’ Registration Act 1350F).
2003 - Akshara Gurukulam a development management school for enhancing the livelihoods of the poor.
2007 - Akshara Livelihoods Private Limited (ALPL) came into existence.
2007 - Akshara Jobs catering to skilled, semi-skilled but uniformed rural youth.
2007 - Chelama LPC registered.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Founder</st>
<p>

G.Murali is an Engineer-rural management professional with 20 years of experience. Murali has worked with National Dairy Development Board, Institute of Rural Management, Anand, Girijan Cooperative Corporation, National Tree Growers’ Cooperative Federation, OUTREACH, Naandi Foundation and Society for Elimination of Rural Poverty. Experience is in the areas of Strategic Planning, Monitoring and Evaluation, Institution Building, Tribal Development, Poverty Projects, Livelihoods of the Poor and Application of Management Concepts in Development.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
livelihoods  means how people make their living in addition to the needs to have reliable sources of food, income, and employment.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aksharakriti.org/component/option,com_docman/task,doc_download/gid,17/Itemid,31">
http://www.aksharakriti.org/component/option,com_docman/task,doc_download/gid,17/Itemid,31</weblink>Livelihoods Framework detailed report(pdf)</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.careindia.org">
http://www.careindia.org</weblink> Care India web site</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.helpageindia.org">
http://www.helpageindia.org</weblink> HelpAge India website</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=1&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fweb.worldbank.org%2FWBSITE%2FEXTERNAL%2FTOPICS%2FEXTPOVERTY%2F0%2C%2CcontentMDK%3A20194762~pagePK%3A148956~piPK%3A216618~theSitePK%3A336992%2C00.html&amp;ei=W8pXR-mTM6DqsgKjzNH4CA&amp;usg=AFQjCNHITp_hb0AeaGoOAL1vvwd8PwXghw&amp;sig2=gf4ay4wvlvHrkpPq1sytFw">
http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=1&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fweb.worldbank.org%2FWBSITE%2FEXTERNAL%2FTOPICS%2FEXTPOVERTY%2F0%2C%2CcontentMDK%3A20194762~pagePK%3A148956~piPK%3A216618~theSitePK%3A336992%2C00.html&amp;ei=W8pXR-mTM6DqsgKjzNH4CA&amp;usg=AFQjCNHITp_hb0AeaGoOAL1vvwd8PwXghw&amp;sig2=gf4ay4wvlvHrkpPq1sytFw</weblink> World Development Report 2000/2001</entry>
</reflist>
 </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aksharakriti.org/">
Akshara's web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lpc.co.in/">
Livelihoods Professionals Collective's web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kalanetha.com/">
Bhoodan Pochampally's web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.social-impact.org/resources.asp/">
Social Impact's web site</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/64959.xml">
Poverty</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.undp.org.in/">
UNDP India</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/">
The UN Millennium Development Goals</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</administration>
</group>
</social_group>
</organization>
</body>
</article>
