<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:37:09[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<software  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106566077">
<director  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="110014939">
<header>
<title>KnowledgeWorkshop</title>
<id>14674174</id>
<revision>
<id>193110026</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-21T20:33:37Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Malcolma</username>
<id>320496</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Personal information managers</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Software</name>
<parameters>
<frequently_updated>
yes</frequently_updated>
<genre>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/283329.xml">
Personal Information Manager</link></genre>
<screenshot>
<image width="250px" src="KnowledgeWorkshopScreenshotShowingHighlighterAndNote.jpg">
</image>
</screenshot>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kworkshop.com">
KnowledgeWorkshop</weblink></website>
<operating_system>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link></operating_system>
<caption>
Multi-tabbed web-browser showing highlighted text and annotation, note, navigation tree and link to a related item.</caption>
<released>
?</released>
<developer>
Learning Management Solutions LLC.</developer>
<name>
KnowledgeWorkshop</name>
<programming_language>
?</programming_language>
<language>
?</language>
<license>
proprietary</license>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>KnowledgeWorkshop</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/11592.xml">
freeware</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/283329.xml">
personal information manager</link> for use on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> operating system. It enables diverse information types (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/34063.xml">
web pages</link>, documents, local files, tasks, e-mails, notes etc.) to be managed from one place. The user interface consists of a multi-tabbed web browser for viewing information, with a navigation tree for accessing the knowledgebase. Web pages (or selections from pages) can be dragged from the browser into the tree to create new items, as can files and folders from <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/445959.xml">
Windows Explorer</link></software>
. These items can be references to web pages, captured snapshots of web pages, clippings from web pages, as well as references to local files, e-mails, notes, tasks, discussion postings etc. Current tools force users to switch from one application to another to view different types of information. Each time the user may have to waste time searching for the particular file or document to open. The concept behind KnowledgeWorkshop is to improve a user's efficiency by breaking down these divisions, and having all information about a particular subject together.<p>

In the process of turning information into knowledge, the human mind interconnects it with related information, prioritizes and personalizes it (adds own <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
meta data</link>). KnowledgeWorkshop supports this process by means of:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the web-page highlighter tool (just like multi-colored highlighting pens) which also enables annotations to be made (akin to scribbling in the margins of a book)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 user-defined categories</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 keywords: these are harvested from web pages, and can also be added manually.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 user-defined or custom attributes (e.g. you can add "color", "price" etc. to information items) and then compare items by these attributes in a tabular report.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Information items can appear in multiple places in the navigation tree (multiparenting)for convenience and flexibility of organization, but without the overhead of maintaining multiple copies of the content.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Related items in different parts of the navigation tree can be connected using "associations", which can also convey meaningful information about the nature of the relationship. Associated items can be viewed simultaneously, and a path through the network of associated items can be followed by clicking on the associated item links.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

It has a built-in support for references/citations so that web page clippings can be traced back to their source.
To facilitate sharing, an export function enables information to be published to either a folder, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/53289.xml">
FTP</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/33455.xml">
web server</link>, or in a form suitable for importing into another user's KnowledgeWorkshop knowledgebase.
KnowledgeWorkshop is produced by Learning Management Solutions LLC.</p>

</bdy>
</director>
</software>
</article>
