<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:35:27[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<technique  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105665146">
<know-how  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105616786">
<method  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105660268">
<header>
<title>Secure communication</title>
<id>1467336</id>
<revision>
<id>238154153</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-13T14:46:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>TWCarlson</username>
<id>2880105</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Espionage techniques</category>
<category>Internet privacy</category>
<category>Secure communication</category>
<category>Secret broadcasting</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Secure communication</b> includes means by which people can share information with varying degrees of certainty that third parties cannot know what was said. Other than communication spoken face to face out of possibility of listening, it is probably safe to say that no communication is guaranteed secure in this sense, although practical limitations such as legislation, resources, technical issues (interception and encryption), and the sheer volume of communication are limiting factors to surveillance. <p>

The purpose of this article is to describe the various means by which security is sought and compromised, the differing kinds of security possible, and the current means and their degree of security readily available.</p>
<p>

With many communications taking place over long distance and mediated by technology, and increasing awareness of the importance of interception issues, technology and its compromise are at the heart of this debate. For this reason, this article focusses on communications mediated or intercepted by technology.</p>
<p>

Also see <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/58608.xml">
Trusted Computing</link></it>, an approach under present development that achieves security in general at the potential cost of compelling obligatory trust in corporate and governmental bodies.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Users and needs</st>
<p>

Many forms of everyday communication are "reasonably" secure, thus, we do not assume telephone calls are intercepted when we use them. However in some areas such as online intellectual property rights, legal, criminal, political and commercial communications, this assumption is inadequate.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<p>

In 1898, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/21473.xml">
Nikola Tesla</link></scientist>
</person>
 demonstrated a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/233091.xml">
radio controlled</link> boat in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<scene wordnetid="108645963" confidence="0.8">
<venue wordnetid="108677628" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/75129.xml">
Madison Square Garden</link></venue>
</scene>
</location>
</area>
</landmark>
</point>
</center>
</position>
</region>
 that allowed secure communication between transmitter and receiver.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

One of the most famous forms of secure communication was the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/740918.xml">
Green Hornet</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
. During WWII, Winston Churchill had to make vital calls to the President of the United States, Franklin D. Roosevelt. These calls talked about such things as shipping and troop movements. At first, the calls were made using a radio phone as this was thought to be secure. Unfortunately, due to the Nazis having a listening station in Holland they were able to hear every last word. As soon as it was realised they stopped using the radio phone and started work on a whole new system, the Green Hornet. It worked by playing a copy of white noise over the conversation and then an identical copy was subtracted on the other end of the line. This meant that anyone listening in would just hear white noise but as the only two identical copies were held with the Prime Minister and the President the conversation was clear to them. As secrecy was paramount, the location of the Green Hornet was only known by the people who built it and Winston Churchill, and if anyone did see him entering the room it was kept in, all they would see was the Prime Minister entering a closet labeled 'Broom Cupboard.' It is the said that because of the way the Green Hornet works it is not able to be beaten, even today.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Nature and limitations of secure communication</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Types of security</st>
<p>

Security can be broadly categorised under the following headings, with examples:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hiding the content or nature of a communication</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/5225.xml">
Code</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
Encryption</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/28733.xml">
Steganography</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Identity Based</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hiding the parties to a communication (prevention of identification, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/181382.xml">
anonymity</link>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/3229135.xml">
Crowds</link>" and similar anonymous group structures.  i.e. it is difficult to identify who said what when it comes from a "crowd".</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Anonymous communication devices (unregistered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/19644137.xml">
cellphone</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/304873.xml">
Internet cafe</link>s)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/78768.xml">
Anonymous proxies</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Hard to trace <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/25750.xml">
routing</link> methods (through unauthorised 3rd party systems, or relays)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hiding the fact that a communication takes place</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 "Security by obscurity" (similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/13616706.xml">
needle in a haystack</link>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Random traffic (creating random data flow in order that the presence of genuine communication is harder to detect and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/480015.xml">
traffic analysis</link> less reliable)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Each of the three is important, and depending on the circumstances any of these may be critical. For example, if a communication is not readily identifiable, then it is unlikely to attract attention for identification of parties, and the mere fact a communication has taken place (regardless of content) is often enough by itself to establish an evidential link in legal prosecutions. It is also important with computers, to be sure where the security is applied, and what is covered.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Borderline cases </st>
<p>

A further category, which touches upon secure communication, is software intended to take advantage of security openings at the end-points. This software category includes <link>
trojan horse</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/57829.xml">
keylogger</link>s and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/28951.xml">
spyware</link>.</p>
<p>

These types of activity are usually addressed with everyday mainstream security methods, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/268622.xml">
antivirus</link> software, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1362296.xml">
firewall</link>s, programs that identify or neutralize <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/2616.xml">
adware</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/28951.xml">
spyware</link>, as well as web filtering programs such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/245025.xml">
proxomitron</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/199697.xml">
privoxy</link> which check all web pages being read and identify and remove common nuisances contained. As a rule they fall under <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
computer security</link> rather than secure communications.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Tools used to obtain security</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Encryption</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
Encryption</link></it>
</indent>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Crypto_key.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Cryptography&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
Encryption</link> is where data is rendered hard to read by an unauthorised party. Since encryption can be made extremely hard to break, many communication methods either use deliberately weaker encryption than possible, or have <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/360788.xml">
backdoor</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
s inserted to permit rapid decryption. In some cases government authorities have required backdoors be installed in secret. Many methods of encryption are also subject to "man in the middle" attack whereby a third party who can 'see' the establishment of the secure communication is made privy to the encryption method, this would apply for example to interception of computer use at an ISP. Provided it is correctly programmed, sufficiently powerful, and the keys not intercepted, encryption would usually be considered secure. The article on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/5749.xml">
key size</link> examines the key requirements for certain degrees of encryption security.</p>
<p>

The encryption can be implemented in way to require the use of encryption, i.e. if encrypted communication is impossible then no traffic is sent, or opportunisticly.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/4299490.xml">
Opportunistic encryption</link> is a lower security method to generally increase the percentage of generic traffic which is encrypted.  This is analogous to beginning every conversation with "Do you speak <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/48877.xml">
Navajo</link>?"  If the response is affirmative, then the conversation proceedes in Navajo, otherwise it uses the common language of the two speakers.  This method does not generally provide <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authentication</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/181382.xml">
anonymity</link> but it does protect the content of the conversation from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/372656.xml">
eavesdropping</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Steganography</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/28733.xml">
Steganography</link> ("hidden writing") is the means by which data can be hidden within other more innocuous data. Thus a watermark proving ownership embedded in the data of a picture, in such a way it is hard to find or remove unless you know how to find it. or, for communication, the hiding of important data (such as a telephone number) in apparently innocuous data (an MP3 music file). An advantage of steganography is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/354643.xml">
plausible deniability</link>, that is, unless one can prove the data is there (which is usually not easy), it is deniable that the file contains any. <it>(Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/28733.xml">
Steganography</link>)</it></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Identity based networks</st>
<p>

Unwanted or malicious behavior is possible on the web since it is inherently anonymous. True identity based networks replace the ability to remain anonymous and are inherently more trustworthy since the identity of the sender and recipient are known. (The telephone system is an example of an identity based network.) </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Anonymized networks</st>
<p>

Recently, anonymous networking has been used to secure communications. In principle, a large number of users running the same system, can have communications routed between them in such a way that it is very hard to detect what any complete message is, which user sent it, and where it is ultimately going from or to. Examples are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/3229135.xml">
Crowds</link>, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/18582150.xml">
Tor</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/538434.xml">
I2P</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/2070675.xml">
Mixminion</link></software>
, various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/454322.xml">
anonymous P2P</link> networks, and others.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Anonymous communication devices</st>
<p>

In theory, an unknown device would not be noticed, since so many other devices are in use. This is not altogether the case in reality, due to the presence of systems such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/1079134.xml">
Carnivore</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/9282.xml">
Echelon</link> which can monitor communications over entire networks, and the fact that the far end may be monitored as before. Examples include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/163387.xml">
payphone</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/304873.xml">
Internet cafe</link>, etc.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods used to "break" security</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Bugging</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/87235.xml">
Covert listening device</link></method>
</device>
</know-how>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</technique>
</it>
</indent>
The placing covertly of monitoring and/or transmission devices either within the communication device, or in the premises concerned.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Computers (general) </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
Computer security</link></it>
</indent>
Any security obtained from a computer is limited by the many ways it can be compromised - by hacking, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/57829.xml">
keystroke logging</link>, <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/360788.xml">
backdoor</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
s, or even in extreme cases by monitoring the tiny electrical signals given off by keyboard or monitors to reconstruct what is typed or seen (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/184781.xml">
TEMPEST</link>, which is quite complex).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Laser reading of windows</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/2244025.xml">
Laser microphone</link></it>
</indent>
In certain cases individuals have had private spoken communications intercepted by means of laser. This usually involves a sensitive laser directed at a window, capable of picking up the tiny glass movements caused by sounds, and conversion back to speech.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Systems offering a degree of secure communication</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Anonymous cellphones</st>
<p>

Cellphones can easily be obtained, but are also easily traced and "tapped". There is no (or only limited) encryption, the phones are traceable - often even when switched off - since the phone and SIM card broadcast their International Mobile Subscriber Identity (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/105868.xml">
IMSI</link>). It is possible for a cellphone company to turn on some cellphones when the user is unaware and use the microphone to listen in on you, and according to James Atkinson, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/16547955.xml">
counter-surveillance</link> specialist cited in the same source, "Security-conscious corporate executives routinely remove the batteries from their cell phones" since many phones' software can be used "as-is", or modified, to enable transmission without user awareness <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.com.com/FBI+taps+cell+phone+mic+as+eavesdropping+tool/2100-1029_3-6140191.html">
http://news.com.com/FBI+taps+cell+phone+mic+as+eavesdropping+tool/2100-1029_3-6140191.html</weblink> and the user can be located within a small distance using signal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/207174.xml">
triangulation</link> and now using built in GPS features for newer models. <criminal wordnetid="109977660" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/161570.xml">
Pablo Escobar</link></criminal>
 was assassinated after he was located by using his cellphone signal.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Landlines</st>
<p>

Analogue landlines are not encrypted and are trivially tapped. Such tapping requires physical access to the line which is easily obtained from a number of places, e.g. distribution points, cabinets and the exchange itself. Tapping a landline in this way would also enable the attacker to make calls which appear to originate from the tapped line.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Anonymous Internet</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/181382.xml">
Anonymity</link></it>
</indent>
Using a third party system of any kind (payphone, Internet cafe) is often quite secure, however if that system is used to access known locations (a known email account or 3rd party) then it may be tapped at the far end, or noted, and this will remove any security benefit obtained. Some countries also impose mandatory registration of Internet cafe users.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/78768.xml">
Anomymous proxies</link> are another common type of protection, which allow one to access the net via a third party (often in a different country) and make tracing difficult. Note that there is seldom any guarantee that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/157935.xml">
plaintext</link> is not tappable, nor that the proxy does not keep its own records of users or entire dialogs. As a result anonymous proxies are a generally useful tool but may not be as secure as other systems whose security can be better assured. Their most common use is to prevent a record of the originating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/14921.xml">
IP</link>, or address, being left on the target site's own records. Typical anonymous proxies are found at both regular websites such as Anonymizer.com and spynot.com, as well as on proxy sites which maintain up to date lists of large numbers of temporary proxies in operation.</p>
<p>

A recent development on this theme arises when wireless Internet connections ("<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/63973.xml">
Wi-fi</link>") are left in their unsecured state. The effect of this is that any person in range of the base unit can <link>
piggyback</link> the connection - that is, use it without the owner being aware. Since many connections are left open in this manner anyway, situations where piggybacking might arise (wilful or unaware) have successfully led to a defense in some cases, since it makes it difficult to prove the owner of the connection  was the downloader, or had knowledge of the use to which unknown others might be putting their connection. An example of this was the Tammie Marson case, where neighbours and anyone else might have been the culprit in the sharing of copyright files.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Conversely, in other cases, people deliberately seek out businesses and households with unsecured connections, for illicit and anonymous Internet usage, or simply to obtain free <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/15612827.xml">
bandwidth</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Programs offering more secure communications</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/424589.xml">
Skype</link></software>
 - secure voice over Internet, secure chat. Uses 128-bit AES (256-bit is the standard) and 1024-bit assymmetrical protocols to exchange initial keys (which is considered relatively weak by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/21888.xml">
NIST</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>). Proprietary. No information on backdoors. An article in 2004 suggested that Skype has relatively weak encryption, but more recent analyses, one by invitation and one by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/18935488.xml">
reverse engineering</link> presented at <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<meeting wordnetid="108307589" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<convention wordnetid="108309086" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/145578.xml">
DEF CON</link></group>
</convention>
</gathering>
</meeting>
</social_group>
 2005, both conclude that Skype uses encryption effectively. Criticism focuses upon its proprietary "black box" design, its relatively short (1536 bit) keys, excessive bandwidth use of user <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/3039014.xml">
supernode</link>s, and excessive trust of other computers able to "speak Skype". <it>(See <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/424589.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Security%22])">
Skype#Security</link></software>
)''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/4401160.xml">
Zfone</link> is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link> secure voice over Internet program, by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<disputant wordnetid="109615465" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<reformer wordnetid="110515194" confidence="0.8">
<militant wordnetid="110315837" confidence="0.8">
<cryptanalyst wordnetid="109981540" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<decoder wordnetid="109995398" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/23486.xml">
Phil Zimmermann</link></decoder>
</scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</cryptanalyst>
</militant>
</reformer>
</person>
</disputant>
</physical_entity>
, the creator of <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/23080.xml">
PGP</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
. As of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/4586467.xml">
April 2006</link> it is being <link>
beta tested</link> prior to release.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 pbxnsip is a SIP-based PBX that uses TLS and SRTP for encrypting the voice traffic. In contrast to other proprietary protocols, the protocol is open so that devices from independent vendors can be used. The encryption includes the relay of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/55951.xml">
Instant Messaging</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/50247.xml">
Presence</link> information as well as the management interface.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Secure <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/14730.xml">
IRC</link></group>
</community>
</gathering>
</social_group>
 and web chat - Some IRC clients and systems use security such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/187813.xml">
SSL</link>. This is not standardised. Likewise some web chat clients such as Yahoo Messenger use secure communications on their web based program. Again the security of these is unverified, and it is likely the communication is not secured other than to and from the client.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/89388.xml">
Trillian</link> - offers secure IM facility, however appears to have weaknesses in key exchange which would enable a "man in the middle" attack with ease. Proprietary, no information on backdoors.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/1915691.xml">
Off-the-Record Messaging</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 is a plugin which adds end-to-end encryption and authentication as well as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/2191130.xml">
Perfect forward secrecy</link> to instant messaging.  It is not a separate protocol but runs under most every <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/55951.xml">
IM</link> protocol.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/239970.xml">
WASTE</link> - open source secure IM, high strength "end to end" encryption, within an anonymised network.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Secure <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
email</link> - some email networks such as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/332222.xml">
hushmail</link>", are designed to provide encrypted and/or anonymous communication. They authenticate and encrypt on the users own computer, to prevent transmission of plain text, and mask the sender and recipient.  <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/2070675.xml">
Mixminion</link></software>
 provides a higher level of anonymity by using a network of anonymizing intermediaries, (similar to how <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/18582150.xml">
Tor</link></software>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/3229135.xml">
crowds</link> work above).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
CryptoHeaven</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/11008139.xml">
secure email</link>, secure instant messaging, secure file storage and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/18949797.xml">
sharing</link>.  Provides end-to-end encryption with <cipher wordnetid="106254239" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/1260.xml">
AES</link></cipher>
 standard. Publicly available client <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/27661.xml">
source code</link> in <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
 language.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<ss1>
<st>
General background</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
Secure computing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/4299490.xml">
Opportunistic encryption</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/331195.xml">
Mass surveillance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/14311200.xml">
Secure messaging</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Software selections and comparisons</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/4617475.xml">
Comparison of VoIP software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/987101.xml">
Comparison of instant messaging clients</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/454322.xml">
Anonymous P2P</link></network>
</group>
</system>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/10997.xml">
Freenet</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/4731056.xml">
Hepting vs. AT&amp;T</link> (a 2006 lawsuit in which the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/18949836.xml">
Electronic Frontier Foundation</link></company>
 alleges <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/17555269.xml">
AT&amp;T</link></company>
 allowed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/21939.xml">
NSA</link> to tap the entirety of its clients' Internet and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
Voice over IP</link> communications)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<scandal wordnetid="107223811" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<informing wordnetid="107212190" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<gossip wordnetid="107223170" confidence="0.8">
<controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<report wordnetid="107217924" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/3460155.xml">
NSA warrantless surveillance controversy</link></psychological_feature>
</group>
</act>
</disagreement>
</report>
</event>
</controversy>
</gossip>
</speech_act>
</collection>
</informing>
</dispute>
</scandal>
</law>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/17176456.xml">
Kish cypher</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
The schematics are illustrated in <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?patentnumber=613809">
U.S. Patent 613,809</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pat2pdf.org/pat2pdf/foo.pl?number=613809">
&nbsp;</weblink> and describes "rotating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/296058.xml">
coherer</link>s".</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2007/04/25/open_wi-fi_child_porn_case/">
Open Wi-Fi proves no defence in child porn case | The Register</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2007/12/11/piggybacking_arrest_made/">
'Extortionist' turns Wi-Fi thief to cover tracks | The Register</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/21888.xml">
NIST</link> recommmendations from 2005 state that 1024-bit asymmetric ciphers are the lowest standard it considers when evaluating ciphers, and that this is expected to be categorized as technically weak or breakable from around 2006-2010. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.keylength.com/index.php">
http://www.keylength.com/index.php</weblink> (click on NIST and scroll to the last table, or see article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/5749.xml">
Key size</link>).</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ise.gmu.edu/~xwangc/Publications/CCS05-VoIPTracking.pdf">
    *  X. Y. Wang, S. Chen and S. Jajodia “Tracking Anonymous Peer-to-Peer VoIP Calls on the Internet”. In Proceedings of the  12th ACM Conference on Computer Communications Security (CCS 2005), November 2005.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</article>
