<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 02:39:06[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>MEDLARS</title>
<id>14702922</id>
<revision>
<id>243437205</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T14:35:52Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CharlotteWebb</username>
<id>1522636</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Information retrieval</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>MEDLARS</b> (<b>Medical Literature Analysis and Retrieval System</b>) is a computerised biomedical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/190988.xml">
bibliographic</link> retrieval system. It was launched by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/408290.xml">
National Library of Medicine</link> in 1964 and was the first large scale, computer based, retrospective search service available to the general public. Its first data base was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/240749.xml">
MEDLINE</link>, a byproduct of the computerised production of the printed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/7494550.xml">
Index Medicus</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<sec>
<st>
Initial development</st>
<p>

Since 1879, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/408290.xml">
National Library of Medicine</link> (NLM) has published Index Medicus, a monthly guide to medical articles in thousands of journals. The huge volume of bibliographic citations were manually compiled at a cost of millions of dollars annually. In 1957 the staff of the NLM started to plan the mechanization of the Index Medicus; what was needed was a way to manipulate all this information to produce subsidiary products. By 1960 a detailed specification was prepared and by the spring of 1961 a request for proposals was sent out to 72 companies to develop the system. As a result a contract was awarded to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/12730.xml">
General Electric Company</link>. The computer (a <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/225721.xml">
Minneapolis-Honeywell 800</link></company>
) which was to run MEDLARS was delivered to the NLM in March 1963, and Frank Bradway Rogers (Director of the NLM 1949 to 1963) said at the time "..If all goes well, the January 1964 issue of Index Medicus will be ready to emerge from the system at the end of this year. It may be that this will mark the beginning of a new era in medical bibliography." </p>
<p>

MEDLARS cost $3 million to develop and at the time of its completion no other publicly available, fully operational electronic storage and retrieval system of its magnitude existed.
The original computer configuration operated from 1964 until its replacement by MEDLARS II in January 1975.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
US Congress, Office of Technology Assessment (1982), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://govinfo.library.unt.edu/ota/Ota_4/DATA/1982/8219.PDF">
MEDLARS and Health Information Policy</weblink>. ISBN 1428924248</entry>
<entry id="2">
Rogers, Frank B. "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=198085">
The Development of MEDLARS</weblink>" Bull Med Libr Assoc. 1964 January; 52(1): 150–151</entry>
<entry id="3">
Miles, Wyndham. The History of the NLM: Chapter 20 - <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/hmd/manuscripts/miles/miles_20.pdf">
Evolution of Computerized Bibliographies</weblink> (1983)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
