<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:36:18[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<institute  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108407330">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<association  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108049401">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>Virginia Bioinformatics Institute</title>
<id>1493799</id>
<revision>
<id>228413325</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-28T16:02:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ibeditor</username>
<id>4899152</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</category>
<category>Research institutes in the United States</category>
<category>Genetics or genomics research institutions</category>
<category>Organizations established in 2000</category>
<category>Bioinformatics organizations</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="320px" src="061018_aero_500x350.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Virginia Bioinformatics Institute building, located on the Blacksburg campus of Virginia Tech
</caption>
</image>

<b>The Virginia Bioinformatics Institute</b> (VBI) is a premier <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/149353.xml">
computational biology</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/467899.xml">
systems biology</link> research facility that opened on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/144404.xml">
Blacksburg</link> campus of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/239897.xml">
Virginia Tech</link> in 2000. It houses over two-hundred employees, multiple supercomputing clusters, and several DNA sequencers, including a massively-parallel high-throughput <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/535080.xml">
Roche</link> <link>
GS-FLXsequencer</link>. VBI is dedicated to the study of the biological sciences. The research platform of VBI focuses on the "disease triangle" of host-pathogen-environment interactions. By using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link>, which combines transdisciplinary approaches to information technology and biology, researchers at VBI interpret and apply vast amounts of biological data generated from basic research to some of today’s key challenges in the <link>
biomedical</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/64919.xml">
environmental</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/572.xml">
agricultural sciences</link>. Work at VBI involves collaboration in diverse disciplines such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../484/147484.xml">
plant pathology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/3954.xml">
biochemistry</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/467899.xml">
systems biology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/9223.xml">
economics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/841429.xml">
synthetic biology</link>. The institute develops genomic, proteomic and bioinformatic tools that can be applied to the study of infectious diseases as well as the discovery of new vaccine, drug and diagnostic targets.<p>

Research projects conducted at VBI: </p>
<p>

<b>Applied Discrete Mathematics</b>
The Applied Discrete Mathematics Group at VBI focuses on computational systems biology, using mathematical tools primarily from discrete mathematics. A major research area is the modeling and simulation of biological networks, in particular gene regulatory networks. The group is developing inference methods to construct dynamic models of networks from high-throughput data sets. Other methods include analysis tools for microarray and metabolomics data, using methods from combinatorics and discrete mathematics. A theoretical mathematics research program focusing on time-discrete dynamical systems over finite state sets complements the network modeling efforts.</p>
<p>

<b>Biochemical Networks Modeling Group Biochemical Networks Modeling Group</b>
This project builds methods to infer genetic networks from gene chip or microarray transcription profiles. The methods developed in this project are used to analyze gene expression data and develop experimental designs. The approach is multi-layered, consisting of initially building a low-resolution dynamic model that fits observed data, and then improving this model to identify hidden variables that will increase its predictive power.</p>
<p>

<b>Complex Pathway Simulator</b> (COPASI)
COPASI is a software package that allows the simulation and detailed analysis of biochemical networks. The package, which is available for use on Windows, Macintosh, Linux and Solaris operating systems, is based on original software developed by Pedro Mendes (Gepasi) and on the STODE software developed at EML Research. The main authors of COPASI are Drs. Stefan Hoops, Sven Sahle, and Ralph Gauges.</p>
<p>

<b>Dissecting Soybean Resistance to Phytophthora Dissecting Soybean Resistance to Phytophthora</b>
The Dissecting Soybean Resistance to Phytophthora project focuses on the mechanisms of quantitative resistance of soybean against the oomycete pathogen Phytophthora sojae, which is one of the most damaging pathogens of soybean crop. Oomycetes are fungus-like organisms that are most closely related to brown algae such as kelp and diatoms. Phytophthora pathogens attack thousands of plant species, including many important crops.</p>
<p>

<b>GenoCAD</b>
A gap currently exists between the few academic groups who have the capability of running small-scale proof-of-concept projects in synthetic biology and the individuals who could identify and benefit from biomedical and industrial applications of this technology. GenoCADTM is an experimental tool designed to address this need by allowing the user to build and verify complex genetic constructs derived from a library of standard genetic parts.</p>
<p>

<b>Mid-Atlantic Regional Center of Excellence</b> (MARCE)
The Middle-Atlantic Regional Center of Excellence for Biodefense and Emerging Infectious Diseases Research (MARCE) focuses on research to enable rapid defense against bioterror and emerging infectious diseases. Fourteen universities, seven government partners, and ten corporate partners are working together to improve our nation's public health response system. Specific diseases and disease-causing agents under investigation include anthrax, West Nile Virus, smallpox, and cryptosporidiosis, among others. The team is also working on needle-free vaccinations and new diagnostic tools. VBI serves as the Bioinformatics and Genomics Research Core for the MARCE, providing data generation, analysis, storage, and training services.</p>
<p>

<b>Network Dynamics and Simulation Science Laboratory</b> (NDSSL) 
The Network Dynamics and Simulation Science Laboratory is pursuing an advanced research and development program for interaction-based modeling, simulation, and associated analysis, experimental design, and decision support tools for understanding large biological, information, social, and technological systems. Extremely detailed, multi-scale computer simulations allow formal and experimental investigation of these systems. The need for such simulations is derived from questions posed by scientists, policy makers, and planners involved with very large complex systems.</p>
<p>

<b>NodMutDB Nodulation Mutant Database</b> (NodMutDB)
Functional genomics research is producing large amounts of information about the symbiosis-related genes, gene functions and regulation in both Rhizobia and their interacting host plants. It is important for this information to be placed in the context of the existing published literature. To address this, a web-accessible relational database, NodMutDB (Nodulation Mutant Database), has been created to provide a comprehensive and accurate resource for depositing, organizing and retrieving information on symbiosis- related genes, mutants and published literature.</p>
<p>

<b>Oomycete Molecular Genetics Research Collaboration Network</b> (OMGN)
The Phytophthora molecular genetics community benefits from a strong culture of collaboration, communication, and sharing of techniques and resources. Many new investigators, from a variety of backgrounds, have become interested in Phytophthora molecular genetics due to the recent blossoming of genetic and genomic tools for this group of organisms. The goal of the Oomycete Molecular Genetics Research Collaboration Network (OMGN) is to facilitate the integration of these investigators into the Phytophthora scientific community and to further strengthen the cooperative culture. A particular emphasis is placed on training and integrating junior faculty and faculty from institutions under-represented in the United States research infrastructure.</p>
<p>

<b>PathoSystems Resource Integration Center</b> (PATRIC)
The PathoSystems Resource Integration Center (PATRIC) is one of eight Bioinformatics Resource Centers (BRCs) funded by the National Institutes of Health through the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases. PATRIC provides a multi-faceted resource for genomic and associated information on important human pathogens. The ultimate goal of this resource is to facilitate the discovery of diagnostics, drugs, and therapeutics for the diseases caused by these organisms.</p>
<p>

<b>Plant-Associated Microbe Gene Ontology Interest Group</b> (PAMGO)
The PAMGO interest group was formed to develop new gene ontology (GO) terms describing the various processes, functions and cellular components related to microbe-host interactions. Plant-associated microbes have evolved similar mechanisms to evade, neutralize or suppress defense systems of their plant hosts and obtain nutrients. Such similarities can only be discovered if a controlled vocabulary is set in place to describe these processes amongst diverse microbe-host interactions. The PAMGO consortium is a collaboration between the Virginia Bioinformatics Institute, Cornell University, North Carolina State University, the University of Wisconsin-Madison, The Institute of Genomic Research (TIGR; a Division of the J.C. Venter Institute), and Wells College. The group works closely with the Gene Ontology Consortium.</p>
<p>

<b>Proteomics Research Resource Center for Biodefense Proteomics Research</b>
VBI is working with Georgetown University and Social and Scientific Systems, Inc (SSS), the Administrative Center of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases-funded Proteomics Research Centers (PRC), to help design, develop, and maintain a publicly accessible Web site containing data and technology protocols generated by each PRC, as well as a catalog that lists reagents and products developed by the sites and available for public distribution. It is anticipated that the PRCs will discover potential targets for the next generation of vaccines, therapeutics and diagnostics.</p>
<p>

<b>Rhizobiales Bioinformatics Resource Center</b> (RhizobialesBRC)
The goal of the Rhizobiales Bioinformatics Resource Center (RhizobialesBRC) is to provide a comprehensive and accurate web-based resource for genomic and associated information on the sequenced Rhizobiales. RhizobialesBRC uses the information technology infrastructure developed by the PathoSystems Resource Integration Center project (PATRIC). The genomic data are managed using Oracle9i/10 and the “Genomics Unified Schema (GUS) and Application Framework”. The database can be queried and the genomes can be browsed via a web interface.</p>
<p>

<b>Seedgenes</b>: Essential Gene Functions in Arabidopsis thaliana
The SeedGenes project identifies and analyzes every Arabidopsis gene essential for seed development. The long-term goal is to use knowledge developed in the experimentally tractable Arabidopsis genome to understand how to improve and maintain those plants which are important to the sustenance of human civilization.</p>
<p>

<b>VBI Microbial Database</b>
The VBI Microbial Database hosts data from different sources for a range of plant pathogenic oomycetes, fungi and bacteria, primarily those organisms under study at VBI. The database is a modified version of the Genomics Unified Schema(GUS),an extensive relational database schema and associated application framework designed to store, integrate, analyze and present functional genomic data.</p>
<p>

<b>Yeast Systems Biology</b>
Oxidative stress affects most organisms—from bacteria to humans—that require oxygen to survive. Oxygen, a very reactive molecule, generates additional reactive and dangerous molecules, known as reactive oxygen species (ROS). Highly toxic, ROS are responsible for cellular stress due to their highly reactive behavior. A number of human diseases, such as Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s, seem to be related to ROS. Aging is also largely attributed to the action of these toxic molecules. This project is developing new mathematical modeling methods for systems biology and improving knowledge of the cellular defenses against oxidative stress. </p>




<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vbi.vt.edu/">
Virginia Bioinformatics Institute website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible expanded " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";background:#660000;color:#FF6600;font-family:serif;" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/239897.xml">
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</link><village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/137686.xml">
Blacksburg, Virginia</link></village>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 2px 0px 0px;" rowspan="11">
<image width="90px" src="Drill_Field_Virginia_Tech_-_cropped.png">
</image>
</col>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:transparent;color:#660000;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/239897.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Academics%22])">
Academics</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../074/1310074.xml">
Virginia-Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine</link></group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/7021837.xml">
Virginia Tech School of Public and International Affairs</link>&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/1310206.xml">
Virginia College of Osteopathic Medicine</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/4724965.xml">
Center for Public Administration and Policy</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/12265748.xml">
Virginia Tech Foundation</link>&nbsp;· 
<conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.8">
<self-propelled_vehicle wordnetid="104170037" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<wheeled_vehicle wordnetid="104576211" confidence="0.8">
<container wordnetid="103094503" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<motor_vehicle wordnetid="103791235" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/8046879.xml">
HEVT</link></motor_vehicle>
</vehicle>
</container>
</wheeled_vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</self-propelled_vehicle>
</car>
</conveyance>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/12255092.xml">
The Educational Media Company at Virginia Tech</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:transparent;color:#660000;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/239897.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Research%22])">
Research</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/1493799.xml">
Virginia Bioinformatics Institute</link></institution>
</association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/14659029.xml">
Virginia Tech Institute for Policy and Governance</link>&nbsp;· 
<computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/447850.xml">
System X</link></machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/12057301.xml">
Virginia Tech Corporate Research Center</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:transparent;color:#660000;;" class="navbox-group">
<sport wordnetid="100523513" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/4130369.xml">
Athletics</link></sport>
</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/1210315.xml">
Fighting Gobblers</link>&nbsp;· 
<music wordnetid="107020895" confidence="0.8">
<song wordnetid="107048000" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<musical_composition wordnetid="107037465" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/334273.xml">
Old Hokie</link></musical_composition>
</auditory_communication>
</song>
</music>
&nbsp;· 
<music wordnetid="107020895" confidence="0.8">
<song wordnetid="107048000" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<musical_composition wordnetid="107037465" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/2007633.xml">
Tech Triumph</link></musical_composition>
</auditory_communication>
</song>
</music>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/1210315.xml">
Hokie Bird</link>&nbsp;· 
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<diversion wordnetid="100426928" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<sport wordnetid="100523513" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<competition wordnetid="101168569" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/13682558.xml">
UVA-VT rivalry</link></competition>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</sport>
</event>
</diversion>
</group_action>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/15190346.xml">
Football</link>&nbsp;· 
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<trophy wordnetid="106709442" confidence="0.8">
<symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<award wordnetid="106696483" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<competition wordnetid="101168569" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/829297.xml">
Commonwealth Cup</link></competition>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</signal>
</award>
</event>
</symbol>
</trophy>
</group_action>
&nbsp;· 
<trophy wordnetid="106709442" confidence="0.8">
<symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<award wordnetid="106696483" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/3075559.xml">
Black Diamond Trophy</link></signal>
</award>
</symbol>
</trophy>
&nbsp;· 
<club wordnetid="108227214" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/16951033.xml">
Men's soccer</link></club>
&nbsp;· 
<club wordnetid="108227214" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/16950581.xml">
Women's soccer</link></club>
&nbsp;· 
<team wordnetid="108208560" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/9756898.xml">
Basketball</link></team>
&nbsp;· 
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<scene wordnetid="108645963" confidence="0.8">
<venue wordnetid="108677628" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/1886330.xml">
Lane Stadium</link></venue>
</scene>
</location>
</area>
</region>
&nbsp;· 
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<scene wordnetid="108645963" confidence="0.8">
<venue wordnetid="108677628" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/1919728.xml">
Cassell Coliseum</link></venue>
</scene>
</location>
</area>
</region>
&nbsp;· 
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<scene wordnetid="108645963" confidence="0.8">
<venue wordnetid="108677628" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/7748025.xml">
English Field</link></venue>
</scene>
</location>
</area>
</region>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/8226054.xml">
Virginia Tech Lacrosse and Soccer Stadium</link>&nbsp;· 
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<cornerback wordnetid="109965787" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<football_player wordnetid="110101634" confidence="0.8">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.8">
<contestant wordnetid="109613191" confidence="0.8">
<coach wordnetid="109931640" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<athlete wordnetid="109820263" confidence="0.8">
<trainer wordnetid="110722575" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/2195445.xml">
Frank Beamer</link></trainer>
</athlete>
</causal_agent>
</leader>
</coach>
</contestant>
</player>
</football_player>
</person>
</cornerback>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;· 
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<coach wordnetid="109931640" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<trainer wordnetid="110722575" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/9487372.xml">
Seth Greenberg</link></trainer>
</scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</leader>
</coach>
</person>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;· 
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.8">
<contestant wordnetid="109613191" confidence="0.8">
<coach wordnetid="109931640" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<trainer wordnetid="110722575" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/15190195.xml">
Jim Weaver</link></trainer>
</causal_agent>
</leader>
</coach>
</contestant>
</player>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:transparent;color:#660000;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/5415035.xml">
Campus</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/5415035.xml">
Virginia Tech campus</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/917054.xml">
Hokie Stone</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/1851858.xml">
Hillcrest Honors Community</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/239897.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22History%22])">
History</link>&nbsp;· 
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/10705678.xml">
Virginia Tech massacre</link></attack>
&nbsp;· 
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/10770587.xml">
Virginia Tech Police</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:transparent;color:#660000;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/239897.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Student+Life%22])">
Life</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/942366.xml">
Virginia Tech Corps of Cadets</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/2074553.xml">
Highty-Tighties</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/6717357.xml">
The Marching Virginians</link>&nbsp;· 
<newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/5486751.xml">
Collegiate Times</link></newspaper>
&nbsp;· 
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/6712434.xml">
New Virginians</link></artist>
&nbsp;· 
<radio_station wordnetid="104044119" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/7775323.xml">
WUVT-FM</link></radio_station>
</p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:transparent;color:#660000;;" class="navbox-group">

Virginia Tech people|
People</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/11457010.xml">
List of Virginia Tech alumni</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/18063237.xml">
Wendell Flinchum</link>&nbsp;· 
<poet wordnetid="110444194" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/10744564.xml">
Nikki Giovanni</link></writer>
</poet>
&nbsp;· 
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.8">
<executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<corporate_executive wordnetid="109966255" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/6103717.xml">
T. Marshall Hahn</link></head>
</causal_agent>
</corporate_executive>
</administrator>
</leader>
</person>
</executive>
</president>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;· 
<president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/3703016.xml">
Charles W. Steger</link></president>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</association>
</organization>
</institute>
</article>
