<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:37:19[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Prolotherapy</title>
<id>1497313</id>
<revision>
<id>244574456</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T14:35:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rjwilmsi</username>
<id>203434</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Inflammations</category>
<category>Orthopedics</category>
<category>Alternative medicine</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="250px" src="Hemwall-Gustav.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Gustav Hemwall circa 1990-1995
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Prolotherapy</b> ("Proliferative Injection Therapy") involves injecting an otherwise non-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/24354.xml">
pharmacological</link> and non-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/4387629.xml">
active</link> irritant solution into the body, generally in the region of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/144865.xml">
tendons</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/17874.xml">
ligaments</link> for the purpose of strengthening weakened connective tissue and alleviating musculoskeletal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/24373.xml">
pain</link>. There is conflicting evidence about its effectiveness and it is an experimental treatment.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Prolotherapy can be distinguished from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/2187254.xml">
sclerotherapy</link>. Sclerotherapy is the use of injections of caustics into the veins, in vascular surgery and dermatology, to remove <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/32834.xml">
varicose veins</link> and other vascular irregularities. Prolotherapy is the use of injections in the treatment of connective tissue weakness and musculoskeletal pain.   Prolotherapy is also called "proliferation therapy" and "regenerative injection therapy."</p>
<p>

Prolotherapy is often used as an alternative to invasive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/210168.xml">
arthroscopic surgery</link>.  A double-blind placebo-controlled study on arthroscopic surgery for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/504841.xml">
osteoarthritis</link> of the knee was published in the <periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/486492.xml">
New England Journal of Medicine</link></periodical>
 in July 2002 and concluded that the group that received actual arthroscopic surgery did not report better function or pain than the placebo group."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  Arthroscopic surgery of the knee is, however, rarely performed for the indication of osteoarthritis, but rather for mechanical tears or disruptions of cartilaginous tissue.  Prolotherapy is not intended to address this type of problem.  Doctors and surgeons have given anecdotal accounts of successful treatment for knee injuries, shoulder separation, and typical injuries to golfers (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/1834851.xml">
epicondylitis</link>, shoulder strain, lower back strain and injury, hip and knee injury)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> However, the vast majority of established musculoskeletal health care professionals do not support prolotherapy as mainstream treatment pending further investigation.</p>
<p>

As of April 2005, doctors at the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/160843.xml">
Mayo Clinic</link></company>
 began supporting prolotherapy.  Robert D. Sheeler, MD (Medical Editor, <it>Mayo Clinic Health letter</it>) first learned of prolotherapy through <official wordnetid="110372373" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/220379.xml">
C. Everett Koop</link></official>
’s interest in the treatment.  Mayo Clinic doctors list the areas that are most likely to benefit from prolotherapy treatment: ankles, knees, elbows, and sacroiliac joint in the low back. They report that "unlike <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/57996.xml">
corticosteroid</link> injections — which may provide temporary relief — prolotherapy involves improving the injected tissue by stimulating tissue growth."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/10013.xml">
evidence-based medicine</link> review<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> of prolotherapy for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/618631.xml">
low back pain</link> concluded: "There is conflicting evidence regarding the efficacy of prolotherapy injections for patients with chronic low-back pain.  If used alone, prolotherapy injections do not have a role in the treatment of chronic low-back pain. When combined with other treatments, they may give prolonged partial relief of pain and disability." </p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Injections of irritant solutions were performed in the late 1800’s to repair hernias and in the early 1900’s for jaw pain due to temporomandibular (jaw) joint laxity. George S. Hackett developed the technique of prolotherapy in the 1940’s.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/1436986.xml">
Gustav Hemwall</link> was a pioneer, beginning his studies and treatments in the 1950s and continuing until the mid 1990s.  In his study of almost 10,000 prolotherapy cases, Dr. Hackett found that over 99 percent of the patients found relief from their chronic pain. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Prolotherapy in clinical practice</st>

<p>

Prolotherapy involves the injection of an irritant solution into the area where connective tissue has been weakened or damaged through injury or strain.  Many solutions are used, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/12950.xml">
Dextrose</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/298762.xml">
Lidocaine</link> (a commonly used local anesthetic), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/24085.xml">
Phenol</link> (an alcohol), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/172732.xml">
Glycerine</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/212514.xml">
Cod Liver Oil</link> extract.  The injection is given into joint capsules or where <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/144865.xml">
tendon</link> connects to bone.  Many points may require injection.  The Injected solution causes the body to heal itself through the process of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/70425.xml">
inflammation</link> and repair.   In the case of weakened or torn connective tissue, induced inflammation and release of growth factor at the site of injury may result in a 30-40% strengthening of the attachment points, although strong scientific evidence supporting this is lacking.  </p>
<p>

Prolotherapy treatment sessions are generally given every two to six weeks. Many patients receive treatment at less and less frequent intervals until treatments are required only every several years, if at all.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

Allen R Banks, Ph.D., has described in detail the theory behind prolotherapy in "A Rationale for Prolotherapy".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Guidelines used by practitioners as indicators for prolotherapy</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Recurrent swelling or fullness involving a joint or muscular region</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Popping, clicking, grinding, or catching sensations with movement</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A sensation of the “leg giving way” with associated back pain</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Temporary benefit from chiropractic manipulation or manual mobilization that fails to ultimately resolve the pain</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Distinct tender points and “jump signs” along the bone at tendon or ligament attachments</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Numbness, tingling, aching, or burning, referred into an upper or lower extremity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Recurrent headache, face pain, jaw pain, ear pain</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Chest pain with tenderness along the rib attachments on the spine or along the front of the chest</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Spine pain that does not respond to surgery, or whose origin is not clear or consistent based on extensive studies</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Evidence based medicine</st>

<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/237721.xml">
Cochrane review</link> of the medical literature as of January 2004 on the efficacy of prolotherapy injections in adults with chronic low-back pain<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> found four <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/241717.xml">
controlled trials</link>, all measuring pain and disability levels at six months.  The review concluded:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

"There is conflicting evidence regarding the efficacy of prolotherapy injections in reducing pain and disability in patients with chronic low-back pain. Conclusions are confounded by clinical heterogeneity amongst studies and by the presence of co-interventions. There was no evidence that prolotherapy injections alone were more effective than control injections alone. However, in the presence of co-interventions, prolotherapy injections were more effective than control injections, more so when both injections and co-interventions were controlled concurrently."
</indent>

The review also noted:  "[m]inor side effects from the treatment, such as increased back pain and stiffness, were common but short-lived."  ("Stiffness" is an expected short-lived side effect, as the goal is to cause irritation and the corresponding body reaction of temporary inflammation and repair.) </p>
<p>

More recently, Rabago et al. [A systematic review of prolotherapy for chronic musculoskeletal pain.  Clin J Sport Med. 2005 Sep;15(5):376-80] noted: "Two [randomized controlled trials] on osteoarthritis reported decreased pain, increased range of motion, and increased patellofemoral cartilage thickness after prolotherapy."</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>
<p>

Most major <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/490201.xml">
medical insurance</link> policies do not cover the treatment. After a 1999 review of the medical evidence, Medicare declined to cover prolotherapy for chronic low back pain citing that prolotherapy "was last examined for coverage by the Health Care Financing Administration (HCFA) in September 1992".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ongoing studies</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Knee injuries</st>
<p>

A randomized, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/277248.xml">
double-blind</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/142821.xml">
placebo</link> control study is currently recruiting patients to determine whether prolotherapy can decrease pain and disability from knee <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/504841.xml">
osteoarthritis</link>.  This study is Sponsored by the National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/391043.xml">
NCCAM</link>).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Tennis elbow</st>
<p>

A randomized, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/277248.xml">
double-blind</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/142821.xml">
placebo</link> control study is currently recruiting patients to determine whether prolotherapy can be an effective treatment for lateral epicondylitis (tennis elbow).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/10612706.xml">
Pin firing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/1436986.xml">
Gustav Hemwall</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/07/health/07brod.html">
Injections to Kick-Start Tissue Repair</weblink>", <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/30680.xml">
New York Times</link>&#32;(2007-08-07).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-24</link>.&nbsp;"Prolotherapy involves a series of injections designed to produce inflammation in the injured tissue. To appreciate the value of such a seemingly counterproductive measure, you need to know something about connective tissue and how the body normally repairs it. When tissues are injured, inflammation is a common natural response. It stimulates substances carried in blood that produce growth factors in the injured area to promote healing. Ligaments, tendons and cartilage have very poor blood supplies, which can result in incomplete healing."&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=12110735 "A controlled trial of arthroscopic surgery for osteoarthritis of the knee" N Engl J Med 2002 Jul 11;347(2):81-8, Moseley JB; O'Malley K; Petersen NJ; Menke TJ; Brody BA; Kuykendall DH; Hollingsworth JC; Ashton CM; Wray NP</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prolotherapy-hhf.org/Prolotherapy_insert%202006.pdf">
Second Annual Prolotherapy Research Forum</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).</entry>
<entry id="4">
Marc Darrow, Prolotherapy: Living Pain Free, Protex Press, ISBN-13: 978-0971450325</entry>
<entry id="5">
Ross A. Hauser, Marion A. Hauser, Prolo Your Pain Away, Beulah Land Press, ISBN-13: 978-0966101096</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Mayo Clinic&#32;(2005).&#32;"Alternative treatments: Dealing with chronic pain". <it>Mayo Clinic Health Letter</it>&#32;<b>23</b>&#32;(4).</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cochrane.org/reviews/en/ab004059.html">
http://www.cochrane.org/reviews/en/ab004059.html</weblink> Cochrane collaboration</entry>
<entry id="8">
Hauser, Ross.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://getprolo.com/the_history_of_prolotherapy.htm">
The History of Prolotherapy.</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-08-26</link>.&nbsp;"In 1955, at an American Medical Association meeting, Dr. Gustav Hemwall was astonished to see so many doctors at one particular exhibit. The presenter was talking about a very successful treatment for chronic low back pain. Nothing was worse at the time for Dr. Hemwall than having a chronic low back pain patient come to him, because the treatments he was able to offer were not very successful. The doctor doing the presentation was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/1497313.xml">
George S. Hackett</link>, M.D., and he was discussing the technique of Prolotherapy. Once the crowd diminished, Dr. Hemwall asked Dr. Hackett how he could learn the treatment described in his book, Ligament and Tendon Relaxation Treated by Prolotherapy. Dr. Hemwall went to Dr. Hackett's office in Canton, Ohio, to learn the technique. Dr. Hemwall became so proficient at administering the technique that Dr. Hackett would later refer patients to him. Prolotherapy owes a great debt to Dr. Hemwall. Between 1955 until his retirement in 1996, he was the main instructor and proponent of Prolotherapy in the United States. He was not a researcher but a clinician, and perhaps the world's greatest Prolotherapist. He treated more than 10,000 patients world wide and collected data on 8,000 of these patients. In 1974, Dr. Hemwall presented his largest survey of 2,007 Prolotherapy patients to the Prolotherapy Association."&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
Banks, Alan.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prolotherapy.com/articles/banks.htm">
A Rationale for Prolotherapy</weblink>".&nbsp;"Prolotherapy, the technology for strengthening lax ligaments, has found increased acceptance in recent years. However, despite its greater use, the mechanism of action of prolotherapy is not well understood. In the past few years a number of advances have been made in the understanding of wound repair. This author believes the increased knowledge which has been made available in the field of wound healing has application to a more complete understanding of prolotherapy. There follows a general discussion of wound healing and a hypothesis which provides a basis for understanding prolotherapy."&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.quackwatch.org/01QuackeryRelatedTopics/prolo.html">
HCFA Decision Memorandum</weblink>".&#32;  <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/879168.xml">
Quackwatch</link></organization>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-24</link>.</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00085722">
http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00085722</weblink> Clinicaltrials.Gov, Joint Injections for Osteoarthritic Knee Pain, web page last updated October 16, 2006</entry>
<entry id="12">
http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show?cond=%22Tennis+Elbow%22&amp;rank=3 Clinicaltrials.Gov, Efficacy Study of Prolotherapy vs Corticosteroid for Tennis Elbow</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prolotherapy.org">
Prolotherapy.org</weblink> is a source for extensive articles, diagrams and other resources related to prolotherapy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://prolotherapy.com/">
Prolotherapy.com</weblink> - a source for information on nonsurgical ligament reconstruction</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aaomed.org">
American Association of Orthopaedic Medicine</weblink> is a non-profit organization that promotes prolotherapy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.camresearch.com">
CAM Prolotherapy Project</weblink>"&#32;(2006-08-06).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-08-06</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/07/health/07brod.html">
Injections to Kick-Start Tissue Repair</weblink>", <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/30680.xml">
New York Times</link>&#32;(2007-08-07).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-24</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
