<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:27:36[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Ink</title>
<id>15292</id>
<revision>
<id>243705015</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T18:23:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>J.delanoy</username>
<id>2372780</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Inks</category>
<category>Articles with specifically-marked weasel-worded phrases</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/3458745.xml">
Ink (disambiguation)</link>.<p>

<image width="150px" src="Füller-tinte_hg.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Bottles of ink from Germany
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

An <b>ink</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/18993825.xml">
liquid</link> containing various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/49598.xml">
pigment</link>s and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/8179.xml">
dye</link>s used for coloring a surface to produce an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/71925.xml">
image</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/32977.xml">
text</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/8560.xml">
design</link>. Ink is used for drawing and/or writing with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/75838.xml">
pen</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/462707.xml">
brush</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/25247.xml">
quill</link>. Thicker inks, in paste form, are used extensively in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/662134.xml">
letterpress</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/18426.xml">
lithographic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/44723.xml">
printing</link>.</p>
<p>

Ink is a complex medium, comprising solvents, pigments, dyes, resins, lubricants, solubilizers, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/133176.xml">
surfactant</link>s, particulate matter, fluorescers, and other materials.  The components of inks serve many purposes; the ink’s carrier, colorants, and other additives are used to control flow, thickness, and appearance of the ink when <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/1893229.xml">
dry</link>.  </p>

<sec>
<st>
Types of ink</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Tintenstrich-detail_2.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Line of a Fountain pen, 50-times magnified
</caption>
</image>

Early varieties include <link>
Egyptian ink</link>, various natural dyes made from metals, the husk or outer covering of beans or seeds, and sea creatures like the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/6633.xml">
cuttlefish</link> (known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/412605.xml">
sepia</link>). <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/17020384.xml">
India ink</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
 is black and originated in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/689.xml">
Asia</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/659960.xml">
Iron gall ink</link> was used by many of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/469482.xml">
old master</link>s for drawing.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/33926.xml">
Walnut ink</link> is erroneously thought to have also been used by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/469482.xml">
old master</link>s, however, there is no proof of this. Walnut inks, if they were used, would have faded fairly quickly and would therefore be unsuitable.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Pigmented inks</st>
<p>

Pigmented inks contain other agents that ensure <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/835157.xml">
adhesion</link> of the pigment to the surface and prevent it from being removed by mechanical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/366023.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Abrasive_wear%22])">
abrasion</link>. These materials are typically referred to as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/58890.xml">
resin</link>s (in solvent-based inks) or <link>
binding agent</link>s (in water-based inks).</p>
<p>

Because pigmented inks stay on the surface of paper, less ink is needed to create the same intensity of color as with dye-based inks.  Pigmented inks also tend to be more resistant to washing out.  For this reason these inks are frequently recommended for applications where erasure is undesirable.  <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/3372324.xml">
Gel inks</link></instrument>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 are particularly resistant to erasure and frequently bear recommendations from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/62312.xml">
forgery</link> experts.</p>
<p>

The particle size of the pigment is very important for the ability to diffuse in the solution inks. Qualities such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/64656.xml">
hue</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/664556.xml">
saturation</link>, and brightness or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/9220187.xml">
lightness</link> are inherent in the ink, and vary depending on the source and type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/49598.xml">
pigment</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Dyes in inks</st>
<p>

Dye-based inks are generally much stronger than pigment-based inks and can produce much more color of a given density per unit of mass. However, because dyes are dissolved in the liquid phase, they have a tendency to soak into paper, thus making the ink less efficient and also potentially allowing the ink to bleed at the edges of an image, producing poor quality printing.</p>
<p>

To circumvent this problem, dye-based inks are made with solvents that dry rapidly or are used with quick-drying methods of printing, such as blowing hot air on the fresh print. Other methods include harder paper <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/492177.xml">
sizing</link> and more specialized paper coatings. The latter is particularly suited to inks used in non-industrial settings (which must conform to tighter toxicity and emission controls), such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/50687.xml">
inkjet printer</link> inks. Another technique involves coating the paper with a charged coating. If the dye has the opposite charge, it is attracted to and retained by this coating, while the solvent soaks into the paper. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/6911.xml">
Cellulose</link>, the material that paper is made of, is naturally charged, and so a compound that complexes with both the dye and the paper's surface will aid retention at the surface. Such a compound in common use in ink-jet printing inks is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/48786.xml">
polyvinyl pyrrolidone</link>.</p>
<p>

An additional advantage of dye-based ink systems is that the dye <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/19555.xml">
molecule</link>s interact chemically with other ink ingredients. This means that they can benefit more than pigmented ink from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/22600.xml">
optical brightener</link>s and color-enhancing agents designed to increase the intensity and appearance of dyes. Because dyes get their color from the interaction of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/9476.xml">
electron</link>s in their molecules, the way in which the electrons can move is determined by the charge and extent of electron <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/653183.xml">
delocalization</link> in the other ink ingredients. The color emerges as a function of the light energy that falls on the dye. Thus, if an optical brightener or color enhancer absorbs light energy and emits it through or with the dye, the appearance changes, as the spectrum of light re-emitted to the observer changes.</p>
<p>

A more recent development in dye-based inks are dyes that react with cellulose to permanently color the paper.  Such inks are not affected by water, alcohol, and other solvents.  As such, their use is recommended to prevent frauds that involve removing signatures, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/2542237.xml">
check washing</link>.  Currently this kind of ink is most often offered for use in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/60284.xml">
fountain pen</link>s.  The most popular manufacturer of this ink is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/5700907.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Noodler's%22])">
Noodler</link>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History of ink</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Ganesha_ink.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Ink drawing of Ganesha under an umbrella (early 19th century). <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/15292.xml">
Ink</link>, called <it>masi</it>, an admixture of several chemical components, has been used in India since at least the 4th century BC.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The practice of writing with ink and a sharp pointed needle was common in early <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<land wordnetid="109334396" confidence="0.8">
<peninsula wordnetid="109388848" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/678583.xml">
South India</link></peninsula>
</land>
</location>
</region>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/16016.xml">
Jain</link> sutras in India were compiled in ink.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> 
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Approximately 5000 years ago, an ink for blacking the raised surfaces of pictures and texts carved in stone was developed in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5042862.xml">
China</link>. This early ink was a mixture of soot from pine smoke, lamp oil, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/13160.xml">
gelatin</link> from animal skins and musk. Other early cultures also developed many colors of ink from available berries, plants and minerals. </p>
<p>

The <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/17020384.xml">
India ink</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
 used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/13890.xml">
ancient India</link> since at least the 4th century BC was called <it>masi</it>, which was an admixture of several chemical components.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Indian documents written in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/559437.xml">
Kharosthi</link> with ink have been unearthed in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/70934.xml">
Chinese Turkestan</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> The practice of writing with ink and a sharp pointed needle was common in early <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<land wordnetid="109334396" confidence="0.8">
<peninsula wordnetid="109388848" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/678583.xml">
South India</link></peninsula>
</land>
</location>
</region>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/16016.xml">
Jain</link> sutras in India were compiled in ink.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> In India, the carbon black from which India ink is produced is obtained by burning bones, tar, pitch, and other substances.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

In ancient Rome, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/14037951.xml">
atramentum</link> was used. In an article for the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/227687.xml">
Christian Science Monitor</link></it>, Sharon J. Huntington describes these other historical inks:</p>
<p>

About 1,600 years ago, a popular ink recipe was created. The recipe was used for centuries. Iron salts, such as ferrous sulfate (made by treating iron with sulfuric acid), were mixed with tannin from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/217384.xml">
gallnuts</link> (they grow on trees) and a thickener. When first put to paper, this ink is bluish-black. Over time it fades to a dull brown.</p>
<p>

Scribes in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/6248342.xml">
medieval</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link> (about AD 800 to 1500) wrote on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/2984155.xml">
sheepskin</link> parchment. One 12th century ink recipe called for hawthorn branches to be cut in the spring and left to dry. Then the bark was pounded from the branches and soaked in water for eight days. The water was boiled until it thickened and turned black. Wine was added during boiling. The ink was poured into special bags and hung in the sun. Once dried, the mixture was mixed with wine and iron salt over a fire to make the final ink.</p>
<p>

The reservoir <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/60284.xml">
fountain pen</link> dates back to 953, when <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/2100593.xml">
Ma'ād al-Mu'izz</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/7245.xml">
caliph</link> of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/8087628.xml">
Egypt</link></country>
, demanded a pen which would not stain his hands or clothes, and was provided with a pen which held ink in a reservoir and delivered it to the nib via gravity and capillary action.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

In the 15th century, a new type of ink had to be developed in Europe for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/23295.xml">
printing press</link> by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<engraver wordnetid="110058155" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/15745.xml">
Johannes Gutenberg</link></engraver>
</person>
. Two types of ink were prevalent at the time: the Greek and Roman writing ink (soot, glue, and water) and the 12th century variety composed of ferrous sulfate, gall, gum, and water.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>  Neither of these handwriting inks could adhere to printing surfaces without creating blurs.  Eventually an oily, varnish-like ink made of soot, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/151183.xml">
turpentine</link>, and walnut oil was created specifically for the printing press.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Modern ink applications</st>
<p>

Up until a few years ago, consumers had very little interest in ink other than refills for their pens.  Fountain pens became a novelty as the disposable <link>
ball point pen</link> took over the market. The introduction of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/13950.xml">
home computing</link> led to home printing. Today, in developed nations, it is rare to find a residence or a business that does not have a printing capability.  As a result, buying ink in the form of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/3787783.xml">
cartridge</link> has once again become a part of the day-to-day shopping experience, similar to buying a bottle of ink fifty years ago.</p>
<p>

Ink refilling services for printer cartridges are offered by large, official printing companies as well as smaller, "unofficial" refill companies. Customers can often cut printing costs by using refill services from a refill company, or buying the new non-OEM brands instead of refilling.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health aspect</st>

<p>

There is a misconception that ink isn't harmful even if swallowed. Once ingested, ink can be hazardous to one's health. Certain inks, such as those used in printers, and even those found in a common pen can be harmful. Though ink will easily not cause death, inappropriate contact can cause effects such as severe headaches, skin irritation, or nervous system damage. These effects can be caused by solvents or by pigment constituents such as <waste wordnetid="114856263" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<compound wordnetid="114818238" confidence="0.8">
<methane_series wordnetid="114951377" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<amine wordnetid="114739004" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<organic_compound wordnetid="114727670" confidence="0.8">
<pollutant wordnetid="114857278" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<aliphatic_compound wordnetid="114601294" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/3586281.xml">
p-Anisidine</link></aliphatic_compound>
</material>
</pollutant>
</organic_compound>
</part>
</amine>
</chemical>
</methane_series>
</compound>
</substance>
</waste>
, which is used in the process of creating the ink's color and shine. The poison control center[] has stated that any consumption of ink should be reported to a local hospital or poison control center.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Writing inks and preservation</st>
<p>

The two most used black writing inks in history are carbon inks and iron gall inks.  Both types create problems for preservationists.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Carbon inks</st>
<p>

Carbon inks were commonly made from lampblack or soot and gum arabic.  Gum arabic keeps the carbon particles in suspension and adhered to paper.  The carbon particles do not fade over time even when in sunlight or bleached.  One benefit of carbon ink is that it is not harmful to the paper.  Over time, the ink is chemically stable and therefore does not threaten the strength of the paper.  Despite these benefits, carbon ink is not the ideal ink for permanence and ease of preservation.  The ink has a tendency to smudge in humid environments and can be washed off an item.  The best method of preserving documents written in carbon ink is to ensure it is stored in a dry environment (Barrow 1972).  Recently, carbon inks made from carbon nanotubes have been successfully created.  They are similar in composition to the traditional inks in that they use a polymer to suspend the carbon nanotubes.  These inks can be used in inkjet printers and produce electrically conductive patterns.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Iron gall inks</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/659960.xml">
Iron gall ink</link>s became prominent in the early 1100's and were used for centuries and thought to be the best type of ink.   However, iron gall ink is corrosive and damages the paper it is on (Waters 1940).  Items containing this ink can become brittle and the writing fades to brown.  The original scores of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/9906294.xml">
Johann Sebastian Bach</link></person>
 are threatened by the destructive properties of iron gall ink.  The majority of his works are held by the German State Library, and about 25% of those are in advanced stages of decay (American Libraries 2000).  The rate at which the writing fades is based on several factors, such as "the proportions of the ink ingredients, the amount deposited on the paper, and the composition of the paper" (Barrow 1972:16).  The corrosion is caused by "two major degradation processes: acid catalysed hydrolysis and iron(II)-catalysed oxidation of cellulose" (Rouchon-Quillet 2004:389).</p>
<p>

Treatment is a controversial subject.  There is no treatment that will undo the damage already caused by the acidic ink.  Deterioration can only be stopped or slowed for a period of time.  There are some people who think it best not to treat the item at all for fear of the consequences.  Others believe that non-aqueous procedures are the best solution.  And then, there are some that believe an aqueous procedure may provide the answer for preserving items written with iron gall ink.  Aqueous treatments include distilled water at different temperatures, calcium hydroxide, calcium bicarbonate, magnesium carbonate, magnesium bicarbonate, and calcium phytate.  There are many possible side effects from these treatments.  There can be mechanical damage, which would further weaken the paper.  The color of the paper or ink may change and ink may bleed.  Other consequences that might arise from aqueous treatment are a change of ink texture or the formation of on the surface of the ink (Reibland &amp; de Groot 1999).  </p>
<p>

Iron gall inks are generally stored in a stable environment, because fluctuating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/223970.xml">
relative humidity</link> increases the rate at which formic acid, acetic acid and furan derivatives form in the material on which the ink was used.  Sulfuric acid acts as a catalyst to cellulose hydrolysis, and iron (II) sulfate acts as a catalyst to cellulose oxidation.  These chemical reactions physically weaken the paper, causing <link>
 brittleness</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Indelible ink</st>

<p>

The word <b>indelible</b> means <b>cannot be removed or erased</b>.
Some types of indelible ink have a very short shelf life because of the solvents used, which evaporate rapidly.</p>
<p>

India, Philippines, Indonesia and other developing countries have used indelible in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/17687359.xml">
electoral stain</link> to prevent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/382165.xml">
electoral fraud</link>. The Election Commission in India has used indelible ink for many elections. Indonesia used it in their last election in Aceh. In Mali, the ink is applied to the fingernail.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Sources</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="CITEREFN.a.2000" style="font-style:normal">N.a.&#32;(March 2000),&#32;"Bach Scores Turning to Dust in German Library",&#32;<it>American Libraries</it>:  24–25</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="CITEREFBarrow1972" style="font-style:normal">Barrow, W.J.&#32;(1972),&#32;<it>Manuscripts and Documents: Their Deterioration and Restoration</it>, Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, ISBN 081390408</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="CITEREFRei.CE.B2.CC.9Elandde_Groot1999" style="font-style:normal">Reiβ̞land, Birgit&#32;&amp;&#32;de Groot, Suzan&#32;(August 15-21, 1999),&#32;"Ink Corrosion: Comparison of the Currently Used Aqueous Treatments for Paper Objects",&#32;<it>Preprint from the 9th International Congress of IADA</it>, pp. 121–129</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="CITEREFRouchon-Quilletet_al.2009" style="font-style:normal">Rouchon-Quillet, V.&#32;&amp;&#32;et al.&#32;(2004),&#32;"The Impact of Gallic Acid on Iron Gall Ink Corrosion",&#32;<it>Applied Physics A</it>&#32;<b>79</b>:  389–392</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="CITEREFWaters2009" style="font-style:normal">Waters, C.E.&#32;(1940),&#32;<it>Inks</it>, U.S. Department of Commerce, National Bureau of Standards, U.S. Government Printing Office</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csmonitor.com/2004/0921/p18s02-hfks.html">
"Think Ink!"</weblink> by Sharon J. Huntington, Christian Science Monitor, September 21, 2004, retrieved January 17, 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "A History of Technology and Invention" by Maurice Audin, page 630.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ainsworth, Mitchell, C., "Inks and Their Composition and Manufacture," Charles Griffin and Company Ltd, 1904.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Martín-Gil J, Ramos-Sánchez MC, Martín-Gil FJ and José-Yacamán M. "Chemical composition of a fountain pen ink". <it>Journal of Chemical Education</it>, 2006, 83, 1476-78</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Banerji, Sures Chandra (1989). <it>A Companion to Sanskrit Literature</it>. Motilal Banarsidass. ISBN 812080063X.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sircar, D.C. (1996).<it>Indian epigraphy</it>. Motilal Banarsidass. ISBN 8120811666.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cuppers, Christoph (1989). "On the Manufacture of Ink." <it>Ancient Nepal - Journal of the Department of Archaeology</it>, Number 113, August-September 1989, pp. 1-7. [The Tibetan text and translation of a work called, ''Bzo gnas nyer mkho'i za ma tog'' by 'Jam-mgon 'Ju Mi-pham-rgya-mtsho (1846-1912) describing various traditional Tibetan techniques of making inks from different sources of soot, and from earth, [[puffball]]s, dung, ''ser-sha'' - a yellow fungus, and the fruit of ''tsi dra ka'' (''Ricinus communis'').]</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/2287697.xml">
Blue Wool Scale</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/898999.xml">
De-inked pulp</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/5298968.xml">
Dokumental</link></institution>
</company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/17687359.xml">
Election ink</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Indestructible ink</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/3767367.xml">
Ink Eradicator</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/65448.xml">
Invisible ink</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/5700907.xml">
Fountain pen inks</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/3372324.xml">
Gel pen</link></instrument>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<manuscript wordnetid="106406979" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/11791934.xml">
Preservation of Illuminated Manuscripts</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</manuscript>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/9396111.xml">
Preservation (library and archival science)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/1024371.xml">
Soy ink</link></commodity>
</merchandise>
</artifact>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/599157.xml">
Stark's Ink</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/12702150.xml">
Tattoo ink</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worldwideschool.org/library/books/tech/printing/FortyCenturiesofInk/toc.html">
Forty Centuries of Ink (David N. Carvalho); A detailed online textbook</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Atramentum.html">
Roman ink article by Alexander Allen In Smith's Dictionary Greek and Roman Antiquities (1875), in LacusCurtius</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mylearning.org/learning/investigate-archaeology/Making%20Roman%20Ink.pdf">
Roman ink recipe, etc.(MyLearning.Org, Yorkshire, UK)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://realscience.breckschool.org/upper/fruen/files/Enrichmentarticles/files/IronGallInk/IronGallInk.html">
Iron Gall Ink (Lois Fruen)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.knaw.nl/ecpa/ink/">
The ink corrosion website (KNAW NL)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.djmcadam.com/ink-recipe.html">
Ancient and Modern Ink Recipes (David N. Carvalho)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mspong.org/cyclopedia/inks.html">
Extensive list of ink recipes</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.printinginks.de">
Printing inks and related subjects Online lecture by University of Printing and Media, Stuttgart, Germany</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://housekeeping.about.com/od/stainremoval/a/inkstains.htm">
Tips on removing ink stains from clothing</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
