<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:06:50[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<header>
<title>GRaPH-Int</title>
<id>15342269</id>
<revision>
<id>218644334</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-11T15:25:55Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DOI bot</username>
<id>6652755</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Public health organizations</category>
<category>Medical genetics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="GraphInt_logo.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

GRaPH-Int Logo
</caption>
</image>
<p>

The <b>Genome-based Research and Population Health International Network</b> (GRaPH-Int) is an international collaboration of experts and researchers focused in the area of population health. The principal goal of the network is to promote the translation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/12388.xml">
genome</link>-based science and technology into improvements in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/2379996.xml">
population health</link>. </p>
<p>

One of GRaPH-Int's key features is the integration of knowledge from a range of disciplines, such as genome-based science, <link>
population sciences</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/53132.xml">
humanities</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/26781.xml">
social sciences</link>. The ‘Int’ underscores the interdisciplinarity of the collaboration, but also signifies that it is international and integrated. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Mission</st>
<p>

The mission of the Genome-based Research and Population Health International Network (GRaPH-Int) is to promote an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/3741372.xml">
international</link> collaboration that facilitates the responsible and effective integration of genome-based knowledge and technologies into public policies, programmes, and services for improving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/2379996.xml">
population health</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Bellagio Initiative </st>
<p>

Modern research in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/12266.xml">
genetics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/19200.xml">
molecular biology</link>, boosted by information emerging from the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/5219699.xml">
Human Genome Project</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
, offers new opportunities for the promotion of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/2379996.xml">
population health</link>. Anticipated benefits include more effective population-based public health disease <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/1228878.xml">
prevention</link> and control activities; population <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/1928867.xml">
screening</link> and predictive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/310782.xml">
genetic testing</link> for common multi-factorial diseases; and targeted populations-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/11869823.xml">
interventions</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. </p>
<p>

However, mining the genome-based information for potential benefits and ensuring that they are effectively implemented, with appropriate attention to avoiding harm, has proven to be an enormous task. A new field within public health, called <link>
public health genomics</link> has evolved which addresses these issues <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>
<p>

A meeting of experts was convened in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/694273.xml">
Bellagio</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/14532.xml">
Italy</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 in 2005 with funding from the <foundation wordnetid="113790712" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/227730.xml">
Rockefeller Foundation</link></institution>
</foundation>
 to address the tasks involved in deriving public health benefit from this vast array of new knowledge. The delegates saw the need for an international network, which would promote the goals of public health genomics. Based on discussions of the challenges involved, they developed the framework and priorities of the Genome-based Research and Population Health International Network (GRaPH-Int).  The Bellagio group defined GRaPH-Int as a network of individuals who are interested in the impact of the interaction between genes and the environment on population health <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

Following the Bellagio meeting, The GRaPH-Int website was launched at the 4th International DNA Sampling Conference - Montreal, June 2006.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Goals</st>
<p>

GRaPH-Int aims to establish itself as an international network that promotes the goals of public health, engages international experts, and shares knowledge and resources. The following six goals have identified for the network:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To provide an international forum for dialogue and collaboration </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To promote relevant research</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To support the development of an integrated knowledge base</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To promote education and training</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To encourage communication and engagement with the public and other stakeholders</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Enterprise</st>
<p>

The GRaPH-Int <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/10336.xml">
Enterprise</link> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.graphint.org/ver2/">
GraPH-Int website</weblink>) was developed and introduced at the Bellagio workshop as a conceptual and systematic description of the flow of information. It describes the process of translating genome-based science and technology into improvements in population health. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Bioportal</st>
<p>

The recent overload of information on public health genome-based science necessitates the creation of an international search engine to link policymakers, researchers and public health professionals to national policy statements, epidemiological data, public health, news and events. GRaPH-Int has undertaken the task of developing this service, and the first phase of development began in 2007. </p>
<p>

This search engine, referred to as the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.graphint.org/ver2/bioportal.cfm">
Bioportal</weblink>, will optimize searches on:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the ethical, legal and social issues surrounding public health genome-based science;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

public health genome-based literature;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

epidemiological data; and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

public health genome-based news and events.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Governance</st>
<p>

GRaPH-Int and its activity are overseen by an Administrative Hub, Secretariat, Executive Committee and a Steering Committee. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 The Administrative Hub </st>
<p>

The GRaPH-Int Administrative Hub is located in <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
 and is funded by the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/1170869.xml">
Public Health Agency of Canada</link></department>
</association>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</institute>
 (PHAC). A major component of the Administrative Hub is the Secretariat (managed by the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.crdp.umontreal.ca">
Centre de recherche en droit public (CRDP)</weblink> ), whose services better enable PHAC, as the designated Administrative Hub for the network.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Executive committee </st>
<p>

The purpose of the GRaPH-Int Executiv Committee is to provide leadership in fulfilling the mission and goals of GRaPH-Int. The founding Executive Committee members are Ron Zimmern, Public Health Genetics Unit (PHGU) now the PHG Foundation, Cambridge, UK, Wylie Burke, Institute for Public Health Genetics (IPHG) and Department of Medical History and Ethics, University of Washington, Seattle, U.S.A., Muin Khoury, National Office of Public Health Genomics (NOPHG), Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, U.S.A., Mohamed Karmali, Laboratory for Foodborne Zoonoses, and Office of Biotechnology, Genomics &amp; Population Health, Public Health Agency of Canada, and Professor Julian Little, Canada Research Chair in Human Genome Epidemiology, University of Ottawa.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Steering committee </st>
<p>

The purpose of the GRaPH-Int Steering Committee is to support the GRaPH-Int Executive Committee in their mission. The Steering Committee is composed of network participants in a mixture that will adequately represent the different institutional, scientific disciplines and perspectives necessary to address the mission and goals of GRaPH-Int. The Founder <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/3452243.xml">
Chairman</link> of the steering committee is Ron Zimmern. </p>
<p>

The Steering Committee elects the following Officers: Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson, and Secretary. The Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson, the past-Chairperson, Secretary, and the Executive Director constitute the Executive Committee. The founding executive committee members include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ron Zimmern, GRaPH-Int Interim Chair</entry>
</list>

Executive Director, PHG Foundation, Cambridge, UK</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mohamed A. Karmali, GRaPH-Int Executive Director</entry>
</list>

Director-General, Laboratory for Foodborne Zoonoses,
Office of Biotechnology, Genomics &amp; Population Health 
Public Health Agency of Canada, Ontario, Canada</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wylie Burke, Institute for Public Health Genetics (IPHG), </entry>
</list>

Department of Medical History and Ethics 
University of Washington, Seattle, USA</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Muin Khoury, Director, National Office of Public Health Genomics, Centers for Disease Control, Atlanta, USA</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Julian Little, Canada Research Chair, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/140699.xml">
University of Ottawa</link></university>
, Ottawa, Canada </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Founding organizations </st>
<p>

The following entities are recognized as GraPH-Int Founding Organizations:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.humgen.umontreal.ca">
HumGen International</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://depts.washington.edu/phgen/">
Institute for Public Health Genetics, University of Washington</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/genomics/">
National Office of Public Health Genomics, Centres for Disease Control</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.phgfoundation.org/">
PHG Foundation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/index-eng.php">
Public Health Agency of Canada</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Membership </st>
<p>

Organizational participation in GRaPH-Int is open to new members throughout the world that have an interest in the development and use of genome-based knowledge and technologies for the benefit of population health. </p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Collins, FS&#32;(1999).&#32;"Shattuck lecture – medical and societal consequences of the Human Genome Project". <it>English Journal of Medicine</it>&#32;<b>34</b>&#32;(1): 28–37.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Khoury, MJ;&#32;W Burke, EJ Thompson&#32;(2000). Genetics and public health in the 21st century.&#32;Oxford University Press..</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Stewart, A;&#32;P Brice, H Burton, P Pharaoh, S Sanderson, R Zimmern&#32;(2007). Genetics, Health Care and Public Policy. An Introduction to Public Health Genetics..&#32;Cambridge University Press.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Burke, W; MJ Khoury, A Stewart, RL Zimmern&#32;(July 2006).&#32;"Bellagio Group. The path from genome-based research to population health: development of an international public health genomics network.". <it>Genetic Medicine</it>&#32;<b>8</b>&#32;(7): 451–458. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097%2F01.gim.0000228213.72256.8c">
10.1097/01.gim.0000228213.72256.8c</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</organization>
</article>
