<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:07:38[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Process Development Execution System</title>
<id>15364809</id>
<revision>
<id>240746679</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-24T20:44:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>RussBot</username>
<id>279219</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Knowledge management</category>
<category>Semantic Web</category>
<category>Information science</category>
<category>Technical communication</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>Process Development Execution System (PDES)</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>, which is used by companies to perform development activities for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/525028.xml">
high-tech</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/39388.xml">
manufacturing</link> processes. A PDES is similar to a Manufacturing Execution System (MES) in several aspects. The central distinguishing factor is that PDESs are tailored for steering the development of a manufacturing process while MES are tailored for executing the volume production using the developed process. Therefore the focus and the toolset of a PDES is more on lower volume but higher flexibility and experimentation freedom. The tools of a MES are more focused on less variance, higher volumes, tighter control, and logistics. Both types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/454746.xml">
application software</link> have in common that they increase <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/174247.xml">
traceability</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/424899.xml">
productivity</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/12115455.xml">
quality</link> (for PDES the quality of the developed manufacturing process in contrast to the quality of the manufactured <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/580039.xml">
good (economics and accounting)</link>/commodity for MES). Additionally both software types share functions including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/30677.xml">
equipment</link> tracking, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/285436.xml">
product</link> genealogy, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/33663.xml">
labor</link> and item tracking, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/166789.xml">
cost</link>ing, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/627040.xml">
electronic signature</link> capture, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/160903.xml">
defect</link> and resolution monitoring, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/4192964.xml">
Executive Dashboard</link>s, and other various reporting solutions.<p>

PDES have many parts and can be deployed on various scales. From simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/9119527.xml">
Work in Progress</link> tracking to a complex solution integrated throughout an enterprise development infrastructure. The later are touching other enterprise systems like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/9310.xml">
Enterprise Resource and Planning System</link>s (ERPs), Manufacturing Execution Systems (MESs), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/597229.xml">
Product Lifecycle Management</link> (PLMs), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/62437.xml">
Supervisory, Control and Data Acquisition</link> (SCADA) solutions and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/1505641.xml">
Scheduling and Planning System</link>s (both long-term and short-term tactical).</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Example: PDES usage during semiconductor device development </st>
<p>

New ideas for manufacturing processes (for new goods/commodities or improved manufacturing) are often based on or can at least benefit from previous developments and existing recipes in use. The same is true when developing new devices e.g. a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/19638.xml">
MEMS</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/235757.xml">
sensor</link> or actuator. A PDES offers an easy way to access these previous developments in a structured manner. Information can be retrieved faster and previous results can be taken into account more efficiently. A PDES typically offers means to display and search result data from different viewpoints and to categorize the data according different aspects. These functionalities are applied to all result <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/18985040.xml">
data</link> like materials, process steps, machines, experiments, documents, pictures etc. The PDES also provides a way to relate entities belonging to the same or similar context and to explore the resulting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/18985062.xml">
information</link>.</p>
<p>

In the phase of assembling process steps to process flows a PDES can help to easily assemble, store, print, and transfer new process flows. By providing access to previously assembled process flows the designer of process flows is able to use those as building blocks or modules in the newly developed flow. The usage of standard building blocks can reduce the design time and the probability of errors drastically.</p>
<p>

A PDES shows its real advantages in the verification phase. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/243391.xml">
Knowledge</link> (e.g. in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/27696.xml">
semiconductor device fabrication</link>: Clean before deposition; After polymer spin-on no temperature higher than 100°C until resist is removed) have a form that can be expressed in a computer readable way; they can be expressed in rules. If a domain expert enters the rules for his/her process steps they can be used by all engineers to check newly developed process flows. For a PDES that means it has to be able to (1) manage rules (2) connect rules with Boolean terms (and, or, not) and (3) to check process flows using these rules. This rule check verifies the principle manufacturability of a newly designed manufacturing flow.</p>
<p>

The processing rule check gives no indication on the functionality or even the structure of the produced good or device. In the area of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/27696.xml">
semiconductor device fabrication</link> the techniques of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/5275369.xml">
semiconductor process simulation</link> / <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/5232898.xml">
TCAD</link> can provide at least an idea about the produced structures. To support this ’virtual fabrication’ a PDES is able to manage simulation models for process steps. Usually the simulation results are seen as standalone data. To rectify this situation PDESs are able to manage the result files in combination with the process flow, too. This enables the engineer to easily compare the expected results with the simulated outcome. The knowledge gained from the comparison can again be used to improve the simulation model. </p>
<p>

After the virtual verification the device is produced in an experimental fabrication environment. A PDES allows to transfer the process flow to the fabrication environment (e.g. in semiconductor: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/4107858.xml">
FAB</link>). This can be done by simply printing out a runcard for the operator or by interfacing to the <link>
MES</link> of the facility. On the other hand a PDES is able to manage and document last minute changes to the flow like parameter adjustments during the fabrication.
During and after processing a lot of measurements are done. The results of these measurements are often produced in the form of files like pictures or simple text files containing rows and columns of data. The PDES is able to manage these files, to link related results together, and to manage different versions of certain files (e.g. reports). Paired with flexible text and graphical retrieval and search methods a PDES provides mechanism to view and assess the accumulated data, information, and knowledge from different perspectives. It provides insight into previous developments concerning information aspects as well as for time aspects.
Finally more and more development activities in the industry are a collaborative effort. This leads to the need to exchange the information between the partners or to transfer process <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/14724.xml">
IP</link> from a vendor to a customer. The PDESs support this transfer while being selective to protect the IPR of the company.
</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

D. Ortloff, J. Popp, T. Schmidt, and R. Brück. Process Development Support Environment: A tool SUITE TO ENGINEER MANUFACTURING SEQUENCES In International Journal of Nanomanufacturing, “Recent Developments and Innovations in NEMS/MEMS devices”, 2007</p>
<p>

T. Schmidt, K. Hahn, T. Binder, J. Popp, A. Wagener, and R. Brück. OPTIMIZATION OF MEMS FABRICATION PROCESS DESIGN BY VIRTUAL EXPERIMENTS. In Proceedings of SPIE: Micro- and Nanotechnology: Materials, Processes, Packaging, and Systems III, Adelaide, volume 6415, 2006. Smart Materials, Nano and Micro-Smart Systems 2006.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/3238520.xml">
Microfabrication</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/2971012.xml">
Manufacturing Process Management</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Manufacturing Execution System </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/27696.xml">
Semiconductor device fabrication</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/19638.xml">
MEMS</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.siliconfareast.com/manufacturing.HTM">
Semiconductor Manufacturing</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.semiconductorglossary.com/">
Semiconductor Glossary</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
