<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:40:05[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Reversible computing</title>
<id>1539548</id>
<revision>
<id>220238330</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-18T22:23:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Digital electronics</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since June 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Mergefrom.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that  be  into this article or section. ()</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<b>Reversible computing</b> includes any <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/5926.xml">
computational process</link> that is (at least to some close approximation) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1699635.xml">
reversible</link>, i.e., time-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/14907.xml">
invertible</link>, meaning that a time-reversed version of the process could exist within the same general <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../087/9087.xml">
dynamical framework</link> as the original process.  For example, within the context of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/47922.xml">
deterministic</link> dynamical frameworks, a necessary condition for reversibility is that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1817475.xml">
transition function</link> mapping states to their successors at a given later time should be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/45196.xml">
one-to-one</link>.</p>
<p>

Probably the largest motivation for the study of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/13615.xml">
hardware</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> technologies aimed at actually implementing reversible computing is that they offer what is the only potential way to improve the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/11944078.xml">
energy efficiency</link> of computers beyond the fundamental <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/3108937.xml">
von Neumann-Landauer limit</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> of <it>kT</it> ln 2 energy dissipated per irreversible <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/264399.xml">
bit operation</link>, where <it>k</it> is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/53702.xml">
Boltzmann's constant</link> of 1.38 &amp;times; 10−23 J/K, and <it>T</it> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/19572300.xml">
temperature</link> of the environment into which unwanted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/9891.xml">
entropy</link> will be expelled.</p>
<p>

There are two major, closely-related, types of reversibility that are of particular interest for this purpose: <it>physical reversibility</it> and <it>logical reversibility</it>.  A process is said to be <it>physically reversible</it> if it results in no increase in physical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/9891.xml">
entropy</link>; it is <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/375900.xml">
isentropic</link></it>. Although <it>in practice</it> no nonstationary physical process can be <it>exactly</it> physically reversible or isentropic, there is no known limit to the closeness with which we can approach perfect reversibility, in systems that are sufficiently well-isolated from interactions with unknown external environments, when the laws of physics describing the system's evolution are precisely known.</p>
<p>

As was first argued by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../519/1385519.xml">
Rolf Landauer</link></scientist>
</person>
 of <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/18622259.xml">
IBM</link></company>
 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, in order for a computational process to be physically reversible, it must also be <it>logically reversible</it>. This statement is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/3108937.xml">
Landauer's Principle</link>.  A discrete, deterministic computational process is said to be logically reversible if the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1817475.xml">
transition function</link> that maps old computational states to new ones is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/45196.xml">
one-to-one function</link>.  </p>
<p>

For computational processes that are nondeterministic (in the sense of being probabilistic or random), the relation between old and new states is not a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/1954969.xml">
single-valued function</link>, and the requirement needed to obtain physical reversibility becomes a slightly weaker condition, namely that the size of a given ensemble of possible initial computational states does not decrease, on average, as the computation proceeds forwards.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 More on Landauer's principle </st>
<p>

Landauer's principle can be understood to be a simple logical consequence of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/133017.xml">
second law of thermodynamics</link> — which states that the entropy of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/402048.xml">
closed system</link> cannot decrease — together with the definition of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/41789.xml">
thermodynamic temperature</link>. For, if the number of possible logical states of a computation were to decrease as the computation proceeded forward (logical irreversibility), this would constitute a forbidden decrease of entropy, unless the number of possible physical states corresponding to each logical state were to simultaneously increase by at least a compensating amount, so that the total number of possible physical states was no smaller than originally (total entropy has not decreased).  </p>
<p>

Yet an increase in the number of physical states corresponding to each logical state means that for an observer who is keeping track of the logical state of the system but not the physical state (for example an "observer" consisting of the computer itself), the number of possible physical states has increased; in other words, entropy has increased from the point of view of this observer.  The maximum entropy of a bounded physical system is finite.  (If the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/14286.xml">
holographic principle</link> is correct, then physical systems with finite <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/27725.xml">
surface area</link> have a finite maximum entropy; but regardless of the truth of the holographic principle, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/25267.xml">
quantum field theory</link> dictates that the entropy of systems with finite radius and energy is finite.)  So, to avoid reaching this maximum over the course of an extended computation, entropy must eventually be expelled to an outside environment at some given temperature <it>T</it>, requiring that energy <it>E</it> = <it>ST</it> must be emitted into that environment if the amount of added entropy is <it>S</it>. For a computational operation in which 1 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/3364.xml">
bit</link> of logical information is lost, the amount of entropy generated is at least <it>k</it> ln 2, and so the energy that must eventually be emitted to the environment is <it>E</it> &amp;ge; <it>kT</it> ln 2.  </p>
<p>

This expression for the minimum energy dissipation from a logically irreversible binary operation was first suggested by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/15942.xml">
John von Neumann</link></scientist>
</person>
 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, but it was first rigorously justified (and with important limits to its applicability stated) by Landauer. For this reason, it is sometimes referred to as being simply the <it>Landauer bound</it> or <it>limit</it>, but if we wish to be more generous to its originator, we may prefer to refer to it as the <it>von Neumann-Landauer</it> (<it>VNL</it>) bound instead.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The reversibility of physics and reversible computing </st>
<p>

Landauer's principle (and indeed, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/133017.xml">
second law of thermodynamics</link> itself) can also be understood to be a direct logical consequence of the underlying reversibility of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/22939.xml">
physics</link>, as is reflected in the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../319/198319.xml">
general Hamiltonian formulation of mechanics</link></concept>
</idea>
, and in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/937739.xml">
unitary time-evolution operator</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanics</link> more specifically.  </p>
<p>

In the context of reversible physics, the phenomenon of entropy increase (and the observed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/296639.xml">
arrow of time</link>) can be understood to be consequences of the fact that our evolved predictive capabilities are rather limited, and cannot keep perfect track of the exact reversible evolution of complex physical systems, especially since these systems are never perfectly isolated from an unknown external environment, and even the laws of physics themselves are still not known with complete precision.  Thus, we (and physical observers generally) always accumulate <it>some</it> uncertainty about the state of physical systems, even if the system's true underlying dynamics is a perfectly reversible one that is subject to <it>no</it> entropy increase if viewed from a hypothetical omniscient perspective in which the dynamical laws are precisely known.</p>
<p>

The implementation of reversible computing thus amounts to learning how to characterize and control the physical dynamics of mechanisms to carry out desired computational operations so precisely that we can accumulate a negligible total amount of uncertainty regarding the complete physical state of the mechanism, per each logic operation that is performed. In other words, we would need to precisely track the state of the active energy that is involved in carrying out computational operations within the machine, and design the machine in such a way that the majority of this energy is recovered in an organized form that can be reused for subsequent operations, rather than being permitted to dissipate into the form of heat.</p>
<p>

Although achieving this goal presents a significant challenge for the design, manufacturing, and characterization of ultra-precise new physical mechanisms for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/5213.xml">
computing</link>, there is at present no fundamental reason to think that this goal cannot eventually be accomplished, allowing us to someday build computers that generate much less than 1 bit's worth of physical entropy (and dissipate much less than <it>kT</it> ln 2 energy to heat) for each useful logical operation that they carry out internally.  </p>
<p>

The motivation behind much of the research that has been done in reversible computing was the first seminal paper on the topic <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>, which was published by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/1624482.xml">
Charles H. Bennett</link></associate>
</scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 of IBM research in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/34751.xml">
1973</link>. Today, the field has a substantial body of academic literature behind it. A wide variety of reversible device concepts, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/18168.xml">
logic gate</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/8707643.xml">
electronic circuit</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/7597.xml">
processor architecture</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/23015.xml">
programming language</link>s, and application <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s have been designed and analyzed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/23269.xml">
physicist</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/9531.xml">
electrical engineer</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/328784.xml">
computer scientist</link>s.  </p>
<p>

This field of research awaits the detailed development of a high-quality, cost-effective, nearly reversible logic device technology, one that includes highly energy-efficient <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/228385.xml">
clocking</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/28738.xml">
synchronization</link> mechanisms. This sort of solid engineering progress will be needed before the large body of theoretical research on reversible computing can find practical application in enabling real computer technology to circumvent the various near-term barriers to its energy efficiency, including the von Neumann-Landauer bound.  This may only be circumvented by the use of logically reversible computing, due to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/133017.xml">
Second Law of Thermodynamics</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Practical logical reversibility </st>
<p>

Any <link>
computational algorithm</link> may be made logically reversible for as long as a complete history of each nonreversible operation can be maintained.  (This is seen in every software application which offers a multi-level "<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="105849040" confidence="0.8">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/1724996.xml">
Undo</link></feature>
</property>
</concept>
</idea>
" feature.)  The history will grow ever larger, so it is limited by available memory.  To partially circumvent that limitation, snapshots of the complete computational state can be saved at various intervals, to provide the ability to jump further backwards in time, although not smoothly.  (This approach is adopted by archival "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/533867.xml">
backup</link>" systems.)</p>
<p>

Reversible computing of this kind is usually not symmetrical in time.  (Reversing an operation may take more time, or less, because the underlying mechanism is different.)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/3168626.xml">
Reversible dynamics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/3015758.xml">
Maximum entropy thermodynamics</link> -- on the uncertainty interpretation of the Second Law of thermodynamics</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1699635.xml">
Reversible process</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/343286.xml">
Toffoli gate</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/1636691.xml">
Fredkin gate</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/25220.xml">
Quantum computing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/6645085.xml">
Billiard-Ball Computer</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/4154909.xml">
3 input universal logic gates</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="105849040" confidence="0.8">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/1724996.xml">
Undo</link></feature>
</property>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
J. von Neumann, Theory of Self-Reproducing Automata, Univ. of Illinois Press, 1966.</entry>
<entry id="2">
R. Landauer, "Irreversibility and heat generation in the computing process," IBM Journal of Research and Development, vol. 5, pp. 183-191, 1961.</entry>
<entry id="3">
C. H. Bennett, "Logical reversibility of computation," IBM Journal of Research and Development, vol. 17, no. 6, pp. 525-532, 1973.</entry>
<entry id="4">
C. H. Bennett, "The Thermodynamics of Computation -- A Review," International Journal of Theoretical Physics, vol. 21, no. 12, pp. 905-940, 1982.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://strangepaths.com/reversible-computation/2008/01/20/en/">
Introductory article on Reversible Computing</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eng.fsu.edu/~mpf/CF05/RC05.htm">
First Interational Workshop on Reversible Computing</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://revcomp.jot.com">
Reversible computing community Wiki</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
