<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:39:16[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<protocol  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106665108">
<direction  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106786629">
<rule  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106652242">
<header>
<title>Professional video over IP</title>
<id>1546973</id>
<revision>
<id>217406583</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-05T22:02:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DPachali</username>
<id>7668550</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Broadcasting</category>
<category>Internet protocols</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Professional video over IP</b> systems use some existing standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/54475.xml">
video codec</link> to reduce the program material to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/50082.xml">
bitstream</link> (such as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/1492465.xml">
MPEG-2 transport stream</link>), and then to use an <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/15323.xml">
Internet Protocol</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 (IP) network to carry that bitstream <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/4269641.xml">
encapsulated</link> in a stream of IP packets. This is typically accomplished using some variant of the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/26163.xml">
RTP</link></rule>
</direction>
</concept>
</idea>
</protocol>
</message>
 protocol.<p>

Carrying professional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/32441.xml">
video</link> over IP networks has special challenges compared to most non-time-critical IP traffic. Many of these problems are similar to those encountered in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
voice over IP</link>, but to a much higher level of engineering requirements. In particular, there are very strict <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/25315.xml">
quality of service</link> requirements which must be fulfilled for use in professional broadcast environments.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Packet loss </st>
<p>

Since even well-engineered IP networks tend to have a small residual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/2928109.xml">
packet loss</link> rate caused by low-probability statistical congestion events and amplification of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/763850.xml">
bit error</link>s in the underlying hardware, most professional solutions use some kind of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/41167.xml">
forward error correction</link> to ensure that the encoded video stream can be reconstructed even if a few packets are lost. This is typically applied at the packet level, since the encapsulated video bitstream is typically only designed to tolerate low levels of bit or burst errors, rather than the loss of whole packets.  Resending packets is not an option because of the sequential nature of the underlying video signal.  For live video, a resent packet would arrive well after the arrival of the next frame of video.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Network delay variation </st>
<p>

Network delay variation can be kept to a minimum by using a high-speed network backbone, and ensuring that video traffic does not encounter excessive queue delays. This is typically done by either ensuring that the network is not too close to its full capacity, or that video traffic is prioritized using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/1536216.xml">
traffic engineering</link> techniques (see below).</p>
<p>

The remaining delay variation can be removed by buffering, at the expense of added time delay. If forward error correction is used, a small proportion of packets arriving after the deadline can be tolerated, since they can be dealt with by being discarded on receipt, and then treated in the same way as lost packets.  Added time delay is particularly unwelcome in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/4455044.xml">
PTZ</link> cameras as it makes operator control difficult at values over 250ms.0</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Timing reconstruction </st>
<p>

The other problem presented by latency variation is that it makes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/28738.xml">
synchronization</link> more complex by making the recovery the underlying timing of the video signal far more difficult. This is typically solved by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/163005.xml">
genlock</link>ing both ends of the system to external <link>
station sync</link> signals, typically generated from sources such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
GPS</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
atomic clock</link>s, thus only requiring the extraction of coarse timing information at the receiving end in order to achieve high-quality video synchronization. The extraction of coarse timing data is typically done using a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/41548.xml">
phase locked loop</link> with a long time constant.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Adequate bandwidth </st>
<p>

Even with packet loss mitigation, video over IP will only work if the network is capable of carrying the content with some reasonable maximum packet loss rate. In practice, this means that video over IP will not work on overloaded networks. Since IP does not of itself offer any traffic guarantees, this must be applied at the network engineering level. One approach to this is the "quantity of service" approach which simply allocates sufficient bandwidth to video-carrying traffic that it will not congest under any possible load pattern. Other approaches include dynamic reduction in frame rate or resolution, <link>
network admission control</link>, <link>
bandwidth reservation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/242669.xml">
traffic shaping</link>, and <link>
traffic prioritization</link> techniques, which require more complex network engineering, but will work when the simple approach of building a non-blocking network is not possible. See <link>
 RSVP</link> for one approach to IP network traffic engineering.  </p>
<p>

The <link>
Pro-MPEG Wide Area Network group</link> has done much recent work on creating a draft standard for interoperable professional video over IP.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Use by Security Industry </st>
<p>

Within the security products industry, IP-based Closed Circuit Television (CCTV) is making gains on the analog market.  Key components of IP-based CCTV remain consistent with analog technologies: <link>
image capture</link>, with a combination of IP-based cameras or analog cameras using IP-based encoders; <link>
image transmission</link>; Storage and Retrieval, which uses techologies such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/54695.xml">
RAID array</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/87409.xml">
iSCSI</link> for recorded and indexed video; and <link>
video management</link>, which affords web browser-enabled management and control of IP-based CCTV systems.</p>
<p>

One key advantage of IP-based CCTV is the ability to use network infastructure, providing adequate bandwidth and availability of switching and routing, rather than coaxial cabling. However, running bandwidth-intensive surveillance video over corporate data networks is a point of organizational contention, depending on the potential impact on network performance. </p>
<p>

A class of companies (including <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/8161229.xml">
Milestone Systems</link></company>
, videoNEXT, Verint and others) produce Video Management Software to help manage capture and storage of video content. Digital video also makes possible Video Content Analysis, which allows automatic detection and identification of various kinds of objects or motion. Companies in this market include VideoIQ, ObjectVideo, and Cernium.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Several manufacturers of CCTV equipment, such as <link>
Dallmeier</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/3315726.xml">
Axis Communications</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/12730.xml">
General Electric</link></company>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/231367.xml">
Bosch</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/18150648.xml">
Pelco</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/168632.xml">
Siemens</link> and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/585363.xml">
Sanyo</link></company>
 are steadily integrating IP network technology into their product portfolios.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Compare with </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Professional video over ATM</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/4003229.xml">
DTM</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csoonline.com/read/090107/fea_analytics.html">
Video Analytics</weblink>, CSO Magazine, September 2007.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ipvideomarket.info/topics/VideoAnalytics">
IP Video Surveillance News and Reviews</weblink>, IP Video Market Info, May 2008.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
</article>
