<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:10:49[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<rule  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105846932">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<procedure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101023820">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<algorithm  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105847438">
<header>
<title>Bees algorithm</title>
<id>15501189</id>
<revision>
<id>227673944</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-24T18:22:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>RogoPD</username>
<id>6054944</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Bees</category>
<category>Artificial intelligence</category>
<category>Combinatorial algorithms</category>
<category>Optimization algorithms</category>
<category>Collective intelligence</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since July 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="150px" src="Merge-arrows.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrows
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  with . ()</col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

The <b>Bees Algorithm</b> is a population-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/28249.xml">
search algorithm</link> first developed in 2005.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> It mimics the food foraging behaviour of swarms of honey bees.  In its basic version, the algorithm performs a kind of neighbourhood search combined with random search and can be used for both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/420555.xml">
combinatorial optimisation</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> and functional optimisation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> </p>

<sec>
<st>
The foraging process in nature</st>
<p>

A colony of honey bees can extend itself over long distances (up to 14 km) and in multiple directions simultaneously to exploit a large number of food sources.A colony prospers by deploying its foragers to good fields. In principle, flower patches with plentiful amounts of nectar or pollen that can be collected with less effort should be visited by more bees, whereas patches with less nectar or pollen should receive fewer bees.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

The foraging process begins in a colony by scout bees being sent to search for promising flower patches. Scout bees move randomly from one patch to another. During the harvesting season, a colony continues its exploration, keeping a percentage of the population as scout bees.</p>
<p>

When they return to the hive, those scout bees that found a patch which is rated above a certain quality threshold (measured as a combination of some constituents, such as sugar content) deposit their nectar or pollen and go to the “dance floor” to perform a dance known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/1646040.xml">
waggle dance</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

This dance is essential for colony communication, and contains three pieces of information regarding a flower patch: the direction in which it will be found, its distance from the hive and its quality rating (or fitness). This information helps the colony to send its bees to flower patches precisely, without using guides or maps. Each individual’s knowledge of the outside environment is gleaned solely from the waggle dance. This dance enables the colony to evaluate the relative merit of different patches according to both the quality of the food they provide and the amount of energy needed to harvest it.  After waggle dancing on the dance floor, the dancer (i.e. the scout bee) goes back to the flower patch with follower bees that were waiting inside the hive. More follower bees are sent to more promising patches. This allows the colony to gather food quickly and efficiently.</p>
<p>

While harvesting from a patch, the bees monitor its food level. This is necessary to decide upon the next waggle dance when they return to the hive. If the patch is still good enough as a food source, then it will be advertised in the waggle dance and more bees will be recruited to that source.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Proposed Bees Algorithm</st>
<p>

The Bees Algorithm  is an optimisation algorithm inspired by the natural foraging behaviour of honey bees to find the optimal solution<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. The algorithm requires a number of parameters to be set, namely: number of scout bees (n), number of sites selected out of n visited sites (m), number of best sites out of m selected sites (e), number of bees recruited for best e sites (nep), number of bees recruited for the other (m-e) selected sites (nsp), initial size of patches (ngh) which includes site and its neighbourhood and stopping criterion. </p>
<p>

<b>The pseudo code for the bees algorithm in its simplest form<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>:</b></p>
<p>

1. Initialise population with random solutions.
2. Evaluate fitness of the population.
3. While (stopping criterion not met) //Forming new population.
4.   Select sites for neighbourhood search.
5.   Recruit bees for selected sites (more bees for best e sites) and evaluate fitnesses.
6.   Select the fittest bee from each patch.
7.   Assign remaining bees to search randomly and evaluate their fitnesses.
8. End While.</p>
<p>

In first step, the bees algorithm starts with the scout bees (n) being placed randomly in the search space. In step 2, the fitnesses of the sites visited by the scout bees are evaluated.
In step 4, bees that have the highest fitnesses are
chosen as “selected bees” and sites visited by them
are chosen for neighbourhood search. Then, in steps
5 and 6, the algorithm conducts searches in the
neighbourhood of the selected sites, assigning more
bees to search near to the best e sites. The bees can
be chosen directly according to the fitnesses
associated with the sites they are visiting.
Alternatively, the fitness values are used to
determine the probability of the bees being selected.
Searches in the neighbourhood of the best e sites
which represent more promising solutions are made
more detailed by recruiting more bees to follow them
than the other selected bees. Together with scouting,
this differential recruitment is a key operation of the
Bees Algorithm. However, in step 6, for each patch only the bee
with the highest fitness will be selected to form the
next bee population. In nature, there is no such a
restriction. This restriction is introduced here to
reduce the number of points to be explored. In step 7,
the remaining bees in the population are assigned
randomly around the search space scouting for new
potential solutions. These steps are repeated until a
stopping criterion is met. At the end of each iteration,
the colony will have two parts to its new population - 
those that were the fittest representatives from a patch 
and those that have been sent out randomly.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications</st>
<p>

The Bees Algorithm, which is inspired by the food foraging behaviour of honey bees, has found many applications in engineering field, such as:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Training neural networks for pattern recognition.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Forming manufacturing cells.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Scheduling jobs for a production machine.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Finding multiple feasible solutions to a preliminary design problems.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Data clustering<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Optimising the design of mechanical components.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Multi-Objective Optimisation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tuning a fuzzy logic controller for a robot gymnast.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/268020.xml">
Evolutionary computation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/762988.xml">
Swarm intelligence</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/9512445.xml">
Manufacturing Engineering Centre</link></institution>
</association>
</institute>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Pham DT, Ghanbarzadeh A, Koc E, Otri S, Rahim S and Zaidi M. The Bees Algorithm. Technical Note, Manufacturing Engineering Centre, Cardiff University, UK, 2005</entry>
<entry id="2">
Duc Truong Pham, Ashraf Afify, Ebubekir Koc "<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://conference.iproms.org/manufacturing_cell_formation_using_the_bees_algorithm_0">
Manufacturing cell formation using the Bees Algorithm</weblink></it>". IPROMS 2007 Innovative Production Machines and Systems Virtual Conference, Cardiff, UK.</entry>
<entry id="3">
D. T. Pham, E. Koç, J. Y. Lee, and J. Phrueksanant, Using the Bees Algorithm to schedule jobs for a machine, Proc Eighth International Conference on Laser Metrology, CMM and Machine Tool Performance, LAMDAMAP, Euspen, UK, Cardiff, p. 430-439, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Pham D.T., Ghanbarzadeh A., Koç E., Otri S., Rahim S., and  M.Zaidi "<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://conference.iproms.org/the_bees_algorithm_a_novel_tool_for_complex_optimisation_problems">
The Bees Algorithm – A Novel Tool for Complex Optimisation Problems</weblink></it>"", Proceedings of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://conference.iproms.org/iproms_2006_0">
IPROMS 2006 Conference</weblink>, pp.454-461</entry>
<entry id="5">
Von Frisch K. Bees: Their Vision, Chemical Senses and Language. (Revised edn) Cornell University Press, N.Y., Ithaca, 1976.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Seeley TD. The Wisdom of the Hive: The Social Physiology of Honey Bee Colonies. Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, Cambridge, 1996.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Bonabeau E, Dorigo M, and Theraulaz G. Swarm Intelligence: from Natural to Artificial Systems. Oxford University Press, New York, 1999.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Camazine S, Deneubourg J, Franks NR, Sneyd J, Theraula G and Bonabeau E. Self-Organization in Biological Systems. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2003.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Von Frisch K. Bees: Their Vision, Chemical Senses and Language. (Revised edn) Cornell University Press, N.Y., Ithaca, 1976.</entry>
<entry id="10">
D. T. Pham, E. Koç, A. Ghanbarzadeh, and S. Otri, Optimisation of the weights of multi-layered perceptrons using the Bees Algorithm, Proc 5th International Symposium on Intelligent Manufacturing Systems, Turkey, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="11">
D. T. Pham, A. Ghanbarzadeh, E. Koç, and S. Otri, Application of the Bees Algorithm to the training of radial basis function networks for control chart pattern recognition, Proc 5th CIRP International Seminar on Intelligent Computation in Manufacturing Engineering (CIRP ICME '06), Ischia, Italy, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="12">
D. T. Pham, S. Otri, A. Ghanbarzadeh, and E. Koç, Application of the Bees Algorithm to the training of learning vector quantisation networks for control chart pattern recognition, Proc Information and Communication Technologies (ICTTA'06), Syria, p. 1624-1629, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="13">
D. T. Pham, A. J. Soroka, A. Ghanbarzadeh, E. Koç, S. Otri, and M. Packianather, Optimising neural networks for identification of wood defects using the Bees Algorithm, Proc 2006 IEEE International Conference on Industrial Informatics, Singapore, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Pham D. T., Zaidi Muhamad, Massudi Mahmuddin, Afshin ghanbarzadeh, Ebubekir Koc, Sameh Otri. Using the bees algorithm to optimise a support vector machine for wood defect classification. IPROMS 2007 Innovative Production Machines and Systems Virtual Conference, Cardiff, UK."<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://conference.iproms.org/using_the_bees_algorithm_to_optimise_a_support_vector_machine_for_wood_defect_classification">
http://conference.iproms.org/using_the_bees_algorithm_to_optimise_a_support_vector_machine_for_wood_defect_classification</weblink></it>" </entry>
<entry id="15">
D. T. Pham, M. Castellani, and A. Ghanbarzadeh, Preliminary design using the Bees Algorithm, Proc Eighth International Conference on Laser Metrology, CMM and Machine Tool Performance, LAMDAMAP, Euspen, UK, Cardiff, p. 420-429, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="17">
D. T. Pham, A. J. Soroka, E. Koç, A. Ghanbarzadeh, and S. Otri, Some applications of the Bees Algorithm in engineering design and manufacture, Proc Int. Conference on Manufacturing Automation (ICMA 2007), Singapore, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="16">
D. T. Pham, S. Otri, A. A. Afify, M. Mahmuddin, and H. Al-Jabbouli, Data clustering using the Bees Algorithm, Proc 40th CIRP Int. Manufacturing Systems Seminar, Liverpool, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="19">
D.T Pham, Ahmed Haj Darwish, E.E Eldukhri, Sameh Otri.  "<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://conference.iproms.org/using_the_bees_algorithm_to_tune_a_fuzzy_logic_controller_for_a_robot_gymnast_0">
Using the Bees Algorithm to tune a fuzzy logic controller for a robot gymnast.</weblink></it>"", Proceedings of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://conference.iproms.org">
IPROMS 2007 Conference</weblink></entry>
<entry id="18">
Pham D.T., Ghanbarzadeh A.  "<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://conference.iproms.org/multi_objective_optimisation_using_the_bees_algorithm">
Multi-Objective Optimisation using the Bees Algorithm</weblink></it>"", Proceedings of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://conference.iproms.org">
IPROMS 2007 Conference</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bees-algorithm.org">
 The Bees Algorithm Official Website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cf.ac.uk">
 Cardiff University</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mec.cf.ac.uk">
 Manufacturing Engineering Centre</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mec.cf.ac.uk/research/body_pics/Bees_Poster.ppt">
 The Bees Algorithm - First Prize-winning Poster</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mec.cf.ac.uk/research/pubs/BEES%20on%20BBC%20Wales.mp3">
 BBC Interview Records</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mec.cf.ac.uk/research/body_pics/Bees_Poster.ppt">
 MEC Bees won ‘best communication’ prize at INTEGR8OR</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/south_east/5285106.stm">
 Boffins put dancing bees to work - BBC News</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</article>
