<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:39:57[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Polypill</title>
<id>1553528</id>
<revision>
<id>241875017</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-29T22:16:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Vernon39</username>
<id>1919155</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Drugs</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In medicine, the term <b>Polypill</b> has been coined to refer to a medication which contains a combination of active ingredients.
<sec>
<st>
Beginnings</st>
<p>

In an important and controversial article in the BMJ in 2003, Wald and Law proposed the
concept of a polypill combining 6 medications that are already on the market and have been
used for decades in order to reduce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/512662.xml">
cardiovascular disease</link>.  Wald and Law used an innovative analytic approach that combined the numerical results from several
high quality meta-analyses of the individual impact of these medications to produce an
estimate of the overall combined effect of the proposed polypill on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/196018.xml">
morbidity</link> and
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/8221.xml">
mortality</link>.</p>
<p>

So, the "polypill" is both </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 an idea for a physical pill - to increase <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/11713267.xml">
adherence</link> / <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/475034.xml">
compliance</link> by reducing the number of pills that a person has to take, and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 a novel methodological approach - in a sense a numeric "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/62329.xml">
meta-analysis</link> of meta-analyses" to estimate the combined impact of several medications and / or interventions.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Since then, there have been many articles written proposing other sorts of "polypills",
and using methodology similar to Wald and Law's.</p>
<p>

One of the most promising is a "polypill" for diabetes (and potentially for pre-diabetes).
(See : Kuehn B. M.  2006.  ""Polypill" Could Slash Diabetes Risks"  JAMA. 2006;296:377-380.)</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Wald and Law's "Polypill" Strategy to Reduce Cardiovascular disease by more than 80 %</st>

<p>

In their paper <it>A strategy to reduce cardiovascular disease by more than 80%</it> (published in the <periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/541927.xml">
British Medical Journal</link></periodical>
) on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/15802.xml">
June 28</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>, Wald and Law  postulated that by using a combination of well known, cheap medications in one pill (the "Polypill") would be a particularly effective treatment against cardiovascular disease.  They presented a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/27576.xml">
statistical model</link> which suggested widespread use of the polypill could reduce mortality due to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/69276.xml">
heart disease</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/625404.xml">
stroke</link>s by up to 80%. The treatment is potentially cheap, with few side effects (in perhaps 10-15% of recipients) and the research was based on data from many trials relating to the individual components.</p>
<p>

To date there have, however, been no actual patient research on the real benefits of the combined medications compared to the inferred benefits - calculated from the overwhelming evidence in favor of the polypill's individual components. The concepts they present are well recognised: reducing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/56558.xml">
blood pressure</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/6437.xml">
cholesterol</link> and taking a low dose of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/1525.xml">
aspirin</link> will help prevent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/69276.xml">
heart disease</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/625404.xml">
stroke</link>.  Tests of the Wald and Law polypill have been recommended in 2005.  Additionally, "polypills" are currently available in India.
<b>Any GP can currently prescribe ALL the components of the polypill separately for her/his patients.</b>  Unfortunately, the ingredients of the polypill are <b>off</b> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/23273.xml">
patent</link>.  Since this would make the polypill quite cheap (some estimates on the BMJ rapid responses were less than 70 pounds per year), there is little financial incentive for pharmaceutical companies to pay the high costs of a clinical trial.  (Naturally, however, large insurers, or <link>
national healthcare systems</link>, may have considerable financial incentive to pay for such trials).</p>
<p>

Wald and Law has taken the unusual and novel perspective that <b>everyone over the age of 55</b> should take a pill containing medications to manage these issues irrespective of individual risks. The idea is that if you reduce all blood pressures and cholesterols in all patients the population will benefit.  Basically, the polypill could be used as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/8000.xml">
default</link> medication
for all people over 55 (or for others with comparable risks).  </p>
<p>

Currently, individual cardiovascular risk can be calculated based on 50 year longitudinal study (and still going) on the population of <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/257273.xml">
Framingham, Massachusetts</link></village>
 (the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/1471689.xml">
Framingham Heart Study</link>). The polypill takes a population based approach to management. The concept of "normal" and treatment thresholds  becomes less relevant when taking a population based approach to disease control.Traditionally, the approach has been to treat only if certain risk thresholds have been reached.</p>
<p>

Paradoxically, even though an individual maybe not reach these traditional thresholds, benefit will still accrue by further reductions in blood pressure, cholesterol etc. This is because there is a sliding scale of risk; the concept of abnormal on one side of the line corresponding to high risk and requiring treatment, and normal on the other side, being low risk requiring no treatment is now under scrutiny.</p>
<p>

Doctors will be treating population risk rather than individual risk factor thresholds as is current mainstream practice. So, if everyone was given the “Polypill” the average blood pressure and cholesterol levels within the population would fall, thus reducing overall population risk.</p>
<p>

The "polypill" would contain 3 blood pressure medications at low dose:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/9078.xml">
diuretic</link>, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/1179611.xml">
bendroflumethiazide</link>,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/180150.xml">
beta-blocker</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/712313.xml">
atenolol</link>,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

an <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="109190918" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/2767.xml">
ACE inhibitor</link></agent>
</causal_agent>
</physical_entity>
 such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/711593.xml">
enalapril</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This is combined with
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/178197.xml">
statin</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/635659.xml">
simvastatin</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/1525.xml">
aspirin</link> at a dose of 75mg</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/54117.xml">
folic acid</link></entry>
</list>

Folic acid has been shown to reduce level of homocysteine in the blood which is another risk factor for heart disease.</p>
<p>

Further research is being planned and coordinated after an international forum recently discussed the concept of the “Polypill”.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Polypill for diabetes and Syndrome X </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/44677.xml">
Diabetes</link> - particularly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/154502.xml">
Type II diabetes</link> is a major cause of morbidity and mortality.
Diabetes also contributes substantially to cardiovascular risk.  Unfortunately, some
of the ingredients in Wald and Law's original polypill may not be advisable for patients
with diabetes (for example : <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/180150.xml">
beta-blockers</link> - which can lead to weight gain, and
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/1179748.xml">
thiazide diuretics</link>).  The polypill for diabetes includes :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/178197.xml">
Statin</link>.  To reduce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/51521.xml">
LDL cholesterol</link> and they also have recently been shown to have <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/726241.xml">
anti-inflamatory</link> properties.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 An  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="109190918" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/2767.xml">
ACE inhibitor</link></agent>
</causal_agent>
</physical_entity>
  (for blood pressure control AND to protect the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/17025.xml">
kidneys</link>).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<medicine wordnetid="103740161" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="114778436" confidence="0.8">
<drug wordnetid="103247620" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/1525.xml">
Aspirin</link></drug>
</agent>
</medicine>
</causal_agent>
</substance>
</physical_entity>
  (anti<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/196121.xml">
platelet</link> and antiinflamatory properties),   and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <knowledge_domain wordnetid="105999266" confidence="0.8">
<life_science wordnetid="106037298" confidence="0.8">
<medical_science wordnetid="106045562" confidence="0.8">
<medicine wordnetid="106043075" confidence="0.8">
<discipline wordnetid="105996646" confidence="0.8">
<science wordnetid="105999797" confidence="0.8">
<natural_science wordnetid="106000400" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/253720.xml">
Metformin</link></natural_science>
</science>
</discipline>
</medicine>
</medical_science>
</life_science>
</knowledge_domain>
 - an excellent medication for diabetes that is also associated with weight loss.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Many people who are overweight are diabetic without knowing it.  Many additional people
have <link>
pre diabetes</link> and may benefit from active intervention.  Overall, people who
have diabetes or prediabetes, high cholesterol and /or high blood pressure and are overweight
are considered to have <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/54439.xml">
metabolic syndrome</link> <b>X</b>, and may benefit substantially from the Diabetes polypill.</p>
<p>

Perhaps, as the polypill strategy becomes widely adopted, people over 55 with a "normal"
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/4788.xml">
body mass index</link> or waist circumference will take the Wald and Law polypill, and the obese or
substantially overweight will take the Diabetes / Syndrome X polypill.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
  Cost Effectiveness  </st>

<p>

If Wald and Law's analysis is correct, major cost savings and productivity gains can be
obtained from a polypill approach.  Similarly, the Diabetes / Syndrome X polypill is
estimated to save 100s of billions of dollars.  </p>
<p>

More importantly, the tremendous human cost of these devastating and underappreciated
chronic diseases can be substantially reduced.  When a person has a stroke, it can
ruin his or her quality of life.  It also places a major burden on carers.
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/284027.xml">
Kidney failure</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/56511.xml">
dialysis</link> (common in end-stage diabetics) is also devastating.</p>
<p>

A health care system or major insurer - like <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/477362.xml">
Kaiser Permanente</link></company>
 - could do very well both
financially and on a human level - if they fully tested and introduced the polypills.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Sources of resistance </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Medical expertise and simplicity of treatment </st>

<p>

If a polypill strategy works for a large percentage of the patient population,
it may threaten some experts and specialists who might stand to lose financially 
(although no doubt most of these experts would be delighted by the human benefits,
and would probably endorse it - despite any personal financial hardship that this might
cause them).</p>
<p>

The polypill - being a simple "off-the-rack" default treatment - also reduces the
sense of control and exercise of expertise that comes from prescribing individually
tailored medication regimens.  Unfortunately, individually tailored approaches may be
more expensive and difficult and time consuming to access.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Lifestyle Modification and "punishing the sinners" </st>

<p>

There are a large cohort of health professionals that advocate <link>
lifestyle modification</link>.
It is true that if you stop smoking, exercise an hour or more a day, and eat a healthy
low fat diet, that over time you can dramatically reduce your cardiovascular risk.</p>
<p>

Unfortunately, most people - in reality - find this far too difficult, unpleasant,
invasive and intrusive to adhere to, and therefore can not - in reality - achieve and
sustain these gains.  </p>
<p>

Furthermore, there is increasing evidence that even among individuals with healthly
lifestyles, that some medications - like statins - can even further reduce one's 
cardiovascular risk.</p>
<p>

It is - no doubt - best to remind patients about the benefits of lifestyle modifications
and encourage them to pursue them, but this does not justify delay of potentially highly
beneficial medications like the polypill.  In practice, most people above 55 will not be able
to sustain sufficient lifestyle modifications, and will benefit from medications such as those
contained in the polypill.</p>
<p>

In a sense, overly strong devotion to the lifestyle modification approach implies
that "sinners" (those who are unable or unwilling to dramatically alter their lifestyle
and habits) should expect to suffer for their non-compliance.  This does not seem to
be an appropriate way to deal with our fellow human beings who - like ourselves - are
sometimes flawed and weak - but nevertheless deserve effective preventive care.</p>
<p>

Naturally, individuals who prefer to first try a lifestyle modification approach should
be encouraged to do so.  But they should also be reminded that many people do not succeed
and that effective medical treatment is available.</p>
<p>

Cardiovascular disease and diabetes are often asymptomatic until substantial irreversible
damage has been done.  This makes a dogmatic "lifestyle modification" approach particularly
dangerous because it may drive away patients from treatment.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Satire </st>

<p>

Wald and Law's approach has generated substantial controversy and criticism.
Some of the more original contributions in this regard have take the form of satire.
One such article - which is quite well written - proposes - with tongue in cheek -
a mixture of many different healthy food types.  The authors have referred to this
as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/1339120.xml">
polymeal</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wald and Law.  2003.  <it>A strategy to reduce cardiovascular disease by more than 80%</it> <periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/541927.xml">
British Medical Journal</link></periodical>
 on June 28, 2003.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kuehn B. M.  2006.  ""Polypill" Could Slash Diabetes Risks"  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/3557058.xml">
JAMA</link>. 2006;296:377-380.</entry>
</list>

</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2008/sep/29/health.medicalresearch">
"Tests start on pill that could lengthen millions of lives: Tablet aims to cut heart attack and stroke risk: Four-in-one drug could be sold for just $1 a month" Sarah Boseley, health editor <it>The Guardian</it>, Monday September 29 2008.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
