<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:14:56[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Gyrokinetic ElectroMagnetic</title>
<id>15547210</id>
<revision>
<id>230882262</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-09T21:05:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Tamtamar</username>
<id>7433319</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Plasma physics</category>
<category>Computational physics</category>
<category>Plasma modeling</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>GEM</b> is short for <b>Gyrokinetic ElectroMagnetic</b>.  GEM is a gyrokinetic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/3532455.xml">
plasma</link> turbulence simulation that uses the <math>\delta f</math> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/596816.xml">
particle-in-cell</link> method.  It is used to study waves, instabilities and nonlinear behavior of tokamak fusion plasmas.  Information about GEM can be found at the GEM web page<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.
There are two versions of GEM, one is a flux-tube version <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> and the other one is a global general geometry
version<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.  Both versions of GEM use a field-aligned coordinate system. Ions are treated kinetically, but averaged over their gyro-obits and electrons are treated as drift-kinetic.
<sec>
<st>
 The modeling of the tokamak plasmas</st>
<p>

GEM solves the electromagnetic gyrokinetic equations which are the appropriate equations for well magnetized plasmas.  The plasma is treated statistically as a kinetic distribution function. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/365876.xml">
distribution function</link> depends on the three-dimensional position, the energy and magnetic moment. The time evolution of the distribution function is described by gyrokinetic theory which simply averages the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/1991528.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22The+Vlasov-Maxwell+system+of+equations%22])">
Vlasov-Maxwell system of equations</link> over the fast gyromotion associated with particles exhibiting cyclotron motion about the magnetic field lines.  This eliminates fast time scales associated with the gyromotion and reduces the dimensionality of the problem from six down to five.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Algorithm to solve the equations</st>
<p>

GEM uses the delta-f <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/596816.xml">
particle-in-cell</link> (PIC) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/3532455.xml">
plasma</link> simulation method. An expansion about an adiabatic response is made for electrons to overcome the limit of small time step, which is caused by the fast motion of electrons.  GEM uses a novel electromagnetic algorithm allowing direct numerical simulation of the electromagnetic problem at high plasma pressures.  GEM uses a two-dimensional domain decomposition (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/16230272.xml">
domain decomposition method</link>) of the grid and particles to obtain good performance on massively parallel computers.  A <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/56098.xml">
Monte Carlo method</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 is used to model small angle <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/1814410.xml">
Coulomb collision</link>s.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Applications</st>
<p>

GEM is used to study nonlinear physics associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/31439.xml">
tokamak</link> plasma turbulence and transport.  Tokamak turbulence driven by ion-temperature-gradient modes, electron-temperature gradient modes, trapped electron modes and micro-tearing modes has been investigated using GEM.  It is also being used to look at energetic particle driven magnetohydrodynamic (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/40310.xml">
magnetohydrodynamics</link>) eigenmodes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cips.colorado.edu/simulation/gem.htm">
Plasma Simulation Group - Center for Integrated Plasma Studies</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
A delta-f method for gyrokinetic simulations with kinetic electrons and electromagnetic perturbuations, Y. Chen and S. Parker, J. Comp. Phys. 189 463 (2003).</entry>
<entry id="3">
Electromagnetic gyrokinetic delta-f particle-in-cell turbulence simulation with realistic equilibrium profiles and geometry, Y. Chen and S. Parker, J. of Comp. Phys. 220 839 (2007)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cips.colorado.edu/simulation/index.htm">
http://cips.colorado.edu/simulation/index.htm</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
