<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:19:33[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>AceMedia</title>
<id>15624374</id>
<revision>
<id>201779533</id>
<timestamp>2008-03-29T09:31:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DumZiBoT</username>
<id>6085301</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from February 2008</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
<category>Multimedia software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=AceMedia&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22AceMedia%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(February 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



<p>

<b>aceMedia</b> is an <link>
EU</link>-funded project that aims at creating a system for multimedia content management.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Features of the aceMedia software include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 it runs on several platforms (PC, set-top box, mobile phone, web interface)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 it manages different users that may that share content, and their associated access rights</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 it includes image, language and video analysis functions that can automatically annotate content or handle textual queries in natural language</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

It was developed by 15 European partners<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> that can be classified in:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 research laboratories that provide innovative technologies from their expertise fields</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 high-tech companies that may re-use or sell (parts of) the software </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 companies that manage image or video databases, that provide the test content</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The project extended from 2004 to 2007, with the final review presented in February 2008. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Description </st>

<p>

The software comes in two flavours, the Personal Content System (PCS) application for home users and the Commercial Content Management (CCM) framework.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 The PCS app </st>

<p>

The PCS is a GUI where the user can import images and videos, organise in folders, annotate them and call content analysis tools on them.</p>
<p>

The content analysis tools include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a person detector that finds standing people in images</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a face analysis method that finds and recognizes faces in images</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a classifier that determines properties on a whole image (like whether it was taken from inside or outside, whether it was by night, etc.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a segmentation engine that detects textured areas on images (like trees, sky, rock, etc.)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 The CCM app </st>
<p>

It includes a web interface from which users can rate images and videos, and search them. Searching can be done with different criteria:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 textual search. Text queries in various languages are "understood" by the system, and searches are performed using all available information, including that from the image analysis algorithms</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 global image similarity, using global image descriptors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 precise image similarity: the user can define image regions (s)he is interested in on an example image, and the system finds the most relevant images</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A reasoning system combines annotations to make sure they are coherent. For example, on an image, a sky region is supposed to be above a rock region.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Architecture </st>

<p>

The PCS application and most of the CCM application are based on a Java framework that manages the content (stored as files) and the metadata (stored in a MySQL database). </p>
<p>

The content analysis tools are implemented in C or C++ and called by the framework.</p>
<p>

The server side of the web interface is in C#.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Future </st>

<p>

Some technologies developed during the lifespan of the project will be used by the participating companies. The main framework is to be published in open-source form.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acemedia.org">
aceMedia main website</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://acemedia.org/aceMedia/partners/index.html">
aceMedia :: The aceMedia consortium</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
