<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:23:15[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<disorder  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114052403">
<condition  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113920835">
<state  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100024720">
<physical_condition  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114034177">
<header>
<title>Internet addiction disorder</title>
<id>15734720</id>
<revision>
<id>243465733</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T17:01:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>McGeddon</username>
<id>455421</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Internet culture</category>
<category>Pornography</category>
<category>Miscellaneous psychiatric disorders</category>
<category>Addiction</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

{}
<b>Internet addiction disorder</b> (<b>IAD</b>) is a hypothetical disorder originally made as a satirical hoax<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> by Ivan Goldberg, M.D., in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/34658.xml">
1995</link>.  He took <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/1560377.xml">
pathological gambling</link> as diagnosed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/8497.xml">
DSM-IV</link> as his model for the spoofed description. <p>

Although IAD was meant to be a hoax, it is promoted as a real condition by some supporters.  Supporters often divide IAD into subtypes by activity, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/5710507.xml">
pornography</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> overwhelming and immoderate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/18984281.xml">
gaming</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> inappropriate involvement in online <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/2041117.xml">
social networking</link> sites or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/33645.xml">
blogging</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>, and Internet shopping addiction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>  Activities which, if done in person, would normally be considered troublesome, such as compulsive gambling or shopping, are sometimes called <b>net compulsions</b>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  Others, such as reading or playing computer games, are troubling only to the extent that these activities interfere with normal life. </p>
<p>

<b>Problematic computer use</b> or <b>pathological computer use</b> are accepted descriptions for excessive computer use that interferes with daily life.  These terms avoid the distracting and divisive term <it>addiction</it> and are not limited to any single cause. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Status</st>
<p>

Despite opposition from many quarters, researcher Kimberly Young, Psy. D. is lobbying for the inclusion of IAD into the DSM-V, the next edition of the DSM.  Some proponents believe that its inclusion would open the doors for private insurance companies to pay for Internet addiction counseling. However, many others argue that IAD is neither a true addiction nor a specific disorder and should not be classified as a mental disorder in DSM-V.  Furthermore, there is no evidence that people needing treatment are being denied it; instead, their situations are coded under other labels, such as <disorder wordnetid="114052403" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/4081458.xml">
ADD</link></physical_condition>
</state>
</condition>
</disorder>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/840273.xml">
depression</link>, according to the underlying situation. </p>
<p>

In June 2007, the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/282197.xml">
American Medical Association</link></organization>
 declined to recommend to the <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/160911.xml">
American Psychiatric Association</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
 that they include IAD as a formal diagnosis in the 2012 edition of the DSM.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Instead, their toned-down response recommended further research of "video game overuse."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>  Members of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/5437395.xml">
American Society of Addiction Medicine</link> opposed calling <link>
Internet overuse</link> and video games a true addiction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> Among the necessary research is a way to define "overuse" and a way to differentiate an "internet addiction" from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/737766.xml">
obsession</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/578436.xml">
self-medication</link> for depression or other disorders, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/8492449.xml">
compulsion</link>.</p>
<p>

While there is mixed agreement about whether Internet Addiction is a legitimate, simultaneously, self-proclaimed sufferers are resorting to the courts for redress. In one recent American case (Pacenza v. IBM Corp.), the plaintiff argued he was illegally terminated in violation of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/1338.xml">
Americans with Disabilities Act</link> owing to his Internet Addiction triggered by Vietnam War-related <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/82974.xml">
Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder</link>. The case is pending before the court in the Southern District of New York (case summarized in Glaser &amp; Carroll, 2007).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Supporters</st>
<p>

According to <academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/16188858.xml">
Maressa Orzack</link></academician>
, director of the Computer Addiction Study Center at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18426501.xml">
Harvard University</link></university>
's McLean Hospital, between five and ten percent of Web surfers suffer some form of Web dependency.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>  </p>
<p>

Another supporter, David Greenfield, Ph.D. of the <link>
Center for Internet Behavior</link> conducted a study with ABC News.com in 1999 and is author of <it>Virtual Addiction.</it>  He believes that some services available over the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> have unique psychological properties which induce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/529089.xml">
dissociation</link>, <link>
time distortion</link>, and instant gratifaction, with about 6% of individuals experiencing some significant impact on their lives. However, he says it may not best be seen as an addiction but rather as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/8492449.xml">
compulsion</link>.  Greenfield claims that sex, gaming, gambling, and shopping online can produce a mood-altering effect. </p>
<p>

According to the <link>
Center for Internet Addiction Recovery</link> (whose director is Kimberly S. Young, a researcher who has lobbied for the recognition of net abuse as a distinct clinical disorder), "Internet addicts suffer from emotional problems such as depression and anxiety-related disorders and often use the fantasy world of the Internet to psychologically escape unpleasant feelings or stressful situations."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Over 60% of people seeking treatment for IAD claim involvement with sexual activities online which they consider inappropriate, such as excessive attention to pornography or involvement in explicit sexual conversations online.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> More than half are also addicted to alcohol, drugs, tobacco, or sex.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

"Several counselors and other experts said time spent on the computer was not important in diagnosing an addiction to the Internet. The question, they say, is whether Internet use is causing serious problems, including the loss of a job, marital difficulties, depression, isolation and anxiety, and still the user cannot stop.
"The line is drawn with Internet addiction," said Mr. Zehr of Proctor Hospital, "when I'm no longer controlling my Internet use. It's controlling me." Dr. Cash and other therapists say they are seeing a growing number of teenagers and young adults as patients, who grew up spending hours on the computer, playing games and sending instant messages. These patients appear to have significant developmental problems, including attention deficit disorder and a lack of social skills."<it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></it></p>
<p>

In a March 2008 editorial published in the American Journal of Psychiatry, Dr. Jerald Block (2008) argues that Internet Addiction should be included as a disorder in the new fifth edition of the APA's Diagnostic &amp; Statistical Manual <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>.  He reasons that symptoms of IA mirror other compulsive/impulsive disorders, including: 1.) excessive use (often associated with a loss of sense of time); 2.) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/419447.xml">
withdrawal</link> symptoms when access is denied; 3.) increasing tolerance (including growing needs for exposure to obtain the same effects); and, 4.) negative repercussions (including social isolation). He notes that research has shown that up to 86% of study subjects showing IA symptoms also exhibited other diagnosable mental health disorders .</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticisms</st>
<p>

IAD suffers first from its misleading title.  Psychiatrist Dr. Goldberg acknowledges that Internet Addiction Disorder is not a true addiction and may in fact be no more than a symptom of other, existing disorders.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>  An overbroad description of addiction leaves open the possibility of every compensatory behavior being declared an addiction.  For example, a person who has lengthy telephone conversations with a friend to avoid an unpleasant situation could be declared "addicted to the telephone" with equal validity as a person who chats on the Internet with the same basic goal at bottom.</p>
<p>

Many others, including <link>
Carol Potera</link>, agree that Internet Addiction is inappropriately named. To the extent that the Internet is a social medium instead of an object, people cannot be addicted to it.  The analogy is made to an environment:  a person can not be truly addicted to living in a favorite town (no matter how distressing a change of home might be), and a goldfish can not be addicted to living in a pond.  </p>
<p>

Secondly, it is widely recognized, even by its supporters, that most if not all "Internet addicts" already fall under existing, legitimate diagnostic labels.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>  For many patients, overuse or inappropriate use of the Internet is merely a manifestation of their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/840273.xml">
depression</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/922.xml">
anxiety</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/2733733.xml">
impulse control</link> disorders, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/1560377.xml">
pathological gambling</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> In this criticism, IAD is compared to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/1324898.xml">
food addiction</link>, in which patients overeat as a form of self-medication for depression, anxiety, etc., without actually being truly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/927.xml">
addicted</link> to eating.</p>
<p>

It is possible that a person could have a pathological relationship with a specific aspects of the Internet, such as bidding on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/297359.xml">
online auctions</link>, viewing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/5710507.xml">
pornography</link>, online gaming, or online gambling (which is included under the existing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/1560377.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Pathological+gambling%22])">
Pathological Gambling</link>), but that does not make the Internet medium itself be addictive.  Here are common problems which are improperly lumped together under the IAD label:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A pathological gambler is a pathological gambler regardless of whether the gambling is done on a computer or face-to-face.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A person with poor impulse control can lose sleep over a suspenseful novel or favorite television show just as easily as he or she can lose sleep over an exciting computer game or the temptation to click on another <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/49547.xml">
web link</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A person with a sexual obsession is still a person with a sexual obsession, whether the pornography is viewed on a screen or on paper. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A person who shops obsessively (including during a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/20419.xml">
manic</link> phase) has an obsessive shopping problem whether the purchases are made in person, by mail, by phone, or online. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A problem day trader, who has a form of pathological gambling, is still a problem day trader regardless of whether the stock trading is done by computer, over the phone, or face-to-face. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Also, there are significant and critical differences between common Internet activities (e-mail, chatting, web surfing) and pathological gambling, which the IAD notion heavily parallels.  The Internet is largely a pro-social, interactive, and information-driven medium, while gambling is seen as a single, anti-social behavior that has very little social redeeming value.  So-called Internet addicts do not suffer from the same damage to health and relationships that are common to established addictions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Prevalence</st>
<p>

One researcher estimates that up to nine million Americans could be labeled as pathological computer users.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

British psychiatrists, reporting last year in the journal Advances in Psychiatric Treatment, say a "significant minority"  - some estimate between five and 10 per cent of online users—are addicted to the Internet, and that while early research suggests most are highly educated, highly introverted males, more recent studies suggest the bulk of the problem is occurring among middle-aged women on home computers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>
<p>

Several countries in Asia, particularly China, and South Korea have been reported to have the highest incidence of computer or Internet addiction among young people.</p>
<p>

Up to 30 percent of South Koreans under 18, or about 2.4 million people, are at risk of Internet addiction, said Ahn Dong-hyun, a child psychiatrist at Hanyang University in Seoul who just completed a three-year government-financed survey of the problem.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>
<p>

Data from China Internet Network Information Center (CNNIC), as of June 30, 2006, showed that 123 million people had gone online, of which 14.9% were teenagers below 18 years old. Chou and Hsiao reported that the incidence rate of Internet Addiction among Taiwan college students was 5.9% <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref>. Wu and Zhu<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> identified 10.6% of Chinese college students as Internet addiction <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref></p>
<p>

One Beijing judge, Shan Xiuyun, claimed that 85 percent of juvenile crime in the city was internet-related.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref> The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/420112.xml">
China Communist Youth League</link> claimed in 2007 that over 17 percent of Chinese citizens between 13 and 17 are addicted to the internet.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>
<p>

Block (2008) cites recent research data that suggested that 13.7% of Chinese adolescents -- roughly 10 million people -- met the diagnostic criterion for Internet Addiction. That insight, reportedly, led to China to restrict use of computers for gaming to three hours per day (2008).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Prognosis</st>
<p>

In many cases, though not all, the problem corrects itself.  "It was Professor Kiesler who called Internet addiction a fad illness. In her view, she said, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/6031216.xml">
television addiction</link> is worse. She added that she was completing a study of heavy Internet users, which showed the majority had sharply reduced their time on the computer over the course of a year, indicating that even problematic use was self-corrective."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Prevention and treatment </st>
<p>

Recovery strategies include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/7144.xml">
content-control software</link>, counseling, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/5750.xml">
cognitive behavioural therapy</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/31398.xml">
twelve-step programs</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<table style="background:transparent; width:100%;" cellpadding="0" class=" multicol" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col align="left" width="50%" valign="top">
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/174397.xml">
Computer addiction</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/1560377.xml">
Compulsive gambling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/2292497.xml">
Video game addiction</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
<col align="left" width="50%" valign="top">
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../480/314480.xml">
Pornography addiction</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/149973.xml">
Procrastination</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/892723.xml">
Workaholic</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nurseweek.com/features/97-8/iadct.html">
Internet Addiction?</weblink> August 8, 1997</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.thinkquest.org/06aug/02049/types_1.htm">
Internet addiction Disorder: The Mind Prison-types</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.thinkquest.org/06aug/02049/types_2.htm">
Internet addiction Disorder: The Mind Prison-types 2</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.thinkquest.org/06aug/02049/types_4.htm">
Internet addiction Disorder: The Mind Prison-types 4</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netaddiction.com/resources/ebay_addiction.html">
eBay Addiction</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netaddiction.com/net_compulsions.htm">
Types of Internet addiction?</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://psychcentral.com/news/2007/06/26/video-games-no-addiction-for-now/">
Video Games No Addiction For Now</weblink> June, 26, 2007</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.cincypost.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070628/NEWS01/706280356">
Medical association backs off labeling 'video-game addiction'</weblink> June 28, 2007</entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnn.com/2007/TECH/fun.games/06/25/addiction.video.games.reut/index.html">
Experts: Video games not an addiction</weblink> June 25, 2007 </entry>
<entry id="10">
Lea Goldman&#32;(<link>
2005-09-05</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://members.forbes.com/forbes/2005/0509/054.html">
This Is Your Brain on Clicks.</weblink>".&#32;  Forbes.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-07-17</link>.</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netaddiction.com/faq.htm">
Frequently Asked Questions</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netaddiction.com/cybersexual_addiction.htm">
Cybersex/Cyberporn Addiction</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/01/fashion/thursdaystyles/01addict.html?pagewanted=2&amp;_r=1&amp;ei=5070&amp;en=29b02b567c2ef1ef&amp;ex=1184731200">
Hooked on the Web: Help Is on the Way</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2008/mar/23/news.internet">
Addiction to internet 'is an illness'</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.physorg.com/news82749930.html">
Experts debate Internet addiction</weblink></entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netaddiction.com/newspr/press_release_index.htm#PR4">
Press Releases #4 at netaddiction.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/01/fashion/thursdaystyles/01addict.html?ex=1184731200&amp;en=29b02b567c2ef1ef&amp;ei=5070">
Hooked on the Web: Help Is on the Way</weblink></entry>
<entry id="19">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.health.am/psy/more/internet-addiction-recognition-and-interventions/">
Prevalence underestimated in problematic Internet use study, CNS Spectrums</weblink>".&#32;<it>Internet Addiction: Recognition and Interventions</it>.&#32;  Armenian Medical Network&#32;(2007).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-07</link>.</entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netaddiction.com/newspr/press_release_index.htm#PR4">
Press Release #4 at netaddiction.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="21">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/18/technology/18rehab.html">
In Korea, a Boot Camp Cure for Web Obsession</weblink>".&#32;  New York Times&#32;(2007).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-07</link>.</entry>
<entry id="20">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.health.am/psy/more/recognize-internet-addiction-as-a-mental-illness/">
Recognize Internet addiction as a mental illness</weblink>".&#32;<it>Internet addiction</it>.&#32;  The Ottawa Citizen&#32;(2007).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-07</link>.</entry>
<entry id="23">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">H.R. Wu and K.J. Zhu&#32;(2004).&#32;"Path analysis on related factors causing Internet addiction disorder in college students". <it>Chin J Public Health 20</it>: pp. 1363–1364.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="22">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">C. Chou and M.C. Hsiao&#32;(2002).&#32;"Internet addiction, usage, gratification, and pleasure experience: the Taiwan college students' case". <it>Comput Educ 35 (2000)</it>: pp. 65–80.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="25">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://observer.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,6903,1646663,00.html">
 China's young escape into the web</weblink>   November 20, 2005 </entry>
<entry id="24">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.health.am/psy/more/link-between-impulsivity-and-internet-addiction/">
The relationship between impulsivity and Internet addiction in a sample of Chinese adolescents</weblink>".&#32;  European Psychiatry&#32;(2007).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-07</link>.</entry>
<entry id="27">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ucc.nd.edu/self-help/internet-dependence">
University of Notre Dame Counceling Center, "Self help - Lost in Cyberspace"</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="26">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pacificepoch.com/newsstories/86510_0_5_0_M/">
17% Of Youth Addicted To Internet</weblink> January 11, 2007 </entry>
<entry id="29">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.thinkquest.org/06aug/02049/text_el/treatments_prev.htm">
Preventions</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="28">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.counseling.txstate.edu/selfHelp/bro/interadd.html">
Texas State University Counceling Center, "Internet addiction"</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="31">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.thinkquest.org/06aug/02049/text_el/treatments_self.htm">
Self-help strategies</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="30">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.thinkquest.org/06aug/02049/text_el/treatments_post.htm">
Post-treatments</weblink> </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Block, J.J. (2008). "Issues for DSM-V: Internet Addiction". American Journal of Psychiatry. 165:3; March 2008; p. 306-307.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caruso, D. (1998). <it>Critics Pick Apart Study on Internet and Depression.</it> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/library/tech/98/09/biztech/articles/14digicom.html">
available online</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hansen, S. (2002). "Excessive Internet usage or 'Internet Addiction'? The implications of diagnostic categories for student users." <it>Journal of Computer Assisted Learning</it> <b>18</b>(2) pp.232-236.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Potera, C. (1998). "Trapped in the Web?" <it>Psychology Today</it>, Mar/Apr 98, <b>31</b>(2) pp.66-70.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Surratt, Carla G (1999). <it>Netaholics? : the creation of a pathology</it> Commack, NY : Nova Science Publishers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Young, Kimberly S. (2001). <it>Caught in the Net: How to Recognize the Signs of Internet Addiction—and a Winning Strategy for Recovery''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</physical_condition>
</state>
</condition>
</disorder>
</article>
