<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:42:45[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network planning and design</title>
<id>1577061</id>
<revision>
<id>243645474</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T13:06:52Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bogdangiusca</username>
<id>9475</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Network architecture</category>
<category>Communication engineering</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Network planning and design</b> is an iterative process, encompassing 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22A+network+planning+methodology%22])">
topological design</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22A+network+planning+methodology%22])">
network-synthesis</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22A+network+planning+methodology%22])">
network-realization</link>, and is aimed at ensuring that a new network or service meets the needs of the subscriber and operator.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
The process can be tailored according to each new network or service.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><p>

This is an extremely important process which must be performed before the establishment of a new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/30322.xml">
telecommunication</link>s network or service. </p>

<sec>
<st>
A network planning methodology</st>
<p>

A traditional network planning methodology involves four layers of planning, namely: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 business planning </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 long-term and medium-term network planning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 short-term network planning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 operations and maintenance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>

Each of these layers incorporate plans for different time horizons, i.e. the business planning layer determines the planning that the operator must perform to ensure that the network will perform as required for its intended life-span. The Operations and Maintenance layer, however, examines how the network will run on a day-to-day basis.</p>
<p>

The network planning process begins with the acquisition of external information. This includes:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 forecasts of how the new network/service will operate;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the economic information concerning costs; and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the technical details of the network’s capabilities.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

It should be borne in mind that planning a new network/service involves implementing the new system across the first four layers of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/22747.xml">
OSI Reference Model</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> This means that even before the network planning process begins, choices must be made, involving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/83235.xml">
protocol</link>s and transmission technologies.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Once the initial decisions have been made, the network planning process involves three main steps:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Topological design</b>: This stage involves determining where to place the components and how to connect them. The (topological) optimisation methods that can be used in this stage come from an area of mathematics called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
Graph Theory</link>. These methods involve determining the costs of transmission and the cost of switching, and thereby determining the optimum connection matrix and location of switches and concentrators.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Network-synthesis</b>: This stage involves determining the size of the components used, subject to <link>
performance criteria</link> such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/41212.xml">
Grade of Service</link> (GoS). The method used is known as "Nonlinear Optimisation", and involves determining the topology, required GoS, cost of transmission, etc., and using this information to calculate a routing plan, and the size of the components.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Network realization</b>: This stage involves determining how to meet capacity requirements, and ensure reliability within the network. The method used is known as "Multicommodity Flow Optimisation", and involves determining all information relating to demand, costs and reliability, and then using this information to calculate an actual physical circuit plan.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

These steps are interrelated and are therefore performed iteratively, and in parallel with one another. The planning process is highly complex, meaning that at each iteration, an analyst must increase his planning horizons, and in so doing, he must generate plans for the various layers outlined above.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The role of forecasting</st>

<p>

During the process of Network Planning and Design, it is necessary to estimate the expected <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/41804.xml">
traffic intensity</link> and thus the <link>
traffic load</link> that the network must support.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> If a network of a similar nature already exists, then it may be possible to take <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/1577055.xml">
traffic measurements</link> of such a network and use that data to calculate the exact traffic load [2]. However, as is more likely in most instances, if there are no similar networks to be found, then the network planner must use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/1522933.xml">
telecommunications forecasting</link> methods to estimate the expected traffic intensity.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

The forecasting process involves several steps as follows:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Definition of problem;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Data acquisition;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Choice of forecasting method;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Analysis/Forecasting;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Documentation and analysis of results.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Dimensioning</st>
<p>

The purpose of dimensioning a new network/service is to determine the minimum capacity requirements that will still allow the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/41212.xml">
Teletraffic Grade of Service</link> (GoS) requirements to be met.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> To do this, dimensioning involves planning for peak-hour traffic, i.e. that hour during the day during which traffic intensity is at its peak.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

The dimensioning process involves determining the network’s topology, routing plan, traffic matrix, and GoS requirements, and using this information to determine the maximum call handling capacity of the switches, and the maximum number of channels required between the switches.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. This process requires a complex model that simulates the behavior of the network equipment and routing protocols.</p>
<p>

A dimensioning rule is that the planner must ensure that the traffic load should never approach a load of 100 percent.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> To calculate the correct dimensioning to comply with the above rule, the planner must take on-going measurements of the network’s traffic, and continuously maintain and upgrade resources to meet the changing requirements.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. Another reason for "overprovisioning" is to make sure that traffic can be rerouted in case a failure occurs in the network.</p>
<p>

Because of the complexity of network dimensioning, this is typically done using specialized software tools. Whereas researches typically develop custom software to study a particular problem, network operators typically make use of commercial network planning software (e.g. <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/15966661.xml">
OPNET Technologies</link></company>
, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wandl.com">
WANDL</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vpisystems.com">
VPISystems</weblink>).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Traffic Engineering</st>

<p>

Comparing to network engineering which adds resource, such as link, router, switch into the network, traffic engineering targets to change traffic path on the existing network to alleviate traffic congestion or accommodate more traffic demand.  </p>
<p>

This technology is critical when the cost of expanding network expansion  is prohibitively high and network load is not optimally balanced.  The first part provides financial motivation for traffic engineering while the second part grants the possibility of deploying this technology.  </p>
<p>

The available technologies for traffic engineering include <link>
MPLS</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
ATM</link> for current Internet backbone.  For example, MPLS allows carriers to provision LSPs with dynamic or explicit routes. The dynamic routes is controlled by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/4956681.xml">
CSPF</link> while the explicit routes are optimized in an offline tool or through a <link>
Path Computation Element</link> which is under study by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/15285.xml">
IETF</link>.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/17086395.xml">
Fast reroute</link> has been implemented by major vendors, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/51746.xml">
Cisco</link> and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link>
Juniper_Networks</link></company>
, to provide localized resilient capability for MPLS networks.  End-to-end protection is an alternative resilient approach.  It provisions a backup route for each primary route. Preplanning enough bandwidth for these backup routes is one of the active topic for survivable network design.  </p>
<p>

Provisioning a large number of LSPs also brought up scalability problem. Various solutions have been proposed and it is still an active topic under study.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Survivability</st>

<p>

Network survivability enables the network to maintain maximum network connectivity and quality of service under failure conditions. It has been one of the critical requirements in network planning and design. It involves design requirements on topology, protocol, bandwidth allocation, etc..  Topology requirement can be maintaining a minimum two-connected network against any failure of a single link or node.  Protocol requirements include using dynamic routing protocol to reroute traffic against network dynamics during the transition of network dimensioning or equipment failures.  Bandwidth allocation requirements pro-actively allocate extra bandwidth to avoid traffic loss under failure conditions.  This topic has been actively studied in conferences, such as the International Workshop on Design of Reliable Communication Networks <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.drcn.org/">
DRCN</weblink>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 Penttinen A., <it>Chapter 10 – Network Planning and Dimensioning, Lecture Notes: S-38.145 - Introduction to Teletraffic Theory</it>, Helsinki University of Technology, Fall 1999.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Farr R.E., <it>Telecommunications Traffic, Tariffs and Costs – An Introduction For Managers</it>, Peter Peregrinus Ltd, 1988.</entry>
</reflist>


</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
