<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:23:25[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<software  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106566077">
<header>
<title>PeakFit</title>
<id>15797535</id>
<revision>
<id>242441182</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T06:55:23Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Analytical software</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from September 2008</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Software</name>
<parameters>
<genre>
<link>
nonlinear peak separation and analysis software</link></genre>
<logo>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.systat.com/images/peakfit_big.gif">
http://www.systat.com/images/peakfit_big.gif</weblink></logo>
<screenshot>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.systat.com/products/PeakFit/show.php?imgimages/big_FILTER.gif&amp;headPeakFit-Offers-Sophisticated-Data-Manipulation">
http://www.systat.com/products/PeakFit/show.php?imgimages/big_FILTER.gif&amp;headPeakFit-Offers-Sophisticated-Data-Manipulation</weblink></screenshot>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.systat.com/products/PeakFit/">
http://www.systat.com/products/PeakFit/</weblink></website>
<latest_release_version>
4.1.2</latest_release_version>
<developer>
Systat Software, Inc.</developer>
<name>
PeakFit</name>
<latest_release_date>
2007</latest_release_date>
<license>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/18934886.xml">
proprietary</link></license>
<operating_system>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link></operating_system>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=PeakFit&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22PeakFit%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



<p>

PeakFit is an automated nonlinear peak separation and analysis software package for scientists performing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/27752.xml">
spectroscopy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/6329.xml">
chromatography</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/349676.xml">
electrophoresis</link>. </p>
<p>

It automatically finds and fits up to 100 peaks to a data set, at a time, enabling users to characterize peaks and find the best equation that fits their data. PeakFit can also enhance the data obtained from traditional numerical methods and lab instruments.</p>
<p>

PeakFit was originally developed by Ron Brown of AISN Software and distributed by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0EIN/is_1996_Oct_8/ai_18742814">
Jandel Scientific Software</weblink> in the late 1980’s but by January 2004, Systat Software acquired the exclusive worldwide rights from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/17886246.xml">
SPSS Inc.</link> to distribute SigmaPlot and other Sigma Series products. </p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Infrared spectroscopy study of nitrogen centers in microdiamonds from Ukrainian Neogene placers</b> Michail N. TARAN, Victor M. KVASNYTSYA, Klaus LANGER, and Katerina O. ILCHENKO European Journal of Mineralogy, Feb 2006; 18: 71 - 81.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>On the Possibility of using Commercial Software Packages for Thermoluminescence Glow Curve Deconvolution Analysis</b> V. Pagonis and G. Kitis Radiat Prot Dosimetry, Aug 2002; 101: 93 - 98.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Cryptococcus neoformans Chemotyping by Quantitative Analysis of 1H Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectra of Glucuronoxylomannans with a Computer-Simulated Artificial Neural Network</b> Robert Cherniak, Homayoun Valafar, Laura C. Morris, and Faramarz Valafar Clin. Diagn. Lab. Immunol., Mar 1998; 5: 146 - 159.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Powder X-Ray Diffraction Analysis of Homogeneous and Heterogeneous Sedimentary Dolostones</b> Brian Jones, Robert W. Luth, and Alexander J. MacNeil Journal of Sedimentary Research, Sep 2001; 71: 790 - 799.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Effects of ramp shortening during linear phase of relaxation on [Ca2+]i in intact skeletal muscle fibers</b> Yandong Jiang and Fred J. Julian Am J Physiol Cell Physiol, Jan 1999; 276: C152 - C160.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>An efficient chromatographic system for lipoprotein fractionation using whole plasma</b> Wendy Innis-Whitehouse, Xianzhou Li, W. Virgil Brown, and Ngoc-Anh Le J. Lipid Res., Mar 1998; 39: 679.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Members of a Novel Class of Arabidopsis Rho Guanine Nucleotide Exchange Factors Control Rho GTPase-Dependent Polar Growth</b> Ying Gu, Shundai Li, Elizabeth M. Lord, and Zhenbiao Yang PLANT CELL, Feb 2006; 18: 366 - 381.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Synchrotron micro-X-ray fluorescence analysis of natural diamonds: First steps in identification of mineral inclusions in situ</b> Husin Sitepu, Maya G. Kopylova, David H. Quirt, Jeffrey N. Cutler, and Thomas G. Kotzer American Mineralogist, Nov 2005; 90: 1740 - 1747.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Thermal and Structural Behavior of Anhydrous Milk Fat. 2. Crystalline Forms Obtained by Slow Cooling</b> C. Lopez, F. Lavigne, P. Lesieur, G. Keller, and M. Ollivon J Dairy Sci, Nov 2001; 84: 2402 - 2412.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Direct visualization of formylpeptide receptor binding on rounded and polarized human neutrophils: cellular and receptor heterogeneity</b> RJ Walter and WA Marasco J. Leukoc. Biol., May 1987; 41: 377.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>The effect of As-Sb substitution in the Raman spectra of tetrahedrite-tennantite and pyrargyrite-proustite solid solutions</b> Sherif Kharbish, Eugen Libowitzky, and Anton Beran European Journal of Mineralogy, Jul 2007; 19: 567 - 574.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>A new approach to determine and quantify structural units in silicate glasses using micro-reflectance Fourier-Transform infrared spectroscopy</b> Kim N. Dalby and Penelope L. King American Mineralogist, Nov 2006; 91: 1783 - 1793.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Hydroxyl ordering in igneous apatite</b> R. Chris Tacker American Mineralogist, Oct 2004; 89: 1411 - 1421.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Stability of magnesiowüstite in Earth's lower mantle</b> Jung-Fu Lin, Dion L. Heinz, Ho-kwang Mao, Russell J. Hemley, James M. Devine, Jie Li, and Guoyin Shen PNAS, Apr 2003; 100: 4405 - 4408.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>A sensitive and convenient method for lipoprotein profile analysis of individual mouse plasma samples</b> David W. Garber, Krishnaji R. Kulkarni, and G. M. Anantharamaiah J. Lipid Res., Jun 2000; 41: 1020.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>A Spectroscopic and Thermodynamic Study of Porphyrin/DNA Supramolecular Assemblies</b> Robert F. Pasternack, Jonas I. Goldsmith, Szilvia Szép, and Esther J. Gibbs Biophys. J., Aug 1998; 75: 1024 - 1031.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>APETx1 from Sea Anemone Anthopleura elegantissima Is a Gating Modifier Peptide Toxin of the Human Ether-a-go-go- Related Potassium Channel</b> M. Zhang, X.-S. Liu, S. Diochot, M. Lazdunski, and G.-N. Tseng Mol. Pharmacol., Aug 2007; 72: 259 - 268.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>The Effects of Force Inhibition by Sodium Vanadate on Cross-Bridge Binding, Force Redevelopment, and Ca2+ Activation in Cardiac Muscle</b> D. A. Martyn, L. Smith, K. L. Kreutziger, S. Xu, L. C. Yu, and M. Regnier Biophys. J., Jun 2007; 92: 4379 - 4390.</entry>
</list>


</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.systat.com/">
Systat Webpage</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.systat.com/products/PeakFit/resources/?sec=1011">
PeakFit Support Webpage</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</software>
</article>
