<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:25:46[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<plant  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103956922">
<header>
<title>El Cajón Dam (Mexico)</title>
<id>15876030</id>
<revision>
<id>243803897</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T02:34:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>The Anomebot2</username>
<id>1979668</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Dams</category>
<category>Mexico articles missing geocoordinate data</category>
<category>Hydroelectric power plants in Mexico</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>El Cajón Dam</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/381399.xml">
hydroelectric dam</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/87990.xml">
Mexican state</link> of <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/222245.xml">
Nayarit</link></village>
. Construction began in 2003 and was completed in June 2007. It cost $800 million to build. It is 2,100&nbsp;feet (640&nbsp;m) long and is 584&nbsp;feet (178&nbsp;m) high. The reservoir holds 177 billion&#32;cubic feet (5.0×109&nbsp;m3) of water, and the generators are capable of producing 750 megawatts of electricity.  The dam is operated by the <link>
Comisión Federal de Electricidad</link>, the state-owned Mexican electric monopoly, known as "CFE".<p>

Throughout the construction of the El Cajón hydroelectric Project, deemed to be completed in 54 months, the following is estimated:</p>
<p>

• A cost exceeding 800 million dollars, An economic benefit of 2 billion Pesos, The creation of 10 thousand direct and indirect jobs, The improvement of access roads that will benefit 20 thousand inhabitants belonging to 40 communities, An annual mean power generation of 1 thousand 228 Gwh, equal to 1.5 times the annual consumption of the State of Nayarit, An installed capacity of 750 MW, equal to lighting 7.5 million light bulbs, An annual savings of two million barrels of fuel oil. An increase in the firm power generation of the Aguamilpa Hydroelectric Station, due to the regulation of the Santiago river and its affluents in the basin, as well as The diversification of the primary energy sources in the National Electric System.  </p>
<p>


http://www.cfe.gob.mx/CAJON/en/]</p>
<p>

Coordinates needed: </p>



</bdy>
</plant>
</article>
