<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:26:03[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Umea Region</title>
<id>15886519</id>
<revision>
<id>204467368</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-09T15:22:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Leolaursen</username>
<id>1803593</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Västerbotten</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>The Umea Region</b> (Swedish: Umeåregionen) is a functional region which consists of six co-operating municipalities in north Sweden; <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/1021942.xml">
Bjurholm</link></village>
, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/1017559.xml">
Nordmaling</link></village>
, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/1021941.xml">
Robertsfors</link></village>
, <link>
Umeå</link>, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/1021935.xml">
Vindeln</link></village>
 and <link>
Vännäs</link>. The geographical area has over 140 000 inhabitants. The Umea Region does not take official decisions about benefits, allowances, invalid vehicle services and similar tasks, but  generates more money to urgent purposes through scale economy depending on joint distribution of service, personal union, mutual buy-ins, etc. 

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

In 1993 the six municipalities made a mutual agreement, approved by the six municipal councils, saying that:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Positive development for one municipality is a positive development for all six municipalities</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Establishment of new companies and investments on one municipality should be welcomed by all without conflicts</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Job opportunities should be spread throughout the Umea Region</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Increased freedom of choice and better service to inhabitants</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Joint development strategies</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The goals and policies for the organisation were:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Better efficiency in the public sector through co-ordination and scale economy</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Co-operation for development of all six municipalities</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The organization must be based upon democratic principals</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Today the tourism industry is the most well-developed joint project in the Umea Region, because the six municipalities together have the sea with beaches and islands, mountains with slalom slopes, forests with wild animals (elk, bear, catamount, wolf, beaver, reindeer), many lakes, rivers and rivulets for canoe-trips and fishing, ruins and heritage buildings, and the quite large city of Umeå with shopping, entertainments, restaurants with food from the cuisines of the world and night life.  </p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
Organization</link>
The council of the region meet four times a year and consists of the local government commissioners (politicians). They set up the strategic plans of the Umea Region. The head officers of the municipalities are the operative steering committee and meet once a month. There are 22 committees, in which representatives from every municipality by activity sit.</p>
<p>

The committees are established in the following operating ranges:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Culture</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Library</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Business</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Education</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Technique</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Planning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tourism</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Staff</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IT</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Care of the aged and the disabled</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Environment</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Communications</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Recreations</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Procurement</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Waste/mud</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Information</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The six municipalities have mutual EU-projects: UME&amp;Co - development of the tourism sector, City and County - local development, Library 2007 - increased access to the libraries, joint library ticket, The Grow Alliance/The train road Botniabanan as a growth factor - growth project within the region</p>
<p>

Financing
The Umea Region is financed by a fixed fee and a variable fee based on the number of inhabitants in the municipality. The annual budget is 1 500 000 SEK.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Today </st>

<p>

The co-operation is now firmly established, and there is an exchange of knowledge and experience between politicians and public officials. The following projects have been realized:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mutual salary system</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mutual leadership within the rescue service</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mutual organization of tourism</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mutual planning of upper secondary schools</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mutual switchboard</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mutual IT-platform</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mutual library</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Umea Region <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.umearegionen.se/">
http://www.umearegionen.se/</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Official tourist site for Umea </entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
