<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:34:17[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108058098">
<bank  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="109213565">
<header>
<title>VakıfBank</title>
<id>16044241</id>
<revision>
<id>242780849</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T16:55:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>AlleborgoBot</username>
<id>3813685</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Companies established in 1954</category>
<category>Banks of Turkey</category>
<category>Companies listed on the Istanbul Stock Exchange</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Company</name>
<parameters>
<location>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/802.xml">
Ankara</link></village>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link></location>
<company_type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/19360669.xml">
Bank</link></company_type>
<homepage>
http://www.vakifbank.com.tr</homepage>
<key_people>
Yusuf Beyazıt</key_people>
<company_name>
VakıfBank</company_name>
<company_logo>
<image width="200px" src="Vakifbank.jpg">
<caption>

VakıfBank logo
</caption>
</image>
</company_logo>
<foundation>
1954</foundation>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>VakıfBank</b> is the 3rd <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkish</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/19360669.xml">
bank</link>. VakıfBank was founded on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/1541.xml">
April 13</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/34982.xml">
1954</link> under the special law <it>Türkiye Vakıflar Bankası Türk Anonim Ortaklığı Kanunu</it>. VakıfBank’s initial purpose was the management of the cash revenues and expenditures of the charitable foundations set up during the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/22278.xml">
Ottoman Empire</link></country>
 period. VakıfBank was established in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/802.xml">
Ankara</link></village>
 and quickly began conducting banking activities with branch offices in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/3391396.xml">
Istanbul</link></village>
</site>
, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/802.xml">
Ankara</link></village>
 and <link>
İzmir</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<ss1>
<st>
1950's to 1980's</st>
<p>

In 1956, after conducting extensive studies and surveys in the major economic centers across <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link>, VakıfBank continued its growth by opening an additional 10 branches. In 1957, VakıfBank made its first venture towards broadening its services with the establishment of <it>Güneş Insurance</it>. Over the next 20 years, VakıfBank continued to expand and widen its geographic presence in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link> by opening new branches throughout <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link>, including in other important commercial and industrial regions. By 1977, VakıfBank had 206 branch offices.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
1980's</st>
<p>

During the 1980s, VakıfBank sought to keep pace with technological advances and placed special emphasis on improving its operations through investment in technology. VakıfBank improved automation and became fully integrated through a centralized mainframe computer system. In 1982, in an effort to conduct banking operations in a more dynamic manner and serve the particular needs of various regions, VakıfBank established regional directorates in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/3391396.xml">
Istanbul</link></village>
</site>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/8318223.xml">
Aegean</link> and the <link>
Çukurova</link> regions.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
1990's</st>
<p>

In the early 1990s, VakıfBank increased the scope of its consumer lending and diversified its loan portfolio by broadening its lending practices to include equipment financing, enterprise loans, auto loans, housing loans as well as loans for marriage, vacation and education. It began to expand its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/17182301.xml">
credit card</link> business by adopting principles of reputation credit and increasing its base of merchant customers, students and working class employees as well as by automating and centralizing its point of sale authorization system. VakıfBank also laid the groundwork to become a leader in alternative distribution channels by introducing self-service banking, telephone banking, and a mobile bank branch office — a full service branch office on wheels <it>Autobank</it>. VakıfBank was the first in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link> to offer payment services by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/17182301.xml">
credit card</link> over the telephone. In 1993, VakıfBank obtained its first syndicated loan in an amount of <it>US$ 38.5 million</it> and established <it>Vakıf Offshore</it> in the Turkish Republic of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/271409.xml">
Northern Cyprus</link></country>
.</p>
<p>

In 1995, VakıfBank overhauled its management structure in order to modernize and conform with contemporary bank management practices. VakıfBank also established its <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/8210131.xml">
New York</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 branch in order to increase its exposure to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/46313.xml">
international markets</link>. The <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/8210131.xml">
New York</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 branch conducts international operations, including trade finance and corporate banking. In 1996, VakıfBank established <it>Vakıf Gayrimenkul</it>, a real estate investment trust, and <it>Vakıf Risk Sermayesi Yatirim Ortakligi A.Ş.</it>, the first venture capital company in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link>. In 1997, VakıfBank conducted its first securitization for <it>US$ 130 million</it> in relation to credit and debit card receivables.</p>
<p>

In 1998, VakıfBank established its first home banking platform for customers with substantial business volume. VakıfBank also installed new computer systems to automate import and export transactions within the branch network for those branches conducting trade finance activities. VakıfBank became the first in Turkey to offer long-term home loans with maturities of up to 20 years. VakıfBank also introduced the <it>VakifBank Primary Schools</it> program, a scheme designed to turn former branch offices into schools for homeless children.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
2000's</st>
<p>

In 2000, VakıfBank completed its first <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/1043930.xml">
Eurobond</link> issue for <it>€200 million</it> with a term of three years. In addition, VakıfBank’s subsidiaries, <it>Güneş Insurance</it>, <it>Vakıf Financial Leasing</it>, <it>Vakıf Investment Trust Company</it>, <it>Vakıf Real Estate Investment Trust Company</it> and <it>Vakıf Venture Capital Company</it> all offered their shares to the public and listed on the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/3022849.xml">
Istanbul Stock Exchange</link></company>
.</p>
<p>

In 2001, VakıfBank also introduced internet banking with the launch of its internet site. VakıfBank currently has over 751,869 internet banking customers, an increase of almost 50% since 2003. In 2001, VakıfBank completed the first long-term borrowing following the Turkish economic crisis through the securitization of diversified payment rights for an amount of <it>US$ 200 million</it> and a term of five years. VakıfBank also became the first Turkish commercial bank to launch a syndicated loan facility following the economic crisis for an amount of <it>US$ 110 million</it>. Also in 2001, VakıfBank established a senior risk committee as well as a bank-wide risk committee, an internal control department and a new data processing center.</p>
<p>

In 2002, VakıfBank had the largest number of credit cards issued in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link> and ranked first in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link> in terms of the number of <link>
Maestro cards</link> issued by a banking institution, according to <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/378791.xml">
MasterCard</link></company>
.</p>
<p>

In 2003, VakıfBank continued its strategy to expand its customer base by effectively promoting both existing and new services to a larger segment of the population, including the upper middle class, middle-aged individuals with a steady source of income. VakıfBank borrowed <it>US$ 200 million</it> in a syndicated deal in which 36 banks participated, including 14 arrangers. In July 2005, VakıfBank increased this syndicated loan to <it>US$ 750 million</it> with 62 banks, including 34 arrangers. In September 2005, VakıfBank closed the 2005‑A Tranche of its new diversified payment rights securitization program which amounted to <it>US$ 750 million</it>. The securitization resulted in the sale of the diversified payment rights to the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/5073345.xml">
SPC</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
. Also in 2005, VakıfBank and <it>VakıfBank Pension Fund</it> sold, respectively, <it>27,900 million</it> and <it>4,300 million</it> Class D common shares of VakıfBank in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/63879.xml">
IPO</link>, representing 21.8% and 3.37%, respectively, of VakıfBank’s total shares.</p>
<p>

Since 2003, VakıfBank has initiated the following projects: a marketing and sales oriented new branch organization to promote customer satisfaction; the <it>Remote Access</it> (EXAPI System) enabling VakıfBank’s customers to trade directly on the <it>Istanbul Stock Exchange</it>; the <it>First Step Mutual Fund</it> for parents wanting to invest for their children; and a branded credit card program for groups such as students, teachers and soldiers as well as the <it>Supporter Credit Card</it> for the fans of the three most popular football clubs in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/1303104.xml">
Turkey Super League</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Present</st>
<p>

In September 2004, VakıfBank mandated an iternational consultancy firm to review the financial and operational performance of VakıfBank. VakıfBank continues to improve operating efficiencies and overall performance through a number of initiatives including: organizational restructuring, including the reorganization of VakıfBank’s head office and the consolidation of certain business units to create increased operating efficiencies; increasing its focus on customers, including expanding its customer base, cross-selling to existing customers and improving customer service by utilizing both its extensive branch network as well as its continually expanding range of alternative distribution channels; remodeling nearly all of its existing branches and exploring opportunities for new branch openings, particularly in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/28863.xml">
Marmara region</link>; 
focusing on sales at the branch level by shifting staff to sales functions; increasing its investment in human resources and optimizing personnel utilization; upgrading and overhauling the capacity and quality of its information technology systems, hardware and applications throughout both VakıfBank’s headquarters and its branch network; and developing its internal control functions, including the implementation of regional portfolio managers in its commercial banking operations and increasing responsibility at the branch level. VakıfBank intends to complete implementation of a majority of these initiatives during 2007. </p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
in Brief</st>
<p>

VakıfBank is one of the leading "multi-specialist" banks in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link>. The modern banking products and services that it offers cover not only corporate, commercial and small-scale enterprise banking, but also the retail and private banking sectors. Being engaged in investment banking and capital market activities in addition to the basic banking products and services, VakıfBank offers the full range of financial products required in this era via state of the art technology including, but not limited to underwriting, financial leasing and factoring services, etc. by means of its financial participations. </p>
<p>

VakıfBank has been reaching out its corporate and individual customers in a most efficient manner through its internet branches, telephone banking branch 1.868 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/46628.xml">
ATM</link>’s and 87.581 units of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/9008.xml">
POS</link> that constitute its alternative distribution channels as well as 311 branches spread throughout the country and undertaking a leading role in the financing of domestic and foreign trade. VakifBank has two international offices located in New York and Bahrain and it also has participation in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/576.xml">
Austria</link></country>
 named <it>VakifBank International AG</it> which has branches in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/55866.xml">
Vienna</link></village>
</site>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/6187.xml">
Cologne</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/10992.xml">
Frankfurt</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mission</st>
<p>

The mission of VakıfBank is to take modern banking forward through new leaps, considering people and information as its most significant capital in parallel with a social banking understanding based on the principle of firstly supporting the customers under all economic circumstances with its widespread branch network, wide range of products and service quality.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Vision</st>
<p>

The vision of VakifBank is to be one of the 3rd largest banks of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ownership Structure</st>
<p>

As of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/20587.xml">
March 31</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>, the share capital of VakıfBank was <it>YTL 2,500 million</it> consisting of <it>250,000,000,000 shares</it>, each share with a nominal value of <it>YTL 0.01</it>. VakıfBank is controlled by over 40,000 charitable foundations managed by the <link>
Turkish Prime Ministry</link>’s <link>
General Directorate of Foundations</link> (the <link>
GDF</link>). On November, 2005, VakıfBank and VakıfBank Pension Fund sold, respectively, 27,900,000,000 and 4,300,000,000 Class D common shares of VakıfBank in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/63879.xml">
IPO</link>, representing 21.8% and 3.37%, respectively, of VakıfBank’s total shares. Following the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/63879.xml">
IPO</link>, the <link>
GDF</link>’s equity interest in VakıfBank was reduced from 74.75% to 58.45% of VakıfBank’s shares.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../519/3678519.xml">
List of banks in Turkey</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
VakıfBank Güneş Sigorta Istanbul</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ziraat.com.tr/">
Official Webpage</weblink></p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:lightsteelblue;" class="navbox-title">
<image width="22x20px" src="Flag_of_Turkey.svg">
<caption>

Flag of Turkey
</caption>
</image>
 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/3022849.xml">
ISE</link></company>
 companies of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/9573841.xml">
Akbank</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/12365657.xml">
Aksa</link></institution>
</company>
&nbsp;· 
<manufacturer wordnetid="108060446" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/5334787.xml">
Anadolu Isuzu</link></business>
</enterprise>
</manufacturer>
&nbsp;· 
<link>
Arçelik</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/5192444.xml">
ASELSAN</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Beko Elektronik</link>&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/5368711.xml">
Denizbank</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<link>
DYO</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Eczacıbaşı İlaç</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Enka</link>&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/591985.xml">
Erdemir</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/4652116.xml">
Finansbank</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/4730160.xml">
Garanti Bank</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/3072085.xml">
HSBC Bank</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<link>
İş Bankası</link>&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/9575253.xml">
Kardemir</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/3631298.xml">
Karsan</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<link>
Koç Holding</link>&nbsp;· 
<beverage wordnetid="107881800" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/11943508.xml">
Kristal Kola</link></beverage>
&nbsp;· 
<link>
Migros</link>&nbsp;· 
<manufacturer wordnetid="108060446" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/10186058.xml">
Otokar</link></institution>
</business>
</enterprise>
</company>
</manufacturer>
&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/12363395.xml">
Petkim</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/5198608.xml">
Petrol Ofisi</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<link>
Sabancı Holding</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Tofaş</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
TÜPRAŞ</link>&nbsp;· 
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/2307042.xml">
Turkcell</link></company>
&nbsp;· 
<airline wordnetid="102690081" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/167925.xml">
Türk Hava Yolları</link></airline>
&nbsp;· 
<link>
Ülker</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Vestel</link></p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:lightblue;" class="navbox-title">
<image width="22px" src="Flag_of_Turkey.svg">
</image>
 Banks of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/9573841.xml">
Akbank</link></company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Albaraka Türk</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Alternatif Bank</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Anadolu Bank</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Bank Asya</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/231026.xml">
Citibank</link></company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/5368711.xml">
Denizbank</link></company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/4652116.xml">
Finansbank</link></company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/1313026.xml">
Fortis</link></company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/4730160.xml">
Garanti Bank</link></company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Halk Bankası</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
İş Bankası</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/3072085.xml">
HSBC</link></company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/13030081.xml">
Oyak Bank</link></institution>
</company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Şekerbank</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/9917553.xml">
Turkish Bank</link></institution>
</company>
&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Türk Ekonomi Bankası</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
VakıfBank</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Yapı Kredi Bankası</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull; <link>
Ziraat Bankası</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>







</sec>
</bdy>
</bank>
</company>
</article>
