<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:36:26[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<car  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="102958343">
<manufacturer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108060446">
<name  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106333653">
<trade_name  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106845599">
<enterprise  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108056231">
<part  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113809207">
<business  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108061042">
<language_unit  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106284225">
<header>
<title>Mikro&apos;67</title>
<id>16121282</id>
<revision>
<id>219810255</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-16T23:44:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bulgariandiecast</username>
<id>6601452</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Mikro&apos;67</category>
<category>Model manufacturers</category>
<category>Toy cars and trucks</category>
<category>Toy brands</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<sec>
<st>
 MATCHBOX </st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="LINCOLN-CONTINENTAL_MX_V.jpg">
<caption>

LINCOLN-CONTINENTAL MX V.jpg
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Mikro'67 is the Bulgarian manufacturer for <manufacturer wordnetid="108060446" confidence="0.8">
<name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.8">
<trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/143466.xml">
Matchbox (toy)</link></language_unit>
</business>
</part>
</enterprise>
</trade_name>
</name>
</manufacturer>
, <b>Gama</b>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/1879052.xml">
Schuco</link>, <manufacturer wordnetid="108060446" confidence="0.8">
<name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.8">
<trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8572675.xml">
NZG</link></language_unit>
</business>
</part>
</enterprise>
</trade_name>
</name>
</manufacturer>
 and other diecast models.</p>
<p>

Over the years, the factory (till 1989 part of the State Economic Group "ДСО МЛАДОСТ"/"DSO Mladost") has changed its own name starting first with "МИР" (from the communist period: "МИР/MIR" which means "peace" in Bulgarian) to МИКРО/МИКРО'67 (post communist period: "МИКРО/Mikro" which means "micro" in Bulgarian). Nowadays both the <b>Mikro</b> and <b>Mikro'67</b> names are used interchangeably.</p>
<p>

After making a deal with the <b>Matchbox</b> company in 1983 the factory initiated the production of the first five <b>Matchbox</b> <it>Superfast</it> models and the first few <it>Superking</it> models. The paint on all the models bearing pearl colors was not very durable, although this condition was later improved. Today it is very hard to find mint condition models from that time -- even in Bulgaria. Up until 1989, 17 <it>Superfast</it> models and 7 <it>Superking</it> models were introduced. Although all of the models had minor variations, they were essentially alike. Importantly, there was one primary condition for leasing the dies to the Bulgarian manufacturer - all the models produced were intended to be sold only to the Bulgarian market -- with no export. Additionally, after using the new dies, <b>MIR</b> was expected to return them.</p>
<p>

In 1991, after the Cold War had ended, production began on the "second wave" of <it>Superfast</it> models. In the beginning there were again limited variations, but some of the early editions have the decals and the colors of the original models. After a few years business relations soured between the <b>Matchbox</b> company and their Bulgarian partner. It seemed that after opening the borders, many of these Bulgarian models were sold abroad and some were very popular. The <b>Matchbox</b> company eventually broke the contract with <b>Mikro</b>, but they were unable get back the dies for some models (big mistake for them). The result of this split is that the <b>Matchbox</b> company doesn't recognize Bulgarian models as authentic <b>Matchbox</b>. After that <b>Mikro'67</b> following no rules, produced thousands of variations by color, decals and wheels. </p>
<p>

At the end of the 90's <b>Mikro</b> began offering advertising graphics on their models. 
Customers who wanted to personalize cars with a name, brand or a graphic could get a manufacturing deal for customized Bulgarian <b>Matchbox</b> models. There is one condition - the customer must order 100 pieces or more although the models may be different. This marketing tool was used by local companies to promote products targeting kids and youngsters and other companies related to auto care and auto parts. International matchbox and other diecast models clubs also got some limited edition models for their members on special events.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 GAMA </st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="OPEL_CORSA_CHEVY.jpg">
<caption>

OPEL CORSA CHEVY.jpg
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

In 1983 parallel with the <b>Matchbox</b> models, production began on the <b>Gama</b> models. The first 1-2 years they were all kit models for assembling and available in only one color -- pearl green. Later they started making the regular factory assembled models, but few <b>Gama</b> models are still in production nowadays.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 SCHUCO </st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="BMW-3ER_REIHE-POLICE.jpg">
<caption>

BMW-3ER REIHE-POLICE.jpg
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

In 1995 <b>Mikro</b> started making <b>Gama</b>/<b>Schuco</b> models for the German market. In the first few years of production they were unavailable on the Bulgarian market, but a limited number of models that didn't meet the German criteria for quality slipped from the factory and got into the hands of local collectors. <b>Mikro</b> was making mainly <it>Opel</it> models, although there were few <it>BMW</it> models and <it>Mercedes Vito</it>, promotional models and construction and other vehicles. The models were made and boxed in cheap boxes, exported to Germany where they were then transferred into their original <b>Schuco</b> boxes. Unlike the <b>Matchbox</b> models, none of the <b>Gama</b> or <b>Schuco</b> models have a sign on the base plate <it>"Made in Bulgaria"</it>. In fact some of them even have the "Made in Germany" or "Made in W.Germany" insignia. Perhaps one of the reasons for this is that the country of manufacture could affect sales because some collectors consider that the German and Chinese editions are and only the best.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Other models </st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Kidco_Burnin_wheels.JPG">
<caption>

Kidco Burnin wheels.JPG
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>Mikro'67</b> made and still make some tin <b>Buddy L</b> and <b>Tonka</b> models. From 2004 are made few <b>NZG</b> (1/50) diecast models.</p>
<p>

Only one diecast model is actually 100% designed and made in Bulgaria. All the rest came from leased dies from toy manufacturers around the world (<b>Matchbox</b>, <b>Gama</b>, <b>Schuco</b>, <b>NZG</b>, <b>Yaxon</b>, <b>Kidco</b>, <b>Tonka</b>, <b>Buddy L</b>).</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Tonka_coca-cola_truck_bulgaria.jpg">
<caption>

Tonka coca-cola truck bulgaria.jpg
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The future </st>

<p>

It is uncertain how much longer <b>Mikro'67</b> will stay in business. Recently they have encountered some problems with the lowered quality of their models, a uniform production list for more than 15 years and other issues leading to low sales. From time to time they run out of parts and make a model with the wheels of another model (even Matchbox wheels sometimes get on a non-Matchbox models) or they switch wheels from model to model, just because it is cheaper. The <b>Mikro</b> website <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mikro67.com/">
www.mikro67.com</weblink>is rarely updated and suffers from a lack of appropriate information and images, supports only the Bulgarian language, and is 90% oriented to tin models.
Product/model catalogs never have been issued to customers or collectors, and there are only two known editions of the A4 size sheets intended for merchants.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Mir_catalog.jpg">
<caption>

Mir catalog.jpg
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Reference </st>

<p>

More information and pictures may be found on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bulgariancollection.com/">
www.bulgariancollection.com</weblink> - a reference site for Bulgarian diecast models.</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</language_unit>
</business>
</part>
</enterprise>
</trade_name>
</name>
</manufacturer>
</car>
</article>
