<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:34:10[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Rice Diet</title>
<id>16183551</id>
<revision>
<id>243250514</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T20:04:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Diets</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Rice Diet</b> is a program specializes in the prevention, treatment and reversal of obesity, hypertension, diabetes and congestive heart failure. The diet consists of fruits, grains, vegetables, beans, and olive oil with small amounts of non-fat dairy and seafood (&amp; lean meats), which is what patients are directed to eat when they return home both for continued weight loss and maintenance. On completion of the program, resources are available for participants to continue with a healthy lifestyle, and to maintain the improved health gained while on the residential program.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
It is crucial that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/36979.xml">
rice</link> be brown rice. White rice has the fiber and nutrients stripped from it vitamins are often put back in but the fiber is lost. Part of what makes the diet work is the fiber in the brown rice.
<sec>
<st>
Origin</st>
<p>

The Rice Diet was created by Walter Kempner, born in Germany in 1903. Joining <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/53273.xml">
Duke University</link></university>
's Department of Medicine in 1934 more as a researcher than a clinician,  he had received his early scientific training in the lab of Otto Warburg and as a consequence was oriented around the problems of cellular oxygen. When the war broke out, he was needed
as a clinician and it was in this role that the Rice Diet was born.  The story goes that he told a woman to eat only rice without salt and fruit and come back in two weeks.  She appeared to have misunderstood and returned after two months  transformed and so the Rice Diet was born.  His original studies addressed the problem of malignant hypertension.  What was soon revealed due to the interconnectedness of the various organ systems, was that the rice diet helped control many other serious conditions including diabetes and cardiovascular disease. </p>
<p>

Kempner was reputed to be a strict disciplinarian and was said to have his patients tested daily for changes and adherence to the program.  He expected complete commitment to the very restricted eating program.  He also strongly recommended daily exercise, mainly walking, to supplement the diet. A careful reading of the literature will reveal that the working theory of the rice diet is to bring more oxygen into the tissues. He found that even slight overall elevation in overall oxygen tension brought with it significant health benefits.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Program</st>
<p>

As well as meals using the Rice Diet, the program provides classes, groups and workshops for stress management and exercise, nutritional lectures, and personal medical supervision.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Menu</st>
<p>

Participants in the program have a limited menu selection initially, then choose from a range of items comprising fresh fruits and vegetables, grains, fish, and legumes (beans), varied daily. The name Rice Diet is somewhat confusing (the diet origins being the study of rice as a staple), as more than 30 food items are available, including a number of rices.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Day 1 - Breakfast, Lunch and Dinner: 2 Starches, 2 Fruits</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Day 2- through 7 - Breakfast: 1 Starch, 1 Non-fat Dairy, 1 Fruit </entry>
</list>

Lunch and Dinner: 3 Starches, 3 Vegetables, 1 Fruit</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Low Salt</st>
<p>

Salt is restricted in the Rice Diet, since the body swells with salt (sodium) and water. Most people's diet contains approx. 4-7 grams of sodium, yet less than half a gram a day is necessary for normal body function. </p>
<p>

Salt is a problem for patients with high blood pressure and kidney failure, and this is true also for most people if present in higher quantities in the diet. Salt stimulates the appetite, whereas herbs and spices simply flavor the food. </p>
<p>

Limiting salt reduces several health risks, including cholesterol, blood pressure, heart size and weight, as well as reducing the need to medicate for these problems. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Rosati, Kitty G.;&#32;Robert Rosati. The Rice Diet Solution: The World-Famous Low-Sodium, Good-Carb, Detox Diet for Quick and Lasting Weight Loss.&#32;Simon &amp; Schuster. ISBN 0425214664.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Rosati, Kitty G.&#32;(January 2, 2007). The Rice Diet Cookbook: 150 Easy, Everyday Recipes and Inspirational Success Stories from the Rice Diet Program Community.&#32;Simon &amp; Schuster. ISBN 1416539220.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ricedietprogram.com">
Rice Diet Website</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
