<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:35:09[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<issue  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105814650">
<header>
<title>Cruise ship pollution in the United States</title>
<id>16220091</id>
<revision>
<id>243801485</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T02:19:04Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>X96lee15</username>
<id>1536919</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Ocean pollution</category>
<category>Cruise ships</category>
<category>Pollution in the United States</category>
<category>Environmental issues with shipping</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The cruise industry is a significant and growing contributor to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/32022.xml">
United States economy</link>, providing more than $32 billion in benefits annually and generating more than 330,000 U.S. jobs, but also making the environmental impacts of its activities an issue to many. Although cruise ships represent a small fraction of the entire <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/28362.xml">
shipping</link> industry worldwide, public attention to their environmental impacts comes in part from the fact that cruise ships are highly visible and in part because of the industry’s desire to promote a positive image.<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/314855.xml">
Cruise ship</link>s carrying several thousand passengers and crew have been compared to “floating cities,” and the volume of wastes that they produce is comparably large, consisting of sewage; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/216928.xml">
wastewater</link> from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/148414.xml">
sink</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/477822.xml">
shower</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/4606337.xml">
galley</link>s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/216193.xml">
graywater</link>); <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/38031.xml">
hazardous waste</link>s; solid waste; oily <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/88168.xml">
bilge water</link>; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/1686070.xml">
ballast water</link>; and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/10934212.xml">
air pollution</link>. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/6026779.xml">
waste stream</link>s generated by cruise ships are governed by a number of international protocols (especially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/308347.xml">
MARPOL</link>) and U.S. domestic laws (including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/647655.xml">
Clean Water Act</link> and the <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../820/16219820.xml">
Act to Prevent Pollution from Ships</link></issue>
), regulations, and standards, but there is no single law or rule. Some cruise ship waste streams appear to be well regulated, such as solid wastes (garbage and plastics) and bilge water. But there is overlap of some areas, and there are gaps in others. Some, such as graywater and ballast water, are not regulated (except in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/12010.xml">
Great Lakes</link>), and concern is increasing about the impacts of these discharges on public health and the environment. In other areas, regulations apply, but critics argue that they are not stringent enough to address the problem — for example, with respect to standards for sewage discharges. Environmental advocates have raised concerns about the adequacy of existing laws for managing these wastes, and they contend that enforcement is weak.</p>
<p>

In 2000, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
U.S. Congress</link> enacted legislation restricting cruise ship discharges in U.S. navigable waters within the state of <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/624.xml">
Alaska</link></symbol>
. <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/5407.xml">
California</link></country>
, <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/624.xml">
Alaska</link></symbol>
, and <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/19977.xml">
Maine</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 have enacted state-specific laws concerning cruise ship pollution, and a few other states have entered into voluntary agreements with industry to address management of cruise ship discharges. Meanwhile, the cruise industry has voluntarily undertaken initiatives to improve <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/3444688.xml">
pollution prevention</link>, by adopting waste management guidelines and procedures and researching new technologies. Concerns about cruise ship pollution raise issues for Congress in three broad areas: adequacy of laws and regulations, research needs, and oversight and enforcement of existing requirements. Legislation to regulate cruise ship discharges of sewage, graywater, and bilge water nationally was introduced in the <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<congress wordnetid="108308800" confidence="0.8">
<meeting wordnetid="108307589" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/2588078.xml">
109th Congress</link></group>
</gathering>
</meeting>
</congress>
</social_group>
, but there was no further congressional action.</p>
<p>

This article describes the several types of waste streams that cruise ships may discharge and emit. It identifies the complex body of international and domestic laws that address pollution from cruise ships. It then describes federal and state legislative activity concerning cruise ships in Alaskan waters and activities in a few other states, as well as current industry initiatives to manage cruise ship pollution.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Background</st>
<p>

More than 46,000 commercial vessels — <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/2506366.xml">
tanker</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/1324895.xml">
bulk carrier</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/262084.xml">
container ship</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/4177.xml">
barge</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/370666.xml">
passenger ship</link>s — travel the oceans and other waters of the world, carrying cargo and passengers for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/39208.xml">
commerce</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/18580879.xml">
transport</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/25381.xml">
recreation</link>. Their activities are regulated and scrutinized in a number of respects by international <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/2383814.xml">
protocols</link> and U.S. domestic laws, including those designed to protect against discharges of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollutants</link> that could harm <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/2192596.xml">
marine resources</link>, other parts of the ambient environment, and human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/80381.xml">
health</link>. However, there are overlaps of some requirements, gaps in other areas, geographic differences in jurisdiction based on differing definitions, and questions about the adequacy of enforcement.</p>
<p>

Public attention to the environmental impacts of the maritime industry has been especially focused on the cruise industry, in part because its ships are highly visible and in part because of the industry’s desire to promote a positive image. It represents a relatively small fraction of the entire shipping industry worldwide. As of January 2008, passenger ships (which include cruise ships and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/50771.xml">
ferries</link>) composed about 12% of the world shipping fleet.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The cruise industry is a significant and growing contributor to the U.S. economy, providing more than $32 billion in total benefits annually and generating more than 330,000 U.S. jobs,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> but also making the environmental impacts of its activities an issue to many. Since 1980, the average annual growth rate in the number of cruise passengers worldwide has been 8.4%, and in 2005, cruises hosted an estimated 11.5 million passengers. Cruises are especially popular in the United States. In 2005, U.S. ports handled 8.6 million cruise embarcations (75% of global passengers), 6.3% more than in 2004. The worldwide cruise ship fleet consists of more than 230 ships, and the majority are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/402049.xml">
foreign-flagged</link>, with <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/17791.xml">
Liberia</link></country>
 and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/22997.xml">
Panama</link></country>
 being the most popular flag countries.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Foreign-flag cruise vessels owned by six companies account for nearly 95% of passenger ships operating in U.S. waters. Each year, the industry adds new ships to the total fleet, vessels that are bigger, more elaborate and luxurious, and that carry  larger numbers of passengers and crew. Over the past two decades, the average ship size has been increasing at the rate of roughly 90&nbsp;feet (27&nbsp;m) every five years. The average ship entering the market from 2008 to 2011 will be more than 1,050&nbsp;feet (320&nbsp;m) long and will weigh more than 130,000 tons.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> </p>
<p>

To the cruise ship industry, a key issue is demonstrating to the public that cruising is safe and healthy for passengers and the tourist communities that are visited by their ships. Cruise ships carrying several thousand passengers and crew have been compared to “floating cities,” in part because the volume of wastes produced and requiring disposal is greater than that of many small cities on land. During a typical one-week voyage, a large cruise ship (with 3,000 passengers and crew) is estimated to generate 210,000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/12882.xml">
gallon</link>s of sewage; 1 million gallons of graywater (wastewater from sinks, showers, and laundries); more than 130 gallons of hazardous wastes; 8 tons of solid waste; and 25,000 gallons of oily bilge water.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Those wastes, if not properly treated and disposed of, can pose risks to human health,
welfare, and the environment. Environmental advocates have raised concerns about the adequacy of existing laws for managing these wastes, and suggest that enforcement of existing laws is weak.</p>
<p>

A 2000 General Accounting Office (GAO) report focused attention on problems of cruise vessel compliance with environmental requirements.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/199096.xml">
GAO</link></agency>
 found that
between 1993 and 1998, foreign-flag cruise ships were involved in 87 confirmed illegal discharge cases in U.S. waters. A few of the cases included multiple illegal discharge incidents occurring over the six-year period. GAO reviewed three major waste streams (solids, hazardous chemicals, and oily bilge water) and concluded that 83% of the cases involved discharges of oil or oil-based products, the volumes of which ranged from a few drops to hundreds of gallons. The balance of the cases involved discharges of plastic or garbage. GAO judged that 72% of the illegal discharges were accidental, 15% were intentional, and 13% could not be determined. The 87 cruise ship cases represented 4% of the 2,400 illegal discharge cases by foreign-flag ships (including tankers, cargo ships and other commercial vessels, as well as cruise ships) confirmed during the six years studied by GAO. Although cruise
ships operating in U.S. waters have been involved in a relatively small number of pollution cases, GAO said, several have been widely publicized and have led to criminal prosecutions and multimillion-dollar fines.</p>
<p>

In 2000, a coalition of 53 environmental advocacy groups petitioned the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
Environmental Protection Agency</link></agency>
 (EPA) to take regulatory action to address pollution by cruise ships.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> The petition called for an investigation of wastewater, oil, and solid waste discharges from cruise ships. In response, EPA agreed to study cruise ship discharges and waste management approaches. As part of that effort, in 2000 EPA issued a background document with preliminary information and recommendations for further assessment through data collection and public information hearings. Subsequently, in December 2007, the agency released a draft cruise ship discharge assessment report as part of its response to the petition. This report summarized findings of recent data collection activities (especially from cruise ships operating in Alaskan waters). EPA expects to issue a completed report by the end of 2008, and at that time will identify a range of options and alternatives to address cruise ship waste streams.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Cruise ship waste streams</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/16219394.xml">
Cruise ship pollution</link></issue>
</it>
</indent>
Cruise ships generate a number of waste streams that can result in discharges to the marine environment, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/19725160.xml">
sewage</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/216193.xml">
graywater</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/38031.xml">
hazardous waste</link>s, oily <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/88168.xml">
bilge</link> water, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/16220606.xml">
ballast water</link>, and solid waste. They also emit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/10934212.xml">
air pollutants</link> to the air and water. These wastes, if not properly treated and disposed of, can be a significant source of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/24358.xml">
pathogen</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/66575.xml">
nutrient</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/51108.xml">
toxic substance</link>s with the potential to threaten human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/80381.xml">
health</link> and damage aquatic life. It is important, however, to keep these discharges in some perspective, because cruise ships represent a small — although highly visible — portion of the entire international shipping industry, and the waste streams described here are not unique to cruise ships. However, particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/6026779.xml">
types of wastes</link>, such as sewage, graywater, and solid waste, may be of greater concern for cruise ships relative to other seagoing vessels, because of the large numbers of passengers and crew that cruise ships carry and the large volumes of wastes that they produce. Further, because cruise ships tend to concentrate their activities in specific coastal areas and visit the same ports repeatedly (especially <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/18933066.xml">
Florida</link></symbol>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/5407.xml">
California</link></country>
, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/8210131.xml">
New York</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/53840.xml">
Galveston</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/11388236.xml">
Seattle</link>, and the waters of <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/624.xml">
Alaska</link></symbol>
), their cumulative impact on a local scale could be significant, as can impacts of individual large-volume releases (either accidental or intentional).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
International laws and regulations</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<legal_document wordnetid="106479665" confidence="0.8">
<treaty wordnetid="106773434" confidence="0.8">
<issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<agreement wordnetid="106770275" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<written_agreement wordnetid="106771653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/308347.xml">
MARPOL 73/78</link></written_agreement>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</agreement>
</issue>
</treaty>
</legal_document>
</document>
</message>
</statement>
&nbsp;and <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../820/16219820.xml">
Act to Prevent Pollution from Ships</link></issue>
</it>
</indent>
<statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<legal_document wordnetid="106479665" confidence="0.8">
<treaty wordnetid="106773434" confidence="0.8">
<issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<agreement wordnetid="106770275" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<written_agreement wordnetid="106771653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/308347.xml">
MARPOL 73/78</link></written_agreement>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</agreement>
</issue>
</treaty>
</legal_document>
</document>
</message>
</statement>
 is one of the most important treaties regulating pollution from ships. <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<legal_document wordnetid="106479665" confidence="0.8">
<treaty wordnetid="106773434" confidence="0.8">
<issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<agreement wordnetid="106770275" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<written_agreement wordnetid="106771653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/308347.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Annexes%22])">
Six Annexes of the Convention</link></written_agreement>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</agreement>
</issue>
</treaty>
</legal_document>
</document>
</message>
</statement>
 cover the various sources of pollution from ships and provide an overarching framework for international objectives. In the U.S., the Convention is implemented through the <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../820/16219820.xml">
Act to Prevent Pollution from Ships</link></issue>
. Under the provisions of the Convention, the United States can take direct enforcement action under U.S. laws against <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/402049.xml">
foreign-flagged</link> ships when pollution discharge incidents occur within U.S. jurisdiction. When incidents occur outside U.S. jurisdiction or jurisdiction cannot be determined, the United States refers cases to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/6162348.xml">
flag state</link>s, in accordance with MARPOL. These procedures require substantial coordination between the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/32223.xml">
Coast Guard</link></activity>
</administration>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</group>
</service>
</event>
</social_group>
</body>
</work>
, the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/31975.xml">
State Department</link></agency>
, and other flag states, and the response rate from flag states has been poor.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Federal laws and regulations</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/16220926.xml">
Regulation of ship pollution in the United States</link></issue>
</it>
</indent>
In the United States, several federal agencies have some jurisdiction over cruise ships in U.S. waters, but no one agency is responsible for or coordinates all of the relevant government functions. The U.S. Coast Guard and EPA have principal regulatory and standard-setting responsibilities, and the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/52563.xml">
Department of Justice</link></agency>
 prosecutes violations of federal laws. In addition, the Department of State represents the United States at meetings of the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/14986.xml">
IMO</link></administration>
</group>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
</social_group>
</body>
 and in international treaty negotiations and is responsible for pursuing foreign-flag violations. Other federal agencies have limited roles and responsibilities. For example, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/37876.xml">
National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</link> (NOAA, <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/70243.xml">
Department of Commerce</link></agency>
) works with the Coast Guard and EPA to report on the effects of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/1827851.xml">
marine debris</link>. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/416918.xml">
Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service</link> (APHIS) is responsible for ensuring <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/25237.xml">
quarantine</link> inspection and disposal of food-contaminated garbage (these APHIS responsibilities are part of the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/58236.xml">
Department of Homeland Security</link></agency>
). In some cases, states and localities have responsibilities as well. For more information about any of the laws described here, see <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/16220926.xml">
Regulation of ship pollution in the United States</link></issue>
.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Sewage</st>
<p>

The Federal Water Pollution Control Act, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/647655.xml">
Clean Water Act</link> (CWA), is the principal U.S. law concerned with limiting polluting activity in the nation’s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/18842308.xml">
stream</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/18842431.xml">
lake</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/78471.xml">
estuaries</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/496983.xml">
coastal waters</link>. Under the act, pollutant discharges from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/7622892.xml">
point source</link>s — a term that includes vessels — are prohibited unless a permit has been obtained. Sewage from cruise ships and other vessels is exempt from the requirement to obtain an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/647655.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Point+sources%22])">
NPDES permit</link>. </p>
<p>

Section 312 of the Clean Water Act seeks to address this gap by prohibiting the dumping of untreated or inadequately treated sewage from vessels into the navigable waters of the United States (defined in the act as within 3&nbsp;miles (4.8&nbsp;km) of shore). Cruise ships are subject to this prohibition. Under Section 312, commercial and recreational vessels with installed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/19167644.xml">
toilet</link>s are required to have marine sanitation devices, which are designed to prevent the discharge of untreated sewage. Beyond 3&nbsp;miles (4.8&nbsp;km), raw sewage can be discharged.  On some cruise ships, especially many of those that travel in Alaskan waters, sewage is treated using Advanced Wastewater Treatment systems that generally provide improved screening, treatment, disinfection, and sludge processing as compared with traditional MSDs. AWTs are believed to be very effective in removing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/24358.xml">
pathogen</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/420598.xml">
oxygen-demanding</link> substances, suspended solids, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
oil</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/2439173.xml">
grease</link>, and particulate metals from sewage, but only moderately effective in removing dissolved metals and nutrients (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/1365.xml">
ammonia</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/21175.xml">
nitrogen</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/23318.xml">
phosphorus</link>).</p>
<p>

Section 312 has another means of addressing sewage discharges, through establishment of no-discharge zones (NDZs) for vessel sewage.
A state may completely prohibit the discharge of both treated and untreated sewage from all vessels with installed toilets into some or all waters over which it has jurisdiction (up to 3&nbsp;miles (4.8&nbsp;km) from land).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Graywater</st>
<p>

Under current federal law, graywater is not defined as a pollutant, nor is it generally considered to be sewage. The Clean Water Act only includes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/216193.xml">
graywater</link> in its definition of sewage for the express purpose of regulating commercial vessels in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/12010.xml">
Great Lakes</link>, under the Section 312 MSD requirements. Thus, currently graywater can be discharged by cruise ships anywhere — except in the Great Lakes. Pursuant to a state law in <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/624.xml">
Alaska</link></symbol>
, graywater must be treated prior to discharge into that state’s waters (see discussion below).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Solid waste</st>
<p>

Cruise ship discharges of solid waste are governed by two laws. Title I of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/5046565.xml">
Marine Protection, Research and Sanctuaries Act</link> makes it illegal to transport garbage from the United States for the purpose of dumping it into ocean waters without a permit or to dump material from outside the U.S. into U.S. waters. Beyond U.S. waters, no MPRSA permit is required for a cruise ship to discharge solid waste. The routine discharge of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/2248284.xml">
effluent</link> incidental to the propulsion of vessels is explicitly exempted from the definition of dumping in the MPRSA.28</p>
<p>

The <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../820/16219820.xml">
Act to Prevent Pollution from Ships</link></issue>
 prohibits the discharge of all garbage within 3&nbsp;nautical miles (5.6&nbsp;km) of shore, certain types of garbage within 12&nbsp;nautical miles (22&nbsp;km) offshore, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/23883.xml">
plastic</link> anywhere. It applies to all vessels operating in U.S. navigable waters and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/916345.xml">
Exclusive Economic Zone</link> (EEZ).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hazardous waste</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/626115.xml">
Resource Conservation and Recovery Act</link> is the primary federal law that governs <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/38031.xml">
hazardous waste</link> management. The owner or operator of a cruise ship may be a generator and/or a transporter of hazardous waste, and thus subject to RCRA rules. Issues that the cruise ship industry may face relating to RCRA include ensuring that hazardous waste is identified at the point at which it is considered generated; ensuring that parties are properly identified as generators, storers, treaters, or disposers; and  determining the applicability of RCRA requirements to each. Hazardous waste generated onboard cruise ships are stored onboard until the wastes can be offloaded for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/70157.xml">
recycling</link> or disposal in accordance with RCRA.29.</p>
<p>

A range of activities on board cruise ships generate hazardous wastes and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/51108.xml">
toxic substance</link>s that would ordinarily be presumed to be subject to RCRA. Cruise ships are potentially subject to RCRA requirements to the extent that chemicals used for operations such as ship maintenance and passenger services result in the generation of hazardous wastes. However, it is not entirely clear what regulations apply to the management and disposal of these wastes. 30 RCRA rules that cover small-quantity generators (those that generate more than 100 kilograms but less than 1,000 kilograms of hazardous waste per month) are less stringent than those for large-quantity generators (generating more than 1,000 kilograms per month), and it is unclear whether cruise ships are classified as large or small generators of hazardous waste. Moreover, some cruise companies argue that they generate less than 100 kilograms per month and therefore should be classified in a third category, as “conditionally exempt small-quantity generators,” a categorization that allows for less rigorous requirements for notification, recordkeeping, and the like.31</p>
<p>

A release of hazardous substances by a cruise ship or other vessel could also theoretically trigger the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/323737.xml">
Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act</link> (CERCLA, or Superfund, 42 U.S.C. 9601-9675), but it does not appear to have been used in response to cruise ship releases.</p>
<p>

In addition to RCRA, hazardous waste discharges from cruise ships are subject to Section 311 of the Clean Water Act, which prohibits the discharge of hazardous substances in harmful quantities into or upon the navigable waters of the United States, adjoining shorelines, or into or upon the waters of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/496983.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Contiguous+zone%22])">
contiguous zone</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Bilge water</st>
<p>

Bilge Water. Section 311 of the Clean Water Act, as amended by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/615194.xml">
Oil Pollution Act of 1990</link> (33 U.S.C. 2701-2720), applies to cruise ships and prohibits discharge of oil or hazardous substances in harmful quantities into or upon U.S. navigable waters, or into or upon the waters of the contiguous zone, or which may affect natural resources in the U.S. EEZ (extending 200&nbsp;miles (320&nbsp;km) offshore). Coast Guard regulations (33 CFR |151.10) prohibit discharge of oil within 12&nbsp;miles (19&nbsp;km) from shore, unless passed through a 15-<amount wordnetid="105107765" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<constant wordnetid="105858936" confidence="0.8">
<unit_of_measurement wordnetid="113583724" confidence="0.8">
<magnitude wordnetid="105090441" confidence="0.8">
<quantity wordnetid="105855125" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<number wordnetid="105121418" confidence="0.8">
<definite_quantity wordnetid="113576101" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/145865.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Parts-per+expressions%22])">
ppm</link></definite_quantity>
</number>
</property>
</quantity>
</magnitude>
</unit_of_measurement>
</constant>
</concept>
</idea>
</amount>
 oil water separator, and unless the discharge does not cause a visible sheen. Beyond 12&nbsp;miles (19&nbsp;km), oil or oily mixtures can be discharged while a vessel is proceeding en route and if the oil content without dilution is less than 100 ppm. Vessels are required to maintain an Oil Record Book to record disposal of oily residues and discharges overboard or disposal of bilge water. </p>
<p>

In addition to Section 311 requirements, the <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../820/16219820.xml">
Act to Prevent Pollution from Ships</link></issue>
 (APPS) implements <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/308347.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Annexes%22])">
MARPOL Annex I</link> concerning oil pollution. APPS applies to all U.S. flagged ships anywhere in the world and to all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/6162348.xml">
foreign flag</link>ged vessels operating in the navigable waters of the United States, or while at a port under U.S. jurisdiction. To implement APPS, the Coast Guard has promulgated regulations prohibiting the discharge of oil or oily mixtures into the sea within 12&nbsp;nautical miles (22&nbsp;km) of the nearest land, except under limited conditions. However, because most cruise lines are foreign registered and because APPS only applies to foreign ships within U.S. navigable waters, the APPS regulations have limited applicability to cruise ship operations. In addition, most cruise lines have adopted policies that restrict discharges of machinery space waste within three miles (5 km) from shore.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

This article is based on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link> <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/370772.xml">
Congressional Research Service</link></agency>
 report: Copeland, Claudia. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncseonline.org/NLE/CRSreports/07Dec/RL32450.pdf">
"Cruise Ship Pollution: Background, Laws and Regulations, and Key Issues"</weblink> (Order Code RL32450). <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/370772.xml">
Congressional Research Service</link></agency>
 (Updated February 6, 2008).</p>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Lloyd’s Maritime Information Services, on the website of the Maritime International Secretaries Services, Shipping and World Trade Facts, at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marisec.org/shippingfacts/keyfacts/">
http://www.marisec.org/shippingfacts/keyfacts/</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
International Council of Cruise Lines, “The Cruise Industry, 2005 Economic Summary.”</entry>
<entry id="3">
U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, “Cruise Ship White Paper,” August 22, 2000, p. 3.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Bell, Tom, “Experts: Mega-birth Needed for Cruise Ships,” Portland Press Herald, Sept. 28, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Bureau of Transportation Statistics, Department of Transportation, “Summary of Cruise Ship Waste Streams.”</entry>
<entry id="6">
U.S. General Accounting Office, Marine Pollution: Progress Made to Reduce Marine Pollution by Cruise Ships, but Important Issues Remain, GAO/RCED-00-48, February 2000. 70 pp. Hereafter, 2000 GAO Report.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Bluewater Network, Petition to the Administrator, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, March 17, 2000. The petition was amended in 2000 to request that EPA also examine <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/10934212.xml">
air pollution</link> from cruise ships; see discussion below.</entry>
<entry id="8">
U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Water, “Draft Cruise Ship Discharge Assessment Report,” EPA842-R-07-005, December 2007. See: U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, “Draft Cruise Ship Discharge Assessment Report, Notice of availability and request for public comments,” Federal Register, vol. 72, no. 244, Dec. 20, 2007, p. 72353.</entry>
<entry id="9">
2000 GAO Report, pp. 19-21.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/6204818.xml">
Marine Environmental Protection</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</issue>
</article>
