<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:39:24[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108058098">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>Classified Ventures</title>
<id>16231067</id>
<revision>
<id>244487853</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T01:23:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Paperissue</username>
<id>8052509</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Classified Ventures, LLC</b>, is a Delaware limited liability company, based in Chicago, owned by a strategic joint-venture of five large media companies -- <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/656391.xml">
Belo Corporation</link>, Gannett Company, Inc., <link>
The McClatchy Corporation</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/368391.xml">
Tribune Company</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/654863.xml">
The Washington Post Company</link></company>
.  To execute its business objectives, Classified Ventures has three leading online businesses verticals Apartments.com, <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/13830461.xml">
Cars.com</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 and Real Estate comprised of HomeScape and HomeGain.com. <p>

While assisting consumers with decisions related to selecting a home, apartment or automobile by providing comprehensive listings of products and information, Classified Ventures is also able to offer advertisers a cost-effective medium to generate a large audience of “in-purchase” consumers across these three categories.</p>

<p>

__TOC__ </p>


<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<p>

Classified Ventures was formed in 1997 by leading media companies each seeking to collectively capitalize on the revenue growth in the online classified advertising categories of automotive, apartments and real estate.  </p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Management Team</st>
<p>

<b>Daniel Jauernig, President and Chief Executive Officer of Classified Ventures</b></p>
<p>

As President and Chief Executive Officer of Classified Ventures, Inc., Daniel Jauernig oversees the strategic direction of the company, business development initiatives and the operations of the company’s three business verticals. He sits on the Classified Ventures' Board of Directors and its Executive Committee.  Jauernig joined Classified Ventures in April 2000 from the former Toronto-based Newcourt Credit Group, Inc. where he served as its Chief Financial Officer. As Chief Financial Officer, he participated and served as a director in several joint ventures including a joint venture between Dell Computers and Newcourt that created Dell Financial Services, a $2 billion lender that underwrites and funds all of Dell Computer's financed sales and Snap-on Credit, a $1 billion joint venture between Snap-on Corporation and Newcourt.</p>
<p>

Jauernig is currently a director of Home Equity Income Trust (TSX: HEQ.UN) a publicly listed income trust that operates Canadian Home Income Plan, a fast growing reverse mortgage lender in Canada.  Jauernig received a Bachelor of Mathematics Honors Degree from the University of Waterloo in Canada. He is also an accredited Canadian chartered accountant and certified management accountant and a United States certified public accountant. </p>

<p>

<b>Dick Burke, Senior Vice President Administration &amp; Corporate Development of Classified Ventures</b></p>
<p>

Dick Burke joined Classified Ventures as Interim General Counsel in May of 1998. In his role as Senior Vice President Administration and Corporate Development, Burke is responsible for the organization's finance, legal, human resources, facilities, enterprise technologies and technology operations functions. Burke is also responsible for Classified Ventures' affiliate network development and corporate development initiatives. Prior to joining Classified Ventures, Burke practiced law at Burke, Warren, MacKay &amp; Serritella, P.C. and at Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom. Burke received a Bachelor of Arts degree from College of the Holy Cross in 1986, and a Juris Doctor from Georgetown University Law Center in 1990.</p>

<p>

<b>Mitch Golub, Senior Vice President and President of Cars.com</b></p>
<p>

As Senior Vice President and General Manager of Cars.com, Mitch Golub is responsible for the strategic and operational direction of the business and Web site including marketing, sales and product development for the automotive segment. Golub has an extensive background in new media, new business start-ups and developing new products. He joined Classified Ventures after a 21-year career at Tribune Company where he served most recently as a Senior Executive in the company's New Media Group.  </p>
<p>

During his tenure at Tribune’s South Florida Sun-Sentinel, he created and managed new businesses in print, online and broadcast. In 1995, he became General Manager for interactive services for the Sun-Sentinel. He was responsible for putting the newspaper online and launching content-rich classified advertising-based products. Later, he developed Digital City South Florida, one of electronic publishing's first broad-based community products, which have become part of America Online's local service network. Golub has served on the Board of Directors of five new media businesses and organizations. He most recently served on the board of MarketDrive Interactive, an Internet company Classified Ventures recently acquired. </p>

<p>

<b>Tim Fagan, Senior Vice President and President, Classified Ventures Real Estate</b> </p>
<p>

Tim Fagan was promoted to President, Classified Ventures Real Estate Division in April 2006.  In his current role, Fagan oversees the strategic direction and operational oversight of Classified Venture's two leading real estate businesses HomeGain and Homescape.  </p>
<p>

Prior to this appointment, Fagan was Senior Vice President and General Manager of Apartments.com, a separate division of Classified Ventures, a role he maintained since January 2001.  Under Fagan’s leadership, the Apartments.com business saw its advertiser base double from 7,000 to over 14,000 and revenues grow by more than 500 percent.  </p>
<p>

Prior to joining Classified Ventures in 1998, Fagan spent five years in commercial lending at Bank of America.  Fagan holds a Bachelor's Degree in Accountancy from the University of Notre Dame and Master's Degree in Finance and Economics from the University of Chicago's Graduate School of Business. </p>

<p>

<b>Kevin Doyle, Senior Vice President &amp; General Manager of Apartments.com</b> </p>
<p>

As Senior Vice President and General Manager of Apartments.com, Kevin Doyle oversees all of the business operations of Apartments.com including sales, marketing, finance, product development, production, customer service and technology. A five year veteran of Classified Ventures, Doyle served as the Vice President of sales from 2001 to 2006.  During this time, Doyle cultivated and managed relationships with national property management companies, trained and directed the internal sales force and developed strategic partnerships with organizations and associations that benefit the multi-family industry, property managers and visitors to Apartments.com. </p>
<p>

As Vice President of Sales, Doyle was responsible for growing the Apartments.com customer base from 8,100 customers in 2001 to more than 14,000 in 2006. Additionally, Doyle was instrumental in the development of programs and resources to facilitate a 90 percent customer retention rate and building a top-notch sales team consisting of more than 100 customer-centric employees located throughout the United States. </p>
<p>

Prior to Apartments.com, Doyle spent 11 years in technology arena including positions with Headhunter.net, BrassRing, Terra-Starr and Chicago Tribune.  Previous accomplishments include creating the first-ever offline career fair for Yahoo Careers and Headhunter.net and contributing to the development of “Silicon Prairie,” a high-tech magazine for IT professionals. Doyle is also a two-time winner of the Campbell Award, a Chicago Tribune top sales honor.  Doyle earned a bachelor's degree in economics from Notre Dame University. </p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Products and Services</st>



<ss1>
<st>
Apartments.com ™</st>
<p>

<b>Apartments.com ™</b> offers renters one of the nation's most comprehensive and vivid online databases of more than three million apartment homes from managed communities, private landlords and newspaper classifieds. With access to real-time rent, streaming apartment walk-through videos, professional photography and floorplans, Apartments.com is able to provide a reliable resource for renters while delivering qualified leads to its advertisers. </p>
<p>

Additionally, Apartments.com reaches renters across the Web, creating easy access to its listings through strategic partnerships with newspapers and some of the nation’s most prominent Web sites. By partnering with more than 10,000 newspapers and strategic partner Web sites, Apartments.com creates new avenues for renters to access its listings while elevating advertiser exposure. Currently, Apartments.com is the exclusive provider of apartment listings to more than 150 newspapers around the country and has secured partnerships with some of the most popular online destinations including AOL Real Estate, MySpace, Univision.com and Yahoo! Real Estate.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Cars.com™</st>
<p>

<b>Cars.com™</b> is the link between consumers and dealers throughout the entire vehicle ownership experience. Cars.com establishes this relationship through the Cars.com Web site, by leveraging the sales and marketing strength of its network of 200 local newspapers and television stations, and through the development of dealer products. Cars.com is a destination for consumers, providing them with the tools, resources and most pertinent information available to make all automotive decisions including the ability to not only choose a car, but also choose a local dealer. </p>
<p>

By providing advertising and direct marketing solutions for dealers both online and off, Cars.com enables dealers to reach customers at all stages of the automotive decision process – from purchase to maintenance to resale. Cars.com also offers integrated solutions to automotive Original Equipment Manufacturer's (OEM’s), and advertising and e-commerce partners interested in accessing automotive consumers through Cars.com's media platform.  Offerings include advertising and sponsorship opportunities, lead management, and an eCRM platform currently utilized by BMW USA (www.bmwusa.com) and Subaru of America (www.subaru.com). </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Homescape.com ™</st>
<p>

<b>Homescape.com ™</b> creates a central location for home buyers and sellers to connect with real estate service providers and access listings throughout the Classified Ventures national network of more than 125 local newspapers. Homescape also provides private-label real estate web technology and data management solutions for its newspapers, supporting both new construction and resale real estate listing content and products.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
HomeGain.com™</st>
<p>
 
<b>HomeGain.com™</b> provides a suite of online marketing solutions to help real estate professionals grow their businesses. While providing real estate brokers and agents with online tools to conduct and manage online advertising, consumers benefit from being able to connect directly with real estate professionals.    </p>
<p>

HomeGain.com has recently settled a class action lawsuit which was filed against them by their very own employees for illegal compensation tactics &amp; various acts of thievery. They have been criticized by employees that were forced to work extraordinarily long hours, up to 100 hours per week without overtime. For several years HomeGain.com purposely avoided paying overtime and denied meal breaks to hundreds of employees resulting in this class action lawsuit. The plaintiffs filed this class action lawsuit because HomeGain.com/Classified Ventures misclassified inside salespersons and operations employees as exempt from overtime pay. The Plaintiffs also accused HomeGain.com of violating the California Labor Code by illegally requiring a release before paying overtime wages and by telling employees not to discuss the terms of the payments.</p>
<p>

HomeGain.com management goals have also been criticized for overcharging real estate agents, brokers, homebuyers, and homesellers for poor services and have settled various lawsuits with real estate professionals throughout the years. Specifically, HomeGain.com is accused of selling inaccurate data, poor leads and not paying rebates. HomeGain.com management is known to not cancelpaid subscriptions of services when requested.</p>
<p>

HomeGain.com is also criticized for its search engine marketing that involves purchasing unqualified leads from internet search engines and then reselling the leads to real estate professionals as "qualified". There have been a handful of complaints filed with the Better Business Bureau. Homegain also requires payment of 27% referral fee of agent/broker commissions from any deal that is closed from the service.</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Newspaper Affiliate Network</st>
<p>

The local newspaper has always been the first place people turn for classified advertising.  Classified Ventures, owned by five of the country’s leading newspaper publishers, was formed to combine the local strength and trusted reputations of leading newspapers across the country with nationally branded products and solutions. The result: the creation of (i) the premier sales channel for online classified advertising, (ii) a trusted environment to help individuals make better and more-informed purchasing decisions, and (iii) a motivated audience to increase the effectiveness of our advertisers. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Company Culture</st>
<p>

With more than 1,100 employees in 32 states, Classified Ventures creates a positive and collaborative working environment by practicing six core values of excellence, integrity, candor, empowerment, teamwork and passion.  Classified Ventures accomplishes this by utilizing the best business practices and living by the mantra of reinvesting back into the business—and employees.  In addition to growing a robust workforce, Classified Ventures is a profitable company, consistently increasing annual revenue by 25 percent or more. </p>
<p>

Classified Ventures also recognizes individual accomplishments across its diverse workforce and encourages professional development.  All employee promotions, accolades and new hires are celebrated through internal and external communications.  Employee education is inspired through the CV 60 sessions where employees can learn about new industry and financial trends, get up to speed on emerging technology and learn from industry experts.  Additionally, more than a dozen dedicated trainers throughout the organization provide development opportunities in areas such as management and leadership, presentation skills, sales, communication and teamwork.  </p>
<p>

Classified Ventures challenges its employees to reach for a healthy lifestyle and fosters camaraderie through sponsored sports programs such as marathons, soccer, softball, Frisbee and bowling.  Classified Ventures also encourages employees to connect with needy children and families, in the community, through partnerships with Habitat for Humanity, We Can Build an Orphanage and Chase Corporate Challenge and the annual adoption of a public grammar school through a Letters to Santa program.</p>
<p>

Classified Ventures employees, including most part-time workers, have access to a comprehensive set of benefits from best-in-call providers, ranging from a company-matching 401K to significantly subsidized medical, dental and vision insurance to no cost life insurance, dismemberment and disability coverage.  </p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.classifiedventures.com/">
Classified Ventures Web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.apartments.com/">
Apartments.com Web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cars.com/">
Cars.com Web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.homescape.com/">
Homescape Web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://homegainsucksass.blogspot.com/">
HomeGain Opinion Blog</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.homegain.com/">
HomeGain Web site</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</company>
</article>
