<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:46:32[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Crude oil washing</title>
<id>1624646</id>
<revision>
<id>236246588</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-04T14:51:02Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>GentlemanGhost</username>
<id>1432059</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Ocean pollution</category>
<category>Petroleum production</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Crude oil washing</b> (COW) is washing out the residue from the tanks of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/15923603.xml">
oil tanker</link> using the crude oil cargo itself, after the cargo tanks have been emptied. Crude Oil is pumped back and  preheated in the slop tanks, then sprayed back via high pressure nozzles in the cargo tanks on to the walls of the tank. Due to the sticky nature of the crude oil, the oil clings  to the tank walls, and such oil adds to the cargo 'remaining on board (the ROB). By COWing the tanks, the amount of ROB is significantly reduced, and with the current high cost of oil, the financial savings are significant, both for the Charterer and the Shipowner. If the cargo ROB is deemed as 'liquid and pumpable' then the Charterers can claim from the owner for any cargo loss  for normally between 0.3% up to 0.5%.  It replaced the <it>load on top</it> and <it>seawater washing</it> systems, both of which involved discharging oil-contaminated water into the sea. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/308347.xml">
MARPOL</link> 73/78 made this mandatory equipment for oil tankers of 20,000 tons or greater deadweight.<p>

__NOTOC__</p>

<sec>
<st>
Seawater washing</st>
<p>

Originally oil tankers used one set of tanks for cargo and about one third of the same tanks were for water <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/1686070.xml">
ballast</link> on their empty trips. High pressure, hot, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/255244.xml">
seawater</link> jets were used to clean the tanks and the mixture of seawater and residue called <it>slops</it> discharged into the sea, as was the oil-contaminated ballast water. The 1954 <link>
OILPOL Convention</link> attempted to reduce the harm by prohibiting such discharges within 50&nbsp;miles (80&nbsp;km) of most land and 100&nbsp;miles (160&nbsp;km) of certain particularly sensitive areas.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Load on top</st>
<p>

The discharges from seawater washing were still considered a problem and during the 1960s the load on top approach began to be adopted. The mixture of cleaning water and residue was pumped into a <it>slop tank</it> and allowed to separate into oil and water during the journey. The water portion was then discharged, leaving only crude oil in the slop tank. This was pumped into the main tanks and the new cargo loaded on top of it, recovering as much as 800 tons of oil which was formerly discarded.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Crude oil washing</st>
<p>

Even with load on top there is still some oil in the discharged water from the slop tank. Starting in the 1970s, equipment capable of using crude oil itself for washing began to replace the water-based washing, leading to the current technique of <it>crude oil washing</it>. This reduces the remaining deliberate discharge of oil-contaminated water and increases the amount of cargo discharged, providing a further benefit to the cargo owner.</p>
<p>

Crude oil washing equipment became mandatory for new tankers of 20,000 tons or more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/4709360.xml">
deadweight</link> with the 1978 Protocol to the 1973 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/308347.xml">
MARPOL</link> Convention. Revised specifications for the equipment were introduced in 1999.</p>
<p>

Modern tankers also use segregated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/3619680.xml">
ballast tanks</link> and these remove the problem of discharge of ballast water.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imo.org/Environment/mainframe.asp?topic_id=306">
International Maritime Organization description of Crude Oil Washing</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
