<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:36:31[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<software  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106566077">
<header>
<title>CrimeView</title>
<id>16280897</id>
<revision>
<id>244597226</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T17:02:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>LilHelpa</username>
<id>8024439</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>ArcGIS Extension</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Software</name>
<parameters>
<genre>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
GIS</link></genre>
<screenshot>
<image width="200px" src="Crimeview.jpg">
</image>
</screenshot>
<operating_system>
<version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/33941.xml">
Windows 2000</link></version>
, <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/33879.xml">
Windows XP</link></version>
</operating_system>
<caption>
Crime Analysis Extension to ArcGIS</caption>
<latest_release_version>
4.2</latest_release_version>
<developer>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/">
The Omega Group</weblink></developer>
<name>
CrimeView</name>
<latest_release_date>
2007</latest_release_date>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>CrimeView</b> is a crime analysis, mapping and reporting software extension to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/2783580.xml">
ArcGIS</link> that was first created by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com">
The Omega Group</weblink> in 1996. It allows for the detailed study of patterns of crime as they relate to geography and time.  In addition the services provided, CrimeView provides for a vast array of automation capabilities to improve a law enforcement agency's ability to serve pertinent information to decision-makers in a timely manner.  The first working CrimeView application was installed at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.indiopd.org/">
Indio Police Department</weblink> in California in August of 1996.  Since that time over two hundred and fifty agencies in forty different states have implemented CrimeView applications, making it one of the most popular crime mapping solutions in the world.  CrimeView was originally created in Avenue, ESRI's open source language.  The software has since undergone numerous transformations and is currently based in the <platform wordnetid="103961939" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<surface wordnetid="104362025" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<tool wordnetid="104451818" confidence="0.8">
<horizontal_surface wordnetid="103536348" confidence="0.8">
<implement wordnetid="103563967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/60402.xml">
.NET</link></implement>
</horizontal_surface>
</tool>
</instrumentality>
</surface>
</artifact>
</platform>
 environment.  Plans are under way to migrate the crime analysis utility to the ArcGIS Server environment in 2008.  This will enable high end analyses to be performed through any Web browser through the use of a server based application.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Background</st>
<p>

CrimeView connects to an agency's existing crime records or reporting system and automatically converts tabular data into locations on a map. This allows for timely analysis and reporting.  Many police departments use CrimeView as part of their <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/police/what-is-compstat.html">
CompStat</weblink> process and Watch Commanders utilize the software in order to help determine the placement of officers in the field. Additional resources can be placed where they are most needed to prevent or most efficiently react to crime. The Lincoln Police Department in Nebraska has been successful in apprehending several repeat offenders through the use of CrimeView's "Hot Spot", "Cyclical Reporting" and Threshold Alert routines.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Servers</st>

<p>

CrimeView can also be implemented through any law enforcement agency's Intranet as <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/police/police_web.html">
CrimeView Web</weblink> or be shared with the general public through the Internet as <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/police/police_community.html">
CrimeView Community</weblink>. These two server based versions of the software are compatible with most standard Web browsers and have been effective with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/1510277.xml">
Community Oriented Policing</link> efforts throughout the United States.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Functions</st>

<p>

Some of the different CrimeView functions include:</p>
<p>

<it>Queries</it> - by any attribute, geographic boundary, or proximity to an address or landmark feature. </p>
<p>

<it>Density Maps</it> - standardized density, hot spot maps, repeat calls. </p>
<p>

<it>Cyclical Reports</it> - combines and saves queries, reports, and graphs to run anytime. </p>
<p>

<it>Exception Reporting</it> – create <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/police/what-is-compstat.html">
COMPSTAT</weblink> style comparison reports. </p>
<p>

<it>Threshold Alert</it> – e-mail alerts (including maps and reports) when activity thresholds have been reached. </p>
<p>

<it>Analyses</it> - crime rate generator, spatial trends. </p>
<p>

<it>Order Labels</it> - plots specific incidents in the order they occur with directionals. </p>
<p>

<it>Statistical Profiler</it> - profiles a data series to help determine where and when the next event is most likely to occur.</p>

</ss2>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Discussion</st>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/">
The Omega Group</weblink> has built hundreds of CrimeView applications for agencies throughout the US and Canada.  San Juan Police Department in Puerto Rico recently implemented CrimeView Desktop.  The San Juan application was launched in 2007 and represents the first CrimeView database implemented in a Spanish speaking region.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gmtgis.com/">
Geographic Mapping Technologies</weblink> was integral in bringing CrimeView to San Juan.  </p>

<p>

CrimeView's Threshold Alert function is currently being used by Lincoln Police Department as a daily reporting mechanism.  The Threshold Alert routine allows the end user to set a threshold for any type of crime by any geography.  If the threshold is exceeded during a specified time period an e-mail alert is sent out to designated recipients.  By setting the threshold to one (1) Lincoln Police Department has been able to create daily reports that are utilized by command staff in the decision making process.</p>

<p>

The Virginia Beach Police Department was able to apprehend a serial rapist in 2006 through the use of CrimeView's hot spot and reporting functions.  Hot spots maps were created showing where and when the most incidents were occurring.  The department placed additional officers at these locations during peak activity times and were able to catch a sexual predator just before he struck again.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>San Diego Union Tribune</it> –  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/articles/cv_sd_union_tribune_1998.htm">
Crime busters get a break in their investigations</weblink>, published August 1998.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>ESRI ArcNews</it> –  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/articles/cv_arcnews_1998.pdf">
Redlands, California, Police Use CrimeView to Predict Trouble Spots</weblink>, published Winter 1998.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>International Association of Crime Analysts</it> –  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iaca.net/Software.asp">
CrimeView CrimeView suite of desktop and Web based applications</weblink>, IACA Web site 2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Utah County Daily Herald</it> –  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theomegagroup.com/articles/cv_utah_county_daily_herald_2002.htm">
Law Enforcement Officials Improving Crime Data Analysis</weblink>, published June 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>National Institute of Justice</it> – San Francisco CrimeMAPS (based on CrimeView) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/nij/maps/links.htm">
CrimeView Community</weblink>, NIJ Web site 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Government Matters 2003</it> – Regional Analysis <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.esri.com/library/reprints/pdfs/govmatters-crimeview.pdf">
CrimeView and Citrix</weblink>, ESRI Press 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Police Chief Magazine</it> – San Francisco Launches <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://policechiefmagazine.org/magazine/index.cfm?fuseaction=display_arch&amp;article_id=296&amp;issue_id=52004">
Crime Mapping System</weblink>, Police Chief Magazine May 2004 Issue.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>City of Lafayette's CrimeView Community Application</it> – City Manager's Blog on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gis.lafayettela.gov/crimeviewcommunity/">
CrimeView Community</weblink>, City of Lafayette, Louisiana 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>West Des Moines City Manager's Blog 2006</it> – City Manager's Blog on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wdmblog.wdm-ia.com/2006/12/crimeview.html">
CrimeView</weblink>, City of West Des Moines, Iowa 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Officer.com</it> – <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.officer.com/web/online/Industry-Business-Wire/CrimeView-Helps-Hartford-Police-Implement-Change-in-Laws/9$33959">
CrimeView Helps Hartford Police Implement Change in Laws</weblink>, posted to Officer.com in December of 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>LaserFiche User News– <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.laserfiche.com/newsroom/usernews/2007/07_07.html">
IT Innovation Helps Claremont Fight Crime</weblink>, LaserFiche Web site, July 2007.</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>IN.GOV</it> – <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.in.gov/library/3118.htm">
CrimeView Community Law Enforcement Map</weblink>, posted to Indiana Government Web site, October 2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Chief Tom Cassady's Blog</it> – Lincoln Police Utilize <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lpd304.blogspot.com/">
CrimeView</weblink>, The Blog Spot 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>CBS News</it> – <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cbs4.com/local/crimeview.crime.rates.2.627391.html">
Neighborhood Crime Rates With the Click of a Mouse</weblink>, CBS News 4, Hollywood, Florida, January 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>GIS Cafe 2008</it> – Gulport Police Launch <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www10.giscafe.com/nbc/articles/view_article.php?section=CorpNews&amp;articleid=504044">
CrimeView</weblink>, Cafe Press 2008.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</software>
</article>
