<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:37:12[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Computational creativity</title>
<id>16300571</id>
<revision>
<id>244674427</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-12T00:05:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ripe</username>
<id>835671</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Artificial intelligence</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Computational creativity</b> (also known as <b>artificial creativity</b>, <b>mechanical creativity</b> or <b>creative computation</b>) is a multidisciplinary endeavour that is located at the intersection of the fields of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/5961.xml">
cognitive psychology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/13692155.xml">
philosophy</link>, and the arts.<p>

The goal of computational creativity is to model, simulate or replicate creativity using a computer, to achieve one of several ends:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	to construct a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/5783.xml">
program</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link> capable of human-level <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/142910.xml">
creativity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	to better understand human creativity and to formulate an algorithmic perspective on creative behavior in humans</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	to design programs that can enhance human creativity without necessarily being creative themselves</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The field of computational creativity concerns itself with theoretical and practical issues in the study of creativity. Theoretical work on the nature and proper definition of creativity is performed in parallel with practical work on the implementation of systems that exhibit creativity, with one strand of work informing the other.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Theoretical issues</st>
<p>

As measured by the amount of activity in the field (e.g., publications, conferences and workshops), computational creativity is a growing area of research. But the field is still hampered by a number of fundamental problems:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Creativity is very difficult, perhaps even impossible, to define in objective terms.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Creativity takes many forms in human activity, some <it>eminent</it> (meaning "recognized" or "ingenious", e.g., <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/736.xml">
Einstein</link></scientist>
</person>
's creativity; sometimes referred to as "Creativity" with a capital C) and some <it>mundane</it>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Creativity can mean different things in different contexts: Is it a state of mind, a talent or ability, or a process? Does it describe a person, an activity or an end-product? Can collaborative work in which exceptional products emerge from simple interactions be considered creative?</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

These are problems that complicate the study of creativity in general, but certain problems attach themselves specifically to <it>computational</it> creativity:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Can creativity be hard-wired? In existing systems to which creativity is attributed, is the creativity that of the system or that of the system's programmer or designer?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

How do we evaluate computational creativity? What counts as creativity in a computational system? Are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/21652.xml">
natural language</link> generation systems creative? Are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/19980.xml">
machine translation</link> systems creative? What distinguishes research in computational creativity from research in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link> generally?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

If eminent creativity is about rule-breaking or the disavowal of convention, how is it possible for an algorithmic system to be creative? In essence, this is a variant of the <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/974.xml">
Ada Lovelace</link></scientist>
 objection to machine intelligence, as recapitulated by modern theorists such as Teresa Amabile:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> If a machine can do only what it was programmed to do, how can its behavior ever be called <it>creative</it>?</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Defining creativity in computational terms</st>
<p>

Since no single perspective or definition seems to offer a complete picture of creativity, the AI researchers Newell, Shaw and Simon <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>developed the combination of novelty and usefulness into the corner-stone of a multi-pronged view of creativity, one that uses the following four criteria to categorize a given answer or solution as creative:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The answer is novel and useful (either for the individual or for society)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The answer demands that we reject ideas we had previously accepted</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The answer results from intense motivation and persistence</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The answer comes from clarifying a problem that was originally vague</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Notice how these criteria touch on many of the stereotypical themes that are typically associated with creativity: newness and value (1), transformation and revolution (2), passion and drive (3), vision and insight (4). These four criteria also combine elements of the producer-perspective and the product-perspective described earlier: criterion (1) characterizes the two most important qualities of a creative product, while criteria (2) – (4) characterize the attitude and actions of the producer of such a product. A given product may satisfy all or none of these criteria, but we should expect products that exhibit all four to be widely perceived as creative, while products that exhibit just some of these criteria will be judged with greater subjectivity and variation. Though no criterion is likely to be either necessary or sufficient, criterion (1) is perhaps the most common hallmark of creativity and thus serves to anchor the others. From a computational perspective, then, one can consider (1) to be a <it>must-have</it> feature, and (2) – (4) as desirable extras.</p>
<p>

Newell and Simon<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> are best known for their contribution to the search-in-a-state-space paradigm of AI, sometimes caricatured as Good Old Fashioned AI (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/339417.xml">
GOFAI</link>), and it is interesting to consider how the GOFAI paradigm can incorporate these criteria. From a search perspective, criterion (1) characterizes the goal or end-state of a computational search, criterion (4) characterizes the starting state from which the search is launched, criterion (3) characterizes the scale of the search, suggesting that many dead-ends are likely to be encountered, while criterion (2) suggests that well-worn pathways through the search space are best avoided if a creative end-state is to be reached.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Key ideas</st>
<p>

Some high-level and philosophical themes recur throughout the field of computational creativity.&#91;&#93;</p>

<ss1>
<st>
P-creativity and H-creativity</st>
<p>

Margaret Boden<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  refers to creativity that is novel <it>merely to the agent that produces it</it> as "P-creativity" (or "psychological creativity"), and refers to creativity that is recognized as novel <it>by society at large</it> as "H-creativity" (or "historical creativity").</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Exploratory and transformational creativity</st>
<p>

Boden also distinguishes between the creativity that arises from an exploration within an established conceptual space, and the creativity that arises from a deliberate transformation or transcendence of this space. She labels the former as "exploratory creativity" and the latter as "transformational creativity", seeing the latter as a form of creativity far more radical, challenging, and rare than the former. Following Newell and Simon’s criteria, we can see that both forms of creativity should produce results that are appreciably novel and useful (criterion 1), but exploratory creativity is more likely to arise from a thorough and persistent search of a well-understood space (criterion 3) while transformational creativity should involve the rejection of some of the constraints that define this space (criterion 2) or some of the assumptions that define the problem itself (criterion 4).</p>
<p>

Boden’s insights have guided work in computational creativity at a very general level, providing more an inspirational touchstone for development work than a technical framework of algorithmic substance. However, Boden’s insights are the subject of formalization, most notably in the work by Geraint Wiggins<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Generation and evaluation</st>
<p>

The criterion that creative products should be novel and useful means that creative computational systems are typically structured into two phases, generation and evaluation. In the first phase, novel (to the system itself, thus P-Creative)  constructs are generated; unoriginal constructs that are already known to the system are filtered at this stage. This body of potentially creative constructs are then evaluated, to determine which are meaningful and useful and which are not. This two-phase structure conforms to the <link>
Geneplore</link> model of Finke, Ward and Smith<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>, which is a psychological model of creative generation based on empirical observation of human creativity.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Combinatorial creativity</st>
<p>

A great deal, perhaps all, of human creativity can be understood as a novel combination of pre-existing ideas or objects. Common strategies for combinatorial creativity include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

placing a familiar object in an unfamiliar setting (e.g., <artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/42650.xml">
Marcel Duchamp</link></artist>
's <it><product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/2098151.xml">
Fountain</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</it>) or an unfamiliar object in a familiar setting (e.g., a fish-out-of-water story such as <it><series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/3376.xml">
The Beverly Hillbillies</link></series>
</it>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Blending two superficially different objects or genres (e.g., a sci-fi story set in the Wild West, with robot cowboys, as in <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/464189.xml">
Westworld</link></movie>
</it>; Jewish <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../217/13217.xml">
haiku</link> poems, etc.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Comparing a familiar object to a superficially unrelated and semantically distant concept (e.g., "Makeup is the Western <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/1968856.xml">
burka</link>"; "A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/9096372.xml">
zoo</link> is a gallery with living exhibits")</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Adding a new and unexpected feature to an existing concept (e.g., adding a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/263748.xml">
scalpel</link> to a <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/313833.xml">
Swiss Army knife</link></characteristic>
</hallmark>
</invention>
; adding a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/667163.xml">
camera</link> to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/19644137.xml">
mobile phone</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Compressing two incongruous scenarios into the same narrative to get a joke (e.g., the <comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/487070.xml">
Emo Philips</link></person>
</comedian>
 joke “Women are always using me to advance their careers. Damned anthropologists!”)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Using an iconic image from one domain in a domain for an unrelated or incongruous idea or product (e.g., using the <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<cowboy wordnetid="109972661" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<laborer wordnetid="110241300" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<workman wordnetid="110791221" confidence="0.8">
<employee wordnetid="110053808" confidence="0.8">
<hired_hand wordnetid="110176679" confidence="0.8">
<ranch_hand wordnetid="110506544" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/1017033.xml">
Marlboro Man</link></ranch_hand>
</hired_hand>
</employee>
</workman>
</causal_agent>
</laborer>
</worker>
</cowboy>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 image to sell cars, or to advertise the dangers of smoking-related impotence).</entry>
</list>

The combinatorial perspective allows us to model creativity as a search process through the space of possible combinations. The combinations can arise from composition or concatenation of different representations, or through a rule-based or stochastic transformation of initial and intermediate representations. <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
Genetic algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/1729542.xml">
neural network</link>s can be used to generate blended or crossover representations that capture a combination of different inputs.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Bisociation</st>
<p>

<skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<disbeliever wordnetid="110015897" confidence="0.8">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<communist wordnetid="109945319" confidence="0.8">
<socialist wordnetid="110618848" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<novelist wordnetid="110363573" confidence="0.8">
<commanding_officer wordnetid="109941964" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<politician wordnetid="110450303" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<atheist wordnetid="109820044" confidence="0.8">
<nonreligious_person wordnetid="109625789" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<essayist wordnetid="110064405" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/18950939.xml">
Arthur Koestler</link></essayist>
</research_worker>
</scholar>
</nonreligious_person>
</atheist>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</leader>
</communicator>
</politician>
</military_officer>
</commanding_officer>
</novelist>
</scientist>
</serviceman>
</intellectual>
</socialist>
</communist>
</person>
</philosopher>
</disbeliever>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
 proposes a very general model of creative combination in his 1964 book <it>The Act of Creation,</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> claiming that scientific discovery, art and humour are all linked by a common mechanism called "<link>
bisociation</link>". Koestler lacked a formal, computational vocabulary for describing bisociation, which he defined as a reconciliation of two orthogonal matrices of thought (conceptual structures, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../341/1886341.xml">
mental space</link>s).</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Conceptual blending</st>
<p>

Mark Turner and Gilles Fauconnier  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> propose a model called Conceptual Integration Networks that elaborates upon the ideas of Koestler by synthesizing ideas from Cognitive Linguistic research into <link>
mental spaces</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/72710.xml">
conceptual metaphors</link>. Their basic model defines an integration network as four connected spaces:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A first input space (contains one conceptual structure or mental space)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A second input space (to be blended with the first input)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A <it>generic space</it> of stock conventions and image-schemas that allow the input spaces to be understood from an integrated perspective</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A <it>blend space</it> in which a selected projection of elements from both input spaces are combined; inferences arising from this combination also reside here, sometimes leading to emergent structures that conflict with the inputs.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Fauconnier and Turner describe a collection of optimality principles that are claimed to guide the construction of a well-formed integration network. In essence, they see blending as a compression mechanism in which two or more input structures are compressed into a single blend structure. This compression operates on the level of conceptual relations.  For example, a series of similarity relations between the input spaces can be compressed into a single identity relationship in the blend.</p>
<p>

Blending theory is an elaborate framework that provides a rich terminology for describing the products of creative thinking, from metaphors to jokes to neologisms to adverts. It is most typically applied retrospectively, to describe how a blended conceptual structure could have arisen from a particular pair of input structures. These conceptual structures are often good examples of human creativity, but blending theory is not a theory of creativity, nor – despite its authors’ claims – does it describe a mechanism for creativity. The theory lacks an explanation for how a creative individual chooses the input spaces that should be blended to generate a desired result.</p>
<p>

Nonetheless, some computational success has been achieved with the blending model by extending pre-existing computational models of analogical mapping that are compatible by virtue of their emphasis on connected semantic structures<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>. More recently, Francisco Câmara Pereira<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> presented an implementation of blending theory that employs ideas both from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/339417.xml">
GOFAI</link> and from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
genetic algorithms</link> to realize some aspects of blending theory in a practical form; his example domains range from the linguistic to the visual, and the latter most notably includes the creation of mythical monsters by combining 3-D graphical models.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Linguistic creativity</st>
<p>

Language provides continuous opportunity for creativity, evident in the generation of novel sentences, phrasings, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/24145.xml">
pun</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/153907.xml">
neologism</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/26226.xml">
rhyme</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/297267.xml">
allusion</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/19593964.xml">
sarcasm</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/44429.xml">
irony</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/28860.xml">
simile</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/20518.xml">
metaphor</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/103533.xml">
analogies</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/380286.xml">
witticism</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/16267.xml">
joke</link>s. The area of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/21652.xml">
natural language</link> generation has been well studied, but these creative aspects of everyday language have yet to be incorporated with any robustness or scale.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Story generation</st>
<p>

Substantial work has been conducted in this area of linguistic creation since the 1970s, with the development of James Meehan's <link>
TALE-SPIN</link>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> system. TALE-SPIN viewed stories as narrative descriptions of a problem-solving effort, and created stories by first establishing a goal for the story’s characters so that their search for a solution could be tracked and recorded. The MINSTREL<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> system represents a complex elaboration of this basis approach, distinguishing a range of character-level goals in the story from a range of author-level goals for the story. Systems like Bringsjord's BRUTUS<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> elaborate these ideas further to create stories with complex inter-personal themes like betrayal. Nonetheless, MINSTREL explicitly models the creative process with a set of Transform Recall Adapt Methods (TRAMs) to create novel scenes from old. The MEXICA<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> model of Rafael Pérez y Pérez and Mike Sharples is more explicitly interested in the creative process of storytelling, and implements a version of the engagement-reflection cognitive model of creative writing.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Metaphor and simile</st>
<p>

The computational study of these phenomena has mainly focussed on interpretation as a knowledge-based process. Computationalists such as Yorick Wilks, James Martin,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> Dan Fass, John Barnden,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> and Mark Lee have developed knowledge-based approaches to the processing of metaphors, either at a linguistic level or a logical level. Tony Veale and Yanfen Hao have developed a system, called Sardonicus, that acquires a comprehensive database of explicit similes from the web; these similes are then tagged as bona-fide (e.g., "as hard as steel") or ironic (e.g., "as hairy as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/1611355.xml">
bowling ball</link>", "as pleasant as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/11848762.xml">
root canal</link>"); similes of either type can be retrieved on demand for any given adjective. They use these similes as the basis of an on-line metaphor generation system called Aristotle<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> that can suggest lexical metaphors for a given descriptive goal (e.g., to describe a supermodel as skinny, the source terms “pencil”, “whip”, “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/33956.xml">
whippet</link>”, “rope”, “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/341989.xml">
stick-insect</link>” and “snake” are suggested).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Analogy</st>
<p>

The process of analogical reasoning has been studied from both a mapping and a retrieval perspective, the latter being key to the generation of novel analogies. The dominant school of research, as advanced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/1940260.xml">
Dedre Gentner</link>. views analogy as a structure-preserving process; this view has been implemented in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/4678739.xml">
Structure Mapping Engine</link> or SME<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>, the MAC/FAC retrieval engine (Many Are Called, Few Are Chosen), ACME (<link>
Analogical Constraint Mapping Engine</link>) and ARCS (<link>
Analogical Retrieval Constraint System</link>). Other mapping-based approaches include Sapper<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref>, which situates the mapping process in a semantic-network model of memory. Analogy is a very active sub-area of creative computation and creative cognition; active figures in this sub-area include <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<professor wordnetid="110480730" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/8758.xml">
Douglas Hofstadter</link></writer>
</professor>
</person>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/3820043.xml">
Paul Thagard</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/5644962.xml">
Keith Holyoak</link>. Also worthy of note here is Peter Turney and Michael Littman's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link> approach to the solving of <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/144716.xml">
SAT</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
-style analogy problems; their approach achieves a score that compares well with average scores achieved by humans on these tests.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Joke generation</st>
<p>

Humour is an especially knowledge-hungry process, and the most successful joke-generation systems to date have focussed on pun-generation, as exemplified by the work of Kim Binsted and Graeme Ritchie.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> This work includes the JAPE system, which can generate a wide range of puns that are consistently evaluated as novel and humorous by young children. An improved version of JAPE has been developed in the guise of the STANDUP system, which has been experimentally deployed as a means of enhancing linguistic interaction with children with communication disabilities. Some limited progress has been made in generating humour that involves other aspects of natural language, such as the deliberate misunderstanding of pronominal reference (in the work of Hans Wim Tinholt and Anton Nijholt), as well as in the generation of humorous acronyms in the HAHAcronym system<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> of Oliviero Stock and Carlo Strapparava.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Neologisms</st>
<p>
 
The blending of multiple word forms is a dominant force for new word creation in language; these new words are commonly called "blends" or "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/16823212.xml">
portmanteau word</link>s" (after <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<clergyman wordnetid="109927451" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/5340.xml">
Lewis Carroll</link></writer>
</clergyman>
</person>
). Tony Veale has developed a system called ZeitGeist<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref> that harvests neological <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/1366018.xml">
headword</link>s from <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/5043734.xml">
Wikipedia</link></web_site>
 and interprets them relative to their local context in Wikipedia and relative to specific word senses in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/33955.xml">
WordNet</link>. ZeitGeist has been extended to generate neologisms of its own; the approach combines elements from an inventory of word parts that are harvested from WordNet, and simultaneously determines likely glosses for these new words (e.g., "food traveller" for "gastronaut" and "time traveller" for "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/66305.xml">
chrononaut</link>"). It then uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
Web search</link> to determine which glosses are meaningful and which neologisms have not been used before; this search identifies the subset of generated words that are both novel ("H-creative") and useful.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Poetry</st>
<p>
 
Like jokes, poems involve a complex interaction of different constraints, and no general-purpose poem generator adequately combines the meaning, phrasing, structure and rhyme aspects of poetry. Nonetheless, Pablo Gervás<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref> has developed a noteworthy system called ASPERA that employs a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/170333.xml">
case-based reasoning</link> (CBR) approach to generating poetic formulations of a given input text via a composition of poetic fragments that are retrieved from a case-base of existing poems. Each poem fragment in the ASPERA case-base is annotated with a prose string that expresses the meaning of the fragment, and this prose string is used as the retrieval key for each fragment. <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/19930.xml">
Metrical</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 rules are then used to combine these fragments into a well-formed poetic structure.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Musical creativity</st>
<p>

Computational creativity in the music domain has focussed both on the generation of musical scores for use by human musicians, and on the generation of music for performance by computers. The domain of generation has included classical music (with software that generates music in the style of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/33163.xml">
Mozart</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/9906294.xml">
Bach</link>) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/15613.xml">
jazz</link>. Most notably, David Cope<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> has written a software system called "Experiments in Musical Intelligence" (or "EMI") that is capable of analyzing and generalizing from existing music by a human composer to generate novel musical compositions in the same style. EMI's output is convincing enough to persuade human listeners that its music is human-generated to a high level of competence.</p>
<p>

Creativity research in jazz has focussed on the process of improvisation and the cognitive demands that this places on a musical agent: reasoning about time, remembering and conceptualizing what has already been played, and planning ahead for what might be played next.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Visual and artistic creativity</st>
<p>

Computational creativity in the generation of visual art has had some notable successes in the creation of both abstract art and representational art. The most famous program in this domain is <link>
Harold Cohen</link>'s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/1887170.xml">
AARON</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> which has been continuously developed and augmented since 1973. Though formulaic, Aaron exhibits a range of outputs, generating black-and-white drawings or colour paintings that incorporate human figures (such as dancers), potted plants, rocks, and other elements of background imagery. These images are of a sufficiently high quality to be displayed in reputable galleries.</p>
<p>

Other software artists of note include the NEvAr system (for "Neuro-Evolutionary Art") of Penousal Machado.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> NEvAr uses a genetic algorithm to derive a mathematical function that is then used to generate a coloured three-dimensional surface. A human user is allowed to select the best pictures after each phase of the genetic algorithm, and these preferences are used to guide successive phases, thereby pushing NEvAr’s search into pockets of the search space that are considered most appealing to the user.</p>
<p>

The Painting Fool is an ambitious system developed by Simon Colton that originated as a system for overpainting digital images of a given scene in a choice of different painting styles, colour palettes and brush types. Given its dependence on an input source image to work with, the earliest iterations of the Painting Fool raised as questions about the extent of, or lack of, creativity in a computational art system. Nonetheless, in more recent work, The Painting Fool has been extended to create novel images, much as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/1887170.xml">
AARON</link> does, from its own limited <it>imagination</it>. Images in this vein include cityscapes and forests, which are generated by a process of constraint satisfaction from some basic scenarios provided by the user (e.g., these scenarios allow the system to infer that objects closer to the viewing plane should be larger and more color-saturated, while those further away should be less saturated and appear smaller). Artistically, the images now created by the Painting Fool appear on a par with those created by Aaron, though the extensible mechanisms employed by the former (constraint satisfaction, etc.) may well allow it to develop into a more elaborate and  sophisticated painter.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Events</st>
<p>

The community of computational creativity has held a dedicated workshop, the International Joint Workshop on Computational Creativity, every year since 1999. Usually held as part of a larger conference event, this workshop series is now autonomous; the most recent stand-alone event was held in September 2008 at the Facultad de Informática, Universidad Complutense de Madrid,  Spain. Previous events in this series include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

IJWCC 2003, Acapulco, Mexico,  as part of IJCAI'2003</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

IJWCC 2004, Madrid, Spain, as part of ECCBR'2004</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

IJWCC 2005, Edinburgh, UK,  as part of IJCAI'2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

IJWCC 2006, Riva del Garda, Italy, as part of ECAI'2006</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

IJWCC 2007, London, UK, a stand-alone event</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The steering committee for these events comprises the following researchers:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Amilcar Cardoso (University of Coimbra, Portugal)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Simon Colton (Imperial College London, UK)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pablo Gervás (Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Francisco C Pereira (University of Coimbra, Portugal)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tony Veale (University College Dublin, Ireland)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Geraint A. Wiggins (Goldsmiths, University of London, UK)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Publication forums</st>
<p>

In addition to the proceedings of these workshops, the computational creativity community has thus far produced two special journal issues dedicated to the topic:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Journal of Knowledge-Based Systems</it>, volume 9, issue 7, November 2006</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>New Generation Computing</it>, volume 24, issue 6, 2006</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite id="CITEREFAmabile1983" style="font-style:normal">Amabile, Teresa&#32;(1983),&#32;<it>The social psychology of creativity</it>, New York, NY: Springer-Verlag</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite id="CITEREFNewell.2C_Allen1963" style="font-style:normal">Newell, Allen, Shaw, J. G., and Simon, Herbert A.&#32;(1963),&#32;<it>The process of creative thinking</it>, H. E. Gruber, G. Terrell and M. Wertheimer (Eds.), Contemporary Approaches to Creative Thinking, pp 63 – 119. New York: Atherton</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite id="CITEREFNewell.2C_Allen1972" style="font-style:normal">Newell, Allen, Simon, Herbert A.&#32;(1972),&#32;<it>Human Problem Solving</it>, Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite id="CITEREFNewell.2C_Allen1963" style="font-style:normal">Newell, Allen, Simon, Herbert A.&#32;(1963),&#32;<it>GPS, A Program that Simulates Human Though</it>, E. A. Feigenbaum and J. Feldman (eds.), R. Oldenbourg KG</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite id="CITEREFBoden1990" style="font-style:normal">Boden, Margaret&#32;(1990),&#32;<it>The Creative Mind: Myths and Mechanisms</it>, London: Weidenfeld and Nicholson</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite id="CITEREFBoden1999" style="font-style:normal">Boden, Margaret&#32;(1999),&#32;<it>Computational models of creativity.</it>, Handbook of Creativity, pp 351&ndash;373</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite id="CITEREFWiggins2006" style="font-style:normal">Wiggins, Geraint&#32;(2006),&#32;<it>A Preliminary Framework for Description, Analysis and Comparison of Creative Systems</it>, Journal of Knowledge Based Systems 19(7), pp. 449-458</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite id="CITEREFFinke.2C_R.1992" style="font-style:normal">Finke, R., Ward, T., and Smith, S.&#32;(1992),&#32;<it>Creative cognition: Theory, research and applications</it>, Cambridge: MIT press.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite id="CITEREFKoestler1964" style="font-style:normal">Koestler, Arthur&#32;(1964),&#32;<it>The Act of Creation</it>, Macmillan</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite id="CITEREFFauconnier.2C_Gilles2007" style="font-style:normal">Fauconnier, Gilles, Turner, Mark&#32;(2007),&#32;<it>The Way We Think</it>, Basic Books</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite id="CITEREFFauconnier.2C_Gilles2007" style="font-style:normal">Fauconnier, Gilles, Turner, Mark&#32;(2007),&#32;<it>Conceptual Integration Networks</it>, Cognitive Science, 22(2) pp 133–187</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite id="CITEREFVeale.2C_Tony2007" style="font-style:normal">Veale, Tony, O’Donoghue, Diarmuid&#32;(2007),&#32;<it>Computation and Blending</it>, Cognitive Linguistics, 11(3-4), special issue on Conceptual Blending</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
 <cite id="CITEREFPereira2006" style="font-style:normal">Pereira, Francisco Câmara&#32;(2006),&#32;<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eden.dei.uc.pt/~camara/AICreativity">
Creativity and Artificial Intelligence: A Conceptual Blending Approach</weblink></it>, Applications of Cognitive Linguistics. Amsterdam: Mouton de Gruyter, </cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
 <cite id="CITEREFMeehan1981" style="font-style:normal">Meehan, James&#32;(1981),&#32;<it>TALE-SPIN</it>, Shank, R. C. and Riesbeck, C. K., (eds.), Inside Computer Understanding: Five Programs plus Miniatures. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
 <cite id="CITEREFTurner1994" style="font-style:normal">Turner, S.R.&#32;(1994),&#32;<it>The Creative Process: A Computer Model of Storytelling</it>, Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
 <cite id="CITEREFP.C3.A9rez_y_P.C3.A9rez.2C_Rafael2001" style="font-style:normal">Pérez y Pérez, Rafael, Sharples, Mike&#32;(2001),&#32;<it>MEXICA: A computer model of a cognitive account of creative writing</it>, Journal of Experimental and Theoretical Artificial Intelligence, 13, pp 119-139</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
 <cite id="CITEREFBringsjord.2C_S.2000" style="font-style:normal">Bringsjord, S., Ferrucci, D. A.&#32;(2000),&#32;<it>Artificial Intelligence and Literary Creativity. Inside the Mind of BRUTUS, a Storytelling Machine.</it>, Hillsdale NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="19">
 <cite id="CITEREFBarnden1992" style="font-style:normal">Barnden, John&#32;(1992),&#32;<it>Belief in Metaphor: Taking Commonsense Psychology Seriously</it>, Computational Intelligence 8, pp 520-552</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
 <cite id="CITEREFMartin1990" style="font-style:normal">Martin, James&#32;(1990),&#32;<it>A Computational Model of Metaphor Interpretation</it>, Academic Press</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="21">
 <cite id="CITEREFFalkenhainer.2C_Brian1989" style="font-style:normal">Falkenhainer, Brian, Forbus, Ken and Gentner, Dedre&#32;(1989),&#32;<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.qrg.northwestern.edu/papers/Files/smeff2(searchable).pdf">
The structure-mapping engine: Algorithm and examples</weblink></it>, Artificial Intelligence, 20(41) pp 1–63, </cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
 <cite id="CITEREFVeale.2C_Tony2007" style="font-style:normal">Veale, Tony, Hao, Yanfen&#32;(2007),&#32;<it>Comprehending and Generating Apt Metaphors: A Web-driven, Case-based Approach to Figurative Language</it>, Proceedings of AAAI 2007, the 22nd AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence. Vancouver, Canada</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="23">
 <cite id="CITEREFBinsted.2C_K.1997" style="font-style:normal">Binsted, K., Pain, H., and Ritchie, G.&#32;(1997),&#32;<it>Children's evaluation of computer-generated punning riddles</it>, Pragmatics and Cognition, 5(2), pp 309&ndash;358</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="22">
 <cite id="CITEREFVeale.2C_Tony2007" style="font-style:normal">Veale, Tony, O’Donoghue, Diarmuid&#32;(2007),&#32;<it>Computation and Blending</it>, Cognitive Linguistics, 11(3-4), special issue on Conceptual Blending</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="25">
 <cite id="CITEREFVeale2006" style="font-style:normal">Veale, Tony&#32;(2006),&#32;<it>Tracking the Lexical Zeitgeist with Wikipedia and WordNet</it>, Proceedings of ECAI’2006, the 17th European Conference on Artificial Intelligence</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="24">
 <cite id="CITEREFStock.2C_Oliviero2003" style="font-style:normal">Stock, Oliviero, Strapparava, Carlo&#32;(2003),&#32;<it>HAHAcronym: Humorous agents for humorous acronyms</it>, Humor: International Journal of Humor Research, 16(3) pp 297–314</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="27">
 <cite id="CITEREFCope2006" style="font-style:normal">Cope, David&#32;(2006),&#32;<it>Computer Models of Musical Creativity</it>, Cambridge, MA: MIT Press</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="26">
 <cite id="CITEREFGerv.C3.A1s2001" style="font-style:normal">Gervás, Pablo&#32;(2001),&#32;<it>An expert system for the composition of formal Spanish poetry</it>, Journal of Knowledge-Based Systems 14(3-4) pp 181&ndash;188</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="29">
 <cite id="CITEREFRomero.2C_Juan2008" style="font-style:normal">Romero, Juan, Machado, Penousal (eds.)&#32;(2008),&#32;<it>The Art of Artificial Evolution: A Handbook on Evolutionary Art and Music</it>, Natural Computing Series. Berlin: Springer Verlag</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="28">
 <cite id="CITEREFMcCorduck1991" style="font-style:normal">McCorduck, Pamela&#32;(1991),&#32;<it>Aaron's Code.</it>, W.H. Freeman &amp; Co., Ltd.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/479884.xml">
Algorithmic composition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<genre wordnetid="105845332" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/4878340.xml">
Algorithmic art</link></kind>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</genre>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/6974.xml">
Computer-generated music</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/353880.xml">
Computer art</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/886680.xml">
Digital poetry</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Further reading</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style="background-color:transparent;table-layout:fixed;" width="100%" cellpadding="0" border="0" cellspacing="0">
<row valign="top">
<col>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thinkartificial.org/artificial-creativity">
An Overview of Artificial Creativity</weblink> on Think Artificial</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cohen, H., <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stanford.edu/group/SHR/4-2/text/cohen.html">
"the further exploits of AARON, Painter"</weblink>, SEHR, volume 4, issue 2: Constructions of the Mind, 1995</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acblog.net/">
Artificial Creativity Blog</weblink></entry>
</list>
</col>
<col>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gero, J. S. and Sosa, R. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.arch.usyd.edu.au/~john/publications/2002/02SosaGeroCAADRIA.pdf">
"Artificial Creativity in Communities of Design Agents"</weblink>, 2006</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 LaDuke, B. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.anti-knowledge.com/book/00_Title.htm">
"Knowledge Machine"</weblink></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Applications and examples</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style="background-color:transparent;table-layout:fixed;" width="100%" cellpadding="0" border="0" cellspacing="0">
<row valign="top">
<col>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://armyofclerks.net/ArchiKluge/index.htm">
ArchiKluge</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://draw-something.robmyers.org/">
draw-something</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ocf.berkeley.edu/~jkunken/glot-bot/">
Glot-Bot v2</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://picbreeder.org">
picbreeder</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://thepaintingfool.com/">
 The Painting Fool</weblink></entry>
</list>
</col>
<col>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soban-art.com/">
generative art by Bogdan Soban</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.1stleft.com/clac/English/index.htm">
CLAC - Software for Logical Composition</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.indiana.edu/~leake/projects/swale/">
The SWALE project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://student.dei.uc.pt/~racosta/jmapper">
jMapper - Java Library for Analogy/Metaphor Generation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://afflatus.ucd.ie/aristotle/">
Aristotle - online metaphor generation and browsing system</weblink></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Institutions and individuals</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style="background-color:transparent;table-layout:fixed;" width="100%" cellpadding="0" border="0" cellspacing="0">
<row valign="top">
<col>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sussex.ac.uk/informatics/profile276.html">
Margaret Boden</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eden.dei.uc.pt/~amilcar/CreativeSystems/">
The Creative Systems Area of the AI Group/CISUC</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xs4all.nl/~notnot">
notnot Creative Systems</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imagination-engines.com/thaler.htm">
Stephen L. Thaler, Ph.D.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
