<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:47:16[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<social_group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107950920">
<society  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107966140">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<header>
<title>Society of Petroleum Engineers</title>
<id>1635629</id>
<revision>
<id>231012500</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-10T13:13:33Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DumZiBoT</username>
<id>6085301</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Engineering societies</category>
<category>petroleum</category>
<category>International nongovernmental organizations</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Society of Petroleum Engineers</b> (SPE) is a professional organization whose mission is to collect, disseminate, and exchange technical knowledge concerning the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/614302.xml">
exploration</link>, development and production of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
oil</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/18993869.xml">
gas</link> resources and related technologies for the public benefit and to provide opportunities for professionals to enhance their technical and professional competence.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

SPE provides a worldwide forum of oil and natural gas exploration and production (E&amp;P) professionals for the exchange of technical knowledge
and a professional home for more than 75,000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/38223.xml">
engineer</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/26997.xml">
scientist</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/312586.xml">
manager</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/4315397.xml">
educator</link>s.  SPE's eLibrary contains more than 42,000 technical papers —  products of SPE conferences and periodicals, made available to the entire industry. SPE has offices in Dallas, Houston, London, Dubai, Moscow and Kuala Lumpur.</p>
<p>

The history of the Society of Petroleum Engineers (SPE) began well before its actual establishment. During the decade after the 1901 discovery of the Spindletop field, the American Institute of Mining Engineers (AIME) saw a growing need for a forum in the booming new field of petroleum engineering. As a result, AIME formed a standing committee on oil and gas in 1913.</p>
<p>

In 1922, the committee was expanded to become one of AIME’s 10 professional divisions. The Petroleum Division of AIME continued to grow throughout the next three decades. By 1950, the Petroleum Division had become one of three separate branches of AIME, and in 1957 the Petroleum Branch of AIME was expanded once again to form a professional society.</p>
<p>

The first SPE Board of Directors meeting was held 6 October 1957, making 2007 the 50th anniversary year for SPE as a professional society.</p>
<p>

The following chronology lists major events in SPE's history and shows how membership has grown over time.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

1950s: During the 1950s, the petroleum membership of AIME grew significantly, leading to restructuring decisions that would shape the future Society of Petroleum Engineers.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

1957: The Petroleum Branch of AIME becomes a full-fledged professional society - the Society of Petroleum Engineers of AIME. On October 6, 1957, the first Board of Directors meeting was held in Dallas, Texas, with President John H. Hammond presiding.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

1958: The SPE Reprint Series begins with the publication of Well Logging. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

1961: The first issue of the Society of Petroleum Engineers Journal is published. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

1979: The first Middle East Oil and Gas Show and Conference is held. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

1985: SPE is incorporated separately from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/4062370.xml">
AIME</link>. Becomes a separate international Society with offices in United States, United Arab Emirates and London.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
 <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/18421265.xml">
SPE Certified Petroleum Professional</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
 </st>

<p>

SPE has instituted a program to certify  petroleum engineers by examination and experience.  The certification states that the person receiving the certification has the necessary technical expertise and experience to be a petroleum professional.</p>
<p>

This certification is similar to the Registration of Petroleum Engineers by the States in the United States.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Reserves Determination </st>

<p>

The Society of Petroleum Engineers has determined the classication of oil and gas reserves.  This classification is used by Oil and Gas Companines and the United States Securities and Exchange Commission in determining the reserves.
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spe.org/spe-site/spe/spe/industry/reserves/Petroleum_Resources_Management_System_2007.pdf">
Petroleum Resources Management System</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spe.org/">
SPE website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>






</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dallas.bizjournals.com/dallas/related_content.html?topic=Society%20of%20Petroleum%20Engineers">
Dallas Business Journal: Society of Petroleum Engineers related content</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</group>
</society>
</social_group>
</organization>
</article>
