<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:38:07[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<library  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103660909">
<format  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106636806">
<header>
<title>CGNS</title>
<id>16350686</id>
<revision>
<id>206187017</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-17T05:58:57Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Zeliboba7</username>
<id>6542617</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>C libraries</category>
<category>Computational fluid dynamics</category>
<category>Computer file formats</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox file format</name>
<parameters>
<genre>
<link>
scientific data format</link></genre>
<latest_release_version>
2.5.3</latest_release_version>
<url>
http://cgns.org</url>
<extension>
cgns</extension>
<name>
CFD General Notation System</name>
<latest_release_date>
March 11, 2007</latest_release_date>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>CGNS</b> stands for <b>CFD General Notation System</b>. It is a general, portable, and extensible standard for the storage and retrieval of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/305924.xml">
CFD</link> analysis data. It consists of a collection of conventions, and free and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/277663.xml">
open software</link> implementing those conventions. It is self-descriptive, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/81193.xml">
machine-independent</link>, documented, and administered by an international steering committee. It is also an American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (<link>
AIAA</link>) recommended practice. The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cgns.org">
CGNS project</weblink> originated in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/18948337.xml">
1994</link> as a joint effort between <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/18933266.xml">
Boeing</link></company>
 and <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/18426568.xml">
NASA</link></agency>
, and has since grown to include many other contributing organizations worldwide. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link>, control of CGNS was completely transferred to a public forum known as the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cgns.org/steering.html">
CGNS Steering Committee</weblink>. This Committee is made up of international representatives from government and private industry.</p>
<p>

The CGNS system consists of two parts: (1) a standard format (known as Standard Interface Data Structure, or SIDS) for recording the data, and (2) software that reads, writes, and modifies data in that format.  The format is a conceptual entity established by the documentation; the software is a physical product supplied to enable developers to access and produce data recorded in that format. </p>
<p>

The CGNS system is designed to facilitate the exchange of data between sites and applications, and to help stabilize the archiving of aerodynamic data.  The data are stored in a compact, binary format and are accessible through a complete and extensible library of functions.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
API</link> (Application Program Interface) is platform independent and can be easily implemented in <link>
 C</link>, <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/72038.xml">
C++</link></programming_language>
, <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/11168.xml">
Fortran</link></programming_language>
 and <link>
Fortran 90</link> applications. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/22757.xml">
Object oriented</link> interface <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cgnspp.sourceforge.net/">
CGNS++</weblink> and <link>
 Python</link> module <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cgns-python.berlios.de">
pyCGNS</weblink> are exist, while they are not maintained.</p>
<p>

The principal target of CGNS is data normally associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/166084.xml">
compressible</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18963754.xml">
viscous</link> flow (i.e., the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/48395.xml">
Navier-Stokes equations</link>), but the standard is also applicable to subclasses such as <link>
 Euler</link> and potential flows. The CGNS standard includes the following types of data. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Structured, unstructured, and hybrid grids</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Flow solution data, which may be nodal, cell-centered, face-centered, or edge-centered</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Multizone interface connectivity, both abutting and overset</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Boundary conditions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Flow equation descriptions, including the equation of state, viscosity and thermal conductivity models, turbulence models, multi-species chemistry models, and electromagnetics</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Time-dependent flow, including moving and deforming grids</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dimensional units and nondimensionalization information</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reference states</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Convergence history</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Association to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/37315.xml">
CAD</link> geometry definitions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 User-defined data </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Much of the standard and the software is applicable to computational field physics in general. Disciplines other than fluid dynamics would need to augment the data definitions and storage conventions, but the fundamental database software, which provides platform independence, is not specific to fluid dynamics.</p>
<p>

CGNS is self-describing, allowing an application to interpret the structure and contents of a file without any outside information. CGNS can make use of either two different low-level data formats:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 an internally-developed and supported method called Advanced Data Format (ADF), based on a common file format system previously in use at McDonnell Douglas</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/635425.xml">
HDF5</link>, a widely used hierarchical data format</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Tools and Guides</st>
<p>

In addition to the CGNS library itself, the following tools and guides are available from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/cgns/">
SourceForge</weblink>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CGNSTools - Includes ADFVIEWER, a browser and editor for CGNS files</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Users Guide code - small practical example CGNS programs written in both Fortran and C</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 F77 Examples - example computer programs written in Fortran that demonstrate all CGNS functionality</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cgns.org/">
CGNS home page</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</format>
</library>
</article>
