<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:43:28[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<computer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103082979">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<device  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103183080">
<machine  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103699975">
<web_site  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106359193">
<header>
<title>Music Australia</title>
<id>16422980</id>
<revision>
<id>222620669</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-30T08:42:05Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Firsfron</username>
<id>158443</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Australian music</category>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Library 2.0</category>
<category>Online databases</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles with possible conflicts of interest</category>
<category>Music websites</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Unbalanced_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>A major contributor to this article or its creator appears to have a  with its subject.</b>
It may require  to comply with Wikipedia's content policies, particularly . Please discuss further on the . <it>(March 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.musicaustralia.org">
Music Australia</weblink>, a national federated online discovery service, was launched on 14th March 2005 at the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au">
National Library of Australia</weblink> by Senator, the Honourable Rod Kemp, Minister for the Arts and Sports. The service is hosted by the National Library of Australia in conjunction with over 50 cultural organisations across Australia. 
<sec>
<st>
 Scope  </st>

<p>

The free service for Australian music resources covers all types, styles and genres of Australian music, and showcases Australia’s musical culture across contemporary and historical periods, from the 19th century to the latest hit.  It contains music scores, sound recordings, websites, pictures, films, multimedia, kits,  objects, archival collections and other music-related material held in libraries, archives, museums, universities, and specialist music and research organisations in Australia.  </p>
<p>

The service contains information about Australian music, including books and theses, information created by Australians about non-Australian music, and biographical entries for Australian musicians, performers, composers, groups and ensembles, festivals and organisations. </p>
<p>

Music Australia's definition of 'Australian music' is broad and inclusive, and covers music published in Australia or music composed or performed by Australians or about Australia or Australians. </p>
<p>

Music Australia functions as a top-layer, federated discovery service to metadata with digital content created, archived and delivered by the contributing organisation. It uses two linked databases, one for Resources and one for People and organisation information. A search will find music and music-related resources physically scattered across Australia, where vast geographical distances, remote locations, dispersed collections and low level of community funding mitigates against easy access to music resources. Music Australia creates and displays a ‘virtual’ Australian national music collection, where the metadata is aggregated centrally by the National Library but returns the user to the home institution to access the resource. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Features </st>

<p>

Music Australia has a simple search interface, with an advanced search option that allows limits to be applied for a refined results set. A successful search will return a result set from the two linked Music Australia resource and people databases.</p>
<p>

The Music Australia service includes themes highlighting a topic by providing a relevant selection of music materials available in the service. A theme can be used as an entry point for resources on a topic in the musical landscape. eg. the Music Australia <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.musicaustralia/themesummary/Musical+Treasures">
National treasures</weblink> theme supports the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nationaltreasures.nla.gov.au/">
National Treasures from Australia’s Great Libraries online exhibition</weblink> </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Permalinks </st>
<p>

Music Australia uses various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/878926.xml">
permalink</link>s to ensure permanent links and access to its resources. These permalinks can be used from any browser and do not require the Music Australia website to be open. </p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Search </st>
<p>

A search permalink can be constructed using the base search www.musicaustralia.org/search/ and adding a term or topic name, eg. the search http://www.musicaustralia.org/search/kangaroos returns a wonderful mixture of music material associated with ‘kangaroos’, including sheet music from Paris in the 1800’s, through dances to football anthems. The search http://www.musicaustralia/search/Waltzing+matilda from any browser, returns all the music resources in Music Australia on 'Waltzing Matilda' </p>


</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Themes </st>
<p>

To see the music resources for a Music Australia theme use the theme permalink base search  
www.musicaustralia/theme/  and add the name of the theme. The theme name is case sensitive so must be added as it appears in the service, eg. the search http://www.musicaustralia/theme/Waltzing+Matilda will return the records for the theme 'Waltzing Matilda' in Music Australia. For themes that have subthemes use the name of the subtheme, eg. the theme 'Australian places' has subthemes for each state and territory and the search http://www.musicaustralia.org/theme/Australian+Capital+Territory returns the selected music resources from the ACT and Canberra subtheme.   </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Persistent identifiers </st>

<p>

A persistent identifier to a resource will provide ongoing access and reference to that resource and can be used whenever a permanent link is required. Persistent identifiers / Cite this page links are provided in Music Australia and are displayed in the full information view of every Music Australia resource and people and organisation record, eg. http://nla.gov.au/nla.cs-ma-an12285853 is the persistent identifier / citation to the record for the Yothu Yindi website, both the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.yothuyindi.com">
current version</weblink> and the  in <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pandora.nla.gov.au/">
archived versions in Pandora</weblink>, Australia's web archive. </p>
<p>

Persistent identifiers are a permanent reference/citation for a resource in a changing digital world. The National Library of Australia implemented its own managed <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au/initiatives/nlapi.html">
naming scheme of persistent identifiers</weblink> for digital resources after assessing that there was no schema currently in use or under development internationally in 2001, that was sufficiently mature to offer a suitable solution in the short-term for its digital collections.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History of development </st>

<p>

Developing and delivering the systems to make this service possible posed enormous challenges to music librarians and information professionals across Australia.  
When the first ideas for a service were floated in 2001, Australia’s music was scattered across many different institutions, libraries, archives, museums and arts and specialists music organisations, and there was no way for users or researchers to find and access them. There were no collections of digitised printed music and although some national institutions had been digitally preserving their sound collections, none were available online.  </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Timeline </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Pilot demonstrator project: November 2001-August 2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Pilot to Production development: March 2003-February 2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Release of Music Australia 1.0:  March 2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Release of Music Australia 2.0: April 2007</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Pilot </st>

<p>

A pilot project commenced in late 2001 and aimed to test the delivery of musical content using a selected set of digitised and born digital scores from the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au">
National Library of Australia</weblink>and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amcoz.com.au/">
Australian Music Centre</weblink>, and sound from the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nfsa.afc.gov.au">
National Film and Sound Archive</weblink>, trialling data exchange and digital delivery across music formats and institutions.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Pilot to Production </st>

<p>

The aim for a production service was to build a cooperative Australian music data-set, as well as a sustainable service model, with Music Australia functioning as both a content provider to and a subject based view of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au/librariesaustralia/databases.html">
Australian National Bibliographic Database (ANBD)</weblink>  </p>
<p>

This required: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Methodologies and systems to be developed to support the complexity of multiple formats of music;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Data harvesting and exchange between many different bibliographic standards to support a centralised data set in MARC;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Content development and support for digitisation programs across institutions; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Work across both library and non-library sectors for a comprehensive coverage of the music landscape, when many music organisations were creating and using data in a myriad of ways and data types.  </entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Resource database </st>
<p>

Music Australia was to consist of 2 linked databases, one for the resource description and one for people and organisation information. The resource database, as a sub-set of the ANDB, was to manage its data in MARC format. This made the data harvest and exchange from libraries and institutions using MARC relatively easy to manage, and to use to develop and build the service as the project team had solid experience with MARC based systems. 
However for music organisations, communities and special projects that were generating shareable data in non-MARC format, we had to explore and develop a methodology to harvest, map and convert a wide range of data types into <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/marc/marcdocz.html">
MARC</weblink>, initially converting the data via <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods2marc-mapping.html">
MODS to MARC</weblink>, and stored in MARCXML.  Later in the development, the methodology changed, moving to direct conversion, some needing initial hand crafting, from the data standard used by an organisation contributing records to Music Australia into MARC, then MARCXML. </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 People and organisation database </st>
<p>

The people and organisation information was to be sourced from a number of areas and contributors. The Project team investigated a number of potential schemas and data formats for this party database during 2003-2004. These investigations indicated that there was no mature schema with which to structure identfying and contextual information about people and organisations associated with Australian music for the Music Australia service. The Project team undertook to develop and implement its own schema, called Music Australia Party Schema (MAPS). As <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mads/">
MADS</weblink>had not yet been published, it was decided to use MODS elements where possible, incorporating some EAC elements, and to use appropriate terminology from MODS and EAC. Following publications of MADS, the MAPS schema was adjusted to reflect many of the MADS structure and terms. Various models or architectures applicable to a federated people and organisation database had to be considered, with the need to deliver data harvested from many different  databases using many different standards, and the need to manage duplicated or even contradictory contextual information, and present this to users in a coherent manner.  </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Content </st>
<p>

As part of the content generation the National Library developed a cooperative plan with the state libraries to digitize Australian sheet music within their emerging digitisation programs. Some state libraries, such as Queensland and Western Australia, also developed arts initiatives to perform and record hitherto unknown historic musical works pertaining to their regions, and others, such as the State Library of South Australia, commenced programs to digitally preserve and deliver sound recordings.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Music Australia 1.0 </st>

<p>

Music Australia 1.0 was successfully launched in March 2005 with a wide and substantial range of content from major and minor contributing institutions. Soon after release the service faced more challenges and changes, motivated by the need for sustainability amidst rapidly changing digital information business models and in response to external demands and user feedback. </p>
<p>

The rapid changes in the music industry, driven by new technology and delivery models, posed many challenges for the service as we strived to stay relevant and to provide to users, for research or recreation, access to Australian music resources. The need to increase and to provide access to Australian digital music, both historical and contemporary, from printed music to the latest digital audio downloads, for users was a driving force as we looked to improve our service. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Music Australia 2.0 </st>

<p>

A new business to government<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business-to-government(B2G)">
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business-to-government(B2G)</weblink> partnership with an Australian digital music supplier provided the opportunity for the service to offer to users access to a database of Australian contemporary online tracks and albums, with 30 second sound samples and pathways for legal digital downloads through e-commerce, while protecting the rights of artists and performers with digital rights management processes. </p>
<p>

This B2G, together with identified service enhancements and bug fixes, combined with recommendations from a user and web usability survey commissioned in 2006, drove the changes to Music Australia 1.0. and resulted in the release of Music Australia 2.0 in April 2007. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Future developments </st>

<p>

The music industry, with its rapidly changing environment, together with innovative technologies, digitisation and the Web 2.0, continues to provide challenges and opportunities to streamline and broaden our Music Australia service into the future, to provide users with simple and easy access to Australian music resources and information, wherever they may be, for both research and recreation.   </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Robyn Holmes and Marie-Louse Ayres.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au/pub/nlanews/2005/may05/may05news.html">
“Australia’s music: online, in time”</weblink>. National Library of Australia news, May 2005. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Robyn Holmes and Marie-Louise Ayres. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au/nla/staffpaper/2004/ayres2.html">
“Music Australia: Towards a National Music Information Infrastructure”</weblink>.  5th International Conference on Music Information Retrieval  Proceedings. Audiovisual Institute Pompeu Fabra University, Barcelona, 2004. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Marie-Louise Ayres. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au/nla/staffpaper/2004/ayres1.html">
"MusicAustralia: Building on National Infrastructure"</weblink>. VALA 2004 Conference, Melbourne, Feb 3-6 2004 </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Roxanne Missingham. [http://www.nla.gov.au/nla/staffpaper/2004/missingham3.html "A New Strategic Direction for the National Library of Australia". Alexandria, 16 (1): 37-48</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Debbie Campbell. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au/nla/staffpaper/2005/campbell3.html">
"Easy To Do: A brief history of federated harvesting in Australia"</weblink>. ETD 2005 conference, 30 September 2005. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Marie-Louise Ayres. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au/nla/staffpaper/2005/ayres1.html">
"Case Studies in implementing Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records[FRBR</weblink>: AustLit and MusicAustralia"],ALJ: the Australian Library Journal February 2005 ,vol 54 no 1, pp 43-54</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Warwick Cathro. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://uksg.metapress.com/app/home/contribution.asp?referrer=parent&amp;backto=issue,5,19;journal,4,61;linkingpublicationresults,1:107730,1">
"Digitization in Australasia"</weblink>. Serials: The Journal for the Serials Community, V.20, No. 1, March 2007, p. 9 - 15 </entry>
</list>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>


</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations .</col>
</row>
</table>


</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.musicaustralia.org">
Music Australia</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nla.gov.au">
National Library of Australia</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amcoz.com.au/">
Australian Music Centre</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nfsa.afc.gov.au">
National Film and Sound Archive</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</entity>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</article>
