<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:36:26[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network Centric Product Support</title>
<id>16620919</id>
<revision>
<id>211272118</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-09T15:22:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Chris the speller</username>
<id>525927</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category> Computer Architecture</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(March 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Network Centric Product Support (NCPS)</b> is an emerging computer architecture that was developed to leverage new information technology and global networks to assist in managing maintenance, support and supply chain of mobile complex products made up of one or more systems, such as an aircraft or fleet. This is accomplished by embedding intelligence through micro-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/33455.xml">
web servers</link> that also function as a computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/68181.xml">
workstation</link> with the aircraft <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/2528024.xml">
Engine control unit</link> or other subsystem, and enabling 2-way communications using existing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> technologies and communications networks. NCPS can be considered to be the support flip side of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/1733505.xml">
Network-centric warfare</link>, as this approach goes beyond traditional performance based logistics initiatives by taking a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/1428810.xml">
complex adaptive system</link> management approach and integrating field maintenance and logistics in a unified factory and field environment. Its evolution began out of insights gained by CDR Dave Loda (USNR) from Network Centric Warfare-based fleet battle experimentation at the US Naval Warfare Development Command (NWDC) in the late 1990s, with initial commercial applications in commercial aviation through United Technologies Corporation beginning in 2001.
<sec>
<st>
Purpose</st>
<p>

Simply put, this architecture extends the existing world wide web infrastructure of networked web servers down into the product at its system's controller level. Its core is an embedded dual function webserver/computer workstation connected to the controller's test ports (in retrofit applications) or can be integrated directly into the controller, hence providing access to controller cycles and sensor information in a clustered, internet addressable node that allows for local or remote access, and the ability to host reconfigurable software that can collect and process data from its mated subsystem controller on board. It creates a localized wireless worldwide web in and around the aircraft that can be securely connected to by a mechanic with any web browser-equipped handheld, independent of the greater worldwide web. Legacy systems usually require a human to manually connect a laptop to the system controller to collect data and carry it back to a location where it can be later transferred to the factory for analysis. </p>
<p>

The architecture also enables communications with other micro-webservers in its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/18949896.xml">
Computer cluster</link> (i.e. the aircraft), or to higher level clusters (such as an internet portal managed fleet and flight operations managers), thus enabling access to personnel and factory engineers at remote office computers through the world wide web. The system operates asynchronously, in that it does not have to be always connected to the world wide web to function; rather it simply operates locally, then synchronizes two-way information relevant to the subsystem, acting as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/1338556.xml">
Gateway (telecommunications)</link> on board that connects with other gateways within the network, which can be airborne or on the ground, on an as-needed basis when communications is available. This can be accomplished through a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/33143.xml">
Wireless LAN Network</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/27683.xml">
satellite</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/735672.xml">
cellular network</link> or other wireless or wired communications capabilities.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Typical Usage</st>
<p>

The extension of the world wide web architecture into the product is important to understand, as all decisions for manufacturing of spare parts, scheduling for flights, and other factory OEM and airline operator functions, are driven primarily by what happens to the product in the field (rate of wear and impending failure, primarily). Predicting the rate of wear, and hence the impact on operations and forecasting for producing spare parts in the future, is critical for optimizing operations for all involved. Managing a complex system such as a fleet of aircraft or vehicles can be accomplished in this manner. For example, coupled with technologies such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/169320.xml">
RFID</link>, the system could track parts from the factory to the aircraft on board, then continue to read the configuration of the subsystem’s replaceable tagged parts, map their configuration to hours run and duty cycles, then process/communicate the projected wear rate through the world wide web back to the operator or factory. In this way mechanical wear rates and future failures can be predicted more accurately and the forecasting of spare parts manufacturing and shipment can be significantly improved. This is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/1434685.xml">
Prognostics</link> Health Monitoring (PHM), which has become possible in recent years with the advent of electronic controllers, and is a recent evolutionary step in aircraft support and maintenance management that began as individual processes prior to World War II and solidified into a manual tracking system to support aircraft fleets in the Korean War. Support for the mechanic comes in local wireless access to technical information stored and remotely updated on board the micro-webserver component relevant to that product, such as service bulletins, factory updates, fault code driven, intelligent 3D computer game-like maintenance procedures, and enabling 2-way voice, text and image communications.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Background and Other Examples</st>
<p>

The original micro-webserver component of NCPS was first developed and demonstrated in 2001 by David Loda, Enzo Macchia, Sam Quadri and Bjorn Stickling, and initially tested on board a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/3400132.xml">
Fairchild-Dornier 328</link> regional jet in January 2002. It was introduced to the public and demonstrated at the Farnborough Air Show in July 2002 and again in 2004 as a flight certified product offering by Altair Avionics, and is beginning to see service in a number of aircraft and helicopters. </p>
<p>

A similar complex systems approach in a completely different application was successfully demonstrated in the Eisenhower <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/43950.xml">
Interstate Highway System</link>, though what is transported in NCPS is information, not cars and trucks. Network Centric Product Support is an architectural concept, and merely connects the major avenues already existing in global communications and the internet into the mobile product, extending maintenance and supply chain processes into a product centric system. For example, to gain information about a particular engine on a mobile aircraft, it is most efficient to send the inquiry to the engine directly and host all information generated and relevant to that system, as well synchronize in a twin remote database for access and queuing when the engine system is not in communications. Other examples where this can be applied include shipping containers, automobiles, spacecraft, appliances, human medical monitoring, or any other complex product with sensors and subsystems that require maintenance support and monitoring.</p>
<p>

More and more organizations are beginning to see the value of a Network Centric approach to managing complex systems, including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/7168628.xml">
Network Centric Operations Industry Consortium</link> (NCOIC), which is an association of leading aerospace and defense contractors in the Network Centric Warfare arena. Network Centric thinking for aircraft operations, including Network Enabled Operations (NEO) demonstrations, also figure prominently in the commercial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/12942905.xml">
Next Generation Air Transportation System</link> (NextGen) approach being made by the US Government to revamping air transportation management in the 21st Century. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 AIAA 2005-7 IMAPP Conferences <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aiaa.org/portal/index.cfm?adview=12&amp;tcspageid=1780&amp;getcomm=206">
http://www.aiaa.org/portal/index.cfm?adview=12&amp;tcspageid=1780&amp;getcomm=206</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ATW Article, June 2007. RFID: Ready for Industry Doubters? <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.atwonline.com/channels/safetySecurity/article.html?articleID=1968">
http://www.atwonline.com/channels/safetySecurity/article.html?articleID=1968</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 AIA DOD Fall 2004 Product Support Conference [https://acc.dau.mil/CommunityBrowser.aspx?id=22403]</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Definition-Of Directory, NCPS <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.definition-of.com/NCPS">
http://www.definition-of.com/NCPS</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 NCPS Applied Research Definition <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.avetec.org/applied-research/project-network-centric.cfm">
http://www.avetec.org/applied-research/project-network-centric.cfm</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Next Generation Air Transportation System (NextGen) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jpdo.gov">
http://www.jpdo.gov</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Network Centric Industry Association (NCOIC) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncoic.org">
http://www.ncoic.org</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Defense Acquisition Community, Performance Based Logistics Definition [https://acc.dau.mil/CommunityBrowser.aspx?id=18074]</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 BNET Article, Oct 2006, Data Transmission Units on Falcon 2000EX and Falcon 7X Business Jets <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_pwwi/is_200610/ai_n16778703">
http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_pwwi/is_200610/ai_n16778703</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 AviationNow: Farnborough Air Show - July 2004: P&amp;W Launches Revolutionary 3-D Directed Maintenance <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.awstonline.com/shownews/04farn/hard01_3.htm">
http://www.awstonline.com/shownews/04farn/hard01_3.htm</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Farnborough Airshow, July 2004, Dornier 328 Microserver Introduction <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imakenews.com/pwconnections/e_article000287220.cfm?x=b11,0,w">
http://www.imakenews.com/pwconnections/e_article000287220.cfm?x=b11,0,w</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Product Application Study, Right Hemisphere Dec 2005, Condition Based Maintenance Solutions <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.righthemisphere.com/company/Del_Value_PrattWhitney_public_WEB.pdf">
http://www.righthemisphere.com/company/Del_Value_PrattWhitney_public_WEB.pdf</weblink> </entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
