<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:50:38[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<law  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108441203">
<concept  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105835747">
<header>
<title>BKS theory</title>
<id>16711283</id>
<revision>
<id>243049759</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-04T22:36:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dirac66</username>
<id>2038644</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Physics</category>
<category>Photons</category>
<category>Quantum mechanics</category>
<category>Conservation laws</category>
<category>Niels Bohr</category>
<category>Fundamental physics concepts</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Bohr-Kramers-Slater</b> (BKS) theory<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> (1924) is perhaps 
more a program than a genuine physical theory, the ideas that are 
developed not being worked out in a quantitative way. The theory 
might be seen as a final attempt at understanding the interaction 
of matter and electromagnetic radiation on the basis of the 
so-called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/1188104.xml">
Old quantum theory</link>, in which quantum 
phenomena are treated by imposing quantum restrictions on 
classically describable behaviour. In particular does the BKS 
theory stick to a <it>classical</it> wave description of the 
electromagnetic field.<p>

The initial idea of the BKS theory originates with 
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../835/405835.xml">
Slater</link></scientist>
</person>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>, who proposed to <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/21210.xml">
Bohr</link></scientist>
</person>
 and 
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/1842122.xml">
Kramers</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
 the following elements of a theory of emission and 
absorption of radiation by atoms, to be developed during his stay 
in Copenhagen: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Emission and absorption of electromagnetic radiation by matter is realized in agreement with <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/736.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Light+and+general+relativity%22])">
Einstein</link></scientist>
</person>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/23535.xml">
photon</link> concept; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 A photon emitted by an atom is guided by a classical electromagnetic field (compare <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/50165.xml">
 de Broglie</link></scientist>
</person>
's ideas published September 1923 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>) consisting of spherical waves, thus enabling to explain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/15112.xml">
interference</link>;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Even when there are no transitions there exists a classical field to which all atoms contribute; this field contains all frequencies at which an atom can emit or absorb a photon, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/22934.xml">
probability</link> of such an emission being determined by the amplitude of the corresponding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/11659.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Applications+in+signal+processing%22])">
Fourier component</link> of the field; the probabilistic aspect is provisional, to be eliminated when the dynamics of the inside of atoms is better known;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The classical field is not produced by the actual motions of the electrons but by `motions with the frequencies of possible <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/177320.xml">
emission and absorption lines</link>' (to be called `<it>virtual</it> oscillators', creating a field to be referred to as `virtual' as well).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Slater's main intention seems to be to reconcile the two conflicting 
models of radiation, viz. the <link>
wave and particle models</link>. He may 
have had good hopes that his idea with respect to oscillators 
vibrating at the <it>differences</it> of the frequencies of electron 
rotations (rather than at the rotation frequencies themselves) 
might be attractive to Bohr because it solved a problem of the latter's <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/4831.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22History%22])">
atomic model</link></concept>
</idea>
, even though the physical meaning of 
these oscillators was far from clear. Nevertheless, Bohr and 
Kramers had two objections to Slater's proposal: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The assumption that photons exist. Even though Einstein's photon hypothesis could explain in a simple way the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/23579.xml">
photoelectric effect</link>, as well as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/67088.xml">
conservation of energy</link> in processes of de-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/516680.xml">
excitation</link> of an atom followed by excitation of a neighboring one, has Bohr always been reluctant to accept the reality of photons, his main argument being the problem of reconciling the existence of photons with the phenomenon of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/15112.xml">
interference</link>. Bohr and Kramers hoped to be able to evade the photon hypothesis on the basis of results obtained by Kramers on describing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/172333.xml">
dispersion of light</link> by means of a classical theory of interaction of radiation and matter;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The impossibility to account for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/67088.xml">
conservation of energy</link> in a process of de-excitation of an atom followed by excitation of a neighboring one. This impossibility followed from Slater's probabilistic assumption, which did not imply any <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/157057.xml">
correlation</link> between processes going on in different atoms.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In the BKS paper the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/55236.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22The+Compton+shift+formula%22])">
Compton effect</link> is discussed as an application of the idea of `<it>statistical</it> conservation of energy and momentum' in a continuous process of scattering of radiation by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/10949251.xml">
sample</link> of free electrons, where "each of the electrons contributes through the emission of  coherent secondary wavelets". Although Compton already had given an attractive account of his experiment on the basis of the photon picture (including conservation of energy and momentum in <it>individual</it> scattering processes), is it stated in the BKS paper that "it seems at the present state of science hardly justifiable to reject a formal interpretation as that under consideration [i.e. the weaker assumption of ''statistical'' conservation] as inadequate". This statement may have prompted experimental physicists to improve `the present state of science' by testing the hypothesis of `statistical energy and momentum conservation'. Anyway, already after one year the BKS theory was falsified by experiments studying correlations between the directions into which the emitted radiation and the recoil electron are emitted in individual scattering processes. Such experiments were independently performed by Bothe and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/78738.xml">
Geiger</link></scientist>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>, as well as by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/432000.xml">
Compton</link></scientist>
</person>
 and Simon<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>. They provided experimental evidence pointing into the direction of energy  and momentum conservation in individual scattering processes (at least, it was shown that the BKS theory was not able to explain the experimental results). More accurate experiments were performed much later<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>.</p>
<p>

As is suggested by his letter to <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/61866.xml">
Born</link></scientist>
</person>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> was for Einstein the corroboration of energy and momentum conservation probably even more important than his photon hypothesis: "Bohr's opinion of radiation interests me very much. But I don't want to let myself be driven to a renunciation of strict causality before there has been a much stronger resistance against it than up to now. I cannot bear the thought that an electron exposed to a ray should by its own free decision choose the moment and the direction in which it wants to jump away. If so, I'd rather be a cobbler or even an employee in a gambling house than a physicist. It is true, my attempts to give the quanta palpable shape have failed again and again, but I'm not going to give up hope for a long time yet." </p>
<p>

Bohr's reaction, too, was not primarily related to the photon 
hypothesis. According to <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/33130.xml">
Heisenberg</link></scientist>
</person>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Bohr would have remarked: "Even 
if Einstein sends me a cable that now an irrevocable proof of the 
physical existence of light-quanta had been found, the message 
cannot reach me, because it has to be transmitted by 
electromagnetic waves.". For Bohr the lesson to be learned from the falsification of the BKS 
theory was not that photons do exist, but rather the limited 
applicability of classical space-time pictures in understanding 
phenomena within the quantum domain. This theme would become 
particularly important a few years later in developing the notion 
of `<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/1530689.xml">
complementarity</link>'. According to Heisenberg also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/1316110.xml">
Born's statistical interpretation</link> had its ultimate roots in the BKS theory. Hence by its failure the BKS theory may yet have provided an important contribution to the revolutionary transition from classical mechanics to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanics</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>
 
<reflist>
<entry id="1">
N. Bohr, Collected 
Works, J. Kalckar, ed. North-Holland, Amsterdam, etc., 1985, Vol. 5, 
pp. 3-216.</entry>
<entry id="2">
J. Mehra and H. Rechenberg, The historical 
development of quantum theory, Springer-Verlag, New York, etc., 
1982, Vol. 1, Part 2, pp. 532-554.</entry>
<entry id="3">
N. Bohr, H.A. Kramers, 
and J.C. Slater, Phil. Mag. <b>47</b>, 785-802 (1924) (German version: 
Zeitschr. f. Physik <b>24</b>, 69-87 (1924)).</entry>
<entry id="4">
Letters from J.C. Slater, November, December 1923, 
reprinted in Ref. 1, pp. 8, 9.</entry>
<entry id="5">
L. de Broglie, Comptes Rendues <b>177</b>, 507-510 (1923).</entry>
<entry id="6">
W. Bothe and H. Geiger, Zeitschr. f. Phys.
<b>26</b>, 44 (1924); Naturwiss. <b>13</b>, 440-441 (1925).</entry>
<entry id="7">
A.H. Compton, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. <b>11</b>, 303-306 (1925); A.H. Compton and A.W. Simon, Phys. Rev. <b>26</b>, 289-299 (1925).</entry>
<entry id="8">
R. Hofstadter and J.A. McIntyre, Phys. Rev. <b>78</b>, 24-28 (1950).</entry>
<entry id="9">
W.G. Cross and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/503394.xml">
N.F. Ramsey</link></scientist>
, Phys. Rev. <b>80</b>, 929-936 (1950).</entry>
<entry id="10">
Letter of April 29, 1924 in: The Born-Einstein Letters, Correspondence between Albert Einstein and Max and Hedwig Born from 1916 to 1955 with commentaries by Max Born, Walker and Company, New York, 1971.</entry>
<entry id="11">
Interview with Mehra, quoted in 
Ref. 2, p. 554</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</concept>
</law>
</article>
