<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:52:11[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<landmark  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108624891">
<company  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108058098">
<header>
<title>Columbia Restaurant</title>
<id>16774295</id>
<revision>
<id>237375347</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-09T21:57:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Paul foord</username>
<id>240061</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>History of Tampa, Florida</category>
<category>Restaurants in Tampa</category>
<category>Landmarks in Tampa</category>
<category>Companies based in Tampa, Florida</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Company</name>
<parameters>
<area_served>
central Florida</area_served>
<location>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/92995.xml">
Tampa, Florida</link></village>
</location>
<type>
Private</type>
<slogan>
Columbia the Gem of Spanish Restaurants</slogan>
<locations>
6</locations>
<name>
Columbia Restaurant</name>
<foundation>
1905 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../156/789156.xml">
Ybor City, Tampa, Florida</link></village>
</foundation>
<industry>
Food Service</industry>
<products>
Spanish Food, Wine &amp; Entertainment</products>
<revenue>
$42M (1991-last published)</revenue>
<parent>
Columbia Restaurant Group</parent>
<homepage>
http://www.columbiarestaurant.com/</homepage>
<key_people>
Casey &amp; Richard Gonzmart</key_people>
<num_employees>
1,200</num_employees>
<company_logo>
<image width="200px" src="columbia100_logo.PNG">
</image>
</company_logo>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

The original <b>Columbia Restaurant</b> is the oldest Spanish restaurant in the United States<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> and one of the largest (with 1,700 seats in 15 dining rooms taking up 52,000 ft²) in the world. Founded in 1905 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../156/789156.xml">
Ybor City, Tampa, Florida</link></village>
, the landmark is still owned by the Hernandez/Gonzmart family and serves authentic Cuban cuisine.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Namesake</st>
<p>

Proud of the successful business and the freedom of America, Casmiro, Sr. named the restaurant, "<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<personification wordnetid="110418101" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/2165190.xml">
Columbia</link></causal_agent>
</person>
</personification>
</physical_entity>
", after hearing the song, "<music wordnetid="107020895" confidence="0.8">
<song wordnetid="107048000" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<musical_composition wordnetid="107037465" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/1428660.xml">
Columbia, the Gem of the Ocean</link></musical_composition>
</auditory_communication>
</song>
</music>
", and reflecting on <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/5635.xml">
Christopher Columbus</link></person>
. Later, he altered the line to read, "Columbia the Gem of Spanish Restaurants" as their motto. The tall ship "Columbia" is part of the logo of the Columbia Restaurant today, and appeared on their matchboxes. La Tacita Restaurant http://www.latacitarestaurant.com</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="ColumbiaTampaAug2008Corner21A.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Columbia Restaurant in Ybor City, Tampa, 2008
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Hernandez/Gonzmart family</st>

<ss1>
<st>
First Generation</st>
<p>

Casimiro Hernandez Sr. came to the United States in 1905 to escape the fighting in Spain. He left New York City and traveled with his family to Tampa. His son was 12 years old. Across the street from their apartment was a small bar, struggling to survive. The elder Hernandez saw the need for a restaurant in the fast growing neighborhood, and with the financial help of a friend, bought the building. To cater to the immigrant workforce in the cigar factories, he provided light meals and strong drinks. He began serving Cuban sandwiches, then added Spanish bean soup. Interestingly, Spanish bean soup did not exist anywhere before that time, even in Spain; Casmiro Hernandez, Sr. created it. Initially, workers could get a free lunch with their purchased drinks. Later, he offered meals for $18 per month, and the business grew. By 1919 it was time to expand, so he acquired the restaurant next door, signing the owner into a partnership. The Columbia was still just a cafe, a place where cigar workers would hang out.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Second Generation</st>
<p>

The founder's son, Casimiro Hernandez Jr. joined his father in the business in 1919 and took over operations in 1927, shortly before his father’s death in 1929. The Junior Casimiro had dreams of transforming the Columbia Restaurant into an elegant dining establishment with music and dancing. This was a bold plan because there were no similar restaurants in all of the Southeastern United States<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> and his father was a "big spender", leaving behind a mountain of debt. A few years later, at the height of the Great Depression, the Columbia's daily receipts totaled $12.42. According to family historians,  Casimiro, Jr. went down the street to the local hardware store and purchased a hammer and nails. He returned to the restaurant and gathered the entire staff around him. Waving the hammer and nails, he warned them, "Another $12-day, and I nail up the dammed joint!" </p>
<p>

Fortunately, better days followed, and in 1935, Casimiro, Jr. was ready to turn his dream into reality. Unfortunately, he had no capital, so he convinced the local banker to make a $35,000 expansion loan. The banker agreed--sealed by a gentleman's handshake! That year, construction began on the first air-conditioned dining room in Tampa, including an elevated dance floor. It opened on Thanksgiving day and was named the <it>Don Quixote</it> dining room, for Casmiro Jr.'s hero.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> 
It was immediately successful, so two years later, the <it>Patio</it> dining room was completed. It resembled courtyards found in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/2736.xml">
Andalucia</link> in southern Spain, and contained a mosaic tiled fountain, marble floors and 30-foot (9.1&nbsp;m)-high palms, surrounded by a second floor balcony. A retractable glass skylight added natural light and fresh air during the day.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Third Generation</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/18251066.xml">
Cesar Gonzmart</link> was born in Tampa and knew the Hernandez family growing up. In 1935 at age 15, Cesar earned $20 a week substituting in the Columbia's band before he went off to college. By his mid-twenties, he had a doctorate in music from the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/1146808.xml">
University of Havana</link></university>
 in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/5042481.xml">
Cuba</link></country>
 and traveled around the world serving as concert violinist, earning $75,000 per year, and played with his orchestra, <it>Cesar Gonzalez and his Magic Violins</it>. </p>
<p>

Meanwhile, Adela Hernandez, the strikingly beautiful granddaughter of Columbia founder Casimiro Hernandez Sr. had graduated from the <private_school wordnetid="108411170" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/176634.xml">
Juilliard School of Music</link></private_school>
 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/645042.xml">
New York City</link></village>
 and became an accomplished concert pianist who also traveled the world with leading orchestras. Notably, Adela played at <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<scene wordnetid="108645963" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<venue wordnetid="108677628" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/169321.xml">
Carnegie Hall</link></venue>
</geographical_area>
</scene>
</tract>
</location>
</area>
</landmark>
</point>
</position>
</region>
</site>
. </p>
<p>

The two reunited and married in 1946. After the wedding, Cesar and Adela Gonzmart performed and traveled the country together, but in 1949, their first son, "Casey" arrived. It was difficult to be a family raising a child while staying in hotels, cooking on hotplates, and being on the road. In 1953, Adela's ailing father convinced his son-in-law to learn the restaurant business and settle down with the family. Cesar started working with Casmiro Hernandez, Jr. at the Columbia for $150 per week, one tenth of what he had been earning. Cesar accepted the reduction in income gracefully, knowing that their family life would be much better. The following year, their second son Richard was born. Although he traded his career as a musician for one as a restaurateur, Cesar Gonzmart regularly serenaded his guests. </p>
<p>

Cesar learned the business quickly, and he and Adela began to have input in the decisions of the Columbia. In 1956, they convinced Casmiro to build another large room, the <it><region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/15743631.xml">
Siboney</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</it> dining room, named after a town in Cuba where American forces landed in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/28265.xml">
Spanish-American War</link> (also the name of a song by a Cuban composer). They also supported the opening of a second restaurant in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/109756.xml">
Sarasota</link></village>
 in 1959, which did very well.   </p>
<p>

During the 1950’s &amp; 1960’s, Tampa’s Ybor City again experienced economic decline. Many of the cigar factories, which once numbered 200, closed, but the Columbia again remained open. During that span of time, some of the world’s greatest Latin music and dancing talent performed at the Columbia, many of whom were friends of Adela and Cesar from back when they were performing on tour. When Adela's father died in 1961, Cesar and Adela were faced with the same kind of debts that her father did when her grandfather died. Eventually, the economy improved and the debts were paid, but almost 25 years passed before the next expansion occurred.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fourth Generation</st>
<p>

Cesar Gonzmart’s son Richard turned down a <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/241128.xml">
Michigan State University</link></university>
 football scholarship and a likely professional football career to follow in his father's footsteps. His father responded by sending Richard to Spain with an American Express card and instructions "to learn the restaurant business by eating out every night." Richard earned degrees from the University of Madrid and the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/538882.xml">
University of Denver</link></ranking>
</university>
 and served as President and CEO of Columbia Restaurant Group. His brother Casey pursued culinary studies in Europe, apprenticing at several restaurants in Paris and in Geneva &amp; Lucerne, Switzerland. Casey also studied Spanish cuisine at the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/2594971.xml">
University of Madrid</link></group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
 and heads recipe development, food production and staff training.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Richard &amp; Casey Gonzmart joined the day-to-day management of the Columbia in the late 1970s.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="StAugFLSept07ColumbiaHypolita.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Columbia Restaurant in St. Augustine, Florida, 2007
</caption>
</image>

Cesar and Adela waited until their sons were educated and married before embarking on an aggressive plan of growth. With Richard and Casey capable of managing restaurants by themselves, they successfully opened units in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/109790.xml">
St. Augustine</link></village>
 (1983), <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/84504.xml">
St. Petersburg</link></village>
 (1988) and <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/109665.xml">
Clearwater</link></village>
 (1989).  </p>
<p>

When Cesar died in 1992, the Columbia Restaurant Group was financially sound. The year Gonzmart left the music business, the Columbia grossed $1 million. In 1991, just before his death, the chain earned $42 million.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> A restaurant in <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/37398.xml">
Disney's</link></company>
 <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/37395.xml">
Celebration</link></village>
 community was opened in 1997 and is doing well. A unit in West Palm Beach opened in 2005, but closed in April, 2008 after sales failed to meet the expectations of Columbia management and company executives had differences with the property managers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fifth Generation</st>
<p>

Adela Hernandez Gonzmart died in 2001, ending the third generation of ownership, but between 1996 and 2007, three of her grandchildren joined the Company full-time, with more to follow...</p>
<p>

A brand new, 5000+ ft² kitchen was built in 2001 at the Ybor City location. Florida's oldest restaurant was given the most modern, state-of-the-art kitchen available. The facility was constructed on space used for a parking lot/delivery area on the south side of the restaurant to avoid disuption of operations.</p>
<p>

The first new dining rooms built at the Ybor City Columbia since 1956 were completed in 2004 in the space that housed the old kitchen. The <it>Familia de Casimiro</it> was named in honor of Richard &amp; Casey’s great-grandfather (founder of the restaurant) and is designed to resemble a Spanish wine cellar, with space for private meetings. The <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/2736.xml">
Andalucia</link></it> was named for the most populous and the second largest community of Spain.</p>
<p>

Both these projects were part of a $6.5 million renovation to prepare the restaurant for its Centennial in 2005. Other completed projects included state-of-the-art restrooms for men &amp; women (with sensor-controlled fixtures), refurbishing the existing dining rooms, new wine cellars (to house their inventory of more than 50,000 bottles), and a new, energy-efficient air conditioning system.</p>
<p>

The Sarasota restaurant will celebrate 50 years at that location in 2009, while the St. Augustine location has been in operation for 25 years in 2008.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Menus</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Food</st>
<p>

The menu is quite extensive; these are some of their signature items.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/31359.xml">
Tapas</link></st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Shrimp and Crabmeat Alcachofas - Baked casserole of shrimp, crabmeat and artichoke hearts topped with grated Romano cheese. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Calamares Fritos "a la Romana" - Tender calamari seasoned and lightly fried. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Queso Fundido - Spanish <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/5117212.xml">
Tetilla cheese</link></commodity>
</merchandise>
</artifact>
 baked in Rioja tomato sauce with toasted Cuban bread. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cakes de Cangrejo - Blue crab meat "cakes" served with passion-fruit aioli sauce. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mejiliones y Chorizo - Fresh Prince Edward Island mussels and sliced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/335617.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Spanish+chorizo%22])">
Chorizo</link>, sauteéd and simmered with extra virgin olive oil, onions, celery, tomato, basil, spinach and garlic splashed with dry white wine and lemon.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Empanadas de Picadillo - Spiced ground beef filled pastry turnovers with roasted corn and black bean salsa.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Soups</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Spanish Bean Soup - Garbanzo beans simmered with smoked ham, chorizo sausage and potatoes in a delicious broth of chicken and ham. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Caldo Gallego - Great Northern beans simmered in a rich stock with smoked ham, chorizo sausage, turnip greens and potatoes. </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Salads</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Columbia's Original 1905 SaladTM - Crisp iceberg lettuce with julienne of baked ham, natural Swiss cheese, tomato, olives, grated Romano cheese and a "famous" garlic dressing. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Beefsteak Tomato Salad - Thick sliced beefsteak tomatoes, topped with sliced red onions, and crumbled Spanish <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/223827.xml">
Cabrales cheese</link>. Served with extra virgin olive oil and Sherry wine vinegar.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Entrées</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/47630.xml">
Paella</link> "A la Valencia" - Clams, mussels, shrimp, scallops, calamares, chicken and pork, baked with Valencia rice, extra virgin olive oil, green peppers, Spanish onions, ripe tomatoes, garlic, spices and splashed with white wine. "Marinera" includes seafood only; "Campesina" includes beef tenderloin, pork, chicken, chorizo and green beans.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Snapper "Alicante" - Snapper, baked in a casserole with sweet Spanish onions, green peppers, a rich gravy, olive oil, fresh garlic, sauterne wine and topped with sliced roasted almonds. Served with yellow rice and garnished with fried eggplant and Shrimp Supreme. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Arroz con Pollo "Valenciana" - ¼ bone-in chicken sauteéd with extra virgin olive oil and green peppers, Spanish onions, tomato, garlic, herbs and baked in casserole with Valencia rice then splashed with Adelita Chardonnay wine and topped with green peas and red pimientos.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Boliche "Criollo" - Roasted Eye round of beef stuffed with chorizo and roasted in flavorful gravy. Served with black beans, white rice and platanos. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Roast Pork "A La Cubana" - Slices of roast pork with a delicious marinade. Served with black beans, white rice, yuca and platanos.    </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Desserts</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Flan - Spanish caramel egg custard. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Crema Catalana - Spanish cream topped with crystallized caramel. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Brazo Gitano "Cien Años" - Spongecake soaked in syrup with Spanish Manzanilla Sherry filled with Spanish cream and strawberries, rolled and topped with meringue. Served tableside with strawberry sauce and flambéed.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Wine</st>
<p>

Any menu featuring Cuban and Spanish cuisine requires a substantive wine list, and the Columbia received <it>Wine Spectator</it> magazine's "Best of Award of Excellence", acknowledging their outstanding collection of Spanish wines (more than 750 wines with an inventory exceeding 50,000 bottles).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> The Columbia also won <it>Wine Enthusiast</it> magazine's "Award of Ultimate Distinction".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

The Columbia also created a line of private label wines to honor the  memory of their family members. The Don Cesar® Crianza, in particular, is very popular among guests. Popular among tourists is the Columbia <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/263860.xml">
Sangria</link>, which is mixed tableside.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Activities</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Flamenco Dancing</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/11558.xml">
flamenco</link>, one of Spain's traditional dances, consists of rhythmic steps performed on a hardwood floor, and originated with Spanish Gypsies. It has evolved through the years to the more structured form we have become familiar with. Classical Spanish dances consist of ballet moves in colorful Spanish costumes accompanied by the sound of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/8630375.xml">
castanets</link>. The Columbia Restaurant Dance Troupe began performing at the Columbia Restaurant in 1985. Shows lasting 45-minutes are performed twice nightly except Sunday: 7:00pm and 9:30pm. There is a nominal cover charge per person for the show. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Community Harvest</st>
<p>

Over 90 nonprofit organizations received more than $122,000 from the Columbia Restaurant’s 11th Annual Community Harvest campaign, held annually in the month of September. The chain donates 5% of all guests’ lunch and dinner checks and allows patrons to designate the charitable organizations their choice. Over the past 10 years, the event has generated more than $820,000 to nonprofits throughout Florida. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Cesar Gonzmart Memorial Golf Tournament</st>
<p>

The CGMGT was begun in 1998 by Columbia Restaurant owners Richard and Casey Gonzmart in memory of their father. Proceeds from the event are donated to a local charity or non-profit organization. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The 7th Annual CGMGT and the Sant 'Yago Education Foundation gave $5,000 to support the American Heart Association's American Heart Heroes Week project, an initiative that provides camp experiences for children with cardiovascular disease.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The 8th Annual CGMGT raised over $55,000 for Moffitt Cancer &amp; Research Institute, the University of South Florida Athletic Association, and the Adela &amp; Cesar Gonzmart Endowed Memorial Scholarship, part of the USF Latino Scholarship Program.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The 13th Annual CGMGT raised over $50,000 for the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../046/3649046.xml">
University of South Florida</link></university>
 in Tampa. The University of South Florida Athletic Association and the Columbia Restaurant Centenario Endowed Scholarship, part of the USF Latino Scholarship Program.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
1905 Day</st>
<p>

On a Sunday in mid-September every year since the restaurant's 75th anniversary in 1980, they celebrate <b>1905 Day</b>. On that day, a special menu with the prices of yesteryear are in effect from noon to 7:00pm, reservations are not accepted, and take-out items are not available.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> Menu items have included:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Chicken &amp; Yellow Rice “Ybor” for $2.95 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Boliche (eye round of beef) for $2.95</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Merluza “Russian Style” for $2.95 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Columbia’s Original “1905 Salad” for $1.95</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sangria for 95¢ </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Flan for 50¢  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Coffee for 5¢</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

According to Richard Gonzmart, President of the Columbia Restaurant Group, "<it>1905 Day</it> is our way of thanking all of our customers who have contributed to the success of the Columbia for over 100 years and five generations of ownership. We are convinced that we would not be celebrating our 102nd anniversary without the support of the communities we serve." </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Celebrity watching</st>
<p>

Throughout its 100+ year history, the Columbia has been frequented by well known politicians, athletes and entertainers. To name a few: <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/5119376.xml">
John F. Kennedy</link></person>
</president>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/4173.xml">
Babe Ruth</link></person>
, <player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/63493.xml">
Ken Griffey, Jr.</link></player>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.8">
<contestant wordnetid="109613191" confidence="0.8">
<ballplayer wordnetid="109835506" confidence="0.8">
<shortstop wordnetid="110592986" confidence="0.8">
<infielder wordnetid="110205457" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<fielder wordnetid="110086568" confidence="0.8">
<athlete wordnetid="109820263" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/605895.xml">
Barry Larkin</link></athlete>
</fielder>
</causal_agent>
</infielder>
</shortstop>
</ballplayer>
</contestant>
</player>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<pianist wordnetid="110430665" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/179572.xml">
Liberace</link></pianist>
</artist>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/420438.xml">
Steven Tyler</link> (<musical_organization wordnetid="108246613" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/149216.xml">
Aerosmith</link></group>
</musical_organization>
), <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<traveler wordnetid="109629752" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<singer wordnetid="110599806" confidence="0.8">
<musician wordnetid="110340312" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<exile wordnetid="110071332" confidence="0.8">
<absentee wordnetid="109757653" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/548242.xml">
Brian Johnson</link></entertainer>
</absentee>
</exile>
</causal_agent>
</musician>
</singer>
</performer>
</traveler>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 (<musical_organization wordnetid="108246613" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/149225.xml">
AC/DC</link></group>
</musical_organization>
), <boxer wordnetid="109870208" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/148021.xml">
Jack Dempsey</link></boxer>
, <boxer wordnetid="109870208" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/154971.xml">
Rocky Marciano</link></boxer>
, <boxer wordnetid="109870208" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/158538.xml">
Evander Holyfield</link></boxer>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<playmate wordnetid="110441037" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/19318.xml">
Marilyn Monroe</link></playmate>
</actor>
</person>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/446518.xml">
Bo Derek</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/59216.xml">
Liza Minnelli</link>, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/158889.xml">
George Clooney</link></actor>
</person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<director wordnetid="110014939" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/26954.xml">
Stephen King</link></writer>
</director>
</person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<presenter wordnetid="110466387" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/532872.xml">
Bryant Gumbel</link></presenter>
</person>
, <actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/18984642.xml">
Brooke Shields</link></actor>
, <celebrity wordnetid="109903153" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<journalist wordnetid="110224578" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<observer wordnetid="110369528" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/253662.xml">
Andy Rooney</link></observer>
</journalist>
</celebrity>
 and <actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/855178.xml">
Lauren Hutton</link></actor>
.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Columbia Shop</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Cookbook</st>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/2620958.xml">
Ferdie Pacheco</link></doctor>
</person>
, the artist, author, television commentator and former fight doctor for Muhammad Ali,  waited tables Cesar at the Columbia when he was 14. Pacheco maintained his friendship with Cesar and his family over the years, and co-authored a 178-recipe cookbook with Adela Gonzmart entitled, <it>The Columbia Restaurant Spanish Cookbook</it>, released in November, 1995.
</p>
</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Cigars</st>
<p>

Several varieties of hand-rolled cigars are available, all made locally in Ybor City.
</p>
</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Gifts/Food</st>
<p>

The shop sells most of the dressings, oils, seasonings, etc. used in the restaurant kitchen, as well as decorative ceramic serving pieces, music, hats, T-shirts, trinkets, gift baskets and gift cards.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.flheritage.com/services/sites/floridians/?section=t#Tampa">
Florida Heritage website: Great Floridians 2000 Program-Cesar Gonzmart</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.visavismag.com/content/view/307/78/">
Tampa's Spanish Restaurant</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.travel-watch.com/columbia.htm">
Travel Watch: Columbia Restaurant by Nick Anis</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://richardservis.tripod.com/thecarefreetravelermagazine/id11.html">
The Carefree Traveler Magazine: 6th Feature Article-Cesar Gonzmart and the Columbia Restaurant by Richard L. Servis Jr.</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m3190/is_n1_v27/ai_13308498/pg_2?tag=artBody;col1">
Nation's Restaurant News: January 4, 1993- Columbia's Gonzmart dies at 72 by Jack Hayes</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://richardservis.tripod.com/thecarefreetravelermagazine/id11.html">
The Carefree Traveler Magazine: 6th Feature Article-Cesar Gonzmart and the Columbia Restaurant by Richard L. Servis Jr.</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bizjournals.com/tampabay/stories/2008/04/21/daily9.html">
Tampa Bay Business Journal: April 21, 2008-Columbia Restaurant closes in West Palm Beach by Janet Leiser</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.winespectator.com/Wine/Dining/Restaurant_Awards/Restaurant_Profile/0,1246,353,00.html">
Wine Spectator Online: Columbia Restaurant, Tampa Florida</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.winemag.com/ME2/dirmod.asp?sid=A3025A36942D43C9A78C6A0CDBC41F4F&amp;nm=Award+Winning+Restaurants&amp;type=ESpotlight&amp;mod=Directories%3A%3ARestaurants&amp;mid=7E4C8360C6054ABEA3F48843326B7A25&amp;tier=2&amp;Keywords=&amp;Tier1=&amp;Tier2=Tampa&amp;Tier3=FL&amp;Tier4=Award%20of%20Ultimate%20Distinction&amp;Tier5=&amp;MultiList=">
 Wine Enthusiast Magazine: America’s Best Wine-Driven
Restaurants of 2007-Columbia Restaurant</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alzheimerresourcecenter.org/Columbia%20Restaurant.html">
Alzheimer Resource Center of Orlando website: 11th Annual Columbia Restaurant Community Harvest</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bizjournals.com/tampabay/stories/2007/10/08/daily36.html">
Tampa Bay Business Journal: October 10, 2007-Restaurant chain cooks up donations by Larry Halstead</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m3190/is_40_35/ai_78902482?tag=rel.res4">
 Nation's Restaurant News: October 1, 2001-Columbia Restaurant helps boost Heart Heroes Week</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tampachamber.com/files/insideview-sepoct2003.pdf">
Tampa Chamber of Commerce/Inside View: Setptmeber/October 2003-The Cesar Gonzmart 8th Annual Memorial Golf Tournament</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://celebrationtowncenter.com/ee/images/uploads/dining/ColumbiaPress1.pdf">
Celebration Town Center: June 18, 2007-Press Release</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.columbiarestaurant.com/">
Columbia Restaurant website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.travel-watch.com/columbia.htm">
Travel Watch review: Ybor City’s World Famous Columbia Restaurant</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.usf.edu/gonzmart/docs/columbia_collection.htm">
University of South Florida Libraries: The Columbia Restaurant &amp; Gonzmart Family Collection</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</company>
</landmark>
</article>
