<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:51:47[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<know-how  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105616786">
<method  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105660268">
<header>
<title>Pre-boot authentication</title>
<id>16789191</id>
<revision>
<id>235070425</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-29T21:46:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>The Anomebot2</username>
<id>1979668</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computer security</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Authentication methods</category>
<category>All articles to be expanded</category>
<category>Articles to be expanded since April 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Pre-boot_authentication&amp;action=edit">
improve this article or section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(April 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>Pre-Boot Authentication</b> (PBA) serves as an extension of the <generic wordnetid="107899976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/Form_4473.xml">
BIOS</link></generic>
 or boot firmware and guarantees a secure, tamper-proof environment external to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> as a trusted authentication layer. The PBA prevents anything being read from the hard disk such as the operating system until the user has confirmed he/she has the correct password or other credentials.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Benefits of Pre-Boot Authentication</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/7066791.xml">
full disk encryption</link> outside of the operating system level <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> of temporary files</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
data-at-rest</link> protection</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
How Pre-Boot Authentication Works</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Generic Boot Sequence</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Basic Input Output System</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Master Boot Record Partition Table</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pre-Boot Authentication</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Operating System Boots</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A PBA environment serves as an extension of the BIOS or boot firmware and guarantee a secure, tamper-proof environment external to the operating system as a trusted authentication layer. The PBA prevents Windows or any other operating system from loading until the user has confirmed he/she has the correct password to unlock the door. That trusted layer eliminates the possibility that one of the millions of lines of OS code can compromise the privacy of personal or company data.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Misnomer</st>
<p>

Sometimes pre-Boot Authentication is a misnomer since a basic OS can be loaded prior to the main operating system in some implementations. Pre-boot authentication can take on a number of forms, it can be a start up (BIOS) password implemented on the Motherboard, or in on the boot volume itself.  In the latter instance the boot sector of a hard drive is overwritten with a small executable which starts the decryption of the drive and hands off the credientals to Windows to continue booting.  While, the Truecrypt<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> is an full disk encryption system it is also pre-boot authentication since you need to enter a password for the drive to boot.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Pre-Boot Authentication Technologies</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Combinations with Full Disk Encryption</st>
<p>

Pre-Boot Authentication is generally provided by a variety of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/7066791.xml">
full disk encryption</link> vendors, but can be installed separately. Some FDE solutions can function without Pre-Boot Authentication, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/16789051.xml">
hardware-based full disk encryption</link>. However, without some form of authentication, encryption provides little protection.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Linux-based Pre-Boot Authentication</st>
<p>

Linux uses a well-known and proven UNIX-based security model. The enormous pool of developer talent is linked to this subject as a large number of individuals with different desires for an environment are pushing and pulling for the most extensible environment possible. The has made Linux remarkably flexible, with the ability to configure a Linux kernel to easily suit individuals needs.  This was key reason that the NSA used Linux as the basis for creating a secure operating system. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

As an open source solution, there are a great variety of developers seeking to use Linux for a variety of purposes, and that means a large amount of driver development often available for free. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/59957.xml">
Smartcard</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/290622.xml">
biometric</link> vendors can have their devices ported to Linux at no cost to themselves. That means greater compatibility and flexibility for future development. In addition, Linux is well-known for playing nice with installed OSes and BIOS, as well as being widely accepted worldwide by both large and small entities.</p>
<p>

There are at least five common CPU architectures, and Linux runs on all of them. Proprietary OSes have advantages, but are limited to those architectures they are actually designed for. By virtue of the fact that its developers have wide-ranging interests and use cases, Linux has been developed to be completely portable to any widely distributed CPU architecture. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

The number of potential conflicts from various security vendors providing their own proprietary operating systems and methodology can interfere with each other and the main Operating System, mean a chaotic mess of race conditions. BIOS incompatibilities, and bootstrap failures.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Authentication Methods</st>
<p>

The standard complement of authentication methods exist for Pre-Boot Authentication including:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Something you know (i.e. username / password)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Something you have (i.e. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/59957.xml">
smart card</link> or other token)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Something you are (i.e. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/290622.xml">
biometric</link> data)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
&amp;gt;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://secude.com/htm/707/en/Pre-Boot_Authentication.htm">
Pre-Boot Authentication</weblink>", <link>
Secude</link>&#32;(February 21, 2008).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-22</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
http://truecrypt.org</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nsa.gov/selinux">
NSA &amp; Linux OS</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://kroah.com/log/2007/01/29/">
linux kernel monkey log</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</method>
</know-how>
</article>
