<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:48:20[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<application  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="106570110">
<header>
<title>Pedestrian detection</title>
<id>16808633</id>
<revision>
<id>238351597</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-14T12:53:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>KYN</username>
<id>505011</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Applications of computer vision</category>
<category>Surveillance</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Pedestrian detection</b> is an essential and significant task in any intelligent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/87179.xml">
video surveillance</link> system, as it provides the fundamental information for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantic</link> understanding of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/32441.xml">
video</link> footages.
<sec>
<st>
Challenges for pedestrian detection </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Various style of clothing in appearance</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Different possible articulations</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The presence of occluding accessories</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frequent occlusion between pedestrians</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Existing Approaches </st>

<p>

Despite the challenges, pedestrian detection still remains an active research area in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/6596.xml">
computer vision</link> in recent years. Numerous approaches have been proposed. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Holistic Detection</st>
<p>

Detectors are trained to search for pedestrians in the video frame by scanning the whole frame. The detector would “fire” if the image features inside the local search window meet certain criteria. Some methods employ global features such as edge template 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, others uses local features like histogram of oriented gradient descriptors <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/14644226.xml">
Histogram of oriented gradients</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. The drawback of this approach is that, the performance can be easily affected by background clutter and occlusions.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Part-based Detection</st>
<p>

Pedestrians are modeled as collections of parts. Part hypotheses are firstly generated by learning local features, which includes edgelet features<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> the orientation features <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>, and etc. These part hypotheses are then joined to form the best assembly of existing pedestrian hypotheses. Though this approach is attractive, part detection itself is a difficult task.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Patch-based Detection</st>
<p>

Recently Bastian et al. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> proposed an approach combining both the detection and segmentation with the name Implicit Shape Model (ISM). A codebook of local appearance is learned during the training process. In the detecting process, extracted local features are used to match against the codebook entries, and each match casts one vote for the pedestrian hypotheses. Final detection results can be obtained by further refining those hypotheses. The advantage of this approach is only a small number of training images are required.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 N. Dalai, B. Triggs, I. Rhone-Alps, and F. Montbonnot. “Histograms of oriented gradients for human detection”, <it>IEEE Computer Society Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</it> (CVPR), page 1:886-893, 2005 </entry>
<entry id="2">
 C. Papageorgiou and T. Poggio, “A Trainable Pedestrian Detection system”, <it>International Journal of Computer Vision</it> (IJCV), page 1:15-33,2000 </entry>
<entry id="3">
Bo Wu and Ram Nevatia, “Detection of Multiple, Partially Occluded Humans in a Single Image by Bayesian Combination of Edgelet Part Detectors”, <it>IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision</it> (ICCV), pages 1:90-97, 2005</entry>
<entry id="4">
 Mikolajczyk, K. and Schmid, C. and Zisserman, A. “Human detection based on a probabilistic assembly of robust part detectors”, <it>The European Conference on Computer Vision</it> (ECCV), volume 3021/2004, pages 69-82, 2005 </entry>
<entry id="5">
 B.Leibe, E. Seemann, and B. Schiele. “Pedestrian detection in crowded scenes” <it>IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</it>(CVPR), pages 1:878-885, 2005</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</application>
</article>
