<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:41:28[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<senior_high_school  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108409617">
<educational_institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276342">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>University of the Philippines, Visayas - Cebu High School</title>
<id>16806607</id>
<revision>
<id>241109349</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-26T12:06:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>High schools in the Philippines</category>
<category>Educational institutions established in 1918</category>
<category> University of the Philippines, Visayas</category>
<category>Cebu</category>
<category>University of the Philippines</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>University of the Philippines, Visayas - Cebu High School</b> is one of the two high schools operated by the University of the Philippines (UP) in the Visayas, one of the UP System's autonomous universities.<p>

Also known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/16806607.xml">
UP High School Cebu</link>, the school is the only one in the Visayas that admits only grade school graduates from the lowest-income bracket.  The high school is one of the programs offered by the Professional Education Division of <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/5962340.xml">
University of the Philippines, Visayas - Cebu College</link></university>
.</p>
<p>

UPV Cebu High School is located in Gorordo Avenue, Lahug, Cebu City, Philippines.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

UP Cebu College was established on May 3, 1918 after the Board of Regents of the University of the Philippines approved the formal petition for a branch of UP in Cebu. It was then known as the Junior College of Liberal Arts.  Three years later, the Junior College of Liberal Arts became a separate unit of the University and was renamed the Junior College of the UP.</p>
<p>

World War II brought about the closure of the College. It reopened in 1947 with only 56 students: 20 were enrolled in the third year and 36 in the fourth year. During the graduation exercises for the school year 1949-1950, 17 graduates received their high school diplomas.</p>
<p>

The College had to close for the second time when its appropriation was omitted from the 1950-51 Appropriations Act.</p>
<p>

Although the College reopened in 1963, it was only on May 31, 1972 that the Board of Regents authorized the establishment of a high school at the University of the Philippines in Cebu.  This high school was intended as a feeder for the College and as a laboratory for the graduate students. Nine teachers and a guidance counselor composed the high school staff. There were only 151 first and second year students.</p>
<p>

On January 1, 1986, UP Cebu College, UP Iloilo College, and UP Tacloban College, officially became part of the UP in the Visayas, an autonomous unit within the UP System.</p>
<p>

On January 10, 1989, the UP Board of Regents adopted the policy of democratized admission for students in the high schools of the UP in the Visayas (Cebu and Iloilo). Under this concept, the high schools of the UPV offer a program to help economically disadvantaged but intellectually deserving students gain access to tertiary-level education, especially within the UP System.  UP High School Cebu then followed the Enriched General Curriculum.</p>
<p>

From June, 2002, until the present, UPV Cebu High School has been following the same Special Science Curriculum as that followed by the UPV Iloilo High School.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mandate to Democratized Access to Education</st>

<p>

In the late 1980s, UPV Cebu High School was under threat of closure due to budget issues.  To avert this threat, the school adopted a policy of democratized admission for students in the high schools of the UP System.  This was initially implemented in during the school year 1989-90 and was fully implemented during the school year 1990-91.</p>
<p>

Under this concept, "every high school in UP is a program for helping economically disadvantaged but deserving students gain access to tertiary level education in UP."  Pursuant to this policy, UPV Cebu High School admits first year students from low-income families. As such, the high school is an experimental laboratory for innovative teaching strategies designed to better prepare these deserving students for access to tertiary education, particularly in the UP System where they can avail of subsidized education through the socialized tuition program.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Admission Requirements</st>
<p>

Incoming first year students from both public and private elementary schools may be admitted into UPV Cebu High School, provided they meet the following requirements:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 must be an elementary school graduate by March 2008;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 must not have previously studied in another high school;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 must have an average grade of 85% or better in Math, Science, English/Reading, Civics/Social Studies, and Filipino subjects at the time of filing of application;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 must have a conduct grade of B or its equivalent; and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 must come from a family whose gross annual income is 150,000 pesos or less.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Curriculum</st>
<p>

The school follows a special science curriculum simultaneously with the <link>
University of the Visayas Laboratory High School</link>.  The curriculum's strength lies in mathematics and the sciences, as well as in research.</p>
<p>

UPV Cebu High School students excel in academics not just through subject content exposure within the confines of the classrooms, but also through the co-curricular and extracurricular opportunities that the school offers to its students.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Campus Life</st>
<p>

Students are encouraged to participate in various curriculum-oriented and extracurricular student organizations.  One of the hallmarks of an education in the University of the Philippines is that most of the learning happens not inside the classroom—but outside of it, through student organizations.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Interest Clubs</st>

<p>

The following student organizations are actively operating:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Stargazers Society (a junior astronomical society)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Science Club (a student organization of science and technology enthusiasts)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Speakers Club (a training club for students who wish to improve their oral communication skills)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Netizens.org (a club of computer enthusiasts)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Glee Club (club for students with skills and abilities in singing and music)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dance Troupe</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 UP Students Theater Arts Guild for Education [UPSTAGE] (a club for students with interest in theater and acting)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Campus Ministry Student Core Group (a group of volunteers that cater to spirituality needs of students)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Youth for Christ (a religious organization)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Student Council</st>

<p>

The Student Council is the highest governing body of the student population.  The officials in the Council are elected by the students themselves.  The following are the elective positions in the Council:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 President</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Vice-President</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Internal Secretary</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 External Secretary</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Treasurer</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Auditor</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Year-level Representatives (one for each year level)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
School Paper</st>

<p>

The official school paper of the high school is the <it>UP Tambuli</it>.  It aims to serve as the watchdog of the the students' rights and the voice of the students through the school paper.  The school paper also aims to serve as a laboratory for the development its staff members' writing and journalistic skills. Any bona fide UPV Cebu High School student is qualified to join as writer of the <it>UP Tambuli</it>.  Students who wish to be admitted to the <it>UP Tambuli</it> undergo a written examination that will test their journalistic skills.   The screening is supervised by the faculty adviser.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Facilities</st>

<p>

UPV Cebu High School has the following facilities for use by its students, faculty, and alumni:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 classrooms</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Learning Enhancement and Development Extension Room (LEADER) &mdash; an audiovisual room and mini-library with the following equipment and materials:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 platform</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 LCD projector screen</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 DVD/VCD player</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 television set</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 karaoke machine with microphones</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 book and magazine collection (mostly donated from private foundations, institutions, and alumni)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 bound theses of graduating high school seniors</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 reading area</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 LEADER.net &mdash; a computer laboratory consisting of a server computer and about 25 workstations; software licenses and computer units are donations from government agencies and private foundations</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 home technology rooms</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 faculty room and Principal's Office</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 open stage</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 open court</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 covered court</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 physics and biology laboratories</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 PTA Office</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Athletics Office</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Guidance Office</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 student canteen</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uphighschoolcebu.edu.ph">
Official Website of UPV Cebu High School</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.upv.edu.ph">
Official Website of University of the Philippines in the Visayas</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>

|-<p>

| style="padding:2px;"|</p>
<p>

<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible expanded " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#800000;color:#fff;height:3em;text-align:center;padding-top:1em;border:1px solid #cccccc;" class="navbox-title">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/10747534.xml">
University of the Philippines, Visayas</link></university>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";background:#006500;color:#fff;height:1.5em;font-size:95%;text-align:center;border:1px solid #cccccc;" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/534536.xml">
<b>Miagao, Iloilo</b></link> &nbsp;·  &nbsp;<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/1356946.xml">
<b>Iloilo City, Iloilo</b></link></village>
 &nbsp;·  &nbsp;<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/285868.xml">
<b>Cebu City, Cebu</b></link></village>
 &nbsp;·  &nbsp;<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/746499.xml">
<b>Tacloban City, Leyte</b></link></village>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#EEEEEE;text-align:center;;" class="navbox-group">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/10747534.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Degree-Granting+Units%22])">
Academics</link></university>
</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;background:#FFFFFF;text-align:left;border:1px solid #cccccc;font-size:90%;padding:0;line-height:130%;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
 <link>
Fisheries and Ocean Sciences</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
Arts and Sciences</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
Technology</link> <link>
Management</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
Iloilo High School</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/16806607.xml">
Cebu High School</link><university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/15909884.xml">
<b>UPV Tacloban College</b></link></university>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#EEEEEE;text-align:center;;" class="navbox-group">
Campus andResearch</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;background:#FFFFFF;text-align:left;border:1px solid #cccccc;font-size:90%;padding:0;line-height:130%;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link>
UPV Iloilo Library</link>&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/10747534.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22History%22])">
UPV History</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <link>
UPV-NIMBB (<it>BIOTECH-UPV</it>)</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
Taklong Island National Marine Reserve (<it>TINMAR</it>)</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#EEEEEE;text-align:center;;" class="navbox-group">
Life</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;background:#FFFFFF;text-align:left;border:1px solid #cccccc;font-size:90%;padding:0;line-height:130%;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<radio_station wordnetid="104044119" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/9241917.xml">
DYUP (FM)</link></radio_station>
&nbsp;·  <radio_station wordnetid="104044119" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/10006402.xml">
DYUP (AM)</link></radio_station>
</col>
</row>
</table>

|}</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>





</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</educational_institution>
</senior_high_school>
</article>
