<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:48:25[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<work  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100575741">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108435388">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<undertaking  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100795720">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<network  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108434259">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>CATER Project</title>
<id>16811045</id>
<revision>
<id>215614877</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-28T23:27:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>The Anomebot2</username>
<id>1979668</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from April 2008</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>European research networks</category>
<category>European Commission projects</category>
<category>FP6 Projects</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

 
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is written like .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=CATER_Project&amp;action=edit">
rewrite this article</weblink> from a . For <b>blatant</b> advertising that would require a fundamental rewrite to become encyclopedic, use  to mark for .&nbsp;<it>(April 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>CATER</b> is a 3-year collaborative research project launched in September 2006 and supported by the <control wordnetid="105196375" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="105196582" confidence="0.8">
<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/9974.xml">
European Commission</link></power>
</authority>
</control>
 under the Sixth Framework Programme (DG Information Society and Media). In this context, CATER is a Specific Targeted Research Projects (STReP) coordinated by Fraunhofer IAO and focusing on developing tools and methods for <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<scheme wordnetid="105905348" confidence="0.8">
<plan wordnetid="105898568" confidence="0.8">
<plan_of_action wordnetid="105902545" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/242604.xml">
 mass customization</link></plan_of_action>
</plan>
</scheme>
</idea>
 in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/13673345.xml">
automotive</link> field.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<row>

<header>
Project Fact Sheet</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Acronym</col>
<col>
CATER</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Full name</col>
<col>
Computerized Automotive Technology Reconfiguration System for Mass Customization</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Website</col>
<col>
www.cater-ist.org</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Instrument</col>
<col>
STREP</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Strategic Objective</col>
<col>
2.5.8 ICT for Networked Businesses objective of the IST priority</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Cost</col>
<col>
5,618 M. EURO</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Start date</col>
<col>
September 1, 2006</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Duration</col>
<col>
36 months</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Objectives of the CATER project </st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="CATER_Logo.jpg">
</image>
</p>
<p>

CATER introduces systems and methodologies that go beyond the traditional approaches of automotive OEMs and in which design is driven by cross-cultural and emotional aspects of customer needs. This is enabled through integration of innovative ideas from diverse expertise of both Europe and Asia. In this way, CATER aims to facilitate business in the automotive industry, by bridging well-known gaps in the automotive ICT world of today, as well as gaps between Europe and Asia by integrating workable approaches from both regions</p>
<p>

CATER also advocates networked business in the automotive field, aiming at a better integration of stakeholders (from OEMs to customers) within the supply chain, to support product planners and designers; while the customers can design their own vehicle via a VR interface in a 3D Web environment.</p>
<p>

To reach its objective of enhancing mass customization of vehicles, CATER develops several tools</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A semantic notation system, which will be used by the concurrent engineering team to address customers’ needs and wants. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A novel engineering methodology, called citarasa, which involves elicitation of customer expertise and feeling in vehicle purchase, and mapping these to vehicle design by concurrent engineering team.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A Do-it-Yourself Design (DIYD) system for vehicle design, which will include a customization database structure and functionality with exemplary product data for vehicle configuration and a web user interface for mass customization, to support the customer in vehicle configuration tasks, taking into account emotional and functional criteria. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A low-cost Virtual Reality interface for vehicle mass customization, allowing a high-quality stereoscopic view of the product and its components, to facilitate the sales process.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A retrieval “module” (MArk) to interface with automotive existing teardown database, enabling better product benchmark and development.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An inter-linked database structure and software architecture based on the above mentioned components, which will support the N-business paradigm, taking into account the needs of all stakeholders in automotive N-business processes, namely vehicle buyers, sales point, market departments, design engineers, manufacturers, logistic chain, part suppliers.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Cater_process.jpg">
<caption>

Cater process.jpg
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

A number of use cases will also be defined to establish the framework for the technical and usability verification, based on most frequent user demands (from the marketing departments of OEM’s) and needs and each of them will simulate the overall service chain from a customer demand to the satisfaction of the order.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 CATER expected benefits to the industry </st>

<p>

CATER benefits to the various stakeholders can be summarized as follows:</p>
<p>

<b>Benefits to the vehicle manufacturers</b></p>
<p>

CATER mass customization system is designed to support manufacturers in building vehicles that customers want, thereby leveraging the market potential of automotive companies. CATER planned developments include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A n-business model for global supply chain,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A semantic notation system, integrating stakeholders to the production process,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A citarasa engineering methodology for better understanding of customer needs, integrating affective and functional requirements, and mapping these to design parameters using data mining and axiomatic design principles,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 New tools &amp; methods for mass customisation: 3D do-it-yourself design within a partially immersive virtual environment, etc.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Benefits to customers</b></p>
<p>

CATER intends to enhance the end-users satisfaction by:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An easier configuration of vehicles through VR interfaces,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Vehicles personalised to customers citarasa need,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Better designed vehicles.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Benefits to OEMs and component suppliers</b></p>
<p>

CATER supports OEMs &amp; component suppliers through:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Early involvement in the product development process through integrated databases of the n-business supply chain,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A unified semantic e-database, enabling a better perception of the market,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A retrieval “module” (MArk) to interface with automotive existing teardown database to enable better product benchmark and develoment.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Partnership </st>
<p>

CATER includes in its partnership a consortium of 14 major European and Asian organisations in the field ranging from vehicle manufacturers (<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/32412.xml">
Volvo</link></company>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../953/44953.xml">
Fiat</link>), OEMs (IC:IDO, Imartis) to research centres or universities (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/341284.xml">
Fraunhofer</link>, <link>
CERTH</link>, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/96631.xml">
University of Nottingham</link></university>
, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/82305.xml">
Nanyang Technological University</link></university>
, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/16788441.xml">
Universiti Malaysia Sarawak</link></university>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/2089384.xml">
University of Stuttgart</link></university>
, <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/427614.xml">
University of Basel</link></institution>
</group>
</educational_institution>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
 and <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/922692.xml">
University of Vaasa</link></university>
) and SMEs (Damai Sciences, Sigma Consultants).</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="CATER_Partnership.jpg">
<caption>

CATER Partnership.jpg
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 CATER Concepts </st>
<p>

<b>Customer needs and citarasa engineering</b> </p>
<p>

Citarasa is formed by the Malay words Cita, that denotes intent, hope, aspiration and expectation, and rasa, indicating taste and feel that is related to affect &amp; emotion. 
CATER developed a methodology for elicitation of customer expertise and citarasa in vehicle purchases, including an explicit method for mapping the customer citarasa to vehicle design for use by a concurrent engineering team. The citarasa database will be implemented online to support customer demand management as well as vehicle configuration tasks.</p>
<p>

<b>Networked solutions in the automotive sector</b> </p>
<p>

CATER will address the need for an inter-linked database structure and software architecture based on the above components, which supports the n-business paradigm, taking into account the needs of all stakeholders in the automotive n-business processes.</p>
<p>

<b>Semantic notation system</b> </p>
<p>

CATER will generate a common semantic notation description, which can be understood and used by the various experts in a concurrent engineering team, based on customers expression of needs. The semantic database in a sense is the "driver" and gelling agent of the various CATER databases.</p>
<p>

<b>Do-it-Yourself Design system for vehicle design</b> </p>
<p>

CATER will develop a web user interface for mass customization, powered by citarasa technology, to support the customer in vehicle configuration tasks, taking into account emotional and functional criteria. A low-cost Virtual Reality interface for vehicle mass customization will also be developed.</p>
<p>

<b>Automotive customisation and retrieval module (MArk)</b> </p>
<p>

CATER will develop a retrieval module (MArk) to interface with automotive existing teardown databases, enabling better product benchmark and development, to be used by vehicle designers, OEM manufacturers and their suppliers. The images in the retrieval system will be in multimedia format including 3D.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="VR_customer.jpg">
<caption>

VR customer.jpg
</caption>
</image>

<it>CATER Conceptual Car Configurator</it></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ve-forum.org/apps/pub.asp?Q=1944&amp;T=Clusters%20and%20Projects">
Computerized Automotive Technology Reconfiguration (CATER) System for Reverse Engineering and Mass Customization</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.researchsea.com/html/article.php/aid/1782/cid/2?PHPSESSID=92ae156683bf...">
Unimas (University Malaysia Sarawak) will collaborate with European and South-East Asian Partners to develop the Computerized Automative Technology Reconfiguration System for Mass Customization (CATER)</weblink></entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ve-forum.org/apps/pub.asp?Q=1271">
AITPL Cluster</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cordis.europa.eu/fetch?CALLER=PROJ_IST&amp;ACTION=D&amp;DOC=1&amp;CAT=PROJ&amp;QUERY=011929c4cea9:d89a:3c6e150d&amp;RCN=79402">
CATER Fact Sheet on Cordis</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cater-ist.org">
www.cater-ist.org</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</network>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</group>
</undertaking>
</event>
</system>
</work>
</article>
