<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:42:06[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<disorder  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="114052403">
<ailment  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="114055408">
<header>
<title>Chronic fatigue syndrome treatment</title>
<id>16823924</id>
<revision>
<id>237722278</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-11T15:00:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>WLU</username>
<id>2118749</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Neurological disorders</category>
<category>Ailments of unknown etiology</category>
<category>Immune system disorders</category>
<category>Syndromes</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Treatment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/50613.xml">
chronic fatigue syndrome</link></b> (CFS) is variable and uncertain, and the condition is primarily <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/16986993.xml">
managed</link> rather than cured.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Treatments include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/180121.xml">
medication</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/13311819.xml">
medical treatment</link>s and <link>
complementary  and alternative medicine</link>. A sytematic review has shown that CFS patients are less susceptible to placebo effects than predicted, and have a low placebo response compared to patients with other diseases.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> CFS is associated with chemical sensitivity,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> and some patients often  respond to a much lower dose of most medications when compared to other patients.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>
<sec>
<st>
Medical treatments</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Antidepressants</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
Antidepressant</link>s are often prescribed to CFS patients. Their purpose can be to treat secondary depression or mood swings, but low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/8126.xml">
dosage</link> tricyclic antidepressants are sometimes prescribed to improve sleep quality and reduce pain.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>. However, antidepressants often have <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../828/151828.xml">
side effect</link>s, some of which can increase CFS symptoms, and baseline metabolism differs between patients. Finding antidepressants, if any, that help the individual patient, is therefore a matter of trial and error.</p>
<p>

Overall, studies into the use of antidepressants in CFS have had mixed results. Some studies have shown a reduction in symptoms with antidepressant use, while others have shown no benefit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>



</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Autonomic nervous system stimulants</st>
<p>

Drugs such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/646618.xml">
atomoxetine</link> (Strattera®), which stimulate the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/166189.xml">
autonomic nervous system</link>, appear to have positive effects in some people with CFS symptoms. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/26th_century.xml">
Amphetamine</link>s and amphetamine analogs may help some patients. For example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/205878.xml">
methylphenidate</link> (Ritalin®) has been found to be significantly better than placebo in relieving fatigue and concentration disturbances in a minority of CFS patients but more research is needed into the long term effects.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/20690.xml">
Modafinil</link> (Provigil®), a medication designed to aid in maintaining wakefulness, has had some positive effect on individuals with CFS, but has not been properly studied. A small study suggested that long-term treatment with modafinil may not be beneficial for CFS patients.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hormones</st>
<p>

Various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/13311.xml">
hormone</link>s have been tried from time to time, including specifically <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/141922.xml">
steroids</link> (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/335380.xml">
cortisol</link>) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/30078.xml">
thyroid</link> hormones. Studies performed by Dr. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<medical_practitioner wordnetid="110305802" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<health_professional wordnetid="110165109" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/14088829.xml">
Jacob Teitelbaum</link></doctor>
</professional>
</writer>
</adult>
</health_professional>
</causal_agent>
</medical_practitioner>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 and by Dr. Kent Holtorf incorporating low-dose cortisol therapy have demonstrated positive results,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>. </p>
<p>

A review published in Endocr Rev. Apr. 2003 By Cleare A J compared two hydrocortisone trials, on CFS patients: the first, a placebo controlled trial carried out by McKenzie et al and published in JAMA Sep 1998, with CDC defined patients many comorbid with psychiatric diagnosis, trialled hydrocortisone at 20 to 30 mg at 0800 plus 5mg at 1400 daily for 3 months. There was a moderate but significant benefit on a global health scale, although not on other more specific measures of fatigue or disability. However, there was significant adrenal suppression (of natural function) in 12 of 33 patients on hydrocortisone. A second study published in Lancet. Feb 1999 by Cleare A J et al in a randomised cross-over trial on CDC patients without comorbid psychiatric conditions, used much lower doses of 5–10 mg, (for 28 days of  active treatment), chosen to represent a dose likely to replace the observed reduction of approximately 30% in 24-h UFC seen in previous studies. There was a clinically significant fall in fatigue scores in 34% on active treatment (28% returning to levels of fatigue at or below the population median score), compared with 13% (9%) on placebo. There were large reductions in self-rated disability scores in those whose fatigue improved. Furthermore, on this dose of hydrocortisone, there was no significant adrenal suppression, and there were no serious adverse effects. The review concluded that “however, the second treatment study was short term only, and the positive effects wore off rapidly on the switch to placebo; thus, routine use of this strategy as a treatment is not recommended without further evaluation”. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>
<p>

A subsequent study published in Am J Med. Jun 2003 by Blockmans D et al, performed a 6-month, randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, crossover study in 100 patients who fulfilled the 1994 CDC criteria for chronic fatigue syndrome. With a combination therapy (5 mg/d of hydrocortisone and 50 microg/day of 9-alfa-fludrocortisone) for 3 months of active treatment, concluded low-dose combination therapy of hydrocortisone and fludrocortisone was not effective in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

A recent review and study published in the Journal of Chronic Fatigue Syndrome in February 2008 by Kent Holtorf, reviewed all previous hydrocortisone trials regarding safety and effectiveness, and concluded that "because treatment with low physiological doses of cortisol (less than 15mg) has been shown to be safe and effective and routine dynamic ACTH testing does not have adequate diagnostic sensitivity, it is reasonable to give a therapeutic trial of physiologic doses of cortisol to the majority of patients with CFS and FM, especially to those who have symptoms that are consistent with adrenal dysfunction, have low blood pressure or have baseline cortisol levels in the low or low-normal range." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Immunoglobulin treatments</st>
<p>
 
The role of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/178769.xml">
intravenous</link> immuno-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/290517.xml">
gammaglobulin</link> (IVIgG) in the management of CFS is said to be unclear following four randomised double blind placebo controlled studies examining <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
immunoglobulin</link>, its short term efficacy, and two follow up studies several years after the trials that showed positive effect. </p>
<p>

In 1990 Lloyd et al published in Am J Med. a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial to determine the effectiveness of high-dose IVIgG. Forty-nine patients (40 with abnormal cell-mediated immunity) participated and showed that 2g/kg/month for 3 months was effective for producing remission and immunological improvement in adult patients with CFS (Australian criteria). When followed up 3 years later Wilson et al found that 66% of the 30 who responded had improved or continued to improve including some who were considered non responders at 3 months.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>
<p>

In 1990 Peterson et al published in Am J Med a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of IV IgG. Thirty patients with CFS were enrolled but did not observe any significant difference between the two groups (CDC 1988 criteria) treated with 1 g/kg or placebo every 30 days for 6 months. At the end of the study, no significant therapeutic benefit could be detected in terms of symptom amelioration or improvement in functional status, despite restoration of IgG1 levels to a normal range. Major adverse experiences were observed in 20% of both the IV IgG and placebo groups. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref></p>
<p>

In 1997 Rowe KS published in J Psychiatr Res. Results of a double blind randomized controlled trial with 71 young adolescents diagnosed with (CDC 1994 defined) CFS to test the efficacy of IVIgG. In this study 1gm/kg/month or placebo for 3 months was given with follow-up at 3 and 6 months. A significant difference was demonstrated between the baseline functional score and the 6 month follow-up and between the mean functional outcomes at 6 months. Adverse effects were common with both active and placebo solutions, but not predictive of response. A follow-up study at 3 years and 5 years with 75% and 78% response found there was no deteriation in overall function over the time, and young people continued to improve although a significant number were still disabled. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref></p>
<p>

A further study in 1997 by Vollmer - Conna et al was published in Am J Med. Ninety-nine adult patients, who fulfilled diagnostic criteria for CFS (Australian criteria, similar CDC 1988), participated in this double-blind, randomized, and placebo-controlled trial. Patients received intravenous infusions with either a placebo solution or one of three doses of immunoglobulin (0.5, 1, or 2 g/kg) on a monthly basis for 3 months. No dose of intravenous immunoglobulin was associated with a specific therapeutic benefit. Adverse reactions, typically constitutional symptoms, were reported by 70% to 80% of patients, with no relationship to immunoglobulin treatment. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>
<p>

Apart from the different criteria on selection of patient subgroups in the various trials, a review in 1999 commented on the mixed results of the trials as follows; Peterson et al did not observe any difference between the two groups in that trial, however noted only 28 subjects completed the study so the results may be subject to Type II error, due to (small) sample size. Volma-Connor et al with variable dosage did not demonstrate a differtence at 3 months however the 3 month follow-up may have been too short a period, given there was no significant difference at 3 months in the 1997 Rowe adolescent study but at 6 months there was (significant differences).
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Immune modulation treatment</st>
<p>

Treatment with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/118117.xml">
staphylococcal</link> vaccine in fibromyalgia/chronic fatigue syndrome patients has been shown to increase the serological responses and the results further show that this response is related to improvement of the clinical outcomes. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref>
There have been 2 RCT trials conducted that show improvements, although regular injections must be continued to maintain the benefits.</p>
<p>

In 1998 Andersson M et al published in the journal Eur J Pain, a small study of 28 CFS patients that compared the effect of vaccination with a staphylococcus toxoid with the injections of sterile water. Clinical global impressions showed significant improvement in the vaccine-treated group. In a follow-up study of 23 patients, the vaccine treatment was continued for 2-6 years. Fifty percent were rehabilitated successfully and resumed half-time or full-time work.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref></p>
<p>

In 2002 Zachrisson O et al published in the journal Eur J Pain, a study on one hundred consecutively referred patients fulfilling the ACR criteria for FM and the 1994 CDC criteria for CFS enrolled in a randomised controlled trial to receive active drug or placebo. Treatment included weekly injections containing 0.1 ml, 0.2 ml, 0.3 ml, 0.4 ml, 0.6 ml, 0.8 ml, 0.9 ml, and 1.0 ml SB staphylococcus toxoid or coloured sterile water, followed by booster doses given 4-weekly for a total of 6 months. The treatment was well tolerated. Intention-to-treat analysis showed 32/49 (65%) responders in the SB group compared to 9/49 (18%) in the placebo group (P0.001). Sixteen patients (33%) in the SB group reduced their CPRS scores by at least 50% compared to five patients (10%) in the placebo group (P 0.01). An increase in CPRS symptoms at withdrawal was noted in the SB group. Maintenance of treatment is required to prevent relapse. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Titrated drugs, hormones and supplements </st>
<p>

In 2001 Jacob Teitelbaum et al published in the Journal of Chronic Fatigue Syndrome results of randomised double blind placebo controlled intent to treat study. Seventy-two FMS patients (thirty-eight active: thirty-four placebo; sixty-nine also met CFS 1994 CDC criteria) received all active or all placebo therapies as a unified intervention. Patients were treated, as indicated by symptoms and/or lab testing, for: (1) subclinical thyroid, gonadal, and/or adrenal insufficiency, (2) disordered sleep, (3) suspected neurally mediated hypotension (NMH), (4) opportunistic infections, and (5) suspected nutritional deficiencies. </p>
<p>

Each patient received either all active or all placebo treatments as a unified intervention. All patients received; for sleep, Melatonin, Valerium Rest plus mixing on an individual basis of a low dose of several sleep medications instead of a high dose of a single agent adjusted so that the patient got 7-8 hours of uninterrupted sleep without waking or next day sedation. For nutritional support; Multivitamin and Magnesium with malic acid. Additional treatments that were individualized based on test results or clinical history included: Ferrous Fumarate, Vitamin B12, Levothyroxine (Synthroid) or desiccated thyroid, Cortisol (Cortef), DHEA, Testosterone Enanthate (Delatestryl) (in males) or natural Testosterone (in females), Estrogen replacement and if uterus present natural progesterone (in females), Oxytocin, Fludrocortisone (Florinef) and increased dietary salt, water &amp; potassium, Sertraline (Zoloft) or Paroxetine (Paxil) or Fluoxetine (Prozac) or Nefazodone (Serzone), Nystatin plus in more severe cases Itraconazole (Sporanox), Metronidazole (Flagyl) followed by Iodoquinol (Yodoxin), Doxycycline. At some time during the study antidepressants; Serotonin Uptake Inhibitors (SSRI's), Amitriptyline and Cyclobenzaprine were added.</p>
<p>

One patient in each group dropped out because of side effects and one in each group dropped out with no reason given. At the final visit, sixteen active patients were "much better," fourteen "better," two "same," zero "worse," and one "much worse" versus three, nine, eleven, six, and four, respectively, in the placebo group (p  .0001, Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel trend test). Significant improvement in the FMS Impact Questionnaire (FIQ) scores (decreasing from 54.8 to 33.2 versus 51.4 to 47.7) and Analog scores (improving from 176.1 to 310.3 versus 177.1 to 211.9) (both with p  .0001 by random effects regression), and Tender Point Index (TPI) (31.7 to 15.5 versus 35.0 to 32.3, p  .0001 by baseline adjusted linear model) were seen. Long-term follow-up (mean 1.9 years) of the active group showed continuing and increasing improvement over time, despite patients being able to wean off most treatments. The analyses of antidepressants showed little impact on the primary comparisons of the active and placebo treatments.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
NADH treatment</st>
<p>

In 1999 L Forsyth et al published in Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol. a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover study in patients with CFS to evaluate the efficacy of the reduced form of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/365558.xml">
NADH</link>). Twenty-six eligible patients who fulfilled the CDC criteria for CFS completed the study. Subjects were randomly assigned to receive either 10 mg of NADH or placebo for a 4-week period. Following a 4-week washout period, subjects were crossed to the alternate regimen for a final 4-week period. No severe adverse effects were observed related to the study drug,  8 of 26 patients (31%) responded favorably to NADH in contrast to 2 of 26 (8%) to placebo. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref></p>
<p>

In 2004 Santaella M et al reported in P R Health Sci J. the results of a randomised study comparing oral therapy with reduced nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) to conventional modalities of treatment in patients with CFS. A total of 31 patients fulfilling the CDC criteria for CFS, were randomly assigned to either NADH or nutritional supplements and psychological therapy for 24 months. The twelve patients who received NADH had a dramatic and statistically significant reduction of the mean symptom score in the first trimester (p  0.001). The authors concluded that the observed effectiveness of NADH over conventional treatment in the first trimester of the trial and the trend of improvement of that modality in the subsequent trimesters warrant further assessment in a larger patient sample. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Other medical treatments</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Allergy identification and treatment</st>
<p>

In cases where CFS-like symptoms may be caused by allergies, enzyme deficiencies or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/1395311.xml">
food intolerance</link>, such as chronic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/28598.xml">
sinusitis</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/63526.xml">
coeliac disease</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/210596.xml">
irritable bowel syndrome</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2237%22])">37</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2238%22])">38</ref> allergy testing, treatments, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/17348660.xml">
elimination diet</link>s may prove beneficial.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Complementary and alternative medicine</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Essential fatty acid treatments</st>
<p>

A number of studies have been carried out supplementing with oils containing derivative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/105948.xml">
essential fatty acid</link>s; with Omega-6, gamma linolenic acid GLA; and with Omega-3, eicosapentaenoic acid EPA and docosahexaenoic acid DHA. The studies below used Efamol marine comprised of evening primrose oil containing GLA together with fishoil concentrate containing EPA and DHA. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref> </p>
<p>

In 1990 Behan and Behan reported a randomised double blind placebo controlled study of 70 patients with post viral fatigue syndrome (PVFS) given the supplements morning and evening for 15 weeks, Of those patients 84% on active treatment vs 22% on placebo (of olive oil) reported improvements of the symptoms, exhaustion, aches and pains, muscle weakness, lack of concentration, dizziness, vertigo, depression, and memory loss. Patients on active treatment also recorded fewer episodes of cardiac palpitations and tachycardia. All these symptoms showed statistically significant improvement. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2241%22])">41</ref> </p>
<p>

In 1990 Behan and Horribin enrolled sixty-three adults with the diagnosis of PVFS in a randomised double-blind, placebo-controlled study. After 3 months, of the patients, 85% on active treatment given the supplements vs. 17% on placebo (of paraffin oil), reported improved or much improved symptoms of fatigue, aches and pains, muscle weakness, lack of concentration, dizziness, vertigo, depression, and memory loss. All these symptoms showed statistically significant improvement. Upon testing only the supplement group's cellular membrane phospholipids, (both n-6 and n-3 EFA feedstock’s) had returned towards normal. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref>  </p>
<p>

In 1999 a double blind controlled study by Warren et al. was reported with fifty patients who fulfilled the Oxford Criteria for CFS, and who had negligible pretreatment differences of red-cell membrane (RBC) lipids compared with controls. The study results showed no significant differences between treated and placebo patients, as opposed to the two previous studies, on a different patient subgroup. “However the question remains whether sunflower oil (as placebo) has therapeutic effects of its own.” <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2243%22])">43</ref>  </p>
<p>

A review of CFS treatments by Reid et al. in 2000, when comparing only the Behan/Horrobin and Warren studies concluded they showed mixed results, and classified dietary supplements as "unknown effectiveness".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2244%22])">44</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Magnesium</st>
<p>

In 1991 Cox et al published in the Lancet results of a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/18909.xml">
magnesium</link> in CFS. In an associated case-control study, 20 patients with CFS had lower red cell magnesium concentrations than did 20 healthy control subjects. In the clinical trial, 32 patients with CFS were randomly allocated either to intramuscular magnesium sulphate every week for 6 weeks (15 patients) or to placebo (17). Patients treated with 100mg of magnesium had improved energy levels, better emotional state, and less pain, as judged by changes in the Nottingham health profile. 12 of the 15 treated patients had benefited from treatment, and in 7 patients energy score improved. By contrast, 3 of the 17 patients on placebo felt better (difference 62%, 95% CI 35 to 90), and 1 placebo patient had a better energy score. Red cell magnesium returned to normal in all patients on magnesium but in only 1 patient on placebo. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2245%22])">45</ref></p>
<p>

A review by Reid et al. in 2000 determined that as 3 subsequent studies had failed to find a deficiency of magnesium in people with chronic fatigue syndrome, that magnesium treatments in dietary supplements have "unknown effectiveness". <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2244%22])">44</ref></p>
<p>

Another review by Werbach also in 2000 on nutritional strategies for treating chronic fatigue syndrome compared 9 studies and concluded there was marginal magnesium deficiency in CFS. In commenting on the trial above said, “These findings are consistent with a report that CFS patients who were not magnesium-deficient failed to benefit from an injection of 580 mg magnesium, six times the dosage received by the group of magnesium deficient patients (that benefitted in the above trial).”  In conclusion said, “It is likely that marginal deficiencies not only contribute to the clinical manifestations of chronic fatigue syndrome, but also are detrimental to the healing processes. Therefore, when feasible, they should be identified by objective testing and their resolution should be assured by repeat testing following the initiation of treatment. Moreover, because of the rarity of serious adverse reactions and the difficulty in ruling out marginal deficiencies, and because some of the therapeutic benefits of nutritional supplements appear to be due to pharmacological effects, it seems rational to consider supplementing CFS patients with the nutrients. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2246%22])">46</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Carnitine treatments</st>

<p>

There have been a number of random controlled trials finding benefit for supplementation with L-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/271056.xml">
carnitine</link> or its esters in CDC defined CFS. </p>
<p>

In a 1997 trial of random crossover design comparing L-carnitine and amantadine, 30 CFS patients who met CDC criteria, were given each medicine for 2 months, with a 2-week washout period between. Only with L-carnitine (1g, 3 times daily) were statistically significant clinical improvements found; and in 12 of the 18 studied parameters, after 8 weeks of treatment. None of the clinical parameters showed any deterioration. The greatest improvement took place between 4 and 8 weeks of L-carnitine treatment.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2247%22])">47</ref></p>
<p>

A 2004 randomised controlled trial with 90 CDC defined patients compared acetyl-L-carnitine, propionyl-L-carnitine, and its combination in 3 groups of 30 CFS patients during 24 weeks. Treatment showed considerable improvement in 59% of the patients in the acetylcarnitine group and 63% in the propionylcarnitine group, but less in the combination group (37%). Acetylcarnitine significantly improved mental fatigue and propionylcarnitine improved general fatigue. Attention concentration improved in all groups, whereas pain complaints did not decrease in any group. Two weeks after finishing treatment, worsening of fatigue was experienced by 52%, 50%, and 37% in the groups respectively. In the acetylcarnitine group, but not in the other groups, the changes in plasma carnitine levels correlated with clinical improvement. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2248%22])">48</ref></p>
<p>

In 2007 in a randomised controlled trial on 96 elderly patients who met CDC criteria for CFS without psychiatric disorders, were given placebo or carnitine supplementation. The active group had significantly greater improvements in various measures than the placebo group for the following parameters: muscle pain; prolonged fatigue after exercise: sleep disorders: physical fatigue: mental fatigue: fatigue severity scale: functional status: mini mental state examination (MMSE) improvements. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2249%22])">49</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Complementary and alternative medicine usage</st>
<p>

Two studies reported increased utilization of alternative treatments by people with CFS vs. without. In one study designed to assess use of alternative medicines and perceived benefits with 63 paired CFS and non-CFS co-twins, 91% of twins with CFS and 71% without CFS used at last one alternative treatment in their life, and a large proportion of all twins considered them helpful. Future research should ascertain the usefulness of alternative practices in the management of CFS.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2250%22])">50</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2251%22])">51</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Rimes KA, Chalder T.&#32;(2005).&#32;"Treatments for chronic fatigue syndrome.". <it>Occupational Medicine</it>&#32;<b>55</b>&#32;(1): 32–39. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Foccmed%2Fkqi015">
10.1093/occmed/kqi015</weblink>. PMID 15699088.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Cho HJ, Hotopf M, Wessely S&#32;(2005).&#32;"The placebo response in the treatment of chronic fatigue syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis.". <it>Psychosom Med</it>&#32;<b>67</b>&#32;(2): 301–13. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097%2F01.psy.0000156969.76986.e0">
10.1097/01.psy.0000156969.76986.e0</weblink>. PMID 15784798.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Jason LA, Taylor RR, Kennedy CL&#32;(2000).&#32;"Chronic fatigue syndrome, fibromyalgia, and multiple chemical sensitivities in a community-based sample of persons with chronic fatigue syndrome-like symptoms". <it>Psychosom Med</it>&#32;<b>62</b>&#32;(5): 655–63. PMID 11020095.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Clauw DJ&#32;(2001).&#32;"Potential mechanisms in chemical intolerance and related conditions". <it>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</it>&#32;<b>933</b>: 235–53. PMID 12000024.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gruber AJ, Hudson JI, Pope HG&#32;(1996).&#32;"The management of treatment-resistant depression in disorders on the interface of psychiatry and medicine. Fibromyalgia, chronic fatigue syndrome, migraine, irritable bowel syndrome, atypical facial pain, and premenstrual dysphoric disorder". <it>Psychiatr. Clin. North Am.</it>&#32;<b>19</b>&#32;(2): 351–69. PMID 8827194.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
National Center for Infectious Diseases&#32;(2005-05-11).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/diseases/cfs/treat.htm">
Treatment of Patients with Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</weblink>"&#32;(htm).&#32;  Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-07</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(1994). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=MtKW0xFPs5sC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR11&amp;dq=%22Bell%22+%22The+Doctor%27s+Guide+to+Chronic+Fatigue+Syndrome:+...%22+&amp;ots=b1A6hRFIZf&amp;sig=BJMOZ-SdQb7Xk1jlMoAc5VHK_QY#PPP1,M1">
The Doctor's Guide to Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</weblink>.&#32;Da Capo Press,&#32;163. ISBN 0201407973.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
Thomas MA, Smith AP.An investigation of the long-term benefits of antidepressant medication in the recovery of patients with chronic fatigue syndrome. Hum Psychopharmacol. 2006 Dec;21(8):503-9</entry>
<entry id="9">
Schonfeldt-Lecuona C, Connemann BJ, Wolf RC, Braun M, Freudenmann RW.Bupropion augmentation in the treatment of chronic fatigue syndrome with coexistent major depression episode. Pharmacopsychiatry. 2006 Jul;39(4):152-4.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Goodnick PJ, Sandoval R, Brickman A, Klimas NG.Bupropion treatment of fluoxetine-resistant chronic fatigue syndrome. Biol Psychiatry. 1992 Nov 1;32(9):834-8.</entry>
<entry id="11">
Hickie IB, Wilson AJ, Wright JM, Bennett BK, Wakefield D, Lloyd AR. A randomized, double-blind placebo-controlled trial of moclobemide in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome.
J Clin Psychiatry. 2000 Sep;61(9):643-8.</entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Blockmans D, Persoons P, Van Houdenhove B, Bobbaers H&#32;(2006).&#32;"Does methylphenidate reduce the symptoms of chronic fatigue syndrome?". <it>Am J Med</it>&#32;<b>119</b>&#32;(2): 167.e23–30. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.amjmed.2005.07.047">
10.1016/j.amjmed.2005.07.047</weblink>. PMID 16443425.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Randall DC, Cafferty FH, Shneerson JM, Smith IE, Llewelyn MB, File SE&#32;(2005).&#32;"Chronic treatment with modafinil may not be beneficial in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome.". <it>J Psychopharmacol</it>&#32;<b>19</b>&#32;(6): 647–60. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177%2F0269881105056531">
10.1177/0269881105056531</weblink>. PMID 16272188.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Teitelbaum J, Bird B, Weiss A, Gould L&#32;(1999).&#32;"Low-dose hydrocortisone for chronic fatigue syndrome.". <it>JAMA</it>&#32;<b>281</b>&#32;(20): 1887–8; author reply 1888–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001%2Fjama.281.20.1887">
10.1001/jama.281.20.1887</weblink>. PMID 10349885.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Holtorf K&#32;(2008).&#32;"Diagnoses and Treatment of Hypothalamic-Pituitary-Adrenal (HPA) Axis Dysfunction in Patients with Chronic Fatigue Syndrome (CFS) and Fibromyalgia (FM)". <it>Journal of Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</it>&#32;<b>14</b>&#32;(3): 59. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1300%2FJ092v14n03_06">
10.1300/J092v14n03_06</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Cleare AJ, Heap E, Malhi GS, Wessely S, O'Keane V, Miell J&#32;(February 1999).&#32;"Low-dose hydrocortisone in chronic fatigue syndrome: a randomised crossover trial". <it>Lancet</it>&#32;<b>353</b>&#32;(9151): 455–8. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0140-6736%2898%2904074-4">
10.1016/S0140-6736(98)04074-4</weblink>. PMID 9989716.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">McKenzie R, O'Fallon A, Dale J, et al&#32;(1998).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=9757853">
Low-dose hydrocortisone for treatment of chronic fatigue syndrome: a randomized controlled trial</weblink>". <it>JAMA</it>&#32;<b>280</b>&#32;(12): 1061–6. PMID 9757853.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="19">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Blockmans D, Persoons P, Van Houdenhove B, Lejeune M, Bobbaers H&#32;(June 2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0002934303001827">
Combination therapy with hydrocortisone and fludrocortisone does not improve symptoms in chronic fatigue syndrome: a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, crossover study</weblink>". <it>Am. J. Med.</it>&#32;<b>114</b>&#32;(9): 736–41. PMID 12829200.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Cleare AJ&#32;(April 2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://edrv.endojournals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=12700181">
The neuroendocrinology of chronic fatigue syndrome</weblink>". <it>Endocr. Rev.</it>&#32;<b>24</b>&#32;(2): 236–52. PMID 12700181.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="21">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Lloyd A, Hickie I, Wakefield D, Boughton C, Dwyer J&#32;(1990).&#32;"A double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of intravenous immunoglobulin therapy in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>Am. J. Med.</it>&#32;<b>89</b>&#32;(5): 561–8. PMID 2146875.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hormoneandlongevitycenter.com/nss-folder/pictures/JOURNAL_CFSF.pdf">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Holtorf K&#32;(2008).&#32;"Diagnoses and Treatment of Hypothalamic-Pituitary-Adrenal (HPA) Axis Dysfunction in Patients with Chronic Fatigue Syndrome (CFS) and Fibromyalgia (FM)". <it>Journal of Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</it>&#32;<b>14</b>&#32;(3): 59. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1300%2FJ092v14n03_06">
10.1300/J092v14n03_06</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</weblink></entry>
<entry id="23">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Peterson PK, Shepard J, Macres M, et al&#32;(1990).&#32;"A controlled trial of intravenous immunoglobulin G in chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>Am. J. Med.</it>&#32;<b>89</b>&#32;(5): 554–60. PMID 2239975.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="22">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Wilson A, Hickie I, Lloyd A, et al&#32;(1994).&#32;"Longitudinal study of outcome of chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>BMJ</it>&#32;<b>308</b>&#32;(6931): 756–9. PMID 8142830.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="25">
 Rowe KS. 1998 “5 Year Follow-Up of Young People with CFS Following the Double Blind Randomised Controlled Intravenous Gammaglobulin Trial” presented at Conference; The Clinical and Scientific Basis of CFS, Sydney 1998, P31 </entry>
<entry id="24">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Rowe KS&#32;(1997).&#32;"Double-blind randomized controlled trial to assess the efficacy of intravenous gammaglobulin for the management of chronic fatigue syndrome in adolescents". <it>J Psychiatr Res</it>&#32;<b>31</b>&#32;(1): 133–47. PMID 9201655.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="27">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Patarca-Montero, Roberto&#32;(1999). Chronic Fatigue Syndrome: Advances in Epidemiologic, Clinical, and Basic Science Research.&#32;Haworth Pr Inc,&#32;97-99. ISBN 0-7890-0697-9.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="26">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Vollmer-Conna U, Hickie I, Hadzi-Pavlovic D, et al&#32;(1997).&#32;"Intravenous immunoglobulin is ineffective in the treatment of patients with chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>Am. J. Med.</it>&#32;<b>103</b>&#32;(1): 38–43. PMID 9236484.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="29">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Andersson M, Bagby JR, Dyrehag L, Gottfries C&#32;(1998).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/eu980058">
Effects of staphylococcus toxoid vaccine on pain and fatigue in patients with fibromyalgia/chronic fatigue syndrome</weblink>". <it>Eur J Pain</it>&#32;<b>2</b>&#32;(2): 133–142. PMID 10700309.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="28">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Zachrisson O, Colque-Navarro P, Gottfries CG, Regland B, Möllby R&#32;(February 2004).&#32;"Immune modulation with a staphylococcal preparation in fibromyalgia/chronic fatigue syndrome: relation between antibody levels and clinical improvement". <it>Eur. J. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. Dis.</it>&#32;<b>23</b>&#32;(2): 98–105. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs10096-003-1062-8">
10.1007/s10096-003-1062-8</weblink>. PMID 14735403.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="31">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Teitelbaum, J; et al.&#32;(2001).&#32;"". <it>Journal of Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</it>&#32;<b>8</b>&#32;(2): 3-28.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="30">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Zachrisson O, Regland B, Jahreskog M, Jonsson M, Kron M, Gottfries CG&#32;(2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1090-3801(02)00044-7">
Treatment with staphylococcus toxoid in fibromyalgia/chronic fatigue syndrome--a randomised controlled trial</weblink>". <it>Eur J Pain</it>&#32;<b>6</b>&#32;(6): 455–66. PMID 12413434.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="34">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Naranch K, Park YJ, Repka-Ramirez MS, Velarde A, Clauw D, Baraniuk JN&#32;(2002).&#32;"A tender sinus does not always mean rhinosinusitis". <it>Otolaryngology--head and neck surgery : official journal of American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</it>&#32;<b>127</b>&#32;(5): 387–97. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1067%2Fmhn.2002.129038">
10.1067/mhn.2002.129038</weblink>. PMID 12447232.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="35">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Baraniuk JN, Clauw DJ, Gaumond E&#32;(1998).&#32;"Rhinitis symptoms in chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>Ann. Allergy Asthma Immunol.</it>&#32;<b>81</b>&#32;(4): 359–65. PMID 9809501.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="32">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Forsyth LM, Preuss HG, MacDowell AL, Chiazze L, Birkmayer GD, Bellanti JA&#32;(February 1999).&#32;"Therapeutic effects of oral NADH on the symptoms of patients with chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>Ann. Allergy Asthma Immunol.</it>&#32;<b>82</b>&#32;(2): 185–91. PMID 10071523.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="33">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Santaella ML, Font I, Disdier OM&#32;(June 2004).&#32;"Comparison of oral nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) versus conventional therapy for chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>P R Health Sci J</it>&#32;<b>23</b>&#32;(2): 89–93. PMID 15377055.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="38">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Aaron LA, Burke MM, Buchwald D&#32;(2000).&#32;"Overlapping conditions among patients with chronic fatigue syndrome, fibromyalgia, and temporomandibular disorder". <it>Arch. Intern. Med.</it>&#32;<b>160</b>&#32;(2): 221–7. PMID 10647761.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="39">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Nightingale Research Foundation; Goldstein, Jay E.; Byron M. Hyde&#32;(1992). The Clinical and scientific basis of myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome.&#32;Ogdensburg, N.Y:&#32;Nightingale Research Foundation,&#32;521-538, chapter57, The Role of Food Intolerance in Chronic Fatigue Syndrome. ISBN 0-9695662-0-4.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="36">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Logan AC, Wong C&#32;(2001).&#32;"Chronic fatigue syndrome: oxidative stress and dietary modifications". <it>Alternative medicine review : a journal of clinical therapeutic</it>&#32;<b>6</b>&#32;(5): 450–9. PMID 11703165.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="37">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Moss-Morris R, Spence M&#32;(2006).&#32;"To "lump" or to "split" the functional somatic syndromes: can infectious and emotional risk factors differentiate between the onset of chronic fatigue syndrome and irritable bowel syndrome?". <it>Psychosomatic medicine</it>&#32;<b>68</b>&#32;(3): 463–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097%2F01.psy.0000221384.07521.05">
10.1097/01.psy.0000221384.07521.05</weblink>. PMID 16738080.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="42">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Behan PO, Behan WM, Horrobin D&#32;(1990).&#32;"Effect of  high doses of essential fatty acids on the postviral fatigue syndrome". <it>Acta Neurol. Scand.</it>&#32;<b>82</b>&#32;(3): 209–16. PMID 2270749.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="43">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Warren G, McKendrick M, Peet M&#32;(1999).&#32;"The role of essential fatty acids in chronic fatigue syndrome. A case-controlled study of red-cell membrane essential fatty acids (EFA) and a placebo-controlled treatment study with high dose of EFA". <it>Acta Neurol. Scand.</it>&#32;<b>99</b>&#32;(2): 112–6. PMID 10071170.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="40">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Carruthers, BM; Jain AK et al.&#32;(2003).&#32;"Myalgic Encephomyelitis / Chronic fatigue Syndrome: Clinical Working Case Definition, Diagnostic and Treatment Protocols (a Consensus Document)". <it>Journal of Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</it>&#32;<b>11</b>&#32;(1): 66.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="41">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(1990) Omega-6 essential fatty acids: pathophysiology and roles in clinical medicine.&#32;New York:&#32;Wiley-Liss,&#32;275-282. ISBN 0-471-56693-4.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="46">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Werbach MR&#32;(April 2000).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thorne.com/altmedrev/.fulltext/5/2/93.pdf">
Nutritional strategies for treating chronic fatigue syndrome</weblink>". <it>Altern Med Rev</it>&#32;<b>5</b>&#32;(2): 93–108. PMID 10767667.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="47">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Plioplys AV, Plioplys S&#32;(1997).&#32;"Amantadine and L-carnitine treatment of Chronic Fatigue Syndrome". <it>Neuropsychobiology</it>&#32;<b>35</b>&#32;(1): 16–23. PMID 9018019.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="44">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Reid S, Chadler T, Cleare A, Hotopf M, Wessely S.&#32;(2000).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1117488">
Extracts from “Clinical Evidence”: Chronic fatigue syndrome</weblink>". <it>British Medical Journal</it>&#32;<b>320</b>&#32;(7230): 292–296.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="45">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Cox IM, Campbell MJ, Dowson D&#32;(1991).&#32;"Red blood cell magnesium and chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>Lancet</it>&#32;<b>337</b>&#32;(8744): 757–60. PMID 1672392.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="51">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Afari N, Eisenberg DM, Herrell R, et al&#32;(2000).&#32;"Use of alternative treatments by chronic fatigue syndrome discordant twins". <it>Integr Med</it>&#32;<b>2</b>&#32;(2): 97–103. PMID 10882883.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="50">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Jones JF, Maloney EM, Boneva RS, Jones AB, Reeves WC&#32;(2007).&#32;"Complementary and alternative medical therapy utilization by people with chronic fatiguing illnesses in the United States". <it>BMC Complement Altern Med</it>&#32;<b>7</b>: 12. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186%2F1472-6882-7-12">
10.1186/1472-6882-7-12</weblink>. PMID 17459162.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="49">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Malaguarnera M, Gargante MP, Cristaldi E, et al&#32;(2007).&#32;"Acetyl l-carnitine (ALC) treatment in elderly patients with fatigue". <it>Arch Gerontol Geriatr</it>. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.archger.2007.03.012">
10.1016/j.archger.2007.03.012</weblink>. PMID 17658628.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="48">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Vermeulen RC, Scholte HR&#32;(2004).&#32;"Exploratory open label, randomized study of acetyl- and propionylcarnitine in chronic fatigue syndrome". <it>Psychosom Med</it>&#32;<b>66</b>&#32;(2): 276–82. PMID 15039515.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style="line-height: 1.3;;" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background: Silver;" class="navbox-title">
<disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/50613.xml">
Chronic fatigue syndrome</link></disease>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: LightYellow;" class="navbox-group">
<b>Medical issues</b></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:left;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/16986853.xml">
Clinical descriptions</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/16806616.xml">
Etiology</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/16806616.xml">
Pathophysiology</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/16823924.xml">
Treatment</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/16986993.xml">
Management</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: LightYellow;" class="navbox-group">
<b>Society and history</b></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:left;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/16723684.xml">
History</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/16320930.xml">
Alternative names</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/16824033.xml">
Controversies</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/16653193.xml">
Outbreaks</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/15873444.xml">
Cultural references</link> &nbsp;·  <disorder wordnetid="114052403" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<ailment wordnetid="114055408" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/15873020.xml">
Notable patients</link></ailment>
</physical_condition>
</state>
</condition>
</disorder>
 &nbsp;·  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/6927593.xml">
Sophia Mirza</link></person>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</ailment>
</disorder>
</article>
