<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:55:04[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Portal:Discrete mathematics/Selected article/1</title>
<id>16884543</id>
<revision>
<id>204994310</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-11T20:29:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cenarium</username>
<id>5711305</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>


<table style="float: right; margin-left: 1em; background-color: transparent; " width="180">
<row>
<col>
 <image location="none" width="175px" src="6n-graf.svg">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 85%; text-align: center; " width="180">
A labeled graph on 6 vertices and 7 edges</col>
</row>
</table>
 Informally speaking, a <b>graph</b> is a set of objects called <it>points</it>, <it>nodes</it>, or <it>vertices</it> connected by links called <it>lines</it> or <it>edges</it>.  In a proper graph, which is by default <it>undirected</it>, a line from point <it>A</it> to point <it>B</it> is considered to be the same thing as a line from point <it>B</it> to point <it>A</it>.  In a <it>digraph</it>, short for <it>directed graph</it>, the two directions are counted as being distinct <it>arcs</it> or <it>directed edges</it>.  Typically, a graph is depicted in diagrammatic form as a set of dots (for the points, vertices, or nodes), joined by curves (for the lines or edges). Graphs have applications in both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link>, and form the basic object of study in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
graph theory</link>.  <p>

Applications of graph theory are generally concerned with labeled graphs and various specializations of these. Many problems of practical interest can be represented by graphs. The link structure of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link> could be represented by a directed graph: the vertices are the web pages available at the website and a directed edge from page <it>A</it> to page <it>B</it> exists if and only if <it>A</it> contains a link to <it>B</it>. A graph structure can be extended by assigning a weight to each edge of the graph. Graphs with weights, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/638908.xml">
weighted graph</link>s, are used to represent structures in which pairwise connections have some numerical values. For example if a graph represents a road network, the weights could represent the length of each road. A digraph with weighted edges in the context of graph theory is called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/1805187.xml">
network</link>. Networks have many uses in the practical side of graph theory, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1039587.xml">
network analysis</link> (for example, to model and analyze traffic networks). </p>
<p>

<table style="padding: 0; margin:0; background:transparent;" width="100%" border="0">
<row>
<col align="left">
<b>
...Archive</b></col>
<col align="center"></col>
<col align="right">
<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/325806.xml">
Read more...</link></b></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
</bdy>
</article>
