<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:28:26[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Knowledge representation</title>
<id>16920</id>
<revision>
<id>244390995</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T15:55:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Beland</username>
<id>57939</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Scientific modeling</category>
<category>Uncategorized pages needing expert attention</category>
<category>Pages needing expert attention</category>
<category>Knowledge representation</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.</b>
Please help recruit one or <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Knowledge_representation&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> yourself. See the  for details.Please consider using  to associate this request with a </col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(February 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>Knowledge representation</b> is an area in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link> that is concerned with how to formally "think", that is, how to use a symbol system to represent "a domain of discourse" - that which can be talked about, along with functions that may or may not be within the domain of discourse that allow inference (formalized reasoning) about the objects within the domain of discourse to occur. Generally speaking, some kind of logic is used both to supply a formal semantics of how reasoning functions apply to symbols in the domain of discourse, as well as to supply (depending on the particulars of the logic), operators such as quantifiers, modal operators, etc. that along with an interpretation theory, give meaning to the sentences in the logic. When we design a knowledge representation (and a knowledge representation system to interpret sentences in the logic in order to derive inferences from them) we have to make trades across a number of design spaces, described in the following sections. The single most important decision to be made, however is the <it>expressivity</it> of the KR. The more expressive, the easier (and more compact) it is to "say something". However, more expressive languages are harder to automatically derive inferences from. An example of a less expressive KR would be propositional logic. An example of a more expressive KR would be autoepistemic temporal modal logic. Less expressive KRs may be both complete and consistent (formally less expressive than set theory). More expressive KRs may be neither complete nor consistent. The key problem is to find a KR (and a supporting reasoning system) that can make the inferences your application needs <it>in time</it>, that is, within the resource constraints appropriate to the problem at hand. This tension between the kinds of inferences an application "needs" and what counts as "in time" along with the cost to generate the representation itself makes knowledge representation engineering interesting. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

There are representation techniques such as frames, rules and  semantic networks which have originated from theories of human information processing. Since knowledge is used to achieve intelligent behavior, the fundamental goal of knowledge representation is to represent knowledge in a manner as to facilitate inferencing (i.e. drawing conclusions) from knowledge. </p>
<p>

Some issues that arise in knowledge representation from an AI perspective are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 How do people represent knowledge? </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 What is the nature of knowledge and how do we represent it?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Should a representation scheme deal with a particular domain or should it be general purpose?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 How expressive is a representation scheme or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/10939.xml">
formal language</link>? </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Should the scheme be declarative or procedural?</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

There has been very little top-down discussion of the knowledge representation (KR) issues and research in this area is a well aged quiltwork. There are well known problems such as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/7347241.xml">
spreading activation</link>" (this is a problem in navigating a network of nodes), "subsumption" (this is concerned with selective inheritance; e.g. an ATV can be thought of as a specialization of a car but it inherits only particular characteristics)  and "classification." For example a tomato could be classified both as a fruit and a vegetable. </p>
<p>

In the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/1467948.xml">
problem solving</link> can be simplified by an appropriate choice of <it>knowledge representation</it>. Representing knowledge in some ways makes certain problems easier to solve. For example, it is easier to divide numbers represented in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/3393371.xml">
Hindu-Arabic numeral</link>s than numbers represented as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/25657.xml">
Roman numeral</link>s.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History of knowledge representation </st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link>, particularly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link>, a number of representations have been devised to structure information. </p>
<p>

KR is most commonly used to refer to representations intended for processing by modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computers</link>, and in particular, for representations consisting of explicit objects (the class of all elephants, or Clyde a certain individual), and of assertions or claims about them ('Clyde is an elephant', or 'all elephants are grey'). Representing knowledge in such explicit form enables computers to draw conclusions from knowledge already stored ('Clyde is grey').</p>
<p>

Many KR methods were tried in the 1970s and early 1980s, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link> question-answering, <link>
neural networks</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/2546.xml">
theorem proving</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/10136.xml">
expert systems</link>, with varying success. Medical diagnosis (e.g., <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/649929.xml">
Mycin</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
) was a major application area, as were games such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/5134.xml">
chess</link>.</p>
<p>

In the 1980s formal computer knowledge representation languages and systems arose. Major projects attempted to encode wide bodies of general knowledge; for example the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/6874.xml">
Cyc</link>" project went through a large encyclopedia, encoding not the information itself, but the information a reader would need in order to understand the encyclopedia: naive physics; notions of time, causality, motivation; commonplace objects and classes of objects. The Cyc project is managed by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/99994.xml">
Cycorp, Inc.</link></institution>
</company>
; much but not all of the data is now freely available.</p>
<p>

Through such work, the difficulty of KR came to be better appreciated. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/5561.xml">
computational linguistics</link>, meanwhile, much larger databases of language information were being built, and these, along with great increases in computer speed and capacity, made deeper KR more feasible.</p>
<p>

Several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/23015.xml">
programming languages</link> have been developed that are oriented to KR. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/23485.xml">
Prolog</link> developed in 1972 (see http://www.aaai.org/AITopics/bbhist.html#mod), but popularized much later, represents propositions and basic logic, and can derive conclusions from known premises. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/17188.xml">
KL-ONE</link> (1980s) is more specifically aimed at knowledge representation itself.</p>
<p>

In the electronic document world, languages were being developed to represent the structure of documents more explicitly, such as <link>
SGML</link> and later <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
XML</link></format>
. These facilitated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
information retrieval</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/42253.xml">
data mining</link> efforts, which have in recent years begun to relate to KR. The Web community is now especially interested in the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
Semantic Web</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
, in which XML-based KR languages such as <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/53847.xml">
RDF</link></format>
, <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/167777.xml">
Topic Maps</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
, and others can be used to make KR information available to Web systems.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Topics in Knowledge representation </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Language and notation </st>
<p>

Some people think it would be best to represent knowledge in the same way that it is represented in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/490620.xml">
human mind</link>, which is the only known working <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/519280.xml">
intelligence</link> so far, or to represent knowledge in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/455766.xml">
human language</link>. Richard L. Ballard, for example, has developed a theory-based semantics system that is language independent, which claims to capture and reason with the same concepts and theory as people.  The formula underlying theory-based semantics is: Knowledge=Theory+Information. Most conventional applications and database systems are language-based.  Unfortunately, we don't know how knowledge is represented in the human mind, or how to manipulate human languages the same way that the human mind does it. One clue is that primates know how to use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/428644.xml">
point and click</link> user interfaces; thus the <it>gesture-based interface</it> appears to be part of our cognitive apparatus, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/84495.xml">
modality</link> which is not tied to verbal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/17524.xml">
language</link>, and which exists in other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/11039790.xml">
animal</link>s besides <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/682482.xml">
human</link>s.</p>
<p>

For this reason, various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/5262.xml">
artificial languages</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/407860.xml">
notation</link>s have been proposed for representing knowledge. They are typically based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/3729225.xml">
logic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link>, and have easily parsed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/12569.xml">
grammar</link>s to ease <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/5926.xml">
machine processing</link>. They usually fall into the broad domain of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/49681.xml">
ontologies</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Ontology languages </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/3215223.xml">
Ontology language</link></it>
</indent>
After <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/87136.xml">
CycL</link></language>
, a number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/3215223.xml">
ontology language</link>s have been developed. Most are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/210648.xml">
declarative language</link>s, and are either <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/485226.xml">
frame language</link>s, or are based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/10983.xml">
first-order logic</link>. Most of these languages only define an upper ontology with generic concepts, whereas the domain concepts are not part of the language definition. <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/6112331.xml">
Gellish English</link></language>
 is an example of an ontological language that includes a full engineering English Dictionary.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Links and structures </st>
<p>

While <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/49547.xml">
hyperlink</link>s have come into widespread use, the closely related <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/341419.xml">
semantic link</link> is not yet widely used. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/239112.xml">
mathematical table</link> has been used since <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/19720404.xml">
Babylon</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</tract>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</site>
ian times. More recently, these tables have been used to represent the outcomes of logic operations, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/30362.xml">
truth table</link>s, which were used to study and model Boolean logic, for example. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/27686.xml">
Spreadsheet</link>s are yet another tabular representation of knowledge. Other knowledge representations are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/41821.xml">
trees</link>, by means of which the connections among fundamental concepts and derivative concepts can be shown. </p>
<p>

Visual representations are relatively new in the field of knowledge management but give the user a way to visualise how one thought or idea is connected to other ideas enabling the possibility of moving from one thought to another in order to locate required information. The approach is not without its competitors.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Notation </st>
<p>

The recent fashion in knowledge representation languages is to use <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
XML</link></format>
 as the low-level syntax. This tends to make the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/41470.xml">
output</link> of these KR languages easy for machines to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/310015.xml">
parse</link>, at the expense of human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/355291.xml">
readability</link> and often space-efficiency. </p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/10983.xml">
First-order predicate calculus</link> is commonly used as a mathematical basis for these systems, to avoid excessive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/7363.xml">
complexity</link>. However, even simple systems based on this simple logic can be used to represent data that is well beyond the processing capability of current computer systems: see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/3244084.xml">
computability</link> for reasons.</p>
<p>

Examples of notations:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/42553.xml">
DATR</link> is an example for representing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/18077.xml">
lexical</link> knowledge </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/53847.xml">
RDF</link></format>
 is a simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/407860.xml">
notation</link> for representing relationships between and among <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/47353.xml">
object</link>s</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Storage and manipulation </st>
<p>

One problem in knowledge representation consists of how to store and manipulate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/243391.xml">
knowledge</link> in an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/237495.xml">
information system</link> in a formal way so that it may be used by mechanisms to accomplish a given task. Examples of applications are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/10136.xml">
expert system</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/19980.xml">
machine translation system</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/356415.xml">
computer-aided maintenance</link> systems and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
information retrieval</link> systems (including database front-ends).</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/29109.xml">
Semantic network</link>s may be used to represent knowledge. Each node represents a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/6978.xml">
concept</link> and arcs are used to define <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/26220.xml">
relation</link>s between the concepts.
One of the most expressive and comprehensively described knowledge representation paradigms 
along the lines of semantic networks is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/2473220.xml">
MultiNet</link> (an acronym for Multilayered Extended Semantic Networks).</p>
<p>

From the 1960s, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/485226.xml">
knowledge frame</link> or just <it>frame</it> has been used.  Each frame has its own name and a set of <b>attributes</b>, or <b>slots</b> which contain values; for instance, the frame for <it>house</it> might contain a <it>color</it> slot, <it>number of floors</it> slot, etc. </p>
<p>

Using frames for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/10136.xml">
expert systems</link> is an application of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/22757.xml">
object-oriented</link> programming, with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/15430.xml">
inheritance</link> of features described by the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/294441.xml">
is-a</link>" link. However, there has been no small amount of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/75802.xml">
inconsistency</link> in the usage of the "is-a" link: <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/853832.xml">
Ronald J. Brachman</link></associate>
</research_worker>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 wrote a paper titled "What IS-A is and isn't", wherein 29 different semantics were found in projects whose knowledge representation schemes involved an "is-a" link. Other links include the "<link>
has-part</link>" link. </p>
<p>

Frame structures are well-suited for the representation of schematic knowledge and stereotypical cognitive patterns. The elements of such schematic patterns are weighted unequally, attributing higher weights to the more typical elements of a  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://moodle.ed.uiuc.edu/wiked/index.php/Schemas">
schema</weblink>. A pattern is activated by certain expectations: If a person sees a big bird, he or she will classify it rather as a sea eagle than a golden eagle, assuming that his or her "sea-scheme" is currently activated and his "land-scheme" is not.</p>
<p>

Frame representations are object-centered in the same sense as  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/29109.xml">
semantic network</link>s are: All the facts and properties connected with a concept are located in one place - there is no need for costly search processes in the database.</p>
<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/7636660.xml">
behavioral script</link> is a type of frame that describes what happens temporally; the usual example given is that of describing going to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/26437.xml">
restaurant</link>. The steps include waiting to be seated, receiving a menu, ordering, etc.
The different solutions can be arranged in a so-called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/2372769.xml">
semantic spectrum</link> with respect to their semantic expressivity.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Other visual search tools are built by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.convera.com/">
Convera Corporation</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kmconnection.com/pguide/KSP2000348.htm">
Entopia, Inc.</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epeople.com/home.shtml">
EPeople Inc.</weblink>, and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.inxight.com/">
Inxight Software Inc</weblink>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/853832.xml">
Ronald J. Brachman</link></associate>
</research_worker>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
; What IS-A is and isn't. An Analysis of Taxonomic Links in Semantic Networks; IEEE Computer, 16 (10); October 1983 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/context/177306/0">
http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/context/177306/0</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/853832.xml">
Ronald J. Brachman</link></associate>
</research_worker>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/11392973.xml">
Hector J. Levesque</link> <it>Knowledge Representation and Reasoning</it>, Morgan Kaufmann, 2004 ISBN-13: 978-1-55860-932-7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/853832.xml">
Ronald J. Brachman</link></associate>
</research_worker>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/11392973.xml">
Hector J. Levesque</link> (eds) <it>Readings in Knowledge Representation</it>, Morgan Kaufmann, 1985, ISBN: 0-934613-01-X</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Randall Davis, Howard Shrobe, and Peter Szolovits; What Is a Knowledge Representation? AI Magazine, 14(1):17-33,1993 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/davis93what.html">
http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/davis93what.html</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/18421597.xml">
Ronald Fagin</link>,<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/2929332.xml">
Joseph Y. Halpern</link>,<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<honoree wordnetid="110183757" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<acquirer wordnetid="109764201" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<recipient wordnetid="109627906" confidence="0.8">
<laureate wordnetid="110249011" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/7235892.xml">
Yoram Moses</link></scholar>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</alumnus>
</laureate>
</recipient>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</acquirer>
</intellectual>
</honoree>
</person>
</physical_entity>
,<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<employee wordnetid="110053808" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/12067215.xml">
Moshe Y. Vardi</link></associate>
</employee>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</worker>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 <it>Reasoning About Knowledge</it>, MIT Press, 1995, ISBN 0-262-06162-7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Jean-Luc Hainaut, Jean-Marc Hick, Vincent Englebert, Jean Henrard, Didier Roland: Understanding Implementations of IS-A Relations. ER 1996: 42-57 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/conf/er/HainautHEHR96.html">
http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/conf/er/HainautHEHR96.html</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hermann Helbig: <it>Knowledge Representation and the Semantics of Natural Language</it>, Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg, New York 2006</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Arthur B. Markman: <it>Knowledge Representation</it>  Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, 1998</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/102392.xml">
John F. Sowa</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
: <it>Knowledge Representation</it>: Logical, Philosophical, and Computational Foundations. Brooks/Cole: New York, 2000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Adrian Walker, Michael McCord, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/102392.xml">
John F. Sowa</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, and Walter G. Wilson: <it>Knowledge Systems and Prolog</it>, Second Edition, Addison-Wesley, 1990</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Artificial Intelligence</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/616985.xml">
Computability logic</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/6874.xml">
Cyc</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/183503.xml">
Description logic</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/239497.xml">
Knowledge base</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/2044947.xml">
Knowledge discovery</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/72896.xml">
Knowledge management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/7512482.xml">
Knowledge representation system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/18550455.xml">
Knowledge retrieval</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
Metadata</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/15623038.xml">
Morphological analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/2473220.xml">
MultiNet</link>, Multilayered Extended Semantic Networks</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/5007318.xml">
Protege (software)</link>, open source system</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
Scientific modeling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
Semantic Web</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/1439193.xml">
Technoscience</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Theory-based_Semantics">
Theory-based Semantics</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/167777.xml">
Topic Maps</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://medg.lcs.mit.edu/ftp/psz/k-rep.html">
What is a Knowledge Representation?</weblink> by Randall Davis and others</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.inf.unibz.it/~franconi/dl/course/">
Introduction to Description Logics course</weblink> by Enrico Franconi, Faculty of Computer Science, Free University of Bolzano, Italy </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ccl.kuleuven.ac.be/LKR/html/datr.html">
DATR Lexical knowledge representation language</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.isi.edu/isd/LOOM/LOOM-HOME.html">
Loom Project Home Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.research.att.com/sw/tools/classic/tm/ijcai-95-with-scenario.html">
Description Logic in Practice: A CLASSIC Application</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/ruleml/">
The Rule Markup Initiative</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://moodle.ed.uiuc.edu/wiked/index.php/Schemas">
Schemas</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nelements.org">
Nelements KOS</weblink> - a generic 3d knowledge representation system</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
