<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:54:44[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network science</title>
<id>16981683</id>
<revision>
<id>235501771</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-01T02:19:04Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Networks</category>
<category>Cybernetics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Network science</b> is a new and emerging scientific discipline that examines the interconnections among diverse physical, informational, biological, cognitive, and social networks.  This field of science seeks to discover common principles, algorithms and tools that govern network behavior.  The National Research Council defines Network Science as "the organized knowledge of networks based on their study using the scientific method."
<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

Several U.S. governmental agencies such as the Department of Defense and the National Science foundation have recently begun to fund research in this field.  The U.S. Military Academy has been teaching the subject matter to cadets and has formed a Network Science Center to facilitate education and research within the Army.  The Army is also in the process of establishing a research center for Network Science at Aberdeen Proving Grounds.  In addition, several universities are conducting active research in various interdisciplinary aspects of network science, such as Harvard, Carnegie Mellon University, Northeastern University, and the University of Pennsylvania, while others, such as Columbia, University of California, Irvine, University of Toronto and many others in the social sciences, for example, have older research programs in this area. In 1977, INSNA, the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/7433852.xml">
International Network for Social Network Analysis</link></network>
</group>
</system>
, was founded by <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/1203090.xml">
Barry Wellman</link></network>
</group>
</system>
, the same year as the startup of the EIES (an Internet forerunner: <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link>
Electronic Information Exchange System</link></university>
) computer conference organized by <link>
Linton C. Freeman</link> and <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/6044579.xml">
Douglas R. White</link></person>
</anthropologist>
 that brought together network scientists from diverse fields<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.  The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/03788733">
Social Networks</weblink> journal was started by Freeman in 1978. For a review of the history of interdisciplinary social network sciences see the 2005 review of : <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cmu.edu/joss/content/articles/volume6/Kadushin/">
The Development of Social Network Analysis: A Study in the Sociology of Science, by L.C. Freeman</weblink> by Charles Kadushin. </p>
<p>

Sub disciplines of network science include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/5162898.xml">
dynamic network analysis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link> analysis, the study of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/1704711.xml">
complex networks</link>, network optimization, network biology, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
graph theory</link>.</p>
<p>

In September 2006, scientists from several universities initiated the International Council On Network Science (ICONS).  This society aims to promote and facilitate the study and education of network science.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Background and history </st>

<p>

The study of networks has emerged in diverse disciplines as a means of analyzing complex relational data. The earliest known paper in this field is the famous <link>
Seven Bridges of Königsberg</link> written by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/17902.xml">
Leonhard Euler</link></scientist>
</person>
 in 1736. Euler's mathematical description of vertices and edges was the foundation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
Graph Theory</link>, a branch of mathematics that studies the properties of pairwise relations in a network structure. The field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
Graph Theory</link> continued to develop and found applications in chemistry (Sylvester, 1878).</p>
<p>

In the 1930s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/1812202.xml">
Jacob Moreno</link>, a psychologist in the Gestalt tradition, arrived in the United States. He developed the sociogram and presented it to the public in April 1933 at a convention of medical scholars. Moreno claimed that "before the advent of sociometry no one knew what the interpersonal structure of a group 'precisely' looked like (Moreno, 1953). The sociogram was a representation of the social structure of a group of elementary school students. The boys were friends of boys and the girls were friends of girls with the exception of one boy who said he like a single girl. The feeling was not reciprocated. This network representation of social structure was found so intriguing that it was printed in the <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/30680.xml">
The New York Times</link></newspaper>
(April 3, 1933, page 17). The sociogram has found many applications and has grown into the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network analysis</link>.</p>
<p>

Probabilistic theory in Network Science developed as an off-shoot of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
Graph Theory</link> with <link>
Paul Erdős</link> and <link>
Alfréd Rényi</link>'s eight famous papers on <link>
random graphs</link>. For <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social networks</link> the <link>
exponential random graph model</link> or p* graph is a notational framework used to represent the probability space of a tie occurring in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link>. An alternate approach to network probability structures is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/17117924.xml">
Network Probability Matrix</link>, which models the probability of edges occurring in a network, based on the historic presence or absence of the edge in a sample of networks.</p>
<p>

The U.S. military became interested in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/1733505.xml">
Network-centric warfare</link> as an operational concept based on network science in 1996. Subsequently, the U.S. Department of Defense has funded numerous research projects in the area of Network Science. As initiated in 2004 by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/17600158.xml">
Frederick I. Moxley</link></scientist>
 with support provided by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/9171604.xml">
David S. Alberts</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, the Department of Defense helped to establish the first Network Science Center in conjunction with the U.S. Army at the United States Military Academy.</p>
<p>

In the 1998, David Krackhardt and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/17363635.xml">
Kathleen Carley</link></scientist>
 introduced the idea of a meta-network with the PCANS Model. They suggest that "all organizations are structured along these three domains, Individuals, Tasks, and Resources. Their paper introduced the concept that networks occur across multiple domains and that they are interrelated. This field has grown into another sub-discipline of network science called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/5162898.xml">
Dynamic Network Analysis</link>.</p>
<p>

More recently other network science efforts have focussed on mathematically describing different network topologies. Duncan Watts reconciled empirical data on networks with mathematical representation, describing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/1457254.xml">
small-world network</link>. <link>
Albert-László Barabási</link> and Reka Albert developed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/227155.xml">
scale-free network</link> which is a topology that contains hub vertices with many connections, while most vertices have relatively few connections.</p>
<p>

Today, network science is an exciting and growing field. Scientists from many diverse fields are working together. Network science holds the promise of increasing collaboration across disciplines, by sharing data, algorithms, and software tools.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Freeman, Linton C. 1984. The Impact of Computer Based Communication of the Social Structure of an Emerging Scientific Speciality. <it>Social Networks</it> 6(3):201-221</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Understanding Network Science," http://www.zangani.com/blog/2007-1030-networkingscience</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Linked: The New Science of Networks</it>, A.-L. Barabási (Perseus Publishing, Cambridge (2002).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=11516">
Network Science</weblink></it>, Committee on Network Science for Future Army Applications, National Research Council. 2005. The National Academies Press (2005)ISBN-10: 0-309-10026-7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Network Science Bulletin</it>, USMA (2007) ISBN 978-1-934808-00-9</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>The Structure and Dynamics of Networks</it> Mark Newman, Albert-László Barabási, &amp; Duncan J. Watts (The Princeton Press, 2006)ISBN 0-691-11357-2</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.netscience.usma.edu/NSW/Papers/Network_Science_Report_Vol1No1.pdf</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://press.princeton.edu/titles/8114.html</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.cra.org/ccc/NSE.ppt.pdf</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.ifr.ac.uk/netsci08/</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
