<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:23:18[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<rule  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105846932">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<procedure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101023820">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<algorithm  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105847438">
<header>
<title>Case-based reasoning</title>
<id>170333</id>
<revision>
<id>238419986</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-14T19:35:01Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rich jj</username>
<id>6747148</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Classification algorithms</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Case-based reasoning</b> (CBR), broadly construed, is the process of solving new problems based on the solutions of similar past problems. An auto <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/840391.xml">
mechanic</link> who fixes an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/9640.xml">
engine</link> by recalling another <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/13673345.xml">
car</link> that exhibited similar symptoms is using case-based reasoning.  A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/17541.xml">
lawyer</link> who advocates a particular outcome in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../812/3276812.xml">
trial</link> based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
legal</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/23004.xml">
precedent</link>s or a judge who creates <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/215403.xml">
case law</link> is using case-based reasoning.  So, too, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/38223.xml">
engineer</link> copying working elements of nature (practicing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/45784.xml">
biomimicry</link>), is treating nature as a database of solutions to problems. Case-based reasoning is a prominent kind of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/103533.xml">
analogy</link> making.<p>

It has been argued that case-based reasoning is not only a powerful method for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/2884728.xml">
computer reasoning</link>, but also a pervasive behavior in everyday human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/1467948.xml">
problem solving</link>.  Or, more radically, that all reasoning is based on past cases experienced or accepted by the being actively exercising choice – <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/1042464.xml">
prototype theory</link> – most deeply explored in human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/5626.xml">
cognitive science</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Process </st>

<p>

Case-based reasoning has been formalized for purposes of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/2884728.xml">
computer reasoning</link> as a four-step process<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Retrieve:</b>  Given a target problem, retrieve cases from memory that are relevant to solving it.  A case consists of a problem, its solution, and, typically, annotations about how the solution was derived.  For example, suppose Fred wants to prepare blueberry <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/210472.xml">
pancakes</link>.  Being a novice cook, the most relevant experience he can recall is one in which he successfully made plain pancakes.  The procedure he followed for making the plain pancakes, together with justifications for decisions made along the way, constitutes Fred's retrieved case.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Reuse:</b>  Map the solution from the previous case to the target problem.  This may involve adapting the solution as needed to fit the new situation.  In the pancake example, Fred must adapt his retrieved solution to include the addition of blueberries.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Revise:</b>  Having mapped the previous solution to the target situation, test the new solution in the real world (or a simulation) and, if necessary, revise. Suppose Fred adapted his pancake solution by adding blueberries to the batter.  After mixing, he discovers that the batter has turned blue – an undesired effect.  This suggests the following revision:  delay the addition of blueberries until after the batter has been ladled into the pan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Retain:</b>  After the solution has been successfully adapted to the target problem, store the resulting experience as a new case in memory.  Fred, accordingly, records his newfound procedure for making blueberry pancakes, thereby enriching his set of stored experiences, and better preparing him for future pancake-making demands.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Comparison to other methods </st>
<p>

At first glance, CBR may seem similar to the rule-induction <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link>.  Like a <link>
rule-induction algorithm</link>, CBR starts with a set of cases or training examples; it forms generalizations of these examples, albeit implicit ones, by identifying commonalities between a retrieved case and the target problem.  </p>
<p>

If for instance a procedure for plain pancakes is mapped to blueberry pancakes, a decision is made to use the same basic batter and frying method, thus implicitly generalizing the set of situations under which the batter and frying method can be used. The key difference, however, between the implicit generalization in CBR and the generalization in rule induction lies in when the generalization is made.  A rule-induction algorithm draws its generalizations from a set of training examples before the target problem is even known; that is, it performs eager generalization.  </p>
<p>

For instance, if a rule-induction algorithm were given recipes for plain pancakes, Dutch apple pancakes, and banana pancakes as its training examples, it would have to derive, at training time, a set of general rules for making all types of pancakes. It would not be until testing time that it would be given, say, the task of cooking blueberry pancakes.  The difficulty for the rule-induction algorithm is in anticipating the different directions in which it should attempt to generalize its training examples.  This is in contrast to CBR, which delays (implicit) generalization of its cases until testing time – a strategy of lazy generalization.  In the pancake example, CBR has already been given the target problem of cooking blueberry pancakes; thus it can generalize its cases exactly as needed to cover this situation. CBR therefore tends to be a good approach for rich, complex domains in which there are myriad ways to generalize a case.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Criticism </st>

<p>

Critics of CBR argue that it is an approach that accepts <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/481925.xml">
anecdotal evidence</link> as its main operating principle. Without statistically relevant data for backing and implicit generalization, there is no guarantee that the generalization is correct.  However, all inductive reasoning where data is too scarce for statistical relevance is inherently based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/481925.xml">
anecdotal evidence</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

CBR traces its roots to the work of <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/1076541.xml">
Roger Schank</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and his students at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/34273.xml">
Yale University</link></university>
 in the early 1980s.  Schank's model of dynamic memory<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> was the basis for the earliest CBR systems: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/13642131.xml">
Janet Kolodner's</link> CYRUS<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> and Michael Lebowitz's IPP<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.  </p>
<p>

Other schools of CBR and closely allied fields emerged in the 1980s, investigating such topics as CBR in legal reasoning, memory-based reasoning (a way of reasoning from examples on massively parallel machines), and combinations of CBR with other reasoning methods.  In the 1990s, interest in CBR grew in the international community, as evidenced by the establishment of an International Conference on Case-Based Reasoning in 1995, as well as European, German, British, Italian, and other CBR workshops.  </p>
<p>

CBR technology has produced a number of successful deployed systems, the earliest being Lockheed's CLAVIER<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>, a system for laying out composite parts to be baked in an industrial convection oven. CBR has been used extensively in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/13544.xml">
help desk</link> applications such as the Compaq SMART system<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Prominent CBR systems </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SMART: Support management automated reasoning technology for Compaq customer service<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Appliance Call Center automation at General Electric<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CLAVIER: Applying case-based reasoning on to composite part fabrication<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 FormTool: Plastics Color Matching<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CoolAir: HVAC specification and pricing system<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdacmumbai.in/index.php/cdacmumbai/research_and_publications/research_groups/kbcs_artificial_intelligence/research/case_based_reasoning">
Vidur</weblink> - A CBR based intelligent advisory system, by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdacmumbai.in/">
C-DAC Mumbai</weblink>, for farmers of North-East India.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/232602.xml">
Decision tree</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
Genetic algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/279688.xml">
Pattern matching</link></concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/103533.xml">
Analogy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1499475.xml">
K-line (artificial intelligence)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/1432366.xml">
Ripple down rules</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Agnar Aamodt and Enric Plaza, "Case-Based Reasoning: Foundational Issues, Methodological Variations, and System Approaches," <it>Artificial Intelligence Communications</it> 7 (1994): 1, 39-52.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Rule-induction algorithms are procedures for learning rules for a given concept by generalizing from examples of that concept.  For example, a rule-induction algorithm might learn rules for forming the plural of English nouns from examples such as <it>dog/dogs</it>, <it>fly/flies</it>, and <it>ray/rays</it>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Roger Schank, Dynamic Memory: <it>A Theory of Learning in Computers and People</it> (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1982).</entry>
<entry id="4">
Janet Kolodner, "Reconstructive Memory: A Computer Model," <it>Cognitive Science</it> 7 (1983): 4.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Michael Lebowitz, "Memory-Based Parsing," <it>Artificial Intelligence</it> 21 (1983), 363-404.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Bill Mark, "Case-Based Reasoning for Autoclave Management," <it>Proceedings of the Case-Based Reasoning Workshop</it> (1989).</entry>
<entry id="7">
Trung Nguyen, Mary Czerwinski, and Dan Lee, "COMPAQ QuickSource: Providing the Consumer with the Power of Artificial Intelligence," in <it>Proceedings of the Fifth Annual Conference on Innovative Applications of Artificial Intelligence</it> (Washington, DC: AAAI Press, 1993), 142-151.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Acorn, T., and Walden, S., SMART: Support management automated reasoning technology for Compaq customer service. In Proceedings of the Tenth National Conference Conference on Artificial Intelligence. MIT Press. (1992).</entry>
<entry id="9">
Cheetham, W., Goebel, K., Appliance Call Center: A Successful Mixed-Initiative Case Study, Artificial Intelligence Magazine, Volume 28, No. 2, (2007). pp 89 – 100.</entry>
<entry id="10">
 Hinkle, D., and Toomey, C. N., CLAVIER: Applying case-based reasoning on to composite part fabrication. Proceeding of the Sixth Innovative Application of AI Conference, Seattle, WA, AAAI Press, (1994). pp. 55-62.</entry>
<entry id="11">
 Cheetham, W., Tenth Anniversary of Plastics Color Matching, Artificial Intelligence Magazine, Volume 26, No. 3, (2005). pp 51 – 61.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Watson, I. Gardingen, D. (1999). A Case-Based Reasoning System for HVAC Sales Support on the Web. In, the Knowledge Based Systems Journal, Vol. 12. no. 5-6, pp.207-214</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
For further reading</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Aamodt, Agnar, and Enric Plaza.  "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iiia.csic.es/People/enric/AICom.html">
Case-Based Reasoning: Foundational Issues, Methodological Variations, and System Approaches</weblink>"  <it>Artificial Intelligence Communications</it> 7, no. 1 (1994): 39-52.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Althoff, Klaus-Dieter, Ralph Bergmann, and L. Karl Branting, eds.  <it>Case-Based Reasoning Research and Development: Proceedings of the Third International Conference on Case-Based Reasoning</it>.  Berlin: Springer Verlag, 1999.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kolodner, Janet.  <it>Case-Based Reasoning</it>.  San Mateo: Morgan Kaufmann, 1993.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Leake, David. "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.indiana.edu/~leake/papers/p-96-01_dir.html/paper.html">
CBR in Context: The Present and Future</weblink>", In Leake, D., editor, Case-Based Reasoning: Experiences, Lessons, and Future Directions. AAAI Press/MIT Press, 1996, 1-30.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Leake, David, and Enric Plaza, eds.  <it>Case-Based Reasoning Research and Development: Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Case-Based Reasoning</it>.  Berlin: Springer Verlag, 1997.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(1998)&#32;in Lenz, Mario; Bartsch-Spörl, Brigitte; Burkhard, Hans-Dieter; Wess, Stefan: Case-Based Reasoning Technology: From Foundations to Applications, Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence&#32;<b>1400</b>.&#32;Springer. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/3-540-69351-3">
10.1007/3-540-69351-3</weblink>. ISBN 3-540-64572-1.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Riesbeck, Christopher, and Roger Schank.  <it>Inside Case-based Reasoning</it>.  Northvale, NJ: Erlbaum, 1989.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Veloso, Manuela, and Agnar Aamodt, eds.  <it>Case-Based Reasoning Research and Development: Proceedings of the First International Conference on Case-Based Reasoning</it>.  Berlin: Springer Verlag, 1995.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/1800740.xml">
Ian Watson</link>. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/bookdescription.cws_home/680655/description#description">
<it>Applying Case-Based Reasoning: Techniques for Enterprise Systems</it>. Elsevier, 1997.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

----
<it>An <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nupedia.com/article/465/">
earlier version</weblink> of the above article was posted on <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/21121.xml">
Nupedia</link></web_site>
.</it></p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</article>
