<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:01:36[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<theory  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105989479">
<header>
<title>History of Solar System formation and evolution hypotheses</title>
<id>17052696</id>
<revision>
<id>243641129</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T12:37:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Serendipodous</username>
<id>414691</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Solar System dynamic theories</category>
<category>History of physics</category>
<category>History of astronomy</category>
<category>Stellar astronomy</category>
<category>Solar System</category>
<category>Planetary science</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<it>"Capture theory" redirects here. For the solar capture theory, see this article's section on Solar System formation. For the lunar capture theory, see this article's section on lunar formation.</it> <p>

<image width="250 px" src="Pierre-Simon_Laplace.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Pierre-Simon Laplace, one of the originators of the nebular hypothesis
</caption>
</image>

Ideas concerning the origin and fate of the world date from the earliest known writings; however, for almost all of that time, there was no attempt to link such theories to the existence of a "Solar System", simply because almost no one knew or believed that the Solar System, in the sense we now understand it, existed. The first step towards a theory of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/6139438.xml">
Solar System formation</link> was the general acceptance of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../588/244588.xml">
heliocentrism</link>, the model which placed the Sun at the centre of the system and the Earth in orbit around it. This conception had been gestating for thousands of years, but was only widely accepted by the end of the 17th century. The first recorded use of the term "Solar System" dates from 1704.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> 
</p>
<sec>
<st>
Currently accepted hypotheses</st>
<p>

<image width="200px" src="Protoplanetary-disk.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Artist's conception of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/245432.xml">
protoplanetary disc</link>
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/6139438.xml">
Formation and evolution of the Solar System</link></it>
</indent>
The most widely accepted theory of planetary formation, known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/212374.xml">
nebular hypothesis</link>, maintains that 4.6 billion years ago, the Solar System formed from the gravitational collapse of a giant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/19895.xml">
molecular cloud</link> which was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/613987.xml">
light year</link>s across. Several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/26808.xml">
star</link>s, including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/26751.xml">
Sun</link>, formed within the collapsing cloud. The gas that formed the Solar System was slightly more massive than the Sun itself. Most of the mass collected in the centre, forming the Sun; the rest of the mass flattened into a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/245432.xml">
protoplanetary disc</link>, out of which the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/22915.xml">
planet</link>s and other bodies in the Solar System formed.</p>
<p>

Just as the Sun and planets were born, so they will eventually die. As the Sun begins to age, it will cool and bloat outward to many times its current diameter, becoming a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/56200.xml">
red giant</link>, before casting off its outer layers (forming what is misleadingly called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/39674.xml">
planetary nebula</link>) and becoming a stellar corpse known as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/33501.xml">
white dwarf</link>. The planets will follow the Sun's course; some will be destroyed, others will be ejected into interstellar space, but ultimately, given enough time, the Sun's retinue will eventually disappear.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Formation hypotheses</st>
<p>

The nebular hypothesis was first proposed in 1734 by <philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/224173.xml">
Emanuel Swedenborg</link></philosopher>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  and later elaborated and expanded upon by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/14631.xml">
Immanuel Kant</link></philosopher>
</person>
 in 1755. A similar theory was independently formulated by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/344783.xml">
Pierre-Simon Laplace</link></scientist>
 in 1796.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> </p>
<p>

In 1749, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/360039.xml">
Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon</link></scientist>
 conceived the idea that that the planets were formed when a comet collided with the Sun, sending matter out to form the planets. However, Laplace refuted this idea in 1796, showing that any planets formed in such a way would eventually crash into the Sun. Laplace felt that the near-circular orbits of the planets were a necessary consequence of their formation. Today, comets are known to be far too small to have created the Solar System in this way.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> </p>
<p>

In 1755, Immanuel Kant speculated that observed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/21664.xml">
nebulae</link> may in fact be regions of star and planet formation. In 1796, Laplace elaborated by arguing that the nebula collapsed into a star, and, as it did so, the remaining material gradually span outward into a flat disc, which then formed the planets.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Alternative theories</st>
<p>

The nebular hypothesis faced initial the obstacle of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/2839.xml">
angular momentum</link>; if the Sun had indeed formed from the collapse of such a cloud, the planets should be orbiting around it far more slowly. The Sun, though it contains almost 99.9 percent of the system's mass, contains just 1 percent of its angular momentum.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Attempts to resolve the angular momentum problem led to the temporary abandonment of the nebular hypothesis in favour of a return to "two-body" theories.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> For several decades, many astronomers preferred the <it>tidal</it> or <it>near-collision</it> hypothesis put forward by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/758413.xml">
James Jeans</link> in 1917, in which the planets were considered to have been formed due to the approach of some other star to the Sun. This near-miss would have drawn large amounts of matter out of the Sun and the other star by their mutual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/30719.xml">
tidal force</link>s, which could have then condensed into planets.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> However, in 1929 astronomer <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/878498.xml">
Harold Jeffreys</link></scientist>
 countered that such a near-collision was massively unlikely.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Objections to the hypothesis were also raised by the American astronomer <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/124021.xml">
Henry Norris Russell</link></scientist>
, who showed that it ran into problems with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/2839.xml">
angular momentum</link> for the outer planets, with the planets struggling to avoid being reabsorbed by the Sun.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

In 1944, the Soviet astronomer <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/858928.xml">
Otto Schmidt</link></scientist>
 proposed that the Sun, in its present form, passed through a dense <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/14979.xml">
interstellar cloud</link>, emerging enveloped in a cloud of dust and gas, from which the planets eventually formed. This solved the angular momentum problem by assuming that the Sun's slow rotation was peculiar to it, and that the planets did not form at the same time as the Sun.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> However, this hypothesis was severely dented by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/2069732.xml">
Victor Safronov</link> who showed that the amount of time required to form the planets from such a diffuse envelope would far exceed the Solar System's determined age.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> </p>
<p>

In 1960, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<astronomer wordnetid="109818343" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/69977.xml">
W. H. McCrea</link></educator>
</mathematician>
</professional>
</adult>
</astronomer>
</scientist>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
 proposed the <it>protoplanet theory</it>, in which the Sun and planets individually coalesced from matter within the same cloud, with the smaller planets later captured by the Sun's larger gravity.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> This theory has a number of issues, such as explaining the fact that the planets all orbit the Sun in the same direction, which would appear highly unlikely if they were each individually captured.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>   </p>
<p>

The <it>capture theory</it>, proposed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/4444520.xml">
M. M. Woolfson</link> in 1964, posits that the Solar System formed from <process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<consequence wordnetid="111410625" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/30719.xml">
tidal</link></consequence>
</phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>
 interactions between the Sun and a low-density <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/238646.xml">
protostar</link>. The Sun's gravity would have drawn material from the diffuse atmosphere of the protostar, which would then have collapsed to form the planets.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> However, the capture theory predicts a different age for the Sun than for the planets, whereas the similar ages of the Sun and the rest of the Solar System indicate that they formed at roughly the same time.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Reemergence of the nebular hypothesis</st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="200 px" src="HST_betaPictoris_comb.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Beta Pictoris seen by the Hubble Space Telescope
</caption>
</image>

In 1978, astronomer A. J. R. Prentice revived the Laplacian nebular model in his Modern Laplacian Theory by suggesting that the angular momentum problem could be resolved by drag created by dust grains in the original disc which slowed down the rotation in the centre.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> Prentice also suggested that the young Sun transferred some angular momentum to the protoplanetary disc and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/192500.xml">
planetesimals</link> through supersonic ejections understood to occur in <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/183932.xml">
T Tauri star</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> However, his contention that such formation would occur in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/74800.xml">
torus</link>es or rings has been questioned, as any such rings would disperse before collapsing into planets.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

The birth of the modern widely accepted theory of planetary formation&mdash;the Solar Nebular Disk Model (SNDM)&mdash;can be traced to the works of Soviet astronomer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/2069732.xml">
Victor Safronov</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> His book <it>Evolution of the protoplanetary cloud and formation of the Earth and the planets</it>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> which was translated to English in 1972, had a long-lasting effect on the way scientists thought about the formation of the planets.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> In this book almost all major problems of the planetary formation process were formulated and some of them solved. The Safronov's ideas were further developed in the works of <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/2170476.xml">
George Wetherill</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
, who discovered <it>runaway accretion</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> By the early 1980s, the nebular hypothesis in the form of SNDM had come back into favour, led by two major discoveries in astronomy. First, a number of apparently young stars, such as <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<recording wordnetid="104063868" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<sound_recording wordnetid="104262678" confidence="0.8">
<memory_device wordnetid="103744840" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<phonograph_record wordnetid="103924069" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/656713.xml">
Beta Pictoris</link></phonograph_record>
</device>
</memory_device>
</sound_recording>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</recording>
</system>
, were found to be surrounded by discs of cool dust, much as was predicted by the nebular hypothesis. Second, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/301728.xml">
Infrared Astronomical Satellite</link>, launched in 1983, observed that many stars had an excess of infrared radiation that could be explained if they were orbited by discs of cooler material. Most astronomers today believe that the Sun's loss of angular momentum can be explained by loss of its matter to space in a phenomenon similar to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/28538.xml">
solar wind</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Outstanding issues</st>
<p>

While the broad picture of the nebular hypothesis is widely accepted,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> many of the details are not well understood and continue to be refined.</p>
<p>

The refined nebular model was developed entirely on the basis of observations of our own Solar System because it was the only one known until the mid 1990s. It was not confidently assumed to be widely applicable to other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/252372.xml">
planetary systems</link>, although scientists were anxious to test the nebular model by finding of protoplanetary discs or even planets around other stars.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> As of March 2008, the discovery of nearly 280 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/9763.xml">
extrasolar planet</link>s<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> has turned up many surprises, and the nebular model must be revised to account for these discovered planetary systems, or new models considered. </p>
<p>

Among the extrasolar planets discovered to date are planets the size of Jupiter or larger but possessing very short orbital periods of only a few days. Such planets would have to orbit very closely to their stars; so closely that their atmospheres would be gradually stripped away by solar radiation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> There is no consensus on how to explain these so-called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/961349.xml">
hot Jupiters</link>, but one leading idea is that of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/1434249.xml">
planetary migration</link>, similar to the process which is thought to have moved Uranus and Neptune to their current, distant orbit. Possible processes that cause the migration include orbital friction while the protoplanetary disc is still full of hydrogen and helium gas<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>
and exchange of angular momentum between giant planets and the particles in the protoplanetary disc.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>
<p>

The detailed features of the planets are another problem.  The solar nebula hypothesis predicts that all planets will form exactly in the ecliptic plane.  Instead, the orbits of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/587247.xml">
classical planets</link> have various (but small) inclinations with respect to the ecliptic.  Furthermore, for the gas giants it is predicted that their rotations and moon systems will also not be inclined with respect to the ecliptic plane.  However most gas giants have substantial axial tilts with respect to the ecliptic, with <planet wordnetid="109394007" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/44475.xml">
Uranus</link></planet>
 having a 98° tilt.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref>   The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/19331.xml">
Moon</link> being relatively large with respect to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/9228.xml">
Earth</link> and other moons which are in irregular orbits with respect to their planet is yet another issue.  It is now believed these observations are explained by events which happened after the initial formation of the Solar System.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> For instance, the large axial tilts of many planets may be explained by giant impacts with massive planetesimals early in the Solar System's evolution.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Solar evolution hypotheses</st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="150 px" src="Eddington_2.jpeg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Arthur Eddington
</caption>
</image>

Attempts to isolate the physical source of the Sun's energy, and thus determine when and how it might ultimately run out, began in the 19th century.  At that time, the prevailing scientific view on the source of the Sun's heat was that it was generated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/619926.xml">
gravitational contraction</link>. In the 1840s, astronomers J. R. Mayer and J. J. Waterson first proposed that the Sun's massive weight causes it to collapse in on itself, generating heat, an idea expounded upon in 1854 by both <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/53311.xml">
Hermann von Helmholtz</link></scientist>
</person>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/33302.xml">
Lord Kelvin</link>, who further elaborated on the idea by suggesting that heat may also be produced by the impact of meteors onto the Sun's surface.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref> However, the Sun only has enough <link>
gravitational potential energy</link> to power its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/44790.xml">
luminosity</link> by this mechanism for about 30&nbsp;million years&mdash;far less than the age of the Earth. (This collapse time is known as the <link>
Kelvin-Helmholtz timescale</link>.)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref></p>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/736.xml">
Albert Einstein</link></scientist>
</person>
's development of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/30001.xml">
theory of relativity</link> in 1905 led to the understanding that nuclear reactions could create new elements from smaller precursors, with the loss of energy. In his treatise <it>Stars and Atoms</it>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
Arthur Eddington</link> suggested that pressures and temperatures within stars were great enough for hydrogen nucei to fuse into helium; a process which could produce the massive amounts of energy required to power the Sun.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref> In 1935, Eddington went further and suggested that other elements might also form within stars.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> Spectral evidence collected after 1945 showed that the distribution of the commonest chemical elements, carbon, hydrogen, oxygen, nitrogen, neon, iron etc, was fairly uniform across the galaxy. This suggested that these elements had a common origin.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> A number of anomalies in the proportions hinted at an underlying mechanism for creation. Lead is heavier than gold, but far more common. Hydrogen and helium (elements 1 and 2) are virtually ubiquitous yet lithium and beryllium (elements 3 and 4) are extremely rare.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> 
</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Red giants</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/56200.xml">
Red giant</link></it>
</indent>
While the unusual spectra of red giant stars had been known since the 19th century,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> it was <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/74641.xml">
George Gamow</link></scientist>
 who, in the 1940s, first understood that they were stars of roughly solar mass that had run out of hydrogen in their cores and had resorted to burning the hydrogen in their outer shells. This allowed <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<astronomer wordnetid="109818343" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/726410.xml">
Martin Schwarzschild</link></astronomer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
 to drew the connection between red giants and the finite lifespans of stars. It is now understood that red giants are stars in the last stages of their life cycles.</p>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/British_R$ail_11001.xml">
Fred Hoyle</link></scientist>
</person>
 noted that, even while the distribution of elements was fairly uniform, different stars had varying amounts of each element. To Hoyle, this indicated that they must have originated within the stars themselves. The abundance of elements peaked around the atomic number for iron, an element that could only have been formed under intense pressures and temperatures. Hoyle concluded that iron must have formed within giant stars.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> From this, in 1945 and 1946, Hoyle constructed the final stages of a star's life cycle. As the star dies, it collapses under its own weight, leading to a stratified chain of fusion reactions: carbon-12 fuses with helium to form oxygen-16; oxygen-16 fuses with helium to produce neon-20, and so on up to iron.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref> There was, however, no known method by which carbon-12 could be produced. Isotopes of beryllium produced via fusion were too unstable to form carbon, and for three helium atoms to form carbon-12 was so unlikely as to have been impossible over the age of the universe. However, in 1952 the physicist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/864749.xml">
Ed Salpeter</link> showed that a short enough time existed between the formation and the decay of the beryllium isotope that another helium had a small chance to form carbon, but only if their combined mass/energy amounts were equal to that of carbon-12. Hoyle, employing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/2792.xml">
anthropic principle</link>, showed that it must be so, since he himself was made of carbon, and he existed. When the matter/energy level of carbon-12 was finally determined, it was found to be within a few percent of Hoyle's prediction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
White dwarfs</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/33501.xml">
White dwarf</link></it>
</indent>
The first white dwarf discovered was in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../963/240963.xml">
triple star system</link> of <natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<celestial_body wordnetid="109239740" confidence="0.8">
<star wordnetid="109444100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/414048.xml">
40 Eridani</link></star>
</celestial_body>
</natural_object>
, which contains the relatively bright <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/19605.xml">
main sequence</link> star <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/414048.xml">
40 Eridani A</link>, orbited at a distance by the closer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/52713.xml">
binary system</link> of the white dwarf <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/414048.xml">
40 Eridani B</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/19605.xml">
main sequence</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/56099.xml">
red dwarf</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/414048.xml">
40 Eridani C</link>.  The pair 40 Eridani B/C was discovered by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/33971.xml">
Friedrich Wilhelm Herschel</link> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/15793.xml">
January 31</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/35523.xml">
1783</link>;<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref>, p. 73 it was again observed by <link>
Friedrich Georg Wilhelm Struve</link> in 1825 and by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../595/622595.xml">
Otto Wilhelm von Struve</link> in 1851.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref>  In 1910, it was discovered by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/124021.xml">
Henry Norris Russell</link></scientist>
, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/459404.xml">
Edward Charles Pickering</link></scientist>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/253620.xml">
Williamina Fleming</link> that despite being a dim star, 40 Eridani B was of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/28927.xml">
spectral type</link> A, or white.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref></p>
<p>

White dwarfs were found to be extremely dense soon after their discovery.  If a star is in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/52713.xml">
binary</link> system, as is the case for Sirius B and 40 Eridani B, it is possible to estimate its mass from observations of the binary orbit.  This was done for Sirius B by 1910,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref> yielding a mass estimate of 0.94 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/172987.xml">
solar mass</link>.  (A more modern estimate is 1.00 solar mass.)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2237%22])">37</ref>  Since hotter bodies radiate more than colder ones, a star's surface brightness can be estimated from its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/1460629.xml">
effective surface temperature</link>, and hence from its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/29329.xml">
spectrum</link>.   If the star's distance is known, its overall luminosity can also be estimated.  Comparison of the two figures yields the star's radius.  Reasoning of this sort led to the realization, puzzling to astronomers at the time, that Sirius B and 40 Eridani B must be very dense.  For example, when <link>
Ernst Öpik</link> estimated the density of a number of visual binary stars in 1916, he found that 40 Eridani B had a density of over 25,000 times the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/26751.xml">
Sun</link>'s, which was so high that he called it "impossible".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2238%22])">38</ref></p>
<p>

Such densities are possible because white dwarf material is not composed of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/902.xml">
atom</link>s bound by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/5993.xml">
chemical bond</link>s, but rather consists of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/3532455.xml">
plasma</link> of unbound <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/54411.xml">
nuclei</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/9476.xml">
electron</link>s.  There is therefore no obstacle to placing nuclei closer to each other than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/1206.xml">
electron orbital</link>s&mdash;the regions occupied by electrons bound to an atom&mdash;would normally allow.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref> Eddington, however, wondered what would happen when this plasma cooled and the energy which kept the atoms ionized was no longer present.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref>  This paradox was resolved by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../966/718966.xml">
R. H. Fowler</link> in 1926 by an application of the newly devised <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanics</link>.  Since electrons obey the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/24669.xml">
Pauli exclusion principle</link></concept>
</idea>
, no two electrons can occupy the same <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/279638.xml">
state</link>, and they must obey <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/159225.xml">
Fermi-Dirac statistics</link>, also introduced in 1926 to determine the statistical distribution of particles which satisfy the Pauli exclusion principle.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2241%22])">41</ref>  At zero temperature, therefore, electrons could not all occupy the lowest-energy, or <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/4930033.xml">
ground</link></it>, state; some of them had to occupy higher-energy states, forming a band of lowest-available energy states, the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/182445.xml">
Fermi sea</link></it>. This state of the electrons, called <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/144428.xml">
degenerate</link></it>, meant that a white dwarf could cool to zero temperature and still possess high energy.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Planetary nebulae</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/39674.xml">
Planetary nebula</link></it>
</indent>
<image location="left" width="200px" src="NGC7293_(2004).jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

NGC 7293, The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/206634.xml">
Helix Nebula</link>
</caption>
</image>

Planetary nebulae are generally faint objects, and none are visible to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/293540.xml">
naked eye</link>.  The first planetary nebula discovered was the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/336123.xml">
Dumbbell Nebula</link> in the constellation of <configuration wordnetid="105731779" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/211517.xml">
Vulpecula</link></configuration>
, observed by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<astronomer wordnetid="109818343" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/7246.xml">
Charles Messier</link></associate>
</astronomer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</person>
</physicist>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 in 1764 and listed as M27 in his <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<catalog wordnetid="106487897" confidence="0.8">
<list wordnetid="106481320" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/20608.xml">
catalogue</link></database>
</list>
</catalog>
</information>
</message>
 of nebulous objects. To early observers with low-resolution telescopes, M27 and subsequently discovered planetary nebulae somewhat resembled the gas giants, and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/33971.xml">
William Herschel</link></scientist>
, discoverer of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/44475.xml">
Uranus</link>, eventually coined the term 'planetary nebula' for them, although, as we now know, they are very different from planets.</p>
<p>

The central stars of planetary nebulae are very hot. Their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/44790.xml">
luminosity</link>, though, is very low, implying that they must be very small. Only once a star has exhausted all its nuclear fuel can it collapse to such a small size, and so planetary nebulae came to be understood as a final stage of stellar evolution. Spectroscopic observations show that all planetary nebulae are expanding, and so the idea arose that planetary nebulae were caused by a star's outer layers being thrown into space at the end of its life.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Lunar origins hypotheses</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/51143.xml">
Giant impact hypothesis</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</psychological_feature>
</theory>
</explanation>
</event>
</thinking>
</process>
</it>
</indent>
<image width="150 px" src="George_Darwin_sepia_tone.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

George Darwin
</caption>
</image>

Over the centuries, many scientific hypotheses have been advanced concerning the origin of Earth's Moon. One of the earliest was the so-called <it>binary accretion</it> model, which concluded that the Moon accreted from material in orbit around the Earth left over from its formation. Another, the <it>fission model</it>, was developed by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/589626.xml">
George Darwin</link></scientist>
</person>
, (son of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/8145410.xml">
Charles Darwin</link></scientist>
</person>
) who noted that, as the Moon is gradually receding from the Earth at a rate of about 4&nbsp;cm per year, so at one point in the distant past it must have been part of the Earth, but was flung outward by the momentum of Earth's then&ndash;much faster rotation. This hypothesis is also supported by the fact that the Moon's density, while less than Earth's, is about equal to that of Earth's rocky <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/1079866.xml">
mantle</link>, suggesting that, unlike the Earth, it lacks a dense iron core. A third hypothesis, known as the <it>capture model</it>, suggested that the Moon was an independently orbiting body that had been snared into orbit by Earth's gravity.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
<it>Apollo</it> missions</st>
<p>

However, these hypotheses were all refuted by the <it><work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<announcement wordnetid="106746580" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106748466" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/1461.xml">
Apollo</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</program>
</announcement>
</message>
</statement>
</work>
</it> lunar missions, which introduced a stream of new scientific evidence; specifically concerning the Moon's composition, its age, and its history. These lines of evidence contradict many predictions made by these earlier models.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref> The rocks brought back from the Moon showed a marked decrease in water relative to rocks elsewhere in the Solar System, and also evidence of an ocean of magma early in its history, indicating that its formation must have produced a great deal of energy. Also, oxygen <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/19600416.xml">
isotope</link>s in lunar rocks showed a marked similarity to those on Earth, suggesting that they formed at a similar location in the solar nebula. The capture model fails to explain the similarity in these isotopes (if the Moon had originated in another part of the Solar System, those isotopes would have been different), while the co-accretion model cannot adequately explain the loss of water (if the Moon formed in a similar fashion to the Earth, the amount of water trapped in its mineral structure would also be roughly similar). Conversely, the fission model, while it can account for the similarity in chemical composition and the lack of iron in the Moon, cannot adequately explain its high orbital inclination and, in particular, the large amount of angular momentum in the Earth/Moon system, more than any other planet&ndash;satellite pair in the Solar System.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref>
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Giant impact hypothesis</st>
<p>

For many years after <it>Apollo</it>, the binary accretion model was settled on as the best hypothesis for explaining the Moon's origins, even though it was known to be flawed. Then, at a conference in Kona, Hawaii in 1984, a compromise model was composed that accounted for all of the observed discrepencies. Originally formulated by two independent research groups in 1976, the <it>giant impact</it> model supposed that a massive planetary object, the size of Mars, had collided with Earth early in its history. The impact would have melted Earth's crust, and the other planet's heavy core would have sunk inward and merged with Earth's. The superheated vapour produced by the impact would have risen into orbit around the planet, coalescing into the Moon. This explained the lack of water (the vapour cloud was too hot for water to condense), the similarity in composition (since the Moon had formed from part of the Earth), the lower density (since the Earth had formed from the Earth's crust and mantle, rather than its core, and the Moon's unusual orbit (since an oblique strike would have imparted a massive amount of angular momentum to the Earth/Moon system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref>
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Outstanding issues</st>
<p>

However, the giant impact model has been criticised for being too explanatory; it can be expanded to explain any future discoveries and as such, makes no predictions. Also, many claim that much of the material from the impactor would have ended up in the Moon, meaning that the isotope levels would be different, but they are not. Also, while water and many other volatile compounds are absent from the Moon's crust, many others, such as manganese, are not.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other natural satellites</st>
<p>

While the co-accretion and capture models are not currently accepted as valid explanations for the existence of the Moon, they have been employed to explain the formation of other natural satellites in the Solar System. <planet wordnetid="109394007" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/38930.xml">
Jupiter</link></planet>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/12505.xml">
Galilean satellites</link> are believed to have formed via co-accretion,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2243%22])">43</ref> while the Solar System's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/6109428.xml">
irregular satellites</link>, such as <planet wordnetid="109394007" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/44371.xml">
Triton</link></planet>
, are all believed to have been captured.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2244%22])">44</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=solar+system&amp;searchmode=none">
"Solar"</weblink>".&#32;<it>etymoline</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 Swedenborg, Emanuel. 1734, (Principia) Latin: Opera Philosophica et Mineralia (English: Philosophical and Mineralogical Works), (Principia, Volume 1) </entry>
<entry id="3">
  <cite style="font-style:normal">See, T. J. J.&#32;(1909).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0003-049X%28190901%2F04%2948%3A191%3C119%3ATPHOTE%3E2.0.CO%3B2-U&amp;size=LARGE">
The Past History of the Earth as Inferred from the Mode of Formation of the Solar System</weblink>". <it>Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society</it>&#32;<b>48</b>: 119. Retrieved on <link>
2006-07-23</link>.</cite>&nbsp; </entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">M. M. Woolfson&#32;(1993).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/cgi-bin/nph-iarticle_query?bibcode=1993QJRAS..34....1W&amp;db_key=AST&amp;page_ind=0&amp;data_type=GIF&amp;type=SCREEN_VIEW&amp;classic=YES">
The Solar System: Its Origin and Evolution</weblink>". <it>Journal of the Royal Astronomical Society</it>&#32;<b>34</b>: 1-20. Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-16</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Woolfson, M. M.&#32;(1984).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1984RSPTA.313....5W">
Rotation in the Solar System</weblink>". <it>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London</it>&#32;<b>313</b>: 5.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Benjamin Crowell&#32;(1998-2006).&#32;"5", <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lightandmatter.com/html_books/2cl/ch05/ch05.html">
Conservation Laws</weblink>.&#32;lightandmatter.com.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">J. R. Dormand &amp; M. M. Woolfson&#32;(1971).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/full/1971MNRAS.151..307D">
The capture theory and planetary condensation</weblink>". <it>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</it>&#32;<b>151</b>: 307. Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-16</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Weidenschilling, S. J.; Spaute, D.; Davis, D. R.; Marzari, F.; Ohtsuki, K.&#32;(1997).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1997Icar..128..429W">
Accretional Evolution of a Planetesimal Swarm</weblink>". <it>Icarus</it>&#32;<b>128</b>: 429&ndash;455. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006%2Ficar.1997.5747">
10.1006/icar.1997.5747</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-13</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Prentice, A. J. R.&#32;(1978).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1978M%26P....19..341P">
Origin of the solar system. I - Gravitational contraction of the turbulent protosun and the shedding of a concentric system of gaseous Laplacian rings</weblink>". <it>Moon and Planets</it>&#32;<b>19</b>: 341&ndash;398.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ferreira, J.;  Dougados, C.; Cabrit, S.&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2006A%26A...453..785F">
Which jet launching mechanism(s) in T Tauri stars?</weblink>". <it>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</it>&#32;<b>453</b>: 785. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1051%2F0004-6361%3A20054231">
10.1051/0004-6361:20054231</weblink>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/38751.xml">
ar&amp;Chi;iv</link>:.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
Nigel Henbest&#32;(1991).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://space.newscientist.com/channel/solar-system/comets-asteroids/mg13117837.100">
Birth of the planets: The Earth and its fellow planets may be survivors from a time when planets ricocheted around the Sun like ball bearings on a pinball table</weblink>".&#32;  New Scientist.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite id="Reference-Safronov-1972" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Safronov, Viktor Sergeevich&#32;(1972). Evolution of the Protoplanetary Cloud and Formation of the Earth and the Planets.&#32;Israel Program for
Scientific Translations. ISBN 0706512251.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">George W. Wetherill&#32;(1989).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/full/1989Metic..24..347W">
Leonard Medal Citation for Victor Sergeevich Safronov</weblink>". <it>Meteoritics</it>&#32;<b>24</b>: 347.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
e. g. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Kokubo, Eiichiro; Ida, Shigeru&#32;(2002).&#32;"Formation of Protoplanet Systems and Diversity of Planetary Systems". <it>Astrophysical Journal</it>&#32;<b>581</b>: 666. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086%2F344105">
10.1086/344105</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Lissauer, J. J.&#32;(2006). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2006ASPC..357...31L">
Planet Formation, Protoplanetary Disks and Debris Disks</weblink>".&#32;L. Armus and W. T. Reach, eds.&#32;<it>The Spitzer Space Telescope: New Views of the Cosmos</it>&#32;<b>357</b>, Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Zeilik-1998" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Zeilik, Michael A.&#32;(1998). Introductory Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, 4th,&#32;Saunders College Publishing. ISBN 0030062284.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</entry>
<entry id="15">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://planetquest.jpl.nasa.gov/TPF/tpf_signsOfLife.cfm">
Planet Quest, Terrestrial Planet Finder</weblink>".&#32;<it>NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="17">
Weaver, D.; Villard, R.&#32;(2007-01-31).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hubblesite.org/newscenter/archive/releases/2007/07/full/">
Hubble Probes Layer-cake Structure of Alien World's Atmosphere</weblink>".&#32;<it>University of Arizona, Lunar and Planetary Laboratory (Press Release)</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-08-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="16">
Jean Schneider.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://exoplanet.eu">
The extrasolar planets encyclopedia</weblink>".&#32;<it>Paris University</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="19">
Benjamin Crowell&#32;(2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lightandmatter.com/html_books/3vw/ch02/ch02.html">
Vibrations and Waves</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="18">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ballester, Gilda E.; Sing, David K.; Herbert, Floyd&#32;(2007).&#32;"The signature of hot hydrogen in the atmosphere of the extrasolar planet HD 209458b". <it>Nature</it>&#32;<b>445</b>: 511. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature05525">
10.1038/nature05525</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="21">
  <cite id="CITEREFLissauer2006" style="font-style:normal">Lissauer, J. J.&#32;(2006),&#32;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2006ASPC..357...31L">
"Planet Formation, Protoplanetary Disks and Debris Disks"</weblink>, in&#32;L. Armus and W. T. Reach,&#32;<it>The Spitzer Space Telescope: New Views of the Cosmos</it>, <b>357</b>, Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series, p. 31, </cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Tsiganis, K.; Gomes, R.; Morbidelli, A.; Levison, H. F.&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v435/n7041/full/nature03539.html">
Origin of the orbital architecture of the giant planets of the Solar System</weblink>". <it>Nature</it>&#32;<b>435</b>&#32;(7041): 459. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature03539">
10.1038/nature03539</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="23">
Heidi B. Hammel&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.apl.ucl.ac.uk/iopw/uworkshop_060905.pdf">
Uranus nears Equinox</weblink>".&#32;<it>Pasadena Workshop</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="22">
"&amp;gt; <cite style="font-style:normal">Fogg, M. J.; Nelson, R. P.&#32;(2007).&#32;"On the formation of terrestrial planets in hot-Jupiter systems". <it>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</it>&#32;<b>461</b>: 1195. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1051%2F0004-6361%3A20066171">
10.1051/0004-6361:20066171</weblink>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/38751.xml">
ar&amp;Chi;iv</link>:.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="25">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Adrián Brunini&#32;(April 2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v440/n7088/full/nature04577.html">
Origin of the obliquities of the giant planets in mutual interactions in the early Solar System</weblink>". <it>Nature</it>&#32;<b>440</b>&#32;(7088): 1163-1165. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature04577">
10.1038/nature04577</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="24">
Frank Crary&#32;(1998).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nineplanets.org/origin.html">
The Origin of the Solar System</weblink>".&#32;<it>Colorado University, Boulder</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="27">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Carl J. Hansen, Steven D. Kawaler, and Virgina Trimble&#32;(2004). Stellar interiors: physical principles, structure, and evolution.&#32;New York:&#32;Springer,&#32;p. 4. ISBN 0-387-20089-4.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="26">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">David Whitehouse&#32;(2005). The Sun: A Biography.&#32;John Wiley and Sons.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="29">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Oscar Straniero, Roberto Gallino, and Sergio Cristallo&#32;(17 October 2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6TVB-4FD0HVC-1&amp;_user=10&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=e850d0d6d39c1d52c950b793d68e59eb">
s process in low-mass asymptotic giant branch stars</weblink>". <it>Nuclear Physics A</it>&#32;<b>777</b>. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/doi%3A10.1016%2Fj.nuclphysa.2005.01.011">
doi:10.1016/j.nuclphysa.2005.01.011</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-02</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="28">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Simon Mitton&#32;(2005).&#32;"Origin of the Chemical Elements", Fred Hoyle: A Life in Science.&#32;Aurum,&#32;197-222.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="31">
The Nuclear Physics Group.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.np.ph.bham.ac.uk/research/anthropic.htm">
Life, Bent Chains, and the Anthropic Principle</weblink>".&#32;<it>The University of Birmingham</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-21</link>.</entry>
<entry id="30">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">J. Faulkner&#32;(2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2003Ap&amp;SS.285..339F">
Fred Hoyle, Red Giants and beyond</weblink>". <it>Astrophysics and Space Science</it>&#32;<b>285</b>&#32;(2): 339-339. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023%2FA%3A1025432324828">
10.1023/A:1025432324828</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="34">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1974AJ.....79..819H">
Astrometric study of four visual binaries</weblink>, W. D. Heintz, <it>Astronomical Journal</it> <b>79</b>, #7 (July 1974), pp. 819&ndash;825.</entry>
<entry id="35">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2005AAS...20720501H">
How Degenerate Stars Came to be Known as White Dwarfs</weblink>, J. B. Holberg, <it>Bulletin of the American Astronomical Society</it> <b>37</b> (December 2005),  p. 1503.</entry>
<entry id="32">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0261-0523(1785)75%3C40%3ACODSBW%3E2.0.CO%3B2-P">
Catalogue of Double Stars</weblink>, William Herschel, <it>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London</it> <b>75</b> (1785), pp. 40&ndash;126</entry>
<entry id="33">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1926BAN.....3..128V">
 The orbit and the masses of 40 Eridani BC</weblink>, W. H. van den Bos, <it>Bulletin of the Astronomical Institutes of the Netherlands</it> <b>3</b>, #98 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/15874.xml">
July 8</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/34609.xml">
1926</link>), pp. 128&ndash;132.</entry>
<entry id="38">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1916ApJ....44..292O">
The Densities of Visual Binary Stars</weblink>, E. Öpik, <it>The Astrophysical Journal</it> <b>44</b> (December 1916), pp. 292&ndash;302.</entry>
<entry id="39">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1924MNRAS..84..308E">
On the relation between the masses and luminosities of the stars</weblink>, A. S. Eddington, <it>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</it> <b>84</b> (March 1924), pp. 308&ndash;332.</entry>
<entry id="36">
<it>Preliminary General Catalogue</it>, L. Boss, Washington, D.C.: Carnegie Institution, 1910.</entry>
<entry id="37">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/w2005ApJ...630L..69L">
The Age and Progenitor Mass of Sirius B</weblink>, James Liebert, Patrick A. Young, David Arnett, J. B. Holberg, and Kurtis A. Williams, <it>The Astrophysical Journal</it> <b>630</b>, #1 (September 2005), pp. L69&ndash;L72.</entry>
<entry id="42">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Paul D. Spudis&#32;(1996).&#32;"Whence the Moon?", The Once and Future Moon.&#32;Smithsonian Institution Press,&#32;157-169.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="43">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Robin M. Canup and William R. Ward&#32;(2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iop.org/EJ/abstract/1538-3881/124/6/3404/">
Formation of the Galilean Satellites: Conditions of Accretion</weblink>"&#32;<b>124</b>: 3404-3423. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086%2F344684">
10.1086/344684</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-22</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="40">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1926MNRAS..87..114F">
On Dense Matter</weblink>, R. H. Fowler, <it>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</it> <b>87</b> (1926), pp. 114&ndash;122.</entry>
<entry id="41">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0080-4630%2819800610%29371%3A1744%3C8%3ATDOTQM%3E2.0.CO%3B2-K">
The Development of the Quantum Mechanical Electron Theory of Metals: 1900-28</weblink>, Lillian H. Hoddeson and G. Baym, <it>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series A, Mathematical and Physical Sciences</it> <b>371</b>, #1744 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/15805.xml">
June 10</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/34640.xml">
1980</link>), pp. 8&ndash;23.</entry>
<entry id="44">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">David Nesvorný, David Vokrouhlický and Alessandro Morbidelli&#32;(2007).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iop.org/EJ/abstract/1538-3881/133/5/1962">
Capture of Irregular Satellites during Planetary Encounters</weblink>". <it>The Astronomical Journal</it>&#32;<b>133</b>: 1962-1976. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086%2F512850">
10.1086/512850</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-22</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</theory>
</article>
