<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 03:58:27[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<sport  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100523513">
<web_site  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106359193">
<header>
<title>Fanball</title>
<id>17086012</id>
<revision>
<id>242424374</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T04:46:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Fantasy sports</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Website</name>
<parameters>
<logo>
<image width="150px" src="Fanball.jpg">
<caption>

Fanball.jpg
</caption>
</image>
</logo>
<type>
Fantasy Sports</type>
<registration>
Required to play</registration>
<current_status>
Active</current_status>
<url>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com">
www.fanball.com</weblink></url>
<launch_date>
1993</launch_date>
<name>
Fanball.com</name>
<owner>
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/523905.xml">
Liberty Media Corporation</link></institution>
</company>
</owner>
<commercial>
Yes</commercial>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

Fanball is a company based in St. Louis, Missouri, that specializes in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/10653.xml">
fantasy sport</link>s products.  Fanball provides commissioner, fantasy games, and fantasy content for baseball, football, basketball, hockey, auto racing, and golf.  Fanball.com consists of products from the acquisition by FUN Technologies of the companies Fanball.com, CDMsports.com, and FantasyCup.com in 2005-2006 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.  FUN Technologies was purchased by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/523905.xml">
Liberty Media Corporation</link></institution>
</company>
 in December of 2007 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.  </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Company History </st>

<p>

Fanball.com, founded in 1993, is known as the Ultimate Fantasy Sports Experience™. Its fantasy sports offerings include games, league management tools, and comprehensive fantasy sports content provided by Fanball.com’s own team of expert fantasy sports beat writers. Fanball also produces baseball, football, and NASCAR magazines <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>.
CBC Distribution and Marketing (CDMsports.com) was launched in December 1991 and offered a salary cap baseball and basketball game in 1992.  In October of 1993, a deal was struck between The Sporting News and CBC to offer salary cap, rotisserie scoring-based baseball, football, basketball, and hockey games branded The Sporting News and operated by CBC.  In late 1994 through 1995, CBC launched CDMsports.com and began to move all of their games to the Internet.  In 1999, CDMsports.com became a founding member of the Fantasy Sports Trade Association <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.   In 2001, CDMsports.com bought TQstats.com and Rototimes.com.  In 2005 CDMsports.com filed a lawsuit against MLB Advanced Media for the right to use player statistics without a license <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>.  CDMsports.com operates over 50 fantasy games.  In 2006, CDMsports.com sold to FUN Technologies <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>. </p>
<p>

Fantasy Sports, Inc. (FantasyCup.com) was launched in the spring of 1993 and remains one of the oldest and largest providers of predominantly fee-based fantasy sports games, accessible through the website at www.fantasycup.com. The company ran highly successful NASCAR Sprint Cup and Nationwide race challenges, as well as a college football season challenge. FantasyCup.com also ran successful March Madness Basketball, British and US Open Golf, NHRA, and Fantasy Surfing games. In October 1999, FantasyCup.com was acquired by Action Performance Companies Inc. as part of the goracing.com initiative. In November 2000, FantasyCup.com was sold to marketing company Silverstar Holdings, Ltd. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. In 2003, Fantasy Sports, Inc. became the first Official NASCAR licensed Fantasy Game provider. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> In 2005, FantasyCup.com was sold to FUN Technologies.</p>
<p>

Fanball offers fantasy games in several sports.  The company also offers several types of games for each sport.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Fantasy Game Summary </st>

<ss1>
<st>
Baseball</st>

<p>

Fanball offers a variety of fantasy baseball games for all levels of competition and style.  There are ten challenge-style games of varying cost and design and one draft-and-play-style game with six price points as well as a commissioner service for people looking for a website to host their local fantasy baseball league.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://diamondchallenge.fanball.com">
The Diamond Challenge</weblink> game allows participants to manage a 28-player starting lineup using a $30 million salary cap and a 12-player taxi squad.  There are six ways to win cash prizes, including overall, division, league, field, all-star break and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize winner takes home $25,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the start of the MLB season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All-Star game.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://internetchallenge.fanball.com">
Internet Challenge Fantasy Baseball</weblink> is a rotisserie-style game that allows player changes twice a week.  Participants manage a 28-player starting lineup using a $30 million salary cap and a 12-player taxi squad.  Participants can win prizes via overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize winner wins $10,000.  There is an entry fee plus nominal transaction fees involved.  This game is played via the Internet only.  The game runs from the start of the MLB season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All-Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hrbaseball.fanball.com">
High Roller Fantasy Baseball</weblink> is a high-risk, high-reward Rotisserie-style fantasy baseball game with a $1,000 entry fee, but no transaction fees.  Participants manage a 28-player starting lineup using a $30 million salary cap and a 12-player taxi squad.  Cash prizes are awarded for overall and league competition.  The Grand Prize winner wins $25,000 and the winner of each 20-team league wins $4,000.  The game runs from the start of the MLB season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ptsbaseball.fanball.com">
Fantasy Baseball 2008</weblink> allows participants to manage a 28-player starting lineup using a $60 million salary cap and a 12-player bench.  There are three ways to win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $15,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the start of the MLB season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://budgetbaseball.fanball.com">
Budget Baseball</weblink> uses point-style scoring.  Participants manage a team of 28 major leaguers using a $60 million salary cap.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $5,000.  This game is played via the Internet only, and runs from the start of the MLB season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://freebaseball.fanball.com">
Free Fantasy Baseball</weblink> is a free-to-enter fantasy baseball game where participants select and manage a team of 28 MLB players within the constraints of a $60 million salary cap and limited roster moves.  Participants can make one free move each week.  Up to an additional 120 moves can be made for a nominal fee.  There are four ways to win prizes, including overall, division, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $5,000.  This game is played via the Internet only.  The game runs from the start of the MLB season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://baseballbracket.fanball.com">
Pick’em 64 Superstar Baseball</weblink> is a six-round bracket game featuring 64 of baseball’s best sluggers and is free to play. Points are awarded for each correct winning hitter selection, which is based on total bases for each round that runs one week. The number of points awarded increases as the tournament progresses. Prizes are awarded for overall, state, and league competitions. The game runs from June 2 through July 13.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://2ndseason.fanball.com">
Diamond Challenge – 2nd Season</weblink> is the mid-season version of Diamond Challenge Fantasy Baseball.  The Grand Prize is $10,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from Monday, May 26, until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game.</p>
<p>

Mid-Season Fantasy Baseball 2008 is the mid-season version of Fantasy Baseball 2008.  The Grand Prize is $10,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game begins with the first MLB game after the All-Star Break and ends with the last game of the regular season.</p>
<p>

Diamond Challenge Playoff is the post-season version of the Diamond Challenge but without player salaries and a salary cap.  Cash prizes are awarded for overall and league competitions.  The Grand Prize is $5,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game begins with the start of the MLB playoffs and runs until the last game of the World Series.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://superchallenge.fanball.com">
Super Challenge Fantasy Baseball</weblink> is Fanball’s way of determining who is the best fantasy baseball team owner on the planet.  Participants with entries in each of four identified fantasy baseball games compete for prizes, which are awarded to the top 25 entries with the lowest overall combined ranking.  The Grand Prize is $250 and a free entry to the following year’s High Roller Fantasy Baseball game.  There is no direct entry fee.  The game runs from the start of the MLB season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/draftandplay?ArenaID=2">
Draft and Play Fantasy Baseball</weblink> is a fantasy baseball game that features 10-team leagues and live online drafts.  Participants draft and manage a team of 22 starters and six reserves, and compete using either Rotisserie-style or point-style scoring.  Prizes are awarded for league competition based on six levels of play with varying entry fees and prizes.  This game is played via the Internet only.  The game runs from the start of the MLB season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/leaguecommissioner?ArenaID=2">
Commissioner MLB</weblink> is a private baseball league manager service and offers a website to manage local leagues for as low as $49.95.  Users can define the league rules and scoring categories while providing stat results, standings, player trades, waiver wire claims, and league finances.  Message boards are also provided so participants can communicate with other league members.  Toll-free customer support is provided as well as email support seven days per week.  This is an Internet-only service.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Basketball</st>

<p>

Fanball offers a variety of fantasy basketball games for all levels of competition and style.  There are four challenge-style games of varying cost and design and one draft-and-play-style game as well as a commissioner service for fantasy players looking for a website to host their local fantasy basketball league.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rotobasketball.fanball.com">
The Fantasy Basketball Challenge</weblink> is a high-risk, high-reward full-service Rotisserie-style basketball game.  Participants manage a 15-player starting lineup using a $30 million salary cap and a 10-player taxi squad.  There are five ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, division, league, field, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $10,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the start of the NBA season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://freebasketball.fanball.com">
 Free Fantasy Basketball</weblink> is a point-style fantasy basketball game.  Participants manage a team of 15 pro basketball players within the constraints of a $60 million salary cap and limited roster moves.  It is free to enter and participants can make one free move each week.  Up to an additional 120 moves can be made for a nominal fee.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, division, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $3,000.  This game is played via the Internet only.  The game runs from the start of the NBA season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pobasketball.fanball.com">
The Playoff Basketball Challenge</weblink> is the post-season version of the Fantasy Basketball Challenge game but without player salaries and a salary cap.  Cash prizes are awarded for overall and league competitions.  The Grand Prize is $5,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game begins with the start of the NBA playoffs and runs through the last game of the NBA Finals. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/draftandplay?ArenaID=4">
Draft and Play Fantasy Basketball</weblink> is a fantasy basketball game that features 10-team leagues and live online drafts.  Participants draft and manage a team of 10 starters and five reserves, and compete using an easy point-style scoring system.  Prizes are awarded for league competition.  There is an entry fee to participate, but no transaction fees.  The game runs from the start of the NBA season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pickem64.fanball.com">
Pick’em 64 Basketball Tournament</weblink> is a six-round bracket game for the Division I Men’s College Basketball Tournament that is free to play.  Points are awarded for each correct winning team selection.  The number of points awarded increases as the tournament progresses.  Prizes are awarded for overall, state, and league competitions.  The Grand Prize is $2,500.  The game runs from the start of the tournament through the championship game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/leaguecommissioner?ArenaID=4">
Commissioner NBA</weblink> is a private basketball league manager service and offers a website to manage participants’ local league throughout the NBA season.  Participants define the league rules and scoring categories while we provide stat results, standings, player trades, waiver wire claims, and league finances.  Message boards are also provided so participants can communicate with other league members.  Toll-free customer support is provided as well as email support seven days per week.  This is an Internet-only service.  Participants may signup a league at any time until the end of the regular season. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Football</st>

<p>

Fanball offers a variety of fantasy football games for all levels of competition and style.  There are nine challenge-style games of varying cost and design and one draft-and-play-style game with six price points as well as a commissioner service for people looking for a website to host their local fantasy football league.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rotofootball.fanball.com">
The Football Challenge</weblink> is a high-risk, high-reward full-service Rotisserie-style football game.  Participants manage a 20-player starting lineup using a $30 million salary cap and a 10-player taxi squad.  There are five ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, division, league, field, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $25,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  Participants may play via toll-free phone, mail, Internet, fax, and email.  The game runs from the start of the NFL season until the last game of the regular season. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hrfootball.fanball.com">
High Roller Fantasy Football</weblink> allows participants to manage a 20-player starting lineup using a $30 million salary cap and a 10-player taxi squad, and compete using Rotisserie-style scoring.  Cash prizes are awarded for overall and league competition.  The Grand Prize is $15,000, and the winner of each 20-team league wins $4,000.  The entry fee is $1000 with no additional fees. The game runs from the start of the NFL season until the last game of the regular season. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ptsfootball.fanball.com">
Fantasy Football</weblink> allows participants to manage a 22-player starting lineup using a $60 million salary cap and an 11-player bench.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $20,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the start of the NFL season until the last game of the regular season. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://budgetfootball.fanball.com">
Budget Football</weblink> allows participants to manage a team of 22 NFL football players using a $60 million salary cap.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $10,000, and the winner of each 10-team league wins $100.  The entry fee is $9.95 and changes are 50 cents each.  The game runs from the start of the NFL season until the last game of the regular season. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://freefootball.fanball.com">
 Free Fantasy Football</weblink> is a free-to-enter fantasy football game where participants select and manage a lineup of 22 NFL football players and teams using a $60 million salary cap and limited roster moves.  It is free to enter and participants can make one free move each week.  Up to an additional 120 moves can be made for a nominal fee.  There are four ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, division, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize winner takes home $5,000.  This game is played via the Internet only, and runs from the start of the NFL season until the last game of the regular season. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://midseasonfootball.fanball.com">
The Mid-Season Football Challenge</weblink> is the mid-season version of the Football Challenge.  Participants manage a 20-player starting lineup using a $28 million salary cap and a 10-player taxi squad.  Participants compete using Rotisserie-style scoring for overall, league, and weekly cash prizes.  The Grand Prize winner takes home $10,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  Participants may play via toll-free phone, mail, Internet, fax, and email.  The game begins with Week 9 NFL games and runs until the last game of the regular season. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://msbudgetfootball.fanball.com">
Mid-Season Budget Football</weblink> is the mid-season version of Budget Football.  Participants manage a team of 22 NFL football players using a $55 million salary cap.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize winner takes home $5,000.  There is an entry fee, but all player changes are free.  Participants may play via toll-free phone, mail, Internet, fax, and email.  The game begins with Week 9 NFL games and runs until the last game of the regular season. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://playofffootball.fanball.com">
The Playoff Football Challenge</weblink> is the post-season version of the Football Challenge game but without player salaries and a salary cap.  Participants select a starting team of 20 NFL football players and 10 reserves that participants think will do the best throughout the playoffs using Rotisserie-style scoring.  Cash prizes are awarded for overall and league competitions.  The Grand Prize winner takes home $5,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  Participants may play via toll-free phone, mail, Internet, fax, and email.  The game begins with the start of the NFL playoffs and runs through the Super Bowl. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fantasypofb.fanball.com">
Fantasy Playoff Football</weblink> is the post-season version of the Fantasy Football game but without player salaries and a salary cap.  Participants select a team of 22 NFL football players and 11 reserves that participants think will do the best throughout the playoffs using an easy point-style scoring system.  Cash prizes are awarded for overall and league competitions.  The Grand Prize winner takes home $3,000.  This is a web-only game and it costs only $10 to play – there are no other fees.  The game begins with the start of the NFL playoffs and runs through the Super Bowl. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/draftandplay?ArenaID=1">
Draft and Play Fantasy Football</weblink> is a fantasy football game that features 10-team leagues and live online drafts.  Participants draft and manage a team of eight starters and seven reserves, and compete using head-to-head weekly matchups and point-style scoring.  Prizes are awarded for league competition based on six levels of play with varying entry fees and prizes.  This game is played via the Internet only.  The game begins Week 1 NFL games and ends with Week 16 NFL games.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/leaguecommissioner?ArenaID=1">
Commissioner NFL</weblink> is a private football league manager service that offers a website to manage participants’ local league for as low as $69.95.  Participants define the league rules and scoring categories while we provide stat results, standings, player trades, waiver wire claims, and league finances.  Message boards are also provided so participants can communicate with other league members.  Toll-free customer support is provided as well as email support seven days per week.  This is an Internet-only service.  Participants may signup a league at any time until the end of the NFL regular season. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Golf</st>

<p>

Fanball offers a variety of fantasy golf games for all levels of competition and style.  Four challenge-style games of varying cost and design are available.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tourtrade1.fanball.com">
 Tour Trade 1</weblink> allows participants to manage a team of nine PGA Tour and 3 Champions Tour golfers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap, and participants win by accumulating the most money earnings.  There are four ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, field, and weekly competitions.  The Grand Prize is $10,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the Bob Hope Chrysler Classic in January through the U.S. Open in June. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tourtrade2.cdmsports.com">
Tour Trade 2</weblink> fantasy golf is essentially a second-half version of Tour Trade 1 fantasy golf.  The Grand Prize is $10,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the AT&amp;T Classic in May through The Tour Championship in September. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://oneanddone.fanball.com">
One and Done Fantasy Golf</weblink> tests participants’ ability to pick a winning PGA Tour golfer each week.  Participants select a unique PGA TOUR golfer each week, for a total of 27 unique golfers during the game, who accumulate money earnings.  Prizes are awarded for overall and division competitions.  The Grand Prize winner nets $5,000.  There is an entry fee, but there are no transaction fees involved. The game runs from the WGC CA Championship in March through The Tour Championship in September. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://majorschallenge.fanball.com">
Majors Challenge Fantasy Golf</weblink> is an easy-to-play and easy-to-follow game that is played during the four Major tournaments.  Participants select four unique foursomes of  PGA Tour golfers who accumulate money earnings for the participant’s team in the Big 4 tournaments:  The Masters, U.S. Open, British Open, and PGA Championship.  Prizes are awarded for overall and event competitions to the entries that accumulate the most money earnings.  The Grand Prize winner nets $3,000.  There is an entry fee, but there are no transaction fees involved.  The game begins in April. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tgcbracket.cdmsports.com">
Million Dollar Match Play Bracket Challenge</weblink> is an easy-to-play and easy-to-follow game in which participants complete a six-round tournament bracket for the WGC-Accenture Match Play Championship.  Participants select the winner in each of the 63 match play match-ups.  Points are awarded for each correct golfer selection. The number of points awarded increases as the tournament progresses.  In addition, as a tiebreaker, participants are asked to predict the total number of holes played during the entire tournament by the tournament champion.  There is no entry fee to play, however the game is Internet-only.  $1,000,000 is awarded to the participant who correctly picks all 63 winners on the tournament bracket.  The Top 3 overall teams with the most total points win Cobra golf merchandise (1st Place - One (1) Cobra L4V Driver and One (1) Cobra Speed Pro 3 Wood;  2nd Place - One (1) Cobra L4V Driver;  and 3rd Place - One (1) Cobra Men’s Baffler).  All prizes are fulfilled by The Golf Channel. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hockey</st>

<p>

Fanball offers a variety of fantasy hockey games for all levels of competition and style.  There are five challenge-style games of varying cost and design as well as a commissioner service for people looking for a website to host their local fantasy hockey league.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ptshockey.fanball.com">
Fantasy Hockey</weblink> is a high-risk, high-reward full-service point-style hockey game that is the ultimate test of participants’ hockey knowledge.  Participants manage a team of 20 pro hockey players within the constraints of a $60 million salary cap.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize winner earns $10,000.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the start of the NHL season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://freehockey.fanball.com">
Free Fantasy Hockey</weblink> is essentially the same setup as Fantasy Hockey in that participants manage a team of 20 pro hockey players within the constraints of a $60 million salary cap, however, there is no entry fee and transaction fees are optional.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $2,500.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  This game is played via the Internet only and there are nominal surcharges for transactions.  The game runs from the start of the NHL season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hockeypool.fanball.com">
Hockey Pool</weblink> allows participants to manage a team of 18 pro hockey players within the constraints of the checkbox player lists.  Cash prizes are awarded for overall and monthly competitions.  The Grand Prize is $10,000.  There is an entry fee but no transaction fees.  The game runs from the start of the NHL season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/draftandplay">
Draft and Play Fantasy Hockey</weblink> is a fantasy hockey game that features 10-team league and live online drafts.  Participants draft and manage a team of 12 pro hockey players and eight reserves, and compete using easy point-style scoring.  Prizes are awarded for league competition.  Each league winner nets a cash prize.  There is an entry fee to participate, but no transaction fees.  The game runs from the start of the NHL season until the last game of the regular season, but it does not include the All Star game. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pohockey.fanball.com">
Fantasy Playoff Hockey</weblink> is the post-season version of our Fantasy Hockey game but without player values and value cap.  Participants select and manage a team of 20 pro hockey players that participants think will do the best throughout the playoffs using an easy point-style scoring system.  Cash prizes are awarded for overall and league competitions.  The Grand Prize winner earns $3,000.  There is an entry fee but no transaction fees.  The game runs from the start of the NHL playoffs and runs until the last game of the Stanley Cup Finals. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/leaguecommissioner/?ArenaID=5">
Commissioner NHL</weblink> is a private hockey league manager and offers a website to manage local leagues for as low as $69.  Participants define the league rules and scoring categories, while we provide stat results, standings, player trades, waiver wire claims, and league finances.  Message boards are also provided so participants can communicate with other league members.  Toll-free customer support is provided as well as email support seven days per week.  This is an Internet-only service.  Participants may signup a league at any time until the end of the regular season. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
NASCAR</st>

<p>

Fanball offers a variety of fantasy auto racing games for all levels of competition and style.  There are eight challenge-style games of varying cost and design to choose from.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/nascar/spring/">
Sprint Cup Challenge – Circuit 1</weblink> allows participants to manage a team of 8 Sprint Cup series drivers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap and accumulate the highest race average.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $25,000 based on the best 14 of 18 weeks.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the Daytona 500 through the Coke Zero 400. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/nascar/midyear/">
Sprint Cup Challenge – Circuit 1.5</weblink> is essentially the same game as Circuit 1, but it starts and ends later and has slightly different prizes.  Participants manage a team of 8 Sprint Cup series drivers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap and accumulate the highest race average.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand is $10,000 based on the best 11 of 15 weeks.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the Coca Cola 600 through the Chevy Rock &amp; Roll 400.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/nascar/fall/">
Sprint Cup Challenge – Circuit 2</weblink> is the second half version of Sprint Cup Circuit 1.  Participants manage a team of 8 Sprint Cup series drivers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap and accumulate the highest race average.  There are three ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $25,000 based on the best 14 of 18 weeks.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the LifeLock.com 400 through the Ford 400. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/busch/spring/">
Nationwide Series Challenge – Circuit 1</weblink> allows participants to manage a team of 8 Nationwide Series drivers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap and accumulate the highest race average.  There are two ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $10,000 based on the best 14 of 18 weeks.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the Camping World 300 through the Camping World 200. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/busch/fall/">
Nationwide Series Challenge – Circuit 2</weblink> is the second half version of Nationwide Series Circuit 1.  Participants manage a team of 8 Nationwide Series drivers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap and accumulate the highest race average.  There are two ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $10,000 based on the best 13 of 17 weeks.  There is an entry fee plus transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the Daytona 250 through the Ford 300. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/pickem/spring/">
Pick’em &amp; Race – Circuit 1</weblink> allows participants to select a unique Sprint Cup driver each week, for a total of 18 unique drivers during the game.  Prizes are awarded for overall and league competitions.  The Grand Prize is $1,000.  There is an entry fee, but there are no transaction fees involved.  The game runs from the Daytona 500 on February 17th through the Coke Zero 400 on July 5th. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/pickem/fall/">
Pick’em &amp; Race – Circuit 2</weblink> is the second half version of Pick’em &amp; Race – Circuit 1.  Participants select a unique Sprint Cup driver each week, for a total of 18 unique drivers during the game.  Prizes are awarded for overall and league competitions.  The Grand Prize is $1,000.  There is an entry fee, but there are no transaction fees involved.  This is an Internet-only game.  The game runs from the LifeLock.com 400 through the Ford 400. (51)</p>
<p>

Victory Lane Challenge allows participants to manage a team of 8 Sprint Cup series drivers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap as well as a garage of 7 drivers.  There are four ways in which participants can win cash prizes, including overall, division, league, and weekly competition.  The Grand Prize is $3,000 based on the best 20 weeks.  There is no entry fee, but there are transaction fees involved if participants choose to make more than one free switch each week.  The game runs from the Daytona 500 through the Chevy Rock &amp; Roll 400.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/nascar/chase/">
Chase For The Fantasy Cup</weblink> allows participants to select five drivers from the top 12 in the Sprint Cup standings before the start of the Sylvania 300.  Points are awarded based on Sprint Cup points that are awarded to each participants’ drivers based on their finish and laps led.  The participant accumulating the most points for the 10 race schedule wins $5,000.  The game begins with the Sylvania 300 and runs through the Ford 400. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/onerace/allstar/">
All-Star Challenge</weblink> is a one-race contest in which participants pick a team of 8 drivers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap.  Points are awarded to teams based on Sprint Cup points that are awarded to each of your drivers based on their finish and laps led.  The participant accumulating the most points for the Sprint All-Star Race XXIV Race wins $1,000 + 2 race tickets and a Speed TV VIP package.  The game is free to play and is confined to the Sprint All-Star Race XXIV Race on May 17th. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stockcar.fantasycup.com/onerace/shootout/">
Fantasy Cup Shootout</weblink> is a one-race contest in which participants pick a team of 8 drivers within the constraints of a $10 million salary cap.  Points are awarded to teams based on Sprint Cup points that are awarded to each of driver based on their finish and laps led.  The participant accumulating the most points for the Budweiser Shootout race wins $1,000 + 2 race tickets and a Speed TV VIP package.  The game is free to play and is confined to the Budweiser Shootout race. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com/draftandplay/?ArenaID=3">
Draft and Play Fantasy Auto Racing</weblink> is a fantasy auto racing game that features 8-team leagues and live online drafts.  Participants draft and manage a team of 6 Sprint Cup drivers and two reserve drivers, and compete using accumulated qualifying and Sprint Cup race points.  Prizes are awarded for league competition.  Each league winner nets a cash prize.  There is an entry fee to participate, but no transaction fees.  The game begins with the Daytona 500 and runs through the Ford 400.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://www.funtechnologies.com/html_fun/press/fun_press_06130502.htm Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
http://www.funtechnologies.com/images_fun/press/fun_press_08_24_06.pdf Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
http://www.funtechnologies.com/images_fun/press/fun_press_12_21_07.pdf Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
http://www.funtechnologies.com/images_fun/press/fun_press_08_21_06.pdf Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fsta.org/about/">
History - Fantasy Sports Trade Association</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
Hiestand, Michael. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/2005-02-09-fantasy-legal-battle_x.htm">
"Fantasy stats part of legal team"</weblink>, <it>USA Today</it>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/11361.xml">
February 9</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>, Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
http://www.funtechnologies.com/images_fun/press/fun_press_08_24_06.pdf Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0EIN/is_2000_Nov_17/ai_67044199">
"Action Performance Companies Inc. Reports Sale of Fantasy Sports Operation"</weblink>, <it>Business Wire</it>,  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/21798.xml">
November 17</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link>. Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/summary_0199-890627_ITMc">
"Fantasy Sports, Inc. enters into an agreement to become first official NASCAR licensed fantasy games provider"</weblink>, <it>Business Wire</it>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/15987.xml">
January 7</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>. Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.law.com/jsp/article.jsp?id=1109128216973">
Pro Sports: Technology Changes Rules of the Game</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sportsbusinessjournal.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=page.feature&amp;featureId=1777">
A real fight over fantasy</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sports.yahoo.com/mlb/news;_ylt=Ap8tlZq02ZKg077gOeqTlWgRvLYF?slug=jp-fantasy042006&amp;prov=yhoo&amp;type=lgns">
The reality of fantasy</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/20/opinion/20sat4.html?ex=1148875200&amp;en=22e49644e456378c&amp;ei=5070">
Royalties on R.B.I.'s?</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/08/08/business/main1877750.shtml">
Baseball Strikes Out In Stats Fight</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=2543720">
Fantasy leagues permitted to use MLB names, stats</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2007/fantasy/06/15/fantasy.lawsuit">
Realities of Fantasy</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stlouis.bizjournals.com/stlouis/stories/2007/06/11/daily50.html?jst=b_ln_hl">
Appellate court hears arguments in CDM fantasy sports suit</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanball.com">
Fanball</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fanballnews.com">
Fanball News</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rototimes.com">
Rototimes.com</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fantasycup.com">
Fantasy Cup</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cdmsports.com">
CDM Sports</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ownersedge.com">
Owner's Edge</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.godfatheroffantasysports.com">
The Godfather of Fantasy Sports Blog</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</web_site>
</sport>
</article>
