<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:50:13[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<university  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108286163">
<business_school  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108281812">
<header>
<title>Institute of Rural Management, Anand</title>
<id>1719455</id>
<revision>
<id>242189053</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T07:13:38Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>718 Bot</username>
<id>5415725</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Universities and colleges in Gujarat</category>
<category>Rural community development</category>
<category>Business schools in India</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_University</name>
<parameters>

<image width="150px" src="Irmalogo.png">
<caption>

Irmalogo.png
</caption>
</image>
<chairman>
<link>
Prof Y. K. Alagh</link></chairman>
<courses>
<link>
Post Graduate Diploma in Rural Management</link></courses>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irma.ac.in/">
www.irma.ac.in</weblink></website>
<state>
<legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/53707.xml">
Gujarat</link></legal_power>
</state>
<established>
1979</established>
<type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/191145.xml">
Autonomous</link></type>
<director>
<link>
Mr. Vivek Bhandari</link></director>
<city>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/10081162.xml">
Anand</link></city>
<country>
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
</country>
<name>
Institute of Rural Management Anand</name>
<motto>
Without education there is no liberation</motto>
<postgrad_label>
<link>
PGDRM , FPRM</link></postgrad_label>
<campus>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/764593.xml">
Rural</link>, 60 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/1797.xml">
acre</link>s</campus>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>Institute of Rural Management, Anand</b> (<b>IRMA</b>) (founded 1979) is an autonomous institution located at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/10081162.xml">
Anand</link> in <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/53707.xml">
Gujarat</link></legal_power>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
 with the mandate of contributing to the professional management of rural organisations. It was founded at the initiative of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/2293000.xml">
National Dairy Development Board</link> and the support of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/553883.xml">
Government of India</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/17399942.xml">
Government of Gujarat</link> and <link>
Swiss Development Co-operation</link>. IRMA works closely with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/89313.xml">
co-operative</link>s, <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/46539.xml">
NGO</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
s, governments, Indian national and international agencies. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Programs</st>

<p>

<b>Doctoral level Programme titled the Fellow Programme in Rural Management (FPRM)</b>  for students and professionals seeking careers in Research, Teaching and specialised knowledge-based positions in Cooperatives and Development Organisations.</p>
<p>

<b>Post-Graduate Programme in Rural Management (PRM)</b>  for those who wish to undertake challenging managerial responsibilities in the rural co-operative sector and development organisations. PRM is recognised as equivalent to a Master’s Degree by the Association of Indian Universities (AIU) and is approved by the All India Council for Technical Education (AICTE).</p>
<p>

<b>Management Development Programmes</b> for in-service managers/ officers working with co-operatives, NGOs, and  government and semi-government organisations engaged in rural development.</p>
<p>

<b>Research and Consultancy</b> for enriching the quality and content of teaching and training activities as well as helping IRMA’s clientèle identify and resolve their management problems.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Campus facilities </st>

<p>

The campus is fully residential equipped with students’ hostels, mess, lecture halls, seminar rooms, library, faculty and administrative offices, auditorium, executive training and development centre, faculty and staff housing, dispensary, and other support facilities. The IRMA staff co-operative store caters to the residents’ daily necessities. Faculty and Staff live in the campus quarters provided, thereby providing facilities for interaction with the participants even beyond formal class rooms.</p>
<p>

<b>Ravi J Mathai Library</b> supports the mission of IRMA through the provision of information resources and services. In this role, the library plays an integral part in the learning process by providing the entire academic community with access to information for fulfilling research requirements, course work assignments, professional development and intellectual growth. This is achieved through collection development, networking, electronic information retrieval, instruction in search strategy and assisted access to an array of resources and data.  Using current technologies, the library seeks to identify and implement innovative means for broadening access to information beyond immediate holdings while continuing to build and maintain an exemplary body of on-site resources.</p>
<p>

<b>Executive Training and Development Centre (ETDC)</b> where the executive training programs and seminars are held, has 35 single occupancy Air Conditioned rooms, four suites, a dining hall, a lounge, conference and syndicate rooms with audio-visual equipment and an exclusive computer laboratory which is networked with the Institutes's main computer center. This facility is available for executive training programmes and conferences planned by the faculty.</p>
<p>

<b>IRMA Auditorium</b> which has a seating capacity of 400 is used for all major events of the Institute and for entertainment. Movies are screened regularly for both the participants of programs and the residents of the campus. It is also used for musical concerts hosted by the Society for Promotion of Indian Culture and Music amongst Youth (SPIC-MACAY) and the cultural programs hosted by the students.</p>
<p>

<b>Students Activities Center</b> (SAC) has a gym-cum-sports complex, with facilities for a regular work-out, badminton and table-tennis courts.</p>
<p>

A co-operative store on the campus is open in the evenings - 6 days a week and provides all the essential items required by the residents on the campus. It is well stocked with provisions and stationery required for the residents.</p>
<p>

Campus dispensary is readily accessible for any basic medication necessary. The Honorary Medical Officer visits the campus for an hour every day and a staff nurse resides on the campus to attend to any medical emergencies.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irma.ac.in">
Official website of IRMA</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irmans.org">
IRMA Alumni Association website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</business_school>
</university>
</article>
