<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:05:36[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<name  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106333653">
<noodle  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107699584">
<header>
<title>Dotori guksu</title>
<id>17255199</id>
<revision>
<id>221163057</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-23T09:07:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Badagnani</username>
<id>308437</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Korean noodles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Korean name</name>
<parameters>
<hangul>
도토리국수</hangul>
<mr>
tot'ori kuksu</mr>
<rr>
dotori guksu</rr>
<hanja>
<it>none''</it></hanja>
</parameters>
</template>


<b><it>Dotori guksu</it></b> are <name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/13133495.xml">
Korean noodles</link></name>
 made from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/922939.xml">
acorn</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/56232.xml">
flour</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/27711.xml">
starch</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/1605200.xml">
salt</link>, and a combination of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/6700.xml">
grain</link>-based flour (usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/80169.xml">
buckwheat</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/36858.xml">
wheat</link>).<p>

<it>Dotori guksu</it> may be made from acorns collected from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/166125.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Section+Lobatae%22])">
red</link> or <plant wordnetid="100017222" confidence="0.8">
<tree wordnetid="113104059" confidence="0.8">
<vascular_plant wordnetid="113083586" confidence="0.8">
<woody_plant wordnetid="113103136" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/73638.xml">
white</link></woody_plant>
</vascular_plant>
</tree>
</plant>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/39696.xml">
oak</link> species and each oak species gives a distinct flavour. Ingredient labels do not list from which type of tree acorns are gathered, most likely due to the large number of oak species and increasing oak <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/508159.xml">
hybridization</link> (especially among white oak varieties), which makes it difficult to recognise and document each type of species.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Origins</st>
<p>

Evidence at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/21189.xml">
Neolithic</link> sites such as <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/16999639.xml">
Amsa-dong</link></village>
 in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/27019.xml">
South Korea</link></country>
 show acorns were part of the human diet. Acorns contain bitter <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/61983.xml">
tannins</link> which would have been leached out to make the acorns edible. They were then ground into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/56232.xml">
flour</link> using a <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/923872.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Saddle+quern%22])">
saddle quern</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/167364.xml">
milling stone</link>.</p>
<p>

It is unknown exactly where acorn noodles were first produced. However, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/797150.xml">
Ogam</link> village, Korea is well known for a long history of acorn cultivation. The village's location by the <link>
Namhangang River</link> and its mountainous climate and landscape is conducive toward large-scale acorn cultivation. The village produces dozens of acorn-based foods, including <it>dotori kalguksoo</it> (acorn knife-cut noodles). </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Varieties</st>
<p>

There are two varieties of acorn noodles: flour-based soba and starch-based vermicelli. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Starch-based</st>
<p>

Acorn vermicelli noodles or <it>dotori naengmyeon</it> (hangul: 냉면 도토리) are made from acorn starch and some combination of potato, rice, or arrowroot starch, wheat flour, and salt. The dried noodles resemble brown plastic threads about 1/10-1/8 cm in diameter. Cooked properly and typically eaten cold, acorn-based <it>naengmyeon</it> noodles have a high elasticity and chewy consistency.   </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Flour-based</st>
<p>

Acorn soba noodles or in Korean, <it>dotori guksu</it> (hangul: 도토리국수) are made from acorn flour and a combination of grain-based flours; such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/80169.xml">
buckwheat</link> and corn, and salt. They are about as thick as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/29178.xml">
spaghetti</link> and are used in hot and cold dishes, such as Zaru Soba (boiled noodles are served cold with a dipping sauce.) Acorn soba noodles may be more healthy than the starch-based acorn vermicelli noodles. The Japanese version of these noodles, <it>donguri-men</it> (Japanese:どんぐり), typically has less acorn flour than the original Korean version.</p>
<p>

Raw acorn noodles are slightly coarser in cut and texture and more brittle than standard buckwheat soba noodles. Cooked acorn soba noodles are nuttier in flavor, healthier, and slightly saltier than buckwheat noodles. In particular, they contain many antioxidants and may be considered an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/1939947.xml">
adaptogenic</link> (anti-cancerous) food.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Differences between starch and flour bases</st>
<p>

A common problem among Korean-manufactured products is that their ingredient labels are often not properly translated. Acorn starch is frequently mislabeled as acorn flour or acorn powder. In reality, acorn starch is essentially highly-refined acorn flour, devoid of fiber, fat, and almost all nutrition. While the acorn itself does indeed contain acorn starch, that starch is not highly-refined. Acorn starch, in contrast, is extracted from the meat of the kernel using a wet process and then dehydrated. The heart, or germ, of the kernel is removed and used for producing acorn oil, which is comparable in flavor and quality to olive oil. The hull is separated from the kernel meat, and the starch is extracted from the kernel meat. It might be more accurate to use the term “acorn meal”, although a meal is a coarser, less refined version of flour. </p>
<p>

Both flour and starch-based acorn noodles are available in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/1960514.xml">
upscale</link> Korean markets. A few Japanese markets also carry acorn soba noodles, but in general, acorn soba noodles are difficult to find.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/1998/11/981126102802.htm">
University Of Richmond. "Researchers Tackle The Nutty Truth On Acorns And Squirrels."</weblink> ScienceDaily 26 November 1998. 29 April 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Use of Acorns for Food in California: Past, Present, Future, David A. Bainbridge Presented at the Symposium on Multiple-use Management of California's Hardwoods, November 12-14, 1986, San Luis Obispo, California.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.motherearthnews.com/Modern-Homesteading/1984-09-01/Acorns-The-Grain-That-Grows-on-Trees.aspx">
Acorns: The Grain That Grows on Trees</weblink> David Bainbridge, September/October 1984, Mother Earth News.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Katherine J. Meyers, Tedmund J. Swiecki, and Alyson E. Mitchell, Understanding the Native Californian Diet: Identification of Condensed and Hydrolyzable Tannins in Tanoak Acorns (Lithocarpus densiflorus): Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry 2006, 54, 76867691</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ortiz, Bev. It Will Live Forever: Traditional Yosemite Indian Acorn Preparation (Berkeley: Heyday Books, 1991)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pavlik, Bruce M., Pamela C. Muick, Sharon Johnson, and Marjorie Popper, 1991 Oaks of California. Los Olivos: Cachuma press and the California Oak Foundation. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

McCarthy, Helen 1993 Managing Oaks and the Acorn Crop. In Before the Wilderness: Environmental Management by Native Californians, edited by Thomas C. Blackburn and Kat Anderson. Menlo Park: Ballena Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.healthhokkaido.com/files/Articles_Oshimi/soba.cfm">
Health Benefits of Soba Noodles</weblink>, from Health Hokkaido, a medical advocacy group.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/5025347.xml">
Dotorimuk</link></name>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</noodle>
</name>
</article>
