<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:10:03[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>High Voltage Isolation and Ground Potential Rise</title>
<id>17325931</id>
<revision>
<id>241314491</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-27T12:45:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Biscuittin</username>
<id>3955768</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Electrical safety</category>
<category>Communication engineering</category>
<category>Uncategorized pages needing expert attention</category>
<category>Pages needing expert attention</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

 <p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.</b>
Please help recruit one or <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=High_Voltage_Isolation_and_Ground_Potential_Rise&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> yourself. See the  for details.Please consider using  to associate this request with a </col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

This article outlines the principles of <b>High Voltage Isolation</b> (HVI) and <b>Ground Potential Rise</b> (GPR).  Most often questions of concern arise to anyone associated with the use of any communication signal (<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<electrical_device wordnetid="103269401" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<circuit wordnetid="103033362" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/993.xml">
analog</link></circuit>
</device>
</electrical_device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/47504.xml">
digital</link>) via a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/33498.xml">
metallic</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/11234274.xml">
fiber optic cable</link>. Providers of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/30322.xml">
telecommunications</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/277750.xml">
electric service</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/185868.xml">
wireless</link> service or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/7587.xml">
CATV</link>, or operating in an isolated manufacturing or mining location, may be working in a hostile electric environment. An unprotected or improperly protected system is unsafe for the public and personnel, and exposes equipment to service interruptions or permanent damage. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Importance</st>
<p>

People who are new to this profession or those who have many years of experience, whether an engineer, architect, tower erector, equipment installer, manager, tradesperson or safety supervisor, need to know or learn the following:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 what the level of exposure may be</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the protection equipment necessary for the work location</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the necessary safety precautions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the accepted codes, standards and practices for addressing</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The Basic High-Voltage Problem</st>

<p>

When hydro power faults occur in electric power systems or when <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/61344.xml">
lightning</link> strikes, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/8929041.xml">
Ground Potential Rise</link> (GPR) occurs, which can damage equipment and injure personnel working on the equipment unless proper <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/15066.xml">
isolation</link></concept>
</idea>
 or protection is provided. The GPR produces a dangerous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/32549.xml">
potential difference</link> between the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/212141.xml">
power station</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/24808.xml">
PCS</link> tower and a remote <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/41215.xml">
ground</link> connection located at a telephone company central office, remote terminal, distant manufacturing building or other sites. Telecommunications cable damage can occur if grounding takes place across the potential difference caused by a power fault or lightning strike.</p>
<p>

Note: Any type of cable such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/80506.xml">
twisted pair</link> telephone cable or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/46380.xml">
coaxial cable</link> and any type of cable plant construction such as aerial, buried or underground,can experience damage. Also, any type of service can be interrupted if proper protection is not provided.</p>
<p>

In general, special protection equipment, corporate policies and procedures are necessary to ensure the safety of personnel and protection of equipment including cables, termination equipment, etc. The reliability of communications circuits is questionable when they are in an unprotected <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/1205325.xml">
high voltage</link> environment. Disturbances on electric power systems and lightning can cause GPR, voltage <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/742288.xml">
induction</link></concept>
</idea>
 on telecommunications cables, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/319613.xml">
power surges</link> and high-voltage <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/11271235.xml">
transients</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Service Performance Objectives (SPO) or Quality of Service</st>

<p>

Telecommunications service is expected to operate with a standard performance objective as outlined below:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class A - Service must be available before, during and after the fault event</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class B – Service must function before and after, but not necessarily during, the fault event</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class C – Interruptible, non-critical service</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Levels of Protection</st>

<p>

Standard protection devices are designed to work under the following GPR conditions:</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Basic Protection Level I</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cable stress below 300 Volts peak asymmetrical</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 All SPO classes of service (A, B and C)</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Basic Protection Level II</st>
<p>
 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cable stress below 1000 Volts peak asymmetrical</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SPO Class B or Class C services</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Basic Protection Level III</st>
<p>
 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Above 1000 Volts peak asymmetrical</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Should require a High Voltage Isolator (HVI)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 All SPO classes of service</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Common Protection Devices</st>

<p>

Protection devices listed below are designed to work under the following categories and levels:</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Basic Protection Level I and II</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Carbon blocks</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/548308.xml">
Gas tube</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/3656002.xml">
Solid state</link> protectors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Solid state hybrid protectors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/1515993.xml">
Heat coil</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Spark gaps</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mutual Drainage Reactors (MDR)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Protection devices listed below are designed to work under the following:</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Basic Protection Level III</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/19725502.xml">
Lightning arrester</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 High <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/41026.xml">
dielectric</link> cables</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/575126.xml">
Isolation transformer</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Neutralizing transformers (Old technology)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Copper HV electronic isolators</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fiber HV electronic isolators</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Electric Power System Telecommunications Equipment and Applications</st>

<p>

There are many types of protective relaying and system control equipment used in the electric power industry which require communications circuits to clear faults, operate the system, protect personnel and equipment, and maintain system reliability.</p>
<p>

Advanced protective relaying schemes that require “Class A” communications circuits are commonly used by the electric power industry to open <link>
High Voltage (HV) circuit breakers</link> at remote locations. Examples of this type of equipment are listed below:</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Protective relaying communications</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Audio tones</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DC pilot wire relaying</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Applications
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Transfer trip</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Breaker failure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Permissive overreaching</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Directional comparison</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Electric power systems use “Class B” communications circuits for the following services:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Supervisory Control and Data Acquisition (SCADA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Telephones for safety, metering and automation circuits</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ground Potential Rise (GPR)</st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/8929041.xml">
Earth potential rise</link></it>
</indent>
The definition of GPR, according to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/2798000.xml">
IEEE Standard</link>s 487 and 367, is: “the product of a ground electrode <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/3123666.xml">
impedance</link>, referenced to remote earth, and the current that flows through that electrode impedance.” The total station GPR is equal to the product of the station ground grid impedance and that portion of the total fault current that flows through it. In other words, GPR follows basic <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<theorem wordnetid="106752293" confidence="0.8">
<proposition wordnetid="106750804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/49090.xml">
Ohm's law</link></proposition>
</theorem>
</message>
</statement>
 calculations for example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/32549.xml">
voltage</link> is equal to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/6207.xml">
current</link> times <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/61577.xml">
resistance</link>. When a ground fault occurs, fault current will divide among all circuit paths back to the source including metallic, earth return, etc. Metallic return paths include overhead ground wires, multi-grounded neutrals, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/3581021.xml">
bonding conductors</link>, station ground grids, messenger wires, metallic cable shields and other conducting materials.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Zone of Influence (ZOI) and the 300-Volt Point</st>

<p>

GPR decays outward in an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/330320.xml">
exponential</link> manner. The ZOI is the area around the ground grid dissipating the energy. Depending on soil <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/61580.xml">
resistivity</link> and the size of the ground grid, the distance to the 300-Volt point on the ZOI can be calculated.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Total Electrical Cable Stress</st>

<p>

The total electrical stress on a communications cable is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/32533.xml">
vectorial</link> sum of the GPR and the induced voltage on the cable under fault conditions. When a faulting electric power line parallels an overhead or underground telecommunications cable, a potentially dangerous voltage is <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/742288.xml">
electromagnetically induced</link></concept>
</idea>
 on the communications conductors. Excessive induction, by itself, can damage equipment and indirectly injure personnel.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Power and Lightning Fault Current Distribution</st>

<p>

GPR will occur at several locations simultaneously. Fault current will divide among all circuit paths back to the source (metallic and earth return, for example) and create GPRs in the process. Metallic return paths include overhead ground wires, multi-grounded neutrals, bonds, station ground grids, and other conducting materials.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
General safety considerations</st>

<p>

Hazardous voltages can appear suddenly as a result of power faults or lightning strikes. Conductive objects (metal, damp saline soils, etc.) can become energized or carry a harmful potential that, if not properly protected, can cause serious injury. Safety of personnel can be achieved through education, proper facility design, and approved and tested insulated safety equipment. Personnel should use approved and tested rubber gloves and/or insulating blankets when working on the highvoltage interface (HVI) equipment.</p>
<p>

Touch potential is the difference between the voltage gradient that one is standing on and the voltage gradient one is touching. A significant difference in touch potential can be hazardous. Step potential is the difference in voltage gradients between a person’s two feet. Shoes, gloves, etc. can provide insulation to touch and step potentials. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Basic personal safety equipment</st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See warning on </it>
</indent>
Proper personal protection equipment, procedures and tools can help job safety and efficiency.</p>
<p>

Rubber Gloves, Leather Protectors and Cotton Liners</p>
<p>

All rubber gloves and other personal protection equipment have to meet safety standards established by national organizations like the <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/659.xml">
American National Standards Institute</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (ANSI) and the <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/852442.xml">
American Society for Testing and Materials</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (ASTM).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Cell sites on electrical towers</st>

<p>

Installing HVI equipment on cell sites is similar to power substation installations. Both copper and fiber optic high-voltage protection equipment are available for cell sites on regular and electric towers. Each situation needs to be carefully analyzed for possible GPR problems. Proper isolation is a primary consideration. Electric power service (i.e., 120/240 Vac) can introduce a remote ground hazard.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Conclusion</st>

<p>

It is of utmost importance to always determine the proper protection scheme when dealing with telecommunication wire line circuits between Hydro sub stations, PCS towers, 911 communications centers and any location where high voltage and high current equipment is co-located with these circuits. The most effective protection will always utilize High Voltage Isolation (HVI) designs and is the most effective against high ground potential rise (GPR) and lightning strike scenarios. It is always best to design for the worst case situation, since more likely than not, this can happen. Protection against both High voltage and  ground potential rise is the best precaution against equipment failures and human injury.</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
