<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:25:53[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<protocol  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106665108">
<direction  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106786629">
<rule  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106652242">
<header>
<title>UUCP</title>
<id>173231</id>
<revision>
<id>238072862</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-13T03:27:02Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jeh</username>
<id>341372</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Network protocols</category>
<category>Usenet</category>
<category>Network file transfer protocols</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>UUCP</b> is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/1171.xml">
abbreviation</link> for <b>Unix to Unix CoPy</b>. The term generally refers to a suite of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/5783.xml">
computer program</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/83235.xml">
protocol</link>s allowing remote execution of commands and transfer of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/7077.xml">
file</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
email</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/18588994.xml">
netnews</link> between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link>s. Specifically, uucp is one of the programs in the suite; it provides a user interface for requesting file copy operations.  The UUCP suite also includes uux (user interface for remote command execution), uucico (communication program), uustat (reports statistics on recent activity), uuxqt (execute commands sent from remote machines), and uuname (reports the uucp name of the local system). <p>

Although UUCP was originally developed on and is most closely associated with <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
, UUCP implementations exist for several other operating systems, including Microsoft's <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/20027.xml">
MS-DOS</link></O>
, Digital's <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/32736.xml">
VAX/VMS</link></O>
, Commodore's <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/18933304.xml">
AmigaOS</link></O>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/20043.xml">
Mac OS</link>.  </p>

<sec>
<st>
Technology</st>
<p>

UUCP can use several different types of physical connections and link-layer protocols, but was most commonly used over dial-up connections. Before the widespread availability of  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> connectivity, computers were only connected by smaller private networks within a company or organization. They were also often equipped with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/19443900.xml">
modems</link> so they could be used remotely from character-mode terminals via dial-up lines.  UUCP uses the computers' modems to dial out to other computers, establishing temporary, point-to-point links between them.  Each system in a UUCP network has a list of neighbor systems, with phone numbers, login names and passwords, etc.  When <it>work</it> (file transfer or command execution requests) is queued for a neighbor system, the uucico program typically calls that system to process the work. The uucico program can also poll its neighbors periodically to check for work queued on their side; this permits neighbors without dial-out capability to participate.  </p>
<p>

Today, UUCP is rarely used over dial-up links, but is occasionally used over <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/15476.xml">
TCP/IP</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

One example of the current use of UUCP is in the retail industry by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/10652579.xml">
Epicor</link></company>
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epicor.com/www/products/retail/RetailSolutions.htm">
CRS Retail Systems</weblink> for transferring batch files between corporate and store systems via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/30538.xml">
TCP</link> and dial-up on <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../906/1579906.xml">
SCO OpenServer</link></O>
, <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/26072.xml">
Red Hat Linux</link></O>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> (with <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<copycat wordnetid="109964411" confidence="0.8">
<compiler wordnetid="109946957" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/6840.xml">
Cygwin</link></writer>
</causal_agent>
</compiler>
</copycat>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
). The number of systems involved, as of early <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>, ran between 1500 and 2000 sites across 60 enterprises.  UUCP's longevity can be attributed to its low/zero cost, extensive logging, native failover to dialup, and persistent queue management. However, this technology is anticipated to be retired in favor of other alternatives.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

UUCP was originally written at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/3712.xml">
AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories</link>, by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<computer_user wordnetid="109951274" confidence="0.8">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/1557599.xml">
Mike Lesk</link></associate>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</engineer>
</programmer>
</computer_user>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
, and early versions of UUCP are sometimes referred to as <it><link>
System V</link> UUCP</it>.  The original UUCP was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/13653181.xml">
rewritten</link> by AT&amp;T researchers Peter Honeyman, David A. Nowitz, and Brian E. Redman and the rewrite is referred to as <it>HDB</it> or <it>HoneyDanBer</it> uucp which was later enhanced, bug fixed, and repackaged as <it>BNU UUCP</it> ("Basic Network Utilities").  All of these versions had security holes which allowed some of the original <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/6010.xml">
internet worm</link>s to remotely execute unexpected shell commands, which inspired <link>
Ian Lance Taylor</link> to write a new version from scratch.  <it>Taylor UUCP</it> was released under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GNU General Public License</link> and became the most stable and bug free version.  Taylor UUCP also incorporates features of all previous versions of UUCP, allowing it to communicate with any other version with the greatest level of compatibility and even use similar config file formats from other versions. UUCP was also implemented for non-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
UNIX</link> operating systems, most-notably MS-DOS systems. Packages such as UUSLAVE/GNUCICO (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/2461831.xml">
John Gilmore</link>, Garry Paxinos, <link>
Tim Pozar</link>), UUPC (Drew Derbyshire) and FSUUCP (Christopher Ambler), brought early Internet connectivity to personal computers, expanding the network beyond the interconnected university systems. FSUUCP formed the basis for many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/4772.xml">
BBS</link> packages such as Galacticomm's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/1615947.xml">
Major BBS</link> and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/5981234.xml">
Mustang Software</link></institution>
</company>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/1892351.xml">
Wildcat! BBS</link> to connect to the UUCP network and exchange email and <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/18588994.xml">
Usenet</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</group>
</act>
</service>
</gathering>
</rule>
</event>
</social_group>
</message>
</system_of_measurement>
</community>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</work>
 traffic.  As an example, UFGATE (John Galvin, Garry Paxinos, <link>
Tim Pozar</link>) was a package that provided a gateway between networks running Fidonet and UUCP protocols.</p>
<p>

FSUUCP was notable for being the only other implementation of Taylor's enhanced 'i' protocol, a significant improvement over the standard 'g' protocol used by most UUCP implementations.</p>
<p>

One surviving feature of uucp is the chat file format, largely inherited by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/1161030.xml">
expect</link> software package.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
UUCP for mail routing</st>
<p>

The uucp and uuxqt capabilities could be used to send e-mail between machines, with suitable mail user interface and delivery agent programs.  A simple uucp mail address was formed from the adjacent machine name, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/7712754.xml">
exclamation mark</link> or <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/7712754.xml">
bang</link></it>, followed by the user name on the adjacent machine.  For example, the address <it>barbox!user</it> would refer to user <it>user</it> on adjacent machine <it>barbox</it>.  </p>
<p>

Mail could furthermore be routed through the network, traversing any number of intermediate nodes before arriving at its destination.  Initially, this had to be done by specifying the complete path, with a list of intermediate host names separated by bangs.  For example, if machine <it>barbox</it> is not connected to the local machine, but it is known that <it>barbox</it> is connected to machine <it>foovax</it> which does communicate with the local machine, the appropriate address to send mail to would be <it>foovax!barbox!user</it>.</p>
<p>

User <it>barbox!user</it> might publish their UUCP email address in a form such as <it>…!bigsite!foovax!barbox!user</it>.  This directs people to route their mail to machine <it>bigsite</it> (presumably a well-known and well-connected machine accessible to everybody) and from there through the machine <it>foovax</it> to the account of user <it>user</it> on <it>barbox</it>. Many users would suggest multiple routes from various large well-known sites, providing even better and perhaps faster connection service from the mail sender.</p>
<p>

Bang paths of eight to ten machines (or <it>hops</it>) were not uncommon in 1981, and late-night dial-up UUCP links would cause week-long transmission times. Bang paths were often selected by both transmission time and reliability, as messages would often get lost.  Some hosts went so far as to try to "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/415847.xml">
rewrite</link>" the path, sending mail via "faster" routes — this practice tended to be frowned upon.</p>
<p>

The "pseudo-domain" ending <b><sphere wordnetid="114514039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/3524656.xml">
.uucp</link></sphere>
</b> was sometimes used to designate a hostname as being reachable by UUCP networking, although this was never formally in the Internet root as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/31115.xml">
top-level domain</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
UUCPNET and mapping</st>
<p>

<b>UUCPNET</b> was the name for the totality of the network of computers connected through UUCP. This network was very informal, maintained in a spirit of mutual cooperation between systems owned by thousands of private companies, universities, and so on.  Often, particularly in the private sector, UUCP links were established without official approval from the companies' upper management.  The UUCP network was constantly changing as new systems and dial-up links were added, others were removed, etc.  </p>
<p>

The <it>UUCP Mapping Project</it> was a volunteer, largely successful effort to build a map of the connections between machines that were <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/43316.xml">
open mail relay</link>s and establish a managed namespace. Each system administrator would submit, by e-mail, a list of the systems to which theirs would connect, along with a ranking for each such connection.  These submitted map entries were processed by an automatic program that combined them into a single set of files describing all connections in the network.  These files were then published monthly in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/21125.xml">
newsgroup</link> dedicated to this purpose.  The UUCP map files could then be used by software such as "pathalias" to compute the best route path from one machine to another for mail, and to supply this route automatically.  The UUCP maps also listed contact information for the sites, and so gave sites seeking to join UUCPNET an easy way to find prospective neighbors.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Connections with the Internet</st>
<p>

Many uucp hosts, particularly those at universities, were also connected to the Internet in its early years, and e-mail gateways between Internet <link>
SMTP</link>-based mail and UUCP mail were developed. A user at a system with UUCP connections could thereby exchange mail with Internet users, and the Internet links could be used to bypass large portions of the slow UUCP network.  A "UUCP zone" was defined within the Internet domain namespace to facilitate these interfaces.  </p>
<p>

With this infrastructure in place, UUCP's strength was that it permitted a site to gain Internet e-mail and <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/18588994.xml">
Usenet</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</group>
</act>
</service>
</gathering>
</rule>
</event>
</social_group>
</message>
</system_of_measurement>
</community>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</work>
 connectivity with only a dial-up modem link to another cooperating computer.  This was at a time when true Internet access required a leased data line providing a connection to an Internet <it>Point of Presence</it>, both of which were expensive and difficult to arrange.  By contrast, a link to the UUCP network could usually be established with a few phone calls to the administrators of prospective neighbor systems. Neighbor systems were often close enough to avoid all but the most basic charges for telephone calls.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Decline</st>
<p>

UUCP usage began to die out with the rise of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/100245.xml">
ISP</link>s offering inexpensive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/101421.xml">
SLIP</link> and <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/23511.xml">
PPP</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 services. The UUCP Mapping Project was formally shut down in late 2000. </p>
<p>

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/18588994.xml">
Usenet</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</group>
</act>
</service>
</gathering>
</rule>
</event>
</social_group>
</message>
</system_of_measurement>
</community>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</work>
 traffic was originally transmitted using the UUCP network, and bang paths are still in use within Usenet message format <it>Path</it> header lines. They now have only an informational purpose, and are not used for routing, although they can be used to ensure that loops do not occur. In general, this form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/295032.xml">
e-mail address</link> has now been superseded by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/27675.xml">
SMTP</link> "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/710197.xml">
@</link> notation", even by sites still using uucp.</p>
<p>

Currently UUCP is used mainly over high cost links (e.g., marine satellite links). UUCP over TCP/IP (preferably encrypted, such as via the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/28814.xml">
SSH</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 protocol) can be used when a computer doesn't have any fixed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/14921.xml">
IP addresses</link> but is still willing to run a standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/20624.xml">
mail transfer agent</link> (MTA) like <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/48600.xml">
Sendmail</link></software>
 or <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/1265916.xml">
Postfix</link></software>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/25750.xml">
routing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/611421.xml">
sitename</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/2460920.xml">
Wizzy Digital Courier</link> — low-cost internet delivery system using UUCP</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Ian Lance Taylor&#32;(June 2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.airs.com/ian/uucp-doc/uucp_7.html#SEC99">
UUCP 'f' Protocol</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-04</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Using &amp; Managing UUCP</it>.  Ed Ravin, Tim O'Reilly, Dale Doughtery, and Grace Todino.  1996, O'Reilly &amp; Associates, Inc. ISBN 1-56592-153-4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/502632.xml">
Mark Horton</link> (1986).  <it>RFC 976: UUCP Mail Interchange Format Standard</it>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/15285.xml">
Internet Engineering Task Force</link> Requests for Comment.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.faqs.org/faqs/uucp-internals/">
UUCP Internals Frequently Asked Questions</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ece.iisc.ernet.in/FAQ">
Setting up Taylor UUCP + qmail on FreeBSD 5.1</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.airs.com/ian/uucp.html">
Taylor UUCP</weblink> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GPL</link> licensed UUCP package.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.airs.com/ian/uucp-doc/uucp.html">
Taylor UUCP Documentation</weblink> - useful information about UUCP in general and various uucp protocols.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The UUCP Project: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uucp.org/history/">
History</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uucp.org/uumap/">
The UUCP Mapping Project</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
</article>
