<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:08:18[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<idea  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105833840">
<concept  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105835747">
<category  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105838765">
<relation  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100031921">
<type  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105840188">
<kind  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105839024">
<header>
<title>Certified Localisation Professional</title>
<id>17339929</id>
<revision>
<id>227269163</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-22T20:08:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Parsecboy</username>
<id>1879095</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Transliteration</category>
<category>Translation</category>
<category>International trade</category>
<category>Word coinage</category>
<category>Training</category>
<category>Globalization</category>
<category>Information technology and development</category>
<category>Technical communication</category>
<category>International relations</category>
<category>Business terms</category>
<category>Types of words</category>
<category>Certification</category>
<category>Linguistics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="120px" src="TILP_CLPsmall.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>
<p>

The <b>Certified Localisation Professional (CLP)</b> programme (also spelled <b>Certified Localization Professional (CLP)</b>, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/2053693.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22-ise=2C+-ize%22])">
spelling differences</link>) provides for the education and certification of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/290809.xml">
professional</link>s working in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/126844.xml">
internationalization and localization</link>. It is offered by The Institute of Localisation Professionals (TILP) which has the primary aim of developing professional practices in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/6860191.xml">
localisation</link> globally. As an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/286539.xml">
institute</link>, TILP is a <link>
professional body</link> that sets <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/229957.xml">
examination</link>s of competence and acts as a licensing authority for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/13028499.xml">
practitioner</link>s. TILP <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tilponline.org">
http://www.tilponline.org</weblink> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
non-profit organization</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/1171.xml">
abbreviated</link> "NPO", also "not-for-profit"), owned by its members and lead by a Council elected at its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/528785.xml">
Annual General Meeting</link>. TILP is the industry's only professional institute based solely on individual membership <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> and represents both localisation industry professionals and professionals active in localisation-related areas. While there are a number of academic and commercial localisation training programmes being offered, the Certified Localisation Professional (CLP) programme is the only professional programme of its kind that is being delivered world-wide and on a not-for-profit basis. It was originally developed in the context of a European Union funded project.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Between 2006 and 2008 it has been supported by the European Union <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.localisation.ie/techlink">
TechLink Project</weblink> under the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.delind.ec.europa.eu">
Europe Asia IT&amp;C Programme.</weblink></p>

<sec>
<st>
Scope</st>

<p>

The CLP programme is offered at three levels<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Level 1 (introductory)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Level 2 (advanced)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Level 3 (professional)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Each level is currently divided into three strands, each reflecting different professions within localisation:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/19881.xml">
Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/9251.xml">
Engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/17526.xml">
Linguistics</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

TILP is involved in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/3024825.xml">
accreditation</link> and accredits course providers offering courses leading to  CLP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/3692331.xml">
certification</link>. TILP itself offers courses leading to Level 1 certification and is planning to offer courses leading to Level 2 (in 2009) and Level 3 (in 2010).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Development Team</st>
<p>

The CLP course material has been developed by members of The Institute of Localisation Professionals (TILP) in order to support the Institute's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/166188.xml">
mission</link> of developing professionalism in the industry. The material has undergone a careful <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/24116.xml">
peer review</link> process and will be constantly updated to reflect the rapid changes in the industry.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
CLP Level 1</st>

<p>

TILP CLP Level 1 courses are based on an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/74677.xml">
online</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/2432523.xml">
self-learning</link> component and an intensive four-day onsite training and examination component. Both components have to be completed before Level 1 certification can be achieved.</p>
<p>

Online course components cover the following modules:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Introduction to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
Information Technology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Localisation and the Software Engineering Lifecycle (see also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/248932.xml">
Software Development</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Software I18N Enablement and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/5295.xml">
Character Handling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Localisation Kitting and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/7077.xml">
File</link> Preparation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

MS Windows-based [User Interface] Localisation Tools</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

MS Windows- based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/644223.xml">
Computer Assisted Translation</link> (CAT) Tools</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Introduction to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/430476.xml">
Terminology</link>, Term Bases and Terminology Resources</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Introduction to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/29090.xml">
Test Plans</link>, Scripts/Cases, Bug Reporting and Classification</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Introduction to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
Website</link> Localisation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Introduction to Localisation <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/24042.xml">
Project Management</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The four-day onsite intensive training courses are being offered by members of the TILP Local Partnership programme in different locations around the world. The onsite training courses are delivered by TILP appointed and accredited trainers in collaboration with local partners. The content of the onsite courses is identical between locations, except for Day 1. The onsite courses are structured as follows:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Day 1</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Introduction to Regional Localisation Issues (the content of this module is adapted to reflect specific local interests and will be delivered by a local trainer)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Day 2</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Localisation Project I - Project Analysis; Project Planning; Internationalization Testing</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Day 3</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Localisation Project II - Translation; Localisation Engineering and Testing; Project Closure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Day 4</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Exam Preparation</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Exams</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Fee Structure and Benefits</st>
<p>

Fees have been agreed with local partners to reflect the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/217149.xml">
purchasing power</link> of people living in the different regions where CLP courses are being offered. This is why course registration fees in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/30305.xml">
developing regions</link> are around €200 while fees in more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/261460.xml">
developed regions</link> are between €500 and €800 euro.</p>
<p>

Course participants receive a special CLP Tools Distribution that includes full versions of:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Alchemy Catalyst 7.0 Translator/Pro Edition*</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SDL Trados 2007 SP2 Freelance Edition*</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SDL Passolo 2007</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Participants also receive:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

One-year Associate Membership of TILP <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tilponline.org">
http://www.tilponline.org</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

One-year subscription to Multilingual magazine <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.multilingual.com">
http://www.multilingual.com</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The Institute of Localisation Professionals (TILP)</st>
<p>

<image width="180px" src="TILP_Logo_lowres.jpg‎" type="thumb">
</image>

The Institute of Localisation Professionals (TILP) has the primary aim of developing professional practices in localisation globally. TILP is a non-profit organisation, owned by its members and lead by a Council elected at its Annual General Meeting. TILP represents both localisation industry professionals and professionals active in localisation-related areas. </p>


<ss1>
<st>
Develop professional practices globally</st>
<p>

It is the primary goal of TILP to develop professional practices in localisation globally. TILP represents localisation industry professionals and professionals active in localisation related areas. These include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Software publishers and publishers of other material using electronic media </entry>
</list>

eContent providers 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Localisation service providers </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tools developers </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Trainers and educators (including third level colleges) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Researchers </entry>
</list>

TILP aims to 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Provide professional certification. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Be the representative body for localisation professionals </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Be the reference point at global level for the localisation industry and those requiring information about it </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Promote the industry through a variety or publications and activities </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Provide the infrastructure for a range of activities supporting the development of the industry </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Maintain direct and regular contact with localisation companies, government departments and agencies, researchers and students, and the media and international consultancy firms </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Activities </st>
<p>

To achieve its aims, TILP will provide professional certification and establish a register of professional members. It will also organise a range of related activities:
Annual conference 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Workshops for localisation professionals </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Executive briefing for the TILP Council </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Support of organisations that contribute to the development of the profession. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Web-site </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lobbying and awareness raising </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Collaboration</st>
<p>

The implementation of the CLP Programme is supported by the European Union of Associations of Translation Companies (EUATC)<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.euatc.org/">
http://www.euatc.org/</weblink>, the European Union TechLink project <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.localisation.ie/techlink">
http://www.localisation.ie/techlink</weblink>, Alchemy Software Development <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alchemysoftware.ie/index.html">
http://www.alchemysoftware.ie/index.html</weblink>, SDL <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sdl.com/en/">
http://www.sdl.com/en/</weblink> and Multilingual magazine <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.multilingual.com/">
http://www.multilingual.com/</weblink>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The TechLink Project</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Logo_Small.jpg‎‎" type="thumb">
<caption>

The Europe-Asia Localisation Technology Training Initiative
</caption>
</image>
 TechLink will link two of Europe’s premier educational institutions in the areas of localisation technology, localisation training and distance learning - the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.localisation.ie">
Localisation Research Centre (LRC)</weblink> based at the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ul.ie">
University of Limerick</weblink>, Ireland, and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://isg.urv.es/">
Intercultural Studies Group</weblink>at the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.urv.cat/en_index.html">
Universitat Rovira I Virgili</weblink> in Spain - with one of India’s premier software technology centres, the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdacmumbai.in/">
C-DAC Mumbai</weblink>(formerly the National Centre for Software Technology) thus supporting its efforts to provide accredited teaching and training for localisers. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tilponline.org">
The Institute of Localisation Professionals</weblink>(TILP) will contribute its expertise in the area of professional certification.</p>
<p>

TechLink’s objectives are to:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Establish and reinforce links between educational centres working with the localisation communities of Europe and Asia. These communities will be accessed initially through the TechLink partners, and later through the TechLink Network, an extension to the already existing Localisation Teaching, Training and Research Network operating under the umbrella of the LRC. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Raise the awareness among the European localisation community, especially amongst researchers, educationalists, tools and technology developers and standards bodies, to the needs and requirements of Asian language communities. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Analyse the educational and training needs of localisers in Asia, specifically India and South East Asia (requirement specification).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Adapt existing curricula and existing localisation teaching and training courses to these needs. </entry>
</list>

Develop distance teaching and training courses (eLearning). 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Accredit Asian educational and training partners by the Institute of Localisation Professionals (TILP). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Offer localisation education and training courses in Asia. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Establish the TechLink network of teaching and training organisations and collaborate with industry associations, including the Globalisation and Localisation Association (GALA) and the Localisation Industry Standards Association (LISA). </entry>
</list>

TechLink will organise University and technical training courses in localisation, using European technology, information, curricula and teaching adapted to the needs and requirements of its Asian partners. Localisation skills will be upgraded, knowledge transferred, institutional capabilities improved, research will be integrated and curricula developed. Beneficiaries will be students, academic and business professionals especially Asian SMEs. The liaison and collaboration established during this project will be long lasting.
Online course material is made available by TechLink (via TILP) for non-commercial use under the Creative Commons license and according to <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tilponline.org/clponline/privacy.shtml">
published policies</weblink>.
TechLink is supported by the European Union Europe Asia Programme</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The European Union Europe Asia Programme</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Europe_Aid_ITC.jpg‎" type="thumb">
</image>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.europa.eu.int/comm/europeaid">
Asia IT&amp;C Programme</weblink> was launched in October 1999 as an initiative by the European Union (EU) in order to co-finance mutually beneficial projects in Information Technology and Communication between Europe and Asia. Information Technology and Communication is a cross-cutting theme, which supports and enhances the development and co-operation policy of the EU. The total budget allocated to the First Phase of the Programme was €30 million. In November 2003 a Second Phase of the Asia IT&amp;C Programme was approved. EU-Asia IT&amp;C Phase II rolls out in 2004 and the indicative amount available for the 2004 Call will be €9.95 million.
The Programme can supply up to 90% co-financing to Information Technology and Communication projects proposed by a consortium of non-profit organisations from EU Member States and selected Asian countries in the areas of agriculture, e-Governance, education, health, environment, and transport. The 90% co-financing will apply only to those actions, where the main beneficiaries are in one of the 8 Least Developed Counties.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/4733.xml">
Bidirectional script support</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/160987.xml">
CJK</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/261460.xml">
Developed regions</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/30305.xml">
Developing regions</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/229957.xml">
Examination</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/1540855.xml">
Globalization Management System</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/3823946.xml">
Glocalization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/1296785.xml">
International Components for Unicode</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/126844.xml">
Internationalization and localization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/419513.xml">
Input method editor</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
Non-profit organization</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <paradigm wordnetid="113804375" confidence="0.8">
<linguistic_relation wordnetid="113797142" confidence="0.8">
<inflection wordnetid="113803782" confidence="0.8">
<grammatical_relation wordnetid="113796779" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/234273.xml">
Separation of concerns</link></grammatical_relation>
</inflection>
</linguistic_relation>
</paradigm>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Region code</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/6860191.xml">
Language localization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/8735708.xml">
Game localization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/13477931.xml">
Computer russification</link>, localization into Russian language</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/221917.xml">
Language code</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Professional body</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/2852772.xml">
Pseudolocalization</link>, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/29090.xml">
software testing</link> method for testing a software product's readiness for localization.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/380586.xml">
Punycode</link>, translating Unicode into the character sets for network host names</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes </st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.multilingual.com/articleDetail.php?id=1039">
New Organizations Serve the Localization Industry</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.multilingual.com/articleDetail.php?id=517">
Certified Localisation Professional</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tilponline.org/clp">
CLP Programme</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wiktionary-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wiktionary
</caption>
</image>

Look up <it>, </it>'<b><it> in <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/156658.xml">
Wiktionary</link></web_site>
, the free dictionary.</it></b></p>



<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Perspectives on Localization</it>, Keiran Dunne (editor), American Translators Association Scholarly Monograph Series XIII, John Benjamins Publishing, [2006]. ISBN 0890-4111</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>.NET Internationalization: The Developer's Guide to Building Global Windows and Web Applications</it>, Guy Smith-Ferrier, Addison-Wesley Professional, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/1332.xml">
7 August</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>.  ISBN 0-321-34138-4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>A Practical Guide to Localization</it>, Bert Esselink, John Benjamins Publishing, [2000].  ISBN 1-58811-006-0</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Business Without Borders: A Strategic Guide to Global Marketing</it>, Donald A. DePalma, Globa Vista Press [2004]. ISBN 978-0976516903</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>The Moving Text: Localization, translation, and distribution</it>, Anthony Pym, John Benjamins Publishing Company, [2004]. ISBN 0929-7316</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</kind>
</type>
</relation>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</article>
