<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:00:27[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Universal Standard Book Code</title>
<id>17399943</id>
<revision>
<id>224012230</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-06T22:51:41Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Fabrictramp</username>
<id>1997572</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from May 2008</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
<category>Research</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
<category>Uncategorized pages needing expert attention</category>
<category>Pages needing expert attention</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from May 2008</category>
<category>Wikify from May 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is written like  and may require .</b>
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Universal_Standard_Book_Code&amp;action=edit">
help improve it</weblink> by rewriting it in an . <it>(May 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.</b>
Please help recruit one or <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Universal_Standard_Book_Code&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> yourself. See the  for details.Please consider using  to associate this request with a </col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Ambox_?.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>All or part of this article may be .</b>
Please help . Suggestions may be on the . <it>(May 2008)</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>


<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Universal_Standard_Book_Code&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(May 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Universal_Standard_Book_Code&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Universal+Standard+Book+Code%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(May 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

The increased use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computers</link> in handling <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/190988.xml">
bibliographic</link> data and the accumulation of large numbers of items, running into millions, will mean less and less involvement of the human element in the various processes such as manual key allocation and quality control. This trend has now become established at least within <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link> professionals and is now accepted as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/928.xml">
axiom</link> that the more we eliminate the human involvement from the internal technical retrieval mechanisms of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/237495.xml">
information system</link> the more successful and free from errors the system will be. Our interest here is the automatic control of large collections of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> records with particular emphasis on unique identification and quality control.</p>
<p>

Today, the identification and control of bibliographic items is primarily based on an arbitrarily allocated key which accompanies the corresponding record throughout its processing history. Typical keys are the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/14919.xml">
ISBN</link> (International Standard Book Number) and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/234930.xml">
ISSN</link> (International Standard Serials Number). The USBC (Universal Standard Book Number) is generated automatically from pertinent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/190988.xml">
bibliographic</link> data elements, independent of centralised bodies such as the SBN (Standard Book Number) agency.</p>

<sec>
<st>
USBC Criteria</st>
<p>

The <b>USBC</b> is an alphanumeric code which is produced by means of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> which does not require any a priori information about the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/190988.xml">
bibliographic</link> item. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/420036.xml">
universality</link> of the code implies that it is possible to regenerate this at any time and at any part of the world by means of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> which conforms to the following criteria:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Unique items receive unique codes.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> is independent of source input.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The code is as short as possible.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> is easy to implement.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The code is regenerable so that the same code is derived for the same item at different times.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The code can be fixed or variable in length, depending on the operational requirements for record identification.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 It is possible to verify the code manually.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Theoretical Basis</st>
<p>

The theoretical basis for the derivation of the code is sound since it is based on the well established <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/14773.xml">
information theory</link>. More specifically, a principle of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/149354.xml">
information science</link> states that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/9891.xml">
entropy</link> of a set of symbols is maximised when the probability of occurrence of each becomes the same. The USBC algorithm utilises this principle to construct codes (keys) from pertinent fields in order to locate and retrieve unique records as well as clusters of records with lexically homogeneous information. The codes derived offer a very high discriminating strength of over 98% with the use of only 7 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/3365.xml">
bytes</link> per code, where each <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/3365.xml">
byte</link> is selected from the least frequent characters found in pertinent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/190988.xml">
bibliographic</link> fields.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Research Information</st>
<p>

The original research was carried out by Professor <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aueb.gr/Users/yannakoudakis/english/index.htm">
E. J. Yannakoudakis</weblink> at the Postgraduate School of Computer Science, University of Bradford, W. Yorkshire, England, between 1975–1978. The project has received funding from the <library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/18934361.xml">
British Library</link></library>
, the Ministry of Education, the European Union and several other organisations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J., Ayres F. H. &amp; Huggill J. A. W., Character coding for bibliographical record control, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://comjnl.oxfordjournals.org/">
Computer Journal</weblink>, Vol. 23, No. 1, pp. 53-60, 1980.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J., Derived search keys for bibliographic retrieval, Proc. 6th ACM Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval, Washington, SIGIR, pp. 220-237, USA, 5-12 June 1983.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ayres F. H., Huggill J. A. W. &amp; Yannakoudakis E. J., The Universal Standard Bibliographic Code (USBC): Its use for cleaning, merging and controlling large databases, Program, Vol. 22, No. 2, pp. 117-132, 1988.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J. &amp; Wu A. K. P., Quasi-Equifrequent group generation and evaluation, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://comjnl.oxfordjournals.org/">
Computer Journal</weblink>, Vol. 25, No. 2, pp. 183-187, 1982.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J., A universal record identification scheme, Computer Bulletin, Vol. 2, No. 33, pp. 20, September 1982.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J., Intelligent matching and retrieval for electronic document manipulation, Text Processing &amp; Document Manipulation, J. C. van Vliet (Ed.), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cambridge.org/">
Cambridge University Press</weblink>, pp. 65-77, April 1986.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J. &amp; Ridley M. J., The DOCMATCH Project: Automating document delivery by linking references to full text databases, Journal of Outlook on Research Libraries, Vol. 11, No. 9, pp. 3-7, 1989.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J., A formal coding structure for database record processing, International Journal of Cybernetics &amp; General Systems KYBERNETES, Vol. 18, No. 1, pp. 60-70, 1989.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J., Ayres F. H. &amp; Huggill J. A. W., An expert system for quality control in cataloguing and document identification, International Journal of Expert Systems for Information Management, Vol. 2, No. 2, pp. 119-139, 1989.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J., Ayres F. H. &amp; Huggill J. A. W., Matching of citations between non-standardized databases, International Journal of the American Society for Information Science, Vol. 41, No. 8, pp. 599-610, 1990.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yannakoudakis E. J. &amp; Ridley M. J., DOCMATCH II: Automated linking between bibliographic and full-text databases, Bibliographic Access in Europe, Lorcan Dempsey (Ed.), Gower, pp. 232-240, 1990.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ayres F. H., Huggill J. A. W., Ridley M. J. &amp; Yannakoudakis E. J., DOCMATCH: Automated input to ADONIS, Journal of Interlending and Document Supply, Vol. 18, No. 3, pp. 92-97, 1990.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ayres F. H., Ellis D., Huggill J. A. W. &amp; Yannakoudakis E. J., The USBC and control of the bibliographic data base, Journal of Information Technology and Libraries, Vol. 1, No. 1, pp. 44-48, March l982.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ayres F. H., Ellis D., Huggill J. A. W. &amp; Yannakoudakis E. J., Coding for Union File Creation: A National Database, British Library Bibliographic Services Division, London, April 1984, ISBN 0-7123-1020-7 (Review In: Program, Vol. 19, No. 4, pp. 391-394, 1985).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
