<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:25:43[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Inductive bias</title>
<id>173926</id>
<revision>
<id>231967570</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-14T20:21:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rajah</username>
<id>107598</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Machine learning</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>inductive bias</b> of a learning <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> is the set of assumptions that the learner uses to predict outputs given inputs that it has not encountered (Mitchell, 1980).<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link>, one aims to construct algorithms that are able to <it>learn</it> to predict a certain target output. To achieve this, the learning algorithm is presented some training examples that demonstrate the intended relation of input and output values. Then the learner is supposed to approximate the correct output, even for examples that have not been shown during training.  Without any additional assumptions, this task cannot be solved exactly since unseen situations might have an arbitrary output value. The kind of necessary assumptions about the nature of the target function are subsumed in the term <it>inductive bias</it> (Mitchell, 1980; desJardins and Gordon, 1995). </p>
<p>

A classical example of an inductive bias is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/36797.xml">
Occam's Razor</link>, assuming that the simplest consistent hypothesis about the target function is actually the best. Here <it>consistent</it> means that the hypothesis of the learner yields correct outputs for all of the examples that have been given to the algorithm.</p>
<p>

Approaches to a more formal definition of inductive bias are based on mathematical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/3729225.xml">
logic</link>. Here, the inductive bias is a logical formula that, together with the training data, logically entails the hypothesis generated by the learner. Unfortunately, this strict formalism fails in many practical cases, where the inductive bias can only be given as a rough description (e.g. in the case of <link>
neural networks</link>), or not at all.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Types of inductive biases</st>
<p>

The following is a list of common inductive biases in machine learning algorithms.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Maximum <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/801135.xml">
conditional independence</link></b>: if the hypothesis can be cast in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/38526.xml">
Bayesian</link> framework, try to maximize conditional independence. This is the bias used in the <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/87339.xml">
Naive Bayes classifier</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Minimum <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/416612.xml">
cross-validation</link> error</b>: when trying to choose among hypotheses, select the hypothesis with the lowest cross-validation error. Although cross-validation may seem to be free of bias, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/1297402.xml">
No Free Lunch</link> theorems show that cross-validation must be biased.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Maximum margin</b>: when drawing a boundary between two classes, attempt to maximize the width of the boundary. This is the bias used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/65309.xml">
Support Vector Machines</link>. The assumption is that distinct classes tend to be separated by wide boundaries.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/331325.xml">
Minimum description length</link></b>: when forming a hypothesis, attempt to minimize the length of the description of the hypothesis. The assumption is that simpler hypotheses are more likely to be true. See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/36797.xml">
Occam's razor</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Minimum features</b>: unless there is good evidence that a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/5245063.xml">
feature</link> is useful, it should be deleted. This is the assumption behind <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/1179950.xml">
feature selection</link> algorithms.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Nearest neighbors</b>: assume that most of the cases in a small neighborhood in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/5245063.xml">
feature space</link> belong to the same class. Given a case for which the class is unknown, guess that it belongs to the same class as the majority in its immediate neighborhood. This is the bias used in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/1775388.xml">
k-nearest neighbor algorithm</link>. The assumption is that cases that are near each other tend to belong to the same class.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Shift of bias</st>
<p>

Although most learning algorithms have a static bias, some algorithms are designed to shift their bias as they acquire more data (Utgoff, 1984). This does not avoid bias, since the bias shifting process itself must have a bias.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/40786.xml">
Bias</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/47278.xml">
Cognitive bias</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/1297402.xml">
No free lunch in search and optimization</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

desJardins, M., and Gordon, D.F. (1995). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/article/desjardins95evaluation.html">
Evaluation and selection of biases in machine learning</weblink>. Machine Learning Journal, 5:1--17, 1995.</p>
<p>

Mitchell, T.M. (1980). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/mitchell80need.html">
The need for biases in learning generalizations</weblink>. CBM-TR 5-110, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ.</p>
<p>

Utgoff, P.E. (1984). Shift of bias for inductive concept learning. Doctoral dissertation, Department of Computer Science, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ.</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
