<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:13:46[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<economist  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="110043643">
<person  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="100007846">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<alumnus  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="109786338">
<header>
<title>Sukhadeo Thorat</title>
<id>17507870</id>
<revision>
<id>231766535</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-13T21:37:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DumZiBoT</username>
<id>6085301</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Jawaharlal Nehru University alumni</category>
<category>Indian economists</category>
<category>People from Maharashtra</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Padma Shri recipients</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>Year of birth missing (living people)</category>
<category>Wikify from May 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Person</name>
<parameters>

<image width="150px" src="">
</image>
<birth_place>
<legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/20629.xml">
Maharashtra</link></legal_power>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
</birth_place>
<alma_mater>
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/1505056.xml">
Jawaharlal Nehru University</link></university>
 (Ph.D)</alma_mater>
<field>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/9223.xml">
Economics</link></field>
<nationality>
<image width="20px" src="Flag_of_India.svg">
</image>
‎  <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
n</nationality>
<name>
Prof. Sukhadeo Thorat</name>
<work_institution>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/1906142.xml">
University Grants Commission</link> (2006 -     )</work_institution>
</parameters>
</template>


<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Sukhadeo_Thorat&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(May 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

Prof. <b>Sukhadeo Thorat</b> (Maharasthra) (born ) is an <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
n <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/57349.xml">
economist</link> and chairman of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/1906142.xml">
University Grants Commission</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Biography</st>
<p>

Sukhadeo Thorat was born in village Mahimapur, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/1906850.xml">
Amravati district</link></district>
</location>
</region>
, <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/20629.xml">
Maharashtra</link></legal_power>
, India. He did B.A from Milind College of Arts, Aurangabad (Maharashtra), M.A. in Economics from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/13353775.xml">
Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Marathwada University</link></university>
, M.Phil/Ph.D in Economics from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/1505056.xml">
Jawaharlal Nehru University</link></university>
, and Diploma in Economic Planning, Main School of Planning Warsaw, Poland. The <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/11018035.xml">
University of Kalyani</link></university>
 and <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/13399981.xml">
Avinashilingam University</link></university>
honoured him by conferring D.Litt on 26.04.2007 and 01.09.2007 respectively<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
International Trips</st>

<p>

From February 1989 to 1991, Prof Thorat was visiting faculty at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/14875.xml">
Iowa State University</link></university>
, USA and Consultant with International Food Policy Research Institute, Washington DC. During all these years of his teaching and research, he has some 13 books and more than 70 Research papers published in esteemed national and International journals. He has worked on more than 25 Research Projects. He has presented around 50 papers in several national and international seminars and conferences. Prof. Thorat has been visited USA, Poland, Sweden, Denmark, Germany, Netherlands, UK, Italy, China, Iran, Nepal, Finland, South Africa, Japan, Ethiopia, Thailand, Philippines, France &amp; Northern Ireland so far.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Memberships</st>

<p>

Prof Thorat has been Member of several bodies like CAPART, Social justice Division of Planning Commission, Academic Council of Dr Babasaheb Ambedkar Central University, Centre of Buddhist Studies, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/413218.xml">
Himachal Pradesh University</link></university>
 and in the governing bodies of many more Institutions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Awards</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <award wordnetid="106696483" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/442893.xml">
Padma Shri</link></award>
 (2008)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dr Ambedkar Chetna Award by Manwatawadi Rachana Manch Jallunder,</entry>
</list>

Punjab</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Academic Positions</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Chairman, UGC since February, 2006. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Faculty Member, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi w.e.f. 1980 onwards. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Visiting Faculty at Department of Economics, Iowa State University, AMES, USA during 1989-1991. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director, Indian Institute of Dalit Studies, New Delhi w.e.f. January, 2003 to February, 2006. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lecturer, Vasantrao Naik College, Aurangabad during 1973-80. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Research Associate of International Food Policy Research Institute, Washington DC, U.S.A. since 1992.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Publications</st>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Books</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Technological Change and Regional Differentiation: An Analysis of Dry Land Agriculture in Maharashtra. Khama, Delhi 1993 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Linkages between Government Spending, Growth, and Poverty in Rural India, (With Shenggen Fan, Peter Hazell), Research Report 110, International Food Policy Research Institute, Washington D.C., 1999 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Slum in Metropolies-Living Environment, (with Prof. Sudesh Nangia), June 2000, Shipra Publication, Delhi. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rural Development-Problem and Prospect, (edited) March, 2001, Pravara Rural Development Association </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Small Hands- Child Labor in South Asia (with? Kristoffel Lieten &amp; Ravi Srivastava) Manohar, Delhi (2003) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Development of Rural Infrastructure in India (with Simita Sirohi) Academic Delhi (2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Industrialization, Economic Reforms and Regional Development: Essays in Honour of Prof Ashok K. Mathur (edited) with Jaya Prakash Pradhan &amp; Vinoj Abraham, Shipra Publication (2004), </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caste, Race, and Discrimination-Discourse in International context (edited) (with Umakant), Rawat Publication, Jaipur (2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reservation and Private Sector: Quest for Equal Opportunity and Growth (Edited) with Aryama and Prasant Negi. (2005), Rawat Publication. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Untouchability in Rural India ? Sage, 2006 (with G. Shah, Harsh Mander, Satish Deshpande &amp; Amrita). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A Reader in Dalit Studies (Edited) (with John Webster), (Forthcoming) Rawat Publication. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dalit human development report 2006 (with Rawat), Forthcoming. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dalits in India ? Social and Economic Profile (forthcoming) Sage. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ambedkar's Role in Economic Planning and Water Policy, August 1998 Shipra Publication, Delhi </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ambedkar in Retrospect ? Essays in Economics, Society, and politics (Edited) with Aryama &amp; Negi ? Rawat Publication. Forthcoming </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ambedkar on Social Exclusion and Inclusive Policy (with Narender), forthcoming.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Papers Published</st>

<p>

<b><it>On general Economics-Agricultural Development, Rural Poverty and other themes</it></b> </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Irrigation, New Agricultural Technology, and Regional Differentiation: Development Experiences of Scarcity Region, in Problems and Prospects of Rural Development in Maharshtra, by V.M. Dandekar, S.D. Gokhale &amp; Ram Takwalke(ed.), Shirvida Prakashan, Pune. 1992 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Peter Hazell and Shenggen Fan: Impact of Public Expenditure on Poverty in Rural India, Economic and Political Weekly, September 30-October 6, 2000. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 With Peter Hazell and Shenggen Fan: Government Spending, Growth and Poverty in Rural India, American Journal of Agricultural Economics 82(4) AAES (USA) 1038-1051, November 2000 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Some theoretical Considerations in Reforms of Rural Institutions in Agricultural Development in India, Edited, S.G. Bhanushali, and A.G. Pujari, Department of Economic, Siwaji University, Kolhapur 1998 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Land holding, Tenancy and Emerging Issues for Land Reform in India in "Agricultural Development Perspective for Ninth Five Year Plan" by Bupat Desai (ed.), Oxford and IBH Delhi, 1996. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Farm Size and Capital Structure- Evidence from Drought Prone Agriculture of Maharashtra, in Productivity, Vol. 35 (2), National Productivity Council, Delhi. July - Sept. 1994 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Land Ownership Structure and Non-Farm Employment of Rural Households in India in Indian Journal of Labor Economics, Special Issue, December 1993. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Regional Dimensions of Rural Credits in India in The Indian Geographical Journal, 66 (2), December 1992. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Theories of Agricultural Development: Trends and Perspective, Economic Paper No: 211, Research Institute for Developing Countries, Warsaw, Poland. 1990 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Land Holding, Agricultural Growth and Rural Poverty in India, (with Peter Hazell &amp; Shenggen Fan) in Peter Hazell and G.S. Bhalla, (editor), "Agricultural Growth and Poverty Linkages in India", International Food Policy Research Institute, Washington D.C., (Forth coming). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Population pressure, Land holding Structure and Land Use Pattern: An Analysis of Interlinkages, in "Population pressure and environmental impact in Himalayan Region" (edited) by Abrol. 1999 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Child Labour in Rural India: Magnitude and Determinants (with Nidi Sadana) in Small Hands ? Child Labor in South Asia (with ? Kristoffel Lieten &amp; Ravi Srivastava) Manohar, Delhi (2003) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Pattern of Urbanization and Strategy for Urban Development in India (with A.Kundu) in National Commission on Urbanization, Research Study Report, Vol. V, Government of India, August 1989. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 With Shenggen Fan and Ashok Gulati, IFPRI: Investment, Subsidies and Pro-Poor Growth in Rural India, Discussion Paper 00716, September 2007 </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b><it>Paper On problems of Dalits, Tribals and Economic of Caste and Babasaheb Ambedkar</it></b> </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 With Joel Lee: Caste Discrimination and Food Security Program, Economic and Political Weekly, October 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caste System and Economic Discrimination: Lesson from theories in Reservation in Private Sector: Quest for Equal Opportunity, Rawat Publication ? 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reservation and Efficiency: Myth and Reality: Economic and Political Weekly, July 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Remedies Against Market Discrimination: International Experiences Reservation in Private Sector: Quest for Equal Opportunity, Rawat Publication ? 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Schemes of Remedies against Market Discrimination including Reservation in Private Sector, Reservation in Private Sector: Quest for Equal Opportunity, Rawat Publication ? 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Globalization and the Dalits', Sukhadeo Thorat and Martin Macwan, in Reservation in Privates Sector: Quest for Equal Opportunity, Rawat Publication ? 2004 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Economic Status of Scheduled Castes Under Five Year Plans, Ambedkar Journal of Social Development and Justice, Vol. V, (1978). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Isolation and Deprivations: Economic Situation of Tribals in India, in Development Issue in India, Edited, Dr. Solanki, 2000, Department of Economics, Dr. Babashaheeb Marathwa University, Aurangabad, Maharashtra. (1978). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Nomadic Tribes of Maharashtra: An Analysis of their Economic Conditions in "Denofied Tribe, October (1978). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Passage to Adulthood: Perception From Below (with comment by Prof. Satish Sabarwal), in Identity and Adulthood by Sudhir Kakkar (ed.), Oxford, Delhi, (1979). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 New Economic Policy and Its Impact on Employment and Poverty of Scheduled Castes in India, Occasional Paper (DSA) Dept. of Sociology, University of Pune, June 1997 and in "Globalization ? Impact on Dalits", Alternative Vikalp, Vol.V. No.5, (1996). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Policy and Economic Change: Emerging Situation of Scheduled Castes in "Fourth World: Ideological Perspective and Developmental Prognoses" by R.K. Nayak, (Edit) Manohar Publication, New Delhi, (1996). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ambedkar's Thoughts on Economic Development and Planning, in "Fourth World: Ideological Perspective and Developmental Prognoses" by R.K. Nayak, (Edit) Manohar Publication, New Delhi, (1996) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 New Economic Policy and Dalits: Dalit International, News letter Waterford, (U.S.A.) Oct. (1997) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ambedkar and the Economic of Hindu Social order: Understanding its Orthodoxy and Legacy, Walter Fernandes "The Emerging Dalit Identify", Indian Social Institute, (1997) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ambedkar's Views on Economic Development Planning and Role of the State, (Dr. Ambedkar's Memorial Lecture), Dr. Ambedkar Center for Economic Studies, University of Madras, Chennai, March, (1999) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Poverty; Caste and Child Labour: Plight of Scheduled caste and Tribal childrens in Child Labour in India Edited. Klues Voll,..F.E.S Foundation, Delhi, (1999) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Social Security in Unorganized Sector, "How Secure are the Scheduled Caste? Special Issue", Indian Journal of Labour Economics, September, (1999) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dalits After India's Independence ? Where do they stand?, International, News letter Waterford, (U.S.A.) October (1999) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Caste and Labour Market Discrimination" (With R.S. Deshpande) Indian Journal of Labour Economics, Conference Issue, November, (1999) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ambedkar and Nation Building: Reflection on Selected Themes in Anand Kumar (Edited) "Nation Building in India", Radiant, December (1999) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dr. Babashaheeb Ambedkar ? Film as a Lost Opportunity Economic and Political Weekly, April 1 ? 14, (2000) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caste System and Economic Inequality ? Theory and Evidence (With R.S. Deshpande) in Ghanshyam Saha, (Edited) "Dalit Identity and Politics", Sage Publication, New Delhi.(2001) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Economic Status of Social Groups in Maharashtra Emerging Issues, in Sukhadeo Thorat (edited) "Rural Development Problem and Prospect", Pravara Rural Development Association, Loni, Maharashtra, p.317., (2001) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oppression and Denial ? Dalit Discrimination in 1990's EPW, February (2002) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hindu Social System and Human Rights of Dalits: Theoretical Perspective and Empirical Evidence, in "Human Rights of Dalits" (Edited) by Prof. Wagmare. (2003) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caste and Labour Market Discrimination ? Reflection on Theory and facts in Special Issue on Schedule caste Arth Vijyan, October (2003) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 On Reservation policy for private sector, EPW, June 19th ? 25th (2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Remedies Against Economic Discrimination ? International Experience of Reservation Policy in Private Sector in Bibek Debroy and Shyam Babu "The Dalit Question ? Reforms and Social Justice, Globus Delhi (2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Situation of Dalits since Independence ? Some Reflections in Bibek Debroy and Shyam Babu "The Dalit Question ? Reforms and Social Justice, Globus Delhi (2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Strategy of Disincentive and Targeting for Population Control ? Implication on Dalits and Tribals", in Ambedkar journal of Social Sciences and Social Justice MHOW, (2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Caste, Race and United Nation's Perspective on Discrimination ? Coping with Challenges from Asia and Africa", in Sukhadeo Thorat and Umakant, "Caste, Race and Discrimination ? Discourses in International context", Rawat Jaipur, (2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Including the Excluded ? Why and How ? in empower.poor.org Tata Crescent Delhi Volume 1 Issue 2 May (2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rural Non farm Employment and Occupational Diversification of Schedule caste, schedule tribe and other ? comparative study, in Rohini Nayyar and A.K. Sharma, Manohar (forthcoming) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Contesting Views on Panchayat Raj ? Ambedkar in the context of 73rd Amendment Act. (with Narender Kumar), in Sukhadeo Thorat (edited) "Ambedkar in Retrospect ? Reflections on Contribution". (Forth Coming) New Delhi, India. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ambedkar and Dalit Question - Perspective on Restructuring Indian Society, in a book edited by Gupta (forthcoming), Hindu College, University of Delhi. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Including the Excluded ? Why and How', Sukhadeo Thorat in empower.poor.org, Tata Crescent, Delhi, Volume I, Issue II, May 2004. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Is Reservation in the Private Sector Warranted?' Sukhadeo Thorat, The Economic Times, New Delhi, September 7, 2005. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Job Reservation in the Private Sector', Sukhadeo Thorat, The Economic Times, New Delhi, March 26, 2005. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Affirmative Action Needs Refocus', Sukhadeo Thorat, The Economic Times, New Delhi, June 15, 2005. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'The Varna of Efficiency', Sukhadeo Thorat, The Economic Times, New Delhi, October 30, 2004. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Economic Exclusion and Inclusive Policy' ? volume VI issue 4 &amp; 5, the Little Magazine. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Paying of Social Debt' ? Economic &amp; Political Weekly, June 17, 2006 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Inclusiveness in Higher Education' ? Hindu, December 07, 2006. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 'Understanding Caste' ? Times of India, December 27, 2006. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b><it>Others</it></b> </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Enforcing Ideology through Power and Violence ? Experience of Caste Discrimination of Dalits", Conference on "Challenging Caste: Ideologies, Violence, Creativity" Wisconsin University, Madison, October 10, 2002. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Growing as an Untouchable ? Social Psychological of Contesting Victim Hood ? Rumbling Personal Reminiscences", Conference on "Caste and Discourses of the Mind", Organized by BAPU Trust, Pune in collaboration with Centre for Behavioural and Social Sciences in Medicine, University College, London, Pun 14th ? 15th December 2002 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Caste, Exclusion/Discrimination and Deprivation: The Situation of Dalits in India, Concept Paper for DFID, Delhi. May 2003 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Educational Situation of Dalit and Adivasi, Key note address in a conference on educational problem of Marginalised groups, Bombay University, March 2004 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Caste, Ethnicity, and Religion: An Overview of Exclusion/Discrimination and Deprivation" Concept Paper for DFID, Delhi. May 2003 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Persistence of Poverty: Why Do Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes Stay Chronically Poor? (Paper presented in Seminar on Chronic poverty in India, IIPA, Delhi and DFID, London, Centre for Studies on Chronic Poverty 2004. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caste Discriminations and Government Food Security Programme, Indian Institute of Dalit Studies Delhi 2004 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Human Poverty, Social Exclusion and Marginalized Groups, Working Paper, UNDP. 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Affirmative Action Policy in India ? Dimension and issues, paper presented in conference on "Inequality and Inclusive Development" Addis Ababa, Ethiopia. 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caste and Poverty, Concept consequences and measurement paper presented in seminar on "Marginalization and Dalits by Development Alternative, Delhi ? 25th October 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Children, Exclusion and Inequality, Paper Presented in Workshop on "Mid Term Review of Program on Children", Organized by UNICEF, Delhi ? 9th November 2005 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Higher Education in India ? Emerging Issues Related to Access, Inclusiveness and Quality (Nehru Memorial Lecture delivered at University of Mumbai)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://www.ficci.com/hesummit07/cv/CV-_Prof_Thorat.pdf</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</alumnus>
</entity>
</person>
</economist>
</article>
