<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:15:59[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<network  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108434259">
<header>
<title>Social network change detection</title>
<id>17576720</id>
<revision>
<id>235106353</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-30T01:54:11Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CmdrObot</username>
<id>1079367</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Social networks</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Social network change detection</b> (SNCD) is a process of monitoring <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link>s to determine when significant changes to their organizational structure occur and what caused them.  This scientific approach combines analytical techniques from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network analysis</link> with those from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/593680.xml">
statistical process control</link>.  SNCD can be used to detect when significant changes occur in a network.  In application, it requires the use of statistical process control charts to detect changes in observable network measures.  By taking measures of a network over time, a control chart can be used to signal when significant changes occur in the network.  <p>

This approach has been demonstrated to be effective on several real world data sets.  A social network was created for a group of 24 Army officers going through a 1 year graduate program at Columbia University (McCulloh, et al., 2007).  SNCD was able to detect the group's comprehensive exam and identified the most likely time of change to be the week that study questions were sent to the group.  An open source social network of the Al-Qaeda terrorist organization was monitored using SNCD, and it signaled a change in the organization prior to the September 11 terrorist attacks on the Pentagon and the World Trade Center (McCulloh, et al., 2007).  SNCD has also been demonstrated to be effective on simulated data.</p>
<p>

SNCD was initially proposed by Major Ian McCulloh, an assistant professor in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/32173.xml">
U.S. Military Academy</link>'s <link>
Network Science Center</link> in 2006.  Since then, SNCD has been presented at a variety of venues from NetSci2007 in New York City to the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/7433852.xml">
International Network for Social Network Analysis</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 annual conference in 2008, to the <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/13094844.xml">
Military Operations Research Society</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
 Working Group on emerging threats and social networks in 2008.  </p>

<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/1704711.xml">
Complex networks</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Exponential random graph model</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/17117924.xml">
Network Probability Matrix</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/16981683.xml">
Network science</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
Social network analysis</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Baller, D., McCulloh, I., Carley, K.M., and Johnson, A.N. (2008). Specific Communication Network Measure Distribution Estimation. Sunbelt XXVIII, the annual conference for the International Network of Social Network Analysts, Saint Petersburg, FL, 24 January, 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Carley, K. M. (2003). Dynamic network analysis. In P. Pattison (Ed.), Dynamic social network analysis: Workshop summary and papers: 133-145. Washington D.C.: The National Academies Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 McCulloh, I., and Carley, K.M. (2008). Social Network Change Detection. Carnegie Mellon University Technical Report, CMU-CS-08-116.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 McCulloh, I., Garcia, G., Tardieu, K., MacGibon, J., Dye, H., Moores, K., Graham, J. M., &amp; Horn, D. B. (2007). IkeNet: Social network analysis of e-mail traffic in the Eisenhower Leadership Development Program.  (Technical Report, No. 1218).  Arlington, VA: U.S. Army Research Institute for the Behavioral and Social Sciences. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 McCulloh, I., Lospinoso, J., and Carley, K.M. (2007). Social Network Probability Mechanics.  Proceedings of the World Scientific Engineering Academy and Society 12th International Conference on Applied Mathematics, Cairo, Egypt, 29-31 December, 2007, pp. 319-325,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 McCulloh, I., Webb, M., Carley, K.M. (2007). Social Network Monitoring of Al-Qaeda. Network Science Report, Vol 1, pp 25-30.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</network>
</article>
