<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:53:42[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Data stream mining</title>
<id>1760301</id>
<revision>
<id>240709267</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-24T17:36:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jacobolus</username>
<id>166386</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> Business intelligence</category>
<category> Data mining</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Data stream mining</b> is the process of extracting knowledge structures from continuous, rapid data records.
A data stream is an ordered sequence of instances that in many applications of data stream mining can be read only once or a small number of times using limited computing and storage capabilities.
Examples of data streams include computer network traffic, phone conversations, ATM transactions, web searches, and sensor data.
Data stream mining can be considered a subfield of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/42253.xml">
data mining</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/2044947.xml">
knowledge discovery</link>.<p>

In many data stream mining applications, the goal is to predict the class or value of new instances in the data stream given some knowledge about the class membership or values of previous instances in the data stream.
Machine learning techniques can be used to learn this prediction task from labeled examples in an automated fashion.
In many applications, the distribution underlying the instances or the rules underlying their labeling may change over time, i.e. the goal of the prediction, the class to be predicted or the target value to be predicted, may change over time.
This problem is referred to as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/3118600.xml">
concept drift</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Software for data stream mining </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/5100865.xml">
RapidMiner</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
: free open-source software for knowledge discovery, data mining, and machine learning also featuring data stream mining, learning time-varying concepts, and tracking drifting concept (if used in combination with its data stream mining plugin (formerly: concept drift plugin))</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Events on data stream mining </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.liaad.up.pt/~iwkduds/">
International Workshop on Knowledge Discovery from Ubiquitous Data Streams</weblink> held in conjunction with the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ecmlpkdd2007.org/">
18th European Conference on Machine Learning (ECML) and the 11th European Conference on Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (PKDD)</weblink> in Warsaw, Poland, in September 2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.niaad.liacc.up.pt/~jgama/SAC07/">
ACM Symposium on Applied Computing Data Streams Track</weblink> held in conjunction with the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acm.org/conferences/sac/sac2007/">
2007 ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC-2007)</weblink> in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/19159283.xml">
Seoul</link></village>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/16749.xml">
Korea</link></country>
, in March 2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~mgaber/iwmesd/">
IEEE International Workshop on Mining Evolving and Streaming Data (IWMESD 2006)</weblink> to be held in conjunction with the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.comp.hkbu.edu.hk/~wii06/icdm/">
2006 IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM-2006)</weblink> in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/13404.xml">
Hong Kong</link></country>
 in December 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.machine-learning.eu/iwkdds-2006/">
Fourth International Workshop on Knowledge Discovery from Data Streams (IWKDDS)</weblink> to be held in conjunction with the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ecmlpkdd2006.org/">
17th European Conference on Machine Learning (ECML) and the 10th European Conference on Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (PKDD) (ECML/PKDD-2006)</weblink> in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<capital wordnetid="108518505" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/3354.xml">
Berlin</link></urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</seat>
</village>
</area>
</center>
</country>
</city>
</capital>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
, in September 2006.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Researchers working on data stream mining </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Joao Gama, University of Porto, Portugal</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Ralf Klinkenberg</link>, University of Dortmund, Germany</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geocities.com/medhatgaber/">
Mohamed Medhat Gaber</weblink>, Monash University, Australia</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://louisville.edu/~o0nasr01/">
Olfa Nasraoui</weblink>, University of Louisville, USA</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csie.nctu.edu.tw/~hfli/">
Hua-Fu Li</weblink>, National Chiao-Tung University, Taiwan</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Eyke Hüllermeier, University of Marburg, Germany</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Bibliographic references </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Grabtree I. Soltysiak S. Identifying and Tracking Changing Interests. International Journal of Digital Libraries, Springer Verlag, vol. 2, 38-53.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Klinkenberg, Ralf: <it>Learning Drifting Concepts: Example Selection vs. Example Weighting</it>. In Intelligent Data Analysis (IDA), Special Issue on Incremental Learning Systems Capable of Dealing with Concept Drift, Vol. 8, No. 3, pages 281--300, 2004.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Klinkenberg, Ralf: <it>Using Labeled and Unlabeled Data to Learn Drifting Concepts</it>. In Kubat, Miroslav and Morik, Katharina (editors), Workshop notes of the IJCAI-01 Workshop on \em Learning from Temporal and Spatial Data, pages 16--24, IJCAI, Menlo Park, CA, USA, AAAI Press, 2001.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Klinkenberg, Ralf and Joachims, Thorsten: <it>Detecting Concept Drift with Support Vector Machines</it>. In Langley, Pat (editor), Proceedings of the Seventeenth International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), pages 487--494, San Francisco, CA, USA, Morgan Kaufmann, 2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Klinkenberg, Ralf and Renz, Ingrid: <it>Adaptive Information Filtering: Learning in the Presence of Concept Drifts</it>. In Sahami, Mehran and Craven, Mark and Joachims, Thorsten and McCallum, Andrew (editors), Workshop Notes of the ICML/AAAI-98 Workshop \em Learning for Text Categorization, pages 33--40, Menlo Park, CA, USA, AAAI Press, 1998.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Koychev I. Gradual Forgetting for Adaptation to Concept Drift. In Proceedings of ECAI 2000 Workshop Current Issues in Spatio-Temporal Reasoning. Berlin, Germany, 2000, pp. 101-106</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Koychev I. and Schwab I., Adaptation to Drifting User’s Interests, Proc. of ECML 2000 Workshop: Machine Learning in New Information Age, Barcelona, Spain, 2000, pp. 39-45 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Maloof, M.A. and Michalski, R.S. Learning Evolving Concepts Using Partial Memory Approach. Working Notes of the 1995 AAAI Fall Symposium on Active Learning, Boston, MA, pp. 70-73, 1995</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Maloof M. and Michalski R. Selecting examples for partial memory learning. Machine Learning, 41(11), 2000, pp. 27-52.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mitchell T., Caruana R., Freitag D., McDermott, J. and Zabowski D. Experience with a Learning Personal Assistant. Communications of the ACM 37(7), 1994, pp. 81-91.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://webmining.spd.louisville.edu/Websites/PAPERS/journal/Computer-Networks-Jnl-Spec-Issue-Web-Dynamics-2006-Mining-Evolving-Streams-Retrospective-Validation.pdf">
Nasraoui O. , Rojas C., and Cardona C., “ A Framework for Mining Evolving Trends in Web Data Streams using Dynamic Learning and Retrospective Validation ”, Journal of Computer Networks- Special Issue on Web Dynamics, 50(10), 1425-1652, July 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://webmining.spd.louisville.edu/Websites/PAPERS/conference/CIKM-2006-Collaborative-Filtering-Recommender-Sys-in-Evolving-Web-Clickstreams.pdf">
Nasraoui O. , Cerwinske J., Rojas C., and Gonzalez F., "Collaborative Filtering in Dynamic Usage Environments", in Proc. of CIKM 2006 – Conference on Information and Knowledge Management, Arlington VA , Nov. 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Schlimmer J., and Granger R. Incremental Learning from Noisy Data, Machine Learning, 1(3), 1986, 317-357.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Scholz, Martin and Klinkenberg, Ralf: <it>Boosting Classifiers for Drifting Concepts</it>. In Intelligent Data Analysis (IDA), Special Issue on Knowledge Discovery from Data Streams, Vol. 11, No. 1, pages 3-28, March 2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Scholz, Martin and Klinkenberg, Ralf: <it>An Ensemble Classifier for Drifting Concepts</it>. In Gama, J. and Aguilar-Ruiz, J. S. (editors), Proceedings of the Second International Workshop on Knowledge Discovery in Data Streams, pages 53--64, Porto, Portugal, 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Schwab I., Pohl W. and Koychev I. Learning to Recommend from Positive Evidence, Proceedings of Intelligent User Interfaces 2000, ACM Press, 241 - 247.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Widmer G. Tracking Changes through Meta-Learning, Machine Learning 27, 1997, pp. 256-286.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Widmer G. and Kubat M. Learning in the presence of concept drift and hidden contexts. Machine Learning 23, 1996, pp. 69-101.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Books </st>
<p>

Gama J., and Gaber M. M. (Eds), Learning from Data Streams: Processing Techniques in Sensor Networks, a book published by Springer Verlag, 2007.
</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/3118600.xml">
Concept drift</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/42253.xml">
Data mining</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
Machine learning</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
