<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:54:14[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Egg donation</title>
<id>1765384</id>
<revision>
<id>238028658</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-12T22:33:07Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Miscellaneous articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Fertility medicine</category>
<category>Donation</category>
<category>Medicine articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Giving</category>
<category>Articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Pages needing expert attention</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Egg donation</b> is the process by which a woman provides one or several eggs (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/190214.xml">
ova</link>, oocytes) for purposes of assisted reproduction or biomedical research. For assisted reproduction purposes, egg donation involves the process of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/57880.xml">
in vitro fertilization</link> as the eggs are fertilized in the laboratory.  After the eggs have been obtained, the role of the <it>egg donor</it> is complete.  Egg donation is part of the process of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/1611358.xml">
third party reproduction</link>.  
<sec>
<st>
Indication</st>
<p>

A need for egg donation may arise for a number of reasons. Infertile couples may resort to acquiring eggs through egg donation when the female partner cannot have genetic children because she may not have eggs that can be successfully fertilized. This situation is often based on advanced reproductive age. Early onset of menopause which can occur in women as early as their 20’s can require a woman to use donor eggs to grow her family. Some women are born without ovaries or other reproductive organs. Sometimes a woman's reproductive organs have been damaged due to disease or have been forced to have them surgically removed.  Another indication would be a genetic disorder on part of the woman that can be circumvented by using eggs from another person. The couple can personally get acquainted with the egg donor, her children and family members. Or a couple can request an anonymous egg donor. Egg donation is also required for gay couples using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/1514981.xml">
surrogacy</link> (see <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.8">
<right wordnetid="105174653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/7466395.xml">
LGBT parenting</link></right>
</union>
).</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Congenital absence of eggs</b> </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/49364.xml">
Turner syndrome</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/5680834.xml">
Gonadal dysgenesis</link></disease>
/agenesis <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Acquired reduced egg quantity / quality</b> </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/411914.xml">
Oophorectomy</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Premature <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/49611.xml">
menopause</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/7172.xml">
Chemotherapy</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/26350.xml">
Radiation therapy</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/93842.xml">
Autoimmunity</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Advanced maternal age <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Compromised ovarian reserve <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Other</b></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Diseases of X-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/1420406.xml">
Sex linkage</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Repetitive fertilization or pregnancy failure <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Ovaries inaccessible for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/11863132.xml">
egg retrieval</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Procedure</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.</b><p>

  may be able to help recruit one.
If a more appropriate  or 
portalexists, please adjust this template accordingly.</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>


Egg donors are recruited, screened, and give consent prior to participation in the IVF process. Some patients bring their own, <it>designated donors</it>, while other patients rely on the services of often <it>anonymous donors</it> typically recruited by <it>egg donor agencies</it> or, sometimes, IVF programs.
Once the egg donor is recruited, she undergoes the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/57880.xml">
IVF</link> stimulation therapy, followed by the egg retrieval procedure. After retrieval, the ova are handed over to the recipient couple, fertilized by the sperm of the male partner in the laboratory, and after several days, the resulting embryo(s) is placed in the uterus of the recipient. For the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/1399392.xml">
embryo transfer</link> the lining of the recipient has been appropriately prepared in a synchronous fashion. The recipient is usually the person who requested the service and then will carry and deliver the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1771587.xml">
pregnancy</link> and keep the baby.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Results</st>
<p>

Results in treatments with the use of egg from donors often have a better than 50% chance of success. With egg donation, women who are past their reproductive years or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/49611.xml">
menopause</link> can become pregnant. The oldest woman thus to give birth is <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/1402506.xml">
Adriana Iliescu</link></person>
, age 66. 
Babies born after egg donation are not genetically related to the recipient.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Donor motivation</st>
<p>

An egg donor may be motivated by a number of reasons to provide eggs. Some egg donors may be altruistic and feel that participation in the reproductive process provides a benefit for another person, sometimes a person they know or are related to. Others may be attracted to the monetary compensation. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Risks</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Egg donor</st>
<p>

Egg donation carries risks for both donor and recipient. The egg donor may suffer complications from IVF, such as bleeding from the oocyte recovery procedure and reaction to the hormones used to induce hyperovulation (producing more than one egg), including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/1417614.xml">
ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome</link> (OHSS) and, rarely, liver failure<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. The long-term impact of egg donation on donors has not been well studied, but apparently some evidence suggests a risk of early menopause and increased risk of ovarian cancer<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>
<p>

According to Jansen and Tucker, writing in the same ART (assisted reproductive technologies) textbook referenced above<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>, the risk of OHSS varies with the clinic administering the hormones, from 6.6 to 8.4% of cycles,half of them "severe." Patients treated with GnRH agonists appear to be at increased risk compared to those treated with GnRH antagonists. The most severe form of OHSS is life threatening. One study in the Netherlands found 10 documented cases of deaths from IVF, with a rate of 1:10,000. "All of these patients were treated with GnRH agonists and none of these cases have been published in the scientific literature." Hormone treatments that can be dangerous in the short-term may have long-term health effects.</p>
<p>

Daniel Navot, writing in the same collection of reports states that mild OHSS is a sign that treatment is working and describes the symptoms of moderate OHSS as "includes significant ovarian englargement (5-12 cm)...abdominal pain, significant bloating, nausea, and diarrhea," symptoms attributable to ovarian enlargement and elevate estrogen levels. Signs that upgrade moderate OHSS to the severe form include liver dysfunction and anasarca.  Criteia for severe OHSS include enlarge ovary, ascites, hemotacrit &amp;gt; 45%, WBC &amp;gt; 15,000, oliguria, creatinine 1.0-1.5 mg/dl, creatinine clearance &amp;gt; 50 ml/min, liver dysfunction, anasarca. Critical OHSS includes enlarged ovary, tense ascites with hydrothorax and pericardial effusion, hematocrit &amp;gt; 55%, WBC &amp;gt; 25,000, oligoanuria, creatinine &amp;gt; 1.6 mg/dl, creatinine clearance &amp;gt; 50 ml/min, renal failure, thromboembolic phenomena,ARDS.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Recipient</st>
<p>

The recipient has the risk of contracting a transmittable disease. While the donor may test negative for HIV, such testing does not exclude the possibility that the donor has contracted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/14170.xml">
HIV</link> very recently, so the recipient faces a residual risk of exposure.</p>
<p>

The recipient also trusts that the genetic and medical history of the donor is accurate.  This factor of trust should not be underestimated in importance.  Donors are paid thousands of dollars; monetary compensation may attract unscrupulous individuals inclined to conceal their true motivations.  Moreover, recipients will have a de facto relationship to the biological parent of their offspring for life.  Half of the child's genetic makeup, and related traits, capabilities, tendencies, etc. will come from the donor.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/79449.xml">
Multiple birth</link> is a common complication if the physician transfers too many embryos. Incidence of twin births is very high.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Custody</st>
<p>

Generally legal documents are signed to hand oocytes over to the recipient and renounce rights of ownership and custody on part of the donor, so that there will be no claims on part of the donor concerning the offspring.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Legality</st>
<p>

Egg donation is regulated and /or prohibited in many countries. In the United States, having an attorney draft a contract is often necessary to establish and confirm the parental rights over any child.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Donor registries</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/14714106.xml">
Donor registration</link></it>
</indent>
A donor registry is a registry to facilitate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/3357949.xml">
donor conceived people</link>, sperm donors and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/1765384.xml">
egg donor</link>s to establish contact with genetic kindred. They are mostly used by donor conceived people to find genetic half-siblings from the same egg- or sperm donor.</p>
<p>

Some donors are non-anonymous, but most are anonymous, i.e. the donor conceived person doesn't know the true identity of the donor. Still, he/she may get the donor number from the fertility clinic. If that donor had donated before, then other donor conceived people with the same donor number are thus genetic half-siblings. In short, donor registries match people who type in the same donor number.</p>
<p>

Alternatively, if the donor number isn't available, then known donor characteristics, e.g. hair, eye and skin color may be used in matching.</p>
<p>

Donors may also register, and therefore, donor registries may also match donors with their genetic children.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womensinstitute.org/institute/egg-donation.html">
Womensinstiture</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
Textbook of Assisted Reproductive Techniques, Laboratory and Clinical Perspectives, edited by David K. Gardner, 2001</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nationalreview.com/lopez/lopez200403260930.asp">
Kathryn Jean Lopez on Egg Selling on National Review Online</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
Textbook of Assisted Reproductive Techniques, Laboratory and Clinical Perspectives, edited by David K. Gardner, 2001</entry>
</reflist>

ASRM Practice Committee Reports, Fertility Sterility 82, Suppl. 1, Sept. 2004.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<benefactor wordnetid="109608709" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<good_person wordnetid="110138767" confidence="0.8">
<donor wordnetid="110025730" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/2557514.xml">
Sperm donation</link></causal_agent>
</donor>
</good_person>
</person>
</benefactor>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/3357949.xml">
Donor conceived people</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.conceiveabilities.com/donor_pg_4b.htm">
Egg Donor Medications</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hfea.gov.uk/cps/rde/xchg/hfea/hs.xsl/271.html">
For Donors - Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority UK</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.FertilityStories.com/eggdonor.htm">
Fertility Stories</weblink> - Stories of couples using egg donation and of women who have chosen to become egg donors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.havewombwilltravel.com">
A book describing egg donation in the Ukraine and then surrogacy in the US</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.parentsviaeggdonation.org">
Parents Via Egg Donation Organization</weblink> was created to provide an informational and supportive environment where parents and parents-to-be can come together to exchange information about all facets of the egg donation process with respect to growing their families.</entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/9728362.xml">
Charity</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/367725.xml">
Donation</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/43846.xml">
Organ donation</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/12687113.xml">
Organ donation under Jewish law</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/530572.xml">
Non-heart beating donation</link>•</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other biologic donations</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
Gamete donation (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/1765384.xml">
Egg donation</link>, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<benefactor wordnetid="109608709" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<good_person wordnetid="110138767" confidence="0.8">
<donor wordnetid="110025730" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/2557514.xml">
Sperm donation</link></causal_agent>
</donor>
</good_person>
</person>
</benefactor>
</physical_entity>
) • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/1510374.xml">
Embryo donation</link> • <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/505536.xml">
Blood donation</link></commodity>
</merchandise>
</artifact>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/3251004.xml">
Body donation</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/844785.xml">
Car donation</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
