<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:20:08[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Brian Horwitz (hockey)</title>
<id>17697861</id>
<revision>
<id>216271405</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-31T22:13:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Brian Horwitz</b> (born <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/15935.xml">
June 16</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/34755.xml">
1983</link>, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/2105954.xml">
Harbor City, California</link>) is a ice hockey player who competes for Cal State Long Beach.
<sec>
<st>
Hockey career</st>
<p>

Brian Horwitz competed for Cal State Long Beach from 2005-2008. In his three year career there he was the leading scorer three years in a row and currently the all-time leading scorer for Long Beach State. Finishing the three years with 107 goals, 123 assists, for a total of 230 points in 90 games played. He also had 236 penalty minutes receiving 150 of those minutes in his first season with the team. Horwitz also owns the single season record for points at Long Beach State accumulating 46 goals and 54 assists for 100 points in 31 games in the 2006-2007 season. This season Horwitz finished 2nd in the league (out of 150+ teams representing approximately 4000 players) with 100 points only 4 points shy of Kent Arsenault who plays at Utah State University and finished with 104 points that season after playing in 39 games. Horwitz also helped lead the team to three regional tournaments and the team's highest ranking at third in the Western Region in the 2007-2008 season. Horwitz received 1st Team All Region honors in the 2006-2007 season and 2nd Team All Region honors in the 2007-2008 season. It is still to be determined whether Horwitz will return to Long Beach State for his final year of eligibility.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Awards</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2007 - First Team West All-Region (ACHA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2007 - Second in National Scoring (ACHA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2008 - Second Team West All-Region (ACHA)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.achahockey.org/player_profile.php?player_id=52900&amp;team_id=13162">
ACHA Stats</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.CollegeHockey.info/profile.php?id=10282">
College Hockey Info</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
