<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:22:14[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Software development effort estimation</title>
<id>17765521</id>
<revision>
<id>229605908</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-03T16:37:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>タチコマ robot</username>
<id>421426</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> Software project management</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/248932.xml">
Software development</link> effort <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/172504.xml">
estimation</link> is the process of predicting the most realistic use of effort required to develop or maintain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> based on incomplete, uncertain and/or noisy input. Effort estimates may be used as input to project plans, iteration plans, budgets, investment analyses, pricing processes and bidding rounds.
<sec>
<st>
 State-of-practice </st>

<p>

Published surveys on estimation practice suggest that expert estimation is the dominant strategy when estimating software development effort<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>
<p>

Typically, effort estimates are over-optimistic and there is a strong over-confidence in their accuracy. The mean effort overrun seems to be about 30% and not decreasing over time. For a review of effort estimation error surveys, see <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. However, the measurement of estimation error is not unproblematic, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Assessing+and+interpreting+the_accuracy+of+effort+estimates%22])">
Assessing and interpreting the_accuracy of effort estimates</link>.
The strong over-confidence in the accuracy of the effort estimates is illustrated by the finding that, on average, if a software professional is 90% confident or “almost sure” to include the actual effort in a minimum-maximum interval, the observed frequency of including the actual effort is only 60-70% <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. </p>
<p>

Currently the term “effort estimate” is used to denote as different concepts as most likely use of effort (modal value), the effort that corresponds to a probability of 50% of not exceeding (median), the planned effort, the budgeted effort or the effort used to propose a bid or price to the client. This is believed to be unfortunate, because communication problems may occur and because the concepts serve different goals 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

Software researchers and practitioners have been addressing the problems of effort estimation for software development projects since at least the 1960s; see, e.g., work by Farr <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> and Nelson <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>.</p>
<p>

Most of the research has focused on the construction of formal software effort estimation models. The early models were typically based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/826997.xml">
regression analysis</link> or mathematically derived from theories from other domains. Since then a high number of model building approaches have been evaluated, such as approaches founded on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/170333.xml">
case-based reasoning</link>, classification and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/232602.xml">
regression trees</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/43444.xml">
simulation</link>, <link>
neural networks</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/49571.xml">
Bayesian statistics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/81251.xml">
lexical analysis</link> of requirement specifications, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/12424.xml">
genetic programming</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/43730.xml">
linear programming</link>, economic production models, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/201158.xml">
soft computing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/49180.xml">
fuzzy logic</link> modeling, statistical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/4211.xml">
bootstrapping</link>, and combinations of one or more of these models. The perhaps most common estimation products today, e.g., the formal estimation models <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/359072.xml">
COCOMO</link> and SLIM have their basis in estimation research conducted in the 1970s and 1980s. The estimation approaches based on functionality-based size measures, e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/4318654.xml">
function points</link>, is also based on research conducted in the 1970s and 1980s, but are re-appearing with modified size measures under different labels, such as “use case points” <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> in the 1990s and 2000s.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Estimation approaches </st>

<p>

There are many ways of categorizing estimation approaches, see for example <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>. The top level categories are the following:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Expert estimation: The quantification step, i.e., the step where the estimate is produced, is based on judgmental processes.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Formal estimation model: The quantification step is based on mechanical processes, e.g., the use of a formula derived from historical data.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Combination-based estimation: The quantification step is based on a judgmental or mechanical combination of estimates from different sources.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Below are examples of estimation approaches within each category.</p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<row>
<header>
Estimation approach</header>
<header>
Category</header>
<header>
Examples of support of implementation of estimation approach</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/103533.xml">
Analogy</link>-based estimation</col>
<col>
Formal estimation model</col>
<col>
ANGEL</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link>
WBS-based</link>(bottom up) estimation</col>
<col>
Expert estimation</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/3231465.xml">
MS Project</link>, company specific activity templates</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Parametric models</col>
<col>
Formal estimation model</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/359072.xml">
COCOMO</link>, SLIM</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Size-based -based estimation models</col>
<col>
Formal estimation model</col>
<col>
 <link>
Function Point</link> Analysis, <link>
Use Case</link> Analysis, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../454/14565454.xml">
Story points</link>-based estimation in <belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<doctrine wordnetid="105943300" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/639009.xml">
Agile software development</link></doctrine>
</belief>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Group estimation</col>
<col>
Expert estimation</col>
<col>
 <belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<doctrine wordnetid="105943300" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/11977622.xml">
Planning poker</link></doctrine>
</belief>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/2764873.xml">
Wideband Delphi</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Mechanical combination</col>
<col>
Combination-based estimation</col>
<col>
 Average of an analogy-based and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/33598.xml">
Work breakdown structure</link>-based effort estimate</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Judgmental combination</col>
<col>
Combination-based estimation</col>
<col>
Expert judgment based on estimates from a parametric model and group estimation</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Selection of estimation approach </st>

<p>

The evidence on differences in estimation accuracy of different estimation approaches and models suggest that there is no “best approach” and that the relative accuracy of one approach or model in comparison to another depends strongly on the context 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>. This implies that different organizations benefit from different estimation approaches. Findings, summarized in <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>, that may support the selection of estimation approach based on the expected accuracy of an approach include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Expert estimation is on average at least as accurate as model-based effort estimation. In particular, situations with unstable relationships and information of high importance not included in the model may suggest use of expert estimation. This assumes, of course, that experts with relevant experience are available. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Formal estimation models not tailored to a particular organization’s own context, may be very inaccurate. Use of own historical data is consequently crucial if one cannot be sure that the estimation model’s core relationships (e.g., formula parameters) are based on similar project contexts.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Formal estimation models may be particularly useful in situations where the model is tailored to the organization’s context (either through use of own historical data or that the model is derived from similar projects and contexts), and/or it is likely that the experts’ estimates will be subject to a strong degree of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/386062.xml">
wishful thinking</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The most robust finding, in many forecasting domains, is that combination of estimates from independent sources, preferable applying different approaches, will on average improve the estimation accuracy <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>.</p>
<p>

In addition, other factors such as ease of understanding and communicating the results of an approach, ease of use of an approach, cost of introduction of an approach should be considered in a selection process.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Uncertainty assessment approaches </st>

<p>

The uncertainty of an effort estimate can be described through a prediction interval (PI). An effort PI is based on a stated certainty level and contains a minimum and a maximum effort value. For example, a project leader may estimate that the most likely effort of a project is 1000 work-hours and that it is 90% certain that the actual effort will be between 500 and 2000 work-hours. Then, the interval [500, 2000] work-hours is the 90% PI of the effort estimate of 1000 work-hours. Frequently, other terms are used instead of PI, e.g., prediction bounds, prediction limits, interval prediction, prediction region and, unfortunately, confidence interval. An important difference between confidence interval and PI is that PI refers to the uncertainty of an estimate, while confidence interval usually refers to the uncertainty associated with the parameters of an estimation model or distribution, e.g., the uncertainty of the mean value of a distribution of effort values. The confidence level of a PI refers to the expected (or subjective) probability that the real value is within the predicted interval<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>.</p>
<p>

There are several possible approaches to calculate effort PIs, e.g., formal approaches based on regression or bootstrapping <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>, formal or judgmental approaches based on the distribution of previous estimation error
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>, and pure expert judgment of minimum-maximum effort for a given level of confidence. Expert judgments based on the distribution of previous estimation error has been found to systematically lead to more realistic uncertainty assessment than the traditional minimum-maximum effort intervals in several studies, see for example <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Assessing and interpreting the accuracy of effort estimates </st>

<p>

The most common measures of the average estimation accuracy is the MMRE (Mean Magnitude of Relative Error), where MRE is defined as: </p>
<p>

<it>MRE</it> = |actual effort − estimated effort| / |actual effort|</p>
<p>

This measure has been criticized <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> and there are several alternative measures, such as more symmetric measures <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref>
, Weighted Mean of Quartiles of relative errors (WMQ) 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> and Mean Variation from Estimate (MVFE) <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref>.</p>
<p>

A high estimation error cannot automatically be interpreted as an indicator of low estimation ability. Alternative, competing or complementing, reasons include low cost control of project, high complexity of development work, and more delivered functionality than originally estimated. A framework for improved use and interpretation of estimation error measurement is included in <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Psychological issues related to effort estimation </st>

<p>

There are many psychological factors potentially explaining the strong tendency towards over-optimistic effort estimates that need to be dealt with to increase accuracy of effort estimates. These factors are essential even when using formal estimation models, because much of the input to these models is judgment-based. Factors that have been demonstrated to be important are: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/386062.xml">
Wishful thinking</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/751106.xml">
anchoring</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/903029.xml">
planning fallacy</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/169305.xml">
cognitive dissonance</link>. A discussion on these and other factors can be found in work by Jørgensen and Grimstad <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/1565926.xml">
Parametric estimating</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/2175809.xml">
Estimation in software engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/2764873.xml">
Wideband Delphi</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/24042.xml">
Project management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<doctrine wordnetid="105943300" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/11977622.xml">
Planning poker</link></doctrine>
</belief>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/6832338.xml">
Cost overrun</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/359072.xml">
COCOMO</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/3653714.xml">
SEER-SEM</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/4318654.xml">
Function points</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
PROBE</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/206886.xml">
PERT</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Special Interest Group on Software Effort Estimation: http://www.forecastingprinciples.com/Software_Estimation/index.html</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General forecasting principles: http://www.forecastingprinciples.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Estimation resources: http://www.itprojectestimation.com/estrefs.htm</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Downloadable research papers on effort estimation: http://simula.no/research/engineering/projects/best</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mike Cohn's Estimating With Use Case Points from article from Methods &amp; Tools: http://www.methodsandtools.com/archive/archive.php?id=25</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Resources on Software Estimation from Steve McConnell: http://www.construx.com/Page.aspx?nid=297</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Jørgensen, M..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simula.no/research/engineering/publications/SE.4.Joergensen.2004.c">
A Review of Studies on Expert Estimation of Software Development Effort</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="2">
Molokken, K.	Jorgensen, M..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=1237981">
A review of software surveys on software effort estimation</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="3">
Jørgensen, M.	Teigen, K.H.	Ribu, K..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6V0N-49N06GS-5&amp;_user=674998&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000036598&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=674998&amp;md5=36c6383445cf481447d06cb30c1ccb63">
Better sure than safe? Over-confidence in judgement based software development effort prediction intervals</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="4">
Edwards, J.S. Moores, T.T.	(1994), "A conflict between the use of estimating and planning tools in the management of information systems.". European Journal of Information Systems 3(2): 139-147.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Goodwin, P. (1998). Enhancing judgmental sales forecasting: The role of laboratory research. Forecasting with judgment. G. Wright and P. Goodwin. New York, John Wiley &amp; Sons: 91-112.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Farr, L.	Nanus, B..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stinet.dtic.mil/oai/oai?verb=getRecord&amp;metadataPrefix=html&amp;identifier=AD0603707">
Factors that affect the cost of computer programming</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="7">
Nelson, E. A. (1966). Management Handbook for the Estimation of Computer Programming Costs. AD-A648750, Systems Development Corp.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Anda, B.	Angelvik, E.	Ribu, K..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springerlink.com/content/7lpyel912m5cr654/">
Improving Estimation Practices by Applying Use Case Models</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="9">
Briand, L. C. and I. Wieczorek (2002). Resource estimation in software engineering. Encyclopedia of software engineering. J. J. Marcinak. New York, John Wiley &amp; Sons: 1160-1196.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Jørgensen, M.	Shepperd, M..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simula.no/research/engineering/publications/Jorgensen.2007.1">
A Systematic Review of Software Development Cost Estimation Studies</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="11">
Shepperd, M.	Kadoda, G..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/Xplore/login.jsp?url=/iel5/32/20846/00965341.pdf?arnumber=965341">
Comparing software prediction techniques using simulation</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="12">
Jørgensen, M..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simula.no/research/engineering/publications/Jorgensen.2007.2">
Estimation of Software Development Work Effort:Evidence on Expert Judgment and Formal Models</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="13">
Winkler, R.L..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6V92-45P4G7H-2B/2/d05dc6c369ab173c5792a05ea1be21d9">
Combining forecasts: A philosophical basis and some current issues Manager</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="14">
Blattberg, R.C.	Hoch, S.J..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/pss/2632364">
Database Models and Managerial Intuition: 50% Model + 50% Manager</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="15">
Jørgensen, M..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simula.no/research/engineering/publications/Jorgensen.2007.2">
Estimation of Software Development Work Effort:Evidence on Expert Judgment and Formal Models</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="17">
Angelis, L.	Stamelos, I..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=594467&amp;dl=ACM&amp;coll=portal">
A simulation tool for efficient analogy based cost estimation</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="16">
Armstrong, J. S..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.forecastingprinciples.com">
Principles of forecasting: A handbook for researchers and practitioners</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="19">
Jørgensen, M..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simula.no/research/engineering/publications/SE.4.Joergensen.2004.e">
Realism in assessment of effort estimation uncertainty: It matters how you ask</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="18">
Jørgensen, M.	Sjøberg, D.I.K..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6V0B-47HC6S5-1&amp;_user=674998&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000036598&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=674998&amp;md5=6cb917a379855c79eebe9f18ca9ac424">
An effort prediction interval approach based on the empirical distribution of previous estimation accuracy</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="21">
Kitchenham, B.	Pickard, L.M.	MacDonell, S.G.	Shepperd,.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;id=IPSEFU000148000003000081000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;gifs=yes">
What accuracy statistics really measure</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="20">
Shepperd, M.	Cartwright, M.	Kadoda, G..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/klu/emse/2000/00000005/00000003/00278191">
On Building Prediction Systems for Software Engineers</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="23">
Miyazaki, Y.	Terakado, M.	Ozaki, K.	Nozaki, H..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=198684">
Robust regression for developing software estimation models</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="22">
Foss, T.	Stensrud, E.	Kitchenham, B.      Myrtveit, I..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=951936">
A Simulation Study of the Model Evaluation Criterion MMRE</weblink>".&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/56938.xml">
IEEE</link>.
</entry>
<entry id="25">
Hughes, R.T.	Cunliffe, A.	Young-Martos, F..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=689296">
Evaluating software development effort model-building techniquesfor application in a real-time telecommunications environment</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="24">
Lo, B.	Gao, X..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dl.acs.org.au/index.php/ajis/article/view/348">
Assessing Software Cost Estimation Models: criteria for accuracy, consistency and regression</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="27">
Jørgensen, M.	Grimstad, S..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simula.no/research/engineering/publications/Simula.SE.112">
How to Avoid Impact from Irrelevant and Misleading Information When Estimating Software Development Effort</weblink>".
</entry>
<entry id="26">
Grimstad, S.	Jørgensen, M..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simula.no/research/engineering/publications/Grimstad.2006.2/simula_pdf_file">
A Framework for the Analysis of Software Cost Estimation Accuracy</weblink>".</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
