<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:11:05[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Oracle Business Intelligence Suite Enterprise Edition</title>
<id>17764590</id>
<revision>
<id>237818795</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-11T23:17:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CmdrObot</username>
<id>1079367</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All pages needing cleanup</category>
<category>Wikify from June 2008</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>Oracle software</category>
<category>Cleanup from June 2008</category>
<category>All articles lacking sources</category>
<category>Articles lacking sources from May 2008</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from May 2008</category>
<category>Wikify from May 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <p>

This article or section has multiple issues. Please help <b><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Oracle_Business_Intelligence_Suite_Enterprise_Edition&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink></b> or discuss these issues on the .
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It does not <b>cite any </b>. Please help improve it by citing . Tagged since May 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It reads like an  and needs to be rewritten from a . Tagged since May 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It may need to be <b>
Articles that need to be wikified|wikified</b> to meet Wikipedia's . Tagged since June 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Its introduction may need to be <b>rewritten</b> to comply with Wikipedia's .  Tagged since May 2008.</entry>
</list>

</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article needs more   to meet Wikipedia's . </b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Oracle_Business_Intelligence_Suite_Enterprise_Edition&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink>by adding useful internal links. (June 2008)</col>
</row>
</table>


Oracle Business Intelligence Enterprise Edition Plus, also known as OBI EE Plus, is Oracle's set of business intelligence tools consisting of former Siebel business intelligence and Hyperion business intelligence offerings.  The former Siebel products were initially marketed by Oracle as Oracle Business Intelligence Enterprise Edition while the "Plus" was added along with the Hyperion tools in 2007.</p>

<p>

Today, the products can leverage a common BI Server providing a level of integration among the tools.  Integration provided includes:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a common service-oriented architecture</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 common data access services</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a common analytic and calculation infrastructure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 common metadata management services</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a common semantic business model</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a common security model and user preferences </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 common administration tools</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
 OBIEE Plus consists of several interdependent components    </st>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle BI Server </entry>
</list>

is an analysis server providing a calculation and aggregation engine that integrates data from multiple relational, unstructured, OLAP,  and other sources. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle BI Answers</entry>
</list>

is an ad-hoc query and analysis tool that processes 
the data from multiple data sources in a pure Web environment.
Users are isolated from data structure complexity and they view 
and work with a logical view of the information.
Users can create charts, pivot tables, reports, and 
dashboards. All of them are fully interactive. Analysis can be
saved, shared, modified, formatted, or integrated in the user's
personalized BI Dashboards.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle BI Interactive Dashboards</entry>
</list>

are interactive Web architecture dashboards that display a required information to help users' decision making.
Access to the information is interactive and based on the 
individual's role and identity. The end user works with live 
reports, charts, tables, prompts, pivot tables, and graphics and
the user also has full capability for modifying and interacting
with these results. Dashboard can aggregate content from other
sources./e.g., the Internet, shared file servers, and document
repositories/ The content of the Dashboard pages can be saved
into Briefing Book.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle BI Delivers     </entry>
</list>

is an alerting tool that provides monitoring and alerting of 
business activity. They are reached via multiple channels such as
email, dashboards, and mobile devices. It includes Web-based 
self-service portal where users can create and subscript alerts. 
Dashboard can initiate and pass contextual information to other
alerts to execute multistep, multiperson, and multiapplication
analytical workflow. It can dynamically determine
recipients and personalize content to reach right users at the 
right time and also with a right information.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle BI Disconnected Analytics      </entry>
</list>

is a solution that offers BI Answers and Dashboards to mobile     
professionals on computers disconnected from the network.
It provides the same intuitive interface for users whether they
are working  in a connected or disconnected mode.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle BI Publisher</entry>
</list>

is a reporting engine capable of generating reports from multiple 
data sources in multiple formats via multiple channels.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle BI Briefing Books</entry>
</list>

reports captured series of snapshots of Oracle BI  Dashboards.        </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle BI Office Plug-In </entry>
</list>

automatically synchronizes information from BI Answers to 
Microsoft Word, Excel, and PowerPoint.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle Hyperion Financial Reporting</entry>
</list>

creates book quality financial reports in a variety of formats (including XBRL) and supports a variety of sources including Oracle's Hyperion performance management applications (EPM)and Oracle Essbase.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hyperion Interactive Reporting</entry>
</list>

pulls data together from operational or analytic sources to create charts, privots, and reports and can access the Oracle BI Server semantic layer.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hyperion SQR Production Reporting</entry>
</list>

provides cross functional reporting from a variety of relational databases and data sources.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hyperion Web Analysis</entry>
</list>

delivers out-of-the-box presentation and reporting for Oracle Essbase and other multi-dimensional sources.</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
