<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:23:23[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108058098">
<header>
<title>Proofpoint, Inc.</title>
<id>17815480</id>
<revision>
<id>243996945</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T21:38:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rbrisco</username>
<id>3579222</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Security software</category>
<category>Companies based in Silicon Valley</category>
<category>Anti-spam</category>
<category>Companies established in 2002</category>
<category>Antivirus software</category>
<category>Spam filtering</category>
<category>Networking companies of the United States</category>
<category>Email filtering</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Company</name>
<parameters>
<type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/1499655.xml">
Private</link></type>
<name>
Proofpoint, Inc.</name>
<foundation>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/35502.xml">
2002</link></foundation>
<industry>
Security software</industry>
<products>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/1336001.xml">
 E-mail filtering</link>  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/313737.xml">
 Anti-spam</link></products>
<logo>
<image width="141px" src="Proofpoint_Inc._Logo.gif">
</image>
</logo>
<location_country>
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
</location_country>
<location_city>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/108167.xml">
Sunnyvale, California</link></village>
</location_city>

<key_people>
Chairman: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/8047694.xml">
Eric Hahn</link>CEO: Gary SteeleCTO: Marcel DePaolis</key_people>
</parameters>
</template>


<sec>
<st>
 History </st>



<p>

<b>Proofpoint, Inc.</b> is an email security and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/9105356.xml">
data loss prevention</link> solution vendor based in Sunnyvale, California. The company was founded in June 2002 by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/8047694.xml">
Eric Hahn</link>, formerly the CTO of . It officially launched July 21, 2003, after raising a $7 million series A funding round, releasing its first product, and lining up six customers as references, and was backed by venture investors Mohr, Davidow Ventures, <link>
 Benchmark Capital</link>), and <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/26977.xml">
Stanford University</link></university>
 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.  An additional $9 million in Series B funding led by New York-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/18724675.xml">
RRE Ventures</link> was announced in October, 2003 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<p>

The company’s first product was the Proofpoint Protection Server for medium and large businesses.  It incorporated what was described as “MLX Technology”, proprietary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link> algorithms applied to the problem of accurately identifying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/459847.xml">
spam email</link> using 10,000 different attributes to differentiate between spam and valid email. The company joined dozens of other anti-spam software providers<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> in a business opportunity fueled by an exponential increase in <link>
spam volume</link> that was threatening worker productivity, making spam a top business priority <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>.  According to Information Week’s 2004 National Technology Readiness Survey, the cost of spam in terms of lost productivity had reached $21.58 billion annually<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.</p>
<p>

The first Proofpoint Protection Server product upgrade was announced in November 2003 and expanded the number of spam detection attributes to more than 50,000.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

In December 2003, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/581114.xml">
Forrester Research</link></company>
 announced the winners of the sixth annual Emerging Technology Showcase awards. Proofpoint was awarded for “Identifying And Dealing With Threats And Nuisances To The Enterprise”.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

In 2004, strict new regulations governing financial disclosures and the privacy of health care data prompted Proofpoint to begin developing new products that would automatically identify and intercept outbound email containing sensitive information.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

In March, 2004, Proofpoint introduced its first hardware appliance, the P-Series Message Protection Appliance (later renamed Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway), using a hardened Linux kernel and Proofpoint's Protection Server 2.0 software.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> It was tested by Infoworld and found to stop 94% of spam.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

Another product introduction in November, 2004 included Protection Server 3.0, with Email Firewall and MLX-based Dynamic Reputation Analysis, and the Content Security Suite, plug-in modules designed for scanning outbound messages and their attachments to assist in compliance with data protection regulations such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/67031.xml">
Sarbanes-Oxley</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/384064.xml">
HIPAA</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/164103.xml">
Gramm-Leach-Bliley</link>.  In combination, this was known as the Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway Appliance. It was reviewed by ChannelWeb<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.crn.com/it-channel/54200259">
http://www.crn.com/it-channel/54200259</weblink>, which observed that it used a “combination of technologies: policy-based management, a spam-filtering engine and adaptive learning technology”.  Implemented by <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/4157.xml">
Brown University</link></university>
, in the first 24 hours the Proofpoint system saved 447 Mb of email storage space by blocking 90,000 spam messages.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>  Infoworld reported that a number of companies were broadening their products to address other messaging issues besides spam, such as compliance violations, phishing scams, and viruses.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>
<p>

The <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/384695.xml">
University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</link></university>
 incorporated Proofpoint software into their CITES Spam Control system with positive results.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> Government Computer News reported that their GCN Lab found the Proofpoint P800 Gateway offered “Maximum control for administrators; highly configurable; optional module prevents e-mailing of classified documents”.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>
<p>

Proofpoint introduced a new product, the Network Content Sentry, as an add-on appliance to the Content Security Suite in August, 2005.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> Designed to monitor online messaging other than email, the appliance monitors Web mail, message boards, blogs and FTP-based communications.  Proofpoint also introduced policy-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
email encryption</link> features, using identity-based encryption technology licensed from Voltage Security. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

At about the same time, the Zero-Hour Anti-Virus software module was released. It was specifically designed to detect and block new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/18994196.xml">
computer viruses</link> before their “signature” is formally identified.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>
<p>

As part of a continuing product expansion related to regulation monitoring, in November, 2005, the Healthcare Privacy Bundle was released as add-on to Messaging Security Gateway appliance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>
<p>

Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway V4.0 was released in March, 2005, with additional capabilities such as directory harvest attack prevention features and enhancements to the Proofpoint MLX Dynamic Reputation software.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

In a step towards simpler operational requirements, the Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway Virtual Edition was released in April, 2007. The product runs as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/32353.xml">
virtual appliance</link> on a host running VMware's virtual server software.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref>  Moving a dedicated hardware appliance to a virtual server eliminates problems associated with proprietary hardware and reduces upgrade costs, <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> though it does require knowledge of VMware's <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/312018.xml">
virtual server architecture</link></company>
.</p>
<p>

Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway V5.0 was released in June, 2007, and was based on a new, integrated architecture, combining all its capabilities into a single platform.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> It could be run either as a dedicated appliance, virtual appliance, or software suite. </p>
<p>

ICSA Labs, an independent division of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/59695.xml">
Verizon Business</link>, announced in April, 2007, that it had certified six anti-spam products under their new testing program, one of which was the Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway. The goal of ICSA Labs' anti-spam product testing and certification is to evaluate product effectiveness in detecting and removing spam. The guidelines also address how well the products recognize e-mail messages from legitimate sources.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref></p>
<p>

Moving into the <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/2262333.xml">
software-as-a-service</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 business, Proofpoint introduced Proofpoint on Demand, a hosted version of its email security and data loss prevention offerings.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> In May, 2008, the company’s hosted offerings were expanded with the introduction of Proofpoint on Demand—Standard Edition.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref> The product is targeted at small-to-medium size businesses that need email security but do not run their own servers or have on-site IT personnel.</p>
<p>

In June 2008, Proofpoint acquired Fortiva, Inc., a provider of on-demand email archiving software for legal discovery, regulatory compliance and email storage management.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Overall Timeline</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jun 2002	Proofpoint, Inc. founded by Eric Hahn</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jul 2003	Raises $7 million series A funding round</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Oct 2003	$9 million in Series B funding led by New York-based RRE Ventures</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Oct 2003	Stuart Ellman, RRE Ventures general partner, joins Proofpoint's Board of Directors</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mar 2005	Strategic partnerships with four email encryption vendors</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mar 2006	Additional $20 million raised in venture capital</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 2006	Sydney, Australia, office opens</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Feb 2008	Additional $28 million raised from DAG Ventures</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jun 2008       Proofpoint, Inc. Acquires SaaS Email Archiving Vendor Fortiva, Inc.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sep 2008       Gartner positions Proofpoint in the Leaders quadrant in the 2008 Magic Quadrant for Email Security Boundaries <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Technology Timeline (product releases) </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jul 2003	Launches first product, Proofpoint Protection Server software</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nov 2003	Product upgrade incorporates MLX Learning Technology</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mar 2004	Introduces first appliance, P-Series Message Protection Appliance</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nov 2004	Protection Server 3.0 with Email Firewall and MLX-based Dynamic Reputation Analysis</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nov 2004	Content Security Suite, plug-in modules for digital asset security and regulation monitoring</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mar 2005	Proofpoint provides hosted anti-spam services</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Aug 2005	Network Content Sentry introduced as add-on appliance to Content Security Suite along with Secure Messaging (email encryption) software module</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sep 2005	Zero-Hour Anti-Virus software module released</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nov 2005	Healthcare Privacy Bundle released as add-on to Messaging Security Gateway appliance</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mar 2006	Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway V4.0 released</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Apr 2007	Messaging Security Gateway Virtual Edition is released</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jun 2007	Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway V5.0 released</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Aug 2007	Proofpoint On Demand is released</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 2008	Proofpoint On Demand—Standard Edition is released, Proofpoint Secure File Transfer software module released</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jun 2008       Proofpoint On Demand Email Archiving is released</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Description of Products and Services</st>
<p>

Proofpoint’s product line is available in four different deployment form factors:</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway</b> messaging security appliance, available in a variety of models for both large enterprises and SMBs</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Messaging Security Gateway Virtual Edition</b> messaging security virtual appliance for VMware Infrastructure.</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Protection Server</b> software for Linux</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint on Demand</b> hosted email security and data loss prevention service </p>
<p>

Add-on modules that address various email security or data loss prevention issues include:</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Spam Detection</b> for defense against spam, adult content and phishing attacks. For connection management, Proofpoint Dynamic Reputation and netMLX technology are also offered.</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Virus Protection</b>™ defends against email-borne viruses, worms, trojans
and other forms of malicious code.</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Zero-Hour Anti-Virus</b> protects against emerging viruses before anti-virus signatures are available</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Content Compliance</b> for defining and enforcing acceptable use policies for message content and attachments</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Digital Asset Security</b> for protecting sensitive digital assets and
confidential information from leaking outside the organization via email.</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Regulatory Compliance</b> for detecting protected health information, protected financial information and other sensitive content in outbound messages</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Secure Messaging</b> for policy-based encryption functionality.</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Network Content Sentry</b> extends Proofpoint’s content security and policy enforcement features to web-based email, blog and message board postings, FTP and other message streams.</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Smart Search</b> is a separate appliance that adds message tracing, forensics and log analytics features</p>
<p>

<b>Proofpoint Secure File Transfer</b> adds secure, large file transfer capabilities.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sanjose.bizjournals.com/sanjose/stories/2003/07/21/story4.html?t=printable">
sanjose.bizjournals.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sanjose.bizjournals.com/sanjose/stories/2003/10/13/daily16.html">
sanjose.bizjournals.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sanjose.bizjournals.com/sanjose/stories/2003/07/21/story4.html?t=printable">
sanjose.bizjournals.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/software/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=17100348">
www.informationweek.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/security/vulnerabilities/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=59300834">
www.informationweek.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2003/1103proofpoint.html">
www.networkworld.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.forrester.com/ER/Press/Release/0,1769,870,00.html">
http://www.forrester.com/ER/Press/Release/0,1769,870,00.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.technologyreview.com/Infotech/13498/">
http://www.technologyreview.com/Infotech/13498/</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2004/0315proofpoint.html">
http://www.networkworld.com/news/2004/0315proofpoint.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.infoworld.com/article/04/05/28/22TCspam_1.html">
http://www.infoworld.com/article/04/05/28/22TCspam_1.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://media.www.browndailyherald.com/media/storage/paper472/news/2005/02/15/CampusNews/New-System.Blocks.90000.Spam.EMails.In.First.24.Hours-864349.shtml">
http://media.www.browndailyherald.com/media/storage/paper472/news/2005/02/15/CampusNews/New-System.Blocks.90000.Spam.EMails.In.First.24.Hours-864349.shtml</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.infoworld.com/article/04/11/08/45NNmes_1.html">
http://www.infoworld.com/article/04/11/08/45NNmes_1.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.news.uiuc.edu/ii/05/0317/cites.html">
http://www.news.uiuc.edu/ii/05/0317/cites.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gcn.com/print/24_7/35399-1.html?topic=prod_reviews">
http://www.gcn.com/print/24_7/35399-1.html?topic=prod_reviews</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Security/Proofpoint-Voltage-Team-on-EMail-Encryption/">
http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Security/Proofpoint-Voltage-Team-on-EMail-Encryption/</weblink></entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2005/091905-proofpoint.html">
http://www.networkworld.com/news/2005/091905-proofpoint.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Security/Proofpoint-Voltage-Team-on-EMail-Encryption/">
http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Security/Proofpoint-Voltage-Team-on-EMail-Encryption/</weblink></entry>
<entry id="19">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=181500346">
http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=181500346</weblink></entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=174401218">
http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=174401218</weblink></entry>
<entry id="21">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/042607-appliance-overload.html">
http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/042607-appliance-overload.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.crn.com/security/199100674">
http://www.crn.com/security/199100674</weblink></entry>
<entry id="23">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/icsa-labs-introduces-formal-testing-of-anti-spam-products,345941.shtml">
http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/icsa-labs-introduces-formal-testing-of-anti-spam-products,345941.shtml</weblink></entry>
<entry id="22">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.byteandswitch.com/document.asp?doc_id=125517">
http://www.byteandswitch.com/document.asp?doc_id=125517</weblink></entry>
<entry id="25">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebizq.net/news/9561.html">
http://www.ebizq.net/news/9561.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="24">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/080707-proofpoint-managed-security-service.html">
http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/080707-proofpoint-managed-security-service.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="27">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/proofpoint-positioned-in-leaders-quadrant-in-2008-email-security-magic-quadrant,539673.shtml">
http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/proofpoint-positioned-in-leaders-quadrant-in-2008-email-security-magic-quadrant,539673.shtml</weblink></entry>
<entry id="26">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS117849+24-Jun-2008+PRN20080624">
http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS117849+24-Jun-2008+PRN20080624</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sanjose.bizjournals.com/sanjose/stories/2003/07/21/story4.html?t=printable">
San Jose Business Journal, Jul 18, 2003</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sanjose.bizjournals.com/sanjose/stories/2003/10/13/daily16.html">
San Jose Business Journal, Oct 14, 2003</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sanjose.bizjournals.com/sanjose/stories/2003/07/21/story4.html?t=printable">
San Jose Business Journal, Jul 18, 2003</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/software/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=17100348">
InformationWeek Research's Outlook 2004 Survey</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/security/vulnerabilities/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=59300834">
Information Week, Feb 3, 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2003/1103proofpoint.html">
Network World, Nov 3, 2003</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.forrester.com/ER/Press/Release/0,1769,870,00.html">
Forrester Press Release, Dec 12, 2003</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.technologyreview.com/Infotech/13498/">
Technology Review, Mar 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2004/0315proofpoint.html">
Network World, Mar 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.infoworld.com/article/04/05/28/22TCspam_1.html">
InfoWorld, May 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.crn.com/it-channel/54200259">
ChannelWeb, Nov 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://media.www.browndailyherald.com/media/storage/paper472/news/2005/02/15/CampusNews/New-System.Blocks.90000.Spam.EMails.In.First.24.Hours-864349.shtml">
Brown  Daily Herald, Apr 2008</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.infoworld.com/article/04/11/08/45NNmes_1.html">
Infoworld, Nov 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.news.uiuc.edu/ii/05/0317/cites.html">
News Bureau, Mar 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gcn.com/print/24_7/35399-1.html?topic=prod_reviews">
Government Computer News, Apr 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Security/Proofpoint-Voltage-Team-on-EMail-Encryption/">
eWeek, Aug 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Security/Proofpoint-Voltage-Team-on-EMail-Encryption/">
Network World, Aug 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2005/091905-proofpoint.html">
Network World, Sep 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=174401218">
CMP TechWeb Compliance Pipeline, Nov 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=181500346">
Information Week, Mar 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.crn.com/security/199100674">
ChannelWeb, Apr 2007</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/042607-appliance-overload.html">
Network World, Apr 2007</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.byteandswitch.com/document.asp?doc_id=125517">
CMP ByteandSwitch, Jun, 2007</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/icsa-labs-introduces-formal-testing-of-anti-spam-products,345941.shtml">
Earth Times, Apr 2007</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/080707-proofpoint-managed-security-service.html">
NetworkWorld, Aug 2008</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebizq.net/news/9561.html">
ebiz, May 2008</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS117849+24-Jun-2008+PRN20080624">
Reuters, Jun 2008</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS98067+15-Sep-2008+MW20080915">
Reuters, Sep 2008</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.proofpoint.com/">
Proofpoint, Inc. corporate website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fortiva.com/">
Fortiva Inc. corporate website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.proofpoint.com/id/wik_email_security">
Proofpoint Research References - Email Security</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</company>
</article>
