<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:26:51[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<scientist  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110560637">
<header>
<title>Kjell Samuelson</title>
<id>17877548</id>
<revision>
<id>219783025</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-16T21:19:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Epolk</username>
<id>286968</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>1932 births</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Systems scientists</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Kjell Samuelson</b> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/34775.xml">
1932</link>) is a <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/5058739.xml">
Swedish</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</autocracy>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/659757.xml">
systems scientist</link>, Sci-Tech <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/542306.xml">
consultant</link>, Professor Emeritus at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/27157.xml">
Stockholm University</link></university>
 and <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/25609.xml">
Royal Institute of Technology</link></university>
, and a pioneer of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/659757.xml">
Systems Science</link> &amp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/5904.xml">
Cybernetics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/5177.xml">
Communications</link> &amp; Informatics Technology and Global Networks. 
<sec>
<st>
 Biography </st>
<p>

Samuelson holds dual Doctors degrees. Since four decades he has been distinguished professor at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/27157.xml">
Stockholm University</link></university>
 and the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/25609.xml">
Royal Institute of Technology</link></university>
, where he launched the first graduate education and doctoral program in Informatics &amp; Systems Science including Cybernetics and Networks. He is further an professor of Information Science, Computers, Systems Engineering, Safety &amp; Security, and General Resource Management at a dozen North American Universities.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

For several years he is an international Sci-Tech advisor to industries and corporations on large-scale management, organizational redesign, and investments for functional development of new infrastructures. He worked as high-level consultant to UNESCO, OECD, UNITAR, ASEAN, UNIDO etc. on regional development. He is past-president in 1975 of the <link>
Society for General Systems Research</link>, now International Systems Science Society, and has fulfilled chair functions of professional consortia and associations such as SGSR, IFIP, ASIS, IEEE, FISCIT, ITCA, ASC, INSIST.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Work </st>
<p>

Samuelson conducts R &amp; D globally on Total Systems, TeleCom, Satellites, Systems Architecture, Enterprise Planning and Management Structures.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
 General systems </st>
<p>

According to Samuelson in 1977 the field of General Systems had grown over the years since the 1950s into a viable interdisciplinary area of applied trans-science. In the 1970s mankind was "facing severe problems of energy, resources, environment, and population, with symptoms like ignorance explosion, data pollution, and lack of order for information and knowledge". Samuelson at that time saw a continuous development of new General Systems Methodologies, which could master such circumstances that could lead to imminent crisis, making use of current information technology, telecommunications and computers as tools.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> </p>
<p>

In the realm of General Systems Samuelson identified the following major directions: <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General Systems Research (GST)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General Systems Theory (GST)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General Systems Thinking (GSt)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General Living Systems (GLS)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General Systems Approach (GSA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General Systems and Cybernetics (GSC)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General Information Systems (GIS)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 General Systems Networks (GSN) </entry>
</list>

This was, as he said, an open-ended list that might become expended as additional slants are born and new applications of General Systems come into existence by everyday experience.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Systems methodologies </st>
<p>

In <it>Information and data in systems</it> in 1976 Samuelson has compiled a list of 45 logical and chronological steps, which can be distinguished in various methodologies. This list of sometimes overlapping states with the first five steps starting with: Ultimate objectives, goals statement, constraints, Needs and requirements to definition of the project or problem.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 From idea towards specification are another nine steps: Idea and inception, conception of solution, conceptual design with a functional model, feasibility study, General systems proposal and master plan, object system analysis, observation of existing systems, alternative designs outlined, identifying alternative technologies, preliminaries and design evaluation towards specification. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The methodological steps continue with the information systems development, starting with: information systems macrostructuring, information study, detail study, decision analysis, data construction and microstructuring, towards file structuring, component design, simulation and conversion towards an experiment with a pilot system and empirical testing of a pilot evaluation.    </entry>
</list>

After the selection of the systems, implementing, installation, testing and evaluation Samuelson determines ten operational steps with the operations: training, maintenance, organizing production resources, product distribution, disposition of waste, result reporting and follow-up review, towards redesign and cessation.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Publications </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1968. <it>Mechanized information storage, retrieval and dissemination</it>. Proceedings of the F.I.D./I.F.I.P. joint conference, Rome, June 14-17,1967. Edited by Kjell Samuelson.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1969. <it>Automated international information networks</it>. Systems design concepts, goal-setting and priorities. FID/TM Panel at the ASIS meeting in San Francisco, 2 October, 1969.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1972. <it>Systems, cybernetics and information networks</it>. by K. Samuelson ... [et al.]. Compiled by FID/TM, Stockholm, Sweden.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1976. <it>Information and data in systems</it>. With Börje Langefors. New York : Petrocelli/Charter.   </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1976. <it>Information systems and networks : design and planning guidelines of informatics for managers, decision makers and systems analysts.</it> With Harold Borko and G. X. Amey. Amsterdam : North-Holland Pub. Co.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1978. <it>Informatics by general systems and cybernetics : a structured methodology for design, anasynthesis, and usage</it>. Stockholm : The Royal Institute of Technology.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.keylab-imie.org/confenis2007/programs/ks.aspx">
Prof. Kjell Samuelson</weblink>. Keynote Speakers at the Confenis 2007. Retrieved 10 June 2008.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 Kjell Samuelson (1977). "General Systems". In: <it>Encyclopedia of Computer Science and Technology: Volume 8</it>. Edited by Jack Belzer and others. CRC Press 1977.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Lars Skyttner (1996), General Systems Theory: An Introduction. p.422-423.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
