<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:27:30[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Hispano Canadian Intercultural School</title>
<id>17947560</id>
<revision>
<id>227572062</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-24T06:10:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>HCISfan</username>
<id>7227828</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking reliable references from June 2008</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All articles lacking sources</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  that appear in reliable, third-party publications.</b>
s and sources affiliated with the subject of the article are generally not sufficient for a Wikipedia article. Please include more appropriate  from , or discuss the issue on the talk page. <it>(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

The <b>Hispano Canadian Intercultural School (HCIS)</b> is the first English-Spanish <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/1570983.xml">
bilingual</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/11749232.xml">
elementary school</link>  in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/64646.xml">
Toronto</link></village>
, <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
. HCIS programs are designed for both Spanish and non-Spanish speakers.</p>


<sec>
<st>
 Mission and Vision </st>

<p>

HCIS' mission and vision entail a dual perspective because, by being bilingual and cross-cultural, both Canadian and Hispanic educational aspects are equally important.</p>

<p>

<b>HCIS’ mission</b> </p>
<p>

To provide students with the opportunity to read, write and speak in Spanish, and to gain a deeper understanding of the various Hispanic cultures and their history while accomplishing the objectives marked by the Ontario Ministry of Education.</p>

<p>

<b>HCIS’ vision is:</b></p>
<p>

To be the place where children enjoy learning in a multicultural atmosphere, acquire the best English-Spanish bilingual education and reinforce their values.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Philosophy </st>

<p>

HCIS Philosophy of Education is the belief in providing a great educational experience that combines teaching excellence, true involvement and cultural awareness and HCIS believes its  role is to help students to develop a deep love and respect for themselves, others, and the environment. HCIS appreciates diversity and encourages solidarity, honesty, respect and the acceptance of others with no prejudice about race or creed.</p>

<p>

HCIS deems that the best learning occurs through an open sharing of ideas in an environment where students feel free to express themselves.   </p>

<p>

HCIS understands that children need to learn about everything and they want to understand everything, so their primary focus is the comprehensive development of the students, which includes knowing themselves as the first step to increase their self esteem and respect.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Programs </st>

<p>

The programs are designed for both Spanish and non-Spanish speakers. The curriculum focuses on acquiring and constantly improving literacy in both languages, developing mathematics skills and gradually learning about Science, Geography and History.</p>
<p>

<b>Academic</b></p>
<p>

For the core courses in English, curriculum marked by the Ontario Ministry of Education is followed. Because of the bilingual nature of the school, there are daily required courses in Spanish as well.</p>

<p>

<b>After school</b></p>
<p>

For our full time students, the first one hour period is dedicated to recreational activities or clubs. The second period is for independent study. Although students are encouraged to finish their homework, they are still allowed to decide what they want to do and they will be supervised at all times.</p>
<p>

For children not attending HCIS in a daily basis, we also offer the “Spanish afterschool” program for which children take 1 hour class twice a week, and “Supervised Homework and Free time Club”</p>

<p>

<b>Summer in Spanish</b></p>
<p>

For the months of July and August a summer program for children who speak Spanish at home and for those who don’t has been implemented. Immersed in a Spanish speaking atmosphere, children will learn or improve their language skills by participating in non-academic activities.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External Link</st>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hcischool.com">
Hispano Canadian Intercultural School</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Related readings </st>

<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/95274.xml">
Jean Piaget</link></philosopher>
</person>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/864530.xml">
Pestalozzi</link></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/481912.xml">
Kurt Hahn</link></p>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/26710.xml">
Socrates</link></philosopher>
</person>
</p>
<p>

<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link>
Howard_Gardner</link></scientist>
</p>
<p>

<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/89008.xml">
Theory of multiple intelligences</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/1040161.xml">
Constructivism (learning theory)</link></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constructivismo_%28pedagog%C3%ADa%29">
Constructivismo</weblink></p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
