<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:30:35[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Social Science Research Resources Network</title>
<id>18047939</id>
<revision>
<id>223875743</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-06T08:10:16Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Navy Blue</username>
<id>6418591</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Websites</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Social Science Research Resources Network (SSRRN)</b> was found in 2008. It is a website that aims to assist social science researchers to conduct research by providing a platform that easily search all free database and statistical programming codes in the internet.<p>

More and more researchers provide their resources free online in recent years as contributions to the social science research network <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. However, these resources are spread in different websites, which consumes researchers' time in searching these information. SSRRN thus provides a platform that gathers information of all free resources together and hence saves researcher’s time in searching resources<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. SSRRN does not host any data and programming codes, but provides a link to the webpage of the owner of the resources. Researchers can post basic information of their resources, i.e. title, descriptions and links, to SSRRN for indexing.</p>



<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
See Talja S. (2002) "Information sharing in academic communities: Types and levels of collaboration in information seeking and use", <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uta.fi/~lisaka/Taljaisic2002_konv.pdf">
PDF format</weblink>,(providing conceptual framework for the description of types and levels of information sharing in relation to document retrieval in academic communities).</entry>
<entry id="2">
See Eddelbüttel D. (2004) "A Code Archive for Economics and Econometrics", <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springerlink.com/content/k367222434k34706/,">
Link</weblink> (Introduces an Internet repository for computer programs written by, and for, economists and econometricians. The repository is similar to SSRRN, which provides a means to aid communication among researchers by using the Internet to share implementations of algorithms.)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1005923.xml">
Academic databases and search engines</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ssrrn.com">
SSRRN</weblink></p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
