<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:29:55[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Compound term processing</title>
<id>18046649</id>
<revision>
<id>238195319</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-13T18:56:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SpBot</username>
<id>7016748</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Information retrieval</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Compound term processing</b> is the name that is used for a category of techniques in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
Information retrieval</link> applications that performs matching on the basis of compound terms. Compound terms are built by combining two (or more) simple terms, for example "triple" is a single word term but "triple heart bypass" is a compound term. For the purpose of information retrieval, it is important to decide which terms to use for searching. In other words, the tasks are to decide (i) if the whole compound term should be considered as an index and, (ii) which of its components are the more relevant for information retrieval. <p>

In August 2003 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/17770654.xml">
Concept Searching Limited</link></company>
 introduced the idea of using statistical Compound Term Processing via an article published in INFORMATION MANAGEMENT AND TECHNOLOGY (VOL 36 PART 4). A British Library Direct catalogue entry can be found here: <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. </p>
<p>

The complete original article can also be downloaded from here: <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. </p>
<p>

Further discussion of Compound Term Processing can be found here: <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. CLAMOUR is a European collaborative project which aims to find a better way to classify when collecting and disseminating industrial information &amp; statistics. In contrast to the techniques discussed by Concept Searching Limited, CLAMOUR appears to be primarily a linguistic approach, rather than one based on statistical modelling. The final project report (dated March 2002) can be found here: <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

Compound Term Processing is important because it allows search (and other Information Retrieval) applications to perform their matching on the basis of multi-word concepts rather than single words in isolation which can be highly ambiguous.</p>
<p>

Most search engines simply look for documents that contain the words that the user enters into the search box (aka "keyword search" engines). <link>
Boolean search</link> engines add a degree of sophistication by allowing the user to specify additional requirements but most users struggle to comprehend and use the necessary syntax (e.g. Tiger NEAR Woods AND (golf OR golfing) NOT Volkswagen). <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/4840390.xml">
Phrase search</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 is easier to understand but can lead to many useful documents being missed if they do not contain the exact phrase specified.</p>
<p>

Techniques for probabilistic weighting of single word terms dates back to at least 1976 and the landmark publication by Stephen E. Robertson <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> and <link>
Karen Spärck Jones</link>: Relevance weighting of search terms originally published in the Journal of the American Society for Information Science. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  Robertson has stated that the assumption of word independence is not justified and exists simply as a matter of mathematical convenience. The objection to assumptions about term independence are not new, dating back to at least 1964 when H. H. Williams expressed it this way: "The assumption of independence of words in a document is usually made as a matter of mathematical convenience". <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/18046649.xml">
Compound term processing</link> is a new approach to an old problem: how to improve the relevance of search results without missing anything important whilst maintaining ease of use. By forming compound (i.e. multi-word) terms and placing these in the search engine's index the search can be performed with a higher degree of accuracy because the ambiguity inherent in single words is no longer a problem. A search for <it>survival rates following a triple heart bypass in elderly people</it> will locate documents about this topic even if this precise phrase is not contained in any document. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/17770654.xml">
concept search</link> using "Compound Term Processing" can extract the key concepts automatically (in this case "survival rates", "triple heart bypass" and "elderly people") and use these to select the most relevant documents.</p>
<p>

In 2004 Anna Lynn Patterson filed a number of patents on the subject of "Phrase based indexing and retrieval" and to which Google subsequently acquired the rights. A full discussion of the patents can be found here: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.webmasterwoman.com/search-engines/phrase-based-indexing.html">
Webmaster Woman</weblink>.  The patents themselves can be found online, for example: <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. </p>
<p>

Statistical Compound Term Processing is more adaptive than the "phrase based indexing and retrieval" detailed by Anna Lynn Patterson in her patent applications. The "phrase based indexing" is targeted at searching the World Wide Web where an extensive statistical knowledge of common searches can be used to identify candidate phrases. Statistical Compound Term Processing is more suited to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/12101316.xml">
Enterprise Search</link> applications where such <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/48166.xml">
a priori</link> knowledge is not available.</p>
<p>

Statistical Compound Term Processing is also more adaptive than the linguistic approach taken by the CLAMOUR project which considers the syntactic properties of the terms (part of speech, gender, number) and their combination. CLAMOUR is highly language dependent, whereas the statistical approach is language independent. </p>

<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/17770654.xml">
Concept Searching Limited</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/12101316.xml">
Enterprise search</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
Information retrieval</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://direct.bl.uk/bld/PlaceOrder.do?UIN=138451913&amp;ETOC=RN">
http://direct.bl.uk/bld/PlaceOrder.do?UIN=138451913&amp;ETOC=RN</weblink> British Library Direct catalogue entry</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.conceptsearching.com/Web/UserFiles/File/Concept%20Searching%20Lateral%20Thinking.pdf">
http://www.conceptsearching.com/Web/UserFiles/File/Concept%20Searching%20Lateral%20Thinking.pdf</weblink> Lateral Thinking in Information Retrieval</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/methods_quality/clamour/coordination/wp03.asp">
http://www.statistics.gov.uk/methods_quality/clamour/coordination/wp03.asp</weblink> National Statistics CLAMOUR project</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/methods_quality/clamour/downloads/Clamour_march2002_final_reportAO.pdf">
http://www.statistics.gov.uk/methods_quality/clamour/downloads/Clamour_march2002_final_reportAO.pdf</weblink>CLAMOUR Final Report </entry>
<entry id="5">
http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~ser/homepage.html Stephen E. Robertson</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~ser/papers/RSJ76.pdf">
http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~ser/papers/RSJ76.pdf</weblink> Relevance weighting of search terms</entry>
<entry id="7">
WILLIAMS, J.H., 'Results of classifying documents with multiple discriminant functions', In : Statistical Association Methods for Mechanized Documentation, National Bureau of Standards, Washington, 217-224 (1965).</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://appft1.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;d=PG01&amp;p=1&amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsrchnum.html&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;s1=%2220060031195%22.PGNR.&amp;OS=DN/20060031195&amp;RS=DN/20060031195">
http://appft1.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;d=PG01&amp;p=1&amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsrchnum.html&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;s1=%2220060031195%22.PGNR.&amp;OS=DN/20060031195&amp;RS=DN/20060031195</weblink> US Patent: 20060031195</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
  External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.conceptsearching.com/">
Concept Searching Limited</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.webmasterwoman.com/search-engines/phrase-based-indexing.html">
Webmaster Woman</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
