<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:25:44[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<operation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100955060">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<attack  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100972621">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Keygen</title>
<id>180457</id>
<revision>
<id>244437278</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T20:13:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DMCer</username>
<id>2862797</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Miscellaneous articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Software piracy</category>
<category>Law articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Cryptographic attacks</category>
<category>Articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Pages needing expert attention</category>
<category>Warez</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.</b><p>

  may be able to help recruit one.
If a more appropriate  or 
portalexists, please adjust this template accordingly.</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

A <b>keygen</b> (a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/16823212.xml">
portmanteau</link> of "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/1030427.xml">
key generator</link>") is a small program that will generate a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
cryptographic</link> key for data encryption. An example is the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/28814.xml">
ssh</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
-keygen.</p>
<p>

Programs that generate valid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/386661.xml">
CD key</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../319/58319.xml">
serial</link>/registration numbers for a piece of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> are also commonly called keygens. These are made available by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/29213.xml">
software cracking</link> groups for free download on various websites dedicated to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/18935579.xml">
software piracy</link>. The use of Keygens to activate software without purchasing a genuine code is illegal.</p>

<sec>
<st>
How registration key generators work</st>
<p>

The author typically uses a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/54390.xml">
disassembler</link> to look at the raw <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/1368.xml">
assembly</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/27661.xml">
code</link> of the program they are writing the keygen for, checking either the software itself or the installer. Once they have access to the program's code, they can locate the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/40988.xml">
subroutine</link>(s) responsible for verifying that the key entered is valid. Using this knowledge, they can <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/18935488.xml">
reverse engineer</link> the algorithm used to generate valid keys, which is then incorporated into the keygen. Sometimes keygens have code incorporated into the keygen to change the written code of a program in order for the code that is given via the keygen to work but, this is not typically done for a keygen as it requires more effort and sometimes added code for it to work.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Problems with keygens</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/351190.xml">
Product activation</link></it>
</indent>

Legal issues aside, there are two major issues in using keygens: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/351190.xml">
Product activation</link> and online key verification. </p>
<p>

Keys generated with a key generator may not work with software that is used online, including downloading <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/475153.xml">
software update</link>s. This is because the user must confirm their serial number every time the software connects to the server, and the key may be invalid for various reasons.</p>
<p>

One reason is that the cracker may have misinterpreted the original algorithm, creating a key that was "good enough" to let the software be installed, but not letting all possible future generated keys be valid.</p>
<p>

Another reason may be that the software developers only accept keys that they know were distributed with the media during production, or had been issued with an online registration, causing a cryptographically correct key to still be denied.</p>
<p>

A third reason could be a secondary unpublished algorithm that is used by the vendor, e.g., to extend the previous example, the characters 0, 7, 9, C, and K are never allowed. The software that confirms the key on the user's machine does not know these numbers and characters are not allowed, and will accept the keygen output, but the online confirmation fails.</p>
<p>

Keys for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/529056.xml">
massively multiplayer online game</link>s are different; usually each key is uniquely generated by the producer and included with the product, usually in a tamper-proof medium such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/3011806.xml">
scratch card</link> or tamper-proof envelope. These keys will usually become uniquely linked to a certain game account upon usage and are rendered "useless" by this process. Therefore, MMOGs are not usually subject to piracy. </p>
<p>

Keygens may also contain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/18994196.xml">
viruses</link> (depending on whom they are downloaded from). When the program is opened, instead of providing a valid key, the program may install harmful software on the computer on which it was installed.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Actions taken by software developers</st>

<p>

Software developers have tried to prevent piracy by using 'Product Activation', which requires the user to connect to the internet or call a number in order to make a program usable. Newer keygens also contain a method to bypass the product activation. Some software manufacturers like Adobe include telephone activation which requires you to give a special code when you call. A method used by some keygens allows one to type the number given by the product to generate the (telephone) activation code which is then typed into the software. Some software developers, such as Norton, have worked around this by not including this feature or making it harder to locate in the program's code. This makes it harder for cracking groups to write an activation code. </p>
<p>

Keygens are widely available but the legality of their use differs internationally.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>




</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</event>
</operation>
</article>
