<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:28:54[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<merchandise  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103748886">
<header>
<title>Lubricant</title>
<id>18069</id>
<revision>
<id>244609293</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T18:08:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rholton</username>
<id>30981</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Petroleum products</category>
<category>Lubricants</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(February 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


A <b>lubricant</b> (sometimes referred to as a "Lube") is a substance (often a liquid) introduced between two moving surfaces to reduce the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/11062.xml">
friction</link> between them, improving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/268344.xml">
efficiency</link> and reducing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/366023.xml">
wear</link>. It is used the the engine of the car to help reduce friction. =]They also have the function of dissolving foreign particles. Petroleum-based lubricants like <name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.8">
<hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/11173100.xml">
Vaseline</link></language_unit>
</characteristic>
</part>
</trade_name>
</hallmark>
</name>
 tend to dissolve petroleum products such as rubber and plastic, while water-based lubricants will dissolve polar chemicals. The lubricant must be replaced when it has dissolved to saturation, because the inability to dissolve additional debris allows abrasive particles to scrape against or become lodged in the working surfaces. Lubricants which dissolve working surfaces (such as Vaseline with rubber) defeat their purpose by corroding the smooth surfaces by their own dissolving power, thus compromising structural integrity, surface smoothness, and system-wide contamination.</p>
<p>

One of the single largest applications for lubricants, in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/216189.xml">
motor oil</link>, is to protect the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/14796.xml">
internal combustion engine</link>s in motor vehicles and powered equipment.</p>
<p>

Typically lubricants contain 90% base oil (most often <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/23195.xml">
petroleum</link> fractions, called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/212419.xml">
mineral oil</link>s) and less than 10% additives.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/192331.xml">
Vegetable oil</link>s or synthetic liquids such as hydrogenated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/2618778.xml">
polyolefin</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/9675.xml">
ester</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/65827.xml">
silicone</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/78517.xml">
fluorocarbon</link>s and many others are sometimes used as base oils.  Additives deliver reduced friction and wear, increased <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18963754.xml">
viscosity</link>, improved viscosity index, resistance to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/155443.xml">
corrosion</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/66313.xml">
oxidation</link>, aging or contamination, etc.  </p>
<p>

Lubricants such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/2819592.xml">
2-cycle oil</link> are also added to some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/10973.xml">
fuel</link>s. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/27127.xml">
Sulfur</link> impurities in fuels also provide some lubrication properties, which has to be taken in account when switching to a low-sulfur <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/81761.xml">
diesel</link>; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/188551.xml">
biodiesel</link> is a popular diesel fuel additive providing additional lubricity.</p>
<p>

Non-liquid lubricants include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/2439173.xml">
grease</link>,  powders (dry <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/12366.xml">
graphite</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/30791.xml">
PTFE</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/295684.xml">
Molybdenum disulfide</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/5081146.xml">
tungsten disulfide</link>, etc.), teflon tape used in plumbing, air cushion and others.   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/14949005.xml">
Dry lubricant</link>s such as graphite, molybdenum disulfide and tungsten disulfide also offer lubrication at temperatures (up to 350 °C) higher than liquid and oil-based lubricants are able to operate.   Limited interest has been shown in low friction properties of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/6717193.xml">
compacted oxide glaze layer</link>s formed at several hundred degrees Celsius in metallic sliding systems, however, practical use is still many years away due to their physically unstable nature. </p>
<p>

Another approach to reducing friction and wear is to use bearings such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/198101.xml">
ball bearing</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/627542.xml">
roller bearing</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/708581.xml">
air bearing</link>s, which in turn require internal lubrication themselves, or to use sound, in the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/2411486.xml">
acoustic lubrication</link>. </p>
<p>

In addition to automotive and industrial applications, lubricants are used for many other purposes, including as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/574981.xml">
personal lubricant</link>, bio-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medical</link> applications (e.g. lubricants for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/2867638.xml">
artificial joint</link>s) and others.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Purpose </st>
<p>

Lubricants perform the following key functions.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Keep moving parts apart</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Reduce friction</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Transfer heat</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Carry away contaminants &amp; debris </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Transmit power</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Protect against wear</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prevent corrosion</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Stop the risk of smoke and fire of objects</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Keep moving parts apart</st>
<p>

Lubricants are typically used to separate moving parts in a system. This has the benefit of reducing friction and surface fatigue together with reduced heat generation, operating noise and vibrations. Lubricants achieve this by several ways. The most common is by forming a physical barrier i.e. a thin layer of lubricant separates the moving parts. This is termed hydrodynamic lubrication. In cases of high surface pressures or temperatures the fluid film is much thinner and some of the forces are transmitted between the surfaces through the lubricant. This is termed elasto-hydrodynamic lubrication.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Reduce friction</st>

<p>

Typically the lubricant-to-surface <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/11062.xml">
friction</link> is much less than surface-to-surface friction in a system without any lubrication. Thus use of a lubricant reduces the overall system friction. Reduced friction has the benefit of reducing heat generation and reduced formation of wear particles as well as improved efficiency. Lubricants may contain additives known as friction modifiers that chemically bind to metal surfaces to reduce surface friction even when there is insufficient bulk lubricant present for hydrodynamic lubrication, e.g. protecting the valve train in a car engine at startup.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Transfer heat</st>

<p>

Both gas and liquid lubricants can transfer heat. However, liquid lubricants are much more effective on account of their high specific <link>
heat capacity</link>. Typically the liquid lubricant is constantly circulated to and from a cooler part of the system, although lubricants may be used to warm as well as to cool when a regulated temperature is required. This circulating flow also determines the amount of heat that is carried away in any given unit of time. High flow systems can carry away a lot of heat and have the additional benefit of reducing the thermal stress on the lubricant. Thus lower cost liquid lubricants may be used. The primary drawback is that high flows typically require larger sumps and bigger cooling units. A secondary drawback is that a high flow system that relies on the flow rate to protect the lubricant from thermal stress is susceptible to catastrophic failure during sudden system shut downs. An automotive oil-cooled <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/30886.xml">
turbocharger</link> is a typical example. Turbochargers get red hot during operation and the oil that is cooling them only survives as its residence time in the system is very short i.e. high flow rate. If the system is shut down suddenly (pulling into a service area after a high speed drive and stopping the engine) the oil that is in the turbo charger immediately oxidizes and will clog the oil ways with deposits. Over time these deposits can completely block the oil ways, reducing the cooling with the result that the turbo charger experiences total failure typically with seized <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/221430.xml">
bearings</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
.
Non-flowing lubricants such as greases &amp; pastes are not effective at heat transfer although they do contribute by reducing the generation of heat in the first place.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Carry away contaminants and debris</st>

<p>

Lubricant circulation systems have the benefit of carrying away internally generated debris and external contaminants that get introduced into the system to a filter where they can be removed. Lubricants for machines that regularly generate debris or contaminants such as automotive engines typically contain detergent and dispersant additives to assist in debris and contaminant transport to the filter and removal. Over time the filter will get clogged and require cleaning or replacement, hence the recommendation to change a car's oil filter at the same time as changing the oil. In closed systems such as gear boxes the filter may be supplemented by a magnet to attract any iron fines that get created.</p>
<p>

It is apparent that in a circulatory system the oil will only be as clean as the filter can make it, thus it is unfortunate that there are no industry standards by which consumers can readily assess the filtering ability of various automotive filters. Poor filtration significantly reduces the life of the machine (engine) as well as making the system inefficient.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Transmit power</st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/884441.xml">
Pascal's law</link> is at the heart of hydrostatic power transmission. Hydraulic fluids comprise a large portion of all lubricants produced in the world.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Protect against wear</st>

<p>

Lubricants prevent wear by keeping the moving parts apart. Lubricants may also contain anti-wear or extreme pressure additives to boost their performance against wear and fatigue.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Prevent corrosion</st>

<p>

Good quality lubricants are typically formulated with additives that form chemical bonds with surfaces to prevent corrosion and rust.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

Romans used rags dipped in animal fat to lubricate wagon wheels; however the science of lubrication (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/489228.xml">
tribology</link>) really only took off with the industrial revolution in the nineteenth century.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 General composition </st>
<p>

Lubricants are generally composed of a majority of base <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
oil</link> and a minority of additives to impart desirable characteristics.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Types of lubricants </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/18993825.xml">
Liquid</link> including emulsions and suspensions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/18993816.xml">
Solid</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<lubricant wordnetid="114890659" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/2439173.xml">
Grease</link></lubricant>
</substance>
s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
Adhesive</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Liquid lubricants</st>
<p>

Liquid lubricants may be characterized in many different ways. One of the most common ways is by the type of base oil used. Following are the most common types.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lanolin (wool grease, natural water repellant)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Water</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mineral oils</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Vegetable (natural oil)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<lubricant wordnetid="114890659" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/522468.xml">
Synthetic oil</link></material>
</lubricant>
</part>
</chemical>
</substance>
</substance>
s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Others</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Note: although generally lubricants are based on one type of base oil or another, it is quite possible to use mixtures of the base oils to meet performance requirements.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Lanolin</st>
<p>

A natural water repellent, lanolin is derived from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/17158563.xml">
sheep</link> wool grease, and is an alternative to the more common petro-chemical based lubricants.  This lubricants are also corrosion inhibitors, protecting against rust, salt and acids.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Water</st>
<p>

Water can be used on its own, or as a major component in combination with one of the other base oils.  Commonly used in engineering processes, such as milling and lathe turning.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Mineral oil</st>
<p>

This term is used to encompass lubricating base oil derived from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/23195.xml">
crude oil</link>.  The <group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/1691321.xml">
American Petroleum Institute</link></group>
 (API) designates several types of lubricant base oil identified <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.api.org/certifications/engineoil/pubs/index.cfm">
http://www.api.org/certifications/engineoil/pubs/index.cfm</weblink> as:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group I - Saturates 90% and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/27127.xml">
sulphur</link> &amp;gt;0.03%, and <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/341646.xml">
Society of Automotive Engineers</link></institution>
</group>
</company>
</society>
</social_group>
 (SAE) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/2204862.xml">
viscosity index</link> (VI) = &amp;gt;80 to 120</entry>
</list>

- Manufactured by solvent extraction, solvent or catalytic dewaxing, and hydro-finishing processes.  Common Group I base oil are 150SN (solvent neutral), 500SN, and 150BS (brightstok)
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group II – Saturates &amp;gt;90% and sulfur 0.03%, and SAE viscosity index &amp;gt;80 to 120</entry>
</list>

- Manufactured by hydrocracking and solvent or catalytic dewaxing processes.  Group II base oil has superior anti-oxidation properties since virtually all hydrocarbon molecules are saturated.  It has water-white color.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group III – Saturates &amp;gt; 90%, sulfur 0.03%, and SAE viscosity index &amp;gt;120</entry>
</list>

- Manufactured by special processes such as isohydromerization.  Can be manufactured from base oil or slax wax from dewaxing process.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group IV – <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/2618778.xml">
Polyalphaolefins</link> (PAO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group V – All others not included above</entry>
</list>

Such as naphthenics, PAG, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/9675.xml">
ester</link>s, and etc.</p>
<p>

<indent level="2">

 In <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/21139.xml">
North America</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, Groups III, IV and V are now described as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/522468.xml">
synthetic lubricants</link>, with group III frequently described as synthesised hydrocarbons, or SHCs.  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link>, only Groups IV and V may be classed as synthetics.
</indent>

The lubricant industry commonly extends this group terminology to include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group I+ with a Viscosity Index of 103 - 108</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group II+ with a Viscosity Index of 113 - 119</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group III+ with a Viscosity Index of &amp;gt;= 140</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Can also be classified into three categories depending on the prevailing compositions:
- Paraffinic
- Naphthenic
- Aromatic</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Vegetable (natural) oils</st>
<p>

These are primarily triglyceride esters derived from plants and animals.  For lubricant base oil use the vegetable derived materials are preferred.  Common ones include high oleic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/86190.xml">
canola oil</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/172190.xml">
castor oil</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/57561.xml">
palm oil</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/2921902.xml">
sunflower seed oil</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/2965997.xml">
rapeseed oil</link> from vegetable, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/2957972.xml">
Tall oil</link> from animal sources.  Many vegetable oils are often hydrolyzed to yield the acids which are subsequently combined selectively to form specialist synthetic esters.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<lubricant wordnetid="114890659" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/522468.xml">
Synthetic oil</link></material>
</lubricant>
</part>
</chemical>
</substance>
</substance>
s</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/2618778.xml">
Polyalpha-olefin</link> (PAO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Synthetic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/9675.xml">
esters</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Polyalkylene</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/519679.xml">
glycols</link> (PAG)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/959629.xml">
Phosphate ester</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Alkylated naphthalenes</link> (AN)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Silicate esters</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Ionic fluids</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Solid lubricants </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Teflon or PTFE </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/30791.xml">
Teflon</link> or PTFE is typically used as a coating layer on, for example, cooking utensils to provide a non-stick surface.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Mineral </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/12366.xml">
Graphite</link>, hexagonal <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/3370.xml">
Boron nitride</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
 (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.advceramics.com/geac/downloads/documents/81503.pdf">
http://www.advceramics.com/geac/downloads/documents/81503.pdf</weblink>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/295684.xml">
Molybdenum disulfide</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/5081146.xml">
Tungsten disulfide</link> are examples of materials that can be used as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/14949005.xml">
solid lubricant</link>s often to very high temperature.   The use of such materials are still restricted by their poor resistance to oxidation (for example, molybdenum disulfide can only be used up to 350C in air, but 1100 in reducing environments).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Other relevant phenomena </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 'Glaze' formation (high temperature wear) </st>

<p>

A further phenomenon that has undergone investigation in relation to high temperature wear prevention and lubrication, is that of '<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/6717193.xml">
glaze</link>' formation (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mysite.wanadoo-members.co.uk/high_temp_wear/mythesis.html">
http://mysite.wanadoo-members.co.uk/high_temp_wear/mythesis.html</weblink>).   This is the generation of a compacted oxide layer which sinters together to form a crystalline 'glaze' (not the amorphous layer seen in pottery) generally at high temperatures, from metallic surfaces sliding against each other (or a metallic surface against a ceramic surface).   Due to the elimination of metallic contact and adhesion by the generation of oxide, friction and wear is reduced.   Effectively, such a surface is self-lubricating.</p>
<p>

As the 'glaze' is already an oxide, it can survive to very high temperatures in air or oxidising environments.   However, it is disadvantaged by it being necessary for the base metal (or ceramic) having to undergo some wear first to generate sufficient oxide debris.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Additives </st>
<p>

A large number of additives are used to impart performance characteristics to the lubricants. The main families of additives are:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
Antioxidant</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/92514.xml">
Detergent</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<addition wordnetid="102679415" confidence="0.8">
<additive wordnetid="102679788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/3155665.xml">
Anti-wear</link></additive>
</addition>
</part>
</component>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<addition wordnetid="102679415" confidence="0.8">
<additive wordnetid="102679788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/3652806.xml">
Metal deactivator</link></additive>
</addition>
</part>
</component>
s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../812/2120812.xml">
Corrosion inhibitors</link>, Rust inhibitors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<addition wordnetid="102679415" confidence="0.8">
<additive wordnetid="102679788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/10153961.xml">
Friction modifier</link></additive>
</addition>
</part>
</component>
s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<addition wordnetid="102679415" confidence="0.8">
<additive wordnetid="102679788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/3155791.xml">
Extreme Pressure</link></additive>
</addition>
</part>
</component>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/724978.xml">
Anti-foaming agent</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/2204862.xml">
Viscosity index improver</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/10290.xml">
Demulsifying/Emulsifying</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Stickiness improver, provide adhesive property towards tool surface (in metalworking)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Complexing agent (in case of greases)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Note that many of the basic chemical compounds used as detergents (example: calcium sulfonate) serve the purpose of the first seven items in the list as well. Usually it is not economically or technically feasible to use a single do-it-all additive compound. Oils for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/3150919.xml">
hypoid</link> gear lubrication will contain high content of EP additives. Grease lubricants may contain large amount of solid particle friction modifiers, such as graphite, molybden sulfide, etc.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Application by fluid types </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Automotive</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/216189.xml">
Engine oil</link>s</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Petrol (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/23639.xml">
Gasoline</link>) engine oils </entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/8540.xml">
Diesel engine</link> oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/334940.xml">
Automatic transmission</link> fluid</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/609147.xml">
Gearbox</link> fluids</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/1338292.xml">
Brake fluid</link></material>
</part>
</chemical>
</substance>
s</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<compound wordnetid="114818238" confidence="0.8">
<macromolecule wordnetid="114944888" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<lipid wordnetid="114938907" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<organic_compound wordnetid="114727670" confidence="0.8">
<molecule wordnetid="114682133" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<oil wordnetid="114966667" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../812/241812.xml">
Hydraulic fluid</link></oil>
</material>
</molecule>
</organic_compound>
</part>
</lipid>
</chemical>
</macromolecule>
</compound>
</substance>
s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tractor (one lubricant for all systems)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link>
Universal Tractor Transmission Oil - UTTO</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link>
Super Tractor Oil Universal - STOU - includes engine</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Other motors</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/2819592.xml">
2-stroke engine oils</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Industrial</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Hydraulic oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Air compressor oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/508504.xml">
Gas Compressor</link> oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/82916.xml">
Gear</link> oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Bearing and circulating system oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Refrigerator compressor oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Steam and gas turbine oils</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Aviation</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/58664.xml">
Gas turbine</link> engine oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/25995.xml">
Piston engine</link> oils</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Marine</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Crosshead cylinder oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Crosshead <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/2142653.xml">
Crankcase</link> oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Trunk piston engine oils</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Stern tube lubricants</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Marketing </st>

<p>

The global lubricant market is generally competitive with numerous manufacturers and marketers. Overall the western market may be considered mature with a flat to declining overall volumes while there is strong growth in the emerging economies. The lubricant marketers generally--- pursue one or more of the following strategies when pursuing business.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Specification:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The lubricant is said to meet a certain specification. In the consumer market, this is often supported by a logo, symbol or words that inform the consumer that the lubricant marketer has obtained independent verification of conformance to the specification.  Examples of these include the API’s donut logo or the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/345898.xml">
NSF</link> tick mark. The most widely perceived is SAE viscosity specification, like <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/341646.xml">
SAE</link></institution>
</group>
</company>
</society>
</social_group>
 10W-40. Lubricity specifications are institute and manufacturer based. In the U.S. institute: API S for petrol engines, API C for diesel engines. For 2007 the current specs are API SM and API CJ. Higher second letter marks better oil properties, like lower engine wear supported by tests. In EU the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/309921.xml">
ACEA</link> specifications are used. There are classes A,B,C,E with number following the letter. Japan introduced the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/4359292.xml">
JASO</link> specification for motorbike engines.
In the industrial market place the specification may take the form of a legal contract to supply a conforming fluid or purchasers may choose to buy on the basis of a manufacturers own published specification.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Original equipment manufacturer (OEM) approval:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Specifications often denote a minimum acceptable performance levels. Thus many equipment manufacturers add on their own particular requirements or tighten the tolerance on a general specification to meet their particular needs (or doing a different set of tests or using different/own testbed engine). This gives the lubricant marketer an avenue to differentiate their product by designing it to meet an OEM specification. Often, the OEM carries out extensive testing and maintains an active list of approved products. This is a powerful marketing tool in the lubricant marketplace. Text on the back of the motor oil label usually has a list of conformity to some OEM specifications, such as MB, MAN, Volvo, Cummins, VW, BMW or others. Manufactures may have vastly different specifications for the range of engines they make; one may not be completely suitable for some other.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Performance:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The lubricant marketer claims benefits for the customer based on the superior performance of the lubricant. Such marketing is supported by glamorous advertising, sponsorships of typically sporting events and endorsements. Unfortunately broad performance claims are common in the consumer marketplace, which are difficult or impossible for a typical consumer to verify. In the B2B market place the marketer is normally expected to show data that supports the claims, hence reducing the use of broad claims. Increasing performance, reducing wear and fuel consumption is also aim of the later API, ACEA and car manufacturer oil specifications, so lubricant marketers can back their claims by doing extensive (and expensive) testing.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Longevity:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The marketer claims that their lubricant maintains its performance over a longer period of time. For example in the consumer market, a typical motor oil change interval is around the 3000-6000 miles (7500-15000 km). The lubricant marketer may offer a lubricant that lasts for 12000 (30000km) miles or more to convince a user to pay a premium. Typically, the consumer would need to check or balance the longer life and any warranties offered by the lubricant manufacturer with the possible loss of equipment manufacturer warranties by not following its schedule. Many car and engine manufacturers support extended drain intervals, but request extended drain interval certified oil used in that case; and sometimes a special oil filter. Example: In older Mercedes-Benz engines and in truck engines one can use engine oil MB 228.1 for basic drain interval. Engine oils conforming with higher specification MB 228.3 may be used twice as long, oil of MB 228.5 specification 3x longer. Note that the oil drain interval is valid for new engine with fuel conforming car manufacturer specification. When using lower grade fuel, or worn engine the oil change interval has to shorten accordingly. In general oils <b>approved</b> for extended use are of higher specification and reduce wear.
In the industrial market place the longevity is generally measured in time units and the lubricant marketer can suffer large financial penalties if their claims are not substantiated.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Efficiency:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The lubricant marketer claims improved equipment efficiency when compared to rival products or technologies, the claim is usually valid when comparing lubricant of higher specification with previous grade. Typically the efficiency is proved by showing a reduction in energy costs to operate the system. Guaranteeing improved efficiency is the goal of some oil test specifications such as <link>
API CI-4</link> <b>Plus</b> for diesel engines. Some car/engine manufacturers also specifically request certain higher efficiency level for lubricants for extended drain intervals.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Operational tolerance:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The lubricant is claimed to cope with specific operational environment needs. Some common environments include dry, wet, cold, hot, fire risk, high load, high or low speed, chemical compatibility, atmospheric compatibility, pressure or vacuum and various combinations. The usual thermal characteristics is outlined with SAE viscosity given for 100°C, like SAE 30, SAE 40. For low temperature viscosity the SAE xxW mark is used. Both markings can be combined together to form a SAE 0W-60 for example. <component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<addition wordnetid="102679415" confidence="0.8">
<additive wordnetid="102679788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/2204862.xml">
Viscosity index</link></additive>
</addition>
</part>
</component>
 (VI) marks viscosity change with temperature, with higher VI numbers being more temperature stable.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Economy:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The marketer offers a lubricant at a lower cost than rivals either in the same grade or a similar one that will fill the purpose for lesser price. (Stationary installations with short drain intervals.) Alternative may be offering a more expensive lubricant and promise return in lower wear, specific fuel consumption or longer drain intervals. (Expensive machinery, un-affordable downtimes.)</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Environment friendly:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The lubricant is said to be environmentally friendly. Typically this is supported by qualifying statements or conformance to generally accepted approvals. Several organizations, typically government sponsored, exist globally to qualify and approve such lubricants by evaluating their potential for environmental harm. Typically, the lubricant manufacturer is allowed to indicate such approval by showing some special mark. Examples include the German “<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<classification wordnetid="105732756" confidence="0.8">
<basic_cognitive_process wordnetid="105701944" confidence="0.8">
<mark wordnetid="105737153" confidence="0.8">
<appraisal wordnetid="105733583" confidence="0.8">
<evaluation wordnetid="105736149" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/1944868.xml">
Blue Angel</link></evaluation>
</appraisal>
</mark>
</basic_cognitive_process>
</classification>
</process>
”, European “<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<classification wordnetid="105732756" confidence="0.8">
<basic_cognitive_process wordnetid="105701944" confidence="0.8">
<mark wordnetid="105737153" confidence="0.8">
<appraisal wordnetid="105733583" confidence="0.8">
<evaluation wordnetid="105736149" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/1451418.xml">
Daisy</link></evaluation>
</appraisal>
</mark>
</basic_cognitive_process>
</classification>
</process>
” Eco label, Global Eco-Label “GEN mark”, Nordic, “White Swan”, Japanese “Earth friendly mark”; USA “Green Seal”, Canadian “Environmental Choice”, Chinese “Huan”, Singapore “Green Label”  and the French “NF Environment mark”.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Composition:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The marketer claims novel composition of the lubricant which improves some tangible performance over its rivals. Typically the technology is protected via formal patents or other intellectual property protection mechanism to prevent rivals from copying. Lot of claims in this area are simple marketing buzzwords, since most of them are related to a manufacturer specific process naming (which achieves similar results than other ones) but the competition is prohibited from using a trademark.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Quality:</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The marketer claims broad superior quality of its lubricant with no factual evidence. The quality is “proven” by references to famous brand, sporting figure, racing team, some professional endorsement or some similar <b>subjective</b> claim. All motor oil labels wear mark similar to "of outstanding quality" or "quality additives", the actual comparative evidence is always lacking.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Disposal and environmental issues </st>
<p>

It is estimated that 40% of all lubricants are released into the environment. 
<it>Disposal:</it>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/70157.xml">
Recycling</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/5638.xml">
burning</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/211285.xml">
landfill</link> and discharge into water may achieve disposal of used <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../069/18069.xml">
lubricant</link>.
There are typically strict regulations in most countries regarding disposal in landfill and discharge into water as even small amount of lubricant can contaminate a large amount of water. Most regulations permit a threshold level of lubricant that may be present in waste streams and companies spend hundreds of millions of dollars annually in treating their waste waters to get to acceptable levels.
Burning the lubricant as fuel, typically to generate electricity, is also governed by regulations mainly on account of the relatively high level of additives present. Burning generates both airborne pollutants and ash rich in toxic materials, mainly heavy metal compounds. Thus lubricant burning takes place in specialized facilities that have incorporated special scrubbers to remove airborne pollutants and have access to landfill sites with permits to handle the toxic ash.
Unfortunately, most lubricant that ends up directly in the environment is due to general public discharging it onto the ground, into drains and directly into landfills as trash. Other direct contamination sources include runoff from roadways, accidental spillages, natural or man-made disasters and pipeline leakages.
Improvement in filtration technologies and processes has now made recycling a viable option (with rising price of base stock and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/23195.xml">
crude oil</link>). Typically various filtration systems remove particulates, additives and oxidation products and recover the base oil. The oil may get refined during the process. This base oil is then treated much the same as virgin base oil however there is considerable reluctance to use recycled oils as they are generally considered inferior. Basestock fractionally vacuum distilled from used lubricants has superior properties to all natural oils, but cost effectiveness depends on many factors. Used lubricant may also be used as refinery feedstock to become part of crude oil. Again there is considerable reluctance to this use as the additives, soot and wear metals will seriously poison/deactivate the critical catalysts in the process. Cost prohibits carrying out both filtration (soot, additives removal) and re-refining (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/8301.xml">
distilling</link>, isomerisation, hydrocrack, etc.) however the primary hindrance to recycling still remains the collection of fluids as refineries need continuous supply in amounts measured in cisterns, rail tanks.
Occasionally, unused lubricant requires disposal. The best course of action in such situations is to return it to the manufacturer where it can be processed as a part of fresh batches.
<it>Environment:</it>
Lubricants both fresh and used can cause considerable damage to the environment mainly due to their high potential of serious water pollution. Further the additives typically contained in lubricant can be toxic to flora and fauna. In used fluids the oxidation products can be toxic as well. Lubricant persistence in the environment largely depends upon the base fluid, however if very toxic additives are used they may negatively affect the persistence. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/171216.xml">
Lanolin</link> lubricants are non-toxic making them the environmental alternative which is safe for both users and the environment.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Societies and industry bodies </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/1691321.xml">
API</link></group>
: American Petroleum Institute</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/5914620.xml">
STLE</link>: Society of Tribologists and Lubrication Engineers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/849807.xml">
NLGI</link>: National Lubricating Grease institute</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/341646.xml">
SAE</link></institution>
</group>
</company>
</society>
</social_group>
: Society of Automotive Engineers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/10081264.xml">
ILMA</link>: Independent lubricant manufacturer association</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/309921.xml">
European Automobile Manufacturers Association</link></group>
</association>
: ACEA</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/4359292.xml">
Japanese Automotive Standards Organization</link>: JASO</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Major publications </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Peer reviewed</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Tribology Transactions</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Journal of Synthetic Lubricants</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Trade periodicals</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Tribology and Lubrication Technology</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Fuels &amp; Lubes International</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Oiltrends</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Lubes n’ Greases</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Compoundings</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Chemical Market Review</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Machinery lubrication</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/172190.xml">
Castor oil</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/354181.xml">
WD-40</link></institution>
</characteristic>
</hallmark>
</company>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>


</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sources</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

API 1509, Engine Oil Licensing and Certification System, 15th Edition, 2002.  Appendix E, API Base Oil Interchangeability Guidelines for Passenger Car Motor Oils and Diesel Engine Oils (revised)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/cgi-bin/article.cgi/esthag/2004/38/i02/pdf/es034236p.pdf">
Boughton and Horvath, 2003, Environmental Assessment of Used Oil Management Methods, Environmental Science and Technology, V38</weblink> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mysite.wanadoo-members.co.uk/high_temp_wear/mythesis.html">
I.A. Inman. <it>Compacted Oxide Layer Formation under Conditions of Limited Debris Retention at the Wear Interface during High Temperature Sliding Wear of Superalloys</it>, Ph.D. Thesis (2003), Northumbria University, ISBN 1-58112-321-3</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.whnet.com/4x4/oil.html">
Mercedes-Benz oil recommendations, extracted from factory manuals and personal research</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.practicingoilanalysis.com/article_detail.asp?articleid=354">
Measuring reserve alkalinity and evaluation of wear dependence</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.practicingoilanalysis.com/article_detail.asp?articleid=873&amp;relatedbookgroup=OilAnalysis">
Testing used oil quality, list of possoble measurements</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.sk/books?id=cwWgbmL5fyIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;hl=en">
Lubricant Additives: Chemistry and Applications, Leslie R. Rudnick, CRC Press.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.widman.biz/Seleccion/Viscosidad/SAE-ISO/sae-iso.html">
SAE-ISO-AGMA viscosity conversion chart</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.widman.biz/Seleccion/Viscosidad/Degrees_API/degrees_api.html">
Chart of API Gravity and Specific gravity</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</merchandise>
</article>
