<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:57:38[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Geospatial</title>
<id>1812361</id>
<revision>
<id>242694202</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T07:19:37Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Michael Hardy</username>
<id>4626</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Geographical technology</category>
<category>Articles with disputed statements from August 2008</category>
<category>All pages needing cleanup</category>
<category>NPOV disputes from August 2008</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>All NPOV disputes</category>
<category>Geodesy</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Cartography</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from August 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Geospatial</b> is a term widely used to describe the combination of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/27667.xml">
spatial</link> software and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/625849.xml">
analytical</link> methods with terrestrial or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/18963910.xml">
geographic</link> datasets.  The term is often used in conjunction with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
geographic information system</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/510905.xml">
geomatics</link>, never separately. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/18992873.xml">
Geospatial Information Officer</link> is the head of geospatial information technology within a civilian, business, government and military organizations.
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Unbalanced_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  of this section is .</b> 
Please see the discussion on the . <it>(August 2008)</it>Please do not remove this message until the </col>
</row>
</table>


Many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
Geographic information system</link> (GIS) products apply the term <b>geospatial analysis</b> in a very narrow context.&#91;&#32; &ndash; &#93;  In the case of vector-based GIS this typically means operations such as map overlay (combining two or more maps or map layers according to predefined rules), simple buffering (identifying regions of a map within a specified distance of one or more features, such as towns, roads or rivers) and similar basic operations. This reflects (and is reflected in) the use of the term spatial analysis within the Open Geospatial Consortium (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/18257846.xml">
OGC</link>) “simple feature specifications”. For raster-based GIS, widely used in the environmental sciences and remote sensing, this typically means a range of actions applied to the grid cells of one or more maps (or images) often involving filtering and/or algebraic operations (map algebra). These techniques involve processing one or more raster layers according to simple rules resulting in a new map layer, for example replacing each cell value with some combination of its neighbours’ values, or computing the sum or difference of specific attribute values for each grid cell in two matching raster datasets. Descriptive statistics, such as cell counts, means, variances, maxima, minima, cumulative values, frequencies and a number of other measures and distance computations are also often included in this generic term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/3190431.xml">
spatial analysis</link>. </p>
<p>

However, the above list of functions cover only the most basic of facilities, albeit those that may be the most frequently used by the greatest number of GIS professionals. To this initial set must be added a large variety of statistical techniques (descriptive, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/416589.xml">
exploratory</link>, and explanatory <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistics</link>) that have been designed specifically for spatial and spatio-temporal data. Today such techniques are of great importance in the social sciences, medicine and criminology, despite the fact that their origins may often be traced back to problems in the environmental and life sciences, in particular ecology, geology and epidemiology. It is also to be noted that spatial statistics is largely an observational science (like astronomy) rather than an experimental science (like agronomy or pharmaceutical research). This aspect of geospatial science has important implications for analysis, particularly the application of a range of statistical methods to spatial problems.</p>
<p>

Limiting the definition of geospatial analysis to 2D mapping operations and spatial statistics remains too restrictive. There are other very important areas to be considered. These include: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/73218.xml">
surface analysis</link> —in particular analysing the properties of physical surfaces, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/12461.xml">
gradient</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/762935.xml">
aspect</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/1796418.xml">
visibility</link>, and analysing surface-like data “fields”; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1039587.xml">
network analysis</link> — examining the properties of natural and man-made networks in order to understand the behaviour of flows within and around such networks; and locational analysis. GIS-based network analysis may be used to address a wide range of practical problems such as route selection and facility location (core topics in the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/43476.xml">
operations research</link>, and problems involving flows such as those found in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/13435.xml">
hydrology</link> and transportation research. In many instances location problems relate to networks and as such are addressed with tools designed for this purpose, but in others existing networks may have little or no relevance or may be impractical to incorporate within the modeling process. Problems that are not specifically network constrained, such as new road or pipeline routing, regional warehouse location, mobile phone mast positioning or the selection of rural community health care sites, may be effectively analysed (at least initially) without reference to existing physical networks. Locational analysis "in the plane" is also applicable where suitable network datasets are not available, or are too large or expensive to be utilised, or where the location algorithm is very complex or involves the examination or simulation of a very large number of alternative configurations.</p>
<p>

A further important aspect of geospatial analysis is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/73362.xml">
visualisation</link> — the creation and manipulation of images, maps, diagrams, charts, 3D views and their associated tabular datasets. GIS packages increasingly provide a range of such tools, providing static or rotating views, draping images over 2.5D surface representations, providing animations and fly-throughs, dynamic linking and brushing and spatio-temporal visualisations. This latter class of tools is the least developed, reflecting in part the limited range of suitable compatible datasets and the limited set of analytical methods available, although this picture is changing rapidly. All these facilities augment the core tools utilised in spatial analysis throughout the analytical process (exploration of data, identification of patterns and relationships, construction of models, and communication of results).</p>

<sec>
<st>
Source</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is written like .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Geospatial&amp;action=edit">
rewrite this article</weblink> from a . For <b>blatant</b> advertising that would require a fundamental rewrite to become encyclopedic, use  to mark for .&nbsp;<it>(August 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


Geospatial Analysis - a free online website and comprehensive guide
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com">
http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Useful links</st>
<p>

American Society for Photogrammetry &amp; Remote Sensing (ASPRS),the Imaging &amp; Geospatial Information Society:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asprs.org">
http://www.asprs.org</weblink></p>
<p>

Association of American Geographers (AAG), Spatial Analysis Special Interest Group
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sam.gmu.edu/">
http://www.sam.gmu.edu/</weblink></p>
<p>

Association for Geographic Information (AGI)
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.agi.org.uk/">
http://www.agi.org.uk/</weblink></p>
<p>

Centre for Advanced Spatial Analysis (CASA):
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casa.ucl.ac.uk">
http://www.casa.ucl.ac.uk</weblink></p>
<p>

Centre for Spatially Integrated Social Science (CSISS):
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csiss.org/">
http://www.csiss.org/</weblink></p>
<p>

Centre for Computational Geography:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ccg.leeds.ac.uk/">
http://www.ccg.leeds.ac.uk/</weblink></p>
<p>

DGI - European Geospatial Intelligence Conference
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dgieurope.com">
http://www.dgieurope.com</weblink></p>
<p>

European Commission Joint Research Centre (CEC/JRC) Geostatistics Unit:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ai-geostats.org">
http://www.ai-geostats.org</weblink></p>
<p>

EURO Working Group on Locational Analysis:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ewgla2.namida.be/">
http://ewgla2.namida.be/</weblink></p>
<p>

Free GIS Organisation – portal and mailing list:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.freegis.org/">
http://www.freegis.org/</weblink></p>
<p>

Geoscience Australia:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ga.gov.au/">
http://www.ga.gov.au/</weblink></p>
<p>

Geospatial Art by Nikolas Schiller:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nikolasschiller.com/blog/index.php/geospatial-art/">
http://www.nikolasschiller.com/blog/index.php/geospatial-art/</weblink></p>
<p>

Geospatial Information &amp; Technology Association
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gita.org">
http://www.gita.org</weblink></p>
<p>

International Association for Mathematical Geology (IAMG)
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iamg.org/">
http://www.iamg.org/</weblink></p>
<p>

Market Research Society, Geodemographics Knowledgebase:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://geodemographics.org.uk">
http://geodemographics.org.uk</weblink></p>
<p>

NCGIA Core curriculum:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geog.ubc.ca/courses/klink/gis.notes/ncgia/toc.html">
http://www.geog.ubc.ca/courses/klink/gis.notes/ncgia/toc.html</weblink> </p>
<p>

National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA)
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nga.mil">
http://www.nga.mil</weblink></p>
<p>

Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC):
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opengeospatial.org">
http://www.opengeospatial.org</weblink></p>
<p>

Royal Geographical Society/Institute of British Geographers: GIS in Teaching
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rgs.org/OurWork/Schools/Teachers/CurriculumDevelopments/GIS/">
http://www.rgs.org/OurWork/Schools/Teachers/CurriculumDevelopments/GIS/</weblink></p>
<p>

Spatial Analysis Laboratory, University of Thessaly, Greece:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prd.uth.gr/res_labs/spatial_analysis/">
http://www.prd.uth.gr/res_labs/spatial_analysis/</weblink></p>
<p>

SPLINT: Spatial Literacy in Teaching
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spatial-literacy.org">
http://www.spatial-literacy.org</weblink></p>
<p>

University Consortium for Geographic Information Science (UCGIS):
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ucgis.org">
http://www.ucgis.org</weblink></p>
<p>

USGS:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.usgs.gov/">
http://www.usgs.gov/</weblink></p>
<p>

USGS Spatial Data Transfer Standard:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mcmcweb.er.usgs.gov/sdts/">
http://mcmcweb.er.usgs.gov/sdts/</weblink></p>
<p>

US National Research Council of the National Academies 
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nationalacademies.org/">
http://www.nationalacademies.org/</weblink></p>
<p>

US Army Topograhic Engineering Center
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tec.army.mil/">
http://www.tec.army.mil/</weblink></p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
