<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:59:52[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<medical_practitioner  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110305802">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<health_professional  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110165109">
<adult  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109605289">
<professional  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110480253">
<doctor  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110020890">
<header>
<title>Francis M. Pottenger, Jr.</title>
<id>1815152</id>
<revision>
<id>243359943</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T04:44:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All pages needing cleanup</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Articles lacking reliable references from January 2008</category>
<category>All articles lacking sources</category>
<category>American physicians</category>
<category>Articles with disputed statements from September 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  that appear in reliable, third-party publications.</b>
s and sources affiliated with the subject of the article are generally not sufficient for a Wikipedia article. Please include more appropriate  from , or discuss the issue on the talk page. <it>(January 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>



<b>Francis M. Pottenger, Jr.</b> (1901 - 1967) was the son of Francis M. Pottenger, Sr., the physician who co-founded the <b>Pottenger Sanatorium</b> for treatment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/30653.xml">
tuberculosis</link> in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/107660.xml">
Monrovia, California</link></village>
. </p>
<p>

He completed his residency at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/1338390.xml">
Los Angeles County Hospital</link> in 1930 and became a full-time assistant at the Sanatorium.  From 1932 to 1942, he also conducted what became known as the Pottenger Cat Study.  </p>
<p>

In 1940, he bought some of the cottages from the Monrovia sanatorium and founded the <b>Francis M Pottenger, Jr. Hospital</b>.  Until closing in 1960, the 42-bed hospital specialized in treating non-tubercular diseases of the lung, especially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/44905.xml">
asthma</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Work</st>
<p>

One particular question that Pottenger addressed in his study had to do with the nutritive value of heat-liable elements—nutrients destroyed by heat and available only in raw foods.</p>
<p>

He applied the principles of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
nutrition</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/9311.xml">
endocrinology</link> early in his practice.  Dr. Pottenger was a pioneer in using crude extracts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/270061.xml">
adrenal cortex</link> as supplements to treat  allergic states and exhaustion.  In his treatment of respiratory diseases such as TB, asthma, allergies and emphysema, he always highlighted proper diet based on the principles discovered by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<dentist wordnetid="110004282" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<dietician wordnetid="110012484" confidence="0.8">
<medical_practitioner wordnetid="110305802" confidence="0.8">
<specialist wordnetid="110631941" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<health_professional wordnetid="110165109" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/7020762.xml">
Weston Price</link></professional>
</adult>
</health_professional>
</causal_agent>
</specialist>
</medical_practitioner>
</dietician>
</person>
</dentist>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
.  At his hospital, he served liberal amounts of liver, butter, cream and eggs to convalescing patients. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Pottenger's cats</st>
<p>

Pottenger used donated laboratory cats to test the potency of the adrenal extract <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/13311.xml">
hormone</link>s he was making. The adrenal glands of these cats were removed for the experiments and Pottenger noted that most of the cats died during or followng the operation.  He was feeding the cats a supposedly nutritive diet consisting of raw milk, cod liver oil and cooked meat scraps of liver, tripe, sweetbread, brains, heart and muscle. </p>
<p>

When the number of donated cats exceeded the supply of food available, Pottenger began ordering raw meat scraps from a local meat packing plant, including organs, meat, and bone; and fed a separate group of cats from this supply.  Within months this separate group appeared in better health than the cooked meat group.  Their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/66365.xml">
kittens</link> were more energetic and, most interestingly, their post-operative death rate was lower.  </p>
<p>

At a certain point, he decided to begin a controlled scientific study.</p>
<p>

Pottenger conducted studies involving approximately 900 cats over a period of ten years, with three generations of cats being studied.  In one study, dubbed the "Milk Study," he reviewed the effects of the following five diets on cats:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Diet A: 1/3 raw meat, cod liver oil and 2/3 raw milk. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Diet B: 1/3 raw meat, cod liver oil and 2/3 pasteurized milk.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Diet C: 1/3 raw meat, cod liver oil and 2/3 evaporated milk.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Diet D: 1/3 raw meat, cod liver oil and 2/3 sweetened condensed milk.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Diet E: raw metabolized vitamin D milk only.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Effects on cats</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pottenger concluded that diet A, consisting exclusively of raw milk and raw meat was the only adequate intake which insured the maintenance of optimal health for the cats.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The cats eating the other four diets had multiple problems:&#91;&#32; &ndash; &#93;</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

By the end of the first generation the cats started to develop degenerative diseases and became quite lazy. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

By the end of the second generation, the cats had developed degenerative diseases by mid-life and started losing their coordination.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

By the end of the third generation the cats had developed degenerative diseases very early in life and some were born blind and weak and had a much shorter life span. Many of the third generation cats couldn't even produce offspring.  There was an abundance of parasites and vermin while skin diseases and allergies increased from an incidence of five percent in normal cats to over 90 percent in the third generation of deficient cats.  Kittens of the third generation did not survive six months.  Bones became soft and pliable and the cats suffered from adverse personality changes. Males became docile while females became more aggressive. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The cats suffered from most of the degenerative diseases encountered in human medicine and died out totally by the fourth generation.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Applicability to humans?</st>
<p>

Although this particular Pottenger cat study has been cited by advocates of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/575131.xml">
raw milk</link> as evidence that it is likely healthier for humans than pasteurized milk, the scientific community does not affirm that inference.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cats are not used as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/5528138.xml">
surrogate</link> test subjects for studies relating to humans due to significantly different metabolic mechanisms.  Cats are <link>
true carnivores</link> needing only meat in their diets, whereas humans are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/159403.xml">
omnivores</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Meat study</st>
<p>

In another study, one group of cats was fed a diet of two-thirds raw meat, one-third raw milk, and cod-liver oil while the second group was fed a diet of two-thirds cooked meat, one-third raw milk, and cod-liver oil. Similarly, only the group fed all raw were healthy.</p>
<p>

At the time of Pottenger's Study the Amino Acid Taurine had been discovered but had not yet been identified as an essential amino acid for Cats. Today many cats thrive on a cooked meat diet where Taurine has been added after cooking. The deficient diets lacked sufficient taurine to allow the cat's to properly form protein structures and resulted in the health effects observed. Pottenger himself concluded that there was likely an "as yet unknown" protein factor that may have been heat sensitive. This aspect shows adequately the importance of essential amino acids for pure carnivores like cats but does not contribute anything to the argument in favour of raw milk.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>


</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Books</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Pottenger's Cats: A Study in Nutrition</it>.  ISBN 0-916764-06-0</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Fundamental Chemistry in Lab</it>.  ISBN 0-673-07877-9</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.price-pottenger.org/">
Price-Pottenger Nutrition Foundation web site.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.realmilk.com/schmid_healthfetish.html">
Francis M. Pottenger, MD and "The Hazards of a Health Fetish" By Ron Schmid, ND</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.beyondveg.com/tu-j-l/raw-cooked/raw-cooked-1h.shtml">
Lesson of the Pottenger's Cats experiment: cats are not humans</weblink>  (a review of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/641274.xml">
raw food</link>ist claims on Pottenger's Cats experiment)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</doctor>
</professional>
</adult>
</health_professional>
</causal_agent>
</medical_practitioner>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
