<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:34:44[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Vector Field Histogram</title>
<id>18207458</id>
<revision>
<id>226027676</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-16T14:34:23Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jiuguang Wang</username>
<id>2430726</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Robotics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/46673.xml">
robotics</link>, <b>Vector Field Histogram (VFH)</b> is a real time <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/4562875.xml">
motion planning</link> algorithm proposed by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/18402529.xml">
Johann Borenstein</link></scientist>
 and <link>
Yoram Koren</link> in 1991.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The VFH utilizes a statistical representation of the robot's environment through the so called histogram grid, and therefore place great emphasis on dealing with uncertainty from sensor and modeling errors. Unlike other obstacle avoidance algorithms, VFH takes into account the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/8386.xml">
dynamics</link> and shape of the robot, and returns steering commands specific to the platform. While considered a local path planner, i.e., not designed for global path optimality, the VFH has been shown to produce near optimal paths. <p>

The original VFH algorithm was based on previous work on <link>
Virtual Force Field</link>, a local path planning algorithm. After its creation in 1991, VFH was updated in 1998 by <link>
Iwan Ulrich</link> and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/18402529.xml">
Johann Borenstein</link></scientist>
, and renamed <b>VFH+</b> (unofficially "Enhanced VFH").<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The approach was updated again in 2000 by Ulrich and Borenstein, and was renamed VFH*.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> VFH is currently one of the most popular local planners used in mobile robotics, competing with the later developed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/18207532.xml">
dynamic window approach</link>. Many robotic development tools and simulation environments contain built-in support for the VFH, such as in the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/10367898.xml">
Player Project</link></software>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
VFH</st>
<p>

The Vector Field Histogram was developed with the aim to be computationally efficient, robust, and insensitive to misreadings. In practice, the VFH algorithm has proven to be fast and reliable, especially when traversing densely populated obstacle courses.</p>
<p>

At the center of the VFH algorithm is the use of statistical representation of obstacles, through histogram grids (see also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/15409471.xml">
occupancy grid</link>). Such representation is well suited for inaccurate sensor data, and gives the potential for the fusion of multiple sensor readings. </p>
<p>

The VFH algorithm contains three major components: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Cartesian histogram grid: a two-dimensional Cartesian histogram grid is constructed with the robot's range sensors, such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/29438.xml">
sonar</link> or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/1461372.xml">
laser rangefinder</link>. The grid is continuously updated in real time.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Polar histogram: a one-dimensional polar histogram is constructed by reducing the Cartesian histogram around the momentary location of the robot. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Candidate valley: consecutive sectors with a polar obstacle density below threshold, known as candidate valleys, is selected based on the proximity to the target direction.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Once the direction of the center of the selected candidate direction is determined, orientation of the robot is steered to match. The speed of the robot is reduced when approaching the obstacles head-on. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
VFH+</st>
<p>

The VFH algorithm was improved in 1998 and renamed the VFH+. Improvements include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Threshold hysteresis: a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/147003.xml">
hysteresis</link> increases the smoothness of the planned trajectory.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Robot body size: robots of different sizes are taken into account, eliminating the the need to manually adjust parameters via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../484/56484.xml">
low-pass filter</link>s.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Obstacle look-ahead: sectors that are blocked by obstacles are masked in VFH+, so that the steer angle is not directed into an obstacle. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Cost function: a cost function was added to better characterize the performance of the algorithm, and also gives the possibility of switching between behaviors by changing the cost function or its parameters.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
VFH*</st>
<p>

The VFH* improves upon the original VFH algorithms by explicitly dealing with the shortcomings of a local planning algorithm, in that global optimality is not ensured. In VFH*, the algorithm verifies the steering command produced by using the <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/100558.xml">
A* search algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 to minimize the cost and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link> functions. While simple in practice, it has been shown in experimental results that this look-ahead verification can successfully deal with problematic situations that the original VFH and VFH+ cannot handle (the resulting trajectory is fast and smooth, with no significant slow down in presence of obstacles).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/4562875.xml">
Motion planning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/18207532.xml">
Dynamic window approach</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Borenstein, J.; Koren, Y.&#32;(1991).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=88137">
The vector field histogram-fast obstacle avoidance for mobilerobots</weblink>". <it>Robotics and Automation, IEEE Transactions on</it>&#32;<b>7</b>&#32;(3): 278-288. Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-30</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ulrich, I.;&#32;Borenstein, J.&#32;(1998). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=677362">
VFH+: reliable obstacle avoidance for fast mobile robots</weblink>".&#32;<it>Robotics and Automation, 1998. Proceedings. 1998 IEEE International Conference on</it>&#32;<b>2</b>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ulrich, I.;&#32;Borenstein, J.&#32;(2000). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=846405">
VFH: local obstacle avoidance with look-aheadverification</weblink>".&#32;<it>Robotics and Automation, 2000. Proceedings. ICRA'00. IEEE International Conference on</it>&#32;<b>3</b>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://playerstage.sourceforge.net/doc/Player-2.0.0/player/group__driver__vfh.html">
VFH+ in Player/Stage/Gazebo</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
