<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:35:18[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Web-to-TV</title>
<id>18228382</id>
<revision>
<id>237373647</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-09T21:47:55Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Leolaursen</username>
<id>1803593</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>Wikify from August 2008</category>
<category>Internet television</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Web-to-TV&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(August 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

A <b>Web-to-TV</b> installation uses a variety of 3rd party components, typically built around a PC capable of running a browser and the most popular codecs (Flash, Windows Media Player, Real, Quicktime, etc.) and a home network.</p>
<p>

The hardware components required for Web-to-TV can be categorized as Media PCs, Media Extenders and Video on Demand.
All of these solutions provide A/V outputs for a TV and Ethernet and Wireless network adapters.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Entertainment PCs</st>
<p>
 
Some examples of stereo cabinet friendly PCs can be found at http://www.web-to-tv.com/players.html and other similar sites.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Media Extenders</st>
<p>

Several companies provide media extenders including <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netgear.com/Products/Entertainment/DigitalMediaPlayers.aspx">
Netgear</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dlink.com/products/?sec=1&amp;pid=655">
Dlink</weblink>. Advanced game consoles - Xbox 360 from Microsoft, PS3 from Sony, and the Nintendo Wii - can be configured to stream or view content delivered from a PC on the user's home network. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
LocalCasting</st>
<p>

A new entry from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zeevee.com/home">
ZeeVee</weblink> connects to the VGA output of a home PC/server and LocalCasts (transmits) it throughout the users house over the existing coax wiring as a normal HD Dolby 5.1 channel that is directly tunable by all connected HDTV's. A unique benefit of this approach is that no additional boxes are required at each TV because only single LocalCast device is required to insert a private channel on the homes coax distribution system. In order to do this the monitor output of the PC is digitized, MPEG2 compressed, and QAM encoded all at HD resolution and in real-time. The LocalCasting PC is controlled with an RF remote or RF keyboard that includes a pointing device to provide normal interactivity with any PC application within a range suitable for the normal home. Another important benefit of this over-the-top approach is that it provides the broadest access to internet content because it supports any content or application that can be viewed on a PC.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Video on Demand</st>
<p>

Examples of video on demand solutions include <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.apple.com/appletv/">
AppleTV</weblink>, the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/175537.xml">
Netflix</link></company>
 player by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/2820048.xml">
Roku</link></company>
 and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vudu.com/">
movie service from Vudu</weblink>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Content subscription solutions</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://kylintv.com">
KylinTV</weblink> provides a "box" that serves a number of Chinese language web channels. The service is sold on a monthly subscription basis.
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/internetNews/idUSN3030690720080530">
Time Warner cable</weblink> announced plans to offer a web to tv solution.
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Internet Ready TV</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sonystyle.com/webapp/wcs/stores/servlet/ProductDisplay?catalogId=10551&amp;storeId=10151&amp;langId=-1&amp;productId=8198552921665090966">
Sony Bravia Internet Link</weblink> provides Web to TV without a PC.</p>
<p>

Sony has also announced plans to integrate this functionality into future TVs. Several major TV suppliers have made similar claims. The advent of high performance, low cost processors from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.arm.com/products/CPUs/ARMCortex-A9_MPCore.html">
ARM</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.intel.com/technology/atom/index.htm">
Intel</weblink> will ultimately bring the Web to (every) TV.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Press References</st>

<p>

Slide's SuperPoke is coming to VH1
CNET News - San Francisco,CA,USA
Who said you couldn't bring the Web to TV? Slide's absurdly popular social-network application "SuperPoke" is coming to a new platform...
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.cnet.com/8300-13577_3-36.html">
CNET News</weblink></p>
<p>

Time Warner Cable: Web to TV Coming
By Gary Kim
Time Warner Cable plans to offer subscribers an easier way to port Internet-delivered video to their television screens, says Glenn Britt, Time Warner Cable CEO, reported by Reuters news service. The future move, with no definite ...
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ipbusinessmag.com/blogs.php">
IP Business News</weblink></p>
<p>

News Bytes: June 3
By Lauren(Lauren)
While web-to-TV technology is still in its early stages, similar models are offered by APPLE’s AppleTV and TiVo, however, neither are capable of surfing for Web videos, which the Time Warner Cable box would be able to do. ...
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://digitalmedianews.blogspot.com/">
Digital Media News</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/stories.pl?ACCT=104&amp;STORY=/www/story/06-25-2008/0004838612&amp;EDATE=">
Programmer, Technology Provider and Analyst Comments</weblink>
PR Newswire (press release) - New York,NY,USA
This in turn will speed up the prospect of a Web-to-TV fully interactive experience. It is the reason we at ComedyNet believe that ActiveVideo is a front ...
See all stories on this topic</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/stories.pl?ACCT=104&amp;STORY=/www/story/06-25-2008/0004838570&amp;EDATE=">
ActiveVideo Networks Unveils First Platform To Bring Web 2.0 ...</weblink>
PR Newswire (press release) - New York,NY,USA
"The enormous market fragmentation in Web-to-TV solutions makes it difficult for us to author interactive and timely content for many diverse platforms," ...
See all stories on this topic</p>



</ss1>
</bdy>
</article>
