<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:36:15[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Theory of conjoint measurement</title>
<id>18253454</id>
<revision>
<id>241514075</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-28T11:31:23Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Gene93k</username>
<id>5014595</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Measurement</category>
<category>Metrology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In the <b>theory of conjoint measurement</b>, the quantitative structure of natural attributes can be discovered in the absence of natural concatenation operations. It is the most general theory of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/19022.xml">
measurement</link> known to science. Fundamental and derived measurement in physics (Campbell, 1920), often thought to be the most general paths to quantification, are actually instances of the theory of conjoint measurement (Michell, 1990).<p>

Conjoint measurement was independently discovered by the economist Debreu (1960) and by the mathematical psychologist <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/2082723.xml">
R. Duncan Luce</link></causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and statistician <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/415974.xml">
John Tukey</link></scientist>
</person>
 (Luce &amp; Tukey, 1964). Luce &amp; Tukey's exposition was algebraic and is therefore considered more general than Debreu's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/29954.xml">
topological</link> work, the latter being a special case of the former (Luce &amp; Suppes, 2002). The significance of the theory of conjoint measurement lies in the fact that non-geometric or "intensive" properties and systems can be quantified. Hence the quantification of such things as psychological attributes (e.g. attitudes, cognitive abilities and utility) is a logical possibility.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Background </st>
<p>

Whilst the German mathematician <link>
Otto Hölder</link> (1901) anticipated features of the theory of conjoint measurement, it was not until the publication of Luce &amp; Tukey's seminal 1964 paper that the theory received its first complete exposition. In the first article of the inaugural issue of the <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, Luce &amp; Tukey (1964) proved that two attributes could be simultaneously quantified if and only if certain ordinal relations held upon a third attribute. Appearing in the next issue of the same journal were important papers by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/161875.xml">
Dana Scott</link></scientist>
</person>
 (1964), who proposed a hierarchy of cancellation conditions for the indirect testing of the solvability and Archimedean <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/928.xml">
axioms</link>, and David Krantz (1964) who connected the Luce &amp; Tukey work to that of Hölder (1901).</p>
<p>

Work soon focussed on extending the theory of conjoint measurement to involve more than just two attributes. Krantz (1968) and <economist wordnetid="110043643" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/165494.xml">
Amos Tversky</link></psychologist>
</person>
</economist>
 (1967) developed what became known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/18632743.xml">
polynomial conjoint measurement</link>, with Krantz (1968) providing a schema with which to construct conjoint measurement structures of three or more attributes. Later, the theory of conjoint measurement (in its two variable, polynomial and <it>n</it>-component forms) received a thorough and highly technical treatment with the publication of the first volume of <it>Foundations of Measurement</it>, which Krantz, Luce, Tversky and philosopher <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/4824664.xml">
Patrick Suppes</link></associate>
</psychologist>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</philosopher>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 cowrote (Krantz, Luce, Suppes &amp; Tversky, 1971).</p>
<p>

Shortly after the publication of Krantz, et al, (1971), work focussed upon developing an "error theory" for the theory of conjoint measurement. Studies were conducted into the number of "two way tables" that supported only single cancellation and both single and double cancellation (Arbuckle &amp; Larimer, 1976; McClelland, 1977). Later enumeration studies focussed on polynomial conjoint measurement (Karabatsos &amp; Ullrich, 2002; Ullrich &amp; Wilson, 1993). These studies found that it is highly unlikely that the axioms of the theory of conjoint measurement are satisfied at random.</p>
<p>

Later, Joel Michell (1988) identified that the "no test" class of tests of the double cancellation axiom was empty. Any instance of double cancellation is thus either an acceptance or a rejection of the axiom. Michell also wrote at this time a non-technical introduction to the theory of conjoint measurement (Michell, 1990) which also contained a schema for deriving higher order cancellation conditions based upon Scott's (1964) work. Using Michell's schema, Ben Richards (Kyngdon &amp; Richards, 2007) recently discovered that some instances of the triple cancellation axiom are "incoherent" as they contradict the single cancellation axiom. Moreover, he identified many instances of the triple cancellation which are trivially true if double cancellation is supported.</p>
<p>

The axioms of the theory of conjoint measurement are not stochastic; and given the ordinal constraints placed on data by the cancellation axioms, order restricted inference methodology must be used (Iverson &amp; Falmagne, 1985). Recently, George Karabatsos and his associates (Karabatsos, 2001; Karabatsos &amp; Sheu, 2004) developed a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/38526.xml">
Bayesian</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/236801.xml">
Markov Chain Monte Carlo</link> methodology for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/24982.xml">
psychometric</link> applications. Karabatsos &amp; Ullrich (2002) demonstrated how this framework could be extended to polynomial conjoint structures. Karabatsos (2005) generalised this work with his multinomial Dirichlet framework, which enabled the probabilistic testing of many non-stochastic theories of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/2081516.xml">
mathematical psychology</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The theory of conjoint measurement</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Axioms</st>
<p>

An additive conjoint system is simply defined as follows:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>Q = f\left(A, X\right)</math>
</indent>

where <math>A = \big\{a, b, c,\ldots \big\}</math> and <math>X = \big\{x, y, z,\ldots \big\}</math> are non-empty (and possibly infinite) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/26691.xml">
sets</link> that are disjoint (that is, <math>A \cap X = \varnothing</math> ) and <it>f</it> is a non-interactive, additive function (i.e. is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/48260.xml">
monotonic function</link> or a function preserved under monontone transformation). Let " <math>\succsim</math> " be a simple order (i.e. one that is transitive, antisymmetric and strongly connected) holding upon the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/5795.xml">
Cartesian product</link></concept>
</idea>
 of <it>A</it> and <it>X</it>, <math>A \times X</math>. Krantz et al (1971) argued the triple <math>Q = \langle A, X, \succsim \rangle</math> is an <it>additive conjoint structure</it> if and only if the following axioms hold:</p>
<p>

1. <it>WEAK ORDER</it>. Suppose " <math>\succsim</math> " is an independent relation upon <math> A \times X \, </math>. <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> are weakly ordered if and only if:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 For all <math> a, b \in A, a \succ b </math> if and only if for some <math> x \in X, \left(a, x\right) \succ \left(b, x\right)</math>;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 For all <math>x, y \in X, x \succ y</math> is defined similarly;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The relation " <math>\succ</math> " is transitive and connected.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

2. <it>SINGLE CANCELLATION</it>. The relation " <math>\succsim</math> " upon <math>A \times X</math> satisfies single cancellation if and only if:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 For all <math>a, b \in A, a \succsim b</math> if and only if for all <math>x \in X, \left(a, x\right) \succsim \left(b, x\right)</math>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 For all <math>x, y \in X, x \succsim y</math> if and only if for all <math>a \in A, \left(a, x\right) \succsim \left(a, y\right)</math>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

3. <it>DOUBLE CANCELLATION</it>. The relation " <math>\succsim</math> " upon <math>A \times X</math> satisfies double cancellation if and only if for every <math>a, b, c \in A</math> and <math>x, y, z \in X</math>, if <math>\left(a, y\right) \succsim \left(b, x\right)</math> and <math>\left(b, z\right)\succsim \left(c, y\right)</math> therefore <math>\left(a, z\right)\succsim \left(c, x\right)</math>.</p>
<p>

4. <it>SOLVABILITY</it>. The relation " <math>\succsim</math> " upon <math>A \times X</math> is solvable if for any three of the four elements, <math>a, b \in A</math> and <math>x, y \in X</math>, the fourth exists such that <math>\left(a, x\right)\sim \left(b, y\right)</math>.</p>
<p>

5. <it>ARCHIMEDEAN CONDITION</it>. Let <math>\mathit{I} \, </math> be any set of consecutive integers (positive or negative, finite or infinite). The set <math>\big\{a_i | a_i \in A, i \in I \big\}</math> is a <it>standard sequence</it> upon <it>A</it> if and only if there exist <math>x, y\in X</math> such that <math>x \nsim y</math> and for all <math>i, i + 1 \in I</math>, then <math>\left(a_i, x\right)\sim \left(a_\left(i+1\right), y\right)</math>. The condition is defined similarly upon <it>X</it>.</p>
<p>

6. <it>ESSENTIALNESS</it>. Attribute <it>A</it> is essential if and only if there exists <math>a, b \in A</math> and <math>x \in X</math> such that not <math>\left(a, x\right)\sim \left(b, x\right)</math>.</p>
<p>

7. <it>SYMMETRY</it>. The relation " <math>\succsim</math> " upon <math>A \times X</math> is symmetric if and only if for <math>a, b \in A</math> there exists <math>x, y\in X</math> such that <math>\left(a, x\right)\sim \left(b, y\right)</math>; and for <math>x', y' \in X</math> there exists <math>a', b' \in A</math> such that <math>\left(a', x'\right) \sim \left(b', y'\right)</math>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Representation theorem</st>

<p>

If in any empirical circumstance Axioms 1 to 7 hold then for <math> a, c \in A </math> and <math> x, z \in X </math>, there exist functions <math>\phi_A \, </math>, <math>\phi_X \, </math> from <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> into the real numbers <math>\langle \Re, \geqslant \rangle</math> such that:</p>
<p>

<math>\left(a, z \right)\succsim\left(c, x \right)\iff \phi_A \left(a\right) + \phi_X \left(z\right)\geqslant\phi_A \left(c\right) + \phi_X \left(x\right)</math>.</p>
<p>

If <math>\phi'_A \, </math> and <math>\phi'_X \, </math> are two other real valued functions satisfying the above expression, there exist <math>\alpha &amp;gt; 0, \beta_A \, </math> and <math>\beta_X \, </math> real valued constants satisfying:</p>
<p>

<math>\phi'_A = \alpha \phi_A + \beta_A \, </math> and <math>\phi'_X = \alpha \phi_X + \beta_X \, </math>.</p>
<p>

That is, <math>\phi'_A, \phi_A, \phi'_X \, </math> and <math>\phi_X \, </math> are measurements of <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> unique up to affine transformation (i.e. each is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
interval scale</link> in Stevens’ (1946) parlance). The mathematical proof of this result is given in Krantz, et al (1971, pp. 261&ndash;266).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Explanation</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="350px" src="Wikipage_single_cancellation.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Figure One: Graphical representation of the single cancellation axiom. It can be seen that <it>a</it> &amp;gt; <it>b</it> because (<it>a</it>, <it>x</it>) &amp;gt; (<it>b</it>, <it>x</it>), (<it>a</it>, <it>y</it>) &amp;gt; (<it>b</it>, <it>y</it>) and (<it>a</it>, <it>z</it>) &amp;gt; (<it>b</it>, <it>z</it>).
</caption>
</image>

Arguably the most critical components of the theory of conjoint measurement are the cancellation axioms. Single cancellation is the lowest form of cancellation within Scott's (1964) hierarchy. Consider one of the attributes, <it>A</it>, that constitutes an additive conjoint system. Single cancellation states that if any two levels, <it>a</it>, <it>b</it>, of this attribute are weakly ordered, then this order holds irrespective of each and every level of the other attribute (<it>X</it>). The same holds for any two levels, <it>x</it>, <it>y</it> of <it>X</it>. Single cancellation is so-called because a single common element of two ordered pairs of elements cancel out to leave the same ordinal relationship holding on the remaining elements. Krantz, et al, (1971) originally called this axiom <it>independence</it>, as the ordinal relation between two levels of an attribute is independent of any and all levels of the other attribute. However, given that the term <it>independence</it> causes confusion with statistical concepts of independence, single cancellation is the preferable term. Figure One is a graphical representation of one instance of single cancellation. </p>
<p>

Satisfaction of the single cancellation axiom is necessary, but not sufficient, for the quantification of attributes <it>A</it> and <it>X</it>. It only demonstrates that the attributes concerned are at least weakly ordered. Informally, single cancellation does not sufficiently constrain the order upon the levels of <it>Q</it> to allow <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> to sustain the representation theorem stated above. For example, consider the ordered pairs (<it>a</it>, <it>x</it>), (<it>b</it>, <it>x</it>) and (<it>b</it>, <it>y</it>). If single cancellation holds then <math>\left(a, x\right)\succsim \left(b, x\right)</math> and <math>\left(b, x\right)\succsim \left(b, y\right)</math>. Hence via transitivity <math>\left(a, x\right)\succsim \left(b, y\right)</math>. The relation between these latter two ordered pairs, informally a <it>left-leaning diagonal</it>, is determined by the satisfaction of the single cancellation axiom, as are all such relations upon <it>Q</it>. </p>
<p>

<image location="left" width="350px" src="Wikipage_double_cancellation.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Figure Two: A Luce - Tukey instance of double cancellation, in which the consequent inequality (broken line arrow) does not contradict the direction of both antecedent inequalities (solid line arrows), so supporting the axiom.
</caption>
</image>

Single cancellation, however, does not determine the "right-leaning diagonal" relations. Even though by transitivity and single cancellation it was established that <math>\left(a, x\right)\succsim \left(b, y\right)</math>, the relationship between (<it>a</it>, <it>y</it>) and (<it>b</it>, <it>x</it>) remains undetermined. It could be that either <math>\left(b, x\right)\succsim \left(a, y\right)</math> or <math>\left(a, y\right)\succsim \left(b, x\right)</math> and such ambiguity cannot remain unresolved. The cancellation conditions higher in Scott's (1964) hierarchy than single cancellation must be invoked to ascertain all right leaning diagonal relations upon <it>Q</it>.</p>
<p>

The double cancellation axiom concerns a class of such relations in which the common terms of two antecedent weak inequalities cancel out to produce a third inequality. Consider the instance of double cancellation graphically represented by Figure Two. The antecendent inequalities of this particular instance of double cancellation are <math>\left(a, y\right) \succsim \left(b, x\right)</math> and <math>\left(b, z\right)\succsim \left(c, y\right)</math>. Given that:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math> \left(a, y\right) \succsim \left(b, x\right)</math> is true if and only if <math>a \oplus y \succsim b \oplus x</math>; and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>\left(b, z\right) \succsim \left(c, y\right)</math> is true if and only if <it>b</it> <math>b \oplus z \succsim c \oplus y</math>, </entry>
</list>

it follows that <math>a \oplus y \oplus b \oplus z \succsim b \oplus x \oplus c \oplus y</math>. Cancelling the common terms results in <math>\left(a, z\right)\succsim \left(c, x\right)</math>. Hence double cancellation can only obtain when <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> possess additive structure; and so hence double cancellation is the "acid test" for the hypothesis of quantity in empirical investigations.</p>
<p>

The number of instances of double cancellation is contingent upon the number of elements <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> contain. If there are <it>n</it> levels of <it>A</it> and <it>m</it> of <it>X</it>, then the number of instances of double cancellation is <it>n</it>! <math>\times</math> <it>m</it>!. Therefore, if <it>n</it> = <it>m</it> = 3, then 3! <math>\times</math> 3! = 36 instances in total of double cancellation. However, all but 6 of these instances are trivially true if single cancellation is true, and if anyone of these 6 instances is true, then all of them are true. One such instance is that shown in Figure Two. Michell (1988) calls this a <it>Luce - Tukey</it> instance of double cancellation. If single cancellation has been tested upon a set of data first and is established, then only the Luce - Tukey instances of double cancellation need to be tested. For <it>n</it> levels of <it>A</it> and <it>m</it> of <it>X</it>, the number of Luce - Tukey double cancellation instances is <math>\tbinom{n}{3}</math><math>\tbinom{m}{3}</math>. For example, if <it>n</it> = <it>m</it> = 4, then there are 16 such instances. If <it>n</it> = <it>m</it> = 5 then there are 100. In any empirical situation, if the direction of the consequent inequality contradicts the direction of <it>both</it> antecedent inequalities, double cancellation is violated and it cannot be concluded that <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> possess additive structure (Michell, 1988).</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="350px" src="Wikipage_triple_cancellation.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Figure Three: An instance of triple cancellation.
</caption>
</image>
The next two axioms involve the concept of continuity. <it>Solvability</it> means that for any three elements of <it>a</it>, <it>b</it>, <it>x</it> and <it>y</it>, the fourth exists such that the equation <math> ax = by\, </math> is solved, hence the name of the axiom. The Archimedean axiom states that a difference between two levels of an attribute cannot be infinitely larger than any other difference. Consider <math>a, b, c, d \in A</math> where <math> a - b \succ c - d </math>. There exists a natural number <it>n</it> such that <math>n \left(c - d\right) \geqslant \left(a - b\right)</math>, where <math>n \left(c - d\right)</math> is a <it>standard sequence</it> <math>a_1, a_2, \ldots, a_\left(n + 1\right)</math> such that <math>c = a_1\, </math> and <math>d = a_2\, </math> (Michell, 1990).</p>
<p>

However, as they involve infinitistic concepts, the solvability and Archimedean axioms cannot be expressed nor implied in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/10983.xml">
first order language</link> sentence (Luce &amp; Narens, 1992). Hence they are not amenable to direct testing in any finite empirical situation. But this does not entail that these axioms cannot be empirically tested. Scott's (1964) finite set of cancellation conditions can be used to indirectly test these axioms; the extent of such testing being empirically determined. For example, if both <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> possess three levels, the highest order cancellation axiom within Scott’s (1964) hierarchy that indirectly tests solvability and Archimedeaness is double cancellation. With four levels it is triple cancellation (Figure 3). If such tests are satisfied, the construction of standard sequences in differences upon <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> are possible. Hence these attributes may be dense as per the real numbers or equally spaced as per the integers (Krantz, et al, 1971). In other words, <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> are continuous quantities.</p>
<p>

<it>Essentialness</it> simply states both <it>A</it> and <it>X</it> must contain levels of differing magnitude. <it>Symmetry</it> means that any interval on one attribute (say, <it>A</it>), an interval on <it>X</it> can be found that is equivalent to the one in <it>A</it>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Conjoint measurement in <it>n</it> - components</st>

<p>

Conjoint measurement in <it>n</it> components is simply a generalisation by Krantz, et al, (1971) of the theory of conjoint measurement to <it>n</it> disjoint attributes, where <it>n</it> <math>\geqslant</math> 3.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Axioms</st>

<p>

Let <math>S_i, i \in N, n \geqslant 3</math> be disjoint attributes. The <it>n</it> + 1 - tuple <math>P = \langle S_1, \ldots, S_n, \succsim \rangle</math> is an <it>n-component additive conjoint structure</it> if and only if " <math>\succsim</math> " satisfies the following axioms:</p>
<p>

1. <it>WEAK ORDER</it>.</p>
<p>

2. <it>SINGLE CANCELLATION</it>. The relation " <math>\succsim</math> " upon <math>\langle S_1 \times S_2 \times, \ldots, \times S_n \rangle</math> satisfies single cancellation if and only if for every <math>M \subset N</math>, the ordering induced by the relation " <math>\succsim</math> " upon the attributes in <it>M</it> for fixed choices <math>s_i \in S_i, i \in N - M</math>, is unaffected by those choices.</p>
<p>

3. <it>RESTRICTED SOLVABILITY</it>. The <it>n</it> + 1 - tuple <math>P = \langle S_1, \ldots, S_n, \succsim \rangle</math> satisfies restricted solvability if and only if for each <math>i \in N</math>, whenever <math>s_1 \ldots \overline{s_i} \ldots s_n \succsim t_1 \ldots t_i \ldots t_n \succsim s_1 \ldots \underline{s_i} \ldots s_n</math>, then there exists <math>s_i \in S_i</math> such that <math>s_1 \ldots s_i \ldots s_n \sim t_1 \dots t_i \ldots t_n</math>.</p>
<p>

4. <it>ARCHIMEDEAN CONDITION</it>.</p>
<p>

5. <it>ESSENTIALNESS</it>. At least three attributes are essential.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Representation theorem</st>

<p>

If and only if the above axioms hold, then there exist the real valued functions <math>\phi_i\, </math> from <math>S_i, i \in N</math>, into the real numbers such that for all <math>s_i, t_i \in S_i</math>,</p>
<p>

<math>s_i \ldots s_n \succsim t_i \dots t_n \iff \sum_{i=1}^n \phi_i \left(s_i\right) \geqslant \sum_{i=1}^n \phi_i \left(t_i\right)</math>.</p>
<p>

If <math>\big\{\phi'_i\big\}</math> is another such family of functions satisfying the above expression, then there exist the real numbers <math>\beta_i, i \in N</math> and <math>\alpha &amp;gt; 0\, </math> such that:</p>
<p>

<math>\phi'_i = \alpha\phi_i + \beta_i\, </math>.</p>
<p>

The mathematical proof of this result is given in Krantz, et al (1971, pp.307-309).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Explanation </st>

<p>

Single cancellation in an <it>n</it>&nbsp;&amp;ge;&nbsp;3 conjoint structure is far more powerful than in the simple two attibute case of conjoint measurement. If the axiom holds upon a proper subset (<it>M</it>) of the total number of attributes involved (<it>N</it>), irrespective of any attribute in the set <it>N</it> – <it>M</it>, then assuming restricted solvability and the Archimedean condition, double cancellation will be satisfied (Krantz, et al, 1971, Lemma 6.14). However, given so little is often known about the structure of non-geometric, "intensive" attributes, the assumption of the solvability and Archimedean conditions is not really justified. All attribute pairs in any simple polynomial must satisfy the higher order cancellation axioms (Krantz &amp; Tversky, 1971). </p>
<p>

However, as Krantz, et al, (1971) noted, empirical tests of these axioms are not easy to conduct with <it>n</it>-attributes. For example, if single cancellation is supported and if all <it>n</it> attributes have exactly the same number of <it>j</it> levels (where <it>j</it>&nbsp;&amp;ge;&nbsp;3), then the total number of instances of double cancellation is equal to <math>\tbinom{j}{3}^2 \tbinom{n}{2} j \left(n - 2 \right)</math>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Arbuckle, J. &amp; Larimer, J. (1976). The number of two-way tables satisfying certain additivity axioms. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>12</it>, 89–100.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Debreu, G. (1960). Topological methods in cardinal utility theory. In K.J. Arrow, S. Karlin and P. Suppes (eds.), <it>Mathematical Methods in the Social Sciences</it>, Stanford University Press, pp. 16 &ndash; 26.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hölder, O. (1901). Die Axiome der Quantität und die Lehre vom Mass. <it>Berichte uber die Verhandlungen der Koeniglich Sachsischen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Leipzig, Mathematisch-Physikaliche Klasse</it>, <it>53</it>, 1&ndash;46. (Part 1 translated by J. Michell and C. Ernst (1996). The axioms of quantity and the theory of measurement. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>40</it>, 235&ndash;252).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Iverson, G. &amp; Falmagne, J.C. (1985). Statistical issues in measurement. <it>Mathematical Social Sciences</it>, <it>10</it>, 131&ndash;153.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Karabatsos, G. (2001). The Rasch model, additive conjoint measurement, and new models of probabilistic measurement theory. <it>Journal of Applied Measurement</it>, <it>2</it>, 389&ndash;423.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Karabatsos, G. (2005). The exchangeable multinomial model as an approach for testing axioms of choice and measurement. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>49</it>, 51&ndash;69.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Karabatsos, G., &amp; Sheu, C.F. (2004). Bayesian order constrained inference for dichotomous models of unidimensional non-parametric item response theory. <it>Applied Psychological Measurement</it>, <it>28</it>, 110&ndash;125.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Karabatsos, G. &amp; Ullrich, J.R. (2002). Enumerating and testing conjoint measurement models. <it>Mathematical Social Sciences</it>, <it>43</it>, 485&ndash;504.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Krantz, D.H. (1964). Conjoint measurement: the Luce - Tukey axiomatisation and some extensions. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>1</it>, 248-277.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Krantz, D.H. (1968). A survey of measurement theory. In G.B. Danzig &amp; A.F. Veinott (Eds.), <it>Mathematics of the Decision Sciences</it>, part 2 (pp.314&ndash;350). Providence, RI: American Mathematical Society.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Krantz, D.H.; Luce, R.D; Suppes, P. &amp; Tversky, A. (1971). <it>Foundations of Measurement, Vol. I: Additive and polynomial representations</it>. New York: Academic Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kyngdon, A. &amp; Richards, B. (2007). Attitudes, order and quantity: deterministic and direct probabilistic tests of unidimensional unfolding. <it>Journal of Applied Measurement</it>, <it>8</it>, 1&ndash;34.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Luce, R.D. &amp; Narens, L. (1992). Intrinsic Archimedeaness and the continuum. In C.W. Savage &amp; P. Erlich (Eds.), <it>Philosophical and foundational issues in measurement theory</it> (pp.15-38). Hillsdale, NJ: Erlbaum.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Luce, R.D., &amp; Suppes, P. (2002). Representational measurement theory. In H. Pashler &amp; J. Wixted (Eds.), <it>Stevens’ handbook of experimental psychology: Vol. 4. Methodology in experimental psychology</it> (3rd ed., pp. 1–41). New York: Wiley.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Luce, R.D. &amp; Tukey, J.W. (1964). Simultaneous conjoint measurement: a new scale type of fundamental measurement. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>1</it>, 1&ndash;27.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 McClelland, G. (1977). A note on Arbuckle and Larimer: the number of two way tables satisfying certain additivity axioms. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>15</it>, 292–295.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Michell, J. (1988). Some problems in testing the double cancellation condition in conjoint measurement. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>32</it>, 466&ndash;473.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Michell, J. (1990). <it>An Introduction to the Logical of Psychological Measurement</it>. Hillsdale, N.J.: Erlbaum.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Scott, D. (1964). Measurement models and linear inequalities. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>1</it>, 233&ndash;247.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Stevens, S.S. (1946). On the theory of scales of measurement. <it>Science</it>, <it>103</it>, 667&ndash;680.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tversky, A. (1967). A general theory of polynomial conjoint measurement. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>4</it>, 1&ndash;20.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ullrich, J.R. &amp; Wilson, R.E. (1993). A note on the exact number of two and three way tables satisfying conjoint measurement and additivity axioms. <it>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</it>, <it>37</it>, 624&ndash;628.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/19022.xml">
Theory of measurement</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
Level of measurement</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
