<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:06:04[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<header>
<title>Angel Flight</title>
<id>1828743</id>
<revision>
<id>242456458</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T09:05:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dontworry</username>
<id>931333</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Non-profit organizations</category>
<category>Aviation terminology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about the nonprofit transportation-facilitating organization.&#32;&#32;For the student professional service organization previously known as "Angel Flight", see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/5987327.xml">
Silver Wings</link>.&#32;&#32;
<b>Angel Flight</b> is the name used by a number of groups whose members provide free transportation for needy patients and perform other missions of community service. Such a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
non-profit organization</link> may be located in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
, or <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
 and they, like other Public Benefit Flying (PBF) organizations, help arrange free, non-emergency transportation for patients who require medical treatment but who <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/64959.xml">
cannot afford</link> to pay for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/1942.xml">
commercial flight</link>. Transportation is provided by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/32705.xml">
volunteer</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/66691.xml">
pilots</link>, often using their own private <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/12612.xml">
general aviation</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/849.xml">
aircraft</link>. In most of Canada, the Volunteer Pilot Program of <financial_institution wordnetid="108054721" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="108406486" confidence="0.8">
<charity wordnetid="108406619" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/2007451.xml">
Hope Air</link></institution>
</charity>
</foundation>
</financial_institution>
 provides a similar service, along with Angel Flight of Vancouver. The only complete list of all the Angel Flight and other Public Benefit Flying Organizations is maintained by the Air Charity Network. <link>
aircharitynetwork.org</link>
<sec>
<st>
How Angel Flight Works</st>
<p>

The Angel Flight organizations themselves do not provide the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/18580879.xml">
transportation</link>. Instead, each acts as a "matchmaker," connecting people who have a compelling need for transportation but can not afford it with individual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/66691.xml">
pilots</link> who are willing to provide free flights as a <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<volition wordnetid="105652593" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<faculty wordnetid="105650329" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/1176679.xml">
charity</link></faculty>
</kind>
</volition>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
.</p>
<p>

Angel Flight volunteers typically serve patients who require specialized medical treatment at a facility far from their homes -- for example, a clinic that has expertise in the treatment of a particular form of a disease. In some cases, other compelling human needs are served, such as transportation to visit a hospitalized family member, or transportation helping in time of emergencies or disasters. Many of the public benefit flying groups helped in the aftermath of Hurricane Katrina, for example.</p>
<p>

The Angel Flight process usually begins when a referring health professional, usually a <link>
social worker</link>, contacts an Angel Flight organization. The referrer describes the points between which transportation is needed, the total number of people and weight, and the condition of the patient.  </p>
<p>

Not every patient is eligible for transportation. For example, patients usually must be medically stable and capable of walking on their own and sitting upright unassisted. The flight must also not be for treatment of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/146290.xml">
medical emergency</link>, because weather or other factors may cause last-minute cancellation of the flight. Often a doctor's signoff is required. Therefore, these flights are not considered to be air ambulance services.</p>
<p>

If the flight request is deemed appropriate then information concerning the date, source, destination, and total passenger count is added to an "available mission list" on that Angel Flight web site or other notification list. Pilot volunteers periodically check the mission list and can assign themselves to a mission that is appropriate to their aircraft and schedule.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Angel Flight Pilots</st>
<p>

Angel Flight missions are made possible by pilots who <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/32705.xml">
volunteer</link> their time, their skills, and the funds required for aircraft operating expenses. Many pilots provide Angel Flights in their own personal aircraft, although some do so using rented aircraft. Pilots must usually meet certain minimum flight experience requirements before they are allowed to command an Angel Flight mission. They also receive training on the special procedures required for Angel Flight.</p>
<p>

Pilots have a variety of reasons for volunteering for Angel Flight missions.  Most do so simply because they enjoy flying, and because providing <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<volition wordnetid="105652593" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<faculty wordnetid="105650329" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/1176679.xml">
charity</link></faculty>
</kind>
</volition>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 transportation is more constructive than getting the proverbial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/1828689.xml">
$100 hamburger</link> or "drilling holes in the sky" (flying just for the sake of flying). The aircraft operating expenses are also generally <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/299485.xml">
tax-deductible</link> (not in Australia however).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History of Angel Flight</st>
<p>

Angel Flight's first organization under that name was founded in 1983 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/3138.xml">
Atlanta, Georgia</link></village>
. Angel Flight of Georgia continues to operate in Georgia, Tennessee, Alabama, Mississippi, North Carolina and South Carolina. Like most groups, Angel Flight of Georgia connects with other Public Benefit Flying Organizations to provide patients with transportation in other areas.</p>
<p>

About the same time, another Angel Flight organization was formed in Santa Monica, California. Originally called Angel Flight of California, it is now known as Angel Flight West and serves most of the western United States.</p>
<p>

The Air Care Alliance, a national umbrella organization for similar volunteer pilot groups throughout the nation, was organized in the early 1990s. Later, in 2000, several of the organizations formed a joint marketing and operational effort called Angel Flight America, with offices in Virginia (now located in Dallas). Angel Flight of Georgia is not a member of Angel Flight America.</p>
<p>

In the summer of 2007, Angel Flight America was renamed the Air Charity Network, and some of its regional organizations also were renamed, such as Angel Flight Southeast, which became Mercy Flight Southeast operating in the states of Georgia, Alabama, South Carolina and Mississippi. In Florida, the operating organization remains Angel Flight Southeast. The parent organization, also now known as Mercy Flight Southeast, continued its affiliation with the former Angel Flight America/now Air Charity Network.</p>
<p>

Air Charity Network flights provide both nationwide coverage for distressed individuals with special medical and humanitarian needs, as well as serve as part of the federal Homeland Security Air Transportation System (H-SEATS) when man-made and natural disasters occur, such as the post-Hurricane Katrina recovery period.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aircareall.org/">
Air Care Alliance - listing all known Public Benefit Flying Organizations</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.angelflight-ga.org/">
Angel Flight of Georgia - Angel Flight Organization</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.angelflight.org">
Angel Flight West - Second Oldest Angel Flight Organization</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.angelflight-europe.org/">
Angel Flight Europe Web Site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.angelflight.org.au/">
Angel Flight Australia</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.patienttravel.org/">
A national Patient Air Transport Helpline</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.angelflightmidatlantic.org/">
Angel Flight Mid-Atlantic</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aircharitynetwork.org/">
Umbrella organization for several Public Benefit Flying Organizations</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.angelflightse.org/">
Public Benefit Flying Organization for Florida</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mercyflightse.org/">
Public Benefit Flying Organization for Georgia, South Carolina, Alabama &amp; Mississippi on behalf of Air Charity Network</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://flightaware.com/live/special/angel-flight/">
Track airborne Angel flights in the US</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.angelflight.org.au/html/latestflight.cfm">
Recent Angel flights in Australia</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://angelmap.pfactor.com">
Show available Angel Flight missions on a Google map</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</organization>
</article>
