<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:41:28[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>VDO-X</title>
<id>18363359</id>
<revision>
<id>238919961</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-17T00:23:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ilse@</username>
<id>141597</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Software</category>
<category>Networks</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>VDO-X</b> (Or 'Video Exchange') is software to setup and manage a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/880860.xml">
Content Delivery Network</link>. 
<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

VDO-X is professional web-based management software to deploy and manage a Content Delivery Network. The software is focussed at large size media assets and large volume delivery.
It offers support for all major streaming delivery services and web servers. These services can be used in a mixed setup.
VDO-X automatically senses the popularity of assets in specific regions of the CDN and automatically copies assets to edge servers near these regions. Viewers are redirected to these servers. In the case of unavailability, viewers are automatically redirected to other edge or core servers.
VDO-X offers full self-provisioning for each user. Users can upload assets, manage assets, setup live streams and see realtime statistics.
Many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
API</link>'s are offered for deep integration with asset management, content management, transcoding, portal and billing systems.
The flexibility and automation level of VDO-X allows a small staff to operate a CDN that handles thousands of delivery servers, thousands of customers and millions views per day.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Basic Functions</st>
<p>

VDO-X allows the administrator to:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Setup <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/28682.xml">
streaming media</link> and <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
web</link></invention>
 servers as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/40967.xml">
core</link>, <link>
fallback</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/242669.xml">
overflow</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/54483.xml">
edge</link> servers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cluster physicals servers into logical delivery farms and edges </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Setup networks via manual <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/15323.xml">
IP</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 addresses or <link>
GeoIP</link> range</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Link edge nodes and networks together for geographical optimization</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Setup commercial hosting packages</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Create account holders, hand out a product, and give them access to specific servers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Migrate servers and accounts on the fly</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

VDO-X allows the operator to:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Monitor the load and availability of each node in the CDN</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 View actual file transmission and checks between the nodes</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Manage traffic from and to the nodes</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

VDO-X allows the account holder to:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Upload streaming media assets for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/147143.xml">
VOD</link> delivery</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Upload any digital asset for file delivery</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Setup mountpoints for live streams</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Manage assets and mountpoints</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 View realtime delivery statistics for all the assets</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Force distribute assets and relays to specific nodes</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Generate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/52078.xml">
embed</link> codes and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link>'s for many media clients</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 View in-depth usage statistics</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Standards </st>
<p>

VDO-X is built around the latest web standards. VDO-X supports <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../124/5205124.xml">
Flash Media Server</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/10060075.xml">
Windows Media Services</link>, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/3943054.xml">
QuickTime Streaming Server</link></software>
, <link>
Wowza Media Server</link>, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/853219.xml">
Icecast</link></software>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/209050.xml">
Internet Information Server</link> and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/2581.xml">
Apache</link></software>
. API's are open, including <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/93489.xml">
RSS</link></format>
, <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
XML</link></format>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/29215.xml">
SOAP</link>. 
Metafile URL generation for many playlist types is supported, including <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/25231.xml">
MOV</link></format>
</software>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/623866.xml">
QTL</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/1957379.xml">
XSPF</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/28704.xml">
SMIL</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/25847.xml">
RAM</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../156/197156.xml">
ASX</link>, <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
XML</link></format>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/290279.xml">
WML</link>. 
Many media clients including QuickTime, Windows Media, Flash, Silverlight, 3GPP are supported. 
Logs are written in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/33434.xml">
W3C</link> format so they can be analyzed by many third party tools.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

<link>
Jet Stream BV</link>, the developers of VDO-X started webcasting in 1994 and developed redirection, monitoring and log processing tools for their increasing number of large webcast projects. These tools were further developed into separate commercial products, alongside a integrated media delivery framework server with support for all major streaming protocols. </p>
<p>

In 2002 Jet Stream launched a project called VDO-X to start a open CDN in the Netherlands. This project is adopted by all the ISP's and broadcasters in the Netherlands. Jet Stream has handed over the project to the <point wordnetid="105865998" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/960105.xml">
Amsterdam Internet Exchange</link></point>
, the worlds <link>
largest internet hub</link>. The AMS-IX Video Working Group is working towards a open CDN protocol. ISP's are implementing the protocol to offload streaming capacity to their own networks. In summer 2008 the European Champions League, the Tour de France and the Olympics were broadcast using the Open CDN approach.</p>
<p>

In 2002 Jet Stream also launched the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/18364008.xml">
StreamZilla</link> media delivery service, which is a popular CDN in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link>, with over 1 billion delivered views in six months and fast growing. This CDN with A+ status for global performance uses a European-wide network to distribute the content globally and is setting up edge servers to increase the performance and capacity in remote regions. StreamZilla is powered by XL Media Server and VDO-X.</p>
<p>

In 2008 Jet Stream has integrated its content delivery management tools into a single, integrated web based management environment, called VDO-X CDN 2008 Suite and is making the software available to the market. A preview of this release is available at the company website.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Market</st>
<p>

VDO-X is used by many Dutch and Belgian broadcasters, and a growing number of European network owners, internet access providers, hosting providers and network operators. VDO-X is also used for a new nation-wide CDN in Russia. Network owners are reluctant to outsource their content delivery to third party CDN operators: they pay a lot to distribute while their own infrastructure is unused. Using VDO-X, anyone with a IP network can upgrade their network to become a full-featured Content Delivery Network.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vdo-x.net">
VDO-X website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
