<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:02:11[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<region  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108630985">
<village  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108672738">
<location  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100027167">
<settlement  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108672562">
<geographical_area  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108574314">
<header>
<title>Mirca</title>
<id>1840947</id>
<revision>
<id>239582688</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-19T15:20:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>The Anomebot2</username>
<id>1979668</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Villages in Croatia</category>
<category>Brač</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Mirca</b> is a small village (pop. 180 regular; 400+ in summer) is one of the 24 villages on island of <link>
Brač</link>, close to the middle of the eastern shore of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/1447.xml">
Adriatic Sea</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/5573.xml">
Croatia</link></country>
.
<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<p>

The original people were here and in the southernmost part of the province of Dalmatia, and before the Roman time and in the Roman province of Dalmatiae, were tribe Dalmati. The whole area prospered well in the Roman time – many of Croatia’s coastal cities developed back at that time (Zadar, Split, etc.), but were not very populated. On the Island Vis (ref. “Issa”), just south of <link>
Brač</link>, there are traces of the vineyards and olive tree (wine and olive oil production facilities) from the old Greek colony’s establishment.</p>
<p>

Then, Croats arrived in the 7th century (a big movement of the south Slavic peoples, pagan people then) and the region became more populated. Croats took over through sheer numerical advantage, and accepted Christianity and Roman style dwellings. Dalmatia became the southern province of the Croatian Kingdom which was independent through 12th century. Ever since then – many Kingdoms were spreading their influence and power in Croatia and in Dalmatia in particular. In 1991 <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/5573.xml">
Croatia</link></country>
 became fully independent again.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Economy</st>

<p>

People on <link>
Brač</link>, and in Mirca, used to be into commercial fishing and typical Mediterranean agriculture (vineyards &amp; wine; almonds; olive oil and such). In the last few decades the tourism industry took over, and a lot of people built houses with apartments and rooms to rent to the summer tourists. Many “outside” people built vacation and summer houses along the shores. In general, Mirca is rather a quiet place to relax and enjoy the sea; some of the other and much bigger villages are full of hotels, bars and discos and fine restaurants (<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/6883605.xml">
Supetar</link></village>
 is only two miles east of Mirca – main ferry connection to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/18952408.xml">
Split</link>; Bol, is on the southern side of Island Brač).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Geography</st>

<p>

Island Brač is one of 1,182 Islands on the eastern, Croatian side of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/1447.xml">
Adriatic Sea</link>; there are 72 Islands permanently populated and Island Brač is the second largest Island (total regular population around 14,000). Small village Mirca, on the northern shore of Brač - across from the city of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/18952408.xml">
Split</link> - was originally positioned around half a mile inland and is now spreading through the sea; thus, there is “upper” Mirca and “lower” Mirca. There is a small harbor and crescent shaped pebble beach. On the eastern side of the beach, there is a very good (grilled fish!) restaurant - “Gumonca” - and on the western side ends in flat rocky shore with the pine woods reaching the sea.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/48361.xml">
Coordinates</link>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stable.toolserver.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Mirca&amp;params=43_23_N_16_31_E_region:HR_type:city">
43°23′N 16°31′E﻿ / ﻿43.383, 16.517</weblink></p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</geographical_area>
</settlement>
</location>
</village>
</region>
</article>
