<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:02:51[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Controlled vocabulary</title>
<id>1850719</id>
<revision>
<id>236430232</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-05T11:50:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>NCurse</username>
<id>539598</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Library cataloging and classification</category>
<category>Searching</category>
<category>Semantic Web</category>
<category>Ontology (computer science)</category>
<category>Knowledge representation</category>
<category>Technical communication</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Controlled vocabularies</b> provide a way to organize knowledge for subsequent retrieval.  They are used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/13200719.xml">
subject indexing</link> schemes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/16575380.xml">
subject heading</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/30334.xml">
thesauri</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/30463.xml">
taxonomies</link>. Controlled vocabulary schemes mandate the use of predefined, authorised terms that have been preselected by the designer of the vocabulary, in contrast to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/21173.xml">
natural language</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/191445.xml">
vocabularies</link>, where there is no restriction on the vocabulary.
<sec>
<st>
 In library and information science </st>

<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/18933569.xml">
library and information science</link> controlled vocabulary is a carefully selected list of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/1449866.xml">
word</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/44975.xml">
phrase</link>s, which are used to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/1707086.xml">
tag</link> units of information (document or work) so that they may be more easily retrieved by a search.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Controlled_vocabulary#endnote_warner">
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Controlled_vocabulary#endnote_warner</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Controlled_vocabulary#endnote_fast">
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Controlled_vocabulary#endnote_fast</weblink>. Controlled vocabularies solve the problems of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/151830.xml">
homographs</link>, 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/67396.xml">
synonyms</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/155327.xml">
polyseme</link>s by ensuring that each concept is described using only one authorized term and each authorised term in the controlled vocabulary describes only one concept. In short, controlled vocabularies reduce ambiguity inherent in normal human languages where the same concept can be given different names and ensure consistency.</p>
<p>

For example, in the Library of Congress Subject Heading (a subject heading system that uses controlled vocabulary), authorised terms (subject headings in this case) have to be chosen to handle choices between variant spellings of the same concept (American versus British), choice among scientific and popular terms (Cockroaches versus Periplaneta americana), choices between synonyms (automobile versus cars) among other difficult issues. </p>
<p>

Choices of authorised terms are based on the principles of <link>
user warrant</link> (what terms users are likely to use), <link>
literary warrant</link> (what terms are generally used in the literature and documents), <link>
structural warrant</link> (terms chosen by considering the structure, scope of the controlled vocabulary).</p>
<p>

Controlled vocabularies also typically handle the problem of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/151830.xml">
homographs</link>, with qualifiers. For example, the term "pool" has to be qualified to refer to either swimming pool, or the game pool to ensure that each authorised term or heading refers to only one concept. </p>
<p>

There are two main kinds of controlled vocabulary tools used in libraries: subject headings and thesauri. While the differences between the two are diminishing, there are still some minor differences.</p>
<p>

Historically subject headings were designed to describe books in library catalogs by catalogers while thesauri were used by indexers to apply index terms to documents and articles. Subject headings tend to be broader in scope describing whole books, while thesauri tend to be more specialised covering very specific disciplines. Also because of the card catalog system, subject headings tend to have terms that are in indirect order (though with the rise of automated systems this is being removed), while thesaurus terms are always in direct order. Subject headings also tend to use more <link>
pre-co-ordination</link> of terms such that the designer of the controlled vocabulary will combine various concepts together to form one authorised subject heading. (e.g.,  children and terrorism) while thesauri tend to use singular direct terms. Lastly thesauri list not only equivalent terms but also narrower, broader terms and related terms among various authorised and non-authorised terms, while historically most subject headings did not.</p>
<p>

For example Library of Congress Subject Heading itself did not have much syndetic structure until 1943, and it was not until 1985 when it began to adopt the thesauri type term "Broader term" and "Narrow term".</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/430476.xml">
terms</link> are chosen and organized by trained professionals (including librarians and information scientists) who possess expertise in the subject area. Controlled vocabulary terms can accurately describe what a given document is actually about, even if the terms themselves do not occur within the document's text. Well known subject heading systems include the Library of Congress system, MESH, and Sears. Well known thesauri include the Art and Architecture Thesaurus and the ERIC Thesaurus.</p>
<p>

Choosing authorized terms to be used is a tricky business, besides the areas already considered above, the designer has to consider the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/11647748.xml">
specific</link>ity of the term chosen, whether to use <link>
direct entry</link>, inter consistency and stability of the language. Lastly the amount of pre-co-ordinate (in which case the degree of enumeration versus synthesis becomes an issue) and post co-ordinate in the system is another important issue </p>
<p>

Controlled vocabularies tagged to documents are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Indexing languages </st>

<p>

There are three main types of indexing languages.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Controlled indexing language - Only approved terms can be used by the indexer to describe the document </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Natural language indexing language - Any term from the document in question can be used to describe the document. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Free indexing language  - Any term (not only from the document) can be used to describe the document.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

When indexing a document, the indexer also has to choose the level of indexing exhaustivity, the level of detail in which the document is described. For example using low indexing exhaustivity, minor aspects of the work will not be described with index terms. In general the higher the indexing exhaustivity, the more terms indexed for each document. </p>
<p>

In recent years <b>free text search</b> as a means of access to documents has become popular. This involves using natural language indexing with an indexing exhaustively set to maximum (every word in the text is <it>indexed</it>). Many studies have been done to compare the efficiency and effectiveness of free text searches against documents that have been indexed by experts using a few well chosen controlled vocabulary descriptors.</p>
<p>

Controlled vocabularies are often claimed to improve the accuracy of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/1315248.xml">
free text search</link>ing, such as to reduce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/442684.xml">
irrelevant</link> items in the retrieval list. These irrelevant items (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/5657877.xml">
false positives</link>) are often caused by the inherent ambiguity of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/21173.xml">
natural language</link>. Take the English word <it>football</it> for example. <it>Football</it> is the name given to a number of different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/988407.xml">
team sport</link>s. Worldwide the most popular of these team sports is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/10568.xml">
Association football</link>, which also happens to be called <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/10568.xml">
soccer</link></it> in several countries. The <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English language</link></language>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/2186657.xml">
word football</link> is also applied to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/25402.xml">
Rugby football</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/25405.xml">
Rugby union</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/25735.xml">
rugby league</link>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/18951490.xml">
American football</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
Australian rules football</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/37688.xml">
Gaelic football</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../963/6963.xml">
Canadian football</link>. A search for <it>football</it> therefore will retrieve documents that are about several completely different sports. Controlled vocabulary solves this problem by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/1707086.xml">
tagging</link> the documents in such a way that the ambiguities are eliminated. </p>
<p>

Compared to free text searching, the use of a controlled vocabulary can dramatically increase the performance of an information retrieval system, if performance is measured by precision (the percentage of documents in the retrieval list that are actually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/442688.xml">
relevant</link> to the search topic). </p>
<p>

In some cases controlled vocabulary can enhance recall as well, because unlike natural language schemes, once the correct authorised term is searched, you don't need to worry about searching for other terms that might be synonyms of that term.   </p>
<p>

However, a controlled vocabulary search may also lead to unsatisfactory <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../341/11705341.xml">
recall</link>, in that it will fail to retrieve some documents that are actually relevant to the search question. </p>
<p>

This is particularly problematic when the search question involves terms that are sufficiently tangential to the subject area such that the indexer might have decided to tag it using a different term (but the searcher might consider the same). Essentially, this can be avoided only by an experienced user of controlled vocabulary whose understanding of the vocabulary coincides with the way it is used by the indexer.</p>
<p>

Another possibility is that the article is just not tagged by the indexer because indexing exhaustivity is low. For example an article might mention football as a secondary focus, and the indexer might decide not to tag it with "football" because it is not important enough compared to the main focus. But it turns out that for the searcher that article is relevant and hence recall fails. A free text search would automatically pick up that article regardless. </p>
<p>

On the other hand free text searches have high exhaustivity (you search on every word) so it has potential for high recall (assuming you solve the problems of synonyms by entering every combination) but will have much lower precision.</p>
<p>

Controlled vocabularies are also quickly out-dated and in fast developing fields of knowledge, the authorised terms available might not be available if they are not updated regularly. Even in the best case scenario, controlled language is often not as specific as using the words of the text itself. Indexers trying to choose the appropriate index terms might mis-interpret the author, while a free text search is in no danger of doing so, because it uses the author's own words. </p>
<p>

The use of controlled vocabularies can be costly compared to free text searches because human experts  or expensive automated systems are necessary to index each entry.  Furthermore, the user has to be familiar with the controlled vocabulary scheme to make best use of the system. But as already mentioned, the control of synonyms, homographs can help increase precision.</p>
<p>

Numerous methodologies have been developed to assist in the creation of controlled vocabularies, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/796657.xml">
faceted classification</link>, which enables a given data record or document to be described in multiple ways.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications</st>
<p>

Controlled vocabularies, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/2583545.xml">
Library of Congress Subject Headings</link>,  are an essential component of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/190988.xml">
bibliography</link>, the study and classification of books. They were initially developed in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/18933569.xml">
library and information science</link>. In the 1950s, government agencies  began to develop controlled vocabularies for the burgeoning journal literature in specialized fields; an example is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/1076794.xml">
Medical Subject Headings</link> (MeSH) developed by the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/408290.xml">
U.S. National Library of Medicine</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
. Subsequently, for-profit firms (called <link>
Abstracting and indexing services</link>) emerged to index the fast-growing literature in every field of knowledge. In the 1960s, an <link>
online bibliographic database</link> industry developed based on dialup <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/43336.xml">
X.25</link></advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 networking. These services were seldom made available to the public because they were difficult to use; specialist librarians called <link>
search intermediaries</link> handled the searching job. In the 1980s, the first <link>
full text</link> databases appeared; these databases contain the full text of the index articles as well as the bibliographic information. Online bibliographic databases have migrated to the Internet and are now publicly available; however, most are proprietary and can be expensive to use. Students enrolled in colleges and universities may be able to access some of these services without charge; some of these services may be accessible without charge at a public library.</p>
<p>

In large organizations, controlled vocabularies may be introduced to improve <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/1219401.xml">
technical communication</link>. The use of controlled vocabulary ensures that everyone is using the same word to mean the same thing.  This consistency of terms is one of the most important concepts in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/1219301.xml">
technical writing</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/72896.xml">
knowledge management</link>, where effort is expended to use the same word throughout a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/161228.xml">
document</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link> instead of slightly different ones to refer to the same thing.</p>
<p>

Web searching could be dramatically improved by the development of a controlled vocabulary for describing Web pages; the use of such a vocabulary could culminate in a <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
Semantic Web</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
, in which the content of Web pages is described using a machine-readable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> scheme. One of the first proposals for such a scheme is the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/8742.xml">
Dublin Core</link></format>
</information>
</message>
 Initiative.</p>
<p>

It is unlikely that a single metadata scheme will ever succeed in describing the content of the entire Web.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Controlled_vocabulary#endnote_doctorow">
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Controlled_vocabulary#endnote_doctorow</weblink> To create a Semantic Web, it may be necessary to draw from two or more metadata systems to describe a Web page's contents. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/3109695.xml">
eXchangeable Faceted Metadata Language</link> (XFML) is designed to enable controlled vocabulary creators to publish and share metadata systems. XFML is designed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/796657.xml">
faceted classification</link> principles.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Controlled_vocabulary#endnote_pilgrim">
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Controlled_vocabulary#endnote_pilgrim</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <cite id="endnote_warner" style="font-style: normal;">
<b>^</b></cite>&nbsp; Amy Warner, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ischool.utexas.edu/~i385e/readings/Warner-aTaxonomyPrimer.html">
A taxonomy primer</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <cite id="endnote_fast" style="font-style: normal;">
<b>^</b></cite>&nbsp; Karl Fast, Fred Leise and Mike Steckel, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boxesandarrows.com/view/what_is_a_controlled_vocabulary_">
What is a controlled vocabulary?</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <cite id="endnote_doctorow" style="font-style: normal;">
<b>^</b></cite>&nbsp; Cory Doctorow, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.well.com/~doctorow/metacrap.htm">
Metacrap</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <cite id="endnote_pilgrim" style="font-style: normal;">
<b>^</b></cite>&nbsp; Mark Pilgrim, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://diveintomark.org/archives/2002/12/03/this_is_xfml">
This is XFML</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imresources.fit.qut.edu.au/vocab/">
Controlled Vocabularies</weblink> Links to examples of thesauri and classification schemes.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/aims/kos_list_type.htm">
Controlled Vocabularies</weblink> Links to examples of thesauri and classification schemes used in the domain of Agriculture, Fisheries, Forestry etc.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/1406260.xml">
Authority control</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/563439.xml">
Controlled natural language</link></language>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/796657.xml">
Faceted classification</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="105849040" confidence="0.8">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/1315248.xml">
Full text search</link></feature>
</property>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
Information retrieval</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
Metadata</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/2372015.xml">
Metadata registry</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/49681.xml">
Ontology (computer science)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/2372769.xml">
Semantic spectrum</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/430476.xml">
Terminology</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/207201.xml">
Technical terminology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/731640.xml">
Text retrieval</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/30334.xml">
Thesaurus</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/2570284.xml">
Universal Data Element Framework</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/3219147.xml">
Vocabulary-based transformation</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boxesandarrows.com/view/controlled_vocabularies_a_glosso_thesaurus">
Controlled vocabularies: a glosso-thesaurus</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.controlledvocabulary.com/">
controlledvocabulary.com</weblink> — explains how controlled vocabularies are useful in describing images and information for classifying content in electronic databases.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gopubmed.com">
GoPubMed - Explore PubMed/MEDLINE with the Controlled Vocabulary Gene Ontology</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.meshpubmed.com">
MeshPubMed - Explore PubMed/MEDLINE with the Controlled Vocabulary MeSH</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://evs.nci.nih.gov/">
NCI Enterprise Vocabulary Services</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/standards/resources/Z39-19-2005.pdf">
ANSI/NISO Z39.19 - 2005 Guidelines for the Construction, Format, and Management of Monolingual Controlled Vocabularies</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.allegrotechindexing.com/article02.htm">
Vocabulary Links:// Thesaurus Design for Information Systems — seminar by Dr. Bella Hass Weinberg</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tematres.r020.com.ar/index.en.html">
TemaTres: open source thesaurus management</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vocabularyserver.com">
Open Source Controlled Vocabulary server</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.daydream.co.uk/controlled_vocabulary.asp">
Designing a Controlled Vocabulary for use with Digital Asset Libraries</weblink> - a basic introduction to CV concepts aimed at those developing them for use with business oriented asset libraries.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
