<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:45:33[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104377057">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Srizbi botnet</title>
<id>18511772</id>
<revision>
<id>244446319</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T21:07:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Waacstats</username>
<id>1951353</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Distributed computing projects</category>
<category>Computer network security</category>
<category>Botnets</category>
<category>Multi-agent systems</category>
<category>Spamming</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Srizbi botnet</b>, also known by its aliases of <b>Cbeplay</b> and <b>Exchanger</b>, is the world's largest or second-largest <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/636268.xml">
botnet</link> depending on expert reports, and is responsible for sending out more than half of all the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/459847.xml">
spam</link> being sent by all the major botnets combined.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The botnets consist of computers infected by the Srizbi <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/30056.xml">
trojan</link>, which sends spam on command. 
<sec>
<st>
 Size </st>
<p>

The size of the Srizbi <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/636268.xml">
botnet</link> is estimated to be around 315,000 compromised machines, with estimation differences being smaller than 5% among various sources.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The botnet is reported to be capable of sending around 60 billion spam messages a day, which is more than half of the total of the approximately 100 billion spam messages sent every day. As a comparison, the highly publicized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/12970258.xml">
storm botnet</link> only manages to reach around 20% of the total amount of spam sent during its peak periods.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

The Srizbi botnet is showing a slight decline after a recent aggressive growth in the amount of spam messages sent out. As of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/15878.xml">
13 July</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>, the botnet is believed to be responsible for roughly 40% of all the spam on the net, a sharp decline from the almost 60% market share in May 2008."<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marshal.com/TRACE/spam_statistics.asp">
Spam statistics from TRACE</weblink>", Marshall&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/15878.xml">
July 13</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Origins </st>
<p>

The earliest reports on Srizbi trojan outbreaks were around June 2007, with small differences in detection dates across <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/268622.xml">
antivirus software</link> vendors.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> However, reports indicate that the first released version had already been assembled on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/20587.xml">
31 March</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Ever since its creation, Srizbi has been growing at an extremely rapid pace, making the botnet the largest generator of spam messages, less than one year into its existence.  There is currently no sign of decline in the number of bots involved in the botnet.</p>
<p>

The Srizbi botnet by some experts is considered the second largest botnet of the Internet.  However, due to controversy surrounding the the <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/16810240.xml">
Kraken botnet</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.darkreading.com/document.asp?doc_id=150292&amp;WT.svl=news1_1">
http://www.darkreading.com/document.asp?doc_id=150292&amp;WT.svl=news1_1</weblink>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.trustedsource.org/TS?do=threats&amp;subdo=blog&amp;id=32">
http://www.trustedsource.org/TS?do=threats&amp;subdo=blog&amp;id=32</weblink>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.f-secure.com/weblog/archives/00001418.html">
http://www.f-secure.com/weblog/archives/00001418.html</weblink> it may be that Srisbi is the largest botnet today.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Spread and botnet composition </st>
<p>

The Srizbi botnet consists of computers which have been infected by the Srizbi <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/30056.xml">
trojan horse</link>. This trojan horse is deployed onto its victim computer through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/11882157.xml">
Mpack</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/20901.xml">
malware</link> kit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> Past editions have used the "n404 web exploit kit" malware kit to spread, but this kit's usage has been deprecated in favor of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/11882157.xml">
Mpack</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

The distribution of these malware kits is partially achieved by utilizing the botnet itself. The botnet has been known to send out spam containing links to fake videos about celebrities, which include a link pointing to the malware kit. Similar attempts have been taken with other subjects such as illegal software sales and personal messages.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Apart from this self-propagation, the MPack kit is also known for much more aggressive spreading tactics, most notably the compromise of about 10,000 websites in June 2007.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> These domains, which included a surprising number of pornographic websites,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> ended up forwarding the unsuspecting visitor to websites containing the MPack program.</p>
<p>

Once a computer becomes infected by the trojan horse, the computer becomes known as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/140274.xml">
bot</link>, which will then be at the command of the owner of the botnet, commonly referred to as the botnet herder.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> The operation of the Srizbi botnet is based upon a number of servers which control the utilization of the individual bots in the botnet. These servers are redundant copies of each other, which protects the botnet from being crippled in case a system failure or legal action takes a server down. These servers are generally placed in countries such as <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/25391.xml">
Russia</link></country>
, where law enforcement against digital crime is limited.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Reactor Mailer </st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/922880.xml">
server-side</link> of the Srizbi botnet is handled by a program called "Reactor Mailer", which is a <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/23862.xml">
Python</link></programming_language>
-based <link>
web component</link> responsible for coordinating the spam sent out by the individual bots in the botnet. Reactor Mailer has existed since 2004, and is currently in its third release, which is also used to control the Srizbi botnet. The software allows for <link>
secure login</link> and allows multiple accounts, which strongly suggests that access to the botnet and its spam capacity is sold to external parties (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/2262333.xml">
Software as a service</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
). This is further reinforced by evidence showing that the Srizbi botnet runs multiple batches of spam at a time; blocks of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/14921.xml">
IP address</link>es can be observed sending different types of spam at any one time. Once a user has been granted access, he or she can utilize the software to create the message they want to send, test it for its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/274137.xml">
spam assassin</link> score and after that send it to all the users in a list of e-mail addresses.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

Suspicion has arisen that the writer of the Reactor Mailer program might be the same person responsible for the Srizbi trojan, as code analysis shows a code fingerprint that matches between the two programs. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> If this claim is indeed true, then this coder might well be responsible for the trojan behind another botnet, named Rustock. According to <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/354414.xml">
Symantec</link></company>
, the code used in the Srizbi trojan is very similar to the code found in the Rostock trojan, and could well be an improved version of the latter.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Srizbi trojan </st>
<p>

The Srizbi trojan is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/422784.xml">
client side</link> program responsible for sending the spam from infected machines. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/59791.xml">
trojan</link> has been credited with being extremely efficient at this task, which explains why Srizbi is capable of sending such high volumes of spam without having a huge numerological advantage in the number of infected computers.</p>
<p>

Apart from having an efficient spam engine, the trojan is also very capable in hiding itself from both the user and the system itself, including any products designed to remove the trojan from the system. The trojan itself is fully executed in <link>
kernel modus</link> and has been noted to employ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/223942.xml">
rootkit</link>-like technologies to prevent any form of detection. By patching the <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/39184.xml">
NTFS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/1010280.xml">
file system</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/197404.xml">
drivers</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/59791.xml">
trojan</link> will make its files invisible for both the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> and any human user utilizing the system. The trojan is also capable of hiding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/11271957.xml">
network traffic</link> it generates by directly attaching <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/650684.xml">
NDIS</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/15476.xml">
TCP/IP</link> drivers to its own process, a feature currently unique for this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/59791.xml">
trojan</link>. This procedure has been proved to allow the trojan to bypass both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1362296.xml">
firewall</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
sniffer</link> protection on the system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

Once the bot is in place and operational, it will contact one of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/1257114.xml">
hardcoded</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/4038708.xml">
servers</link> from a list it carries with it. This server will then supply the bot with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/17413320.xml">
zip</link> file containing a number of files required by the bot to start its spamming business. The following files have been identified to be downloaded:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 000_data2 - mail server domains</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 001_ncommall - list of names)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 002_senderna - list of possible sender names</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 003_sendersu - list of possible sender surnames</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 config - Main spam configuration file</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 message - HTML message to spam</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 mlist - Recipients mail addresses</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 mxdata - MX record data</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

When these files have been received, the bot will first initialize a software routine which allows it to remove files critical for revealing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/27911.xml">
spam</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/223942.xml">
rootkit</link> applications. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> After this procedure is done, the trojan will then start sending out the spam message it has received from the control server.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Incidents </st>

<p>

The Srizbi botnet has been the basis for several incidents which have received media coverage in the regular media. Several of the most notable ones will be described below here. This is by no means a complete list of incidents, but just a list of the major ones.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 The "Ron Paul"  incident </st>
<p>

In October 2007, several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/313737.xml">
anti-spam</link> firms noticed an unusual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/27911.xml">
spam</link> campaign emerging. Unlike the usual messages about counterfeit watches, stocks or penis enlargement, the mail contained promotional information about <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/24113.xml">
presidential candidate</link> <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<congressman wordnetid="109955781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/168715.xml">
Ron Paul</link></congressman>
</person>
. The <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<congressman wordnetid="109955781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/168715.xml">
Ron Paul</link></congressman>
</person>
 camp dismissed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/27911.xml">
spam</link> as being not related to the official presidential campaign. A spokesman told the press "If it is true, it could be done by a well-intentioned yet misguided supporter or someone with bad intentions trying to embarrass the campaign. Either way, this is independent work, and we have no connection."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

Later, the spam was confirmed as coming from the Srizbi network.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> Through the capture of one of the control servers involved,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> investigators learned that the spam message had been sent to up to 160 million <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
e-mail</link> addresses by as few as 3,000 bot computers. The spammer himself has only been identified by his internet <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/16301990.xml">
handle</link> "nenastnyj"; his or her real identity has not been determined.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Malicious spam tripling volumes in a week </st>
<p>

In the week from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/15818.xml">
20 June</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link> Srizbi managed to triple the amount of malicious spam send from an average 3% to 9.9%, largely due to its own effort.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> This particular spam wave was an aggressive attempt to increase the size of the Srizbi botnet by sending e-mails to users which warned them that they had been videotaped naked.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> Sending this message, which is a kind of spam referred to as "Stupid Theme", was an attempt to get people to click the malicious link included in the mail, before realizing that this message was most likely <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/27911.xml">
spam</link>. While old, this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/26907.xml">
social engineering</link> technique has still been proved effective for the means of spammers.</p>
<p>

The size of this operation shows that the power and monetary income from a botnet is closely based upon its spam capacity: more infected computers translate directly into greater revenue for the botnet owner. It also shows the power botnets have to increase their own size, mainly by using a part of their own strength in numbers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/636268.xml">
Botnet</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/12970258.xml">
Storm botnet</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/11882157.xml">
MPack malware kit</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/459847.xml">
E-mail spam</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<transgression wordnetid="100745005" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<crime wordnetid="100766234" confidence="0.8">
<wrongdoing wordnetid="100732746" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/1727651.xml">
Internet crime</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</wrongdoing>
</crime>
</event>
</transgression>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/863095.xml">
Internet security</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Jackson Higgins, Kelly&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/19353.xml">
May 8</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.darkreading.com/document.asp?doc_id=153271">
Srizbi Botnet Sending Over 60 Billion Spams a Day</weblink>", Dark Reading.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
Pauli, Darren&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/19353.xml">
May 8</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/145631/srizbi_botnet_sets_new_records_for_spam.html">
Srizbi Botnet Sets New Records for Spam</weblink>", PC World.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
Popa, Bogdan&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/2564.xml">
April 10</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.softpedia.com/news/Meet-Srizbi-The-Largest-Botnet-Ever-82992.shtml">
Meet Srizbi, the Largest Botnet Ever</weblink>", Softpedia.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
E. Dunn, John&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/19675.xml">
May 13</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csoonline.com/article/356219/Srizbi_Grows_Into_World_s_Largest_Botnet">
Srizbi Grows Into World's Largest Botnet</weblink>", CSO Online.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.symantec.com/security_response/writeup.jsp?docid=2007-062007-0946-99&amp;tabid=1">
Trojan.Srizbi</weblink>", Symantec&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/16181.xml">
July 23</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sophos.com/security/analyses/viruses-and-spyware/trojrkagena.html">
Troj/RKAgen-A Trojan (Rootkit.Win32.Agent.ea, Trojan.Srizbi) - Sophos security analysis</weblink>", Sophos&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/1005.xml">
August</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
Stewart, Joe&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/8354.xml">
December 4</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.secureworks.com/research/threats/ronpaul/?threat=ronpaul">
Inside the "Ron Paul" Spam Botnet</weblink>", SecureWorks.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
Keizer, Gregg&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/15861.xml">
July 5</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9026323">
Mpack installs ultra-invisible Trojan</weblink>", ComputerWorld.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
Blog, TRACE&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/18935042.xml">
March 7</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marshal.com/trace/traceitem.asp?article=595&amp;thesection=trace">
Srizbi uses multi-pronged attack to spread malware</weblink>", Marshal Limited.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
McKenzie, Grey&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/15799.xml">
June 25</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nationalcybersecurity.com/blogs/778/-Srizbi-Botnet-Is-Largely-Responsible-for-Recent-Sharp-Increase-In-Spam.html">
Srizbi Botnet Is Largely Responsible for Recent Sharp Increase In Spam</weblink>", National Cyber Security.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marshal.com/trace/traceitem.asp?article=568&amp;thesection=trace">
Srizbi spam uses celebrities as lures</weblink>", TRACE Blog&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/11025.xml">
February 20</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
 Keizer, Gregg&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/15805.xml">
June 10</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9025198">
Hackers compromise 10k sites, launch 'phenomenal' attack</weblink>", ComputerWorld.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
Keizer, Gregg&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/15857.xml">
June 22</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9025578">
Porn sites serve up Mpack attacks</weblink>", ComputerWorld.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.securityfocus.com/brief/328">
Spying on bot nets becoming harder</weblink>", SecurityFocus&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/22530.xml">
October 12</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
Hayashi, Kaoru&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/15842.xml">
June 29</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;"[https://forums.symantec.com/syment/blog/article?message.uid=305311 "Spam from the Kernel: Full-Kernel Malware Installed by MPack"]", Symantec.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
Paul, Ryan&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/8352.xml">
December 6</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arstechnica.com/news.ars/post/20071206-researchers-track-ron-paul-spam-back-to-reactor-botnet.html">
Researchers track Ron Paul spam back to Reactor botnet</weblink>", ARS Technica.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
Cheng, Jacqui&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/22437.xml">
October 31</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arstechnica.com/news.ars/post/20071031-ron-paul-camp-gets-over-enthusiastic-with-spam.html">
Researchers: Ron Paul campaign e-mails originating from spambots</weblink>", ARS Technica.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="19">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blog.protectwebform.com/p/45">
The Naked Truth About the Srizbi Botnet</weblink>", Protect Web Form Blog&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/19632.xml">
May 19</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
Salek, Negar&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/15799.xml">
June 25</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.securecomputing.net.au/News/115170,one-of-the-biggest-threats-to-internet-users-today-srizbi.aspx">
One of the biggest threats to Internet users today: Srizbi</weblink>", SC Magazine.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
Walsh, Sue&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/15801.xml">
June 27</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.allspammedup.com/2008/06/spam-volume-triples-in-a-week/">
Spam Volume Triples In A Week</weblink>", All Spammed Up.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/636268.xml">
Botnets</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Main articles</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/636268.xml">
Botnet</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/6010.xml">
Computer worms</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/20901.xml">
Malware</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/1569607.xml">
Malbot</link>&nbsp;·  </col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Notable botnets</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/12970258.xml">
Storm botnet</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
&nbsp;·  <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/16810240.xml">
Kraken botnet</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
&nbsp;·  <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/18511772.xml">
Srizbi botnet</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</article>
