<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:46:38[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<body  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107965085">
<university  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108286163">
<social_group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107950920">
<educational_institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276342">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>University of the Philippines Information Technology Training Center</title>
<id>18537311</id>
<revision>
<id>242389014</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T01:15:32Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Educational institutions in Quezon City</category>
<category>Educational institutions established in 2004</category>
<category>University of the Philippines</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The University of the Philippines Information Technology Training Center or UP ITTC is a program of the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/190490.xml">
University of the Philippines</link></university>
 together with the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/2603765.xml">
Japan International Cooperation Agency</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
 or JICA. The UP ITTC strives to accomplish the following goals: to produce top-notch IT graduates in five years; to produce IT graduates with Japanese language training; to be the leading training institution for IT certification; to be a model IT training institution in the region in five years; and to be sustainable even after the technical cooperation period. The UP ITTC also hosts the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/17557096.xml">
Philippine Youth Congress in Information Technology</link> or Y4iT every September, the biggest IT event in the nation.<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Upittc-logo.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Helping You Build a Solid IT Career
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

On 26 February 2004, upon UP President Francisco Nemenzo’s recommendation, the UP Board of Regents (BOR) approved the creation of the ITTC Program under the Office of the Vice-President for Development. The BOR appointed a Program Director for UP ITTC on 22 July 2004.</p>
<p>

For its full-scale implementation, the University proposed a project for funding by the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/2603765.xml">
Japan International Cooperation Agency</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
 (JICA). This was dubbed as the Japan-Philippines Technical Cooperation Project on Philippine IT Human Resource Development (ITHRD), which was approved by JICA and started operation on 20 July 2004, for a term of four years.</p>
<p>

In the “Record of Discussions” signed by JICA and the University on 09 July 2004, the project purpose was stated as follows:  To conduct high-level and practical IT training in an effective and efficient manner, in cooperation with other universities and industries, and to match the needs of the industry.</p>
<p>

JICA and UP had a series of discussions with respect to the measures to be undertaken for the successful implementation of UP ITTC. As a result, they made firm commitments on the allocation of resources. </p>
<p>

<b>Philosophy</b>
The UP ITTC believes in “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/287010.xml">
kaizen</link>” (continuous improvement) to attain quality IT education that will greatly contribute to Philippine development.</p>
<p>

<b>Vision</b>
The UP ITTC is the partner of choice for quality IT training and is a model of effective academe, industry, and government collaboration.</p>
<p>

<b>Mission</b>
The UP ITTC produces world-class IT professionals with high-level skills required by the industry.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Courses</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Fulltime Courses</st>
<p>

As a training center with specialization tracks in <it>Applications Development</it>, <it>Network Systems</it>, and <it>Mobile Computing and Embedded Systems</it>, UP ITTC offers a one-year full time training course with a Certificate in Information Technology. Yearly admission and scholarship examinations are conducted at the UP Diliman Campus (Quezon City) and in various areas in the provinces, such as Bacolod, Bicol, Butuan, and Tacloban.</p>
<p>

Qualified enrollees are college graduates of Computer Science and IT-related courses as well as graduates of other courses who possess a high aptitude for IT and who dream of becoming part of the IT industry.</p>
<p>

UP ITTC fulltime students generally take Japanese language lessons everyday and prepare themselves for the Japanese Language Proficiency Test (JLPT) Levels 3 and 4. They are also primed for the <qualification wordnetid="104717139" confidence="0.8">
<fitness wordnetid="104716864" confidence="0.8">
<suitability wordnetid="104715487" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/11777722.xml">
PhilNITS</link></suitability>
</fitness>
</qualification>
 Fundamental Engineer (FE) examinations held every April and October.</p>
<p>

The fulltime IT training program runs for four 10-week quarters. The revised direct cost of studying in UP ITTC, inclusive of training fee miscellaneous and other incidental fees, is PhP 97,350.00 for one year.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Short Courses</st>
<p>

The UP ITTC short courses are modular. The duration of each module can be anywhere from three days to two weeks. These are taken on a part-time basis. See the list of offered courses below.</p>
<p>

o   ASP.NET Programming (Using Visual Basic .NET)
o   Basic 2D Animation
o   Basic 3D Animation Using Maya
o   Basic Web Animation Using Flash
o   Basic Web Development 
o   Better Management of the IT Procurement Process
o   C Programming
o   C++ Programming
o   Cisco Certified Network Associate 1 (CCNA1)
o   Cisco Certified Network Associate 2 (CCNA2)
o   Cisco Certified Network Associate 3 (CCNA3)
o   Cisco Certified Network Associate 4 (CCNA4)
o   Delivery of High Impact Business Presentations
o   Enterprise Resource Planning for Managers
o   Game Development
o   Introduction to C# Programming with Microsoft .NET
o   Introduction to Embedded Systems (Mobots)
o   Introduction to Oracle PL/SQL
o   Introduction to Visual Basic .NET 
o   IP Telephony
o   Java EE
o   Java Programming I (Basic)
o   Java Programming II (Intermediate)
o   Java Programming III (Advanced)
o   Linux System Administration
o   Microsoft Access
o   Microsoft Project
o   Mobile Applications Development Using Java ME
o   Object-Oriented Analysis and Design Using UML
o   PhilNITS FE Exam Review
o   PHP &amp; MySQL 
o   Project Management
o   Risk Assessment and Management of High Value Projects
o   Ruby on Rails
o   Software Engineering and Information Security
o   Structured Cabling
o   Understanding Business Intelligence</p>
<p>

From 2005 to 2007, a total of 1,277 participants attended the short courses—71 in 2005, 435 in 2006, and 771 in 2007. The government, academe, private industry, and NGO sectors were all represented in the mix of participants. The short course CCNA1 garnered the highest number of trainees, with a total of 168 for the year 2007. This 2008, for the first two quarters, the total number of participants is 468.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Partners</st>
<p>

<b>Government</b>
o   Japan International Cooperation Agency (JICA)
o   Japan Foundation
o   Japan External Trade Organization (JETRO Manila)
o   Board of Investments (BOI)
o   Commission on Higher Education (CHED)
o   Commission on Information and Communications Technology (CICT)
o   Department of Science and Technology (DOST)
o   Department of Trade and Industry (DTI)
o   National Economic and Development Authority (NEDA)
o   Philippine National IT Standards Foundation (PhilNITS)</p>
<p>

<b>Industry</b>
o   Association for Overseas Technical Scholarship (AOTS)
o   Center of the International Cooperation for Computerization (CICC)
o   Electronic Industries Association of the Philippines, Inc. (EIAPI)
o   Japanese Chamber of Commerce and Industry of the Philippines, Inc. (JCCIPI)</p>
<p>

<b><university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/190490.xml">
University of the Philippines</link></university>
</b>
o   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/192981.xml">
UP Diliman</link>
o   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/7398946.xml">
UP College of Engineering</link>
o   <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/1999626.xml">
UP Department of Computer Science</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>

o   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/769934.xml">
UP Department of Electrical and Electronics Engineering</link>
o   <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.kssp.upd.edu.ph/linguistics/">
UP Department of Linguistics</weblink>
o   <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ac.upd.edu.ph/">
UP Asian Center</weblink>
o   <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.upd.edu.ph/~cba/">
UP College of Business Administration</weblink>
o   <link>
University of the Philippines, Los Baños</link>
o   <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/5962340.xml">
University of the Philippines, Visayas - Cebu College</link></university>
</p>
<p>

<b>UP SITF</b>
The UP System Information Technology Foundation, Inc. (UP SITF) acts as the resource generation arm of the UP ITTC which includes, but is not limited to, human resource development, infrastructure and equipment, and research and development initiatives. It strengthens industry partnerships and the establishment and management of a scholarship fund. UP ITTC is one of its flagship activities.</p>
<p>

<b>Cooperating organizations</b>
o   Computing Society of the Philippines (CSP)
o   Philippine Society of IT Educators (PSITE)
o   Electronic Industries Association of the Philippines, Inc. (EIAPI)
o   International Electronics and Technical Institute, Inc. (IETI)
o   Philippine Computer Society (PCS)
o   Philippine Software Association (PSIA)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
eGovernment projects</st>
<p>

<b>Buddyworks</b> is a project that seeks to reduce the inequities in the Philippine health care system and help curb the impact of the exodus of health care providers. It uses electronic information and communications technologies to provide and support health care for underserved communities and geographically remote areas where health care expertise is largely unavailable. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

The <b>Philippine eLib</b> is a collaborative project of the National Library of the Philippines (NLP), <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/190490.xml">
University of the Philippines</link></university>
 (UP), Department of Science and Technology (DOST), Department of Agriculture (DA), and the Commission on Higher Education (CHED). It hopes to provide for the information needs of all sectors of society in a convenient, affordable, and efficient way of delivery. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://telehealth.upm.edu.ph/bw/">
Buddyworks</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.elib.gov.ph/">
Philippine eLib</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/190490.xml">
University of the Philippines</link></university>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/192981.xml">
UP Diliman</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/1999626.xml">
UP Department of Computer Science</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/17557096.xml">
Philippine Youth Congress in Information Technology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/16728321.xml">
Philippine Society of Information Technology Educators</link></organization>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <qualification wordnetid="104717139" confidence="0.8">
<fitness wordnetid="104716864" confidence="0.8">
<suitability wordnetid="104715487" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/11777722.xml">
PhilNITS</link></suitability>
</fitness>
</qualification>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://y4it.up.edu.ph">
Y4iT</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ittc.up.edu.ph/ithrd/">
UP ITTC Nihongo Site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://upittc.livejournal.com/">
UP ITTC Official Blog Site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ittc.up.edu.ph/">
UP Information Technology Training Center</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://engg.upd.edu.ph/cs">
UP College of Engineering - Department of Computer Science</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</group>
</educational_institution>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
</article>
