<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:49:27[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Criminal code section 342</title>
<id>18609705</id>
<revision>
<id>229103684</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-31T21:48:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Slysplace</username>
<id>3404724</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All pages needing cleanup</category>
<category>Wikipedia introduction cleanup</category>
<category>Canadian law</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>To comply with Wikipedia's , the introduction of this article may need to be rewritten.</b>
Please discuss this issue on the  and read the to make sure the section will be inclusive of all essential details.</col>
</row>
</table>


<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106667317" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/476776.xml">
Criminal Code of Canada</link></code>
</written_communication>
 Section 342 is stated in part IX which is called 'Offences against Rights of Property'<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. It deals specifically with 'Offences Resembling Theft'. This criminal code is closely related with how <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/341598.xml">
computer crime</link> is defined and handled in <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
.<p>

There are currently four parts of Section 342 of the Criminal Code of Canada:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Section 342 deals with theft, forgery of credit cards.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Section 342.01 deals with Making, having or dealing in instruments for forging or falsifying credit cards.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Section 342.1 deals with Unauthorized use of computer</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Section 342.2 deals with Possession of device to obtain computer service</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Note that the criminal code goes through a lot of amendments and this version might not be the latest version.</p>
<p>

= <b>Definitions and Informations</b> =
</p>
<sec>
<st>
<b>Section 342</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></st>
<p>

Section 342 makes possessing unauthorized credit data and trafficking in credit card passwords an offence. The criminal code states:</p>
<p>

Every person who:
<indent level="1">

(a) steals a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/17182301.xml">
credit card</link>,
</indent>
:(b) forges or falsities a credit card,
<indent level="1">

(c) possesses, uses or traffics in a credit card or a forged or falsified credit card, knowing that it was obtained, made or altered
</indent>
::(i) by the commission in Canada of an offence, or
<indent level="2">

(ii) by an act or omission anywhere that, if it had occurred in <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
, would have constituted an offence, or
</indent>
:(d) uses a credit card knowing that it has been revoked or canceled.</p>
<p>

is guilty of:
<indent level="1">

(e) an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding <b>ten years</b>, or
</indent>
:(f) an offence punishable on summary conviction.</p>
<p>

In this section ‘traffic” means, in relation to a credit card or credit data, to sell, export from or import into Canada, distribute or deal in any other way.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<b>Section 342.01</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></st>
<p>

This section says that any transaction and possession of any instruments that is intended for use in forging or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/11283.xml">
falsifying</link> credit card is illegal. The full definition of this criminal code states:</p>
<p>

Every person who, without lawful justification or excuse,
<indent level="1">

(a) makes or repairs,
</indent>
:(b) buys or sells,
<indent level="1">

(c) <entity wordnetid="100001740" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/307592.xml">
exports</link></entity>
 from or <entity wordnetid="100001740" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/14567.xml">
imports</link></entity>
 into Canada, or
</indent>
:(d) possesses</p>
<p>

any instrument, device, apparatus, material or thing that the person knows has been used or knows is adapted or intended for use in forging or falsifying credit cards</p>
<p>

is guilty of:
<indent level="1">

(e) an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding <b>ten years</b>, or
</indent>
:(f) an offence punishable on summary conviction.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<b>Section 342.1</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></st>
<p>

Unauthorized use of computer is often used to laid charges for hacker or someone who is involved in computer related offences. This section states:</p>
<p>

Every one who, fraudulently and without <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/1109956.xml">
colour of right</link>,
<indent level="1">

(a) obtains, directly or indirectly, any computer service,
</indent>
:(b) by means of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/9532.xml">
electro-magnetic</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/1198.xml">
acoustic</link>, mechanical or other device, intercepts or causes to be intercepted, directly or indirectly, any function of a computer system,
<indent level="1">

(c) uses or causes to be used, directly or indirectly, a computer system with intent to commit an offence under paragraph (a) or (b) or an offence under section 430 in relation to data or a computer system, or
</indent>
:(d) uses, possesses, traffics in or permits another person to have access to a computer password that would enable a person to commit an offence under paragraph (a), (b) or (c)</p>
<p>

is guilty of:
<indent level="1">

(e) an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding <b>ten years</b>, or
</indent>
:(f) an offence punishable on summary conviction.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Additional Information</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “computer password” means any data by which a computer service or computer system is capable of being obtained or used;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “computer program” means data representing instructions or statements that, when executed in a computer system, causes the computer system to perform a function;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “computer service” includes data processing and the storage or retrieval of data;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “computer system” means a device that, or a group of interconnected or related devices one or more of which,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

(a) contains computer programs or other data, and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

(b) pursuant to computer programs,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

(i) performs logic and control, and</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

(ii) may perform any other function;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “data” means representations of information or of concepts that are being prepared or have been prepared in a form suitable for use in a computer system;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “electro-magnetic, acoustic, mechanical or other device” means any device or apparatus that is used or is capable of being used to intercept any function of a computer system, but does not include a hearing aid used to correct subnormal hearing of the user to not better than normal hearing;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “function” includes logic, control, arithmetic, deletion, storage and retrieval and communication or telecommunication to, from or within a computer system;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “intercept” includes listen to or record a function of a computer system, or acquire the substance, meaning or purport thereof;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 “traffic” means, in respect of a computer password, to sell, export from or import into Canada, distribute or deal with in any other way.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<b>Section 342.2</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></st>
<p>

This section says that any transaction and possession of any instruments that is intended for committing offence under section 342.1 is illegal. The full definition of this criminal code states:</p>
<p>

Every person who, without lawful justification or excuse, makes, possesses, sells, offers for sale or distributes any instrument or device or any component thereof, the design of which renders it primarily useful for committing an offence under section 342.1, under circumstances that give rise to a reasonable inference that the instrument, device or component has been used or is or was intended to be used to commit an offence contrary to that section,</p>
<p>

is guilty of:
<indent level="1">

(a) an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding <b>two years</b>, or
</indent>
:(b) an offence punishable on summary conviction.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Related Criminal Code</st>
<p>

The followings are some criminal code sections that are related with section 342 or computer crime in Canada:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Section 430(1.1) which deals with mischief in relation to data.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Section 326(1) which deals with theft of telecommunication service.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Section 327(1) which deals with possession of device to obtain telecommunication facility or service.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/showdoc/cs/C-46/bo-ga:l_IX-gb:s_335//en#anchorbo-ga:l_IX-gb:s_335</entry>
<entry id="2">
http://www.canlii.ca/ca/sta/c-46/sec342.html</entry>
<entry id="3">
http://www.canlii.ca/ca/sta/c-46/sec342.01.html</entry>
<entry id="4">
http://www.canlii.ca/ca/sta/c-46/sec342.1.html</entry>
<entry id="5">
http://www.canlii.ca/ca/sta/c-46/sec342.2.html</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
