<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:57:10[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Odds algorithm</title>
<id>18712065</id>
<revision>
<id>241722544</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-29T07:46:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Alaibot</username>
<id>1324179</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Uncategorized from September 2008</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Uncategorized pages</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<sec>
<st>
Odds-algorithm</st>

<p>

The <b>odds-algorithm</b>  is a mathematical method to compute  optimal
strategies for a class of problems  which  belong to the domain  of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/7189886.xml">
optimal stopping</link>. Its solution determines the <b>odds-strategy</b>, and the importance of the
odds-strategy lies in its optimality, as explained below. </p>
<p>

The odds-algorithm applies to a class of problems called  <b>last-success</b>- problems. Formally the objective is to maximize the probability of identifying in a 
sequence of sequentially observed independent events  a last specific event. This identification must be done on-line, that is, at the time of observation. No recall on preceding observations is permitted. Usually a specific
event is defined by the decision maker as an event which is of true interest to her/him in the view of "stopping"
in order to take
a well-defined action. Such
problems  are encountered  in several
real-world situations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Examples</st>
<p>
 
Two different situations exemplify  the  interest in maximizing the probability to stop on a last specific event.</p>
<p>

1. Suppose a car is advertised for sale (best offer) on the internet.  n  people respond and ask to see the car. They all insist
that they would need the immediate decision whether  their offer is accepted or not. Define an offer <it>interesting</it>, coded <b>1</b> say,  if it is better than all preceding offers, and coded  <b>0</b> otherwise. The offers will form a random sequence of 0's and 1's. Only 1's are of interest to the seller, and with each 1 he/she may fear that there will be no further 1's. It follows from the definition that the very last 1 is the highest offer. Maximizing the probability of selling on the last 1 therefore means maximizing the probability of selling <b>best.</b> </p>
<p>

2. A physician, using a special treatment, may use the code 1
for a successful treatment, 0 otherwise. Treating a sequence of n patients with the same treatment 
he/she wants to minimize unnecessary sufferings, and, at the same time, obtain <b>all </b> successes in the sequence of patients.
Stopping on the last 1 in such a random sequence of 0's and 1's means to realize this objective.  Since
the physician has no prophetical power, his/her objective translates into the goal of finding a strategy maximizing the probability
of stopping on the last 1.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Definitions </st>
<p>

Consider a sequence of n independent events. Associate with this sequence another sequence <math> I_1,\, I_2,\, ... ,\, I_n </math>  with values 1 or 0.   Here  <math> \,I_k =1</math> stands for
the event that the kth observation is interesting (as defined by the decision maker), and <math>\, I_k=0</math> for non-interesting.
Let <math> \,p_k = P( \,I_k\,=1)</math> be the probability that the kth event is interesting. Further let
<math> \,q_k = \,1- p_k </math> and <math> \,r_k = p_k/q_k</math>. Note that 
<math> \,r_k</math> represents the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../069/172069.xml">
odds</link> of the kth event turning out to be interesting, 
explaining the name of the odds-algorithm.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Algorithmic procedure of the odds-algorithm</st>
<p>

The odds-algorithm sums up the odds in reverse order 
<indent level="1">

<math>\,r_n\, + r_{n-1}\,+ r_{n-2}\, + . . .  </math>, 
</indent>
until this sum reaches or exceeds the value 1 for the first time. If this happens at index <math> \,s</math>, it saves <math> \,s</math> and the corresponding sum 
<indent level="1">

<math>\,R_s = \,r_n\, + r_{n-1}\,+ r_{n-2}\, + . . .  +r_s </math>. 
</indent>
If the sum of the odds  does not reach 1, it sets <math> \,s = 1</math>.  At the same time it computes 
<indent level="1">

<math>\,Q_{n}=q_n q_{n-1}... q_s</math>.  The output is
</indent>

a)   <math> \,s </math> (stopping threshold)</p>
<p>

b)   <math>\,w = Q_s R_s  </math> (win probability)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Odds-Strategy</st>
<p>

The odds-strategy is the rule to observe the events one after the other and to stop
on the first interesting event from index <b>s</b> onwards (if any), where <b>s</b> is the stopping threshold of output a).</p>
<p>

The importance of the odds-strategy, and hence of the odds-algorithm, lies in the following Odds-Theorem.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Odds-Theorem </st>
<p>

The Odds-theorem states that </p>
<p>

i)    The odds-strategy is <b>optimal</b>, that is, it maximizes the probability of stopping on the last 1.</p>
<p>

ii)   The win probability of the odds-strategy equals   <math>\,w= Q_s R_s  </math></p>
<p>

iii)  If <math>\, R_s \ge \,1 </math>, the win probability <math>\, w</math> is always at least <math> \,1/e = 0.378...</math>, and this lower bound is <b>best possible.</b></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Features of the Odds-algorithm</st>
<p>

The odds-algorithm computes the optimal <b>strategy</b> and the <b>optimal win probability</b> at the same time. Also, the number of operations of the odds-algorithm is (sub)linear in n. Hence no quicker algorithm can possibly
exist for all sequences, so that the odds-algorithm is, at the same time, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/22402.xml">
optimal</link> as an algorithm. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications</st>
<p>

Applications reach from medical questions in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/241717.xml">
clinical trials</link> over sales problems, <link>
secretary problems</link>, 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/234198.xml">
portfolio</link> selection, (one-way) search strategies, trajectory problems and the <link>
parking problem</link> to problems in on-line <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/41348.xml">
Maintenance</link>
and others.</p>
<p>

There exists, in the same spirit, an Odds-Theorem for continuous-time arrival processes with independent increments such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/102660.xml">
Poisson process</link> (Bruss(2000)). In some cases, the odds are not necessarily
known in advance (as in Example 2 above) so that the application of the odds-algorithm is not directly possible. In this case each step
can use <link>
sequential estimates</link> of the odds. This is meaningful, if the number of unknown parameters is not large compared with the number n of observations. The question of optimality is then more complicated, however, and requires additional studies. 
Generalizations of the odds-algorithm allow for different rewards for failing to stop
and wrong stops as well as replacing independence assumptions by weaker ones (Ferguson (2008))</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/1971750.xml">
secretary problem</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/241717.xml">
clinical trial</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Maintenance,repair and operations</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
House selling  Problem</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Parking problem</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
F. Thomas Bruss </link><it> Sum the Odds to One and Stop</it>, <link>
Annals of Probability</link>  Vol. 28, 1384-1391 (2000).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ---<it> A note on Bounds for the Odds-Theorem of Optimal Stopping</it>, <link>
Annals of Probability</link>  Vol. 31,  1859-1862,  (2003).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ---<it> The art of a right decision.</it>  Newsletter of the <link>
European Mathematical Society </link>, Issue 62, 14-20,  (2006).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
 T.S. Ferguson </link>  (2008, unpublished) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mitsushi Tamaki:<it>Optimal Stopping on Trajectories and the Ballot Problem</it>, <link>
Journal of Applied Probability</link>  Vol.  38, 946-959 (2001).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Shoo-Ren Hsiao and Jiing-Ru. Yang: <it>Selecting the Last Success in Markov-Dependent Trials</it>,  <link>
Journal of Applied Probability</link>,  Vol. 93,  271-281,  (2002.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 B. Iung,  E.  Levrat and  E. Thomas:  <it>Odds-Algorithm - based Opportunistic Maintenance Task Execution for Preserving Product Conditions</it>, <link>
CIRP-Annals</link> Maintenance, Vol. 56, Issue 1, 13-16,  (2007).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style="width: auto;"</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is .</b>
Please  this article to list it with similar articles. <it>(September 2008)</it>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
