<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:02:20[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<procedure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101023820">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Prospective memory</title>
<id>1873056</id>
<revision>
<id>196317049</id>
<timestamp>2008-03-06T17:07:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mattisse</username>
<id>1386816</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Memory processes</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Prospective memory</b> may be defined as remembering to remember (Winograd, 1988) or remembering to perform an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/527474.xml">
intended</link> action. One difference between prospective and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/4415702.xml">
retrospective memory</link> is that instead of recalling past actions, events, or knowledge, prospective <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/18844.xml">
memory</link> is self-initiated and does not operate directly on external stimuli (Einstein &amp; McDaniel, 2000, 2005). Examples of prospective memory include remembering to take certain documents to the office, remembering to call someone at night, and remembering to take a medicine.  Prospective memory consists of recalling an action or an intention triggered by either a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/569399.xml">
stimulus</link> or 'event' or a time. An example of event-based prospective memory, meeting a friend (the cue) might remind you to pass on a message (the intention). A time-based example would be remembering to watch TV at 8pm, recalling a meeting or appointment at a certain time, or to go to a store while it was open.<p>

Event-based prospective memory can be exploited using deliberate acts that will produce a notable event at the time that the memory needs to be recalled such as setting an alarm or placing a shoe in the sink to remind you to take the trash out in the morning. Prospective memory can be enhanced by ordinary acts such as making a grocery list or a to-do list.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Attention </st>
<p>

A current debate is the extent to which prospective memory requires <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/68753.xml">
attentional resources</link> to identify a cue (reminder). That is, prior to meeting the friend to whom you need to pass on the message, are any attentional resources devoted to maintaining this intention? The preparatory and attentional and memory process (PAM) theory (Smith, 2003; Smith &amp; Bayen, 2004) argues that <it>some</it> resources are always necessary. </p>
<p>

In contrast, the multi-process model (McDaniel &amp; Einstein, 2000) argues that a process as important as prospective memory would have a number of underlying mechanisms. According to this model, the properties of the prospective task, the nature of what you are doing at the time, and a number of other variables will influence whether cue identification is automatic or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/13619556.xml">
effortful</link>.</p>
<p>

Relatedly, it has also been argued that it may be how hard you perceive that it will be to identify the cue that mediates how much mental effort is used to monitor for it (Hicks, Marsh &amp; Cook, 2005; Marsh, Hicks &amp; Cook, 2005). Recent studies suggest that effortful monitoring is not always required to identify cues (Hicks, Marsh &amp; Cook, 2005, Einstein et al., 2005). This is consistent with the intuitive experience of an intention spontaneously 'popping' to mind (Meier, Zimmermann &amp; Perrig, 2006).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Footnotes </st>
<p>


</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(February 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Einstein, G. O., McDaniel, M. A., Thomas, R., Mayfield, S., Shank, H., Morrisette, N., et al. (2005). Multiple processes in prospective memory retrieval: Factors determining monitoring versus spontaneous retrieval. <it>Journal of Experimental Psychology: General, 134</it>, 327-342.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hicks, J. L., Marsh, R. L., &amp; Cook, G. I. (2005). Task interference in time-based, event-based, and dual intention prospective memory conditions. <it>Journal of Memory and Language, 53</it>, 430-444.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Marsh, R. L., &amp; Hicks, J. L. (1998). Event-based prospective memory and executive control of working memory. <it>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition, 24</it>, 336-349.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

McDaniel, M. A., &amp; Einstein, G. O. (2000). Strategic and automatic processes in prospective memory retrieval: A multiprocess framework. <it>Applied Cognitive Psychology, 14</it>, S127-S144.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

McDaniel, Mark A., and Einstein, Gilles O. (2007). "Prospective Memory: An Overview and Synthesis of an Emerging Field". Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Meier, B., Zimmermann, T., Perrig, W.J. (2006). Retrieval experience in prospective memory: Strategic monitoring and spontaneous retrieval. <it>Memory, 14</it>, 872-889.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Smith, R. E. (2003). The cost of remembering to remember in event-based prospective memory: Investigating the capacity demands of delayed intention performance. <it>Journal of Experimental Psychology-Learning Memory and Cognition, 29</it>(3), 347-361.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Smith, R. E., &amp; Bayen, U. J. (2004). A multinomial model of event-based prospective memory. <it>Journal of Experimental Psychology-Learning Memory and Cognition, 30</it>(4), 756-777.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Winograd, E. (1988). <it>Some observations on prospective remembering</it>. In M. M. Gruneberg, P. E. Morris &amp; R. N. Sykes (Eds.), Practical Aspects of Memory: Current Research and Issues (Vol. 2, pp. 348-353). Chichester: Wiley.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/4402098.xml">
Aging and memory</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</article>
