<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:11:09[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<university  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108286163">
<college  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108278169">
<educational_institution  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108276342">
<header>
<title>Indian Institute of Information Technology, Allahabad</title>
<id>1875444</id>
<revision>
<id>230147007</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-06T06:45:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Tassedethe</username>
<id>7098284</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Indian Institute of Information Technology</category>
<category>Educational institutions established in 1999</category>
<category>Allahabad</category>
<category>Information technology education</category>
<category>Engineering colleges in Uttar Pradesh</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox University</name>
<parameters>

<image width="125px" src="IIITA.JPG">
<caption>

IIIT Allahabad Logo
</caption>
</image>
<free_label>
About <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/17226194.xml">
IIIT</link></free_label>
<mascot>
Converging of the Rivers Ganga and Yamuna</mascot>
<postgrad>
200</postgrad>
<undergrad>
500</undergrad>
<colors>
Red (Power)</colors>
<state>
<legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/231623.xml">
Uttar Pradesh</link></legal_power>
</state>
<established>
1999</established>
<kjkjk___postgrad_label>
Graduate</kjkjk___postgrad_label>
<type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/56083.xml">
Public</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/9252.xml">
Education</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/25524.xml">
Research</link></type>
<homepage>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iiita.ac.in/">
www.iiita.ac.in</weblink></homepage>
<city>
<site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/10234471.xml">
Allahabad</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</tract>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</site>
</city>
<country>
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
</country>
<free>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://acmserver.cs.ucr.edu/~amitra/iiit/IIITA_about.pdf">
http://acmserver.cs.ucr.edu/~amitra/iiit/IIITA_about.pdf</weblink></free>
<name>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/17226194.xml">
Indian Institute of Information Technology</link>, <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/10234471.xml">
Allahabad</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</tract>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</site>
</name>
<motto>
Pragyanam Brahm</motto>
<head>
Prof. M.D.Tiwari</head>
<faculty>
40</faculty>
<campus>
Urban, A 100-acre (0.40&nbsp;km2) Campus Built on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/548796.xml">
Penrose</link> Geometry and binary <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/17949.xml">
Fibonacci</link></scientist>
</person>
 series depicted on the walls</campus>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

The <b>'Indian Institute of Information Technology, Allahabad</b> (<b>'IIIT-A</b>') was established in 1999, as a center of excellence in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
Information Technology</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link> by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/553883.xml">
Government of India</link>.  The institute was conferred the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/1250676.xml">
Deemed University</link>" status in the year 2000 .  The Institute thus became empowered to have a perpetual seal and award degrees subsequent to the conduct of its own examinations.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Mission </st>

<p>

The Institute has been conceived with the ambitious objectives of developing professional expertise and skilled manpower in Information Technology (IT) and related areas. This will enable the country to exploit efficiently emerging opportunities, and meet economic challenges being thrown up by the rapid global IT revolution, which is influencing virtually every area of development and social activity. As an apex nucleating institute in the area of IT, the establishment of IIIT-A, is a major step of Govt. of India towards strengthening the indigenous capability necessary for exploiting profitably and harnessing multi-dimensional facets of IT at all levels, and attaining expertise to enable the country to emerge as a leading player in the global arena.the institute has also started courses in electronics and communication to be at par in the ICE age. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Campus </st>

<p>

The institute is located on a new campus at Jhalwa, on the outskirts of Allahabad. Some portion of the Nehru Science Center, within the Allahabad University campus, is also on lease.</p>
<p>

The Jhalwa campus includes two Computer Centers with six labs each, 16 lecture halls, electronic library, and a residential campus. An open air theater, stadium and various recreational facilities are under development.</p>
<p>

The NSC complex includes five laboratories, eight computer laboratories, five lecture halls, a conference room, auditorium, library, cafeteria, office space and other facilities. The total covered area is about 25,000&nbsp;sq&nbsp;ft (2,300&nbsp;m2). Besides this, there is an open space of 50,000&nbsp;sq&nbsp;ft (4,600&nbsp;m2). that is used for parking, lawns and sporting activities.</p>
<p>

The new campus has been developed on 100&nbsp;acres (0.40&nbsp;km2) of land at Devghat, Jhalwa, on the outskirts of Allahabad. The architecture aims to transcend established design conventions and make a statement about the similarities between atoms and bits. Instead of the traditional geometric lines, the campus and other buildings have been styled on patterns developed by mathematical physicist, Roger Penrose. </p>
<p>

<b>Residential Campus</b></p>
<p>

The residential campus consists of three men's hostels with capacity for 240 students each, two women's hostels for 60 students, 40-room air-conditioned guest house and staff residences for senior professors and other staff. Faculty hostels with two-room and one-room units meant for visiting professors are also be provided.</p>
<p>

Sports facilities will be located within the main campus, with a 500-seat sports complex.</p>
<p>

This infrastructure is proposed to accommodate the needs of the institute for more than a decade.</p>
<p>

<b>Hostels</b></p>
<p>

There are separate hostels for men and women, with single rooms (for the senior most batches) and twin sharing rooms. The spacious accommodations are provided with computers, along with 24-hour backup power supply. The hostel mess caters to the students' meals. Facilities for recreation and sports like cricket, football, badminton and table tennis are available with more on the way.</p>
<p>

The freshmen batches are housed in another hostel situated in Naini, which can accommodate over 200 students.</p>
<p>

The students have access to a regular bus service from the Jhalwa campus to central Allahabad (the Nehru Science Centre campus). The bus service also covers the Naini and Civil Lines areas.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Academics </st>

<p>

<b>Bachelor of Technology (IT and ECE)</b></p>
<p>

IIITA offers a B.Tech degree in Information Technology and Electronics &amp; Communications Engineering. Entrance to the course from year 2003 is through the All-India exam conducted by CBSE.</p>
<p>

This course is arguably one of the best in the country in the field of information technology and electronics &amp; communications engineering. Its greatest strength is its adaptability to the changing industry requirements. A student here is not only learning the newest technologies, but is also given ample industry exposure. </p>
<p>

Admissions to the four year B.Tech. Program in both the branches (IT &amp; ECE) of the Institute is made through All India Entrance Examination by appropriate bodies, as decided by Govt. of India from time to time. Currently, the examination is conducted by CBSE under the name and style of AIEEE. Official Notification of this examination is given wide publicity through national dailies during September-December every year. Application forms-cum-Brochure are made available throughout the country through various Banks. The examination is scheduled usually in May the following year and held at several centers spread over the entire length and breadth of the country, including J&amp;K and NE states.</p>
<p>

Based upon the merit in the written examination, Central Counseling Board of AIEEE invites candidates for counseling at selected centers, closes to the respective home places of candidates &amp; seats for various participating institutions are allotted, based upon individual merit.</p>
<p>

There are a total of 208 seats out of which 135 are for General category candidates, 27 for SC, 14 for ST while 5 seats are reserved for physically handicapped candidates. Also there are 27 seats available for NRI students.</p>
<p>

Admissions to foreign nationals/ NRI is only admissible against these seats. For this it is mandatory to have qualified SAT-II Examination with a minimum score of 1800, apart from having completed his/ her qualifying degree from abroad.</p>
<p>

<b>Master of Business Administration in Information Technology</b></p>
<p>

The two-year management course at IIIT-A is organized into four semesters. In the first year students gain knowledge on all the disciplines of management with focus on Information Technology through 14 rigorous courses followed by a summer project in the Industry. During the second year students can take up the electives according to there interest in any one of the functional areas of Finance, IT or Marketing. Apart from the 10 courses, their will be two projects. In the 3rd Year the students will study an existing system under the astute guidance of their faculty and finally in the last semester the project asks for constant visits back in the Industry, asking the students to address the industry problems and provide consultancy. All the academic courses require case studies, reports and course projects by students, as programme seeks to develop managers for an integrated understanding of all business functions. The course incorporates flexibility in accordance with the latest practices in the Industry. Overall the rigorous curriculum of the MBA programme has a judicious blend of courses that provide an in-depth understanding of the operational and strategic aspects of managing with Information Technology. </p>
<p>

<b>Master of Technology in Information Technology</b></p>
<p>

IIIT started its M.Tech. programme in July, 2002. At present, there are four M.Tech Programs: -</p>
<p>

1. M.Tech. (Intelligent Systems)                  is.iiita.ac.in
2. M.Tech. (Wireless Communication &amp; Computing)   wcc.iiita.ac.in
3. M.Tech. (Bio Informatics)                      bi.iiita.ac.in
4. M.Tech. (Software Engineering)                 se.iiita.ac.in
5. M.Tech. (Robotics)
6. M.Tech.  (Micro-Eectronics)
7. M.Tech. (Human Computer Intraction)</p>
<p>

Each stream has 20 seats out of which 5 seats are reserved for sponsored candidates from reputed industries. All the M.Tech students (other than sponsored candidates) are admitted on the basis of GATE score and test/interview conducted by the institution. Candidates having GATE score are eligible for a monthly stipend of Rs. 5000 for maximum four semesters.</p>
<p>

<b>Master of Science in Cyber Law and Information Security</b></p>
<p>

IIITA started its 2 year Masters of Science in Cyber Law &amp; Information Security in 2004, in order to meet the latest legal and security issues arising with the rapidly changing technology. Focus is on environmental security measures for e-commerce and foster healthy trade practices. The course is designed to create a true legal technocrates to face the challenges of securing technological implementations in the society.</p>
<p>

<b>Doctoral Programme</b></p>
<p>

Students may enroll in the doctoral programme directly after B.Tech or after M.Tech. The objective of the programme is to promote the development of futuristic IT applications and patentable products, ideas, technologies. The institute intends to contribute to society through these highly qualified students, who have specialized in frontier areas of Information Technology. Research and development is now the focal point of the institute and our stress is on collaborative and interdisciplinary work. We introduce students to a research environment that contains facilities comparable to the best in the world. Some of the areas of interest for the institute are as follows:</p>
<p>

1. Networking, Internet, E- commerce, E-Governance, Web based Education, Content design and delivery</p>
<p>

2. AI, Intelligent/KB systems, Knowledge management, Behavioural modeling, ITS</p>
<p>

3. Industrial Automation – Design, process, production, control, security</p>
<p>

4.Chemical structures and modeling – Chemicals, new materials, polymers, Pharmaceuticals etc.</p>
<p>

5.Bio systems - Genetic modeling, medical informatics, Nano technologies</p>
<p>

6. Modeling and informatics pertaining to economic, financial and social systems</p>
<p>

7. Eco systems, GIS, Environmental modeling, Geo systems and Geophysical systems.</p>
<p>

8. Image processing, Image restoration, Applications to art, crafts, sculpture and architecture</p>
<p>

9. Disaster management</p>
<p>

10.Informatics and computation in Indian languages, Informatics for rural areas,
IT enabled services and IT enabled education</p>
<p>

11. Surveillance and security for industry and defence, safety in general and in
transportation systems in particular</p>
<p>

A substantial portion of the work will be accomplished via simulation and modeling and design and fabrication of products/applications.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Clubs </st>
<p>

<b>INDEM</b></p>
<p>

The INDEM (IIITA Network Development, Engineering and Management) represents the Network and System Admins at IIITA. The INDEM is the meeting point of the innovative technical minds in the institute, apart from academics. INDEM keeps innovating, experimenting and implementing the cutting edge technology at the campus LAN apart from routine maintenance and management of Internet/Intranet services.</p>
<p>

<b>Robita</b></p>
<p>

The robotics club of IIITA encourages students to explore and experiment with robot design, artificial intelligence programming and related areas. Robot fabrication workshops are also conducted.</p>
<p>

<b>Literary Club</b></p>
<p>

Organizes debates, extempores and other literary competitions. It is also responsible for publishing IMHO (in English) and Swacchanda (in Hindi), two magazines for in-campus circulation.</p>
<p>

<b>RangTarangani - Dramatics Club</b></p>
<p>

The dramatics club at IIIT, RangTarangani is responsible for organizing workshops (acting as well as scriptwriting) and holding drama competitions where young talent can be showcased. The club has been active in staging excellent performances both in Hindi and English at various occasions. Innovation- one act play competition is an annual feature of the club.</p>
<p>

<b>Virtuosi - Music Club</b></p>
<p>

The IIITA music club which is a showcase of the musical talent of the institute. The club apart from having a college band has been successful in putting up wonderful performances and also being helpful in letting the student bite the music bug.</p>
<p>

<b>Spirit - Sports Club</b></p>
<p>

The IIITA Sports club brings to you the spirit of life, the spirit of competition, the spirit to win, the spirit to participate and ultimately prove the one within you. We have the energy, the courage and the enthusiasm to bring to you the most lively sports events of IIITA.</p>
<p>

<b>Ushma - Dance Club</b></p>
<p>

Synergy of thought, symphony of movement, artistic expression and a sense of idyllic beauty - this symbolizes the ushma of the dance club.</p>
<p>

<b>Thunderbolt - Audio Lights Club</b></p>
<p>

The institute is proud to have the services of this club, which has been very efficient in managing lights, audio equipment, visual recording of various events staged at IIITA.</p>
<p>

<b>Stambh - Program Management and Publicity Club</b></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Universal Digital Library </st>
<p>

The Campus houses the Universal Digital Library, a branch of the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/209791.xml">
Million Book Project</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
 which would for the first time in history, enable all the significant literary, artistic, and scientific works of mankind can be digitally preserved and made freely available, in every corner of the world, for education, study, and appreciation.</p>
<p>

Up until now, the transmission of our cultural heritage has depended on limited numbers of copies in fragile media.  The fires of Alexandria irrevocably severed our access to any of the works of the ancients. In a thousand years, only a few of the paper documents we have today will survive the ravages of deterioration, loss, and outright destruction.  With no more than 10 million unique book and document editions before the year 1900, and perhaps 100 million since the beginning of recorded history, the task of preservation is much larger.  With new digital technology, though, this task is within the reach of a single concerted effort for the public good, and this effort can be distributed to libraries, museums, and other groups in all countries.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Indo-Russian Center for Biotechnology (IRCB)</st>

<p>

Under the umbrella of Indo-Russian Integrated Long Term Programme (ILTP) in Science &amp; Technology, several joint R &amp; D projects are being implemented. Russian institutions have been offering technologies for commercialisation in India. Similarly, Indian side has been offering technologies developed in India for validation and commercialisation in Russia. Technology transfer activities in engineering materials, electronics, laser science and technology, catalysis, space science and technology has been significant.</p>
<p>

Biotechnology over the years has emerged as a frontline area of mutual interest and benefit amongst the two countries. While deliberating on these issues, the sub-working group on biotechnology in its meeting held on 8th December, 1999 endorsed the view of the ILTP joint council that there is a need to establish a joint Indo-Russian centre for biotechnology (IRCB) as centres of excellence with a clear objective on networking and co-ordinating various activities under Indo-Russian collaboration in biotechnology. The Sub-Working group on biotechnology during its third meeting in June, 2000 in Moscow also strongly recommended the proposal. Prof. MM Joshi, the Minister for Science and Technology announced it formally during his visit to Russia in July, 2000.</p>
<p>

The agreement for establishment of this centre was formally concluded on 5th November 2001 in Moscow during the visit of the Indian Prime Minister to Russia between the Department of Science &amp; Technology on the Indian side and the Russian Academy of Sciences on the Russian side.</p>
<p>

The centre was inaugurated by Prof. MM Joshi at Allahabad on 23rd December 2001. </p>
<p>

The First project at this center is the <link>
HCRPDB</link>, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
Database</link> Retrieval &amp; Mining System for Human Cell <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../480/569480.xml">
Receptors</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
Proteins</link>.  HCRPDB has been designed to generate information for structure based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/180121.xml">
drug</link> design on cell receptors proteins and allows retrieval of protein sequence related information.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
IIITA's extension Campus at <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/664005.xml">
Amethi</link></legal_power>
</st>

<p>

IIITA has an extension campus at <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/664005.xml">
Amethi</link></legal_power>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/2336743.xml">
Sultanpur District</link>, Uttar Pradesh,  Rajiv Gandhi Institute of Information Technology. <politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/305010.xml">
Rahul Gandhi</link></politician>
, MP from the Amethi <parliament wordnetid="108319198" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/275456.xml">
Lok Sabha</link></parliament>
 Constituency, laid the foundation stone for the new extension centre of IIIT-Allahabad at Amethi on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/1862.xml">
April 14</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>.  It shall serve to enable deep penetration of Information Technology and allied education domains into India's sub-urban and rural areas.  The project is likely to cost about Rs 35 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/121420.xml">
crore</link>, although final details are yet to be worked out.  To start with, the extension center shall offer B Tech in information technology and the student strength is likely to be 60 in the first year along with six faculty members.</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iiita.ac.in/">
IIIT Allahabad website</weblink>  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://effervescence.iiita.ac.in/">
Effervescence, Cultural Festival of IIIT</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://trinetra.iiita.ac.in/">
IIITA Webcasting Service</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://udl.iiita.ac.in/">
Universal Digital Library (UDL)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ircb.iiita.ac.in/">
Indo-Russian Center for Biotechnology (IRCB)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/17226194.xml">
IIIT</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Institutes</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/1110951.xml">
International Institute of Information Technology, Hyderabad</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/6729199.xml">
Indian Institute of Information Technology and Management, Gwalior</link>&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/1875444.xml">
Indian Institute of Information Technology, Allahabad</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/5454763.xml">
WBUT</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/11641622.xml">
Indian Institute of Information Technology, Bhubaneswar</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/4691807.xml">
Indian Institute of Information Technology and Management, Thiruvananthapuram</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/11683699.xml">
Indian Institute of Information Technology Design and Manufacturing, Jabalpur</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Admissions</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/2412401.xml">
AIEEE</link>&nbsp;·  <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/3530241.xml">
Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
&nbsp;·  <link>
Policy of Reservation</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</educational_institution>
</college>
</university>
</article>
