<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:04:33[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104377057">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Geocoding</title>
<id>1876018</id>
<revision>
<id>242149555</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T02:48:33Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Zingi</username>
<id>172088</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Geocodes</category>
<category>Geographic information systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/2014678.xml">
Geocoding (disambiguation)</link>.<p>

<b>Geocoding</b> is the process of finding associated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/48361.xml">
geographic coordinates</link> (often expressed as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/17616.xml">
latitude</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/17617.xml">
longitude</link>) from other geographic data, such as <link>
street addresses</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/51550.xml">
zip codes</link>.  With geographic coordinates the features can be mapped and entered into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
Geographic Information Systems</link>, or the coordinates can be embedded into media such as digital photographs via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/1870398.xml">
geotagging</link>.</p>
<p>

Reverse Geocoding is the opposite: finding an associated textual location such as a street address, from geographic coordinates.</p>
<p>

A <b>geocoder</b> is a piece of software or a (web) service that helps in this process.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Address interpolation</st>
<p>

A simple method of geocoding is address <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/14569.xml">
interpolation</link>.  This method makes use of data from a street <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
geographic information system</link> where the street network is already mapped within the geographic coordinate space.  Each street segment is attributed with address ranges (e.g. house numbers from one segment to the next).  Geocoding takes an address, matches it to a street and specific segment (such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/948686.xml">
block</link>, in towns that use the "block" convention).  Geocoding then interpolates the position of the address, within the range along the segment.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Example</st>
<p>

Take for example: <it><location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/3038969.xml">
742 Evergreen Terrace</link></location>
</it></p>
<p>

Let's say that this segment (for instance, a block) of Evergreen Terrace runs from 700 to 799.  Even-numbered addresses would fall on one side (e.g. west side) of Evergreen Terrace, with odd-numbered addresses on the other side (e.g. east side).  742 Evergreen Terrace would (probably) be located slightly less than halfway up the block, on the west side of the street.  A point would be mapped at that location along the street, perhaps offset some distance to the west of the street centerline.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Complicating factors</st>
<p>

However, this process is not always as straightforward as in this example.</p>
<p>

Difficulties arise when:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Distinguishing between ambiguous addresses such as 742 Evergreen Terrace and 742 W Evergreen Terrace.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Geocoding new addresses for a street that is not yet added to the geographic information system database.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

While there might be 742 Evergreen Terrace in Springfield, there might also be a 742 Evergreen Terrace in Shelbyville.  Asking for the city name (and state, province, country, etc. as needed) can solve this problem.  Some situations require use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/51549.xml">
postal code</link>s or district name for disambiguation.  For example, there are multiple 100 Washington Streets in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/3775.xml">
Boston</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1645518.xml">
Massachusetts</link></country>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> because several cities have been annexed without changing street names.</p>
<p>

Finally, several caveats on using interpolation.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The typical attribution of a street segment assumes that all "even" numbered parcels are on one side of the segment, and all "odd" numbered parcels are on the other. This is often not true in real life.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Interpolation assumes that the given parcels are evenly distributed along the length of the segment. This is almost never true in real life; it is not uncommon for a geocoded address to be off by several thousand feet.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Segment Information (esp. from sources such as TIGER) includes a maximum upper bound for addresses and is interpolated as though the full address range is used.  For example, a segment (block) might have a listed range of 100-199, but the last address at the end of the block is 110.  In this case, address 110 would be geocoded to 10% of the distance down the segment rather than near the end.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Most interpolation implementations will produce a point as their resulting "address" location. In reality, the physical address is distributed along the length of the segment, i.e. consider geocoding the address of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/235723.xml">
shopping mall</link> - the physical lot may run quite some distance along the street segment (or could be thought of as a two-dimensional space-filling polygon which may front on several different streets - or worse, for cities with multi-level streets, a three-dimensional shape that meets different streets at several different levels) but the interpolation treats it as a singularity.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A very common error is to believe the accuracy ratings of a given map's geocodable attributes. Such "accuracy" currently touted by most vendors has no bearing on an address being attributed to the correct segment, being attributed to the correct "side" of the segment, nor resulting in an accurate position along that correct segment.  With the geocoding process used for <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<statistic wordnetid="106021499" confidence="0.8">
<census wordnetid="100653388" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<count wordnetid="100634586" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<demographic wordnetid="106022076" confidence="0.8">
<datum wordnetid="105816622" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/447689.xml">
U.S. Census</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</datum>
</demographic>
</investigation>
</event>
</count>
</information>
</census>
</statistic>
</work>
 TIGER datasets, 5-7.5% of the addresses may be allocated to a different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/105254.xml">
census tract</link>, while 50% of the geocoded points might be located to a different property parcel. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Because of this, it is quite important to avoid using interpolated results except for non-critical applications, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/1668848.xml">
pizza delivery</link>. Interpolated geocoding is usually not appropriate for making authoritative decisions, for example if life safety will be impacted by that decision.  Emergency services, for example, do not make an authoritative decision based on their interpolations; an ambulance or fire truck will always be dispatched regardless of what the map says.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Other techniques</st>
<p>

Other means of geocoding might include locating a point at the centroid (center) of a land parcel, if parcel (property) data is available in the geographic information system database.  In rural areas or other places lacking high quality street network data and addressing, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
GPS</link> is useful for mapping a location.  For traffic accidents, geocoding to a street intersection or midpoint along a street centerline is a suitable technique.  Most highways in developed countries have <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/285728.xml">
mile markers</link> to aid in emergency response, maintenance, and navigation.  It is also possible to use a combination of these geocoding techniques - using a particular technique for certain cases and situations and other techniques for other cases.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Uses</st>
<p>

Geocoded locations are useful in many GIS analysis and cartography tasks.</p>
<p>

Geocoding is common on the web, for services like finding driving directions to or from some address, or finding a list of the geographically nearest store or service locations.</p>
<p>

Geocoding is one of several methods of obtaining geographic coordinates for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/1870398.xml">
geotagging</link> media, such as photographs or <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/93489.xml">
RSS</link></format>
 items.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Privacy concerns</st>
<p>

The proliferation and ease of access to geocoding (and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Reverse_geocoding%22])">
reverse-geocoding</link>) services raises privacy concerns.  For example, in mapping crime incidents, law enforcement agencies aim to balance the privacy rights of victims and offenders, with the public's right to know.  Law enforcement agencies have experimented with alternative geocoding techniques that allow them to mask some of the locational detail (e.g., address specifics that would lead to identifying a victim or offender).  As well, in providing online <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/1386551.xml">
crime mapping</link> to the public, they also place disclaimers regarding the locational accuracy of points on the map, acknowledging these location masking techniques, and impose terms of use for the information.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/1870398.xml">
Geotagging</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/2208016.xml">
Geolocation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/1436748.xml">
Geocoded photo</link>, which includes methods of geocoding images</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/7403047.xml">
C-squares</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 and <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/2245722.xml">
QDGC</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
, geocoding methods for statistical mapping (marine life, avian populations, humans, etc)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://local.google.com/maps?q=100+Washington+Street%2C+Boston">
Google Maps</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ratcliffe, Jerry H.&#32;(2001).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jratcliffe.net/papers/Ratcliffe%20(2001)%20On%20the%20accuracy%20of%20TIGER-type%20geocoding.pdf">
On the accuracy of TIGER-type geocoded address data in relation to cadastral and census areal units</weblink>". <it>International Journal of Geographic Information Sciences</it>&#32;<b>15</b>&#32;(5).</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://earth-info.nga.mil/gns/html/">
GEOnet Names Server</weblink> - Freely available GIS information for areas outside of the U.S.A. and Antarctica, updated monthly by the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA) and the U.S. Board on Geographic Names (US BGN)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://geonames.usgs.gov/">
Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</weblink> - Freely available database containing information on almost 2 million physical features, places, and landmarks in the U.S.A.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://geobase.ca/">
Geobase</weblink> - Free geospatial data for Canada, including administrative boundaries, digital elevation data, geodetic network, data alignment layer, geographical names, and national road network</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.directionsmag.com/article.php?article_id=670&amp;trv=1">
Three Standard Geocoding Methods</weblink> (in North America) - article</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.directionsmag.com/article.php?article_id=2492&amp;trv=1">
The Evolution of Geocoding: Moving Away from Conflation Confliction to Best Match</weblink> - article</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geoinfo.info/geoinfo2003/papers/geoinfo2003-25.pdf">
A Flexible Addressing System for Approximate Geocoding</weblink> - paper presented at Geoinfo 2003</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geocoder.com.ar/geocoder/en/">
Geocoder.com.ar</weblink> (in Argentina) - Free geographical information about Argentina, like latitude and longitude of an address, a place or feature, using XML in response to HTTP GET invocation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

[https://webgis.usc.edu USC Gecoder] Free US geocoding with multiple reference data sources. Processes uploaded databases (access, csv, text delimited) and single addresses.</entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</article>
