<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:54:26[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Project Mutual Telephone</title>
<id>18958507</id>
<revision>
<id>241735560</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-29T09:40:44Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Alaibot</username>
<id>1324179</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Uncategorized from September 2008</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Uncategorized pages</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

Project Mutual Telephone Company has provided continuous telephone service in the Mini-Cassia area  in Idaho  since 1916. When PMT was organized with 34 telephone customers, it based its future on providing quality service to its members. In 1956, PMT installed its first local direct dial telephone system. The system served approximately 1,700 customers and was state-of-the-art technology for the time. In 1962 direct dial long distance was added. The 70’s and 80’s produced continued growth for PMT, the information age was in full swing and again PMT responded by adding updated technologies; the first digital central office in Idaho, fiber optic cable and expanded features were added for continued member satisfaction. By the end of 1983, all of PMT’s systems were interconnected through a completely digital network.<p>

In the late 90’s, service was expanded into Burley, Oakley and Heyburn. Today, PMT is a full service communication company, providing local and long distance telephone service, dial up, high speed DSL and wireless internet as well as cable television and IPTV. In 2004, PMT expanded its network into Twin Falls, and now serves several anchor businesses in the area and several residential customers on the canyon rim. PMT proudly added Syringa Wireless as a cellular partner in 2006.</p>
<p>

Today PMT serves over 12,000 members throughout the Magic Valley in Idaho and employs 75 full-time employees</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style="width: auto;"</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is .</b>
Please  this article to list it with similar articles. <it>(September 2008)</it>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
</bdy>
</article>
