<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:09:36[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108058098">
<header>
<title>NokVAULT</title>
<id>18987775</id>
<revision>
<id>239874557</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-20T22:27:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>JLaTondre</username>
<id>394292</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cryptographic software</category>
<category>Software companies of Canada</category>
<category>Free security software</category>
<category>Security software companies</category>
<category>Disk encryption</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Software</name>
<parameters>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nokvault.com">
nokVAULT.com</weblink></website>
<operating_system>
<version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/33879.xml">
Windows XP</link></version>
, <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
</operating_system>
<size>
5.3 MB</size>
<developer>
nokVAULT Corp.</developer>
<name>
nokVAULT</name>
<programming_language>
<programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/6021.xml">
C</link></programming_language>
,<programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/72038.xml">
C++</link></programming_language>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/466448.xml">
Assembler</link></programming_language>
<latest_release_date>
June 30, 2008</latest_release_date>
<language>
English, Portuguese</language>
<license>
nokVAULT <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/49764.xml">
EULA</link></license>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>nokVAULT</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/454746.xml">
software application</link> designed as a personal electronic safe and file <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> tool for protecting and hiding sensitive and confidential computer data, files, and programs. 

<p>

According to the company website <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nokvault.com">
nokvault.com</weblink>, the software’s proprietary operating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/50394.xml">
Kernel (computer science)</link> and installation-unique file system creates an encrypted “file vault” independent of the computer’s host <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>. nokVAULT employs anti-reverse-engineering techniques and application memory buffer encryption to obstruct attempts to compromise the protected files within the vault, and makes encrypted data resistant to unauthorized scanning utilities, hackers and  forensic tools.</p>
<p>

A unique feature is dynamic on-the-fly <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/7160942.xml">
Filesystem-level encryption</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 and decryption that automatically retains the original security settings of files after use or modification. The feature avoids the need to decrypt and encrypt with every use, and also enables on-the-fly file decryption of entire software applications and file directories for immediate utilization.</p>
<p>

nokVAULT offers users a choice of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/1562888.xml">
AES</link> (Advanced Encryption Standard) with up to 256-bit key size, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/23576.xml">
Blowfish</link> encryption with up to 512-bit key size. The nokVAULT File Encryption software includes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/912934.xml">
on-the-fly encryption</link> feature, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/631063.xml">
key management</link> system to help users keep track of the encryption keys associated with various files, and a secure erase feature that permanently deletes files and any linked traces to files to make then unrecoverable by any recovery tool or utility. Compatible with 32-bit versions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/33879.xml">
Microsoft Windows XP</link> and <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
 operating systems, nokVAULT is an Internet-distributed licensed product also available in a full-featured free trial version.</p>

<p>

<table style="clear: left; margin-bottom: .5em; float: left; padding: .5em 1.4em .8em 0; background: none; width: auto;" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>
__TOC__</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Security Kernel </st>
<p>

The nokVAULT software is based on the company’s proprietary nokKERNEL foundation technology, a parallel kernel that coexists with the host operating system. The company claims having the nokKERNEL installed parallel to the operating system during the reboot process instead of running on the host operating system is a major security advantage, maintaining that the independent kernel is less vulnerable to attacks, and avoids inheriting security flaws associated with the host operating system.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Dynamic Encryption Algorithms </st>
<p>

nokVAULT supports two encryption methods of encryption, the first using proprietary dynamic encryption and second using known non-proprietary encryption <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/5244.xml">
ciphers</link>: AES, and Blowfish. Encrypting a file in-place secures the file contents, and disables any unauthorized accessibility to the file. Encrypted in-place files will remain visible as files located within the host operating system, but cannot be accessed or opened without a key. Adding a file to the secure-area vault will automatically encrypt the file, and make it invisible to the host operating system when the vault is closed. </p>
<p>

Using proprietary dynamic algorithm generators, <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> nokVAULT renders the secure-area vault undetectable by anyone using the computer. nokVAULT-protected files are accessible only with the encryption key password or the unique nokVAULT product license password. The company states that nokVAULT has no “back door” password access, and that operating system or computer hardware administrative privileges or security policies applied to files grant no access to nokVAULT-protected files. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Out of Operating System Secure Storage </st>
<p>

nokVAULT uses an out of OS secure file system and kernel to handle dynamic encryption algorithm generation, file encryption and file decryption procedures. All files located within nokVAULT’s secure-area vault are invisible, inaccessible, and untraceable to users, operating system administrators, and computer super-users.  The result is a File Encryption solution that hides files where no intruder or hacker can see them. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Operation </st>
<p>

Using a Microsoft Windows drag-and-drop user interface, the nokVAULT application enables persistent encryption of files located anywhere in computer folders, disks and removable devices, with encrypted data and files remaining secure wherever they reside until accessed with specific designated key policy. nokVAULT’s installation-unique encrypted file system creates a secure-area “vault” that cannot be accessed or detected by the host operating system or hard drive utilities. </p>
<p>

nokVAULT offers a key management system to create, organize, and manage many different encryption settings and key policies. An encryption setting can be constant for all encrypted files, or can be changed for each file encrypted, functionality useful for exporting encrypted files and sharing keys with other people. nokVAULT’s key management system enables viewing all keys created, and the associated files secured using a specific key policy. </p>
<p>

nokVAULT can be configured to automatically close and secure the vault after a designated period of user inactivity, when the computer is idle, or when the computer enters sleep modes, hibernation, or shutdown.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>


<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Crypto_key.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Cryptography&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/2285143.xml">
Cryptographic software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/50394.xml">
Kernel (computer science)</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/2285143.xml">
Encryption software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/15036.xml">
Information security</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Brent MacLean, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jbm.net/pages.asp?pgidx=86&amp;menu=Dynamic%20file%20encryption">
http://www.jbm.net</weblink> . June 21, 2008 "DYNAMIC FILE ENCRYPTION". Retrieved on 2008-08-27.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</company>
</article>
