<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:07:49[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Networksims</title>
<id>18988905</id>
<revision>
<id>243192099</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T15:10:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Miss Madeline</username>
<id>172769</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>
<p>

NetworkSims is a Cisco simulator which supports a wide range of Cisco products, Cisco router, Cisco switch, Cisco PIX/ASA and Cisco wireless. It has various topologies, and fault-finding challenges, along with fun activities. The Web link is at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://networksims.com">
NetworkSims</weblink>. It covers a wide range of devices, and includes on-line tests. It has been rated as a useful simulator for teaching CCNP <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.proprofs.com/forums/index.php?s=5ee3e30fb7230bbbd12e161b2f07058a&amp;showtopic=18329&amp;pid=83747&amp;st=0&amp;#entry83747">
CCNP</weblink>, and is seen as being a safe study site from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.certguard.com/search.asp?Site=networksims.com">
CertGuard</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

The simulator was developed by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://buchananweb.co.uk">
Prof Bill Buchanan</weblink> and originally named Network-emulators, with a Web site address of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://network-emulators.com">
network-emulators.com</weblink>. It has been developed within the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdcs.soc.napier.ac.uk">
Centre for Distributed Computing and Security</weblink> in the School of Computing at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Napier_University">
Napier University</weblink>. Originally it used Flash, but has since evolved using the Microsoft .NET framework.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Certification Areas</st>
<p>

The focus of the simulator package is on Cisco certifications including CCNA, CCSP, CCVP, Wireless, and MPLS. There is a good deal of debate on the usage of simulators (such as Boson and NetworkSims) and the usage of emulators (such as Dynamips). At present the emulators give good experience of real-life hardware, but do not quite have the fine-grained assessment of the NetworkSim simulator <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sadikhov.com/forum/index.php?showtopic=111052">
Debate</weblink>. It thus looks like there's a place for the two types, to give broad coverage in networking teaching.</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
