<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:01:40[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>NPAD</title>
<id>19064419</id>
<revision>
<id>237748141</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-11T17:17:07Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ewaukau</username>
<id>6607136</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>NPAD</b> is the Network Path and Application Diagnosis project, which provides free software that analyzes the performance of end-to-end computer network paths.  NPAD is typically used to determine why performance is poor along a given path through a computer network. <p>

To use NPAD, one has to direct a web browser to one of the "NPAD Diagnostic Servers". This causes a client applet to start on the local computer. The client applet will then ask the user for some desired performance parameters and test the <link>
TCP</link> performance of the network path between the client and the NPAD diagnostic server.  The result is a report that shows the measurements collected during the test and a pass/fail analysis of the measurements. If the quality of the path is too low to support the desired performance parameters, the report will give the path a failing grade.  Each time a test is run, a new report is created and stored on the NPAD server in the form of a web page.  Each report contains links to "help pages" that describe the meaning of measurements and the algorithms used to analyze them. </p>
<p>

The NPAD server uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/19064652.xml">
Web100</link> to measure the attributes of the <link>
TCP</link> path to the client.  NPAD software was developed with support from the National Science Foundation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://www.nsf.gov/</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mid-Atlantic Crossroads - http://maxgigapop.net</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pittburgh Supercomputing Centers - http://www.psc.edu/networking/projects/pathdiag/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

National Science Foundation - http://www.nsf.gov</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Web100 - http://web100.com</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External link</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.psc.edu/networking/projects/pathdiag/">
NPAD diagnose tool</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
