<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:14:16[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Construction Photography</title>
<id>19075182</id>
<revision>
<id>243945462</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T18:08:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jamavr</username>
<id>8015086</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Stock_photography</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from September 2008</category>
<category>Wikify from September 2008</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Company</name>
<parameters>
<type>
Private</type>
<name>
Construction Photography</name>
<foundation>
2001</foundation>
<industry>
<link>
 Stock Photography</link>, Video Production, Media Management</industry>
<location_country>
<autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link>
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
</location_country>
<location_city>
<link>
 London</link></location_city>
<homepage>
http://www.constructionphotography.com</homepage>
<key_people>
Jean-Francois Cardella (founder + MD)Lucy Moore (CFO)</key_people>
</parameters>
</template>


<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article needs more   to meet Wikipedia's . </b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Construction_Photography&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink>by adding useful internal links. (September 2008)</col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Construction_Photography&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Construction+Photography%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



<p>

<b>Construction Photography</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/731773.xml">
photo library</link> and agency based in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/17867.xml">
London</link></village>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1048927.xml">
UK</link>. It was established in 2001 by talented photographers with accolades such as  <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<depository wordnetid="103177349" confidence="0.8">
<museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/2256616.xml">
World Press Photo</link></museum>
</depository>
</facility>
</artifact>
 award to provide the construction and built environment industries an affordable and independent alternative to established multinational agencies such as <link>
Getty images</link> and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/483624.xml">
Corbis</link></company>
. The company has positioned itself within the creative production sector and online stock image market by identifying a “global niche market” opportunity, creating a one-stop shop to the built environment worldwide.</p>
<p>

Using innovative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/925719.xml">
Digital asset management</link> software technology Construction Photography delivers creative content over the internet with a secure streamlined online work flow to major players such as government organizations (<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/31145.xml">
Transport for London</link></company>
, <control wordnetid="105196375" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="105196582" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<executive_agency wordnetid="108123696" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/966144.xml">
Highways Agency</link></administration>
</executive_agency>
</group>
</agency>
</power>
</administrative_unit>
</social_group>
</authority>
</body>
</control>
, ConstructionSkills <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/6896179.xml">
Waste &amp; Resources Action Programme</link></institution>
</administration>
</group>
</company>
</social_group>
</body>
 as well as multinational corporations such as <link>
Vinci Plc</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/1690139.xml">
Lafarge</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/1734843.xml">
Compass Group</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/2211521.xml">
Corus Group</link></company>
, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gardiner.com">
Gardiner &amp; Theobald</weblink>, Murphy Group.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> etc).</p>
<p>

Construction Photography is the largest supplier of assignment images for the construction industry worldwide managing over 1 million images across all its client base. It has a stock collection of over 100,000 built environment related images of which 30,000 are available online and a roster of 170 elite assignment photographers operating from 15 countries.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Photography and video might seem to be a peripheral activity in the construction industry, but in today’s business environment, image and communication is of vital importance. The traditional photo and video agencies have generally neglected the construction industry, seeing it as unglamorous and destined for the high street photographer.  On the other hand, Construction Photography has demonstrated how vibrant and visually rewarding this industry can be. They have quickly acquired a portfolio of clients amongst the major world players. For the first time the Industry could rely on a trusted specialist both in imaging and the processes surrounding it. Over and above the knowledge of the industry, the creativity and reliability, the agency’s success is also due to ShootTracker® an innovative streamlined online workflow which helps corporations to commission and brief photographers, edit images online, distribute to the media within minutes after a shoot, and archive and maintain the images for multi-use and legacy.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Line of business and skills</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Image licensing and search </st>
<p>

The library license Rights Managed and Royalty Free images from a number of content providers, photographers, agencies, museums and libraries around the world. In 2007 Construction Photography signed an agreement with the Russian state news agency <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/5178882.xml">
Ria novosti</link> to represent its built environment content worldwide <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. In March 2005 Construction Photography launched a new generation of search engine including a feature called “Image Weight”. The search results are primarily ordered by image weight. Images increase in weight when users add them to a lightbox or a cart or open an image preview or large preview. Each action has a different weight. Images also decrease in weight when they are removed from a lightbox or from the cart etc. A complex algorithm calculates in real time all these parameters to give each image a constant updated weight. Also included in this complex algorithm were the upload date and the keyword relevance to the search. Commercial libraries have the constant dilemma of how to return images to their users, search results order relying mostly on the choice of editors based on their knowledge and experience. This proved a very subjective approach and a time consuming effort for the administrators of the website, ranking images manually and updating the ranking order on a daily basis with new content being uploaded. With Construction Photography's Image Weight system, customers have a direct influence over the image results as most relevant and popular images are returned first. The process is fully automated providing not only a sound sales strategy but a fair decision for all the agency contributors. In 2007 Construction Photography has launch some further improvement to its "Image Weight" system with the ability for their editors to overwrite weighting on a batch or on single image in order to promote quickly new content, exclusive imagery or simply outstanding visual content. Royalty Free and Rights Managed images can have different weight algorithm depending on sales strategy.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Photo assignments </st>
<p>

The agency produces imagery for most industries within the built environment: construction, engineering, architecture, property development and house building, machinery, rail and energy. Their ground breaking workflow allows clients to order shoots and edit them online with images uploaded on editing galleries within minutes after a shoot. Skills includes:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 360 Virtual Tours</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Aerial</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Architecture</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Creative &amp; Lifestyle</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Progress Legal photography</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mast photography</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Portraiture</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 PR &amp; Press photo call</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Still life &amp; Products</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Time Lapse</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Webcam</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Video production </st>
<p>

The agency focuses on broadcast quality content, media products and services for business-to-business, business-to-customer and business-to-employee communications.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Promotional Film</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Short clips for Tender submissions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Training and Health and Safety videos</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Events and Launches</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Internal communications</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Aerial footage</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Time Lapse videos</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Media management </st>
<p>

Construction Photography is the exclusive distributor of The Data Archive media management software <it>(The Data Archive is the parent company of Construction Photography)</it>. The web based digital assets management software helps companies within the built environment to manage their media content over the internet including photographs, videos, any type of media files or documents. The secure service also includes hosting, metadata management and data migration.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health and safety certifications</st>
<p>

Photography for the construction industry requires some very specific technical knowledge from the photographers and cameramen as well as a number of critical awareness of Health and Safety requirements. These regulations have dictated in many ways how photographers can access and work on site. Some photographers have stated on occasions that ever increasing Health and Safety regulations can reduce the photographer’s creativity with some images although perfectly adequate being rejected by Construction Photography’s editors for non-compliance to health and safety regulations. Experienced site photographers have the additional challenge to create powerful images bearing in mind technical issues such as telephoto lens compression or wide angles distorting the reality and making great images un-usable from a corporate perspective.   </p>
<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chas.gov.uk">
Contractor Health and Safety Assessment Scheme</weblink> (CHAS) is a government body which gives accreditation to companies that meet the UK standards in areas such as technical ability, equalities, insurance cover, environment and health and safety. After 3700 assignments Construction Photography has been awarded a CHAS accreditation in 2007.</p>
<p>

Other accreditations include:
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/5116656.xml">
Personal Track Safety</link> cards for photographers and cameramen working on live rail.
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cscs.uk.com/RunScript.asp?p=ASP\Pg0.asp">
CSCS</weblink> cards acting as proof of occupational competence by all personnel getting access on site, contractors, public and private clients and others. They cover hundreds of occupations from bricklayers to Senior Management.
BOS card required for work within the oil industry i.e.: offshore oil rigs</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Awards</st>
<p>

Construction Photography was a finalist for the 2007 Construction Industry IT Awards <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> organised by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.contractjournal.com">
Contract Journal</weblink> the UK weekly magazine for the construction industry published by <link>
 RBI</link> (Reed Business Information). The agency was a finalist again for the Quality in Construction 2008 Awards <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> organised by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnplus.co.uk">
Construction News</weblink> the other main weekly magazine published by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emapconstructionnetwork.co.uk">
Emap Construct</weblink> for Excellence in use of ICT.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Industry membership</st>
<p>

Construction Photography is an accredited member of BAPLA <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> the British Association of Picture Libraries and Agencies. BAPLA is the UK trade association with over 400 member companies. It represents the vast majority of commercial picture libraries and agencies in the UK.  </p>
<p>

In 2005 Construction Photography joined <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cepic.org/english/members/membersearch.php#">
CEPIC</weblink>, the Coordination of European Picture Agencies Press Stock Heritage, which was established in Berlin in 1993 as a European economic interest group. CEPIC represents over 900 picture sources in Europe with members from seventeen different European countries. The aim of CEPIC is to be a united voice for the picture library and agency associations of Europe.</p>
<p>

The agency is also a member of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.useplus.com">
The Picture Licensing Universal System</weblink> (PLUS), a worldwide Coalition of leading companies, associations, and industry experts who have joined this unprecedented non-profit mandate to clearly define and standardize the core aspects of image licensing and its management. PLUS will make every license simpler, more transparent, more secure, and of greater value for everyone on every side of the process.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cskillsimagelibrary.co.uk/news.asp?id=3">
ConstructionSkills</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.murphygroupimages.co.uk/news.asp?id=2">
Murphy Group</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.constructionphotography.com/newsletters/newsletter.asp?view=10">
Ria Novosti distribution press release</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stockindexonline.com/index.php?q=IndustryNews&amp;id_new=1976">
Stock Index Online</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rbicreativeservices.com/cjou/cj_awards07_www/finalists_2007.htm">
Construction Industry IT Awards</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.qicawards.com/2008Winners.asp?m_pid=0&amp;m_nid=28124">
Quality in Construction 2008 Awards</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bapla.org.uk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=47&amp;Itemid=90&amp;favm=87">
BAPLA</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.constructionphotography.com/Default.aspx">
Construction Photography website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
