<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:02:57[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Alaska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission</title>
<id>19111438</id>
<revision>
<id>240553352</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-23T22:51:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Quidam65</username>
<id>507227</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Government of Alaska</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Alaska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission</b> (AOGCC) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/2847102.xml">
quasi-judicial</link> agency in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
U.S.</link> state of <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/624.xml">
Alaska</link></symbol>
, within Alaska's Department of Administration.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> It was originally established in 1955, was subsequently abolished, but was eventually reestablished. This Commission is responsible for overseeing oil and gas drilling and production, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/3292675.xml">
reservoir</link> depletion, and certain other operations on private and state-owned lands in Alaska.
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

A territorial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/26783.xml">
statute</link> created the Alaska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission in 1955, before Alaska became a state in 1959.  At that time, the Commission comprised the Territorial Governor, Commissioner of Mines, and Highway Engineer. Rules and regulations for the Commission's activities took effect in 1958.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

In 1959, the Oil and Gas Conservation Commission was temporarily abolished, and its duties were transferred to the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/18296055.xml">
Alaska Department of Natural Resources</link></agency>
.  In 1968, the Division of Oil and Gas was formed within the Department of Natural Resources.  In 1976, the word "conservation" was added back to the division's title, and it became the Division of Oil and Gas Conservation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

In 1977, with oil production occurring in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/105585.xml">
Prudhoe Bay</link>, the <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/426213.xml">
Alaska Legislature</link></legislature>
 decided that an independent quasi-judicial agency should be created in the executive branch of the state. The present independent agency was at first located within the Department of Natural Resources, but in 1980 was transferred to the Department of Commerce and Economic Development. In 1994, it was transferred to the Department of Administration.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Commission Structure</st>
<p>

The structure of the membership has changed throughout the years, though it has consistently been a three-person Commission.</p>
<p>

Under the current structure, adopted in 1979, one member must be a registered petroleum engineer, one member must be a registered geologist, and one member must represent the public at large (i.e., a citizen in neither of the two categories listed above).</p>
<p>

Among the Commission's most well-known members is <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<governor wordnetid="110140314" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/2941511.xml">
Sarah Palin</link></governor>
</person>
, appointed by then Governor Frank Murkowski. She served from 2003-2004 and later became Governor of Alaska and the 2008 Republican nominee for Vice President of the United States.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mission</st>
<p>

The Commission is tasked to work in-hand with the oil industry to maximize production, administer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/14285414.xml">
correlative rights</link>, and improve resource recovery. It also administers an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/980309.xml">
underground injection</link> program for enhanced oil recovery and underground disposal of oil field waste, as authorized by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</link>. As part of this injection process, oil corporations must obtain an Aquifer Exemption Order granted by the AOGCC in areas with deep groundwater supplies. Some environmental groups such as the Cook Inletkeeper as well as First Nation People have contested these Orders, fearing they may contaminate groundwater supplies. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The Commission also holds oversight of wastewater disposal known as "wastewater drain fields"; as such, oil corporations are permitted to dispose of wastewater in the soil when certain requirements are met, and reject Orders when not met. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Additionally, the Commission adjudicates certain oil and gas disputes between owners, including disputes where the state is a party. It is designed to cooperate with industry, while still meeting its regulatory requirements.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  The Commission's website lists their primary mission is "to protect the public interest in exploration and development of oil and gas resources, while ensuring conservation practices, enhancing resource recovery, and protecting the health, safety, environment, and property rights of Alaskans."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Though the Cook Inletkeeper website notes "2 billion gallons of toxic waste" are disposed of in the Cook Inlet waterway every year by oil corporations <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Footnotes</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.state.ak.us/admin/ogc/WhoWeAre/history.shtml">
"Oil and Gas Conservation Commission, Who We Are - History (Updated 15 May 2006).</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aogcc.alaska.gov/orders/aeo/aeoindex.shtml">
"AOGCC Aquifer Exemption Orders Index"</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="3">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aogcc.alaska.gov/orders/aeo/aeo10.pdf">
"AOGCC Aquifer Exemption Order No. 10"</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.state.ak.us/admin/ogc/WhoWeAre/welcome.shtml">
"Oil and Gas Conservation Commission, Who We Are - Welcome (Updated 12 May 2006).</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.state.ak.us/admin/ogc/WhoWeAre/mission.shtml">
"Oil and Gas Conservation Commission, Who We Are - Mission (Updated 15 May 2006).</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.inletkeeper.org/energy/oil.htm">
"Cook Inletkeeper Energy Campaign - Oil &amp; Gas"</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aogcc.alaska.gov/">
Official website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
