<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:17:00[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>IT baseline protection</title>
<id>19170396</id>
<revision>
<id>240637752</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-24T08:14:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Girolamo Savonarola</username>
<id>61898</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>information technology management</category>
<category>computer security</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>IT baseline protection</b> signifies standard security measures for typical IT systems.
<sec>
<st>
 Concept </st>
<p>

The foundation of an IT baseline protection concept is initially not a detailed risk analysis. It proceeds from overall hazards. Consequently, sophisticated classification according to damage extent and probability of occurrence is ignored. Three protection needs categories are established. With their help, the protection needs of the object under investigation can be determined. Based on these, appropriate personnel, technical, organizational and infrastructural security measures are selected from the IT Baseline Protection Manual.</p>
<p>

The <link>
Federal Office for Security in Information Technology</link>'s IT Baseline Protection Manual offers a "cookbook recipe" for a normal level of protection. Besides probability of occurrence and potential damage extents, implementation costs are also considered. By using the Baseline Protection Manual, costly security analyses requiring expert knowledge are dispensed with, since overall hazards are worked with in the beginning. It is possible for the relative layman to identify measures to be taken and to implement them in cooperation with professionals.</p>
<p>

The FSI grants a baseline protection certificate as confirmation for the successful implementation of baseline protection. In stages 1 and 2, this is based on self declaration. In stage 3, an independent, FSI-licensed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/224700.xml">
auditor</link> completes an audit. Certification process internationalization has been possible since 2006. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/3585535.xml">
ISO 27001</link> certification can occur simultaneously with IT baseline protection certification. (The ISO 27001 standard is the successor of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/1136070.xml">
BS 7799-2</link>). This process is based on the new <link>
FSI security standards</link>. This process carries a development price which has prevailed for some time. Corporations having themselves certified under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/1136070.xml">
BS 7799-2</link> standard are obliged to carry out a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/219072.xml">
risk assessment</link>. To make it more comfortable, most deviate from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/19170396.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Protection+needs+determination%22])">
protection needs analysis</link> pursuant to the IT Baseline Protection Manual. The advantage is not only conformity with the strict <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/2226538.xml">
Federal Office for Security in Information Technology</link>, but also attainment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/1136070.xml">
BS 7799-2</link> certification. Beyond this, the FSI offers a few help aids like the policy template and the <link>
GSTOOL</link>.</p>

<p>

One <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/237536.xml">
data protection</link> component is available, which was produced in cooperation with the <link>
Federal Commissioners for Data Protection and Information Freedom</link> and the state data protection authorities and integrated into the IT Baseline Protection Catalog.  This component is not considered, however, in the certification process.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Baseline protection process </st>
<p>

The following steps are taken pursuant to the baseline protection process during <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/19170396.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22IT+structure+analysis%22])">
structure analysis</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/19170396.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Protection+needs+determination%22])">
protection needs analysis</link>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The IT network is defined.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IT structure analysis is carried out.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Protection needs determination is carried out.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A baseline security check is carried out.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IT baseline protection measures are implemented.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Creation occurs in the following steps:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IT <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/19170396.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22IT+structure+analysis%22])">
structure analysis</link> (survey) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Assessment of  <link>
protection need</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Selection of actions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Running comparison of nominal and actual.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 IT structure analysis </st>
<p>

An IT network includes the totality of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/174521.xml">
infrastructur</link>al, organizational, personnel, and technical components serving the fulfillment of a task in a particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/462545.xml">
information processing</link> application area. An IT network can thereby encompass the entire IT character of an institution or individual division, which is partitioned by organizational structures as, for example, a departmental network, or as shared <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<furnishing wordnetid="103405265" confidence="0.8">
<table wordnetid="104379243" confidence="0.8">
<furniture wordnetid="103405725" confidence="0.8">
<console_table wordnetid="103092883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/454746.xml">
IT applications</link></console_table>
</furniture>
</table>
</furnishing>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
, for example, a personnel information system. It is necessary to analyze and document the information technological structure in question to generate an IT security concept and especially to apply the IT Baseline Protection Manual. Due to today's usually heavily networked IT systems, a <link>
network topology plan</link> offers a starting point for the analysis. The following aspects must be taken into consideration:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The available <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/174521.xml">
infrastructure</link>,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The organizational and personnel framework for the IT network,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Networked and non-networked <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
IT systems</link> employed in the IT network.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The communications connections between IT systems and externally,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IT applications run within the IT network.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Protection needs determination </st>
<p>

The purpose of the protection needs determination is to investigate what protection is sufficient and appropriate for the information and information technology in use.
In this connection, the damage to each application and the processed information, which could result from a breach of confidentiality, integrity or availability, is considered. Important in this context is a realistic assessment of the possible follow-on damages. A division into the three protection needs categories "low to medium", "high" and "very high" has proved itself  of value. "Public", "internal" and "secret" are often used for confidentiality.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Modelling </st>
<p>

Heavily networked IT systems typically characterize information technology in government and business these days. As a rule, therefore, it is advantageous to consider the entire IT system and not just individual systems within the scope of an IT security analysis and concept. To be able to manage this task, it makes sense to logically partition the entire IT system into parts and to separately consider each part or even an IT network. Detailed documentation about its structure is prerequisite for the use of the IT Baseline Protection Manual on an IT network. This can be achieved, for example, via the IT structure analysis described above. The IT Baseline Protection Manuals components must ultimately be mapped onto the components of the IT network in question in a modelling step.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Baseline security check </st>
<p>

The baseline security check is an organisational instrument offering a quick overview of the prevailing IT security level. With the help of interviews, the status quo of an existing IT network (as modelled by IT baseline protection) relative to the number of security measures implemented from the IT Baseline Protection Manual is investigated. The result is a catalog in which the implementation status "dispensable", "yes", "partly", or "no" is entered for each relevant measure. By identifying not yet, or only partially, implemented measures, improvement options for the security of the information technology in question are highlighted.</p>
<p>

The baseline security check gives information about measures, which are still missing (nominal vs. actual comparison). From this follows what remains to be done to achieve baseline protection through security. Not all measures suggested by this baseline check need to be implemented. Peculiarities are to be taken into account!  It could be that several more or less unimportant applications are running on a server, which have lesser protection needs. In their totality, however, these applications are to be provided with a higher level of protection. This is called the (<link>
cumulation effect</link>).</p>
<p>

The applications running on a server determine its need for protection. In this connection, it is to be noted that several IT applications can run on an IT system. When this occurs, the application with the greatest need for protection determines the IT systems protection category. </p>
<p>

Conversely, it is conceivable that an IT application with great protection needs does not automatically transfer this to the IT system. This may happen because the IT system is configured redundantly, or because only an inconsequential part is running on it. This is called the (<link>
distribution effect</link>). This is the case, for example, with clusters.</p>
<p>

The baseline security check maps baseline protection measures. This level suffices for low to medium protection needs. This comprises about 80 % of all IT systems according to FSI estimates. For systems with high to very high protection needs, risk analysis based information security concepts, like for example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/3585535.xml">
ISO 27001</link>, are usually used.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 IT Baseline Protection Catalog and standards </st>
<p>

During its 2005 restructuring and expansion of the <link>
IT Baseline Protection Manual</link>, the FSI separated methodology from the IT Baseline Protection Catalog. The <link>
BSI 100-1</link>, <link>
BSI 100-2</link>, and <link>
BSI 100-3</link> standards contain information about construction of an information security management system (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/652702.xml">
ISMS</link>), the methodology or basic protection approach, and the creation of a security analysis for elevated and very elevated protection needs building on a completed baseline protection investigation.</p>
<p>

<link>
BSI 100-4</link>, the "Emergency management" standard, is currently in preparation. It contains elements from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/7363065.xml">
BS 25999</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/83883.xml">
ITIL</link> Service Continuity Management combined with the relevant IT Baseline Protection Catalog components, and essential aspects for appropriate  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/91099.xml">
Business Continuity Management</link> (BCM). Implementing these standards renders <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/3692331.xml">
certification</link> is possible pursuant to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/7363065.xml">
BS 25999</link>-2. The FSI has submitted the FSI 100-4 standards design for online commentary under <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>
<p>

The FSI brings its standards into line with international norms this way.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Literature </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
FSI</link>:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bsi.bund.de/gshb/Leitfaden/GS-Leitfaden.pdf">
IT Baseline Protection Guidelines (pdf, 420 kB)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 FSI: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bsi.bund.de/gshb/deutsch/download/it-grundschutz-kataloge_2006_de.pdf">
IT Baseline Protection Cataloge 2007</weblink> (pdf)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 FSI: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bsi.bund.de/literat/bsi_standard/index.htm">
FSI IT Security Management and IT Baseline Protection Standards</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.humpert-partner.de/conpresso/_rubric/index.php?rubric=6">
Frederik Humpert: <it>IT-Grundschutz umsetzen mit GSTOOL. Anleitungen und Praxistipps für den erfolgreichen Einsatz des BSI-Standards</it>, Carl Hanser Verlag München, 2005.</weblink> (ISBN 3-446-22984-1)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Norbert Pohlmann, Hartmut Blumberg: <it>Der IT-Sicherheitsleitfaden. Das Pflichtenheft zur Implementierung von IT-Sicherheitsstandards im Unternehmen</it>, ISBN 3-8266-0940-9</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bsi.de/literat/bsi_standard/bsi-standard_100-4_v090.pdf">
<it>Entwurf BSI 100-4''</it></weblink> (pdf)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bsi.bund.de/english/index.htm">
Federal Office for Security in Information Technology</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.branchenbuch-it-sicherheit.de/">
IT Security Yellow Pages</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bsi.bund.de/english/gstool/index.htm">
IT Baseline protection tools</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
