<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:13:45[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Turbo timer</title>
<id>1922032</id>
<revision>
<id>242253653</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T14:31:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Sherurcij</username>
<id>120909</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Engine technology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>turbo timer</b> is a device designed to keep an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/14796.xml">
automotive engine</link> running for a pre-specified period of time in order to automatically execute the cool-down period required to prevent premature turbo wear and failure. After a period of driving when a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/30886.xml">
turbocharger</link> has been working hard, it is important to let the engine run at idle speed for a period of time, allowing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/508504.xml">
compressor</link> assembly to cool from the lower <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/18993869.xml">
gas</link> temperatures in both the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/303716.xml">
exhaust</link> and intake tracts. At the same time the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/216189.xml">
lubricating oil</link> from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/14796.xml">
engine</link> is able to circulate properly so the turbine won't burn the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/216189.xml">
lubricating oil</link> that would otherwise be trapped within the charger with the turbine rotating at high speed.  With regard to modern automotive turbochargers, the need for a turbo timer can be eliminated by simply ensuring the car does not produce any 'boost' (during driving) for several minutes prior to the ignition being shut off.<p>

Turbo timers also have the added benefit of allowing the operator to adjust the engine <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/1318086.xml">
RPM</link>'s that the turbo begins producing boost.</p>
<p>

Most turbo timers are based on digital electronics.</p>



</bdy>
</article>
