<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:14:02[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Olive oil extraction</title>
<id>1925618</id>
<revision>
<id>239091542</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-17T19:44:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lysis rationale</username>
<id>5148104</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Food industry</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="Capernaum_roman_olive_press_by_David_Shankbone.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

An olive mill and an olive press dating from Roman times in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/346261.xml">
Capernaum, Israel</link>.
</caption>
</image>
<b>Olive oil extraction</b>  is the process of extracting the oil present in the olive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/57425.xml">
drupe</link>s for food use.  The oil is produced in the <link>
mesocarp</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/23977.xml">
cells</link>, and stored in a particular type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/32347.xml">
vacuole</link> called a <link>
lipovacuole</link>, i.e., every cell contains a tiny olive oil droplet. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
Olive oil</link> extraction is the process of separating the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
oil</link> from the other fruit contents (vegetative extract liquid and solid material). This separation is attained only by physical means, i.e., oil and water don’t mix, so they are relatively easy to separate. This contrasts with other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/192331.xml">
 oils</link> that are extracted with chemical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/37431.xml">
solvents</link> (generally <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/105952.xml">
hexane</link>).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  The first operation when extracting olive oil is washing the olives, to reduce the presence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
contaminant</link>s, especially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/4229946.xml">
soil</link> which can create a particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/10591.xml">
flavour</link> defect called "soil taste".
<sec>
<st>
 Traditional method: olive press </st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="OliveOilFactoryMorocco.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Grinder with two millstones and in the foreground several fiber disks
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Marokko-162.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Press with stack of fiber disks
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

People have used olive presses since Greeks first began pressing olives over 5000 years ago. Extant Roman era olive presses survive to the present time, with a notable collection present at <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/1204088.xml">
Volubilis</link></site>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/19291.xml">
Morocco</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> An olive press works by applying pressure to olive paste to separate the liquid oil and vegetation water from the solid material. The oil and vegetation water are then separated by standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/286016.xml">
decantation</link>.</p>
<p>

This basic method is still widely used today, and it’s still a valid way of producing high quality olive oil if adequate precautions are taken.</p>
<p>

First the olives are ground into an olive paste using large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/167364.xml">
millstone</link>s. The olive paste generally stays under the stones for 30 to 40 minutes. This has three objectives:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 to guarantee that the olives are well ground</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 to allow enough time for the olive drops to join to form the largest droplets of oil</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 allow the fruit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/9257.xml">
enzymes</link> to produce some of the oil aromas and taste</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Rarely, olive oil mills use a modern crushing method with a traditional press.</p>
<p>

After grinding, the olive paste is spread on fiber disks, which are stacked on top of each other, then placed into the press. Traditionally the disks were made of hemp or coconut fiber, but nowadays they’re made of synthetic fibers which are easier to clean and maintain.</p>
<p>

These disks are then put on a hydraulic piston, forming a pile. Pressure is applied on the disks, thus compacting the solid phase of the olive paste and percolating the liquid phases (oil and vegetation water). The applied hydraulic pressure can go to 400 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../780/582780.xml">
 atm</link>.</p>
<p>

To facilitate separation of the liquid phases, water is run down the sides of the disks to increase the speed of percolation.</p>
<p>

The liquids are then separated either by a standard process of decantation or by the means of a faster vertical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/106284.xml">
centrifuge</link>.</p>
<p>

The traditional method is a valid form of producing high quality olive oil, if after each extraction the disks are properly cleaned from the remains of paste; if not the leftover paste will begin to ferment thereby producing inconsistencies of flavours (called defects) that will contaminate the subsequently produced olive oil.
A similar problem can affect the grindstones, that in order to assure perfect quality, also require cleaning after each usage.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Advantages and disadvantages </st>

<p>

Proper cleaning produces higher quality oil.  Grindstones, while ancient in design, are a suitable way to grind olives, because this method  breaks up the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/57425.xml">
drupe</link>'s pulp while only slightly touching the nut and the skin. This reduces the release of the oil <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/198711.xml">
oxidation</link> enzymes present in these organs.
In addition, in this extraction method, the introduction of water is minimal when compared to the modern one, thus reducing the washing off of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/362892.xml">
polyphenol</link>s.
The exhausted paste, called <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../094/683094.xml">
pomace</link></it>, has a low content of water making it an easier residue to manage.</p>
<p>

<b>Advantages</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Better grinding of the olives, reducing the release of oil <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/198711.xml">
oxidation</link>  enzymes</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reduced added water, minimizing the washing of polyphenols</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Pomace with a low content of water easier to manage</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Disadvantages</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Difficult cleaning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Non continuous process with waiting periods thus exposing the olive paste to the action of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/22303.xml">
oxygen</link> and light.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Requires more manual labour</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Longer time period from harvest to pressing</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Modern method: decanter centrifugation </st>

<p>

The modern method of olive oil extraction uses an industrial decanter to separate all the phases by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/286021.xml">
centrifugation</link>.  In this method the olives are crushed to a fine paste.  This can be done by a hammer crusher, disc crusher, depitting machine or knife crusher.  This paste is then <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/3343853.xml">
malaxed</link> for 30 to 40 min in order to allow the small olive droplets to agglomerate. The aromas are created in these two steps through the action of fruit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/9257.xml">
enzyme</link>s.</p>
<p>

Afterwards the paste is pumped in to an industrial decanter where the phases will be separated. Water is added to facilitate the extraction process with the paste.</p>
<p>

The decanter is a large capacity horizontal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/106284.xml">
centrifuge</link> rotating approximately 3000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/1318086.xml">
 rpm</link>, the high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/7532.xml">
centrifugal force</link> created allows the phases to be readily separated according to their different densities (solids &amp;gt; vegetation water &amp;gt; oil). Inside the decanter's rotating conical drum there is a coil that rotates a few rpm slower, pushing the solid materials out of the system.</p>
<p>

<image location="center" width="500px" src="Decanter.gif" type="thumb">
<caption>

Diagram of a working decanter. The three phases are separated according to their densities
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The separated oil and vegetation water are then rerun through a vertical centrifuge, working around 6000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/1318086.xml">
rpm</link> that will separate the small quantity of vegetation water still contained in oil and vice versa.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Three, two, and two and a half phases decanters </st>

<p>

With the <b>three phases</b> oil decanter, a portion of the oil polyphenols is washed out due to the higher quantity of added water (when compared to the traditional method), producing a larger quantity of vegetation water that needs to be processed.</p>
<p>

The <b>two phases</b> oil decanter was created as an attempt to solve these problems. Sacrificing part of its extraction capability, it uses less added water thus reducing the phenol washing. The olive paste is separated into two phases: oil and wet pomace. This type of decanter, instead of having three exits (oil, water and solids), has only two. The water is expelled by the decanter coil together with the pomace, resulting in a wetter pomace that is much harder to process industrially. Many pomace oil extraction facilities refuse to work with these materials because the energy costs of drying the pomace for the hexane oil extraction often make the extraction process sub-economical. In practice, then, the two phases decanter solves the phenol washing problem but increases the residue management problem.</p>
<p>

The <b>two and a half phases</b> oil decanter is a compromise between the two previous types of decanters. It separates the olive paste into the standard three phases, but has a smaller need for added water and also a smaller vegetation water output. Therefore the water content of the obtained pomace comes very close to that of the standard three phases decanter, and the vegetation water output is relatively small, minimizing the residue management issues.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Advantages and disadvantages </st>

<p>

<b>Advantages</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Compact machinery - one decanter can take the place of several presses</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Continuous and automated</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Limited labor required</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 highest percent of oil extraction</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Vegetable water disposal less of a problem</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Olive oil from two-phase centrifugation systems contains more phenols, tocopherols, trans-2-hexenal and total aroma compounds and is more resistant to oxidation than oil from three-phase ones and from hydraulic presses</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Disadvantages</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Expensive</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 More technical labor required</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 High energy consumption</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Pomace may end up moist</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Greater amount of vegetable water to be disposed of</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reduced antioxidants due to added water</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Subject to wear from rocks, grit</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Sinolea </st>
<p>

The Sinolea method to extract oil from the olives was introduced in 1972;<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> in this process, rows of metal discs or plates are dipped into the paste; the oil preferentially wets and sticks to the metal and is removed with scrapers in a continuous process. It’s based on the different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/113302.xml">
 surface tension</link> of the vegetation water and the oil, these different physical behaviors allow the olive oil to adhere to a steel plaque while the other two phases stay behind.</p>
<p>

<b>Sinolea</b> works by continuously introducing several hundreds of steel plaques in to the paste thus extracting the olive oil. This process is not completely efficient leaving a large quantity of oil still in the paste, so the remaining paste has to be processed by the standard modern method (industrial decanter).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Advantages and disadvantages </st>

<p>

<b>Advantages</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Higher polyphenol content of oil</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Low temperature method</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Automated</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Low labor</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oil/water separation step is not needed</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Low energy requirement</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Disadvantages</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Often must be combined with one of the above methods in order to maximize oil extraction which requires more space and labor.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Large surface areas can lead to rapid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/66313.xml">
oxidation</link> of the olive product</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sale of future machines currently outlawed in the <economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
European Union</link></economy>
 due to difficulty in cleaning large surface areas.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 First cold pressed – cold extraction </st>

<p>

Many oils are marketed as first cold pressed or cold extraction, this is a denomination describing the temperature at which the oil was obtained.</p>
<p>

In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
EU</link> these designations are regulated by article 5 of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://europa.eu.int/smartapi/cgi/sga_doc?smartapi!celexapi!prod!CELEXnumdoc&amp;lg=EN&amp;numdoc=32002R1019&amp;model=guichett">
Regulation 1019 of 2002</weblink>. This article states that in order to use these designations the olive oil bottler must prove that the temperature of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/3343853.xml">
malaxation</link> and extraction was under 27°C (80°F).</p>
<p>

For olive oil bottled outside EU countries this regulation does not apply, and thus the consumer has no assurance that these statements are true.</p>
<p>

The temperature of malaxation and extraction is crucial due to its effect on olive oil quality. When high temperatures are applied the more volatile aromas are lost and the rate of oil oxidation is increased, producing therefore lower quality oils. In addition, the chemical content of the polyphenols, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/5538293.xml">
antioxidants</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/32512.xml">
vitamin</link>s present in the oil is reduced by higher temperatures.  The temperature is adjusted basically by controlling the temperature of the water added during these two steps. High temperatures are used to increase the yield of olive oil obtained from the paste.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Alternative configurations </st>

<p>

Some producers, in order to maximise product quality, choose to combine the traditional grinding method, the stone mill, with a modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/2072855.xml">
decanter</link>. This technique produces more selective grinding of the olives, reduces the malaxation time olive paste, and avoids the complicated cleaning of the olive press fibre disks. Because the use of the stone mill requires a loading and unloading phase, this extraction method is discontinuous, i.e. there times where the all machinery is stopped, therefore it is generally not used on a large commercial scale, being applied only at small scale olive mills producing high quality olive oil.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Consumer point of view </st>

<p>

High quality olive oil can be obtained by all the methods if proper measures are taken. Olive oil quality is equally dependent on the quality of the olives themselves and on the time they have to wait from harvesting to extraction, in addition to the extraction method itself.</p>
<p>

The 2 worst “enemies” of olive oil are: Oxygen and light. Once an olive is harvested, it should be pressed within 24 hours. Oxidation begins immediately upon harvesting. In the period between harvest and grinding, the fruits' enzymes are very active and increasingly degrade the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/790808.xml">
endogenous</link> oil, and therefore oil obtained after a longer wait is of lower quality, presenting higher acidity (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/661100.xml">
oleic acid</link> percentage).</p>
<p>

In addition, if additional oxygen is allowed to interact with the olive paste during the extraction process, the acidity level will increase further. Sealed extraction methods are best to prevent the continued introduction of oxygen, as well as light to the oil.</p>
<p>

Lastly, after extraction of the oil is complete, the oil must be stored in cool stainless steel silos that are pumped free of oxygen. This will ensure the quality of the oil; the integrity and stability of the chemical makeup of the oil.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Future prospects </st>

<p>

The future of olive extraction points to reducing the negative aspects of the present methods, decreasing the degradation oil produced by the extraction process in itself.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reducing the oxidation by performing part of the process of malaxation and the extraction under a controlled <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/21175.xml">
nitrogen</link> atmosphere</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Extracting the nut of the olive before grinding, this will reduce the release of oxidative enzymes present in this organ, and yield a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../094/683094.xml">
pomace</link> that is free from wood residues, making it possible to be used in animal feeding</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reducing the addition of water to minimize the washing of polyphenols</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Improving the sinolea method, through an increase in the efficiency of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/207601.xml">
adsorption</link> of the oil to the plates, thus reducing the need for the use of standard methods of extraction</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
Olive oil</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/3701684.xml">
Amurca</link>, a byproduct in olive oil extraction, historically used for many purposes</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
F. D. Gunstone, <it>Vegetable Oils in Food Technology: Composition, Properties, and Uses</it>, 2002, CRC Press, 351 pages ISBN 0849328160</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.megalithic.co.uk/article.php?sid=14906">
C. Michael Hogan, <it>Volubilis</it>, The Megaoithic Portal, ed. Andy Burnham (2007)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
Dimitrios Boskou, <it>Olive Oil: Chemistry and Technology</it>, Contributor American Oil Chemists Society, 2006, AOCS Press, 268 pages  ISBN 189399788X</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://europa.eu.int/smartapi/cgi/sga_doc?smartapi!celexapi!prod!CELEXnumdoc&amp;lg=EN&amp;numdoc=32002R1019">
EU Regulation 1019 of 2002</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.olivetree.eat-online.net/">
The Olive Tree World - Olive Oil</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
