<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:20:04[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<standard  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107260623">
<header>
<title>ADL Registry</title>
<id>19267972</id>
<revision>
<id>237857860</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-12T03:18:55Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CJLL Wright</username>
<id>259138</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>content registries</category>
<category>All articles lacking sources</category>
<category>e-learning</category>
<category>XML-based standards</category>
<category>Articles lacking reliable references from September 2008</category>
<category>content repositories</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  that appear in reliable, third-party publications.</b>
s and sources affiliated with the subject of the article are generally not sufficient for a Wikipedia article. Please include more appropriate  from , or discuss the issue on the talk page. <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>



The <b>Advanced Distributed Learning Registry</b> was developed by the <link>
ADL Initiative</link> and is the central search point for the discovery of digital objects related to DoD training, education, performance, and decision-aiding that can be redeployed, rearranged, repurposed, and rewritten. In much the same way that a card from the card catalog contains descriptive information about books in a library, the ADL Registry contains all of the registered entries that contain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> about the digital object in a repository. "It is the first instance of a registry-based approach to repository federation resulting from the Content Object Repository Discovery and Registration/Resolution Architecture (CORDRA) project."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

The ADL Registry provides centrally searchable information, in the form of metadata records (not actual objects). The metadata describes many different kinds of objects to enable their discovery and reuse regardless of their location or origin.  Like <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/28165.xml">
SCORM</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
, DoD Instruction (DoDI) 1322.26 Development, Management, and Delivery of Distributed Learning. DoDI 1322.26 requires that all acquired or developed SCORM content packages shall include metadata, be registered in the ADL-R, and be maintained in DoD Components’ repositories that are searchable and accessible.</p>
<p>

This centralized registration is now required through a DoD Instruction (1322.26) “Development, Management and Delivery of Distributed Learning.” Precisely what is registered are the metadata that describe the learning object in a structured way. This is accomplished through a component of SCORM, the Learning Object Metadata standard, now designated as IEEE 1484.12.1. In this way, the author, creation date, version number, keywords and other vital information for this individual object is available to the developer, instructor or student with a single search.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

The mandatory metadata that is required by the ADL Registry to contribute an item is a subset of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/1955471.xml">
Learning Object Metadata</link> IEEE LOM standard] and has been adapted for use in the ADL community of practice. Additional LOM elements can be used to more fully describe registered objects since the ADL Registry indexes all metadata so that others can find, redeploy, rearrange, repurpose, or rewrite digital objects.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Unique Aspects</st>
<p>

Unlike a standard Internet search engine, the ADL Registry provides highly-targeted search results, significantly reducing the number of irrelevant matches because digital objects:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Are intentionally made visible and searchable by the contributor who is best able to accurately describe them and has vetted them.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Can be available for search and discovery without providing direct access to them.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Can be discovered even when they are not accessible to general web search engines.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

Few would question the value of Web-searching technologies such as Google and Yahoo. However, these technologies do not address important requirements of the learning, education and training communities. Three key limitations are:</p>
<p>

Google-type Web search uses indexed data that is created by “crawling” through the entire World Wide Web to see what is accessible and machine readable. A good deal of digital content used for learning is not accessible to Web crawlers (by policy or lack of infrastructure) or is unreadable because it is in a digital format that Web crawlers can’t easily interpret or the digital object is not available or indexed.</p>
<p>

Google-type Web search finds everything and anything that might be relevant; there is no reliable means to filter content for authenticity, validity, currency and other criteria to limit the results to truly relevant learning content.</p>
<p>

Mission-critical use cases cannot afford the hit-or-miss nature of today’s “index-everything” search strategies.</p>
<p>

Web searching using Google and similar services provides fabulous value on many levels and will no doubt evolve and improve over time, as search algorithms become more sophisticated. But, the solution to finding content that is intentionally created for specific learning objectives, or that has special, well-crafted, instructional or informational value, and that has been vetted, authorized and made available for use by those who really need it, remains a technical and organizational challenge.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>


<p>

ADL Registry metadata is:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Expressed using the [IEEE [Learning Object Metadata] (LOM)] standard.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Encoded as Extensible Markup Language (XML™).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Submitted manually through the ADL Registry web site.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Submitted automatically through RIM-Lite, a system developed to interface with the ADL Registry.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/28165.xml">
SCORM</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/14274979.xml">
Advanced Distributed Learning</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations .</col>
</row>
</table>


<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adlregistry.adlnet.gov/">
Official site of the ADL Registry</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.adlnet.gov/">
Official ADL Initiative site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adlnet.gov/News/articles/index.aspx?ID=480/">
ADL Guidelines for Creating Reusable Content with SCORM 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.military-training-technology.com/article.cfm?DocID=2363">
DoD Learning Content: Search and Discovery</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.military-training-technology.com/article.cfm?DocID=1800">
ADL Advocate: Making the Vision of Learning Anytime, Anywhere, a Reality</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://adlregistry.adlnet.gov/about/developers/">
http://adlregistry.adlnet.gov/about/developers/</weblink> <it>The ADL Registry and CORDRA, Volume 2: ADL Registry Overview and User’s Guide''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</standard>
</article>
