<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:08:41[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network tap</title>
<id>1933660</id>
<revision>
<id>244378026</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T14:40:33Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Oldcommguy</username>
<id>7517258</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Networking hardware</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>network TAP</b> is a hardware device which provides a way to access the data flowing across a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/4122592.xml">
computer network</link>.  Computer networks, including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>, are collections of devices, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computers</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/25748.xml">
routers</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/28284.xml">
switches</link>, that are connected to each other.  The connections can utilize different technologies, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/9499.xml">
Ethernet</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/14739.xml">
802.11</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/41149.xml">
FDDI</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
ATM</link>.  In many cases, it is desirable for a third party to monitor the network traffic between two points in the network, point A and point B.  If the network between points A and B consists of a physical cable, a <b>network TAP</b> may be the best way to accomplish this monitoring.  The network TAP has at least three ports -- an <b>A</b> port, a <b>B</b> port, and a <b>monitor</b> port.  To place a TAP between points A and B, the network cable between point A and point B is replaced with a pair of cables, one going to the TAP's A port, one going to the TAP's B port.  The TAP passes through all traffic between A and B, so A and B still think they are connected to each other, but the TAP also copies the traffic between A and B to its monitor port, enabling a third party to listen.<p>

Network TAPs are commonly used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/113021.xml">
network intrusion detection systems</link>,<link>
VoIP recorders</link>,  <link>
network probes</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/11839689.xml">
RMON</link> probes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
packet sniffer</link>s, and other monitoring and collection devices and software that require access to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/219558.xml">
network segment</link>.  TAPs are used in security applications because they are non-obtrusive, are not detectable on the network, can deal with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/2112491.xml">
full-duplex</link> and non-shared networks, and will usually <it>pass-through</it> traffic even if the TAP stops working or loses power.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Terminology </st>

<p>

The term <b>network TAP</b> is analogous to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/91221.xml">
phone tap</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/216792.xml">
vampire tap</link>.  Some vendors have phrases for  which <b>TAP</b> is an acronym, for example Net Optics, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.datacomsystems.com/">
Datacom Systems</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.NetworkTAPs.com/">
Network Instruments</weblink> use <b>test access port</b> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.criticaltap.com/">
Network Critical</weblink> uses <b>test access point</b>; however, those are most likely <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/36982.xml">
bacronym</link>s.</p>
<p>

The monitored traffic is sometimes referred to as the <it>pass-through</it> traffic, while the ports that are used for monitoring are the <it>monitor</it> ports.</p>
<p>

Vendors will tend to use terms in their marketing such as <it>breakout</it>, <it>passive</it>, <it>aggregating</it>, <it>regeneration</it>, <it>inline power</it>, and others.  Common meanings will be discussed later.  Unfortunately, vendors do not use such terms consistently.  Before buying any products, be sure to understand the available features, and check with vendors or read the product literature closely to figure out how marketing terms correspond to reality.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 New Filterable TAP Technology </st>

<p>

A new type of TAP or Network Access Point is available and it is a filterable TAP.
The rational for this is especially in the 10 Gigabit environment, having 10 Gig Test equipment is very expensive, so why not use the less expensive and available 1 Gigabit monitoring and analysis tools. A filterable Tap using advanced filtering can parse off the data, applications, VLAN...etc to the 1 Gig port for deep analysis and monitoring, including IDS requirements.
Filtered access is also the best way to focus on the business important or other specific areas of your network. As one gets into the higher speeds and 10 Gigabits is a very high speed, one cannot analyze with old capture and decode everything philosophy. So, focused access is the best way and the only way with higher data speeds.
Any Filterable Tap you consider must have a simple GUI for easy setup and management as well as collect the layer one and two data plus allow for auto saving and easy access by graphing programs. Remember with IPv6 the number of errorred frames, corrupted frames...etc is a must to know.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Advantages and features </st>

<p>

Older network technologies tended to be <it>shared</it>.  Connecting a monitoring device to a <it>shared</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/219558.xml">
network segment</link> (ie. piece of a network) was very easy -- just connect the monitoring device as you would any other host, and enable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/357817.xml">
promiscuous mode</link>.  Modern network technologies tend to be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/40614.xml">
switched</link>, meaning that devices are connected using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/3988040.xml">
point-to-point</link> links.  If a monitoring device is connected to such a network, it will only see its own traffic.  The network TAP allows the monitoring device to view the contents of a point-to-point link.</p>
<p>

Modern network technologies are often <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/2112491.xml">
full-duplex</link>, meaning that data can travel in both directions at the same time.  If a network link allows 100 Mbit/s of data to flow in each direction at the same time, this means that the network really allows 200 Mbit/s of aggregate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/30932.xml">
throughput</link>.  This can present a problem for monitoring technologies if they have only one monitor port.  So network TAPs for full-duplex technologies usually have two monitor ports, one for each half of the connection.  The listener must use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/2274179.xml">
channel bonding</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/1952952.xml">
link aggregation</link> to merge the two connections into one aggregate interface to see both halves of the traffic.  Other monitoring technologies do not deal well with the full-duplex problem.</p>
<p>

Once a network TAP is in place, the network can be monitored without interfering with the network itself.  Other network monitoring solutions require <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/584997.xml">
in-band</link> changes to network devices, which means that monitoring can impact the devices being monitored.</p>
<p>

Once a TAP is in place, a monitoring device can be connected to it as-needed without impacting the monitored network.</p>
<p>

Some TAPs have multiple output ports, or multiple pairs of output ports for full-duplex, to allow more than one device to monitor the network at the TAP point.  These are often called <it>regeneration</it> TAPs.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Fiber_optic_tap.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A passive fiber optic tap.
</caption>
</image>

Some TAPs, particularly fiber TAPs, can use no power and no electronics at all for the <it>pass-through</it> and <it>monitor</it> portion of the network traffic.  This means that the TAP should never suffer any kind of electronics failure or power failure that results in a loss of network connectivity.  One way this can work, for fiber-based network technologies, is that the TAP divides the incoming light using a simple physical apparatus into two outputs, one for the <it>pass-through</it>, one for the <it>monitor</it>.  This can be called a <it>passive</it> TAP.  Other TAPs use no power or electronics for the <it>pass-through</it>, but do use power and electronics for the <it>monitor</it> port.  These can also be referred to as <it>passive</it>.</p>
<p>

Some TAPs operate at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/78300.xml">
physical layer</link> of the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/22747.xml">
OSI model</link></system_of_measurement>
</advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 rather than the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/40996.xml">
data link</link> layer.  For example, they work with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/2940457.xml">
multi-mode fiber</link> rather than <link>
1000BASE-SX</link>.  This means that they can work with most data link network technologies that use that physical media, such as ATM and some forms of Ethernet.  Network TAPs that act as simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/582410.xml">
optical splitter</link>s, sometimes called <it>passive TAPs</it> (although that term is not used consistently) can have this property.</p>
<p>

Some network TAPs offer both duplication of network traffic for monitoring devices and SNMP services. Most major network TAP manufacturers offer TAPs with remote management through Telnet, HTTP, or SNMP interfaces, including  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.criticaltap.com/">
Network Critical</weblink>,<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netoptics.com/">
Net Optics</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.NetworkTAPs.com/">
Network Instruments</weblink>, and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vssmonitoring.com/">
VSS Monitoring</weblink>. Such network TAP hybrids can be helpful to network managers who wish to view baseline performance statistics without diverting existing tools. Alternately, SNMP alarms generated by managed TAPs can alert network managers to link conditions that merit examination by analyzers to intrusion detection systems.</p>
<p>

Some TAPs get some of their power (ie. for the <it>pass-through</it>) or all of their power (ie. for both <it>pass-through</it> and <it>monitor</it>) from the network itself.  These can be referred to as having <it>inline power</it>.</p>
<p>

Some TAPs can also reproduce low-level network errors. Like short frames, bad CRC or just corrupted one.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Disadvantages and problems </st>

<p>

Network TAPs require additional hardware, so are not as cheap as technologies that leverage capabilities that are built-in to the network. They are easier to manage and normally provide more data than some network devices though. </p>
<p>

Network TAPs can require <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/2274179.xml">
channel bonding</link> on monitoring devices to get around the problem with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/2112491.xml">
full-duplex</link> discussed above. Vendors usually refer to this as aggregation as well.</p>
<p>

Putting a network TAP into place can disrupt the network being monitored for a short time. It's better than taking a network down multiple times to deploy a monitoring tool though. Building a monitoring access platform across the entire network is preferred.</p>
<p>

Monitoring large networks using network Taps can require a lot of monitoring devices.  Some argue that other technologies <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/185529.xml">
scale</link> better. SPAN ports are presumed free, but require more configuration than TAPs. Remote management capabilities and easy-to-use GUI's available with today's TAPs help strengthen the argument for them.</p>
<p>

Even fully <it>passive</it> network TAPs introduce new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/1724836.xml">
points of failure</link> into the network. Make sure you look for dual power and TAPs that report problems via SNMP.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Comparison to other monitoring technologies </st>

<p>

Many different types of monitoring are desirable.</p>
<p>

The simplest type of monitoring is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/9878372.xml">
logging in</link> to an interesting device and running programs or commands that show performance statistics and other data.  This is the cheapest way to monitor a network, and is highly appropriate for small networks.  However, it does not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/185529.xml">
scale</link> well to large networks.  It can also impact the network being monitored; see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/1437617.xml">
observer effect</link>.</p>
<p>

Another way to monitor devices is to use a remote management protocol such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/41710.xml">
SNMP</link> to ask devices about their performance.  This <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/185529.xml">
scales</link> well, but is not necessarily appropriate for all types of monitoring.  For example, 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/113021.xml">
network intrusion detection systems</link> require a lot of host resources, so it is desirable to run such software on centralized monitoring systems rather than on individual hosts.  Also, politically, sometimes one group runs the network and another group runs the computers, so the group that runs the network wants to have monitoring capabilities independent of the group that runs the computers.</p>
<p>

Another method to monitor networks is by enable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/357817.xml">
promiscuous mode</link> on the monitoring host, and connecting it to a <link>
shared segment</link>.  This works well with older <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/17739.xml">
LAN</link> technologies such as <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/9614300.xml">
10BASE-T</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 Ethernet networks and FDDI networks.  On such networks, any host can automatically see what all other hosts were doing by enabling promiscuous mode.  However, modern switched network technologies such as those used on modern Ethernets provide, in effect, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/3988040.xml">
point-to-point</link> links between pairs of devices, so it is hard for other devices to see traffic.</p>
<p>

Another method to monitor networks is to use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/702709.xml">
port mirroring</link> (called "SPAN", for Switched Port Analyzer, by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/51746.xml">
Cisco</link></company>
, and given other names by some other vendors) on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/25748.xml">
routers</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/28284.xml">
switches</link>.  This is a low-cost alternative to network TAPs, and solves many of the same problems.  However, not all routers and switches support port mirroring and, on those that do, using port mirroring can affect the performance of the router or switch.  These technologies may also be subject to the problem with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/2112491.xml">
full-duplex</link> described elsewhere in this article, and there are often limits for the router or switch on how many pass-through sessions can be monitored, or how many monitor ports can monitor a given session.</p>
<p>

Check out the article on SPAN versus TAP for a deeper look - 
http://www.lovemytool.com/blog/2007/08/span-ports-or-t.html</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<analyzer wordnetid="102708711" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
Packet sniffer</link></instrument>
</analyzer>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/702709.xml">
Port mirroring</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Companies making network TAPs </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.criticaltap.com/">
Network Critical</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.NetworkTAPs.com/">
NetworkTAPs.com a division of Network Instruments</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lan-wan-tap.com/">
Comcraft</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.datacomsystems.com/">
Datacom Systems</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.netoptics.com/">
Net Optics</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vssmonitoring.com/">
VSS Monitoring</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cubro.net/">
Cubro</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Companies making Filter TAPs </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.criticaltap.com/">
Network Critical</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cubro.net">
Cubro</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vssmonitoring.com">
VSS Monitoring</weblink></entry>
</list>

</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
