<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:23:23[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<school  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108276720">
<educational_institution  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108276342">
<header>
<title>Shantiniketan Indian School</title>
<id>19370999</id>
<revision>
<id>243141342</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T09:43:41Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Oddharmonic</username>
<id>37486</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Schools in Qatar</category>
<category>Educational institutions established in 2000</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Shantiniketan Indian School</b> was founded on 27th July 2000 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/53868.xml">
Doha</link></village>
 Qatar by a team of promoters who felt the need to establish a school to provide quality education at affordable fees. Classes from Play School to Standard 6 began on 4th September 2000 at the B-Ring Road Campus. On 1st April 2003 Std. 9 was added and in April 2004 Std. 10 began. The new managing committee has plans to add +1 and +2 shortly <p>

The schools is affiliated to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/1585320.xml">
CBSE</link> and is approved by the Ministry of Education ,Doha Qatar Currently their are about 6000 students in classes KG - X and the school runs in 2 premises, ome in Musheirb ( classes II - X ) and the other in Doha Jadeed ( Playschool - standard I )</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Objectives </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To inculcate an integral view of life based on norms and values</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To create an atmosphere of all round development of a student's personality</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To provide education in the light of CBSE guidelines</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To make the students aware of the global realities and to create a sense of responsibility and accountability among them</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To develop a character of mutual cooperation, mutual tolerance, mutual respect and farsightedness in such a manner that they would become the responsible citizens of the future world</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Planning </st>
<p>

To achieve its objectives, the school takes the following measures :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Developing a classroom environment to facilitate communicative teaching and learning process</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Adopting the approach to give individual attention for redressal of student's grievances</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Implementing appropriate teaching methodology to upgrade student's standard of knowledge</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Arranging co-curricular activities for multi dimensional personality development</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Periodic assessment of the students to apply remedial measures</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Identifying the reasons of poor performance of the students and arranging academic support for the needy</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Establishing a parent's forum to solicit their suggestions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Organising subject clubs to stimulate intellectual curiosity, clear thinking and accurate perception of the subject</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Arranging the workshop for the staff to equip them with latest teaching methodology</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Regular parent teacher interaction</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Developing Prefect System in school buses to have a closer touch with transport grievances</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The Faculty </st>
<p>

To achieve its objectives, the school has a well qualified team of experienced teachers
Principal : Mr. Tajammul Husain
Headmistress : Mrs. Vidya Jacob
Assist. Headmistress : Mrs. Radha</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Facilities </st>
<p>

The school has a well equipped computer and science laboratory and a library which is currentlyundergoing renovations</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</article>
