<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:08:10[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Extension conflict</title>
<id>1938220</id>
<revision>
<id>219280628</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-14T13:26:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Mac OS</category>
<category>Anti-patterns</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Extensions_Manager_Mac_OS_9.1.png" type="thumb">
</image>
<p>

<b>Extension conflicts</b> were sometimes a problem on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/19006979.xml">
Apple Macintosh</link> computers running versions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/20043.xml">
Mac OS</link> prior to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
X</link>, especially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/345354.xml">
System 7</link>. <pause wordnetid="115271008" confidence="0.8">
<extension wordnetid="115272382" confidence="0.8">
<time_interval wordnetid="115269513" confidence="0.8">
<delay wordnetid="115272029" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/1757447.xml">
Extension</link></delay>
</time_interval>
</extension>
</pause>
s were bundles of code that extended the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>'s capabilities by directly patching <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/102908.xml">
OS calls</link>, thus receiving control instead of the operating system when applications (including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/156166.xml">
Finder</link>) made system calls. Generally, once an extension had done what it wanted, it was supposed to pass on the (possibly modified) system call to the operating system's routine. If multiple extensions want to patch the same system call, they end up receiving the call in a chain, the first extension in line passing it on to the next, and so on, until the last extension passes to the operating system. If an extension doesn't hand the next extension in line what it is expecting, bad things result, ranging from unexpected behavior to full system crashes.</p>
<p>

In addition, extensions sometimes competed for system resources with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/454746.xml">
applications</link>, utilities and other extensions, leading to <abnormality wordnetid="114501726" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<anomaly wordnetid="114505821" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/279631.xml">
crashes</link></anomaly>
</physical_condition>
</state>
</condition>
</abnormality>
 and general instability. The public perception of extension conflicts was a major factor in the Mac OS's reputation for instability before the <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
-based OS X was released.</p>
<p>

The problem of extension conflicts shouldn't be over-emphasized. Many users happily loaded every extension they could find on their computer, with little or no impact. Others fastidiously avoided any non-essential extensions as a way of avoiding the problem. Others were judicious in the addition of extensions.</p>
<p>

This problem became more serious through the mid-1990s as resource-hungry <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/20420.xml">
multimedia</link> technologies such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/25231.xml">
QuickTime</link></format>
</software>
 were installed as extensions. In addition, a number of applications, especially <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/20288.xml">
Microsoft Office</link></software>
, required a large number of extensions. Many Macintosh users had hundreds of extensions running on their systems, all of varying age and quality. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/37085.xml">
Buggy</link>, damaged and outdated extensions were the most common cause of problems. Some users had to remember to turn off problematic extensions when running certain programs. </p>
<p>

Later versions of System 7 included the <b>Extensions Manager</b>, which allowed users to turn off specific extensions or groups of extensions at startup. <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/4152616.xml">
Conflict Catcher</link></software>
, a third party utility, automatically detected conflicts and problematic extensions, otherwise a time-consuming task that required users to turn off extensions in sets until they found the conflict. Extensions were only loaded at startup time, meaning that any attempted change required a reboot.</p>
<p>

The most common time for extension conflicts to start was the release of a new version of the operating system, followed closely by the installation of a new application that either conflicted with existing extensions, or installed extensions that conflicted with the existing set.</p>
<p>

All of this was mitigated by the ease with which extensions and the operating system itself could be swapped in and out: Instead of modifying configuration files as on other operating systems, extensions simply had to reside in a particular folder to be picked up. In addition, the Mac was perfectly happy to have two (or more) system folders present on a hard drive. Only the "blessed" system folder would be loaded at startup. So, when a new version of the operating system was to be installed, or a new application, the user could easily duplicate the system folder, perform the install, and then fall back if a problem resulted.</p>
<p>

Extension conflicts came to an end with the release of Mac OS X, which uses a different extension mechanism.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/40948.xml">
Configuration management</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/1425449.xml">
Dependency management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<window wordnetid="104587648" confidence="0.8">
<supporting_structure wordnetid="104361095" confidence="0.8">
<framework wordnetid="103391770" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/59441.xml">
DLL hell</link></framework>
</supporting_structure>
</window>
</artifact>
</structure>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.drmac.net/tips/resolve_ec.html">
How to resolve an extension conflict</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
