<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:25:05[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Organizational patterns</title>
<id>19424660</id>
<revision>
<id>243163634</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T12:20:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jcoplien</username>
<id>5234324</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Patterns</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

Organizational patterns are recurring structures of relationship, usually in a professional organization, that help the organization achieve its goals.
The patterns are usually inspired by analyzing multiple professional organizations and finding common structures in their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social networks</link>.
Such patterns are collected and organized into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/182837.xml">
pattern language</link>s, which are published as a foundation for process improvement and organizational design, largely in the software development community.
Organizational pattern efforts since 1991 have led to a small body of literature and a community of research and support, both of which have close ties to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/164952.xml">
software pattern</link> community.
Organizational patterns broadly support <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/14371753.xml">
knowledge sharing</link> about <link>
organizational design</link> and support <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/1300192.xml">
corporate memory</link> of reorganizations and process changes.
They are often used as the foundation of project <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/1671672.xml">
retrospective</link>s.<p>

Organizational patterns are inspired in large part by the principles of the software pattern community, that in turn takes it cues from <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<architect wordnetid="109805475" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/7612.xml">
Christopher Alexander</link></creator>
</research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</architect>
</physical_entity>
's work on patterns of the built world.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
Organizational patterns also have roots in  <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/452673.xml">
Kroeber</link></person>
</anthropologist>
's classic anthropological texts on the patterns that underlie culture and society.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>
They in turn have provided inspiration for the Agile software development movement,
and for the creation of parts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/445396.xml">
Scrum</link> and of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/34193.xml">
XP</link> in particular.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

An early explicit citation to patterns of social structure can be found in the anthropological literature.</p>
<p>

Patterns are those arrangements or systems of internal relationship which give to any culture its coherence or plan, and keep it from being a mere accumulation of random bits.
They are therefore of primary importance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

<anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/452673.xml">
Kroeber</link></person>
</anthropologist>
 speaks of <it>universal patterns</it> that describe some overall scheme common to all human culture; of <it>systemic patterns</it> are broad but normative forms relating to beliefs, behaviors, signs, and economics; and <it>total culture patterns</it> that are local. <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/452673.xml">
Kroeber</link></person>
</anthropologist>
 notes that systemic patterns can pass from culture to culture:</p>
<p>

A second kind of pattern consists of a system or complex of cultural material that has proved its utility as a system and therefore tends to cohere and persist as a unit; it is modifiable only with difficulty as to its underlying plan. Any one such systemic pattern is limited primarily to one aspect of culture, such as subsistence, religion, or economics; but it is not limited areally, or to one particular culture; it can be diffused cross-culturally, from one people to another. . . . What distinguishes these systemic patterns of culture—or well-patterned systems, as they might also be called—is a specific interrelation of their component parts, a nexus that holds them together strongly, and tends to preserve the basic plan... As a result of the persistence of these systemic patterns, their significance becomes most evident on a historical view.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

The pattern aspect of <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/452673.xml">
Kroeber</link></person>
</anthropologist>
's view fits very well the systems-thinking pattern view of <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<architect wordnetid="109805475" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/7612.xml">
Christopher Alexander</link></creator>
</research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</architect>
</physical_entity>
 in the field of architecture.
Alexander's books became an inspiration for the software world, and in particular for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/22757.xml">
object-oriented programming</link> world, in about 1993.
Organizational patterns in the sense they are recognized in the software community today first made an appearance at the original <link>
Hillside Group</link> workshop that would lead to the pattern community and its <link>
PLoP</link> conferences.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

The <link>
Hillside Group</link> sent out a call for pattern papers and, in 1995, held the first pattern conference at Allerton Park in central Illinois in the United States.
The second conference, also at Allerton, would follow a year later.
These first two <link>
PLoP</link> conferences witnessed a handful of organizational patterns:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The RaPPEL pattern language (1995) by Bruce Whitenack that described organizational structures suitable to requirements acquisition; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Caterpillar's Fate pattern language (1995) by Norm Kerth that described organizational structures supporting evolution from analysis to design; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A work by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/653567.xml">
James Coplien</link></writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 (1995) describing several years of organizational research at Bell Laboratories; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Episodes, a pattern language by Ward Cunningham (1996) describing key points of what today we would call Agile software development; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A pattern language by Neil Harrison (1996) on the formation and function of teams. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A flurry of associated publications and follow-up articles followed quickly thereafter, including an extemporization of the organizational patterns approach in the Bell Labs Technical Journal,
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>
an invited piece in ASE,
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>
a CACM article by Alistair Cockburn
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>
and, shortly thereafter, a pattern-laden book by Alistair,
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>
as well as chapters by Benualdi
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>
and Janoff
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>
in the <it>Patterns Handbook.</it>
It was also about this time that Michael Beedle et al. published patterns that described explicit extensions to existing organizational patterns, for application in projects using a then five-year-old software development framework called Scrum.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>
A few more articles, such as the one by Brash et al.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>
also started to appear.</p>
<p>

Little more happened on the organizational patterns front until the publication of the book by Berczuk et all on configuration management patterns;
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>
this was a break-off effort from the effort originally centered at Bell Labs.</p>
<p>

In the mean time, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/653567.xml">
Jim Coplien</link></writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 and Neil Harrison had been collecting organizational patterns and combining them into a collection of four pattern languages.
Most of these patterns were based on the original research from Bell Laboratories, which studied over 120 organizations over the period of a decade.
These empirical studies were based on subject role-play in software development organizations, reminiscent of the sociodramas of <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/1812202.xml">
Moreno</link></scientist>
's original <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link> approach.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref>
However, the pattern language also had substantial input from other sources and in particular the works by Cockburn, Berczuk, and Cunningham.
This collection was published as <it>Organizational Patterns of Agile Software Development</it> in 2004.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>
<p>

One of the most recent organizational pattern articles comes from an early pattern contributor and advocate, the object design pioneer Grady Booch.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Principles of Discovery and Use </st>

<p>

Like other patterns, organizational patterns aren't created or invented: they are discovered (or "mined") from empirical observation.
The early work on organizational patterns at Bell Laboratories focused on extracting patterns from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link> analysis.
That research used empirical role-playing techniques to gather information about the structure of relationships in the subject organization.
These structures were analyzed for recurring patterns across organization and their contribution to achieving organizational goals.
The recurring successful structures were written up in <link>
pattern form</link> to describe their tradeoffs and detailed design decisions (forces), the context in which they apply, along with a generic description of the solution.</p>
<p>

Patterns provide an incremental path to organizational improvement.
The pattern style of building something (in this case, an organization) is:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Find the weakest part of your organization;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Find a pattern that is likely to strengthen it;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Apply the pattern;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Measure the improvement or degradation;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If the pattern improved things, go to step 1 and find the next improvement; otherwise, undo the pattern and try an alternative.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

As with Alexander-style patterns of software architecture, organizational patterns can be organized into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/182837.xml">
pattern language</link>s: collections of patterns that build on each other.
A pattern language can suggest the patterns to be applied for a known set of working patterns that are present.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Example </st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Organizational Patterns, Agile, and Other Work </st>

<p>

The history of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/1041120.xml">
Agile</link> software development and of organizational patterns have been entwined since the beginning.
Kent Beck was the shepherd (interactive pattern reviewer) of the Coplien paper for the 1995 <link>
PLoP</link>,
and he mentions the influence of this work on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/34193.xml">
XP</link> in a 2003 publication.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref>
The idea of daily Scrum meetings in fact came from a draft of an article for Dr. Dobb's Journal
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref>
that described the organizational patterns research on the Borland QPW project.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref>
Beedle's early work with Sutherland brought the pattern perspective more solidly into the history of Scrum.
More recently, the Scrum community has taken up newfound interest in organizational patterns
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref>
and there is joint research going forward between the two communities.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Alexander, Christopher. A Pattern Language. Oxford University Press, ©1979.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Kroeber, Alfred L. Anthropology: Culture, Patterns, and Process. New York: Harcourt, Brace and World, 1948.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Kroeber, op. cit., p. 119</entry>
<entry id="4">
Kroeber, op. cit., pp. 120 - 121.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Coplien, James. The Culture of Patterns. In Branislav Lazarevic, ed., Computer Science and Information Systems Journal 1, 2, Belgrade, Serbia and Montenegro, November 15, 2004, pp. 1-26.
</entry>
<entry id="6">
Whitenack, Bruce. RAPPeL: a requirements-analysis-process pattern language for object-oriented development.
In James Coplien and Doug Schmidt, eds., Pattern Languages of Program Design. Addison-Wesley, 1995, pp. 259 - 291.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Kerth, Norm. Caterpillar's Fate: a pattern language for the transformation from analysis to design.
In James Coplien and Doug Schmidt, eds., Pattern Languages of Program Design. Addison-Wesley, 1995, pp. 293 - 320.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Coplien, James. Organizational Patterns. In James Coplien and Doug Schmidt, eds., Pattern Languages of Program Design. Addison-Wesley, 1995, pp. 183 - 237.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Cunningham, Ward. Episodes: a pattern language of competitive development. In Vlissides et al, eds., Pattern Languages of Program Design - 2. Addison-Wesley, 1996, pp. 371 - 388.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Harrison, Neil. Organizational Patterns for Teams. In Vlissides et al, eds., Pattern Languages of Program Design - 2. Addison-Wesley, 1996, pp. 345 - 352.</entry>
<entry id="11">
Harrison, Neil B. and James O. Coplien. Patterns of productive software organizations. Bell Labs Technical Journal, 1(1):138-145, Summer (September) 1996.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Cain, Brendan G., James O. Coplien, and Neil B. Harrison. Social Patterns in Productive Software Organizations. In John T. McGregor, editor, Annals of Software Engineering, 259-286. Baltzer Science Publishers, Amsterdam, December 1996.</entry>
<entry id="13">
Cockburn, Alistair. The interaction of social issues and software architecture.
CACM 39(10), October 1996.
</entry>
<entry id="14">
Cockburn, Alistair. Surviving Object-Oriented Projects. Addison-Wesley, 1997.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Genualdi, Patricia. Improving software development with process and organizational patterns.
In Linda Rising, ed. The Patterns Handbook. Cambridge University Press, 1998, pp. 121 - 129.</entry>
<entry id="17">
Michael A. Beedle, Martine Devos, Yonat Sharon, Ken Schwaber, and Jeff Sutherland. SCRUM: An extension pattern 
language for hyperproductive software development. Washington University Technical Report TR #WUCS-98-25, 1998.
</entry>
<entry id="16">
Janoff, Norm. Organizational patterns at AG communication systems.
In Linda Rising, ed. The Patterns Handbook. Cambridge University Press, 1998, pp. 131 - 138.</entry>
<entry id="19">
Berczuk, Steve, Brad Appleton and Kyle Brown. Software Configuration Management Patterns: Effective Teamwork, Practical Integration. Addison-Wesley, 2003.</entry>
<entry id="18">
Brash, Danny, et al. Evaluating organizational patterns for supporting business knowledge management.
Proceedings of the 2000 information resources management association international conference on Challenges of information technology management in the 21st century. IGI Publishing, May 2000.
</entry>
<entry id="21">
Coplien, James and Neil Harrison. Patterns of Agile Software Development. Addison-Wesley, ©2004.</entry>
<entry id="20">
Moreno, J. L. Who shall survive?: foundations of sociometry, group psychotherapy and sociodrama. Washington, D.C.: Nervous and Metnal Disease Publishing Co., 1934.
</entry>
<entry id="23">
Fraser, Steven, Kent Beck, Bill Caputo, Tim Mackinnon, James Newkirk and Charlie Pool. “Test Driven Development (TDD).” In M. Marchesi and G. Succi, eds., XP 2003, LNCS 2675, pp. 459 — 462, 2003. © Springer-Verlag, Berlin and Heidelberg, 2003.</entry>
<entry id="22">
Booch, Grady.
Architectural Organizational Patterns.
IEEE Software 25(3), May 2008, pp. 18 - 19. 
</entry>
<entry id="25">
Sutherland, Jeff.  Origins of Scrum. Web page <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jeffsutherland.com/scrum/2007/07/origins-of-scrum.html">
http://jeffsutherland.com/scrum/2007/07/origins-of-scrum.html</weblink>, accessed 22 September 2008. July 5, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="24">
Coplien, James O., and Jon Erickson. Examining the Software Development Process. Dr. Dobb's Journal of Software Tools, 19(11):88-95, October 1994.
</entry>
<entry id="26">
Sutherland, Jeff. Scrum and Organizational Patterns. Web page <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jeffsutherland.com/scrum/2008/02/scrum-and-organizational-patterns.html">
http://jeffsutherland.com/scrum/2008/02/scrum-and-organizational-patterns.html</weblink>,
accessed 22 September 2008. February 2, 2008.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
