<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:08:34[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<site  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108651247">
<hill  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="109303008">
<structure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104341686">
<building  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="102913152">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<header>
<title>Monte Testaccio</title>
<id>1946321</id>
<revision>
<id>241972777</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T09:19:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>AlleborgoBot</username>
<id>3813685</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Economy of ancient Rome</category>
<category>Roman sites of the Lazio</category>
<category>Pottery</category>
<category>Hills of Rome</category>
<category>Ancient Roman buildings and structures in Rome</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="width: 250px; font-size: 85%;" align="right" cellpadding="4" class="infobox bordered">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style="background-color: #E0E0BB; font-size: larger;" align="center">
 <image width="30px" src="SPQRomani.svg">
</image>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<b>Monte Testaccio</b></header>
</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="text-align: center;">
 <image width="250px" src="Testaccio_monte_dei_cocci_051204-12-13.JPG">

</image>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
Location</header>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/2655214.xml">
Regione XIII <it>Aventinus''</it></link></col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
Built in</header>
<col>
1st century BC (?) to3rd century AD</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
Built by/for</header>
<col>
n/a</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
Type of structure</header>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/2417700.xml">
Waste mound</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" align="center">
<p>

<image width="250px" src="Roma_Plan.jpg">
</image>
 
<image width="10px" src="Blue_pog.svg">
</image>
<b>Monte Testaccio</b></p>
</col>
</row>
</table>

<b>Monte Testaccio</b> (alternatively spelled <b>Monte Testaceo</b>; also known as <b>Monte dei cocci</b>) is an artificial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/2417700.xml">
mound</link> in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/25458.xml">
Rome</link></village>
</site>
 composed almost entirely of <it>testae</it> (<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/14708.xml">
Italian</link></language>
: <it>cocci</it>), fragments of broken <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../812/51812.xml">
amphora</link>e dating from the time of the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/25507.xml">
Roman Empire</link></country>
, some of which were labelled with <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/3743406.xml">
tituli picti</link></it>. It is one of the largest spoil heaps found anywhere in the ancient world, covering an area of 20,000&nbsp;square metres (220,000&nbsp;sq&nbsp;ft) at its base and with a volume of approximately 580,000&nbsp;cubic metres (760,000&nbsp;cu&nbsp;yd). It has a circumference of nearly a kilometre (0.6&nbsp;mi) and stands 35&nbsp;metres (115&nbsp;ft) high, though it was probably considerably higher in ancient times.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> It stands a short distance away from the east bank of the River <river wordnetid="109411430" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/30359.xml">
Tiber</link></river>
, near the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/16791421.xml">
Horrea Galbae</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 where the state-controlled reserve of olive oil was stored in the late second century AD.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The mound later had both religious and military significance.
<sec>
<st>
Structure and purpose</st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="150px" src="Testaccio_monte_dei_cocci_a_via_Galvani_051204-02.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Terraces on Monte Testaccio
</caption>
</image>

The huge numbers of broken amphorae at Monte Testaccio provides a vivid indication of the colossal amount of food that was required to sustain imperial Rome, which was at the time the world's largest city with a population of at least one million people. It has been estimated that the hill contains the remains of as many as 53&nbsp;million <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link> amphorae, in which some 6&nbsp;billion litres (1.3&nbsp;billion imperial gallons/1.6&nbsp;billion U.S. gallons) of oil were imported.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Studies of the hill's composition suggest that Rome's imports of olive oil reached a peak towards the end of the second century AD, when as many as 130,000 amphorae were being deposited on the site each year. The vast majority of those vessels had a capacity of some 70&nbsp;litres (15&nbsp;imp gal/18&nbsp;U.S. gal); from this it has been estimated that Rome was importing at least 7.5&nbsp;million liters (1.6&nbsp;million imperial gal/2&nbsp;million U.S. gal) of olive oil annually. As the vessels found at Monte Testaccio appear to represent mainly state-sponsored olive oil imports, it is very likely that considerable additional quantities of olive oil were imported privately.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Monte Testaccio was not simply a haphazard waste dump; it was clearly a highly organised and carefully engineered creation, presumably managed by a state administrative authority. Excavations carried out in 1991 showed that the mound had been raised as a series of level terraces with retaining walls made of nearly intact amphorae filled with sherds to anchor them in place. Empty amphorae were probably carried up the mound intact on the backs of donkeys or mules and then broken up on the spot, with the sherds laid out in a stable pattern. Lime appears to have been sprinkled over the broken pots to neutralise the smell of rancid oil.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

As the oldest parts of Monte Testaccio are, naturally, at the bottom of the mound, it is difficult to say with any certainty when it was first created. Deposits found by excavators have been dated to a period between approximately AD 140 to 250, but it is possible that dumping could have begun on the site as early as the first century BC. The mound has a roughly triangular shape comprising two distinct platforms, the eastern side being the oldest. At least four distinct series of terraces were built in a stepped arrangement. Layers of small sherds were laid down in some places, possibly to serve as paths for those carrying out the waste disposal operations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Re-use and disposal of amphorae</st>

<p>

The hill was constructed using mostly the fragments of large globular 70-litre (15&nbsp;imp gal/18&nbsp;U.S. gal) vessels from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/770608.xml">
Baetica</link> (the <stream wordnetid="109448361" confidence="0.8">
<body_of_water wordnetid="109225146" confidence="0.8">
<river wordnetid="109411430" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/68692.xml">
Guadalquivir</link></river>
</body_of_water>
</stream>
 region of modern <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
), of a type known as Dressel 20. It also included smaller numbers of two types of amphorae from <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<see wordnetid="108586825" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108654360" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/664792.xml">
Tripolitania</link></district>
</state>
</location>
</seat>
</see>
</administrative_district>
</area>
</center>
</region>
 (Libya) and <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108654360" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/1386128.xml">
Byzacena</link></district>
</state>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 (Tunisia). All three types of vessel were used to transport olive oil. However, it is not clear why Monte Testaccio was built using only olive oil vessels. The oil itself was probably decanted into bulk containers when the amphorae were unloaded at the port, in much the same way as other staples such as grain. There is no equivalent mound of broken grain or wine amphorae and the overwhelming majority of the amphorae found at Monte Testaccio are of one single type, which raises the question of why the Romans found it necessary to dispose of the amphorae in this way.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

One possibility is that the Dressel 20 amphora, the principal type found at Monte Testaccio, may have been unusually difficult to recycle. Many types of amphora could be re-used to carry the same type of product or modified to serve a different purpose—for instance, as drain pipes or flower pots. Fragmentary amphorae could be pounded into chips to use in <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/6034513.xml">
opus signinum</link></it>, a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/5371.xml">
concrete</link> widely used as a building material, or could simply be used as landfill. The Dressel 20 amphora, however, broke into large curved fragments that could not readily be reduced to small sherds. It is likely that the difficulty of reusing or repurposing the Dressel 20s meant that it was more economical to discard them.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<it>Tituli picti''</it></st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Tituli_picti_dressel.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A Dressel 20 amphora with examples of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/3743406.xml">
tituli picti</link></it> and potters' stamps found at Monte Testaccio
</caption>
</image>

Monte Testaccio has provided archaeologists with a rare insight into the ancient Roman economy. The amphorae deposited in the mound were often labelled with <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/3743406.xml">
tituli picti</link></it>, painted or stamped inscriptions which record information such as the weight of the oil contained in the vessel, the names of the people who weighed and documented the oil and the name of the district where the oil was originally bottled. This has allowed archaeologists to determine that the oil in the vessels was imported under state authority and was designated for the <it>annona urbis</it> (distribution to the people of Rome) or the <it>annona militaris</it> (distribution to the army).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Indeed, some of the inscriptions found on mid-second century vessels at Monte Testaccio specifically record that the oil they once contained was delivered to the <it>praefectus annonae</it>, the official in charge of the state-run food distribution service. It is possible that Monte Testaccio was also managed by the <it>praefectus annonae</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

The <it>tituli picti</it> on the Monte Testaccio amphorae tend to follow a standard pattern and indicate a rigorous system of inspection to control trade and deter fraud. An amphora was first weighed while empty, and its weight was marked on the outside of the vessel. The name of the export merchant was then noted, followed by a line giving the weight of the oil contained in the amphora (subtracting the previously determined weight of the vessel itself). Those responsible for carrying out and monitoring the weighing then signed their names on the amphora and the location of the farm from which the oil originated was also noted. The maker of the amphora was often identified by a stamp on the vessel's handle.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> </p>
<p>

The inscriptions also provide evidence of the structure of the oil export business. Apart from single names, many inscriptions list combinations such as "the two Aurelii Heraclae, father and son", "the Fadii", "Cutius Celsianus and Fabius Galaticus", "the two Junii, Melissus and Melissa", "the partners Hyacinthus, Isidore and Pollio", "L. Marius Phoebus and the Vibii, Viator and Retitutus." This suggests that many of those involved were members of joint enterprises, perhaps small workshops involving business partners, father-son teams and skilled <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/13149886.xml">
freedmen</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Later history</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Testaccio_1625.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

The Testaccio district in 1625, showing Monte Testaccio surrounded by wasteland
</caption>
</image>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Monte_testaccio_novecento.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Monte Testaccio in the 19th century
</caption>
</image>

The use of Monte Testaccio as an amphora dump appears to have ceased after about the 260s, perhaps due to the city's harbour facilities being moved elsewhere. A new type of amphora was also introduced around this time to transport olive oil.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

The area around the hill was largely abandoned after the fall of Rome. A print of 1625 depicts Monte Testaccio standing in isolation in an area of wasteland within the ancient city walls,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> and even as late as the mid-19th century the surrounding area was little more than a "romantic desert" on which was situated only "a few shabby houses".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> It was the scene of jousts and tournaments during the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/18836.xml">
Middle Ages</link>, when Monte Testaccio was the scene of pre-<fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<time wordnetid="115122231" confidence="0.8">
<festival wordnetid="115162388" confidence="0.8">
<day wordnetid="115123115" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/39726.xml">
Lent</link></day>
</festival>
</time>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
en celebrations. As part of the festivities, two carts filled with pigs were hauled to the top of the hill, then allowed to run back down the steep slope to be smashed to pieces along with their porcine passengers. The watching revellers would then dismember the pigs on the spot and carry the parts off to be roasted and eaten.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

Monte Testaccio was still used as a place of recreation when <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/26773.xml">
Stendhal</link></writer>
</person>
 visited in 1827.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> A  19th century traveller, visiting a few years earlier, described the annual festival that was held on the summit of the hill:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

"Each Sunday and Thursday during the month of October, almost the whole population of Rome, rich and poor, throng to this spot, where innumerable tables are covered with refreshments, and the wine is drawn cool from the vaults. It is impossible to conceive a more animating scene than the summit of the hill presents. Gay groups dancing the <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<form wordnetid="106290637" confidence="0.8">
<art wordnetid="102743547" confidence="0.8">
<word wordnetid="106286395" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<dance wordnetid="107020538" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/2154883.xml">
saltarella</link></language_unit>
</dance>
</part>
</word>
</art>
</form>
</artifact>
</creation>
, intermingled with the jovial circles which surround the tables; the immense crowd of walkers who, leaving their carriages below, stroll about to enjoy the festive scene ..."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>
</indent>

The hill gained a brief military significance in 1849 when it was used as the site of an Italian gun battery, under the command of <soldier wordnetid="110622053" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/36931.xml">
Giuseppe Garibaldi</link></person>
</soldier>
, in the successful defence of Rome against an attacking French army.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> Its economic significance was somewhat greater, as the hill's interior was discovered to have unusual cooling properties which investigators attributed to the ventilation produced by its porous structure. This made it ideal for wine storage and caves were excavated to keep wine cool in the heat of the Roman summer. </p>
<p>

Monte Testaccio also had a religious significance; it was formerly used on <vacation wordnetid="115137890" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/58009.xml">
Good Friday</link></vacation>
 to represent the hill of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/387583.xml">
Golgotha</link> in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<capital wordnetid="108518505" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<see wordnetid="108586825" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/16043.xml">
Jerusalem</link></urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</seat>
</see>
</area>
</center>
</city>
</capital>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, when the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<duty wordnetid="100719494" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<function wordnetid="100720565" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/23056.xml">
Pope</link></function>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</duty>
</work>
 would lead a procession to the summit and placed crosses to represent those of <information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<inflammation wordnetid="114336539" confidence="0.8">
<punishment wordnetid="101160342" confidence="0.8">
<appearance wordnetid="107321772" confidence="0.8">
<belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<laminitis wordnetid="114348895" confidence="0.8">
<happening wordnetid="107283608" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="105823932" confidence="0.8">
<corporal_punishment wordnetid="101161161" confidence="0.8">
<execution wordnetid="101163779" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_control wordnetid="101123598" confidence="0.8">
<deity wordnetid="109505418" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<symptom wordnetid="114299637" confidence="0.8">
<manifestation wordnetid="107323231" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/1095706.xml">
Jesus</link></manifestation>
</symptom>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</spiritual_being>
</deity>
</social_control>
</event>
</group_action>
</execution>
</corporal_punishment>
</evidence>
</happening>
</laminitis>
</belief>
</appearance>
</punishment>
</inflammation>
</information>
 and the two thieves crucified alongside him. Monte Testaccio is still crowned with a cross in commemoration of the event. It was not until after <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
World War II</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
 that the area around the hill was redeveloped as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/18247421.xml">
working class</link> neighbourhood.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>
<p>

The first archaeological investigation of Monte Testaccio began in January 1872 under the German archaeologist <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<archeologist wordnetid="109804806" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/4530096.xml">
Heinrich Dressel</link></scientist>
</archeologist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</person>
</anthropologist>
</physical_entity>
, who published his results in a pioneering study in 1878. Further important work was carried out in the 1980s by the Spanish archaeologists Emilio Rodríguez Almeida and José Remesal Almeida.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/949245.xml">
Roman commerce</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/640999.xml">
Urban archaeology</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Claridge, Amanda (1998). <it>Rome: An Oxford Archaeological Guide</it>, First, Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press, 1998, p. 367–368. ISBN 0192880039</entry>
<entry id="2">
J. Theodore Peña, <it>Roman pottery in the archaeological record</it>, p. 300–306. Cambridge University Press, 2007. ISBN 0521865417</entry>
<entry id="3">
Lynne C. Lancaster, <it>Concrete Vaulted Construction in Imperial Rome: Innovations in Context</it>, p. 81. Cambridge University Press, 2005. ISBN 0521842026</entry>
<entry id="4">
Bryan Ward-Perkins, <it>The Fall of Rome: And the End of Civilization</it>, pp. 91–92. Oxford University Press, 2005. ISBN 0192807285.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Julian Bennett, <it>Trajan: Optimus Princeps : A Life and Times</it>, p. 2. Routledge, 1997. ISBN 0415165245</entry>
<entry id="6">
See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/4162307.xml">
Grain supply to the city of Rome</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
David Stone Potter, <it>A Companion to the Roman Empire</it>, p. 293. Blackwell Publishing, 2006. ISBN 0631226443</entry>
<entry id="8">
J. A. Crook, <it>Law and Life of Rome</it>, p. 229. Cornell University Press, 1994. ISBN 0801492734</entry>
<entry id="9">
Mireille Corbier, "Coinage, society and economy", in <it>The Cambridge Ancient History</it> 2nd edition vol. XII, p. 403. Eds. Alan K. Bowman, Peter Garney &amp; Averil Cameron. Cambridge University Press, 2005. ISBN 0521301998</entry>
<entry id="10">
George Macaulay Trevelyan, <it>Garibaldi's Defense of the Roman Republic 1848 to 1849</it>, p. 201. Longmans, 1907</entry>
<entry id="11">
Paul Hetherington, <it>Medieval Rome: A Portrait of the City and Its Life</it>, p. 29. Rubicon Press, 1994. ISBN 0948695331</entry>
<entry id="12">
Matilda Webb, <it>The Churches and Catacombs of Early Christian Rome: A Comprehensive Guide</it>, p. 205. Sussex Academic Press, 2001. ISBN 1902210581</entry>
<entry id="13">
Selina Martin, <it>Narrative of a Three Years' Residence in Italy, 1819-1822</it>, pp. 126–127. W.F. Wakeman, 1831</entry>
<entry id="14">
Frank J. Korn, <it>Hidden Rome</it>, pp.86–87. Paulist Press, 2003. ISBN 0809141094</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dressel, H. 1878. <it>Ricerche sul monte testaccio.</it> Rome : Salviucci, 1878.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rodriguez Almeida, E. 1980. "Alcuni aspetti della topografia e dell' archeologia attorno al monte Testaccio." In JM Blazquez Martinez, ed. <it>Produccion y comercio del aceite en la antiguedad</it> (Madrid): 103-31. ISBN 8474910250</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rodriguez Almeida, E. 1984. <it>Il Monte Testaccio, ambiente, storia, materiale.</it> Rome: Quasar. ISBN 8885020577</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rodriguez Almeida, E. &amp; Remesal Almeida, José. 1994. <it>Excavaciones arqueológicas en el Monte Testaccio (Roma).</it> Madrid : Ministerio de Cultura, Dirección General de Bellas Artes y Archivos, Instituto de Conservación y Restauración de Bienes Culturales. ISBN 8481810061</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/48361.xml">
Coordinates</link>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stable.toolserver.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Monte_Testaccio&amp;params=41_52_33.4266_N_12_28_32.4984_E_region:IT-RM_type:landmark">
41°52′33.4266″N 12°28′32.4984″E﻿ / ﻿41.875951833, 12.475694</weblink>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.testaccio.roma.it">
Story, Pictures and song of Monte Testaccio</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ceipac.gh.ub.es/MOSTRA/u_expo.htm">
Monte Testaccio website by Universitat de Roma "La Sapienza" and Universitat de Barcelona</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=41.875952,12.475694&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=41.8761,12.475458&amp;spn=0.002892,0.007167&amp;t=k&amp;z=18">
Satellite view of Monte Testaccio</weblink> (Google Maps)</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
</hill>
</site>
</article>
