<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:28:51[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Deep Freeze (software)</title>
<id>19484779</id>
<revision>
<id>242518012</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T15:51:43Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Stifle</username>
<id>473485</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Deep Freeze</b> is an application suite for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>, and <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 by Faronics Corporation. Deep Freeze gives <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/154985.xml">
administrators</link> the ability to protect the core <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> files and configuration files of an environment without eliminating the usability for (most) end users.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<sec>
<st>
Use</st>
<p>

Deep Freeze protects the computer by utilizing a separate <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/55380.xml">
partition</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard disk drive</link> for write back. When the computer is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/241972.xml">
rebooted</link>, this partition is treated empty again and existing information on it is unaccessible. This allows users to make 'virtual' changes to the system, giving them the appearance that they can modify core files or even delete them, and even make the system unusable to themselves, but upon reboot the 'frozen' state of the operating system is restored.</p>
<p>

To make changes, a system administrator must 'unfreeze' the system partition, make any needed changes, and 'freeze' it again. These changes, in this way, are saved to the protected partition instead of the 'unfrozen' write back partition.</p>
<p>

While Deep Freeze will allow users to have the comfort of virtually modifying the system as they like, it does not control the programming of individual applications that are installed. If, for example, a user account under Windows is a 'limited' account, regardless if the users can actually effect some files or not, some application installers will assume the user can not and inform them they must be an administrator. In some applications, this can be bypassed by working in 'Windows 98 Compatibility mode', which has no such user restrictions that programs typically mind, but many application installers still find trouble with this.</p>
<p>

Deep Freeze only protects the operating system in a 'fresh booted' state. The protections the software offers can often be bypassed, for example, by installing a malicious, system wide application, especially if other users find this application popular and accept that it being installed when they log in means it is authentic. One user could install a modified version of a popular web browser that's been designed to save passwords to a server on the internet, then log out, then other users who log in would see that browser and may use it out of preference. To use the computer more safely, the user would have to restart the computer first.</p>
<p>

Deep Freeze also can not protect against direct access to a disk drive when the hosting operating system is not in control of the system. That is, if another operating system can be boot from another <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard disk</link>, a <link>
USB device</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/41458.xml">
optical media</link>, they will have real access to the contents of the frozen and unfrozen partitions. This may be protected against by setting the first hard disk as the only bootable hard disk and password protecting the BIOS configuration, but if physical access to the computer is available, this can be bypassed with a BIOS reset or rearranging the hard drive installation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.faronics.com/html/deepfreeze.asp">
http://www.faronics.com/html/deepfreeze.asp</weblink></entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Aaron Ricadela (June 28, 2005) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/management/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=164903260">
<it>Microsoft Tests Tool For Computer Classrooms''</it></weblink> <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/13200877.xml">
InformationWeek</link></magazine>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Jonathan Blum (January 14, 2008) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://money.cnn.com/2008/01/14/smbusiness/macworld.fsb/?postversion=2008011412">
<it>Macworld preview: New tools for small biz''</it></weblink> <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/16922134.xml">
Fortune Small Business</link></publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</press>
</creation>
</print_media>
</magazine>
</product>
</work>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.faronics.com/">
Faronics Home Page</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
