<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:17:11[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Marr Prize</title>
<id>19521901</id>
<revision>
<id>241775839</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-29T14:30:52Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jiuguang Wang</username>
<id>2430726</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Science and engineering awards</category>
<category>Computer vision</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Marr Prize</b> is a prestigious award in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/6596.xml">
computer vision</link> given by the committee of the International Conference on Computer Vision. Named after <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<neurobiologist wordnetid="110353928" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<neuroscientist wordnetid="110354580" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/417031.xml">
David Marr</link></research_worker>
</neuroscientist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</neurobiologist>
</biologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, the Marr Prize is considered one of the top honors for a computer vision researcher. 
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 At the moment this article is only a list. This list itself does not provide the information that this article should include. Please help Wikipedia by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Marr_Prize&amp;action=edit">
expanding this article</weblink>, and once it is a sufficient article please remove this message.</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
Papers</st>

<ss1>
<st>
1st ICCV, 1987, London, United Kingdom</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Paper: David Heeger, Optical Flow using Spatiotemporal Filters </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Honorable Mention Papers: </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 John Tsotsos, A `Complexity Level' Analysis of Immediate Vision</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Michael Kass, Andrew Witkin, and Demetri Terzopoulos, Snakes: Active Contour Models</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Yiannis Aloimonos and Issac Weiss, Active Vision</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
2nd ICCV, 1988, Tampa, U.S.A.</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Paper: Brian Funt and Jian Ho, Color from Black and White </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Honorable Mention Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 David Lowe, Organization of Smooth Image Curves at Multiple Scales</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Vishvjit Nalwa, Representing Oriented Piecewise C2 Surfaces </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
3rd ICCV, 1990, Osaka, Japan</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Paper: Shree Nayar, Katsushi Ikeuchi, and Takeo Kanade, Shape from Interreflections </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
4th ICCV, 1993, Berlin, Germany</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Charles A. Rothwell, David A. Forsyth, Andrew Zisserman, and Joseph L. Mundy, Extracting Projective Structure from Single Perspective Views of 3D Point Sets </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
5th ICCV, 1995, Cambridge, U.S.A.</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Michael Oren and Shree Nayar, A Theory of Specular Surface Geometry</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Toshikazu Wada, Hiroyuki Ukida, and Takashi Matsuyama, Shape from Shading with Interreflections under a Proximal Light Source: Distortion-Free Copying of an Unfolded Book </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Honorable Mention Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Paul Viola and William Wells III, Alignment by Maximization of Mutual Information</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Anders Heyden, Reconstruction from Image Sequences by Means of Relative Depths</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Yalin Xiong and Steven Shafer, Hypergeometric Filters for Optical Flow and Affine Matching </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
6th ICCV, 1998, Bombay, India</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Marc Pollefeys, Reinhard Koch, and Luc Van Gool, Self-Calibration and Metric Reconstruction in spite of Varying and Unknown Internal Camera Parameters</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Phil Torr, Andrew Fitzgibbon, and Andrew Zisserman, The Problem of Degeneracy in Structure and Motion Recovery from Uncalibrated Image Sequences </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Honorable Mention Paper: Richard Szeliski and Polina Golland, Stereo Matching with Transparency and Matting</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
7th ICCV, 1999, Kerkyra, Greece</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Kiriakos Kutulakos and Steven Seitz, A Theory of Shape by Space Carving</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Yi Ma, Stefano Soatto, Jana Kosecka, and Shankar Sastry, Euclidean Reconstruction and Reprojection up to Subgroups </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Honorable Mention Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Michael Black and David Fleet, Probabilistic Detection and Tracking of Motion Discontinuities</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Ying Nian Wu and Song-Chun Zhu, Equivalence of Texture Modeling and Analysis? </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
8th ICCV, 2001, Vancouver, Canada</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Kentaro Toyama and Andrew Blake, Probabilistic Tracking in a Metric Space</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Steven Seitz, The Space of All Stereo Images </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Honorable Mention Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Yaron Caspi and Michal Irani, Alignment of Non-Overlapping Sequences</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Lior Wolf and Amnon Shashua, On Projection Matrices and their Applications in Computer Vision </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
9th ICCV, 2003, Nice, France</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Papers</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Andrew Fitzgibbon, Yonatan Wexler, and Andrew Zisserman, Image-based Rendering using Image-based Priors</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Zhuowen Tu, Xiangrong Chen, Alan L. Yuille, and Song-Chun Zhu, Image Parsing: Unifying Segmentation, Detection and Recognition</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Paul Viola, Michael J. Jones, and Daniel Snow, Detecting Pedestrians using Patterns of Motion and Appearance </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
10th ICCV, 2005, Beijing, China</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Paper: "Globally Optimal Estimates for Geometric Reconstruction Problems", Fredrik Kahl, Didier Henrion </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Honorable Mention</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 "A Theory of Refractive and Specular Shape by Light-Path Triangulation", Kiriakos N. Kutulakos, Eron Steger</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 "Detecting Irregularities in Images and in Video", Oren Boiman, Michal Irani</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 "On the Spatial Statistics of Optical Flow", Stefan Roth, Michael J. Black</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
11th ICCV, 2007, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marr Prize Paper: Bradley Davis, P. Thomas Fletcher, Elizabeth Bullitt, Sarang Joshi: Population Shape Regression From Random Design Data </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Honorable Mention:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Ying Nian Wu, Zhangzhang Si, Chuck Fleming, Song-Chun Zhu: Deformable Template As Active Basis</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Abhijeet Ghosh, Shruthi Achutha, Wolfgang Heidrich, Matthew O'Toole: BRDF Acquisition with Basis Illumination</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Manmohan Chandraker, Sameer Agarwal, David Kriegman, Serge Belongie: Globally Optimal Affine and Metric Upgrades in Stratified Autocalibration</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.isbe.man.ac.uk/~bim/CVPeople/prize_papers.html">
Award history</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
