<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:29:15[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>RCR Wireless News</title>
<id>19525715</id>
<revision>
<id>242048553</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T18:21:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cthemphill</username>
<id>7966995</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>RCR Wireless News</b> Group publishes a portfolio of media and information products enabling intelligence on all things wireless for industry leaders and enterprise volume buyers. Published since 1981, RCR Wireless News, a weekly print product, and RCRWireless.com, a daily electronic product, report on the entire wireless communications ecosystem. The newspaper is also the official show daily for some of the industry's biggest trade shows, including CTIA in the spring and fall and WiMAX World, and it is the Consumer Electronics Show’s official wireless publication. RCR Wireless News’ target audience is executive and managerial-level professionals at leading wireless industry organizations and volume buyers at enterprise-class organizations. RCR Wireless News is owned by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/6132011.xml">
Crain Communications Inc</link>., the publisher of over 30 titles including <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/3468467.xml">
Advertising Age</link></magazine>
, B2B, Automotive News, <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/643024.xml">
AutoWeek</link></publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</press>
</creation>
</print_media>
</magazine>
</product>
</work>
, Crain's City Business Publications, and <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/15629452.xml">
TelevisionWeek</link></magazine>
.  
<sec>
<st>
 Editorial </st>
<p>

RCR Wireless News’ world-class <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section&amp;template=editorialTeam">
editorial team</weblink>, is led by the respected <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/Columnists?tag=Tracy%20Ford&amp;tagid=3588">
Tracy Ford</weblink>, and since 1981 has produced the premier news source for the wireless communications industry. The editorial team is geared to stay on top of all of the breaking news in the wireless ecosystem and aims to be first to publish the most important news of the day. It is our dedication to editorial excellence that leads executives to consistently choose RCR Wireless News over other industry publications. Fifteen years of successive readership studies conducted by third-party polling firms over independent lists have consistently shown the preference for the RCR Wireless News brand as the best read, most relied on and most respected publication and Web site in the industry. The most recent study,(8) in July 2008, polling attendees of the industry association’s leading event, CTIA, concludes that RCR Wireless News is the preferred and most trusted media brand.  </p>

<p>

Editorial coverage of the entire wireless communications ecosystem is balanced among industry, technology and business topics and is delivered through news, analysis, features, business reports and product-oriented content. Information published is organized around principal content areas including wireless carriers, distributors/retailers, networks, handsets, spectrum, regulations, mobile content, the iPhone and iPhone killers, mobile advertising, mobile search mobile applications development and mobile applications in business.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Audience </st>
<p>

Core audience:  Now estimated at more than 250,000 unique readers each month, comprised of senior industry leaders and IT managers and corporate executives at major telecom carriers, network providers, telecom manufacturers, distributors and retailers, and enterprise-volume end users &amp; government regulatory agencies. The newspaper has a primary subscriber base of 50,000 (1) and considering pass-along copies (2) we are delivering a universe of 150,000 with the print newspaper.  RCR Wireless News has virtually 100% coverage of U.S.-based wireless service providers.  The RCRWireless.com website serves more than 130,000 unique visitors each month.(7) and electronic newsletters are delivered to a registered audience exceeding 70,000 each day.(3) Special alerts are also produced so that wireless industry professionals can stay informed on industry happenings when critical news breaks.</p>

<p>

The market served is projected to be a $100 billion technology opportunity.(5)  Nearly 90% of RCR Wireless News subscribers are actively involved in purchasing and making buying decisions on a wide range of wireless telecom and computing technologies and business and professional services.(3)
•	More than $800 million of these products and services are due to be purchased by our subscribers' organizations to support their wireless projects this year. (5)
•	86% of subscribers’ companies will be spending on Computer Hardware
•	85% of subscribers’ companies will be spending on Subscriber Equipment: Handset Devices and Accessories
•	77% of subscribers’ companies will be spending on Network Software
•	69% of subscribers’ companies will be spending on Network Infrastructure
•	63% of subscribers’ companies will be spending on Device Components 
•	61% of subscribers’ companies will be spending on OSS/Billing Services </p>

<p>

RCR Wireless News publishes information in a variety of media (print, web, video, 
e-mail, events), offering multiple points of entry, frequency and customization that can be integrated and scaled to fit any budget level or marketing objective.</p>

<p>

RCR Wireless News subscribers turn to us for information they don’t get elsewhere and 93% regularly read the newspaper each week.  RCRWireless.com readers typically return to the site one to three times per week, spending more than a half hour.(2)  Other publications or Web sites most regularly read or visited by our subscribers are, respectively: Wireless Week at 54%, Wall Street Journal at 33%, Telephony at 30%, and Fierce Wireless and CTIA SmartBrief, both at 18%(2). </p>
<p>

Share of Advertising Market (4) – RCR Wireless News is the market leader, carrying 75% of the display advertising in 2008.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Online Sections </st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/spectrum_auction/">
Spectrum Auction</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/cell_phone_accessories/">
Cell Phone Accessories</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/iphone_iphone_killers/">
iPhone / iPhone Killers</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/wireless_technology/">
Wireless Technology</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/wireless_networks/">
Wireless Networks</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mobile_content/">
Mobile Content</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/wireless_providers/">
Wireless Providers</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mobile_devices/">
Mobile Devices</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mobile_banking/">
Mobile Banking</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mobile_entertainment/">
Mobile Entertainment</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/wireless_facts_and_figures/">
Wireless Facts and Figures</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/associations/">
Associations</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mobile_video_and_tv/">
Mobile Video and TV</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/quarterly_earnings/">
Quarterly Earnings</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/opinion/">
Opinion</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mvno/">
MVNO</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mobile_phone_advertising/">
Mobile Phone Advertising</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/wireless_internet/">
Wireless Internet</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/fcc_wireless_regulation/">
FCC Wireless Regulation</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/wireless_retailers/">
Wireless Retailers</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mobile_search/">
Mobile Search</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/mobile_enterprise_in_business/">
Mobile Enterprise in Business</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/wireless_m2m_telemetry/">
Wireless M2M Telemetry</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/location_based_services/">
Location Based Services</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcrwireless.com/section/wireless_application_developers/">
Wireless Application Developers</weblink> </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>
 
(1)	BPA Circulation Statement, Dec, 2007</p>
<p>

(2)	Advantage Research RCRWN Subscriber Profile, 2/07</p>
<p>

(3)	RCRWN Registered Audience/Subscriber Analysis, 7/08</p>
<p>

(4)	IMS eBasket report on advertising in wireless publications, Jan. thru June, 2008</p>
<p>

(5)	Yankee Group/RCRW market study 7/08</p>
<p>

(6)	Synthesis of data from IDC, Yankee Group and other leading market analysts</p>
<p>

(7)	Omniture HBX data analysis of RCRW.com Web site</p>
<p>

(8)	Readex Research (blind) study of CTIA attendees, 7/08</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
