<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:29:57[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108435388">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<network  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108434259">
<header>
<title>ZigBee</title>
<id>195337</id>
<revision>
<id>243159812</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T11:57:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>PatrickFlaherty</username>
<id>6765807</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles needing additional references from February 2008</category>
<category>Wireless networking</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Home automation</category>
<category>Personal area networks</category>
<category>IEEE 802</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article needs additional  for .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=ZigBee&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding .  Unsourced material may be and removed.<it> (February 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>ZigBee</b> is the name of a specification for a suite of high level communication protocols using small, low-power <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/275724.xml">
digital radio</link>s based on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/455777.xml">
IEEE 802.15.4-2006</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/27065.xml">
standard</link> for <link>
wireless personal area network</link>s (WPANs), such as wireless headphones connecting with cell phones via short-range radio.  The technology is intended to be simpler and cheaper than other <link>
WPANs</link>, such as <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/3742.xml">
Bluetooth</link></system_of_measurement>
</machine>
</device>
</standard>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
.  ZigBee is targeted at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/42852.xml">
radio-frequency</link> (RF) applications that require a low data rate, long battery life, and secure networking.</p>
<p>

The <b>ZigBee Alliance</b> is a group of companies which maintain and publish the Zigbee standard.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>
<p>

ZigBee is a low-cost, low-power, wireless <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/912687.xml">
mesh networking</link> standard. The low cost allows the technology to be widely deployed in wireless control and monitoring applications, the low power-usage allows longer life with smaller batteries, and the mesh networking provides high reliability and larger range.</p>
<p>

The ZigBee Alliance, the standards body which defines ZigBee,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> also publishes application profiles that allow multiple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/69922.xml">
OEM</link> vendors to create interoperable products. The current list of application profiles either published or in the works are:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Home Automation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ZigBee Smart Energy</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Telecommunication Applications</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Personal Home</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hospital Care</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The relationship between <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/455777.xml">
IEEE 802.15.4</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 and ZigBee is similar to that between <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/14739.xml">
IEEE 802.11</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/816807.xml">
Wi-Fi Alliance</link>. The ZigBee 1.0 specification was ratified on 14 December 2004 and is available to members of the ZigBee Alliance. Most recently, the ZigBee 2007 specification was posted on 30 October 2007. The first ZigBee Application Profile, Home Automation, was announced 2 November 2007.</p>
<p>

For non-commercial purposes, the ZigBee specification is available free to the general public.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> An entry level membership in the ZigBee Alliance, called Adopter, costs <currency wordnetid="113385913" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/18717338.xml">
 US$</link></currency>
 3500 annually and provides access to the as-yet unpublished specifications and permission to create products for market using the specifications.  </p>
<p>

ZigBee operates in the industrial, scientific and medical (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/15286.xml">
ISM</link>) radio bands; 868 MHz in Europe, 915 MHz in countries such as USA and Australia, and 2.4 GHz in most jurisdictions worldwide. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/29816.xml">
technology</link> is intended to be simpler and cheaper than other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/23303.xml">
WPAN</link>s such as <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/3742.xml">
Bluetooth</link></system_of_measurement>
</machine>
</device>
</standard>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
. ZigBee chip vendors typically sell integrated radios and microcontrollers with between 60K and 128K flash memory, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/486512.xml">
Freescale</link> MC13213, the Ember EM250 and the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/47768.xml">
Texas Instruments</link></company>
 CC2430. Radios are also available stand-alone to be used with any processor or microcontroller. Generally, the chip vendors also offer the ZigBee software stack, although independent ones are also available.</p>
<p>

"As of 2006, the retail price of a Zigbee-compliant transceiver is approaching $1, and the price for one radio, processor, and memory package is about $3."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Comparatively, the price of consumer-grade Bluetooth chips is now under $3.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

The first stack release is now called <it>Zigbee 2004</it>. The second stack release is called <it>Zigbee 2006</it>, and mainly replaces the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/62287.xml">
MSG</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/626934.xml">
KVP</link> structure used in 2004 with a "cluster library". The 2004 stack is now more or less obsolete.</p>
<p>

<it>Zigbee 2007</it>, now the current stack release, contains 2 stack profiles, stack profile 1 (simply called ZigBee), for home and light commercial use, and stack profile 2 (called ZigBee Pro). ZigBee Pro offers more features, such as multi-casting, many-to-one routing and high security with Symmetric-Key Key Exchange (SKKE), while ZigBee (stack profile 1) offers a smaller footprint in RAM and flash. Both offer full mesh networking and work with all ZigBee application profiles.</p>
<p>

ZigBee 2007 is fully backward compatible with ZigBee 2006 devices: a ZigBee 2007 device may join and operate on a ZigBee 2006 network and vice versa. Due to differences in routing options, ZigBee Pro devices must become non-routing ZigBee End-Devices (ZEDs) on a ZigBee 2006 or ZigBee 2007 network, the same as ZigBee 2006 or ZigBee 2007 devices must become ZEDs on a ZigBee Pro network. The applications running on those devices work the same regardless of the stack profile beneath them.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Uses </st>
<p>

ZigBee protocols are intended for use in embedded applications requiring low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/311441.xml">
data rate</link>s and low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/374978.xml">
power consumption</link>. ZigBee's current focus is to define a general-purpose, inexpensive, self-organizing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/912687.xml">
mesh network</link> that can be used for industrial control, embedded sensing, medical data collection, smoke and intruder warning, building automation, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/184978.xml">
home automation</link>, etc.  The resulting network will use very small amounts of power -- individual devices must have a battery life of at least two years to pass ZigBee certification<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.</p>
<p>

Typical application areas include </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Home Entertainment and Control</b>&nbsp;&mdash; Smart lighting, advanced temperature control, safety and security, movies and music</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Home Awareness</b>&nbsp;&mdash; Water sensors, power sensors, smoke and fire detectors, smart appliances and access sensors</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Mobile Services</b>&nbsp;&mdash; m-payment, m-monitoring and control, m-security and access control, m-healthcare and tele-assist</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Commercial Building</b>&nbsp;&mdash; Energy monitoring, HVAC, lighting, access control</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b> Industrial Plant</b>&nbsp;&mdash; Process control, asset management, environmental management, energy management, industrial device control</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Device types</st>
<p>

There are three different types of ZigBee devices:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>ZigBee coordinator(ZC)</it>: The most capable device, the coordinator forms the root of the network tree and might bridge to other networks.    There is exactly one ZigBee coordinator in each network since it is the device that started the network originally.  It is able to store information about the network, including acting as the Trust Centre &amp; repository for security keys.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>ZigBee Router (ZR)</it>: As well as running an application function a router can act as an intermediate router, passing data from other devices.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>ZigBee End Device (ZED)</it>: Contains just enough functionality to talk to the parent node (either the coordinator or a router); it cannot relay data from other devices. This relationship allows the node to be asleep a significant amount of the time thereby giving long battery life. A ZED requires the least amount of memory, and therefore can be less expensive to manufacture than a ZR or ZC.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Protocols</st>
<p>

The protocols build on recent algorithmic research (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/1016665.xml">
Ad-hoc On-demand Distance Vector</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/1168458.xml">
neuRFon</link>) to automatically construct a low-speed ad-hoc network of nodes.  In most large network instances, the network will be a cluster of clusters.  It can also form a mesh or a single cluster. The current profiles derived from the ZigBee protocols support beacon and non-beacon enabled networks.</p>
<p>

In non-beacon-enabled networks (those whose beacon order is 15), an unslotted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/40846.xml">
CSMA/CA</link> channel access mechanism is used. In this type of network, ZigBee Routers typically have their receivers continuously active, requiring a more robust power supply. However, this allows for heterogeneous networks in which some devices receive continuously, while others only transmit when an external stimulus is detected. The typical example of a heterogeneous network is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/7649490.xml">
wireless light switch</link>: the ZigBee node at the lamp may receive constantly, since it is connected to the mains supply, while a battery-powered light switch would remain asleep until the switch is thrown.  The switch then wakes up, sends a command to the lamp, receives an acknowledgment, and returns to sleep.  In such a network the lamp node will be at least a ZigBee Router, if not the ZigBee Coordinator; the switch node is typically a ZigBee End Device.</p>
<p>

In beacon-enabled networks, the special network nodes called ZigBee Routers transmit periodic beacons to confirm their presence to other network nodes. Nodes may sleep between beacons, thus lowering their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/41078.xml">
duty cycle</link> and extending their battery life.  Beacon intervals may range from 15.36 milliseconds to 15.36 ms * 214 = 251.65824 seconds at 250 <link>
kbit/s</link>, from 24 milliseconds to 24 ms * 214 = 393.216 seconds at 40 kbit/s and from 48 milliseconds to 48 ms * 214 = 786.432 seconds at 20 kbit/s. However, low duty cycle operation with long beacon intervals requires precise timing, which can conflict with the need for low product cost. </p>
<p>

In general, the ZigBee protocols minimize the time the radio is on so as to reduce power use. In beaconing networks, nodes only need to be active while a beacon is being transmitted.  In non-beacon-enabled networks, power consumption is decidedly asymmetrical: some devices are always active, while others spend most of their time sleeping.</p>
<p>

ZigBee devices are required to conform to the IEEE 802.15.4-2003 Low-Rate Wireless Personal Area Network (WPAN) standard. The standard specifies the lower <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/630770.xml">
protocol</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/41310.xml">
layer</link>s&mdash;the physical layer (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/78300.xml">
PHY</link>), and the medium access control (<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/207472.xml">
MAC</link></method>
</rule>
</direction>
</know-how>
</protocol>
</message>
) portion of the data link layer (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/152949.xml">
DLL</link>).  This standard specifies operation in the unlicensed 2.4&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/14121.xml">
GHz</link>, 915&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/14121.xml">
MHz</link> and 868&nbsp;MHz <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/15286.xml">
ISM band</link>s.  In the 2.4&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/14121.xml">
GHz</link> band there are 16 ZigBee channels, with each channel requiring 5&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/14121.xml">
MHz</link> of bandwidth. The center frequency for each channel can be calculated as, FC = (2350 + (5 * ch))&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/14121.xml">
MHz</link>, where ch = 11, 12, ..., 26.</p>
<p>

The radios use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/41049.xml">
direct-sequence spread spectrum</link> coding, which is managed by the digital stream into the modulator.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/41551.xml">
BPSK</link> is used in the 868 and 915&nbsp;MHz bands, and orthogonal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/41551.xml">
QPSK</link> that transmits two bits per symbol is used in the 2.4&nbsp;GHz band.  The raw, over-the-air data rate is 250 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/17152.xml">
kbit</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/26873.xml">
s</link> per <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/156700.xml">
channel</link> in the 2.4&nbsp;GHz band, 40 kbit/s per channel in the 915&nbsp;MHz band, and 20&nbsp;kbit/s in the 868&nbsp;MHz band.  Transmission range is between 10 and 75 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/18947.xml">
meter</link>s (33 and 246 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/202482.xml">
feet</link>), although it is heavily dependent on the particular environment. The maximum output power of the radios is generally 0 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/41003.xml">
dBm</link> (1 mW). </p>
<p>

The basic channel access mode is "carrier sense, multiple access/collision avoidance" (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/47083.xml">
CSMA/CA</link>). That is, the nodes talk in the same way that people converse; they briefly check to see that no one is talking before they start. There are three notable exceptions to the use of CSMA. Beacons are sent on a fixed timing schedule, and do not use CSMA.  Message acknowledgments also do not use CSMA. Finally, devices in Beacon Oriented networks that have low latency real-time requirements may also use Guaranteed Time Slots (GTS), which by definition do not use CSMA.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Software and hardware</st>
<p>

The software is designed to be easy to develop on small, cheap microprocessors.  The radio design used by ZigBee has been carefully optimized for low cost in large scale production.  It has few <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/1665281.xml">
analog</link> stages and uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/39068.xml">
digital circuit</link>s wherever possible. </p>
<p>

Even though the radios themselves are cheap, the ZigBee Qualification Process involves a full validation of the requirements of the physical layer. This amount of concern about the Physical Layer has multiple benefits, since all radios derived from that semiconductor mask set would enjoy the same RF characteristics. On the other hand, an uncertified physical layer that malfunctions could cripple the battery lifespan of other devices on a ZigBee network. Where other protocols can mask poor sensitivity or other esoteric problems in a fade compensation response, ZigBee radios have very tight engineering constraints: they are both power and bandwidth constrained. Thus, radios are tested to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/3768176.xml">
ISO 17025</link> standard with guidance given by Clause 6 of the 802.15.4-2006 Standard. Most vendors plan to integrate the radio and microcontroller onto a single chip.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controversy</st>
<p>

A white paper published by a European manufacturing group (associated with the development of a competing standard, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/2685825.xml">
Z-Wave</link>) claims that wireless technologies such as ZigBee, which operate in the 2.4 GHz RF band, are subject to significant interference - enough to make them unusable.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> It claims that this is due to the presence of other wireless technologies like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/33143.xml">
Wireless LAN</link> in the same RF band. The ZigBee Alliance released a white paper  refuting these claims.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> After a technical analysis, this paper concludes that ZigBee devices continue to communicate effectively and robustly even in the presence of large amounts of interference.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

ZigBee-style networks began to be conceived about 1998, when many installers realized that both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/63973.xml">
WiFi</link> and <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/3742.xml">
Bluetooth</link></system_of_measurement>
</machine>
</device>
</standard>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 were going to be unsuitable for many applications.  In particular, many engineers saw a need for self-organizing ad-hoc digital radio networks. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The IEEE 802.15.4 standard was completed in May 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In the summer of 2003, Philips Semiconductors, a major mesh network supporter, ceased the investment.  Philips Lighting has, however, continued Philips' participation, and Philips remains a promoter member on the ZigBee Alliance Board of Directors.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The ZigBee Alliance announced in October 2004 that the membership had more than doubled in the preceding year and had grown to more than 100 member companies, in 22 countries.  By April 2005 membership had grown to more than 150 companies, and by December 2005 membership had passed 200 companies.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The ZigBee specifications were ratified on 14 December 2004.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The ZigBee Alliance announces public availability of Specification 1.0 on 13 June 2005, known as ZigBee 2004 Specification.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The ZigBee Alliance announces the completion and immediate member availability of the enhanced version of the ZigBee Standard in September 2006, known as ZigBee 2006 Specification.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

During the last quarter of 2007, ZigBee PRO, the enhanced ZigBee specification was finalized.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Origins of Zigbee name</st>

<p>

An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/31771.xml">
urban myth</link> perpetuated by the Zigbee Alliance is that the term “ZigBee” originates from the silent, but powerful method of communication used by honeybees to report information about food sources. The myth says that the communication system is known as the “ZigBee Principle"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. By "dancing" around in a zig-zag <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/1646040.xml">
waggle dance</link>, a bee is able to share critical information, such as the location, distance, and direction of a newly discovered food source to its fellow hive members. However, no such term exists in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/2252132.xml">
apiology</link>, the scientific study of honeybees. <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/289616.xml">
Robert Metcalfe</link></scientist>
, inventor of Ethernet and a worker on the initial development on Zigbee, confirmed to a journalist in 2004 that the name was initially meaningless and had been chosen from a long list on the basis that it had no trademark liabilities<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/8638682.xml">
Comparison of wireless data standards</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/2526997.xml">
EnOcean</link></institution>
</company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/7268361.xml">
Wibree</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/2685825.xml">
Z-Wave</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/13054443.xml">
ZigBee specification</link></network>
</group>
</system>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zigbee.org/en/about/">
Our Mission</weblink>".&#32;  zigbee.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zigbee.org/en/spec_download/download_request.asp">
ZigBee Specification Download Request</weblink>".&#32;  zigbee.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Adams, Jon;&#32;Bob Heile.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spectrum.ieee.org/oct06/4666">
Busy as a ZigBee</weblink>".&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/56938.xml">
IEEE</link>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-16</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_templates">
Compare with Other Technologies</weblink>".&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/3743.xml">
Bluetooth SIG</link>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-16</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
http://www.microcontroller.com/news/atmel_microcontrollers_avr.asp
</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.z-wavealliance.org/modules/iaCM-DocMan/?docId=53&amp;mode=DE">
WLAN Interference to IEEE802.15.4</weblink>".&#32;  z-wavealliance.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-22</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zigbee.org/imwp/download.asp?ContentID=11745">
ZigBee and Wireless Frequency Coexistence</weblink>".&#32;  zigbee.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-22</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.meshnetics.com/zigbee-faq/">
ZigBee FAQ</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="9">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.zdnet.co.uk/blog/0,1000000567,10003969o-2000331777b,00.htm">
Rupert Goodwins' Diary</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-10-05</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zigbee.org">
Zigbee Alliance homepage</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ieee802.org/15/pub/TG4.html">
IEEE 802.15.4 web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jennic.com/elearning/zigbee/index.htm">
ZigBee Tutorial</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.daintree.net/resources/index.php">
ZigBee Resources</weblink> including whitepapers and specification updates</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</network>
</group>
</system>
</article>
