<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:18:00[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Semantic data model</title>
<id>19558680</id>
<revision>
<id>243777093</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T00:11:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mdd</username>
<id>113850</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles incorporating text from public domain works of the United States Government</category>
<category>Data modeling</category>
<category>Systems analysis</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="320px" src="A2_4_Semantic_Data_Models.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Semantic data models.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
</caption>
</image>

A <b>semantic data model</b> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/27010.xml">
software engineering</link> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/759422.xml">
data modeling</link> technique to define the meaning of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/18985040.xml">
data</link> within the context of its interrelationships with other data. A semantic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/82871.xml">
data model</link> is an abstraction which defines how the stored <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/37673.xml">
symbol</link>s relate to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/327722.xml">
real world</link>. A semantic data model is sometimes called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/58267.xml">
conceptual data model</link>.
<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

The logical data structure of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/8513.xml">
database management system</link> (DBMS), whether <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/247075.xml">
hierarchical</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/185098.xml">
network</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/26220.xml">
relational</link>, cannot totally satisfy the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/522449.xml">
requirements</link> for a conceptual definition of data because it is limited in scope and biased toward the implementation strategy employed by the DBMS. Therefore, the need to define data from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/19539838.xml">
conceptual view</link> has led to the development of semantic data modeling techniques. That is, techniques to define the meaning of data within the context of its interrelationships with other data. As illustrated in the figure. The real world, in terms of resources, ideas, events, etc., are symbolically defined within physical data stores. A semantic data model is an abstraction which defines how the stored symbols relate to the real world. Thus, the model must be a true representation of the real world.</p>
<p>

The overall goal of semantic data models is to capture more meaning of data by integrating relational concepts with more powerful abstraction concepts known from the <link>
Artificial Intelligence</link> field. The idea is to provide high level modelling primitives as integral part of a data model in order to facilitate the representation of rela world situations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

The need for semantic data models was first recognized by the U.S. Air Force in the mid-1970s as a result of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/1673666.xml">
Integrated Computer-Aided Manufacturing</link> (ICAM) Program. The objective of this program was to increase manufacturing productivity through the systematic application of computer technology. The ICAM Program identified a need for better analysis and communication techniques for people involved in improving manufacturing productivity. As a result, the ICAM Program developed a series of techniques known as the IDEF (ICAM Definition) Methods which included the following:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/2361538.xml">
IDEF0</link> used to produce a “function model” which is a structured representation of the activities or processes within the environment or system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/3180013.xml">
IDEF1</link> used to produce an “information model” which represents the structure and semantics of information within the environment or system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
IDEF2</link> used to produce a “dynamics model” which represents the time varying behavioral characteristics of the environment or system.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Applications </st>
<p>

A semantic data model can be used to serve many purposes. Some key objectives include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Planning of Data Resources: A preliminary data model can be used to provide an overall view of the data required to run an enterprise. The model can then be analyzed to identify and scope projects to build shared data resources.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Building of Shareable Databases: A fully developed model can be used to define an application independent view of data which can be validated by users and then transformed into a physical database design for any of the various DBMS technologies. In addition to generating databases which are consistent and shareable, development costs can be drastically reduced through data modeling.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Evaluation of Vendor Software: Since a data model actually represents the infrastructure of an organization, vendor software can be evaluated against a company’s data model in order to identify possible inconsistencies between the infrastructure implied by the software and the way the company actually does business.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Integration of Existing Databases: By defining the contents of existing databases with semantic data models, an integrated data definition can be derived. With the proper technology, the resulting conceptual schema can be used to control transaction processing in a distributed database environment. The U.S. Air Force Integrated Information Support System (I2S2) is an experimental development and demonstration of this type of technology applied to a heterogeneous DBMS environment.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/3180013.xml">
IDEF1X</link> is the semantic data modeling technique. It is used to produce a graphical information model which represents the structure and semantics of information within an environment or system. Use of this standard permits the construction of semantic data models which may serve to support the management of data as a resource, the integration of information systems, and the building of computer databases.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/58267.xml">
Conceptual schema</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<datum wordnetid="105816622" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/752991.xml">
Entity-relationship model</link></datum>
</information>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/1800596.xml">
Information model</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/8113127.xml">
Relational Model/Tasmania</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/19539838.xml">
Three schema approach</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<image width="30px" src="NIST_logo.svg">
</image>
 <it>This article incorporates text from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link> publication of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/21888.xml">
National Institute of Standards and Technology</link>, a U.S. government agency.</it></p>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.itl.nist.gov/fipspubs/idef1x.doc">
FIPS Publication 184</weblink> released of IDEF1X by the Computer Systems Laboratory of the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST). 21 December 1993.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"Semantic data modelling" In: <it>Metaclasses and Their Application</it>. Book Series Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Publisher Springer Berlin / Heidelberg. Volume Volume 943/1995.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Johan ter Bekke (1992). <it>Semantic Data Modelling</it>. Prentice Hall. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Alfonso F. Cardenas and Dennis McLeod (1990). <it>Research Foundations in Object-Oriented and Semantic Database Systems</it>. Prentice Hall. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Peter Gray, Krishnarao G. Kulkarni and, Norman W. Paton (1992). <it>Object-Oriented Databases: A Semantic Data Model Approach</it>. Prentice-Hall International Series in Computer Science.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Michael Hammer and Dennis McLeod (1978). "The Semantic Data Model: a Modeling Mechanism for Data Base Applications." In: <it>Proc. ACM SIGMOD Int’l. Conf. on Management of Data</it>. Austin, Texas, May 31 - June 2, 1978, pp. 26-36.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soc.napier.ac.uk/module.php3?op=getresource&amp;cloaking=no&amp;resourceid=7462386">
Semantic Data Models</weblink> Course – Object Oriented Datatabase Systems, by Colin Jack &amp; Colin Keillor (2008).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jhterbekke.net/SemanticDataModeling.html">
Semantic Data Modeling</weblink> Johan ter Bekke tribute site.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
