<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:18:13[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Health information technology</title>
<id>19565233</id>
<revision>
<id>243176438</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T13:34:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ryanjo</username>
<id>1145144</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Health care informatics</category>
<category>Patient safety</category>
<category>Medical informatics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<sec>
<st>
Introduction</st>
<p>

<b>Health information technology</b> (HIT) provides the umbrella framework to describe the comprehensive management of health information and its secure exchange between consumers, providers, government and quality entities, and insurers. Health information technology (HIT) in general are increasingly viewed as the most promising tool for improving the overall quality, safety and efficiency of the health delivery system (Chaudhry et al., 2006).  Broad and consistent utilization of HIT will: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Improve health care quality; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prevent medical errors; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Reduce health care costs; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Increase administrative efficiencies; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Decrease paperwork; and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Expand access to affordable care.</entry>
</list>

Interoperable health IT will improve individual patient care, but it will also bring many public health benefits including: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Early detection of infectious disease outbreaks around the country; </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Improved tracking of chronic disease management; and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Evaluation of health care based on value enabled by the collection of de-identified price and quality information that can be compared.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Concepts and Definitions</st>
<p>

Health information technology (HIT) is “the application of information processing involving both computer hardware and software that deals with the storage, retrieval, sharing, and use of health care information, data, and knowledge for communication and decision making” (Brailer, &amp; Thompson, 2004).  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/29816.xml">
Technology</link> is a broad concept that deals with a species' usage and knowledge of tools and crafts, and how it affects a species' ability to control and adapt to its environment.  However, a strict definition is elusive; "technology" can refer to material objects of use to humanity, such as machines, hardware or utensils, but can also encompass broader themes, including systems, methods of organization, and techniques.  For HIT, technology represents computers and communications attributes that can be networked to build systems for moving health information.  Informatics is yet another integral aspect of HIT.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/4964625.xml">
Informatics</link> is the science of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/18985062.xml">
information</link>, the practice of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/315578.xml">
information processing</link>, and the engineering of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/237495.xml">
information systems</link>.  Informatics underlies the academic investigation and practitioner application of computing and communications technology to healthcare, health education, and biomedical research.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/351581.xml">
Health informatics</link> is intersection of information science, computer science, and health care.  Health informatics describes the use and sharing of information within the healthcare industry with contributions from computer science, mathematics, and psychology.  It deals with the resources, devices, and methods required for optimizing the acquisition, storage, retrieval, and use of information in health and biomedicine.  Health informatics tools include not only computers but also clinical guidelines, formal medical terminologies, and information and communication systems.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/351581.xml">
Medical informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/1075969.xml">
nursing informatics</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/3123084.xml">
pharmacy informatics</link> are subdisciplines that inform health informatics from different disciplinary perspectives.  The processes and people of concern or study are the main variables.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Implementation of HIT</st>
<p>

The Institute of Medicine’s (2001) call for the use of electronic prescribing systems in all healthcare organizations by 2010 heightened the urgency to accelerate United States hospitals’ adoption of CPOE systems.  In 2004, President Bush signed an  Executive Order titled the President’s Health Information Technology Plan, established a ten-year plan  as this technology is essential to put the needs and the values of the patients first and gives patients information they need to make clinical and economic decisions.  According to a study by RAND Health, the US healthcare system could save more than $81 billion annually, reduce adverse healthcare events and improve the quality of care if it were to widely adopt <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/351581.xml">
health information technology</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The most immediate barrier to widespread adoption of technology is cost: patients benefit from better health, and payers benefit from lower costs; however, hospitals pay in both higher costs for implementation and lower revenues due to reduced patient length of stay.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Types of technology</st>
<p>

In a recent study about the adoption of technology in the United States, Furukawa, and colleagues (2008) classified applications for prescribing to include electronic medical records (EMR), clinical decision support (CDS), and computerized physician order entry (CPOE). They further defined applications for dispensing to include bar-coding at medication dispensing (BarD), robot for medication dispensing (ROBOT), and automated dispensing machines (ADM). And, they defined applications for administration to include electronic medication administration records (EMAR) and bar-coding at medication administration (BarA).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Electronic Health Record (EHR)</st>
<p>

<image width="250px" src="EHRadoption.gif" type="thumb">
<caption>

US medical groups' adoption of EHR (2005)
</caption>
</image>
Although frequently cited in the literature the <b><standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/1129641.xml">
Electronic health record</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</b> (EHR), previously known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/930653.xml">
Electronic medical record</link> (EMR), there is no consensus about the definition (Jha et al., 2008).  However, there is consensus that EMRs can reduce several types of errors, including those related to prescription drugs, to preventive care, and to tests and procedures.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  Important features of modern EHR software include automatic drug-drug/drug-food interaction checks and allergy checks, standard drug dosages and patient education information, such as describing common side effects. Recurring alerts remind clinicians of intervals for preventive care and track referrals and test results. Clinical guidelines for disease management have a demonstrated benefit when accessible within the electronic record during the process of treating the patient.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  Advances in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/351581.xml">
health informatics</link> and widespread adoption of interoperable electronic health records promise access to a patient's records at any health care site. A 2005 report noted that medical practices in the United States are encountering barriers to adopting an EHR system, such as training, costs and complexity, but the adoption rate continues to rise (see chart to right).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Since 2002, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/16462572.xml">
National Health Service</link> of the United Kingdom has placed emphasis on introducing computers into healthcare. As of 2005, one of the largest projects for a national EHR is by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/16462572.xml">
National Health Service</link> (NHS) in the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
.  The goal of the NHS is to have 60,000,000 patients with a centralized electronic health record by 2010. The plan involves a gradual roll-out commencing May 2006, providing  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/197817.xml">
general practice</link>s in England access to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/1515790.xml">
National Programme for IT</link> (NPfIT), the NHS component of which is known as the "Connecting for Health Programme".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> However, recent surveys have shown physicians' deficiencies in understanding the patient safety features of the NPfIT-approved software.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Computerized Provider (Physician) Order Entry (CPOE)</st>
<p>

Prescribing errors are the largest identified source of preventable errors in hospitals. A 2006 report by the Institute of Medicine estimated that a hospitalized patient is exposed to a medication error each day of his or her stay.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>
Computerized provider order entry (CPOE), formerly called <b><work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<treatment wordnetid="100658082" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<care wordnetid="100654885" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/2021968.xml">
Computer physician order entry</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</care>
</event>
</treatment>
</work>
</b>, can reduce total medication error rates by 80%, and adverse (serious with harm to patient) errors by 55%.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>  A 2004 survey by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Leapfrog%22])">
Leapfrog</link> found that 16% of US clinics, hospitals and medical practices are expected to be utilizing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/2021968.xml">
CPOE</link> within 2 years.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> In addition to electronic prescribing, a standardized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/60600.xml">
bar code</link> system for dispensing drugs could prevent a quarter of drug errors.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Consumer information about the risks of the drugs and improved drug packaging (clear labels, avoiding similar drug names and dosage reminders) are other error-proofing measures. Despite ample evidence of the potential to reduce medication errors, competing systems of barcoding and electronic prescribing have slowed adoption of this technology by doctors and hospitals in the United States, due to concern with interoperability and compliance with future national standards.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> Such concerns are not inconsequential; standards for electronic prescribing for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/2870773.xml">
Medicare Part D</link> conflict with regulations in many US states.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Technological Innovations, Opportunities, and Challenges</st>
<p>

Handwritten reports or notes, manual order entry, non-standard abbreviations and poor legibility lead to substantial errors and injuries, according to the Institute of Medicine (2000) report.  The follow-up IOM (2004) report, Crossing the quality chasm: A new health system for the 21st century, advised rapid adoption of electronic patient records, electronic medication ordering, with computer- and internet-based information systems to support clinical decisions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>  However, many system implementations have experienced costly failures (Ammenwerth et al., 2006). Furthermore, there is evidence that CPOE may actually contribute to some types of adverse events and other medical errors.(Campbell et al., 2007) For example, the period immediately following CPOE implementation resulted in significant increases in reported adverse drug events in at least one study (Bradley, Steltenkamp, &amp; Hite, 2006) and evidence of other errors have been reported.(Bates, 2005a; Bates, Leape, Cullen, &amp; Laird, 1998; Bates; 2005b) Collectively, these reported adverse events describe phenomena related to the disruption of the complex adaptive system resulting from poorly implemented or inadequately planned technological innovation.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Technological Iatrogenesis</st>
<p>

Technology may introduce new sources of error <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>  Technologically induced errors are significant and increasingly more evident in care delivery systems.  Terms to describe this new area of error production include the label technological iatrogenesis <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> for the process  and e-iatrogenic <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> for the individual error.  The sources for these errors include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Prescriber and staff inexperience may lead to a false sense of security; that when technology suggests a course of action, errors are avoided.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Shortcut or default selections can override non-standard medication regimens for elderly or underweight patients, resulting in toxic doses. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

CPOE and automated drug dispensing was identified as a cause of error by 84% of over 500 health care facilities participating in a surveillance system by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/644263.xml">
United States Pharmacopoeia</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Irrelevant or frequent warnings can interrupt work flow.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References and Resources</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Citations</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
RAND Healthcare: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rand.org/pubs/research_briefs/RB9136/index1.html">
Health Information Technology: Can HIT Lower Costs and Improve Quality?</weblink> Retrieved on July 8, 2006</entry>
<entry id="2">
American College of Physicians Observer: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acponline.org/journals/news/sep04/emr.htm">
How EMR software can help prevent medical mistakes</weblink> by Jerome H. Carter (September 2004)</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kensaku Kawamoto, fellow1, Caitlin A Houlihan, E Andrew Balas, David F Lobach&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/330/7494/765">
Improving clinical practice using clinical decision support systems: a systematic review of trials to identify features critical to success</weblink>". <it>British Medical Journal</it>&#32;<b>330</b>: 765–768. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136%2Fbmj.38398.500764.8F">
10.1136/bmj.38398.500764.8F</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2006-06-29</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gans D, Kralewski J, Hammons T, Dowd B&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.healthaffairs.org/cgi/content/abstract/24/5/1323">
Medical groups' adoption of electronic health records and information systems</weblink>". <it>Health affairs (Project Hope)</it>&#32;<b>24</b>&#32;(5): 1323–1333. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1377%2Fhlthaff.24.5.1323">
10.1377/hlthaff.24.5.1323</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2006-07-04</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
NHS Connecting for Health: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.connectingforhealth.nhs.uk/delivery/">
Delivering the National Programme for IT</weblink> Retrieved August 4, 2006</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">C J Morris, B S P Savelyich, A J Avery, J A Cantrill and A Sheikh&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://qhc.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/14/3/164">
Patient safety features of clinical computer systems: questionnaire survey of GP views</weblink>". <it>Quality and Safety in Health Care</it>&#32;<b>14</b>: 164–168. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136%2Fqshc.2004.011866">
10.1136/qshc.2004.011866</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2006-07-08</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">The Institute of Medicine&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nap.edu/catalog/11623.html">
Preventing Medication Errors</weblink>". <it>The National Academies Press</it>. Retrieved on <link>
2006-07-21</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">David W. Bates, MD, et al&#32;(1998).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/abstract/280/15/1311">
Effect of Computerized Physician Order Entry and a Team Intervention on Prevention of Serious Medication Errors</weblink>". <it>JAMA</it>&#32;<b>280</b>: 1311–1316. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001%2Fjama.280.15.1311">
10.1001/jama.280.15.1311</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2006-06-20</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.leapfroggroup.org/media/file/Leapfrog-Survey_Release-11-16-04.pdf">
Hospital Quality &amp; Safety Survey</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;  The Leapfrog Group&#32;(2004).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-07-08</link>. </entry>
<entry id="10">
Kaufman, Marc&#32;(<link>
2005-07-21</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/07/20/AR2006072000754.html">
Medication Errors Harming Millions, Report Says. Extensive National Study Finds Widespread, Costly Mistakes in Giving and Taking Medicine</weblink>", The Washington Post, pp.&nbsp;A08.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-07-21</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
Institute of Medicine&#32;(2001).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nap.edu/books/0309072808/html">
Crossing the Quality Chasm: A New Health System for the 21st Century</weblink>".&#32;  The National Academies Press.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-06-29</link>.</entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ross Koppel, PhD, et al&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/abstract/293/10/1197">
Role of Computerized Physician Order Entry Systems in Facilitating Medication Errors</weblink>". <it>JAMA</it>&#32;<b>293</b>: 1197–1203. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001%2Fjama.293.10.1197">
10.1001/jama.293.10.1197</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2006-06-28</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
Lohr, Steve&#32;(<link>
2005-03-09</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/09/technology/09compute.html?ei=5089&amp;en=402b792e748d99a2&amp;ex=1268110800&amp;adxnnl=1&amp;partner=rssyahoo&amp;adxnnlx=1150474153-xVix1BcYkvTKJpuLyHStrQ">
Doctors' Journal Says Computing Is No Panacea</weblink>", The New York Times.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-07-15</link>.&nbsp; </entry>
<entry id="14">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Patrick Palmieri, et al&#32;(2007).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hom.ba.ttu.edu/FordPub/Palmieri_JHCRM_2008_Technological%20iatrogenesis.pdf">
Technological iatrogenesis: New risks force heightened management awareness</weblink>". <it>Journal of Healthcare Risk Management</it>&#32;<b>27</b>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
  <cite style="font-style:normal">Weiner, et al&#32;(2007).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jamia.org/cgi/reprint/14/3/387.pdf">
e-Iatrogenesis: The most critical unintended consequence of CPOE and other HIT</weblink>". <it>Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association</it>&#32;<b>14</b>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
Santell, John P&#32;(2004).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.usp.org/pdf/EN/patientSafety/slideShows2004-12-09.pdf">
Computer Related Errors: What Every Pharmacist Should Know</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;  United States Pharmacopia.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-06-20</link>.</entry>
</reflist>

In process of converting references into citations (in the body).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ammenwerth, E., Talmon, J., Ash, J. S., Bates, D. W., Beuscart-Zephir, M. C., Duhamel, A., Elkin, P. L., Gardner, R. M., &amp; Geissbuhler, A. (2006).  Impact of CPOE on mortality rates – contradictory findings, important messages.” Methods Inf Med, 45(6): 586-593.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ash, J. S., Sittig, D. F., Poon, E. G., Guappone, K., Campbell, E., &amp; Dykstra, R. H. (2007).  The extent and importance of unintended consequences related to computerized provider order entry.” Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association, 14(4): 415-423.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bates, D. (2005a).  Computerized Physician Order entry and medication errors: finding a balance. Journal of Biomedical Informatics, 38(4): 250-261.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bates, D.W. (2005b).  Physicians and ambulatory electronic health records.  Health Affairs, 24(5): 1180-1189.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bates, D. W., Leape, L. L., Cullen, D. J., &amp; Laird, N. (1998).  Effect of computerized physician order entry and a team intervention on prevention of serious medical errors.  Journal of the American Medical Association, 280: 1311-1316.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bradley, V. M., Steltenkamp, C. L., &amp; Hite, K. B. (2006).  Evaluation of reported medication errors before and after implementation of computerized practitioner order entry.  Journal Healthc Inf Manag, 20(4): 46-53.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Brailer, D., &amp; Thompson, T.  (2004).  Health IT strategic framework. Washington, DC: Department of Health and Human Services.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Chaudhry, B. Wang , J., &amp; Wu, S. et al., (2006).  Systematic review: Impact of health information technology on quality, efficiency, and costs of medical care, Annals of Internal Medicine, 144(10), 742–752.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Campbell, E. M., Sittig, D. F., Ash, J. S., Guappone, K. P., &amp; Dykstra, R. H. (2007).  In reply to:  “e-Iatrogenesis: The most critical consequence of CPOE and other HIT.  Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Furukawa, M. F., Raghu, T. S., Spaulding, T. J., &amp; Vinze, A. (2008).  Health Affairs, 27, (3), 865-875.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Institute of Medicine (2001). Crossing the quality chasm: A new health system for the 21st century.  Washington, D.C: National Academies Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jha, A. K., Doolan, D., Grandt, D., Scott, T. &amp; Bates, D. W. (2008).  The use of health information technology in seven nations.  International Journal of Medical Informatics, corrected proof in-press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kawamoto, K. H., Caitlin, A., Balas, E. A., &amp; Lobach, D. F. (2005). “Improving clinical practice using clinical decision support systems: A systematic review of trials to identify features critical to success.” British Journal of Medicine, 330(7494): 765-774.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sidrov, J. (2006).  It ain’t necessarily so: The electronic health record and the unlikely prospect of reducing healthcare costs. Health Affairs, 25(4): 1079-1085.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Governmental –United States</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) Health Information Technology site located at: http://healthit.ahrq.gov/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA) Health Information Technology site located at: http://www.hrsa.gov/healthit/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

United States Department of Health &amp; Human Services (HHS), Health Information Technology (HIT) Site located at: http://www.hhs.gov/healthit/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

United States White House, Transforming Health Care: The President’s Health Information Technology Plan located at: http://www.whitehouse.gov/infocus/technology/economic_policy200404/chap3.html</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Standards and Regulation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

American Health Information Community (AHIC) Successor organization site located at: http://www.ahicsuccessor.org/hhs/ahic.nsf/index.htm</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

American National Standards Institute (ANSI) Healthcare Information Technology (HIT) site located at: http://www.ansi.org/standards_activities/standards_boards_panels/hisb/hitsp.aspx?menuid=3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Certification Commission for Healthcare Information Technology (CCHIT) site located at: http://www.cchit.org/</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Professional –General</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

American Medical Informatics Association site located at http://www.amia.org/</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Professional –HIT</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

National Alliance for Health Information Technology for senior leadership site located at:  http://www.nahit.org/</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Professional –Medical</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

American Academy of Family Practitioners, Center for Health Information Technology  located at: http://www.centerforhit.org/</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Professional –Nursing</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

TB posted</entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

Subdomains of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/2231630.xml">
(bio)medical</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/1629559.xml">
health care informatics</link> include: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/3206010.xml">
clinical informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/1075969.xml">
nursing informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/14611016.xml">
imaging informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/835574.xml">
consumer health informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/4905289.xml">
public health informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/905043.xml">
dental informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/11990693.xml">
clinical research informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/1730701.xml">
veterinary informatics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/3123084.xml">
pharmacy informatics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/1075969.xml">
nursing informatics</link>.</p>
</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
