<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:29:26[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Munax</title>
<id>19571579</id>
<revision>
<id>243386921</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T09:00:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rick.nolan</username>
<id>7937793</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Company</name>
<parameters>
<company_logo>
<image width="150px" src="Munaxlogo.png">
<caption>

Munaxlogo.png
</caption>
</image>
</company_logo>
<company_name>
Munax</company_name>
<company_slogan>
Find it all in a single mouse click</company_slogan>
<company_type>
Private</company_type>
<foundation>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/26741.xml">
Stockholm</link></village>
, <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/5058739.xml">
Sweden</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</autocracy>
 (2007)</foundation>
<industry>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
Search Engine</link> systems, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
computer software</link></industry>
<location_country>
Sweden</location_country>
<location_city>
Stockholm</location_city>
<products>
(See article)</products>
<homepage>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.munax.com/">
www.munax.com</weblink>  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.playaudiovideo.com/">
Audio Video Image search engine</weblink></homepage>
<key_people>
Claes-Göran Fridh, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/3452243.xml">
Chairman</link>Jan-Olof Granlund, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/52234.xml">
CEO</link>  Johan Berg, CPO</key_people>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>Munax</b> is a <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/5058739.xml">
Swedish</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</autocracy>
 company which develops LHPE (Large Hyper-Parallel Execution) search engine systems. Munax XE, is an all-content search engine and powers nation wide as well as world wide public search engines with page, document, audio, video, images, software and email search. Other customers include vertical search engines and mobile operators.<p>

For <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/20420.xml">
multimedia</link>, Munax also develops functionality that let the visitors pre-listen to audio and pre-view videos, making it more easily for the visitor to decide what song or video he is looking for before playing it, or visiting the site hosting it. The visitor can also decide to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/886722.xml">
transcode</link> any multimedia file to make it moveable to the mobile phone or any type of multimedia player. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Munaxoffice.png">
<caption>

Munax Headquarters
</caption>
</image>
 
After earning his <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/236722.xml">
Master of Science</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/2641938.xml">
Applied Physics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/9531.xml">
Electrical Engineering</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
Computer Science</link>, Jan-Olof Granlund worked several years as an independent consultant when he in 2002 started the work on the specification of the Munax search engine system. The goal was to (1) develop a number of new algorithms for ranking, independent of the type of data and (2) efficient distribution and scaling of processing power and data over a large cluster of computers. 
The specification for implementation was ready in 2003/2004 and the first system (Munax P1) was released in 2005. By that time, a smaller company was founded in the U.S.A. for demoing the Munax system and a Munax P1 license was sold to the public search engine <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/18168682.xml">
Leit.is</link></web_site>
, which is today the leading search engine on <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/14531.xml">
Iceland</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
. 
In 2006 the search engine product Munax XE was released. Munax AB was founded in march 2007 and has its headquarters in the center of <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/26741.xml">
Stockholm</link></village>
, <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/5058739.xml">
Sweden</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</autocracy>
 with shareholders from Sweden, Iceland, U.S.A. and China.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Munax features </st>
<p>

On the <b>system level</b>, Munax can be installed on a single <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link> or an arbitrary number of computers on a local area network, or over computers on the internet. The execution is logically distributed over subsystems, not machines. One machine can host several subsystems and/or one subsystem can span over several machines. This way, Munax can be scaled and distributed freely and each machine's execution power can be utilized to its maximum. 
On the <b>indexing level</b>, Munax full-indexes a long range of document types, including: htm html shtm shtml jhtm asp php php3 pdf ps doc xls ppt rtf wp wp5 wp6 wpd txt c cpp h. When it comes to link-indexing in Munax, this is more complex than just indexing the anchor text and the URL. Amongst other things, Munax relates each link to the other links on the page and to the text of the page itself. Munax supports the link-indexing of, including: gif, jpg, tga, bmp, iff, img, jif, mac, msp, pcx, pic, tif, ico, jpe, mp3, wav, ram, snd, mp4, aif, mid, vqf, la1, lav, mp2, avi, mpg, mpeg, rm, qt, asx, mov, fli, flc, eps, wri, asc, fmk, for, zip, gzip, tar, arc, lzh, sit, rar, arj, dd, tgz, lha, exe, hqx, dll, vbs, vxd, bat, cmd, class, jar, java, jav and email addresses. Munax knows what type of files these are and groups them accordingly. Munax also allows for structured indexing, i.e. the indexing of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
xml</link> files and automatically creates each xml tag as an individual search item. 
On the <b>search level</b>, several independent ranking algorithms processes the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/3125116.xml">
inverted index</link> together with hundreds of search parameters to produce the final ranking for each document. 
For the visitor, Munax provides a long range of search features, including the search for pages, documents, audio, video, images, compressed files, torrents, software and email addresses, or to get all type of results on the same page (composite search, supersearch). The visitor can also decide which ranking algoritms to be used, search across domains, search within sites, before/after/between dates, demand objects-on-page, pre-view &amp; pre-listen to multimedia files and view objects-on-page and pages with the tags stripped away.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 PlayAudioVideo </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Munpav.png">
<caption>

PlayAudioVideo search page
</caption>
</image>

Munax started the construction of the PlayAudioVideo <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/20420.xml">
multimedia</link> search engine in july 2007 and opened it for beta testers in december the same year. PlayAudioVideo, beta 1, was opened for the public in february 2008 and beta 2 opened in june 2008. 
PlayAudioVideo is the first true search engine for multimedia, i.e. providing search on the web for images, video and audio/music in the same search engine. Through Munax composite search, the visitor gets the results for all three multimedia types on the same result page, or he can decide to search for each individual type. Audio and Video can be pre-listened and pre-viewed before connecting to the original multimedia file. This saves time when deciding among versions of the same song or video. 
The visitor can start his own web application and make any search result accessible in any type of device. This includes audio for mp3 players and video and audio for mobile phones and/or VCD/DVD.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Mobile operators, Metasearch engines </st>
<p>

Munax has acknowledged the demand from the mobile operators to provide their customers with search beyond the traditional text search. The mobile phones of today are multimedia enabled and Munax provides the users with the search and play of songs and videos regardless of the type of device being used. 
For <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/548297.xml">
metasearch engines</link>, Munax provides any type of search, including traditional text search (pages/documents) and multimedia search, to be presented on their result pages.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Corporates &amp; Small businesses </st>
<p>

Munax provides a long range of search products, to be installed on the corporate's computers, to index their local area network, their web site and/or sites on the web. Munax can be tailored individually to suit the needs for each corporate. Munax also provides outsourced search, i.e. any corporate can have their website indexed and searchable from the Munax search engine, but presented as if the search results came from the corporate itself. With or without <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authentication</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Munax name and logo </st>
<p>

MUNAX, from <b>Mun</b>in and Cor<b>ax</b>. 
The latin name for the Raven is Corvus Corax, as named in 1758 by Carolus Linnaeus, the Swedish biologist who invented the two-name system of classifying organisms by Latin names. Munin is one of the two ravens of Odin, the god of visdom in the Nordic Viking mythology (Viking ages 700 A.D. – 1100 A.D.). The ravens fly over the earth. They remember everything. When the ravens come back, they tell Odin what they have seen. Just the same way as the Munax ravens (crawlers) tell the Munax database what they have seen.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networksolutions.com/whois/results.jsp?domain=munax.com">
Whois for Munax</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://i-newswire.com/pr153486.html">
Munax, PlayAudioVideo opens for world wide access</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.leit.is">
Munax powers the leading Icelandic search engine</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ericsson.com/ericsson/corpinfo/publications/telecomreport/archive/2008/multimedia/article3.shtml">
Ericsson Corp., One-stop launched for multimedia searches</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.munax.com/news_affs.htm">
Affärsstrategerna AB invests in Munax</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.playaudiovideo.com">
The World's first multimedia (audio, video, images) search engine</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.astrateg.se/pressmeddelande.asp?id=314&amp;year=2008">
Munax AB opens the multimedia search engine PlayAudioVideo</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.euroinvestor.co.uk/News/ShowNewsStory.aspx?StoryID=9873398">
PlayAudioVideo, Bigger better and easier to use</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pandia.com/sew/621-playaudiovideo.html">
Pandia, Playaudiovideo indexes movies, music and images</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.metro.se/se/article/2008/02/20/16/0022-48/index.xml">
Metro Teknik, The first Multimedia search engine</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nyteknik.se/nyheter/it_telekom/internet/article68818.ece">
Swedish Munax finds all media files</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://computersweden.idg.se/2.2683/1.146645">
Swedish company challenges Google on video search</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
