<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:30:42[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<scientist  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="110560637">
<header>
<title>Tom Gruber</title>
<id>19627280</id>
<revision>
<id>243561196</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T01:09:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mdd</username>
<id>113850</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>1959 births</category>
<category>American computer scientists</category>
<category>Living people</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Thomas Robert (Tom) Gruber</b> (1959) is an American <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/328784.xml">
Computer scientist</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/14629.xml">
inventor</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/39862.xml">
entrepreneur</link> with a focus on systems for knowledge sharing and collective intelligence. He did foundational work in <link>
ontology engineering</link> and is well-known for his definition of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/22261.xml">
ontologies</link> in the context of <link>
Artificial Intelligence</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<sec>
<st>
 Biography </st>
<p>

Tom Gruber studied <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
Psychology</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
Computer Science</link> at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/3403776.xml">
Loyola University</link> in New Orleans where he received a double major B.S. in 1981 and graduated summa cum laude. He had designed and implemented a computer-assisted instruction (CAI) system for programmed-curriculum courses. It was the first of its kind at the university, and is used routinely by the Psychology department for introductory courses. In 1984 he received a M.S. in Computer and Information Science at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/248445.xml">
University of Massachusetts</link></university>
. His Master's research had resulted in the design and implementation of an intelligent communication <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/72750.xml">
prosthesis</link> assistant, a computer system which enables people with severe physical disabilities who cannot otherwise speak to communicate in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/21173.xml">
natural language</link> presented in displayed, written, or spoken form. For years later in 1988 at the University of Massachusetts he received there a Ph.D. in Computer and Information Science with the dissertation "The Acquisition of Strategic Knowledge". His dissertation research had addressed a critical problem for Artificial Intelligence--knowledge acquisition--with a computer assistant that acquires strategic knowledge from experts.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

From 1988 to 1994 Gruber has been a Research Associate at the Knowledge Systems Laboratory of the Computer Science Department at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/26977.xml">
Stanford University</link></university>
. He has been working on the How Things Work, SHADE, and Knowledge Sharing Technology projects. In 1994 he became Senior Project Leader, Enterprise Integration Technologies and proposed and designed several projects using the Internet to create shared, virtual environments for collaborative learning and work (for ARPA, NASA, NIST). Proposed a business plan for corporate training. In 1995 he founded and became Chief Technology Officer of <link>
Intraspect Software</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> an enterprise software company that pioneered the space of collaborative knowledge management. Intraspect applications help professional people collaborate in large distributed communities, continuously contributing to a collective body of knowledge. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

He has been a member of journal editorial boards of the "Knowledge Acquisition", "IEEE Expert" and "Internation Journal of Human-Computer Studies".</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Work </st>
<p>

Grubers research interested in the 1990s were in the field of developing intelligent networked software to support human collaboration and learning. Areas of specialty include: knowledge acquisition, knowledge representation, computer-supported collaborative work, computer-mediated communication for design, and knowledge sharing technology.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Web collaboration and knowledge sharing </st>
<p>

At Stanford University in the early 1990's, Gruber was a pioneer in the use of the Web for collaboration and knowledge sharing. He invented HyperMail, a widely-used open source application that turns email conversations into collective memories, which chronicled many of the early discussions that helped define the Web. He built ontology-engineering tools and established the first web-based public exchange for ontologies, software, and knowledge bases.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Ontology </st>
<p>

The <link>
Artificial Intelligence</link> (AI) community has been researching the knowledge representation and retrieval problems for a long time. Their approach to define standard facilities to describe human knowledge at any granularity level and to obtain ability. The basis of the AI approach is ontologies, which means the consensus conceptualization of the real world. This is initially defined by Tom Gruber in 1993. Once the needed ontologies are established, people can index the unstructured knowledge of existing documents and convert them to formal represented knowledge. Then searchers can utilize some kind of intelligent agents to browse, modify and query the knowledge basis.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> </p>
<p>

Work in Artificial Intelligence has been exploring the use of formal ontologies as a way of specifying content-specific agreements for the sharing and reuse of knowledge among software entities. Gruber has taken an engineering perspective on the development of such ontologies. <link>
Formal ontologies</link> are viewed as designed artifacts, formulated for specific purposes and evaluated against objective design criteria. We describe the role of ontologies in supporting knowledge sharing activities, and then present a set of criteria to guide the development of ontologies for these purposes. Gruber has shown how these criteria are applied in case studies from the design of ontologies for engineering mathematics and bibliographic data. Selected design decisions are discussed, and alternative representation choices and evaluated against the design criteria.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 The Semantic Web </st>
<p>

The <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
Semantic Web</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9632.xml">
ecosystem</link> of interaction among computer systems. The social web is an ecosystem of conversation among people. Both are enabled by conventions for layered services and data exchange. Both are driven by human-generated content and made scalable by machine-readable data. Yet there is a popular misconception that the two worlds are alternative, opposing ideologies about how the web ought to be. Folksonomy vs. ontology. Practical vs. formalistic. Humans vs. machines.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

This is nonsense According to Gruber (2006)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, and it is time to embrace a unified view. He has come to the vision of the Semantic Web as a substrate for collective intelligence. The best shot we have of collective intelligence in our lifetimes is large, distributed human-computer systems. The best way to get there is to harness the "people power" of the Web with the techniques of the Semantic Web. In this presentation I will show several ways that this can be, and is, happening.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 RealTravel </st>
<p>

Grubers current project is RealTravel.com<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>, which aspires to be the best place on the web to share knowledge and experiences about travel. RealTravel provides an environment for a community of travel enthusiasts to create beautiful travel journals of their adventures, share them with friends and family, and learn from other like-minded travelers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/19638350.xml">
IDEF5</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/10937684.xml">
Social Semantic Web</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/9561470.xml">
Soft ontology</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Publications </st>
<p>

Gruber published several articles and some books<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>. A selection:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1989. <it>The Acquisition of Strategic Knowledge</it>. Dissertation University of Massachusetts. Academic Press. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Articles a selection:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1992. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tomgruber.org/writing/onto-design.pdf">
"Toward Principles for the Design of Ontologies Used for Knowledge Sharing"</weblink>. In: <it>International Journal Human-Computer Studies</it>. Vol 43, p.907-928. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1993. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-ksl.stanford.edu/people/gruber/gruber-cv.html">
"A Translation Approach to Portable Ontology Specifications"</weblink>. In: <it>Knowledge Acquisition</it>, 5(2):199-220, 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2008, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tomgruber.org/writing/ontology-in-encyclopedia.htm">
Ontology</weblink>. Entry in the Encyclopedia of Database Systems, Ling Liu and M. Tamer Özsu (Eds.), Springer-Verlag, to appear in 2008.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://iswc2006.semanticweb.org/program/keynote_gruber.php">
Tom Gruber Keynote</weblink> at ISWC2006. Retrieved 6 Oktober 2008.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-ksl.stanford.edu/people/gruber/gruber-cv.html">
Thomas Robert Gruber</weblink>. Home page at Stanford. Last updated 1995. Retrieved 6 October 2008.</entry>
<entry id="3">
 Zhifeng Yang (2002). "Applying Information Retrieval Technology to Incremental Knowledge Management". In: <it>Engineering and Deployment of Cooperative Information Systems: First International Conference, EDCIS 2002, Beijing, China, September 17-20, 2002 : Proceedings</it>. Yanbo Han (Red.) p.117-120</entry>
<entry id="4">
Thomas Gruber (1993). "Toward Principles for the Design of Ontologies Used for Knowledge Sharing". In: <it>International Journal Human-Computer Studies</it> Vol. 43, Issues 5-6, Novemer 1995, p.907-928.</entry>
<entry id="5">
[http://tomgruber.org/technology/realtravel.htm </entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gruber:Thomas_R=.html">
DBLP: Thomas R. Gruber</weblink>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tomgruber.org/">
Tom Gruber</weblink> Recent homepage.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-ksl.stanford.edu/people/gruber/">
Tom Gruber</weblink> Homepage in 1994 at Stanford</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</scientist>
</article>
