<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:33:40[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Citizens Campaign for the Environment</title>
<id>19722010</id>
<revision>
<id>244459894</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T22:25:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CceNH</username>
<id>8051636</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<sec>
<st>
 <b>History:</b> </st>

<p>

<b>Citizens Campaign for the Environment (CCE)</b> was formed in 1985 by a small group of concerned citizens who recognized the need to provide public involvement in the course of advancing stronger environmental policy. Today, after 20 years as a not-for-profit, non-partisan advocacy organization, CCE has grown to an 80,000-member organization with offices in Farmingdale, NY, White Plains, NY, Albany, NY, Syracuse, NY, Buffalo, NY, and New Haven, CT. CCE continues to work to empower the public by providing members with opportunities to participate in the political process and thereby advance a progressive environmental agenda.</p>
<p>

Through education, research, lobbying and public outreach, CCE helps citizens to increase their influence and activism, both individually and collectively. Through such activism, citizens will have a stronger voice in the development of public policies and legislative agendas.</p>
<p>

CCE's experienced program staff works to identify key environmental concerns in communities across New York State and coastal Connecticut. By working with other environmental activists and through ongoing communication with local, state and federal elected officials and environmental and public health agencies, CCE has been successful in advancing policies and programs that benefit the natural environment and public health. Our achievements through public involvement have resulted in greater awareness and protection of drinking water quality, preservation of open spaces and a reduction in pollutants that impair our air and water resources<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Highlights of CCE’s Recent Victories </st>


<p>

<b>MTBE (Methyl Tertiary Butyl Ether) now banned in the Tri-State</b> region<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. Seven years after CCE launched their campaign to protect drinking water from MTBE contamination, a majority of states, including Connecticut, New York and New Jersey, have banned MTBE. Additionally, the federal oxygenate requirement ended on May 5, 2006, ending federal incentives for MTBE in our nation’s gasoline. Contaminating wells and aquifers across the tri-state area, MTBE is an EPA classified possible carcinogen.</p>
<p>

<b>CCE stops EPA plan to dump dredged spoils in Long Island</b> Sound<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. After CCE members sent in almost 11,000 letters to state and local leaders, NY and CT Governors agreed to phase out dumping of untreated dredged materials into Long Island Sound! The agreement calls for the development of a Dredged Material Management Plan focuses on using alternative technologies for dredged materials and establishes the phase-out of open water dumping.</p>
<p>

<b>Broadwater Victory!</b>
New York State Governor Paterson Says NO to Broadwater—The public prevails over Big Oil<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>!
Governor David Paterson announced on April 10, 2008, at Sunken Meadow State Park on Long Island to a crowd of Broadwater opponents that the State finds the Broadwater proposal to violate the Coastal Zone Management Act and ruled the project inconsistent with the values and uses of the Sound. The proposal, to place a Liquefied Natural Bas Barge in the middle of Long Island Sound, would have threatened local ecosystems and required an unprecedented "no public access zone" in open waters of the Sound. This challenging campaign to stop Broadwater spanned three years.</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
