<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:33:59[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Jessica M. Bibliowicz</title>
<id>19738249</id>
<revision>
<id>244689516</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-12T01:45:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mufka</username>
<id>2742610</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Candidates for speedy deletion</category>
<category>Possible copyright violations</category>
<category>Copyright violations for speedy deletion</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-speedy" style="font-size:95%;"</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="border: none; padding: 0px; width: 1px;"></col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 
This page  may meet Wikipedia’s &#32;as a copyright infringement of http://pages.stern.nyu.edu/~gdaly/JBibliowicz.html.&#32;This criterion applies only if the material was introduced at once by a single person, there is no non-infringing content on either the page or its history worth saving, and there is no credible assertion of public domain, fair use, or free license. See . of http://pages.stern.nyu.edu/~gdaly/JBibliowicz.html()G12<p>

If this page does not meet the criteria for speedy deletion, or you intend to fix it, please remove this notice, but <b>do not remove this notice from pages that you have created yourself</b>. If you created this page and you disagree with its proposed speedy deletion, please add:
<indent level="1">

&amp;gt;
</indent>
<b>directly below</b> this tag, and then explain why you believe this article should not be deleted on . This will alert administrators to permit you the time to write your explanation. See .</p>
<p>

Consider the possibility that a copy of the article on another website was obtained from Wikipedia.  Also, verify if the submitter of this page has been  about our .<it>: check , <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Jessica_M._Bibliowicz&amp;action=history">
history</weblink> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Jessica_M._Bibliowicz&amp;diff=0">
last</weblink>), and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Log&amp;page=Jessica_M._Bibliowicz">
logs</weblink> before <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Jessica_M._Bibliowicz&amp;wpReason=%5B%5BWikipedia%3ACopyright+violations%7CCopyright+violation%5D%5D+of+http%3A%2F%2Fpages.stern.nyu.edu%2F%7Egdaly%2FJBibliowicz.html+%28%5B%5BWP%3ACSD%23G12%7CCSD+G12%5D%5D%29&amp;action=delete">
deletion</weblink>.</it> Consider checking <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?q=%22Jessica+M.+Bibliowicz%22">
Google</weblink>.
<indent level="1">

<it>Please consider placing the :</it>
</indent>
:<it> ~~~~</it>
<indent level="1">

<it>on the talk page of the author.''</it></indent>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-delete" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Copyright-problem.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The  has performed a web search with the contents of this page, and it appears to include a substantial copy of:
<indent level="1">

http://pages.stern.nyu.edu/~gdaly/JBibliowicz.html
</indent>
Unless evidence is provided to the contrary (e.g. evidence of GFDL permission or public domain status), editors will assume that this text is a , and will soon delete the copy.
<b>Before removing this notice, you should:</b>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>If  is in error:</b>  Simply note so on .</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Replace the copyright text with your own work.</b>  Note that simply modified or rephrased text is <it>still</it> an infringement — to remove the copyrighted contents you will need to completely remove them and then write totally new text to replace it.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Replace the copyrighted contents with a </b>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Check whether it is reasonable to revert to one of the previous versions of the article</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Or, just <b>remove the copyrighted contents</b> if it is not critical to the article.</entry>
</list>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<p>

Jessica M. Bibliowicz is President and Chief Executive Officer of National Financial Partners.  National Financial Partners was created to form the nation's premier financial services distribution system providing specialized financial care to high net-worth individuals and mid-sized corporations.   NFP was founded in 1999 with a significant capital investment from Apollo Management, L.P. and has since acquired over 100 independent firms specializing in estate planning, corporate benefits and financial planning.</p>
<p>

Prior to joining NFP, Ms. Bibliowicz served as President and Chief Operating Officer of John A. Levin &amp; Co., a registered investment advisor.  Ms. Bibliowicz's career in the financial services industry began in 1981.   She spent eight years in the Asset Management Division of Shearson Lehman Brothers and joined Salomon Brothers after they purchased Lehman Management's Private Client Group.  In 1992, she became the Director of Sales and Marketing for Prudential Mutual Funds and in 1994 became head of Smith Barney Mutual Funds.</p>
<p>

Ms. Bibliowicz is a frequent guest on CNBC, CNN, Fox Business News and has been featured in national publications such as Business Week, Financial Planning, Investment Advisor, Registered Representative, InvestmentNews, Crain's New York Business, and The New York Times.</p>
<p>

Ms. Bibliowicz is a Governor of the Boys &amp; Girls Club of America and is Regional Chair for the Northeast Region.  She serves on the Board of Directors of Eaton Vance Mutual Funds, the Governor's Committee on Scholastic Achievement and the Securities Industry Association.   She is also a member of the Hedge Funds Advisory Group of Cornell University's Investment Committee.</p>
<p>

Ms. Bibliowicz graduated from Cornell University and lives with her husband and children in New York.</p>
</bdy>
</article>
