<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:08:17[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Hobie cat</title>
<id>1976053</id>
<revision>
<id>235455589</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-31T21:45:16Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SPUI</username>
<id>113059</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>NPOV disputes from December 2007</category>
<category>Articles with limited geographic scope</category>
<category>Multihulls</category>
<category>All articles to be expanded</category>
<category>Articles to be expanded since April 2007</category>
<category>Articles to be expanded since July 2007</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="46px" src="Globe_important.svg">
<caption>

Globe icon
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The examples and perspective in this article or section may not represent a  of the subject.
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Hobie_cat&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> or discuss the issue on the . <it>(June 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

 <p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="ambox_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section has been nominated to be checked for its .</b>
Discussion of this nomination can be found on the . <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>


<p>

A <b>Hobie Cat</b> is a small <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/195952.xml">
catamaran</link> (or two-hulled) sailboat manufactured by the Hobie Cat Company of Oceanside, California, USA. Begun as a manufacturer of surf boards in the late 1950s, Hobie (named after Hobie Alter, the company's founder) began manufacturing catamaran sailboats in the late 1960s and has become the largest manufacturer of small catamarans in the world. Today, Hobie's line of products ranges from surf boards to catamaran sailboats to kayaks, though the Hobie Cat Company is most famous around the world for its catamarans. Hobie also designed a very successful monohull, the Hobie 33.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

After sailing on the world's first ocean-going catamaran, the <link>
 Manu Kai</link>, Hobie patented the idea.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  In 1967, he designed the Hobie 14 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/195952.xml">
Catamaran</link>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/12178388.xml">
Hobie</link> wanted to make a boat that you could easily launch into the surf from the beach, sail, and bring back through the surf. In 1969, Hobie released the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1895621.xml">
Hobie 16</link>, the most popular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/195952.xml">
catamaran</link> ever and the most competitive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/195952.xml">
catamaran</link> class in the world. Over 100,000 Hobie Cats are sailing around the world.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Current and notable past models</st>

<p>

Different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/195952.xml">
catamaran</link> models range from 10&nbsp;feet (3&nbsp;m) in length to 21&nbsp;feet (6&nbsp;m), and beams range from 6.8&nbsp;feet (2.1&nbsp;m) to 8.5&nbsp;feet (2.6&nbsp;m), mast heights range from 20 to 33&nbsp;feet (10&nbsp;m).</p>
<p>

<table align="center" class="wikitable">
<header>
 <link>
Length Over All</link></header>
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/42167.xml">
Beam</link></header>
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/186374.xml">
Draft</link></header>
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/33931.xml">
Weight</link></header>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/58064.xml">
Mast</link></col>
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/6801.xml">
Crew</link></header>
<header>
Model</header>
<header>
Description</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
12'</col>
<col>
53"</col>
<col>
9"</col>
<col>
195 pounds ( 88.45 Kg )</col>
<col>
19'</col>
<col>
1 to 2</col>
<col>
Bravo</col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
13'</col>
<col>
7'</col>
<col>
11"</col>
<col>
245 pounds ( 111.13 Kg )</col>
<col>
20'</col>
<col>
1 to 4</col>
<col>
Wave</col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
16'</col>
<col>
42" to 112"</col>
<col>
2" to 2'</col>
<col>
115 pounds ( 52.12 Kg )</col>
<col>
15'2"</col>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
Adventure Island</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/389849.xml">
Trimaran</link>, (pedal) MirageDrive</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
16'7"</col>
<col>
7'8" to 10'4"</col>
<col>
10"</col>
<col>
390 pounds ( 177 Kg )</col>
<col>
25'</col>
<col>
1 to 5</col>
<col>
Getaway</col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
14'</col>
<col>
7'8"</col>
<col>
8"</col>
<col>
240 pounds</col>
<col>
22'3"</col>
<col>
1 to 3</col>
<col>
Hobie 14</col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
16'7"</col>
<col>
7'11"</col>
<col>
10"</col>
<col>
320 pounds ( 145.2 Kg )</col>
<col>
26'6"</col>
<col>
1 to 4</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1895621.xml">
Hobie 16</link></col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
17'</col>
<col>
8'</col>
<col>
5" to 1'6"</col>
<col>
340 pounds</col>
<col>
27'7"</col>
<col>
1 to 2</col>
<col>
Hobie 17 (SE or Sport)</col>
<col>
 <link>
SE main only, Sport adds jib</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
17'</col>
<col>
8'3"</col>
<col>
6" to 3'9"</col>
<col>
340 pounds ( 125 Kg )</col>
<col>
27'9"</col>
<col>
1 to 2</col>
<col>
FX-One</col>
<col>
 <link>
main only</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
18'</col>
<col>
8'</col>
<col>
10" to 2'6"</col>
<col>
400 to 439 pounds ( ? Kg )</col>
<col>
28'1"</col>
<col>
2 to 4</col>
<col>
Hobie 18</col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
33'</col>
<col>
8'</col>
<col>
5'6"</col>
<col>
4000 pounds</col>
<col>
36'</col>
<col>
4-6</col>
<col>
 <link>
Hobie 33</link></col>
<col>
 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/862111.xml">
Monohull</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
18'</col>
<col>
8'6"</col>
<col>
7" to 3'9"</col>
<col>
397 pounds ( 180 Kg )</col>
<col>
29'6"</col>
<col>
1 to 4</col>
<col>
Tiger</col>
<col>
 <link>
F18 class</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
19'6"</col>
<col>
8'6"</col>
<col>
5" to 2'9"</col>
<col>
420 pounds ( ? Kg )</col>
<col>
31'</col>
<col>
?</col>
<col>
Miracle 20</col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
20'</col>
<col>
8'6"</col>
<col>
?</col>
<col>
419 pounds ( ? Kg )</col>
<col>
31' 2"</col>
<col>
2</col>
<col>
Fox</col>
<col>
 <link>
Hobie Cat Europe, Formula 20 class</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
21'</col>
<col>
8'6"</col>
<col>
9+'</col>
<col>
600 pounds</col>
<col>
29'</col>
<col>
?</col>
<col>
Hobie 21SC</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
21'</col>
<col>
10' to 14'</col>
<col>
?</col>
<col>
?</col>
<col>
33'</col>
<col>
?</col>
<col>
Hobie 21SE</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
22'</col>
<col>
19'</col>
<col>
?</col>
<col>
320 pounds ( 145 Kg )</col>
<col>
( 2 ) 18'</col>
<col>
2</col>
<col>
TriFoiler</col>
<col>
 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/7103722.xml">
Sailing hydrofoil</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/389849.xml">
Trimaran</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Rotomolded Boats: Bravo, Wave, Getaway</st>


<p>

This series of boats is created of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/2326697.xml">
rotomolded</link> plastic and is intended for casual and new sailors.</p>
<p>

The Bravo is the smallest Hobie sailboat at 12' and is intended for one person but can carry two.  The relatively narrow beam (53") compared to its 19' mast leads to considerable <it>heeling</it>, or tipping of the boat compared to other catamarans.  The Bravo has the distinction of being able to furl its sail around the mast.</p>
<p>

The Wave is intended for one to four passengers, but is easily handled by one with its 13' length, 7' beam, and 20' mast.  The Wave was designed by the <link>
Morelli/Melvin Engineering firm</link>, and has proved to be extremely popular with beach resorts and rental operations.  It is often praised for being rugged and easy to sail.  While described as slow and underpowered by catamaran standards,  it has a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/566573.xml">
Portsmouth yardstick</link> similar to a <specification wordnetid="106725067" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/526184.xml">
Laser (dinghy)</link></specification>
 that is often considered to be a performance dinghy.  Although marketed as a recreational sailboat,  an owner-controlled racing class has organized and held regattas since 1998.  </p>
<p>

The Getaway is marketed as a "social boat" and is designed with room for up to 6 people, more than Hobie Cat's other boats.  The boat has a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/1392277.xml">
trampoline</link> both forward and aft of the mast, and is the only rotomolded Hobie to come stock with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/187108.xml">
jib</link> and have an available <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/4577681.xml">
trapeze</link>.  At 16'7", the Getaway is the same length as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Hobie+16%22])">
Hobie 16</link>; the beam is 7'8" and the mast is 25' tall.</p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hobie Dragoon</st>

<p>

The Hobie Dragoon was designed by Hobie Cat Europe as a youth trainer for racing.  Age target was 12 to 14 years.  Double trapeze and spinnaker option to introduce young sailors to high performance. Length: 12' 10",  Beam: 7' 1",  Mast Length: 21',  Sail Area: 118&nbsp;sq&nbsp;ft (11.0&nbsp;m2). Main plus Jib,  Weight: 230&nbsp;lb (100&nbsp;kg).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Hobie 14 </st>

<p>

The Hobie 14 was the original catamaran designed by Hobie Alter.  The general shape and design of the boat is very similar to the later Hobie 16. They share many of the same parts; with the sails down, they are hard to tell apart without a tape measure. The 14 was originally designed to be sailed as a unirig with just a main sail. It is possible to convert a standard 14 into a Hobie 14 "Turbo", also known as the JT14, by adding a jib, trapeze and dolphin striker. No longer manufactured by Hobie North America, the Hobie 14 is still produced in limited numbers by Hobie Europe.</p>
<p>

The Hobie 14 is infamously known for its forward mast and very bent banana shaped hull. The forward mast and odd shaped hulls make the boat quite sensitive to weight placement fore and aft.  If the skipper sits too far forward, he or she can cause the leward bow to dig in, resulting in a pitchpole.  Hobie 14s are great for younger sailors that want a solo-able multihull that can be held down without much weight.  The boat does not carry passengers well, but used boats can be found quite cheaply.</p>
<p>

The boat is slightly faster than the Wave as a standard, and much faster as a Turbo, but cannot carry anywhere near the amount of weight that the Wave can.  It is known for being difficult to tack without a jib.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1895621.xml">
Hobie 16</link></st>

<p>

<it>See Also Separate Wikipedia Entry: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1895621.xml">
Hobie 16</link></it></p>
<p>

The 16 is the most popular Hobie Cat, both for recreational purposes and as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/2035421.xml">
one-design</link> racer.  The boat is 16'7" long, 7'11" wide, and has a mast 26'6" tall, but only weighs 320 pounds.  As with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Hobie+14%22])">
14</link>, it is intended to be sailed from the beach through the surf, and to be surfed back in on the waves to the beach.  Instead of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../217/383217.xml">
daggerboard</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/526180.xml">
centerboards</link>, the 16 has asymmetrical hulls which act like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/2239614.xml">
foils</link> and keep the boat from <it>crabbing</it>, or slipping sideways from the force of the wind.  Both jib and main sails are fully <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/2637151.xml">
batten</link>ed and total 218&nbsp;square feet (20&nbsp;m2).  A trapeze is usually used by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/6801.xml">
crew</link> (and <rank wordnetid="114429985" confidence="0.8">
<military_rank wordnetid="114431471" confidence="0.8">
<status wordnetid="113945919" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/2155405.xml">
skipper</link></state>
</status>
</military_rank>
</rank>
 too in higher winds) to keep the boat from heeling too much.</p>
<p>

One notable flaw is the tendency of the boat to 'pitchpole' when running downwind; the sail plan and distribution of the flotation of the hulls is such that it can push the bows down far enough to dip them under the water, stopping the front of the boat and leading to a <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<plan wordnetid="105898568" confidence="0.8">
<plan_of_action wordnetid="105902545" confidence="0.8">
<tactic wordnetid="105905152" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/2636669.xml">
cartwheel</link></tactic>
</plan_of_action>
</plan>
</idea>
 or sommersault and subsequent capsize of the boat.  Sailors compensate for this by putting their weight as far aft as they can while running downwind. Because of the curved contour of the hulls, in lighter air where pitchpoling isn't a threat, the boat can be steered in much the same fashion as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/222354.xml">
sailboard</link>: as the crew shifts weight fore and aft, the boat tends to turn into or away from the wind. In this manner, the skipper can "trim" the rudders to minimize the force that must be exerted on the tiller extension.</p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hobie 17</st>

<p>

This boat was available in two 'trim packages': the Sport has a jib and a small <conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<vessel wordnetid="104530566" confidence="0.8">
<craft wordnetid="103125870" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<sailing_vessel wordnetid="104128837" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/1658669.xml">
boomlett</link></vehicle>
</sailing_vessel>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</craft>
</vessel>
</conveyance>
 that is not attached to the mast and is intended for recreational use by two people, while the SE has only the main sail, a full boom, and is designed to be raced by one person.  It is 17' long, 8' wide, has a 27' 7" mast and 168 square feet (15.6 m²) of sail area (200 ft² or 18.6 m² with the jib).  Both models have swinging centerboards and 'wings', which are made of aluminum tubing that plug into the hulls and covered with reinforced vinyl or mesh covers that can be used as seats, backrests, or provide more leverage when trapezing.  The uni-rig or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/211646.xml">
catboat</link> sail plan allows the 17SE to 'point' well, or sail closer to straight upwind than many other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/48520.xml">
Sloop</link>-rigged catamarans. As of 2007,  this boat is also out of production.</p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
FX-One</st>

<p>

The FX-One is an import from the France-based <link>
Hobie Cat Europe</link> company.  Similar to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Hobie+17%22])">
17</link>, this boat is designed for single-handed racing.  With or without the optional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/1275469.xml">
gennaker</link>, this boat is not eligible for the <link>
Formula 17</link> multihull class.  Relatively uncommon in North America, the FX-One is 17' long, 8' 4" wide, with a 27' 9" mast and 172 square feet (16.0 m²) of sail area (much more with the spinnaker), and weighs in at 326 pounds (148 kg) with the Formula 17 set-up.</p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hobie 18</st>


<p>

Many people consider the Hobie 18 the quintessential “beach cat.” The Hobie 18 was designed to be not only fast but also rugged. It is designed to be sailed by a crew of two, but can easily carry four passengers when cruising. Experienced sailors can sail the Hobie 18 solo. Unlike the smaller Hobie 14 and 16, the Hobie 18 uses a symmetrical hull design. Although this design gives the 18 a speed advantage, it requires the use of daggerboards when sailing close-hauled or reaching to prevent slipping. The typical configuration for the Hobie 18 is with a both a main sail and a jib. The jib on the 18 is set up on a rolling/ furling system that wraps the jib around the forestay when it isn’t needed. The 18 also uses a built-in traveler car on the rear crossbar. The traveler, which varies the lateral connection point of the main sheet, allows the crew greater flexibility and control when trimming the mainsail. A double trapeze system is also standard equipment on the Hobie 18. Optionally the Hobie 18 may be equipped with wing seats (similar to the 17). Much to the dismay of many Hobie enthusiasts, the Hobie 18 is currently out of production. 
Length= 18',  Beam= 8',  Mast = 28' 1", Sail = 240&nbsp;sq&nbsp;ft (22&nbsp;m2).   Weight = 400&nbsp;lb (180&nbsp;kg)    Hobie 18 Magnum Wing seats (mid 80's style) add 39&nbsp;lb (18&nbsp;kg). </p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hobie 33</st>
<p>

The Hobie 33 is a 33-foot (10&nbsp;m) monohull lift-keel boat designed to be very light and very fast. It is considered a ULDB or ultralight displacement boat. It was intended to be a trailerable, one design racer/cruiser.  The design was the brainchild of Hobie Alter and Sheldon Coleman Sr.  To start the project a Bill Lee designed ULDB Santa Cruz 27 named "Redline" was purchased, analyzed and then raced in southern California. Once the design stage started Lewie and John Wake were brought in to lend racing yacht design experience.  Hobie 18 designer and legendary surfer Phil Edwards designed the keel and rudder. The keel is retractable for ease of trailering.  There is an active class association and national championships yearly.   The Hobie 33 is still a competitive offshore sailing yacht and as recently as 2006, 'Mad Max' was the Overall Winner in the largest international yacht race, The Newport to Ensenada Race, beating vessels of all lengths from 26-90 feet.  In 2005 the Hobie 33 was first in the doublehanded division of Transpac and went on to win it's class against fully crewed boats.
The home page of the class association is http://www.hobie33.com/index.html</p>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Hobie_cat&amp;action=edit">
improve this article or section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(July 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Tiger</st>

<p>

The Tiger, another Hobie Cat Europe import, is Hobie Cat's entry into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/3204604.xml">
Formula 18</link> multihull class.  The Tiger has been very popular and successful both in class racing and Formula 18.  At 18' long, 8' 6" wide, with a 29' 6" mast and 227&nbsp;square feet (21&nbsp;m2) of sail area (452&nbsp;square feet (42&nbsp;m2) with the spinnaker). It weighs in at a minimum of 396 lb (180 kg) as to conform to the Formula 18 specifications. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Miracle 20</st>

<p>

In contrast to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Tiger%22])">
Tiger</link>, the Miracle 20 has 250&nbsp;square feet (23&nbsp;m2) of sail area and takes advantage of light winds.  The 20 is 19' 6" long, 8' 6" wide, with a 31' mast, and weighs 420 pounds.  Some of the early production models had a high rate of hull failures due to a manufacturing defect,  but this was rectified in later models.  As of June, 2007 this model is no longer in production.
The Miracle 20 is designed by Jack Groeneveld, a Dutch catamaran sailor (European champion Prindle 19,winner of the Prindle 19 nationals etc.)</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hobie Fox</st>

<p>

The Hobie Fox was designed by Hobie Cat Europe to meet the Formula 20 racing class rules. The hull shape was designed by world champion A-Class sailor Nils Bunkerberg.  It is a modern wave-piercing hull.  It has a double trapeze, asymmetrical spinnaker with snuffer retrieval system, high performance daggerboards, race rudders, and sails designed by Giorgio Zuccoli.  It is 20' long, has a 8' 6" beam and weighs 419&nbsp;lb (190&nbsp;kg).  Mainsail area is 194 sq/ft (18sq meters.) Jibsail area is 52 sq/ft (4.8sq meters.) Spinnaker area is 269 sq/ft (25sq meters.)</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hobie 21SC</st>

<p>

The 21SC (for Sport Cruiser) was Hobie Cat's first 'family boat'.  Intended for casual sailing, this boat has a front trampoline, wings, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/39846.xml">
outboard motor</link>-mount, and a built-in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/1767371.xml">
cooler</link>.  Though larger than the  at 21' long, 8' 6" wide, with a 29' mast and 222&nbsp;square feet (21&nbsp;m2) of sail, the 21SC was quickly displaced by the more rugged, cheaper Getaway and has been phased out by Hobie Cat.</p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hobie 21SE</st>
<p>

The 21SE hulls are similar to the 21SC but the similarities end there, the 21SE is a performance oriented boat.  It is no longer in production but it had a beam of nearly 10' and 14' with the wings.  It also had centerboards instead of daggerboards a 33' mast and 300&nbsp;sq&nbsp;ft (28&nbsp;m2). of sail.  It had arched, curved crossbars.  It was raced as a one design boat in professional racing circuits.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
TriFoiler</st>
<p>

The TriFoiler is the most unusual of Hobie Cat's boats. Designed by Greg Ketterman, this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/389849.xml">
trimaran</link> has two sails, one on each <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/352760.xml">
ama</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/13761.xml">
hydrofoils</link> that lift the hulls out of the water at speed. It lifts on the foils at wind speeds between 10 and 11&nbsp;mph (18&nbsp;km/h) and quickly accelerates to twice that speed in seconds. On its foils, it sails at approximately twice wind speed and can pull 2+ g's in turns.  The Trifoiler is a production variant of the A class world sailing record holder Longshot, also designed and built by Ketterman.</p>
<p>

The boat seats two persons.  At 22' long, 19' wide, with two 18' masts, and 145 kg (320 lb), the TriFoiler is the biggest multihull ever produced by Hobie Cat. The two sails have a total sail area of 215 sq ft (150&nbsp;sq&nbsp;ft (14&nbsp;m2) reefed). The TriFoiler's high price-tag, fragility, and usage limited to winds between 10 and 25&nbsp;mph (40&nbsp;km/h) with low waves, led Hobie Cat to discontinue production as of 2005.  Approximately 30 Trifoilers were built prior to production starting at Hobie in 1995 and another 190 were produced by Hobie before halt of production.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Racing</st>


<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Hobie_cat&amp;action=edit">
improve this article or section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(April 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Davison, Phil (2008.05.03) <it>Record-breaking aviator who became a legendary surfer</it> The <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/136566.xml">
Financial Times</link></newspaper>
</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/12178388.xml">
Hobart "Hobie" Alter</link> founder and creator of the <b>Hobie Cat</b></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hobiecat.com/sailing/all_models.html">
Hobie Cat sailing models</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hobiecat.com/sailing/">
Hobie Sailing</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hca-na.org/">
Hobie Class of North America</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hobieclass.com/">
International Hobie Class</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.catsailor.com/waves/wave.html">
International Wave Class Association</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hobiecat.org.uk/">
BHCCA - British Hobie Cat Class Association</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Classes and types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/195952.xml">
catamaran</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/389849.xml">
trimaran</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/20025.xml">
multihull</link>(worldwide list)</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/3204134.xml">
A-Catamaran</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link>
ARC 17</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link>
ARC 21</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link>
ARC 22</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/12627349.xml">
Astus 14.1</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/7886115.xml">
Astus 16.1</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/7886825.xml">
Astus 20.1</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/3299955.xml">
Beachcat</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/7676998.xml">
Sprint 15</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/18934959.xml">
Dart 16</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/18629471.xml">
Dart 18</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link>
Dragonfly 800</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/3204756.xml">
Formula 16</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/3204604.xml">
Formula 18</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/1976053.xml">
Hobie</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link>
Mystere</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/17002889.xml">
Nacra</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/1158924.xml">
Proa</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link>
RC 27</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link>
RC 30</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/18914290.xml">
SL 16</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/3288821.xml">
Taipan 4.9</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/18731346.xml">
Topcat</link>&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <specification wordnetid="106725067" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/196241.xml">
Tornado</link></specification>
&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/5010000.xml">
Open Ocean Performance Sixties</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;&amp;bull;  <link>
Unicorn</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
