<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:11:42[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<intellectual  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109621545">
<alumnus  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109786338">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<scholar  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110557854">
<header>
<title>Rob Wrubel</title>
<id>1981643</id>
<revision>
<id>210188413</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-04T21:52:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Chowbok</username>
<id>54304</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Year of birth missing (living people)</category>
<category>Yale University alumni</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Rob Wrubel</b> is a serial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/39862.xml">
entrepreneur</link> and former CEO of Ask Jeeves.  He currently serves as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/52234.xml">
CEO</link> of Aptimus, Inc.<p>

Aptimus, based in San Francisco, CA, is a Point-of-Action online advertising network that reaches engaged users by placing offers in the transactional areas of Web sites they trust. The network consists of ten targeted channels that reach over 10 million consumers each month. Aptimus' uadvertising network delivers qualified customer leads through presenting offers at the points of download, log-in, registration, and other active locations across a diverse set of major publishers such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/1397.xml">
AOL</link></company>
, Tickle, DriverGuide, PictureTrail. The company's proprietary optimization technology presents advertisers' offers on the Web sites where they reach consumers, automatically targeting based on prior consumer response in each location and each individual consumer's demographics.</p>
<p>

Wrubel is also the co-founder and former co-CEO of Whole Body / Yoga Works based in Santa Monica, CA. Yoga Works is the largest operator of Yoga and alternative fitness studios in the Los Angeles county. Yoga Works operates 14 studios located in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/18110.xml">
Los Angeles</link>, <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/45330.xml">
Orange County</link></county>
, and <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/645042.xml">
New York City</link></village>
. The company provides over 1000 classes a week in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/34258.xml">
yoga</link> and other forms of alternative fitness including pilates &amp; meditation. The company also provides professional training programs, workshops, retreats, corporate on-site Yoga and retail product merchandising. Whole Body's plan is to become the leading lifestyle brand and provider of mind-body fitness services in the country.</p>
<p>

From June 2001 to July 2002, Wrubel was an Entrepreneur-in-residence at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/18774830.xml">
Highland Capital Partners</link> where he developed new business concepts for venture funding.</p>
<p>

Before that, Wrubel was the Chief Executive Officer of Ask Jeeves from 1998 to 2001. He grew the company from a 15-employee start-up to a public-market software and services company with $100 million in sales and among the most successful start-ups of the Internet economy. Wrubel created one of the first enduring brands on the Internet, providing consumers new to the Internet an easy way to find what they were looking for on the Web. He raised over $300 million in financing, establishing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/429624.xml">
Ask Jeeves</link> joint venture in three continents. The company was most recently sold to Barry Diller's IAC for $1.95 billion.</p>
<p>

From 1993 to 1998, Wrubel was the Chief Operating Officer of Knowledge Adventure, Inc., the country's largest educational software company. Wrubel was one of the founding team who helped develop and launch the nation's most popular educational software products including <it>JumpStart Software</it>. Wrubel helped grow Knowledge Adventure from a start-up of 20 people with a few hundred thousand in sales to a $250 million in sales software company in five years. Knowledge Adventure was first sold to Cendant and then eventually acquired by Vivendi for $850 million in 1999. </p>
<p>

Before Knowledge Adventure, Wrubel was the Assistant Managing Editor of <it>Financial World Magazine</it> in New York where he wrote nationally recognized articles and features on business and industry trends. </p>
<p>

Wrubel spent his first professional year out of college on <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<street wordnetid="104334599" confidence="0.8">
<way wordnetid="104564698" confidence="0.8">
<thoroughfare wordnetid="104426618" confidence="0.8">
<road wordnetid="104096066" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/37274.xml">
Wall Street</link></road>
</thoroughfare>
</way>
</street>
</artifact>
, helping develop mergers and acquisition analysis to interest-rate swap derivative financial instruments. </p>
<p>

Rob obtained a Bachelor of Arts in History and Economics from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/34273.xml">
Yale University</link></university>
 in 1983.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 References </st>




</sec>
</bdy>
</scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
