<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:17:18[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<proposal  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107162194">
<recommendation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106671637">
<advice  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106671484">
<header>
<title>PSQM</title>
<id>1984332</id>
<revision>
<id>224402974</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-08T18:19:56Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dgtsyb</username>
<id>6383940</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Telecommunications</category>
<category>ITU-T recommendations</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>PSQM</b> (<b><it>Perceptual Speech Quality Measure</it></b>) is a computational and modeling algorithm defined in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/14836.xml">
ITU</link> Recommendation <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/14744.xml">
ITU-T</link> P.861 that objectively evaluates and quantifies voice quality of voice-band (300 - 3400 Hz) 
Speech codecs|speech codecs.
It may be used to rank the performance of these 
Speech codecs|speech codecs with differing speech input levels, talkers, bit rates and transcodings. The ITU-T has Withdrawn P.861 and replaced it with P.862 (<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/11604994.xml">
PESQ</link></advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</message>
) which contains an improved speech assessment algorithm.
<sec>
<st>
Why It's Used</st>
<p>

Using the PSQM standard allows automated, simulation-based test methodologies to objectively rate both speech clarity and transmitted voice quality. Various software and/or hardware products have been developed to facilitate this testing. This results in considerable savings in cost and time over the traditional practice of using large groups of people to subjectively evaluate voice signals and assess voice quality.  Moreover, it yields objective results that are reliable and reproducible. This is very important to telephony providers who are mandated to maintain high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/25315.xml">
Quality of Service</link> standards.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The Algorithm</st>
<p>

PSQM uses a psychoacoustical mathematical modeling (both perceptual and cognitive) algorithm to analyze the pre and post transmitted voice signals, yielding a PSQM value which is a measure of signal quality degradation and ranges from 0 (no degradation) to 6.5 (highest degradation). In turn, this result may be translated into a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/1645752.xml">
Mean Opinion Score</link> (MOS), which is an accepted measure of the perceived quality of received media on a numeric scale ranging from 1 to 5. A value of 1 indicates unacceptable, poor quality voice while a value of 5 indicates high voice quality with no perceptible issues.</p>
<p>

The PSQM algorithm converts the physical-domain signal(s) into the perceptually meaningful psychoacoustic domain through a series of nonlinear processes such as time-frequency mapping, frequency warping and intensity warping, </p>
<p>

The quality of the coded speech is judged on the differences in the internal representation. The difference is used for the calculation of the noise disturbance as a function of time and frequency. Besides perceptual modeling, the PSQM algorithm uses cognitive modeling such as loudness scaling and asymmetric masking in order to get high correlations between subjective and objective measurements.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Its Limitations</st>
<p>

PSQM as originally conceived was not developed to account for network <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/25315.xml">
Quality of Service</link> perturbations common in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
Voice over IP</link> applications, items such as packet loss, delay variance (jitter) or non-sequential packets. These conditions usually give inappropriate results under heavy network load simulations, failing to account for a very real perceived loss of voice quality. Attempts to duplicate network fault conditions by introducing significant packet loss result in PSQM values that correspond to falsely inflated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/1645752.xml">
MOS</link> values.</p>
<p>

In order to overcome this limitation, PSQM+ was developed by modifying the original algorithm. PSQM+ generates results that seem to more accurately reflect the adverse performance of 
Speech codecs|speech codecs under realistic network load conditions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Other Considerations</st>
<p>

Other issues involve the lack of standardization in test signals used to evaluate various 
Speech codecs|speech codecs. PSQM provides more reliable and consistent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/1645752.xml">
MOS</link> scores if used in accordance with ITU recommended methods for objective and subjective assessment of quality (ITU-T p.800/p.830/p.861). These recommendations include using both male and female gender voice reference signals at an average level of -20dB. The type, gender, duration, gain of the voice or signal can all have a minor impact on the PSQM value or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/1645752.xml">
MOS</link> score as does the threshold levels, number of calls made and other configuration settings of the environment.  When comparing voice quality measurements the signal, environment and configurations should all be taken into account.</p>
<p>

Many 
Speech codecs|speech codecs exist and are used in a wide variety of applications. Careful selection of appropriate speech codec(s) is necessary to match system requirements. A list of common 
Speech codecs|speech codecs and their associated PSQM/PSQM+ derived <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/1645752.xml">
MOS</link> values obtained under various network load conditions is available.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/11604994.xml">
Perceptual Evalution of Speech Quality (PESQ), the successor technology for PSQM</link></advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/1645752.xml">
Mean Opinion Score</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">


Speech codecs|speech codecs</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
Voice over IP</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-P.861/e">
ITU-T P.861</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>


Speech codecs|speech codecs</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</message>
</article>
