<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:09:29[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Plastic recycling</title>
<id>1999119</id>
<revision>
<id>243750799</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T22:08:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rjwilmsi</username>
<id>203434</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>NPOV disputes from December 2007</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
<category>Articles containing how-to sections</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since January 2008</category>
<category>Plastics</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Recycling</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Mergefrom.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that  be  into this article or section. ()</col>
</row>
</table>


<image location="right" width="150px" src="Plastic_recycle.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Sorted household plastic waiting to be hauled away for reprocessing.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<table style="font-size: 90%;float: right" class="infobox">
<header style="background: #ccf; text-align: center">
<b>Recycling Concepts</b></header>
<row>
<col>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/1533268.xml">
Waste hierarchy</link></concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/70157.xml">
Recycling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/4065672.xml">
Reuse</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/3808169.xml">
Regiving</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/185313.xml">
Freeganism</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="background: #ccf; text-align: center">
<b>Materials</b></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/1999119.xml">
Plastic recycling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/5443767.xml">
Aluminium recycling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/13207354.xml">
Battery recycling</link></concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/3053725.xml">
Glass recycling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/1524589.xml">
Paper recycling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/10193761.xml">
Textile recycling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/10448817.xml">
Recycling timber</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/1068262.xml">
Scrap</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>

<b>Plastic recycling</b> is the process of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/4290854.xml">
recover</link>ing scrap or waste <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/23883.xml">
plastics</link> and reprocessing the material into useful products, sometimes completely different from their original state. For instance, this could mean melting down <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/27061.xml">
soft drink</link> bottles then making model army figures and ammunition..</p>
<p>

Before recycling, plastics are sorted according to their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/70154.xml">
resin identification code</link>.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/292941.xml">
PET</link>, for instance, has a resin code of 1.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Processing</st>
<p>

When compared to other materials like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/12581.xml">
glass</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/19042.xml">
metal</link> materials, plastic polymers require greater processing to be recycled. Plastics have a low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/9891.xml">
entropy</link> of mixing, which is due to the high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/60034.xml">
molecular weight</link> of their large polymer chains. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/106231.xml">
macromolecule</link> interacts with its environment along its entire length, so its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/10274.xml">
enthalpy</link> of mixing is large compared to that of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/66581.xml">
organic</link> molecule with a similar structure. Heating alone is not enough to dissolve such a large molecule; because of this, plastics must often be of nearly identical composition in order to mix efficiently.</p>
<p>

When different types of plastics are melted together they tend to <link>
phase-separate</link>, like oil and water, and set in these layers. The <link>
phase boundaries</link> cause structural weakness in the resulting material, meaning that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/11471537.xml">
polymer blend</link>s are only useful in limited applications.</p>
<p>

Another barrier to recycling is the widespread use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/8179.xml">
dyes</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/10165481.xml">
fillers</link>, and other additives in plastics. The polymer is generally too <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18963754.xml">
viscous</link> to economically remove fillers, and would be damaged by many of the processes that could cheaply remove the added dyes. Additives are less widely used in beverage containers and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/1613879.xml">
plastic bag</link>s, allowing them to be recycled more frequently.</p>
<p>

The use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/6104177.xml">
biodegradable plastic</link>s is increasing.  If some of these get mixed in the other plastics for recycling, the recycled plastic is less valuable.</p>
<p>

Many such problems can be solved by using a more elaborate <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/19583.xml">
monomer</link> recycling</it> process, in which a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/6247.xml">
condensation polymer</link> essentially undergoes the inverse of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/23872.xml">
polymerization</link> reaction used to manufacture it.  This yields the same mix of chemicals that formed the original polymer, which can be purified and used to synthesize new polymer chains of the same type.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/201829.xml">
Du Pont</link> opened a pilot plant of this type in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/471799.xml">
Cape Fear, North Carolina</link>, USA, to recycle PET by a process of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/190458.xml">
methanolysis</link>, but it closed the plant due to economic pressures.</p>
<p>

Another potential option is the conversion of assorted polymers into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/23195.xml">
petroleum</link> by a much less precise <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/213682.xml">
thermal depolymerization</link> process.  Such a process would be able to accept almost any polymer or mix of polymers, including <link>
thermoset</link> materials such as vulcanized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/38393.xml">
rubber</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/65037.xml">
tire</link>s and the biopolymers in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/50873.xml">
feather</link>s and other agricultural waste.  Like natural petroleum, the chemicals produced can be made into fuels as well as polymers.  A pilot plant of this type exists in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/122784.xml">
Carthage, Missouri</link></village>
, USA, using turkey waste as input material. <it>See the main article on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/213682.xml">
thermal depolymerization</link>.</it>  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/262256.xml">
Gasification</link> is a similar process, but is not technically recycling since polymers are not likely to become the result.</p>
<p>

Recently, a process has also been developed in which many kinds of plastic can be used as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/5299.xml">
carbon</link> source in the recycling of scrap <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/27058.xml">
steel</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Yet another process that is gaining ground with startup companies (especially in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
, <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/15573.xml">
Japan</link>) is heat compression. The heat compression process takes all unsorted, cleaned plastic in all forms, from soft plastic bags to hard industrial waste, and mixes the load in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/429884.xml">
tumblers</link> (large rotating drums resembling giant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/317900.xml">
clothes dryer</link>s). The most obvious benefit to this method is the fact that all plastic is recyclable, not just matching forms. But criticism rises from the energy costs of rotating the drums, and heating the post-melt pipes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/922636.xml">
Recycling of PET bottles</link></it>
</indent>

Post-consumer PET (number 1) is often sorted into different color fractions. This sorted post-consumer PET waste is crushed, pressed into bales and offered for sale to recycling companies. PET flakes are used as the raw material for a range of products that would otherwise be made of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/3508478.xml">
polyester</link>.</p>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/9877910.xml">
PVC recycling</link></it>
</indent>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/24458.xml">
PVC</link>- or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/32436.xml">
Vinyl</link> Recycling has historically been difficult to perfect on the industrial scale. But within the last decade several viable methods for recycling or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/5585091.xml">
upcycling</link> PVC <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/23883.xml">
plastic</link> have been developed.</p>
<p>

The most-often recycled plastic, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/1911597.xml">
HDPE</link> or number 2, is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/1648512.xml">
downcycled</link> into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/6420379.xml">
plastic lumber</link>, tables, roadside curbs, benches, truck cargo liners, trash receptacles, stationery (e.g rulers) and other durable plastic products and is usually in demand.</p>
<p>

The white plastic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/1447078.xml">
foam peanut</link>s used as packing material are often accepted by shipping stores for reuse.</p>
<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/9282173.xml">
Israel</link></country>
 successful trials have shown that plastic films recovered from mixed municipal waste streams can be recycled into useful household products such as buckets.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Similarly, <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/6300466.xml">
agricultural plastics</link></issue>
 such as <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/757240.xml">
mulch film</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/757206.xml">
drip tape</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/246507.xml">
silage</link> bags are being diverted from the waste stream and successfully recycled <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> into much larger products for industrial applications such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../780/529780.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Plastic/Rubber+Composite%22])">
plastic composite railroad ties</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  Historically, these agricultural plastics have primarily been either landfilled or burned on-site in the fields of individual farms.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

CNN reports that Indian Dr. S. Madhu of the Kerala Highway Research Institute has formulated a road surface that includes recycled plastic.  Aggregate, bitumen (asphalt) with plastic that has been shredded and melted at a temperature below 220 degrees C (428 °F) to avoid pollution. This road surface is claimed to be very durable and monsoon rain resistant.  The plastic is sorted by hand, which is economical in India. The test road used 60 kg of plastic for an approx. 500m long, 8m wide, two-lane road. Since the US annually uses 100 million metric tons of plastic, it could pave 1.67 billion km of single-lane road this way.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Consumers</st>

<p>

Plastic recycling rates lag far behind those of other items, such as newspaper (about 80%) and cardboard (about 70%). One reason is that consumers often don’t understand the types of plastics that can be recycled in their area. Types of plastics are assigned a number, called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/70154.xml">
resin identification code</link>, which is usually stamped or printed on the bottom of containers and surrounded by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/1532080.xml">
recycling symbol</link> (a triangle of arrows). (See the table in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/23883.xml">
Plastic</link>.) Numbers 1, 2, and 6 are the most-often recycled plastics in the United States. Many municipal recycling programs exist in the United States.</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section contains 
Articles containing how-to sections|instructions, advice, or how-to content.</b>
<p>

The purpose of Wikipedia is to present facts, not to teach subject matter. Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Plastic_recycling&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> either by rewriting the how-to content or by  it to .</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>


Consumers can find out which plastics are accepted in their local area and how to recycle, prepare and transfer them by contacting their local recycling hauler (usually the local city or county solid waste or public works department, or a private company). Generally, paper labels do not need to be removed from plastic bottles or containers, but lids should be thrown away because they typically are made from a type of plastic that is not recyclable. Plastic bottles and containers must be rinsed, squashed, and placed in recycle bins for collection. Plastic grocery bags are often accepted by stores in recycling containers placed near the entranceways. </p>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Ambox_?.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>All or part of this article may be .</b>
Please help . Suggestions may be on the . <it>(August 2007)</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>


<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="ambox_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section has been nominated to be checked for its .</b>
Discussion of this nomination can be found on the . <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


In the UK, the amount of post-consumer plastic being recycled is relatively low<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>, due in part to a lack of recycling facilities. Only a few exist in the whole country and many people do not know what plastics can be recycled. Furthermore, most of the plastic that is re-used is sent to China to be recycled, raising ethical questions as well as concern that such recycling costs more CO2 emissions than simply burying in landfill. Others will counterclaim that many recycling programs exist in the UK, and landfill is not an option if there are no sites to fill. One of the largest recyclers of PET bottles is based there and also has initiated one of the first "bottle to bottle" recycling businesses in the world. Many other 'waste' products are sent to China for recycling, using the often empty containers that are used for delivering goods to the UK and that are sent back for re-use.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Plastic Identification Code</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/70154.xml">
Resin identification code</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</it>
</indent>

Seven groups of plastic polymers,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> each with specific properties, are used worldwide for packaging applications (see table below). Each group of plastic polymer can be identified by its Plastic Identification code (PIC) - usually a number or a letter abbreviation. For instance, Low-Density Polyethylene can be identified by the number 4 and/or the letters "LDPE". The PIC appears inside a three-chasing arrow recycling symbol. The symbol is used to indicate whether the plastic can be recycled into new products.</p>
<p>

The PIC was introduced by the Society of the Plastics Industry, Inc. which provides a uniform system for the identification of different polymer types and helps recycling companies to separate different plastics for reprocessing. Manufacturers of plastic food packaging and containers can voluntarily mark their products with the PIC. Consumers can identify the plastic types based on the codes usually found at the base or at the side of the plastic food packaging and containers. The PIC is usually not present on packaging films, as it is not practical to collect and recycle most of this type of waste.</p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<row>
<header>
Plastic Identification Code</header>
<header>
Type of plastic polymer</header>
<header>
Properties</header>
<header>
Common Packaging Applications</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <image width="100px" src="Plastic-recyc-01.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/292941.xml">
Polyethylene Terephthalate</link>(PET, PETE)</col>
<col>
Clarity, strength, toughness, barrier to gas and moisture.</col>
<col>
Soft drink, water and salad dressing bottles; peanut butter and jam jars</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <image width="100px" src="Plastic-recyc-02.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/1911597.xml">
High Density Polyethylene</link>(HDPE)</col>
<col>
Stiffness, strength, toughness, resistance to moisture, permeability to gas.</col>
<col>
Milk, juice and water bottles; trash and retail bags.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <image width="100px" src="Plastic-recyc-03.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/24458.xml">
Polyvinyl Chloride</link>(V)</col>
<col>
Versatility, clarity, ease of blending, strength, toughness.</col>
<col>
Juice bottles; cling films; PVC piping</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <image width="100px" src="Plastic-recyc-04.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../217/2138217.xml">
Low Density Polyethylene</link>(LDPE)</col>
<col>
Ease of processing, strength, toughness, flexibility, ease of sealing, barrier to moisture.</col>
<col>
Frozen food bags; squeezable bottles, e.g. honey, mustard; cling films; flexible container lids.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <image width="100px" src="Plastic-recyc-05.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/201689.xml">
Polypropylene</link>(PP)</col>
<col>
Strength, toughness, resistance to heat, chemicals, grease and oil, versatile, barrier to moisture.</col>
<col>
Reusable microwaveable ware; kitchenware; yogurt containers; margarine tubs; microwaveable disposable take-away containers; disposable cups and plates.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <image width="100px" src="Plastic-recyc-06.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/168393.xml">
Polystyrene</link>(PS)</col>
<col>
Versatility, clarity, easily formed</col>
<col>
Egg cartons; packing peanuts; disposable cups, plates, trays and cutlery; disposable take-away containers;</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <image width="100px" src="Plastic-recyc-07.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col>
 Other (often <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/536313.xml">
polycarbonate</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/233778.xml">
ABS</link>)</col>
<col>
Dependent on polymers or combination or polymers</col>
<col>
Beverage bottles; baby milk bottles; electronic casing.</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>


The quantity of post-consumer plastics recycled has increased every year since at least 1990.  In 2006 the amount of plastic bottles recycled reached a record high of 2,220,000,000 pounds.

The amount of PET bottles recycled in 2006 increased more than 102 million pounds compared to 2005. 

HDPE bottle recycling increased in 2005 to 928 million pounds.

All plastic bottles were recycled at a rate of 24 percent in 2005.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnn.com/2005/TECH/08/10/plastic.steel.reut/index.html">
Steel</weblink> CNN, Accessed 9.11.06</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oaktech-environmental.com/plastictrials.htm">
Plastic trial procedure</weblink> Oaktech Environmental website, accessed 9.11.06</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rkoindustries.com/id26.html">
Agricultural plastics recycling process</weblink> Agricultural plastics recycling website, accessed 07.11.08</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rti-railroad-tie.com/id5.html">
Plastic Composite Railroad Tie Facts</weblink> Plastic Composite Railroad Ties website, accessed 01.21.08</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://environmentalrisk.cornell.edu/AgPlastics/References/Garthe&amp;Kowal-a.pdf">
Recycling Used Agricultural Plastics</weblink> James W. Garthe, Paula D. Kowal, PennState University, Agricultural and Biological Engineering</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wasteonline.org.uk/resources/InformationSheets/Plastics.htm#_Hows">
Plastics</weblink> wasteonline.org.uk, Accessed 10.18.07</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ava.gov.sg/FoodSector/FoodSafetyEducation/Food+Facts/SafeUsePlasticContainers/index.htm">
Safe Use Of Plastic Food Packaging And Containers</weblink>".</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/487247.xml">
Reuse of water bottles</link></concept>
</idea>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://environment.about.com/od/reducingwaste/a/corn_plastic.htm">
 Why are So Few Food Containers Made of Recyclable Plastic? about.com</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.americanchemistry.com/s_plastics/bin.asp?CID=1102&amp;DID=4645&amp;DOC=FILE.PDF">
American Chemistry Council: Plastic Packaging Resin Codes</weblink>  </entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Health issues of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/23883.xml">
plastics</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/753475.xml">
Plasticizers</link>: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../552/343552.xml">
Phthalate</link>s</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/4953420.xml">
DIBP</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/6888751.xml">
DBP</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/3007126.xml">
BBP</link> aka BBzP&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/3003614.xml">
DEHP</link> aka DOP&nbsp;·  <link>
DIDP</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
DINP</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
DIDP</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other plasticizers</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/959629.xml">
Organophosphates</link>&nbsp;·  <ion wordnetid="109315159" confidence="0.8">
<particle wordnetid="109386422" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="109224911" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<anion wordnetid="109197815" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/2908805.xml">
Adipate</link></anion>
</natural_object>
</body>
</particle>
</ion>
-based (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/3151279.xml">
DEHA</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/3000562.xml">
DOA</link>)</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Hardeners</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/1001430.xml">
Bisphenol A</link> (in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/536313.xml">
Polycarbonates</link>)</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other additives</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<retardant wordnetid="109408250" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<waste wordnetid="114856263" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="109190918" confidence="0.8">
<pollutant wordnetid="114857278" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/801852.xml">
PBDEs</link></material>
</pollutant>
</agent>
</part>
</causal_agent>
</substance>
</waste>
</physical_entity>
</retardant>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/48230.xml">
PCBs</link>&nbsp;·  <waste wordnetid="114856263" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<compound wordnetid="105870180" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<pollutant wordnetid="114857278" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/1867619.xml">
Organotin</link></material>
</pollutant>
</part>
</compound>
</substance>
</waste>
s</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/23883.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Negative+health+effects%22])">
Health issues</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/223011.xml">
Teratogen</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/6445.xml">
Carcinogen</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/903152.xml">
Endocrine disruptor</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/44677.xml">
Diabetes</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/56435.xml">
Obesity</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Miscellaneous</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/24458.xml">
PVC</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/1999119.xml">
Plastic recycling</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/11614796.xml">
Plastic bottle</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/301888.xml">
Vinyl chloride</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/13932142.xml">
dioxin</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/168393.xml">
polystyrene</link>&nbsp;·  <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<polymer wordnetid="114994328" confidence="0.8">
<compound wordnetid="114818238" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/201308.xml">
Styrofoam</link></material>
</part>
</chemical>
</compound>
</polymer>
</substance>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/30791.xml">
PTFE</link> (Teflon)&nbsp;·  <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<vote wordnetid="100182213" confidence="0.8">
<referendum wordnetid="100181640" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<proposition wordnetid="106750804" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/570103.xml">
California Proposition 65 (1986)</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</proposition>
</event>
</referendum>
</vote>
</group_action>
</message>
</statement>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/154347.xml">
List of environmental health hazards</link>&nbsp;·  <process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<consequence wordnetid="111410625" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/1410400.xml">
Persistent organic pollutant</link></consequence>
</issue>
</phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
