<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:10:18[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<society  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107966140">
<fraternity  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108229467">
<header>
<title>Pi Alpha Phi</title>
<id>2014068</id>
<revision>
<id>244458295</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T22:16:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cydebot</username>
<id>1215485</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>United States student societies</category>
<category>Fraternities and sororities</category>
<category>Philanthropic organizations</category>
<category>Asian American organizations</category>
<category>Organizations based in California</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Fraternity</name>
<parameters>
<scope>
National</scope>
<symbol>
<it>Brotherhood Links''</it></symbol>
<chapters>
13 Chapters, 2 Associate</chapters>
<colors>
Berkeley Blue and California Gold</colors>
<state>
California</state>
<type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/18739286.xml">
Social</link></type>
<homepage>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pialphaphi.com">
Pi Alpha Phi National Website</weblink></homepage>
<city>
Berkeley</city>
<country>
USA</country>
<founded>
1929</founded>
<birthplace>
UC Berkeley</birthplace>
<address>
2534 Warring Street</address>
<name>
Pi Alpha Phi</name>
<emphasis>
<ethnic_group wordnetid="107967382" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/148898.xml">
Asian-American</link></ethnic_group>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/2538117.xml">
Interest</link></emphasis>
<motto>
<it>"A Tradition of Excellence Since 1929"''</it></motto>
<crest>
<image width="150px" src="Crest1926.jpg">
<caption>

Pi Alpha Phi crest
</caption>
</image>
</crest>
<letters>
<b>ΠΑΦ</b></letters>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>Pi Alpha Phi (ΠΑΦ also known as PAPhis, Pineapples)</b>  is an <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
American</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/19725260.xml">
university</link>-level <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/7954524.xml">
fraternity</link>. It was founded in 1929 at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/31922.xml">
University of California, Berkeley</link></ranking>
</university>
. Pi Alpha Phi is the first <ethnic_group wordnetid="107967382" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/148898.xml">
Asian-American</link></ethnic_group>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/2538117.xml">
Interest Fraternity</link>. Since its founding in the early 20th century, the fraternity has expanded with active chapters at campuses throughout the United States.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

Pi Alpha Phi Fraternity was established in 1929 at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/31922.xml">
University of California, Berkeley</link></ranking>
</university>
 by six founding fathers: D. Wing Tom, Wing Chan, Elmer Leong, Chack Chan, Tim Jang, and George Lee. Pi Alpha Phi's six founders formed their own Asian American fraternity in part because traditional Greek fraternities legally discriminated against them. Following the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/55668.xml">
Chinese Exclusion Act</link>, the emergence of the first Chinese-American fraternity served as an organizational and academic haven to the sons of Chinese-American immigrants attending the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/31922.xml">
University of California, Berkeley</link></ranking>
</university>
. Though not the first nationally recognized, Pi Alpha Phi's standards and traditions have paved the template for other young Asian-American fraternities half a century later.</p>
<p>

After forming the fraternity, Wing Chan was elected as its first president. D. Wing Tom served as the Vice President and Elmer Leong as the Secretary. They wanted to establish an organization that would be based on the bonds of friendship, mutual experience, academic excellence and brotherhood. The name Pi Alpha Phi was derived from the initials of the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/11887.xml">
Greek</link></language>
 phrase meaning "To advance through brotherly ties; the thirst for learning."</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Founders</st>


<p>

The Founding Fathers of Pi Alpha Phi hailed primarily from the state of California. Elmer Leong, George Lee, and D. Wing Tom were from the SF Bay Area. Tim Jang, Wing Chan, and his younger brother Chack Chan came from the Central Valley Region of California. All were born in America with the exception of Wing Chan, who came from China at an early age.   </p>
<p>

The men studied science and engineering, which was considered a better path to employment after graduation since discrimination prevented most Asians from entering into law, medicine or other graduate disciplines.</p>
<p>

Their challenges grew as they found out that student lodging was often not rented to those of Asian heritage. It was especially difficult for Tim, Wing and Chack from the Central Valley for whom commuting was not an option. The problem was solved by the goodwill of a sympathetic German woman known as Mother Tusch, who also had been a victim of racism. The seeds of brotherhood were planted in the cabin she rented to Wing, Elmer and D. Wing Tom behind her house near Sather Gate.</p>
<p>

The six men proceeded with their college careers, engaging in academic and social events, as well as athletics. Elmer Leong even joined the university track team. They found great comfort and camaraderie in their small group but felt compelled to turn their group into more than a circle of friends, more than a club, more than a social gathering. They decided to form a formal fraternity of brothers that would bind them forever; a fraternity that would break the status quo and seek recognition by the university system.</p>
<p>

Following graduation in the early 1930s, the Founding Fathers found life difficult. The country was in the midst of the Great Depression and discrimination against those of Asian heritage for jobs was even more prevalent. Four of the six - Wing Chan, Chack Chan, D. Wing Tom and George Lee - went to southern China to find employment and new lives. Tim and Elmer decided to stay in America to continue their education and start a career despite the difficult circumstances. The four in China prospered, with Wing teaching chemistry at a university in Canton, Chack Chan working in the local aircraft industry, George Lee pursuing a medical degree; and all four found their wives and started their families.</p>
<p>

In 1937, with the advent of war in China, all returned home to America with the exception of Wing, who returned after World War II. During wartime, each of the founding fathers made contributions to their country. For example, Tim enlisted in the U.S. Navy Seabees. He served as a construction corpsman for the 132nd Naval Construction Battalion in the Pacific. Chack put his engineering skills to use as a draftsman at the famed Henry J. Kaiser naval shipyard in Richmond, California, where many of the country's great war ships were built.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mission Statement</st>
<p>

Pi Alpha Phi focuses itself on several core values, which are written into its <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pialphaphi.com/aboutus/mission.asp">
mission statement</weblink>. These include:
</p>
<ss1>
<st>
 Brotherhood </st>
<p>

The Fraternity encourages mutual trust, respect, and loyalty among its members. The Fraternity creates an extended family that nurtures life-long "friendships" through the shared bonds of tradition, shared values, and unity.</p>

<ss3>
<st>
National Convention</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>First Annual - Arcadia, CA (Embassy Suites) - hosted by Epsilon Chapter, Riverside CA - Convention House Party at Diamond Bar</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>2001 - San Francisco, CA - hosted by Alpha Chapter, Berkeley, CA - Kamakazi Party at Oakland Convention Center</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>2002 - Los Angeles, CA (Bonaventure Hotel) hosted by Epsilon Chapter, Riverside, CA - Tsunami Party at Club SOHO, Joint exchange with National Alpha Phi Gamma Sorority (They had their convention in the same location)</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>2003 - Irvine, CA -  hosted by Eta Chapter, Irvine, CA - First ever 4 day convention on Memorial day weekend. Joint exchange and party at Knotts Berry Farm with National alpha Kappa Delta Phi (They had their convention in the same location)</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>2005 - Koreatown, CA - hosted by Theta Chapter, San Diego, CA</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>2006 - Las Vegas, NV - hosted by Kappa Chapter, Arizona</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>2007 - Irvine, CA - hosted by Eta Chapter, Irvine, CA</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>2008 - Berkeley, CA hosted by Alpha Chapter, Berkeley, CA - Joint Convention with National SOPi. Sponsored by Princeton Review.</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

----</p>

</ss3>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Academic Excellence </st>
<p>

The Fraternity creates a studious environment and encourages each of its members to achieve his greatest academic potential. The Fraternity supports all educational endeavors and recognizes exceptional academic achievement.
----
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Philanthropy </st>
<p>
 
The Fraternity is committed to its responsibility to serve others and encourages participation in activities for the betterment of not only the Asian American community, but the community as a whole.  One of its national events is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/4258255.xml">
Jade Ribbon Campaign</link>.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Jade Ribbon Campaign</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Jrc_txt.svg">
<caption>

Jrc txt.svg
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The Jade Ribbon Campaign spreads awareness of the
greatest health disparity between Asian Americans and
white Americans: liver cancer, 80% of which is caused
by chronic hepatitis B infection.</p>
<p>

The dragon the fraternity purchased was thought to
have a capacity of only 20 people, but when it was put
together, it was much longer. Although the dragon may
not have been the most elaborate of the parade, it was
definitely the longest, as the crowd surely recognized
as the dragon snaked through the downtown parade
route.</p>
<p>

The fraternity members took advantage of our opportunity
by having a great turnout: almost 100 fraternity
members showed up to participate and share in the
bonds of brotherhood. Running a dragon at the parade
has always been a great opportunity for the fraternity’s
members to work together, build the bonds of brotherhood,
and celebrate cultural traditions. This year, they
were also able to support a great philanthropic cause:
the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/4258255.xml">
Jade Ribbon Campaign</link>.</p>
<p>

----</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Leadership </st>
<p>

The Fraternity provides opportunities to fulfill important duties within the organization and helps members develop leadership skills in preparation for their future careers and endeavors.
----
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Asian American Awareness </st>
<p>

The Fraternity believes in learning Asian American culture, heritage and history. The Fraternity encourages its members to pass on this knowledge to others.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Cross Cultural Acceptance </st>
<p>

When Pi Alpha Phi was founded in the 1920s, traditional Greek fraternities along with the rest of the nation, legally discriminated against <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/526594.xml">
men of color</link>. Since they were banned from joining a traditional Greek fraternity, Pi Alpha Phi's Founding Fathers wanted to ensure that Asian American Awareness would forever be an important part of the Fraternity.</p>
<p>

Today, the basic premise of the fraternity remains largely unchanged. Although the fraternity is open to people of all ethnic backgrounds it still retains its Asian American character. With emphasis on brotherhood, the fraternity works to create lifelong bonds that extend far beyond the university setting. The basic goals of brotherhood attained through shared experience, friendship and academics remain unaltered. Although the organization has evolved from generation to generation, the vision of Pi Alpha Phi and its members is the same today as it was for six Berkeley men in 1926.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Chinese Historical Society of Southern California </st>
<p>

Established in 1975, a non-profit organization dedicated to bringing together people with a common interest in the history of Chinese and Chinese-Americans in Southern California. Society Conducts research, collects materials and artifacts and disseminates information. Pi Alpha Phi Alumnus are mentioned quite a few times in this book. Refer to Notable Alumni section.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 San Francisco Chinese New Year Parade </st>

<p>

From the mid 1980’s to the early 2000’s, Pi Alpha
Phi was a mainstay in the parade, operating what had
affectionately become known as the “Pi Alpha Phi
Dragon”. 
It was an event that truly exemplified the close bonds
of brotherhood among the chapters of the fraternity:
an opportunity for fraternity members all over to come
together, have fun, and celebrate a cultural tradition.</p>
<p>

Since 2002, due to several factors including the retiring
of our dragon as well as criteria changes for
participating organizations, the fraternity has not
participated in the parade. </p>
<p>

Their efforts were rewarded when the parade committee
graciously extended a parade invitation to Pi Alpha
Phi and its partner the Jade Ribbon Campaign to operate
a Jade Ribbon Dragon.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Chinese New Year Parade, 2000, 2002 and 2006</st>
<p>

http://youtube.com/watch?v=uAwhlTLlAZQ</p>



</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Chinese New Year Parade, 2007</st>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Jade Ribbon Campaign</st>

<p>

The Jade Ribbon Campaign spreads awareness of the
greatest health disparity between Asian Americans and
white Americans: liver cancer, 80% of which is caused
by chronic hepatitis B infection.</p>
<p>

The dragon the fraternity purchased was thought to
have a capacity of only 20 people, but when it was put
together, it was much longer. Although the dragon may
not have been the most elaborate of the parade, it was
definitely the longest, as the crowd surely recognized
as the dragon snaked through the downtown parade
route.</p>
<p>

The fraternity members took advantage of our opportunity
by having a great turnout: almost 100 fraternity
members showed up to participate and share in the
bonds of brotherhood. Running a dragon at the parade
has always been a great opportunity for the fraternity’s
members to work together, build the bonds of brotherhood,
and celebrate cultural traditions. This year, they
were also able to support a great philanthropic cause:
the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/4258255.xml">
Jade Ribbon Campaign</link>.</p>
<p>

http://medstaging.stanford.edu/liver/</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Chapters </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Α</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/31922.xml">
University of California, Berkeley</link></ranking>
</university>
 - 1929</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>B</b> Chapter - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/251208.xml">
State University of New York, Stony Brook</link> - 1990 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Γ</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/31924.xml">
University of California, Davis</link></ranking>
</university>
 - 1990</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Δ</b> Chapter - <link>
San José State University</link> - 1991 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Ε</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/230311.xml">
University of California, Riverside</link></ranking>
</university>
 - 1993 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Ζ</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/31923.xml">
University of California, Santa Cruz</link></university>
 - 1995  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Η</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/44757.xml">
University of California, Irvine</link></ranking>
</university>
 - 1998 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Θ</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/31927.xml">
University of California, San Diego</link></ranking>
</university>
 - 2000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ι</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/31740.xml">
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor</link></university>
 - 2000 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Κ</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/32015.xml">
University of Arizona, Tucson</link></university>
 - 2002 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Μ</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/241128.xml">
Michigan State University</link></university>
 - 2003  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ν</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/89510.xml">
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</link></university>
 - 2003 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ξ</b> Chapter - <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/31776.xml">
University of Washington</link></university>
 - 2004</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Associate Chapters</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/211917.xml">
University of California, Santa Barbara</link></ranking>
</university>
 - 2006</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/465598.xml">
State University of New York, Buffalo</link> - 2008</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notable Alumni </st>
<p>

Today Pi Alpha Phi's Alumni Association consists of one of the largest networks of alumni spanning back from the mid 1920s.  The following are some notable alumni:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Johnson Chao</link> &mdash; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/52234.xml">
Chief Executive Officer</link> of <link>
Takira</link> Inc.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/5307649.xml">
Thomas Chinn</link> &mdash; former Sacramento City Councilman</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Gilbert Choy</link> &mdash; leading <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5042862.xml">
China</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/57349.xml">
economist</link> and Director at Dresdner Kleinwort Benson</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Edwin M. Epstein</link> &mdash; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/185793.xml">
Professor Emeritus</link> at UC Berkeley, Haas School of Business</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Edward Gee</link> &mdash; first licensed Chinese-American <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/63089.xml">
real estate</link> agent in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/49728.xml">
San Francisco, CA</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Dr. Timothy S. Gee</link> &mdash; One of the country’s leaders in the field of cancer research</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Professor Bill Hing</link> &mdash; Professor of Asian American Studies and the School of Law <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/31924.xml">
UC Davis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
George Kan</link> &mdash; Vice President of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/13973.xml">
Hewlett-Packard</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Dr. Frank Y. Lee</link> &mdash; served on the 1984 U.S. <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/22576.xml">
Olympic</link></psychological_feature>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
 Committee</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Wing Lew</link>&mdash; Vice President of St. Joseph Lead and Mineral Company</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Mike Lee, Esq.</link> &mdash; President of the <link>
San Francisco Bar Association</link> former attorney of the <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/4375.xml">
Barry Bonds</link></player>
</person>
 single-season Major League record 73rd Home Run Baseball Trial. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<benefactor wordnetid="109608709" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<good_person wordnetid="110138767" confidence="0.8">
<coach wordnetid="109931640" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<philanthropist wordnetid="110421956" confidence="0.8">
<trainer wordnetid="110722575" confidence="0.8">
<executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.8">
<donor wordnetid="110025730" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/11267339.xml">
Evan Leong</link></scholar>
</head>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</leader>
</administrator>
</donor>
</executive>
</trainer>
</philanthropist>
</intellectual>
</coach>
</good_person>
</person>
</benefactor>
</physical_entity>
 &mdash; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/506181.xml">
filmmaker</link>, "Forging a Feature: The Journey of BLT", “Better Luck Tomorrow", "Finishing the Game: The Search for a New Bruce Lee",The Fast and "the Furious: Tokyo Drift"</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Dr. Allen Lim Ph.D</link> &mdash; Air Force Engineer of the Year</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Dr. Wing Mar</link> &mdash; UC Berekeley 1949 &mdash; retired family physician, founding member of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/19060873.xml">
Chinese Historical Society of Southern California</link>. Published Portraits of Pride Book.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<judge wordnetid="110225219" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/12429344.xml">
Delbert E. Wong</link></judge>
 &mdash; retired Superior Court Judge, <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
World War II</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/327806.xml">
veteran</link> First person of Chinese descent to be appointed to the judiciary in the continental United States. Appointed as the Special Master in the O.J. Simpson murder trial.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
George Q. Woo</link> &mdash; Executive Secretary of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/6588738.xml">
Chinese Six Companies</link> or The Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/194551.xml">
Sammy Davis, Jr.</link></actor>
 &mdash; made an honorary brother, renown American entertainer and civil rights activist</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Pi Alpha Phi alumni are influential in the entertainment industry. Members such as Brian Gee, Tien Truong, Edward Labao, and Wilson Wu have worked on such feature films as E.T., Toy Story, Terminator 2, Jurassic Park, Star Wars: Episode I and II, A.I.: Artificial Intelligence, Space Jam, X-Men, Shrek, and the Hulk.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controversy</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 San José State University </st>
<p>

In January 2003, Lambda Phi Epsilon member and junior at SJSU, Alam Kim, was killed in a fight between members of Lambda Phi Epsilon and Pi Alpha Phi. Alam Kim was an alumnus of <school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/1315302.xml">
Lowell High School</link></school>
 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/49728.xml">
San Francisco, California</link></village>
, where he commanded the Lowell Boys Drill Team. Friends say Alam was trying to stop the fight between the two fraternities before he was killed by getting stabbed through his heart.  Although a homicide suspect has not been singled out, a $1 million warrant was issued for Long Duy Tran, a 20-year-old San Jose man who is considered a major suspect in the incident. Long Duy Tran is not a member of either organization.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Tony Burchyns&#32;(2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://media.www.thespartandaily.com/media/storage/paper852/news/2003/01/31/CampusNews/Warrant.Issued.For.Suspect.In.Fraternity.Fight-1496236.shtml">
Warrant issued for suspect in fraternity fight</weblink>"&#32;(in English).&#32;  Spartan Daily - San Jose State University.&#32;Retrieved on September 10, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Chronicle Staff Writers&#32;(2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2003/01/26/MN231151.DTL">
Fraternity feud's unlikely victim</weblink>"&#32;(in English).&#32;  SFGate.com.&#32;Retrieved on September 10, 2007.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Websites </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pialphaphi.com">
Official Online Home of Pi Alpha Phi</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chssc.org">
Chinese Historical Society of Southern California</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/4258255.xml">
Stanford Jade Ribbon Campaign</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
News Articles</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asian-nation.org/headlines/2005/09/new-politics-of-race-at-berkeley/">
Asian-Nation, September 29, 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wildcat.arizona.edu/media/storage/paper997/news/2006/02/17/News/New-Gay.Asian.Fraternities.Secure.Campus.Recognition-1618507.shtml?norewrite200605300939&amp;sourcedomain=wildcat.arizona.edu">
Arizona Daily Wildcat, February 17, 2006</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</fraternity>
</society>
</organization>
</article>
