<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:19:21[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<look  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100877127">
<fundamental_quantity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113575869">
<time_period  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="115113229">
<time  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="115122231">
<observation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100879759">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<sensory_activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100876737">
<day  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="115123115">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<sensing  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100876874">
<header>
<title>International Day for Tolerance</title>
<id>2017915</id>
<revision>
<id>205386651</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-13T19:14:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Vina-iwbot</username>
<id>727408</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Recurring events established in 1995</category>
<category>United Nations days</category>
<category>November observances</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>International Day for Tolerance</b> is an annual observance declared by <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/31901.xml">
UNESCO</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/34658.xml">
1995</link> to generate public awareness of the dangers of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/44379.xml">
intolerance</link>. It is observed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/21726.xml">
November 16</link>.
<sec>
<st>
Context</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Preamble</st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

Bearing in mind that the <treaty wordnetid="106773434" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/88805.xml">
United Nations Charter</link></treaty>
 states: 'We, the peoples of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/31769.xml">
United Nations</link> determined to save succeeding generations from the scourge of war, ... to reaffirm faith in fundamental human rights, in the dignity and worth of the human person, ... and for these ends to practise tolerance and live together in peace with one another as good neighbours',
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Recalling that the Preamble to the Constitution of UNESCO, adopted on 16 November 1945, states that 'peace, if it is not to fail, must be founded on the intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind',
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Recalling also that the Universal Declaration of Human Rights affirms that 'Everyone has the right to freedom of thought, conscience and religion' (Article 18), 'of opinion and expression' (Article 19), and that education 'should promote understanding, tolerance and friendship among all nations, racial or religious groups' (Article 26),
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Noting relevant international instruments including: 
</indent>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/98677.xml">
International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/1365652.xml">
International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<meeting wordnetid="108307589" confidence="0.8">
<issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<convention wordnetid="108309086" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/1435150.xml">
Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination</link></group>
</convention>
</gathering>
</issue>
</meeting>
</social_group>
,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/143988.xml">
Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<meeting wordnetid="108307589" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<convention wordnetid="108309086" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/46489.xml">
Convention on the Rights of the Child</link></group>
</collection>
</convention>
</gathering>
</meeting>
</social_group>
</law>
,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/1973410.xml">
1951 Convention relating to the Status of Refugees</link> and its 1967 Protocol and regional instruments,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/1435066.xml">
Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/220419.xml">
Convention against Torture and other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link>
Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance Based on Religion or Belief</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link>
Declaration on the Rights of Persons Belonging to National or Ethnic, Religious and Linguistic Minorities</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link>
Declaration on Measures to Eliminate International Terrorism</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/3792788.xml">
Vienna Declaration</link> and Programme of Action of the <link>
World Conference on Human Rights</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link>
Copenhagen Declaration</link> and Programme of Action adopted by the <link>
World Summit for Social Development</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link>
UNESCO Declaration on Race and Racial Prejudice</link>,</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 the <link>
UNESCO Convention and Recommendation against Discrimination in Education</link>, </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

Bearing in mind the objectives of the Third Decade to Combat Racism and Racial Discrimination, the World Decade for Human Rights Education, and the International Decade of the World's Indigenous People,
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Taking into consideration the recommendations of regional conferences organized in the framework of the United Nations Year for Tolerance in accordance with UNESCO General Conference 27 C/Resolution 5.14, as well as the conclusions and recommendations of other conferences and meetings organized by Member States within the programme of the United Nations Year for Tolerance,
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Alarmed by the current rise in acts of intolerance, violence, terrorism, xenophobia, aggressive nationalism, racism, anti-Semitism, exclusion, marginalization and discrimination directed against national, ethnic, religious and linguistic minorities, refugees, migrant workers, immigrants and vulnerable groups within societies, as well as acts of violence and intimidation committed against individuals exercising their freedom of opinion and expression - all of which threaten the consolidation of peace and democracy, both nationally and internationally, and are obstacles to development,
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Emphasizing the responsibilities of Member States to develop and encourage respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms for all, without distinction as to race, gender, language, national origin, religion or disability, and to combat intolerance,
</indent>
Adopt and solemnly proclaim this Declaration of Principles on Tolerance</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

Resolving to take all positive measures necessary to promote tolerance in our societies, because tolerance is not only a cherished principle, but also a necessity for peace and for the economic and social advancement of all peoples,
</indent>

<indent level="1">

We declare the following:
</indent>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Article 2 - State level</st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

legislation, law enforcement and judicial and administrative process. It also requires that economic and social opportunities be made available to each person without a2.1 Tolerance at the State level requires just and impartial ny discrimination. Exclusion and marginalization can lead to frustration, hostility and fanaticism.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

2.2 In order to achieve a more tolerant society, States should ratify existing international human rights conventions, and draft new legislation where necessary to ensure equality of treatment and of opportunity for all groups and individuals in society.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

2.3 It is essential for international harmony that individuals, communities and nations accept and respect the multicultural character of the human family. Without tolerance there can be no peace, and without peace there can be no development or democracy.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

2.4 Intolerance may take the form of marginalization of vulnerable groups and their exclusion from social and political participation, as well as violence and discrimination against them. As confirmed in the Declaration on Race and Racial Prejudice, 'All individuals and groups have the right to be different' (Article 1.2).
</indent>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Article 3 - Social dimensions</st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

3.1 In the modern world, tolerance is more essential than ever before. It is an age marked by the globalization of the economy and by rapidly increasing mobility, communication, integration and interdependence, large-scale migrations and displacement of populations, urbanization and changing social patterns. Since every part of the world is characterized by diversity, escalating intolerance and strife potentially menaces every region. It is not confined to any country, but is a global threat.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

3.2 Tolerance is necessary between individuals and at the family and community levels. Tolerance promotion and the shaping of attitudes of openness, mutual listening and solidarity should take place in schools and universities and through non-formal education, at home and in the workplace. The communication media are in a position to play a constructive role in facilitating free and open dialogue and discussion, disseminating the values of tolerance, and highlighting the dangers of indifference towards the rise in intolerant groups and ideologies.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

3.3 As affirmed by the UNESCO Declaration on Race and Racial Prejudice, measures must be taken to ensure equality in dignity and rights for individuals and groups wherever necessary. In this respect, particular attention should be paid to vulnerable groups which are socially or economically disadvantaged so as to afford them the protection of the laws and social measures in force, in particular with regard to housing, employment and health, to respect the authenticity of their culture and values, and to facilitate their social and occupational advancement and integration, especially through education.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

3.4 Appropriate scientific studies and networking should be undertaken to co-ordinate the international community's response to this global challenge, including analysis by the social sciences of root causes and effective countermeasures, as well as research and monitoring in support of policy-making and standard-setting action by Member States.
</indent>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Article 4 - Education</st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

4.1 Education is the most effective means of preventing intolerance. The first step in tolerance education is to teach people what their shared rights and freedoms are, so that they may be respected, and to promote the will to protect those of others.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

4.2 Education for tolerance should be considered an urgent imperative; that is why it is necessary to promote systematic and rational tolerance teaching methods that will address the cultural, social, economic, political and religious sources of intolerance - major roots of violence and exclusion. Education policies and programmes should contribute to development of understanding, solidarity and tolerance among individuals as well as among ethnic, social, cultural, religious and linguistic groups and nations.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

4.3 Education for tolerance should aim at countering influences that lead to fear and exclusion of others, and should help young people to develop capacities for independent judgement, critical thinking and ethical reasoning.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

4.4 We pledge to support and implement programmes of social science research and education for tolerance, human rights and non-violence. This means devoting special attention to improving teacher training, curricula, the content of textbooks and lessons, and other educational materials including new educational technologies, with a view to educating caring and responsible citizens open to other cultures, able to appreciate the value of freedom, respectful of human dignity and differences, and able to prevent conflicts or resolve them by non-violent means.
</indent>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Article 5 - Commitment to action</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

We commit ourselves to promoting tolerance and non-violence through programmes and institutions in the fields of education, science, culture and communication.
</indent>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Article 6 - International Day for Tolerance</st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

In order to generate public awareness, emphasize the dangers of intolerance and react with renewed commitment and action in support of tolerance promotion and education, we solemnly proclaim 16 November the annual International Day for Tolerance
</indent>

</p>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/3556702.xml">
Tolerance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/31901.xml">
UNESCO</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<award wordnetid="106696483" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/10199333.xml">
UNESCO-Madanjeet Singh Prize</link></signal>
</award>
</symbol>
 for the promotion of tolerance and non-violence. The winner of this bi-annual award established in 1996 is announced on the International Day for Tolerance.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unesco.org/tolerance/declaeng.htm">
Declaration of the Principles of Tolerance</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</sensing>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</day>
</sensory_activity>
</event>
</observation>
</time>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
</look>
</article>
