<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:14:29[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Homebuilt computer</title>
<id>2030760</id>
<revision>
<id>234913008</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-29T02:38:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Robotje</username>
<id>100235</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Personal computers</category>
<category>DIY culture</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="clear: right; margin-bottom: .5em; float: right; padding: .5em 0 .8em 1.4em; background: none; width: auto;" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>
__TOC__</col>
</row>
</table>
A <b>Homebuilt Computer</b> system is a computer assembled from available components, rather than purchased as a complete system from a computer system supplier.
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

Computers have been built at home for a long time, starting with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/32798.xml">
Victorian era</link> pioneer <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/5698.xml">
Charles Babbage</link></scientist>
 in the 1820s. A century later, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/16810.xml">
Konrad Zuse</link></scientist>
</person>
 built his own machine when <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/2047439.xml">
electromechanical</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/26590.xml">
relay</link> technology was widely available. The hobby really took off with the early development of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/19553.xml">
microprocessors</link>, and since then many enthusiasts have constructed their own computers. </p>
<p>

Early examples from the United Kingdom include the <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<digital_computer wordnetid="103196324" confidence="0.8">
<personal_computer wordnetid="103918480" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../552/2419552.xml">
Newbear 77/68</link></personal_computer>
</digital_computer>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 and <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<digital_computer wordnetid="103196324" confidence="0.8">
<personal_computer wordnetid="103918480" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/95668.xml">
Nascom</link></personal_computer>
</digital_computer>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 designs from the late 70's and early 80's. Some were made from kits of components, or simply distributed as board designs. The development of standardized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/152036.xml">
S-100 bus</link> components made the process easier, but the development of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/13950.xml">
home computer</link>s, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/15032.xml">
IBM PC</link> (and its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/49803.xml">
derivatives</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/874123.xml">
clones</link>), and the industry of specialized component suppliers that grew up around this market in the mid 80's have made building computers much easier.  Computer building is no longer limited to specialists.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Development as a hobby </st>

<p>

Assembling custom PCs from components is now a well established adjunct to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/1336512.xml">
PC gaming</link>, and has evolved into a minor art form with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/308765.xml">
case modification</link>s such as illuminated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/4045710.xml">
case fan</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/169146.xml">
cold cathode</link> lamps, windowed and transparent cases, customized cabling, and stylized paint jobs. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/175973.xml">
Overclocking</link> enthusiasts take efficiency further, building systems that seek a higher performance than the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/5218.xml">
CPU</link> manufacturers' rating by modifying core CPU voltages and clock settings, and using high-efficiency cooling strategies ranging from oversized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/344123.xml">
heat sink</link>s to advanced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/531184.xml">
water cooling</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/46238.xml">
refrigeration</link> systems.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Standardization </st>

<p>

The same availability of standardised PC components that makes computer building so easy and widespread has led to the development of small scale custom PC assembly; with so called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/2288348.xml">
"white box"</link> PCs and commercial "build to order" services ranging in size from small local supply operations to large International operations.</p>
<p>

Practically all PCs except <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/198584.xml">
laptop</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/250851.xml">
portable</link> systems are largely built from interchangeable standard parts because PC manufacturers enjoy an advantage of scale, and the system assemblers derive a commercial advantage from multiple sources of interchangeable parts. Even in the more specialised laptop market, a considerable degree of standardisation exists "under the covers". Unfortunately many "big name" systems and especially laptops also contain components that vary widely from the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/43594.xml">
de facto</link>" standards that generic PC systems follow, which are only obtainable from the system assemblers concerned. You can visit http://www.computer-anatomy.com to find out more.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Types </st>

<p>

Since it is possible to adapt, expand, update, or otherwise customise any PC within the limits of the PCs conformance to standard component interfaces, homebuilt PC systems form a continuum from standard system suppliers offerings adapted with an alternative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/113624.xml">
video card</link> or uprated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard disk</link>, up to systems built from scratch from components, owing nothing to any specific system assembler.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Kits and barebones systems </st>

<p>

Computer kits include all of the hardware (and sometimes the operating system software, as well) needed to build a complete computer. Because the components are pre-selected by the vendor, the planning and design stages of the computer-building project are eliminated, and the builder's experience will consist solely of assembling the computer and installing the operating system. In theory, the kit supplier will have tested the components to assure that they are compatible and free of conflicts.</p>
<p>

A "<link>
barebones computer</link>" is a variation on the kit concept. A barebones system typically consists of a computer case with a power supply, motherboard, processor, and processor cooler. A wide variety of other combinations are also possible: some barebones systems come with just the case and the motherboard, while other systems are virtually complete. In either case, the purchaser will need to obtain and install whatever parts are not included in the barebones kit (typically the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard drive</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/25847.xml">
Random Access Memory</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/327929.xml">
peripheral devices</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>).</p>
<p>

Like mass-produced computers, barebones systems and computer kits are often targeted to particular types of users, and even different age groups. Because many home computer builders are gamers, for example, and because gamers are often young people, barebones computers marketed as "gaming systems" often include features such as neon lights and brightly-colored cases, as well as features more directly related to performance such as a fast processor, a generous amount of Random Access Memory, and a powerful video card. Other kits and barebones systems may be specifically marketed to users of an "alternative" operating system like <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
, with components selected on the basis of their compatibility and performance with that operating system.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Scavenged and "cannibalized" systems </st>

<p>

Many amateur-built computers are built primarily from used or "spare" parts. There are variety of possible reasons why a person would choose to build a "new" computer from old parts. For example, it's sometimes necessary to build a computer that will run an obsolete operating system or proprietary software for which updates are no longer available, and which will not run properly on a current platform. Economic reasons may also require an individual to build a new computer from used parts, especially among youth or in developing countries where the cost of new equipment places it out of reach of average people.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Advantages and disadvantages </st>
<p>

Building one's own computer arguably affords tangible benefits compared to purchasing a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/63137.xml">
mass-produced</link> model, such as:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Being able to choose exactly which components are to be used.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Customizing the machine to the user's exact needs and preferences.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Avoiding the advertising links, trial software, and other commission-driven additions and modifications that increasingly are made to mass-market computers prior to their being shipped.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ensure that one has all the individual driver and OS discs - many manufactured computers only come with one or two discs. one of which is the OS, and another is a "restore to factory condition" disc, which included all the "Bloatware"  mentioned above. This in inhibits latter modifiablility (mentioned below).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Being able to make modifications to the original build at a later date with little hassle.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 May be less expensive than a mass-manufactured PC, especially if extensively customization is desired.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Enjoyment, personal satisfaction, and educational experience.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

For the general public, however, the lack of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/638229.xml">
technical support</link> and warranty protection (other than what may or may not be provided by the individual component and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> manufacturers) may be a significant disadvantage.  However, one must remember that a person who is capable of designing and building a PC will most likely have sufficient knowledge and technical know-how to maintain their system, and will require little "technical support" from manufacturers.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Homebuilt computers and alternative operating systems </st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Case_mod.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Side view of a typical home built PC. The motherboard and internal components are on display.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Because almost all mass-manufactured PCs ship with some version of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> pre-installed, individuals who wish to use operating systems other than Windows (for example, <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/1223807.xml">
BSD</link>) often choose to build their own computers. Their reason for doing so is not always related to saving money on an operating system.</p>
<p>

Because Microsoft Windows is the <it>de facto</it> standard for PCs, hardware <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/9101.xml">
device drivers</link> can readily be found that will enable virtually any component designed for the PC architecture to function on a Windows platform. However, the same isn't true for alternative operating systems like Linux and BSD, so these system users have to be careful to avoid hardware that is incompatible with their choice of operating system. Even among hardware devices that technically will "work" with these alternative operating systems, some will work better than others. Therefore, many users of non-Microsoft operating systems choose to build their own computers from components known to work particularly well with their preferred platforms.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dmoz.org/Computers/Hardware/FAQs,_Help,_and_Tutorials/Build_Your_Own_PC/">
Build Your Own PC</weblink> at the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<subsidiary_company wordnetid="108003935" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18949501.xml">
Open Directory Project</link></institution>
</subsidiary_company>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</property>
</undertaking>
</company>
</event>
</possession>
</work>
</entry>
</list>
</p>











</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
