<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:20:19[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Strategic early warning system</title>
<id>2036722</id>
<revision>
<id>243965112</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T19:26:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Sethbot</username>
<id>68471</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Business terms</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing context</category>
<category>Wikipedia introduction cleanup</category>
<category>Strategic management</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The introduction to this article provides <b>insufficient context</b> for those unfamiliar with the subject.
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Strategic_early_warning_system&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink> with a .</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

The aim of an <b>Strategic Early Warning System</b> (SEWS) is to assist organizations in dealing with discontinuities or strategic “surprises”. By detecting “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/275871.xml">
weak signals</link>” (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<economist wordnetid="110043643" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/2496640.xml">
Igor Ansoff</link></scholar>
</mathematician>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</economist>
</physical_entity>
, 1975), which can be perceived as important discontinuities in an organizational environment, SEWS allows organizations to react <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/29607.xml">
strategically</link> ahead of time. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Underlying theory</st>

<p>

The underlying assumption of SEWS is that discontinuities do not emerge without warning. These warning signs can be described as “weak signals”. The concept of “weak signals” (Ansoff, 1975) aims at early detection of those signals which could lead to strategic surprises and to an event which has the potential to jeopardise an organization’s strategy. Furthermore, the concept of a SEWS is intended to constitute an important part of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/239450.xml">
strategic management</link> system, operating real-time in an organization, and assisting in identifying the new, which emerges as “weak signals”. </p>
<p>

Detecting “weak signals” is achieved by scanning the organizational environment. The concept of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/252668.xml">
environmental scanning</link> (Aguilar,1967) describes a process whereby the environment in which an organization operates is systematically scanned for relevant information. The purpose is to identify early signals of possible environmental change and to detect environmental change already underway.</p>
<p>

The need for a formal strategic early warning process in organizations is based in large part on the existence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/17099795.xml">
blindspots</link> at their top, which prevents leaders and executives from identifying weak signals of change (Gilad, 1998). Any formal SEWS process must incorporate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/17099795.xml">
blindspots analysis</link> as part of its cycle. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Phases</st>
<p>

The ideal SEWS process has three phases. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Phase 1</b> is characterised by the information gathering of “weak signals”, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/1360154.xml">
trends</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/381055.xml">
issues</link>. The scanning itself relies primarily on examining various media sources, the technique of content analysis (Nasbitt, 1982). </entry>
</list>

The scanning activity is complemented by monitoring trends and issues that have already drawn attention. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Phase 2</b> is one of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/18507525.xml">
diagnosis</link>, which is characterized by three steps:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 In-depth analysis of the trend or issue, examining the core and the various contexts of this phenomenon. The aim is to gain an impression of the possible potential development of an issue or trend. Stakeholder theory may be used to understand actors in a specific industry (Comai and Tena, 2006) </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The second step has several objectives. </entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

The attempt should be made to think creatively about how the particular trend or issue could evolve. </entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

The nature of the contexts needs to be examined in order to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link> several trends or issues, thus providing an understanding of the mutual influences on and of trends and issues. </entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

It is important, due to the limited resources in any organization, to identify and select those trends and issues that are particularly relevant. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Phase 3</b> describes the formulation of an appropriate strategy to react to the trends and issues which have been identified and labelled as relevant.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Aguilar, F. J. (1967), Scanning the Business Environment, The Macmillian Company, New York.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ansoff, H. I. (1975), “Managing Strategic Surprise by Response to Weak Signals”, California Management Review, vol. XVIII no. 2, pp. 21-33.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ansoff, H. I. (1980), “Strategic Issue Management”, Strategic Management Journal, vol. 1, pp. 131-148.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/Mapping-Anticipating-Competitive-Landscape-Alessandro/dp/8493517879/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1223493913&amp;sr=8-1">
Comai, A. and Tena, J. (2006), Mapping and Anticipating the Competitive Landscape. Emecom Ediciones, Barcelona.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nasbitt, J. (1982), Megatrends, Warner Books, New York.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gilad, Ben (1998). Business Blindspots. UK: Infonortics.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0814407862">
Gilad, B. (2003), Early Warning: Early Warning: Using Competitive Intelligence to Anticipate Market Shifts, Control Risk, and Create Powerful Strategies", AMACOM</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/9042276.xml">
Society of Competitive Intelligence Professionals</link></p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
