<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:29:38[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<model  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110324560">
<assistant  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109815790">
<worker  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109632518">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<network  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108434259">
<header>
<title>Bayesian network</title>
<id>203996</id>
<revision>
<id>243244225</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T19:38:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Bayesian networks</category>
<category>Graph models (statistics)</category>
<category>Statistical models</category>
<category>Networks</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it has <b>insufficient  .</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations .</col>
</row>
</table>


A <b>Bayesian network</b> (or a <b>belief network</b>) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/447298.xml">
probabilistic graphical model</link> that represents a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/32818.xml">
variable</link>s and their probabilistic independencies. For example, a Bayesian network could represent the probabilistic relationships between diseases and symptoms. Given symptoms, the network can be used to compute the probabilities of the presence of various diseases. <p>

Formally, Bayesian networks are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/204002.xml">
directed acyclic graph</link>s whose nodes represent variables, and whose arcs encode conditional independencies between the variables.  Nodes can represent any kind of variable, be it a measured parameter, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/2649330.xml">
latent variable</link> or a hypothesis. They are not restricted to representing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/25685.xml">
random variable</link>s, which represents another "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/38526.xml">
Bayesian</link>" aspect of a Bayesian network.  Efficient algorithms exist that perform <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/317465.xml">
inference</link> and learning in Bayesian networks. Bayesian networks that model sequences of variables (such as for example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/29468.xml">
speech signals</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/1107659.xml">
protein sequences</link>) are called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/1242713.xml">
dynamic Bayesian network</link>s.  Generalizations of Bayesian networks that can represent and solve decision problems under uncertainty are called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/1194259.xml">
influence diagrams</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Definitions and concepts</st>

<p>

If there is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/325806.xml">
arc</link> from node <it>A</it> to another node  <it>B</it>, <it>A</it> is called a <it>parent</it> of <it>B</it>, and <it>B</it> is a <it>child</it> of <it>A</it>. The set of parent nodes of a node <it>X</it>i is denoted by parents(<it>X</it>i). A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/204002.xml">
directed acyclic graph</link> is a Bayesian Network relative to a set of variables if the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/879637.xml">
joint distribution</link> of the node values can be written as the product of the local distributions of each node and its parents:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\mathrm P(X_1, \ldots, X_n) = \prod_{i=1}^n \mathrm P(X_i \mid \operatorname{parents}(X_i)).\,</math>
</indent>

If node <math>X_i</math> has no parents, its local probability distribution is said to be <it>unconditional</it>, otherwise it is <it>conditional</it>. If the value of a node is <it>observed</it>, then the node is said to be an <it>evidence</it> node. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Independencies and <it>d</it>-separation</st>
<p>

The graph encodes independencies between variables. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/801135.xml">
Conditional independence</link> can be determined by the graphical property of <b> <it>d</it></b><b>-separation</b>. If two sets of nodes <it>X</it> and <it>Y</it> are <it>d</it>-separated in the graph by a third set <it>Z</it>, then the corresponding variable sets <it>X</it> and <it>Y</it> are independent given the variables in <it>Z</it>.  The minimal set of nodes which <it>d</it>-separates node <it>X</it> from all other nodes is given by <it>X</it> 's <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/1169984.xml">
Markov blanket</link></network>
</group>
</system>
.  </p>
<p>

A path p (allowing paths that are not directed) is said to be d-separated (or blocked) by a set of nodes Z if and only if one of the following holds:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 p contains a <it>chain</it> i → m → j such that the middle node m is in Z,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 p contains a <it>fork</it> i ← m → j such that the middle node m is in Z,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 p contains an <it>inverted fork</it> (or <it>collider</it>) i → m ← j such that the middle node m is not in Z and no descendant of m is in Z.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A set Z is said to d-separate x from y in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/204002.xml">
directed acyclic graph</link> G if all paths from x to y in G are d-separated by Z.  The 'd' in d-separation stands for 'directional', since the behavior of a three node link on a path depends on the direction of the arrows in the link. </p>
<p>

Two nodes are (unconditionally) independent if the two nodes have no common ancestors (since this is equivalent to saying all paths between these nodes contain at least one <it>collider</it>, which is equivalent to saying that the two nodes are d-separated by the empty set).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Causal Bayesian networks</st>
<p>

A Bayesian network is a carrier of the conditional independencies of a set of variables, not of their causal connections. However, causal relations can be modelled by the closely related <link>
causal Bayesian network</link>. The additional semantics of the causal Bayesian networks specify that if a node <it>X</it> is actively caused to be in a given state <it>x</it> (an operation written as <it>do(x)</it>), then the probability density function changes to the one of the network obtained by cutting the links from <it>X</it>'s parents to <it>X</it>, and setting <it>X</it> to the caused value <it>x</it>. Using these semantics, one can predict the impact of external interventions from data obtained prior to intervention.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Example </st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="400px" src="SimpleBayesNet.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A simple Bayesian network.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Suppose that there are two events which could cause grass to be wet: either the sprinkler is on or it's raining.  Also, suppose that the rain has a direct effect on the use of the sprinkler (namely that when it rains, the sprinkler is usually not turned on.)  Then the situation can be modelled with the adjacent Bayesian network.  All three variables have two possible values T (for true) and F (for false).</p>
<p>

The joint probability function is:</p>
<p>

<math>\mathrm P(G,S,R)=\mathrm P(G|S,R)\mathrm P(S|R)\mathrm P(R)</math></p>
<p>

where the names of the variables have been abbreviated to <it>G = Grass wet</it>, <it>S = Sprinkler</it>, and <it>R = Rain</it>.</p>
<p>

The model can answer questions like "What is the probability that it is raining, given the grass is wet?" by using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/5791.xml">
conditional probability</link> formula and summing over all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/979528.xml">
nuisance variable</link>s:
<indent level="1">

</indent>
<math> \mathrm P(\mathit{R}=T \mid \mathit{G}=T) 
=\frac{\mathrm P(\mathit{G}=T,\mathit{R}=T)}{\mathrm P(\mathit{G}=T)} 
=\frac{\sum_{\mathit{S} \in \{T, F\}}\mathrm P(\mathit{G}=T,\mathit{S},\mathit{R}=T)}{\sum_{\mathit{S}, \mathit{R} \in \{T, F\}} \mathrm P(\mathit{G}=T,\mathit{S},\mathit{R})}
</math>
<indent level="1">

<math> = \frac{(0.99 \times 0.01 \times 0.2 = 0.00198_{TTT}) + (0.8 \times 0.99 \times 0.2 = 0.1584_{TFT})}{0.00198_{TTT} + 0.288_{TTF} + 0.1584_{TFT} + 0_{TFF}} \approx 35.77 %.</math>
</indent>

As in the example numerator is pointed out explicitly, the joint probability function is used to calculate each iteration of the summation function. In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/113039.xml">
numerator</link> marginalizing over <math>\mathit{S}</math> and in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/1704824.xml">
denominator</link> marginalizing over <math>\mathit{S}</math> and <math>\mathit{R}</math>.</p>
<p>

If, on the other hand, we wish to answer an interventional question: "What is the likelihood that it would rain, given that we wet the grass?" the answer would be governed by the post-intervention joint distribution function <math>\mathrm P(S,R|do(G=T)) = P(S|R) P(R)</math> obtained by removing the factor <math>\mathrm P(G|S,R)</math> from the pre-intervention distribution. As expected, the likelihood of rain is unaffected by the action: <math>\mathrm P(R|do(G=T)) = P(R)</math>.</p>
<p>

Using a Bayesian network can save considerable amounts of memory, if the dependencies in the joint distribution are sparse. For example, a naive way of storing the conditional probabilities of 10 two-valued variables as a table requires storage space for <math>2^{10} = 1024</math> values. If the local distributions of no variable depends on more than 3 parent variables, the Bayesian network representation only needs to store at most <math>10*2^3 = 80</math> values.</p>
<p>

One advantage of Bayesian networks is that it is intuitively easier for a human to understand (a sparse set of) direct dependencies and local distributions than complete joint distribution.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Inference </st>

<p>

Because a Bayesian network is a complete model for the variables and their relationships, it can be used to answer probabilistic queries about them. For example, the network can be used to find out updated knowledge of the state of a subset of variables when other variables (the <it>evidence</it> variables) are observed. This process of computing the <it>posterior</it> distribution of variables given evidence is called probabilistic inference. The posterior gives a universal <link>
sufficient statistic</link> for detection applications, when one wants to choose values for the variable subset which minimize some expected loss function, for instance the probability of decision error.  A Bayesian network can thus be considered a mechanism for automatically applying <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<theorem wordnetid="106752293" confidence="0.8">
<proposition wordnetid="106750804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/49569.xml">
Bayes' theorem</link></proposition>
</theorem>
</message>
</statement>
 to complex problems.</p>
<p>

The most common exact inference methods are <link>
variable elimination</link>, which eliminates (by integration or summation) the non-observed non-query variables one by one by distributing the sum over the product; <link>
clique tree propagation</link>, which caches the computation so that many variables can be queried at one time and new evidence can be propagated quickly; and <link>
recursive conditioning</link>, which allows for a space-time tradeoff and matches the efficiency of variable elimination when enough space is used.  All of these methods have complexity that is exponential in the network's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/159023.xml">
treewidth</link>. The most common approximate inference algorithms are stochastic <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/236801.xml">
MCMC</link></method>
</know-how>
 simulation, <link>
mini-bucket elimination</link> which generalizes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/800010.xml">
loopy belief propagation</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../480/1208480.xml">
variational methods</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Parameter learning </st>

<p>

In order to fully specify the Bayesian network and thus fully represent the joint probability distribution, it is necessary to specify for each node <it>X</it> the probability distribution for <it>X</it> conditional upon <it>X</it>'s parents. The distribution of <it>X</it> conditional upon its parents may have any form. It is common to work with discrete or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/21462.xml">
Gaussian distributions</link> since that simplifies calculations. Sometimes only constraints on a distribution are known; one can then use the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/201718.xml">
principle of maximum entropy</link> to determine a single distribution, the one with the greatest <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/15445.xml">
entropy</link> given the constraints.  (Analogously, in the specific context of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/1242713.xml">
dynamic Bayesian network</link>, one commonly specifies the conditional distribution for the hidden state's temporal evolution to maximize the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/11071463.xml">
entropy rate</link> of the implied stochastic process.) </p>
<p>

Often these conditional distributions include parameters which are unknown and must be estimated from data, sometimes using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/140806.xml">
maximum likelihood</link> approach.  Direct maximization of the likelihood (or of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/357672.xml">
posterior probability</link>) is often complex when there are unobserved variables.  A classical approach to this problem is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/470752.xml">
expectation-maximization algorithm</link> which alternates computing expected values of the unobserved variables conditional on observed data, with maximizing the complete likelihood (or posterior) assuming that previously computed expected values are correct.  Under mild regularity conditions this process converges on maximum likelihood (or maximum posterior) values for parameters.  A more fully Bayesian approach to parameters is to treat parameters as additional unobserved variables and to compute a full posterior distribution over all nodes conditional upon observed data, then to integrate out the parameters.  This approach can be expensive and lead to large dimension models, so in practise classical parameter-setting approaches are more common.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Structure learning </st>

<p>

In the simplest case, a Bayesian network is specified by an expert and is then used to perform inference. In other applications the task of defining the network is too complex for humans. In this case the network structure and the parameters of the local distributions must be learned from data.</p>
<p>

Learning the structure of a Bayesian network (i.e., the graph) is a challenge pursued within <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link>. The basic idea goes back to a recovery algorithm
developed by Rebane and Pearl (1987)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> and rests
on the distinction between the three possible types of 
adjacent triplets allowed in a directed acyclic graph (DAG):</p>
<p>

<math>X \rightarrow Y \rightarrow Z</math>
<math>X \leftarrow Y \rightarrow Z</math>
<math>X \rightarrow Y \leftarrow Z</math></p>
<p>

Type 1 and type 2 represent the same dependencies (i.e., <math>X</math> and <math>Z</math> are independent given <math>Y</math>) and are, therefore, indistinguishable. Type 3, however, can be uniquely identified, since <math>X</math> and <math>Z</math> are marginally independent and all other pairs are dependent. Thus, while the <it>skeletons</it> (the graphs stripped of arrows) of these three triplets are identical, the directionality of the arrows is partially identifiable. The same distinction applies when <math>X</math> and <math>Z</math> have common parents, except that one must first condition on those parents. Algorithms have been developed to systematically determine the skeleton of the underlying graph and, then, orient all arrows whose directionality is dictated by the conditional independencies observed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

An alternative method of structural learning uses optimization based search. It requires a <link>
scoring function</link> and a <link>
search strategy</link>. A common scoring function is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/357672.xml">
posterior probability</link> of the structure given the training data. The time requirement of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/103127.xml">
exhaustive search</link> returning back a structure that maximizes the score is <link>
superexponential</link> in the number of variables. A local search strategy makes incremental changes aimed at improving the score of the structure. A global search algorithm like <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/236801.xml">
Markov chain Monte Carlo</link></method>
</know-how>
 can avoid getting trapped in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/298420.xml">
local minima</link>. Friedman et al. talk about using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/427282.xml">
mutual information</link> between variables and finding a structure that maximizes this. They do this by restricting the parent candidate set to <it>k</it> nodes and exhaustively searching therein.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Applications </st>
<p>

Bayesian networks are used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/20590.xml">
modelling</link> knowledge in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/356382.xml">
gene regulatory network</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/969126.xml">
protein structure</link>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medicine</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/1331441.xml">
document classification</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
information retrieval</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/76332.xml">
image processing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/7176679.xml">
data fusion</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/469578.xml">
decision support system</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/9251.xml">
engineering</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
law</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

The term "Bayesian networks" was coined by Pearl (1985) to emphasize three aspects:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

The often subjective nature of the input information.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

The reliance on Bayes's conditioning as the basis for updating information.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

The distinction between causal and evidential modes of reasoning, which underscores <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/149117.xml">
Thomas Bayes</link></scientist>
</person>
's posthumously published paper of 1763.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Informal variants of such networks were first used by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/51481.xml">
legal scholar</link> <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<dean wordnetid="109996784" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<academic_administrator wordnetid="109758885" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/3402619.xml">
John Henry Wigmore</link></scholar>
</head>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</academic_administrator>
</alumnus>
</leader>
</administrator>
</dean>
</communicator>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/7723785.xml">
Wigmore chart</link>s, to analyse <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../812/3276812.xml">
trial</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/2001231.xml">
evidence</link> in 1913.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>:66-76  Another variant, called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/590893.xml">
path diagrams</link>, was developed by the geneticist <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<geneticist wordnetid="110126424" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/1700593.xml">
Sewall Wright</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</geneticist>
</biologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> and used in social and behavioral sciences (mostly with linear parametric models).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/49571.xml">
Bayesian inference</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<theorem wordnetid="106752293" confidence="0.8">
<proposition wordnetid="106750804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/49569.xml">
Bayes' theorem</link></proposition>
</theorem>
</message>
</statement>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/49571.xml">
Bayesian statistics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/12680566.xml">
Chow-Liu tree</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/447298.xml">
Graphical model</link></network>
</group>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</system>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/1194259.xml">
Influence diagram</link></network>
</group>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
Machine learning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/1731488.xml">
Polytree</link></network>
</group>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/11228012.xml">
Variable-order Bayesian network</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/2007748.xml">
Structural equation modeling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/213446.xml">
World view</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Footnotes </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Rebane, G. and Pearl, J., "The Recovery of Causal Poly-trees from Statistical Data," <it>Proceedings, 3rd Workshop on Uncertainty in AI,</it> (Seattle, WA) pp. 222-228,1987</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite id="Reference-Pearl-2000" style="font-style:normal" class="book"><person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/699964.xml">
Pearl, Judea</link></scientist>
</person>
&#32;(2000). Causality:  Models, Reasoning, and Inference.&#32;<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/73199.xml">
Cambridge University Press</link></company>
. ISBN 0-521-77362-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
P. Spirtes and C. Glymour, "An algorithm for fast recovery of sparse causal graphs", <it>Social Science Computer Review,</it> Vol. 9, pp. 62-72, 1991.</entry>
<entry id="4">
P. Spirtes, C. Glymour, and R. Scheines, <it>Causation, Prediction, and Search,</it> New York: Springer-Verlag, 1993</entry>
<entry id="5">
T. Verma and J. Pearl, "Equivalence and Synthesis of Causal Models," <it>Proceedings of the Sixth Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence,</it> (July, Cambridge, MA), pp. 220-227, 1990. Reprinted in P. Bonissone, M. Henrion, L. N. Kanal and J. F. Lemmer (editors), <it>Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence 6,</it> Amsterdam: Elsevier Science Publishers, B.V., pp. 225-268, 1991</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Luis M. de Campos, Juan M. Fernández-Luna and Juan F. Huete&#32;(2004).&#32;"Bayesian networks and information retrieval: an introduction to the special issue". <it>Information Processing &amp; Management</it>&#32;<b>40</b>: 727-733.&#32;Elsevier. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.ipm.2004.03.001">
10.1016/j.ipm.2004.03.001</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">G. A. Davis&#32;(2003).&#32;"Bayesian reconstruction of traffic accidents". <it>Law, Probability and Risk</it>&#32;<b>2</b>: 69–89. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Flpr%2F2.2.69">
10.1093/lpr/2.2.69</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">J. B. Kadane and D. A. Schum&#32;(1996). A Probabilistic Analysis of the Sacco and Vanzetti Evidence.&#32;New York:&#32;Wiley. ISBN 0-471-14182-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">O. Pourret, P. Naim and B. Marcot&#32;(2008). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wiley.com/go/pourret">
Bayesian Networks: A Practical Guide to Applications</weblink>.&#32;Chichester, UK:&#32;Wiley. ISBN 978-0-470-06030-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
Judea Pearl (1985). "Bayesian Networks: A Model of Self-Activated Memory for Evidential Reasoning". In Proceedings of the 7th Conference of the Cognitive Science Society, University of California, Irvine, CA, pp. 329-334, August 15-17.</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Thomas Bayes&#32;(1763).&#32;"An Essay towards solving a Problem in the Doctrine of Chances. By the late Rev. Mr. Bayes, F.R.S., communicated by Mr. Price, in a letter to John Canton, A.M., F.R.S.". <it>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London</it>&#32;<b>53</b>: 370–418. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098%2Frstl.1763.0053">
10.1098/rstl.1763.0053</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
Wright, Sewall (1921) "Correlation and Causation," <it>Journal of Agricultural Research</it>, 20:557-585.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 I. Ben-Gal (2007), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eng.tau.ac.il/~bengal/BN.pdf">
Bayesian Networks</weblink>, in F. Ruggeri, R. Kenett, and F. Faltin (editors), Encyclopedia of Statistics in Quality and Reliability, John Wiley &amp; Sons.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Enrique Castillo, José Manuel Gutiérrez, and Ali S. Hadi (1997). <it>Expert Systems and Probabilistic Network Models</it>. New York: <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/1418949.xml">
Springer-Verlag</link></institution>
</company>
. ISBN 0-387-94858-9</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 N. E. Fenton, and M. Neil, "[https://www.dcs.qmul.ac.uk/~norman/papers/Combining%20evidence%20in%20risk%20analysis%20using%20BNs.pdf Combining evidence in risk analysis using Bayesian Networks]."</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Finn V. Jensen&#32;(2001). Bayesian Networks and Decision Graphs.&#32;<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/1418949.xml">
Springer</link></institution>
</company>
.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 M. Neil, N. E. Fenton, and M. Tailor (2005), "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dcs.qmul.ac.uk/~norman/papers/oprisk.pdf">
Using Bayesian Networks to model Expected and Unexpected Operational Losses</weblink>," Risk Analysis: An International Journal, Vol. 25(4), pp. 963-972.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Judea Pearl (1986), "Fusion, propagation, and structuring in belief networks". <it>Artificial Intelligence</it> <b>29</b>(3):241&ndash;288.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Judea Pearl&#32;(1988). Probabilistic Reasoning in Intelligent Systems.&#32;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/8306989.xml">
Morgan Kaufmann</link>. ISBN 0-934613-73-7.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Judea Pearl and Stuart Russell. Bayesian Networks, in M. A. Arbib (editor), <it>Handbook of Brain Theory and Neural Networks</it>, pp. 157&ndash;160, Cambridge, MA: <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/719601.xml">
MIT Press</link></company>
, 2003, ISBN 0-262-01197-2.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 J. W. Comley and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~dld">
D. L. Dowe</weblink>, "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~dld/David.Dowe.publications.html#ComleyDowe2005">
Minimum Message Length, MDL and Generalised Bayesian Networks with Asymmetric Languages</weblink>", <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=10478&amp;mode=toc">
chapter 11</weblink> (pp<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~dld/Publications/2005/ComleyDowe2005MMLGeneralizedBayesianNetsAsymmetricLanguages_p265.jpg">
265</weblink>&ndash;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~dld/Publications/2005/ComleyDowe2005MMLGeneralizedBayesianNetsAsymmetricLanguages_p294.jpg">
294</weblink>) in P. Grunwald, M. A. Pitt and I. J. Myung (editors), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?sid=4C100C6F-2255-40FF-A2ED-02FC49FEBE7C&amp;ttype=2&amp;tid=10478">
Advances in Minimum Description Length: Theory and Applications</weblink>, Cambridge, MA: <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/719601.xml">
MIT Press</link></company>
, April 2005, ISBN 0-262-07262-9. (This paper puts <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/232602.xml">
decision tree</link>s in internal nodes of Bayes networks using <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~dld/MML.html">
Minimum Message Length</weblink> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/302210.xml">
MML</link>). An earlier version is <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~dld/David.Dowe.publications.html#ComleyDowe2003">
Comley and Dowe (2003)</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~dld/Publications/2003/Comley+Dowe03_HICS2003_GeneralBayesianNetworksAsymmetricLanguages.pdf">
.pdf</weblink>.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Christian Borgelt and Rudolf Kruse. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fuzzy.cs.uni-magdeburg.de/books/gm/">
Graphical Models &ndash; Methods for Data Analysis and Mining</weblink>, Chichester, UK: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/2319469.xml">
Wiley</link>, 2002, ISBN 0-470-84337-3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Kevin B. Korb;&#32;Ann E. Nicholson&#32;(2004). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/bai">
Bayesian Artificial Intelligence</weblink>.&#32;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/834382.xml">
CRC Press</link>. ISBN 1-58488-387-1.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.ust.hk/faculty/lzhang/bio.html">
Nevin Lianwen Zhang</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.ubc.ca/spider/poole/">
David Poole</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.ubc.ca/spider/poole/papers/canai94.pdf">
A simple approach to Bayesian network computations</weblink>, Proceedings of the Tenth Biennial Canadian Artificial Intelligence Conference (AI-94), Banff, AB, May 1994, 171-178. This paper presents variable elimination for belief networks.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/~heckerman/">
David Heckerman</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/research/pubs/view.aspx?msr_tr_id=MSR-TR-95-06">
A Tutorial on Learning with Bayesian Networks</weblink>.  In Learning in Graphical Models, M. Jordan, ed. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 1999.  Also appears as Technical Report MSR-TR-95-06, Microsoft Research, March, 1995.  An earlier version appears as Bayesian Networks for Data Mining, Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery, 1:79-119, 1997.  The paper is about both parameter and structure learning in Bayesian networks.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/research/pubs/view.aspx?msr_tr_id=MSR-TR-95-06">
A tutorial on learning with Bayesian Networks</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.niedermayer.ca/papers/bayesian/bayes.html">
An Introduction to Bayesian Networks and their Contemporary Applications</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dcs.qmw.ac.uk/%7Enorman/BBNs/BBNs.htm">
On-line Tutorial on Bayesian nets and probability</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Software resources: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.ubc.ca/~murphyk/Bayes/bnsoft.html">
Kevin's Murphy's List</weblink>, or <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/bai/book/appendix_b.pdf">
Korb &amp; Nicholson's List</weblink>.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</network>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
