<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:14:14[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<device  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103183080">
<instrument  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103574816">
<header>
<title>Committee for the Abolition of the Third World Debt</title>
<id>2045710</id>
<revision>
<id>82027577</id>
<timestamp>2006-10-17T17:17:44Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bwpach</username>
<id>904939</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Human rights instruments</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Committee for the Abolition of the Third World Debt</b> (CADTM) is an international network of activists who strive to develop and implement radical alternatives that would contribute to the maintenance, and indeed retrieval, of fundamental <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/13831.xml">
human right</link>s all over the world.<p>

Through such actions as the publishing of a magazine and volumes of essays and the organising of seminars, lectures, debates, training sessions, international conferences and campaigns, it hopes to raise people’s awareness of North - South inequalities. With the same aim in view it participates in a number of national and international initiatives and in citizens’ mobilisations. Another of CADTM’s avenues of action is to lobby ministers, members of parliament and other politically active citizens.</p>
<p>

CADTM’s specific focus is the Third World Debt and its aim is to achieve the cancellation of the external public debt in third world countries and subsequently to break the spiral of deeper and deeper indebtedness by setting up models of socially fair and environmentally sustainable development.</p>
<p>

In this perspective CADTM works towards
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the setting up of a development funds that would be democratically controlled by local populations and financed through the cancellation of the public external debt of third world countries;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the retrocession of all ill-acquired goods;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the taxation of speculative financial transactions (similar to the tax proposed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/31175.xml">
Tobin</link>) ;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

an increase in the official aid budget of rich countries to 0.7% of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/12594.xml">
GDP</link>;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the setting up of a world tax on large incomes;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the global conversion of military expenditure into social and cultural expenditure.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

CADTM also demands
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the setting up of a new international economic and structural regime through the suspension of the <central_bank wordnetid="108349916" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/15251.xml">
IMF</link></central_bank>
’s and the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/33309.xml">
WB</link></association>
</institute>
’s adjustment policies;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

a radical reform of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/33873.xml">
WTO</link>’s underlying logic, which at the moment favours rich countries against poor countries;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

a strict control on financial markets;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the suppression of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/18618102.xml">
tax haven</link>s.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Finally CADTM supports <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/11185.xml">
women’s emancipation</link>, peoples’ right to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/29269.xml">
self-determination</link>, radical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/178753.xml">
land reform</link>s and a general reduction of working hours.</p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.cadtm.org/</entry>
</list>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</instrument>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</article>
