<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:15:20[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>ALARP</title>
<id>2050151</id>
<revision>
<id>243280785</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T22:11:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Gaius Cornelius</username>
<id>293907</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Risk</category>
<category>Articles to be expanded since September 2008</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Safety</category>
<category>All articles to be expanded</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>ALARP</b> stands for "<b>as low as reasonably practicable</b>", and is a term often used in the milieu of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/286550.xml">
safety-critical</link> and <link>
high-integrity system</link>s. The <b>ALARP principle</b> is that <it>the residual risk shall be as low as reasonably practicable</it>. It has particular connotations in UK <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/19041444.xml">
 Health and Safety law</link>.<p>

For a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/25617.xml">
risk</link> to be ALARP it must be possible to demonstrate that the cost involved in reducing the risk further would be grossly disproportionate to the benefit gained. The ALARP principle arises from the fact that it would be possible to spend infinite time, effort and money attempting to reduce a risk to zero. It should not be understood as simply a quantitive measure of benefit against detriment. It is more a best common practice of judgement of the balance of risk and societal benefit.   </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Factors </st>

<p>

In this context, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/25617.xml">
risk</link> is the combination of the frequency and the consequence of a specified hazardous event.</p>
<p>

The following factors are likely to be considered when deciding whether or not a risk is <it>tolerable</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Health and safety guidelines</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The specification</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 International standards and laws</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Suggestions from advisory bodies</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Another factor that comes into the ALARP principle, is the cost of assessing the improvement gained in an attempted risk reduction. In extremely complex systems, this can be very high, and could be the limiting factor in practicability of risk reduction.</p>
<p>

Determining that a risk has been reduced to ALARP involves an assessment of the risk to be avoided, of the sacrifice (in money, time and trouble) involved in taking measures to avoid that risk, and a comparison of the two. This is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/374583.xml">
Cost Benefit Analysis</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Origin in UK law </st>

<p>

The term ALARP arises from UK legislation, particularly the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/4389830.xml">
Health and Safety at Work etc. Act 1974</link>, which requires "Provision and maintenance of plant and systems of work that are, so far as is reasonably practicable, safe and without risks to health". The phrase So Far As is Reasonably Practicable (SFARP) in this and similar clauses is interpreted as leading to a requirement that risks must be reduced to a level that is As Low As is Reasonably Practicable (ALARP).</p>
<p>

The key question in determining whether a risk is ALARP is the definition of <b>reasonably practicable</b>. This term has been enshrined in the UK <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/215403.xml">
case law</link> since the case of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/17628388.xml">
Edwards v. National Coal Board</link></it> in 1949. The ruling was that the risk must be insignificant in relation to the sacrifice (in terms of money, time or trouble) required to avert it: risks must be averted unless there is a <b>gross disproportion</b> between the costs and benefits of doing so.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Including gross disproportion means that an ALARP judgement in the UK is not a simple cost benefit analysis, but is weighted to favour carrying out the safety improvement. However, there is no broad consensus on the precise factor that would be appropriate.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Use outside the UK </st>
<p>

Outside the UK the ALARP principle is often not used; instead standards and 'good engineering practice' are adhered to, and legislation tends to require absolute levels of safety.</p>
<p>

Where the ALARP principle is used, it may not have the same implications as in the UK, as "reasonably practicable" may be interpreted according to the local culture, without introducing the concept of gross disproportionality.</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=ALARP&amp;action=edit">
improve this section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Legal Challenge </st>
<p>

A 10 year legal battle in the <supreme_court wordnetid="108336188" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/87187.xml">
European Court of Justice</link></supreme_court>
 resulted in the SFARP principle being upheld on 14 June 2007.</p>
<p>

The <control wordnetid="105196375" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="105196582" confidence="0.8">
<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/9974.xml">
European Commission</link></power>
</authority>
</control>
 had claimed that the SFARP wording in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/4389830.xml">
Health &amp; Safety at Work Act</link> did not fully implement the requirements of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/19506115.xml">
Framework Directive</link>. The Directive gives employers an absolute duty "to ensure the safety and health of workers in every aspect related to the work", whereas the Act qualifies the duty "So Far As is Reasonably Practicable". The court dismissed the action and ordered the Commission to pay the UK's costs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Had the case been upheld, it would have called into question the proportionate approach to safety risk management embodied in the ALARP principle.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Carrot diagrams </st>
<p>

<image width="397px" src="Carrot_Diagram.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

ALARP Carrot Diagram
</caption>
</image>

So called <link>
carrot diagram</link>s are often used to display risks. They are called carrot diagrams, because they have an elongated triangle in the centre, which looks like a carrot, and indicates the high (reducible) risks at the top and the low (insignificant) risks at the bottom. The region in between is sometimes called the <b>ALARP region</b>; however this is misleading because the ALARP principle applies to all regions. A better name is the 'Tolerable Region', because risks in this region can sometimes be tolerated, if they cannot practically be reduced, in return for the benefits provided by the system or installation that causes the risks.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/2952577.xml">
Safety Integrity Level</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://oxcheps.new.ox.ac.uk/new/casebook/cases/Cases%20Chapter%2025/Edwards%20v%20National%20Coal%20Board.doc">
Edwards v. National Coal Board.</weblink> (1949) All ER 743 (CA)</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:62005J0127:EN:HTML">
Judgement of the Court</weblink> on Case C-127/05</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/press/2007/c07007.htm">
Press release</weblink> by the UK <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/361308.xml">
Health and Safety Executive</link></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/risk/theory/alarp.htm">
UK Health and Safety Executive ALARP Guidance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/risk/theory/alarpcheck.htm">
UK Health and Safety Executive ALARP Cost Benefit Analysis</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dstan.mod.uk/data/00/056/01000400.pdf">
UK Defence Standard 00-56 Safety Management Requirements</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
