<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:30:12[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Meta element</title>
<id>20556</id>
<revision>
<id>243674763</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T15:49:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ray1938</username>
<id>8025224</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>HTML</category>
<category>Search engine optimization</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Meta elements</b> are  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/274393.xml">
HTML</link> or XHTML elements used to provide structured <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> about a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/34063.xml">
Web page</link>. Such elements must be placed as tags in the head section of an <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 or <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/18984580.xml">
XHTML</link></format>
 document.  Meta elements can be used to specify page description, keywords and any other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> not provided through the other head elements and attributes. <p>

The meta element has four valid attributes: content, http-equiv, name and scheme. Of these, only content is a required attribute.</p>

<sec>
<st>
An example of the use of the meta element</st>
<p>

In one form, meta elements can specify <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/2701104.xml">
HTTP</link> headers which should be sent before the actual content when the HTML page is served from Web server to client. For example: </p>


<p>

This specifies that the page should be served with an HTTP header called 'Content-Type' that has a value 'text/html'. This is a typical use of the meta element, which specifies the document type so a client (browser or otherwise) knows what content type to render.</p>
<p>

In the general form, a meta element specifies name and associated content attributes describing aspects of the HTML page. For example:</p>


<p>

In this example, the meta element identifies itself as containing the 'keywords' relevant to the document, Wikipedia and encyclopedia.</p>
<p>

Meta tags can be used to indicate the location a business serves:</p>


<p>

In this example, geographical information is given according to zip codes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Meta element used in search engine optimization</st>
<p>

Meta elements provide information about a given webpage, most often to help search engines categorize them correctly. They are inserted into the HTML document, but are often not directly visible to a user visiting the site.</p>
<p>

They have been the focus of a field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/59252.xml">
marketing</link> research known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/187946.xml">
search engine optimization</link> (SEO), where different methods are explored to provide a user's site with a higher ranking on search engines. In the mid to late 1990s, search engines were reliant on meta data to correctly classify a webpage and webmasters quickly learned the commercial significance of having the right meta element, as it frequently led to a high ranking in the search engines — and thus, high traffic to the website.</p>
<p>

As search engine traffic achieved greater significance in online marketing plans, consultants were brought in who were well versed in how search engines perceive a website. These consultants used a variety of techniques (legitimate and otherwise) to improve ranking for their clients.</p>
<p>

Meta elements have significantly less effect on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/4555947.xml">
search engine results page</link>s today than they did in the 1990s and their utility has decreased dramatically as search engine robots have become more sophisticated. This is due in part to the nearly infinite re-occurrence (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/1789102.xml">
keyword stuffing</link>) of meta elements and/or to attempts by unscrupulous website placement consultants to manipulate (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/43651.xml">
spamdexing</link>) or otherwise circumvent search engine ranking <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithms</link>.</p>
<p>

While <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/187946.xml">
search engine optimization</link> can improve search engine ranking, consumers of such services should be careful to employ only reputable providers. Given the extraordinary competition and technological craftsmanship required for top search engine placement, the implication of the term "search engine optimization" has deteriorated over the last decade. Where it once implied bringing a website to the top of a search engine's results page, for the average consumer it now implies a relationship with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/43651.xml">
keyword spamming</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/225779.xml">
optimizing</link> a site's internal search engine for improved performance.   </p>
<p>

Major search engine robots are more likely to quantify such extant factors as the volume of incoming links from related websites, quantity and quality of content, technical precision of source code, spelling, functional v. broken hyperlinks, volume and consistency of searches and/or viewer traffic, time within website, page views, revisits, click-throughs, technical user-features, uniqueness, redundancy, relevance, advertising revenue yield, freshness, geography, language and other intrinsic characteristics.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
The keywords attribute</st>
<p>

The keywords attribute was popularized by <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
s such as <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/1101513.xml">
Infoseek</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/366024.xml">
AltaVista</link></company>
 in 1995, and its popularity quickly grew until it became one of the most commonly used meta elements<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. By late 1997, however, search engine providers realized that information stored in meta elements, especially the keyword attribute, was often unreliable and misleading, and at worst, used to draw users into spam sites. (Unscrupulous webmasters could easily place false keywords into their meta elements in order to draw people to their site.)</p>
<p>

Search engines began dropping support for metadata provided by the meta element in 1998, and by the early 2000s, most search engines had veered completely away from reliance on meta elements. In July 2002 AltaVista, one of the last major search engines to still offer support, finally stopped considering them<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. </p>
<p>

No consensus exists whether or not the keywords attribute has any impact on ranking at any of the major search engines today. It is speculated that it does, if the keywords used in the meta can also be found in the page copy itself. 37 leaders in search engine optimization concluded in April 2007 that the relevance of having your keywords in the meta-attribute keywords is little to none<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The description attribute</st>
<p>

Unlike the keyword attribute, the description attribute is supported by most major search engines, like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo</link> and <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/4325491.xml">
Live Search</link></web_site>
, while <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 will fall back on this tag when information about the page itself is requested (e.g. using the related: query). The description attribute provides a concise explanation of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/34063.xml">
Web page</link>'s content. This allows the webpage authors to give a more meaningful description for listings than might be displayed if the search engine was unable to automatically create its own description based on the page content. The description is often, but not always, displayed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/4555947.xml">
search engine results page</link>s, so it can impact click-through rates. Industry commentators have <it>suggested</it> that major search engines also consider keywords located in the description attribute when ranking pages.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> W3C doesn't specify the size of this description meta tag, but almost all search engines recommend it to be shorter than 200 characters of plain text.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The language attribute</st>
<p>

The language attribute tells search engines what natural language the website is written in (e.g. English, Urdu or French), as opposed to the coding language (e.g. HTML). It is normally a 2 letter abbreviation for the language name. It is of most use when a website is written in multiple languages and can be included on each page to tell search engines in which language a particular page is written. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The robots attribute</st>
<p>

The robots attribute controls whether search engine spiders are allowed to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/7602386.xml">
index</link> a page, or not, and whether they should follow links from a page, or not. The noindex value prevents a page from being indexed, and nofollow prevents links from being <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/33120.xml">
crawled</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
. Other values are available that can influence how a search engine indexes pages, and how those pages appear on the search results. The robots attribute is supported by several major search engines <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>. There are several additional values for the robots meta attribute that are relevant to search engines, such as NOARCHIVE and NOSNIPPET, which are meant to tell search engines what not to do with a Web pages content. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>. Meta tags are not the best option to prevent search engines from indexing content of your website. A more reliable and efficient method is the use of the Robots.txt file (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/101673.xml">
Robots Exclusion Standard</link>).</p>
<p>

NOINDEX tag tells a search engine not to index a specific page. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/3766084.xml">
NOFOLLOW</link> tag tells a search engine not to follow the links on a specific page. NOARCHIVE tag tells a search engine not to store a cached copy of your page. NOSNIPPET tag tells Google not to show a snippet (description) under your a search engine listing, it will also not show a cached link in the search results</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Additional attributes for search engines</st>

<ss3>
<st>
NOODP</st>
<p>

The search engines <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo!</link></company>
 and <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/4325491.xml">
MSN</link></web_site>
 use in some cases the title and abstract of the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<subsidiary_company wordnetid="108003935" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18949501.xml">
Open Directory Project</link></institution>
</subsidiary_company>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</property>
</undertaking>
</company>
</event>
</possession>
</work>
 (ODP) listing of a Web site for the title and/or description (also called snippet or abstract) in the search engine results pages (<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/4555947.xml">
SERPS</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
). To give <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/294834.xml">
webmaster</link>s the option to specify that the ODP content should not be used for listings of their website, Microsoft introduced in May 2006 the new "NOODP" value for the "robots" element of the meta tags <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. Google followed in July 2006<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> and Yahoo! in October 2006<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>.</p>
<p>

The syntax is the same for all search engines who support the tag.</p>
<p>

&amp;lt;META NAME="ROBOTS" CONTENT="NOODP"&amp;gt;</p>
<p>

Webmasters can decide if they want to disallow the use of their ODP listing on a per search engine basis</p>
<p>

Google: &amp;lt;META NAME="GOOGLEBOT" CONTENT="NOODP"&amp;gt;</p>
<p>

Yahoo! &amp;lt;META NAME="Slurp" CONTENT="NOODP"&amp;gt;</p>
<p>

MSN and Live Search: &amp;lt;META NAME="msnbot" CONTENT="NOODP"&amp;gt;</p>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
NOYDIR</st>
<p>

Yahoo! also used next to the ODP listing the content from their own Yahoo! directory but introduced in February 2007 a meta tag that provides webmasters with the option to opt-out of this<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>.</p>
<p>

<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/3359563.xml">
Yahoo! Directory</link></web_site>
 titles and abstracts will not be used in search results for their pages if the NOYDIR tag is being added to a Web page.</p>
<p>

&amp;lt;META NAME="ROBOTS" CONTENT="NOYDIR"&amp;gt;</p>
<p>

&amp;lt;META NAME="Slurp" CONTENT="NOYDIR"&amp;gt;</p>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Robots-NoContent</st>
<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo!</link></company>
 also introduced in May 2007 the attribute value: class="robots-nocontent".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> This is not a meta tag, but an attribute and value, which can be used throughout Web page tags where needed. Content of the page where this attribute is being used will be ignored by the Yahoo! crawler and not included in the search engine's index.</p>
<p>

Examples for the use of the robots-nocontent tag:</p>
<p>

&amp;lt;div class="robots-nocontent"&amp;gt;excluded content&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;</p>
<p>

&amp;lt;span class="robots-nocontent"&amp;gt;excluded content&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;</p>
<p>

&amp;lt;p class="robots-nocontent"&amp;gt;excluded content&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</p>

</ss3>
</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Academic studies</st>
<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 does not use HTML keyword or meta tag elements for indexing. The Director of Research at Google, Monika Henziger, was quoted (in 2002) as saying, "Currently we don't trust metadata" <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>. Other search engines developed techniques to penalize Web sites considered to be "cheating the system". For example, a Web site repeating the same meta keyword several times may have its ranking <it>decreased</it> by a search engine trying to eliminate this practice, though that is unlikely. It is more likely that a search engine will ignore the meta keyword element completely, and most do regardless of how many words used in the element.</p>
<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 does, however, use meta tag elements for displaying site links. The title tags are used to create the link in search results:</p>
<p>

Site name - Page title - Keyword description</p>

<p>

The meta description often appears in <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 search results to describe the link:</p>




</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Redirects</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/1753130.xml">
Meta refresh</link> elements can be used to instruct a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/33173.xml">
Web browser</link> to automatically refresh a webpage after a given time interval. It is also possible to specify an alternative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link> and use this technique in order to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/636686.xml">
redirect</link> the user to a different location. Using a meta refresh in this way and solely by itself rarely achieves the desired result. For Internet Explorer's security settings, under the miscellaneous category, meta refresh can be turned off by the user, thereby disabling its redirect ability entirely.</p>
<p>

Many Web design tutorials also point out that client side redirecting tends to interfere with the normal functioning of a Web browser's "back" button. After being redirected, clicking the back button will cause the user to go back to the redirect page, which redirects them again. Some modern browsers seem to overcome this problem however, including <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/166842.xml">
Safari</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<browser wordnetid="106571301" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/210892.xml">
Mozilla Firefox</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</browser>
</program>
</application>
</software>
 and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/18996620.xml">
Opera</link></software>
.</p>
<p>

It should be noted that auto-redirects via markup (versus server side redirects) are not in compliance with the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/33149.xml">
W3C's</link></company>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/5291317.xml">
Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 1.0</link> (guideline 7.5).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
HTTP message headers</st>
<p>

Meta elements of the form  can be used as alternatives to http headers. For example,  would tell the browser that the page "expires" on June 21 2006 21:05:27 GMT and that it may safely cache the page until then.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Alternative to meta elements</st>
<p>

An alternative to meta elements for enhanced subject access within a website is the use of a back-of-book-style index for the website. See examples at the websites of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aussi.org">
Australian Society of Indexers</weblink> and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asindexing.org">
American Society of Indexers</weblink>.</p>
<p>

In 1994, <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/643872.xml">
ALIWEB</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
, which was likely the first Web search engine, also used an index file to provide the type of information commonly found in meta keywords attributes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/53847.xml">
Resource Description Framework</link></format>
 (RDF)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://w3schools.com/tags/tag_meta.asp">
Meta tag list at W3Schools</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.howrank.com/Meta-Tag-Generator.php">
Valid Meta Tag Generator</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spiderwebtechnologies.com/articles/meta-tags-web.html">
Importance of Meta Tags</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3c-at.de/wordpress/2008/05/14/metatags/">
Meta Tag</weblink> (German)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dtools.net/keyword-generator/">
Keywords Meta Tag Generator</weblink> by dtools</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://meta.dtools.net/">
Online Meta Tags analyzer</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Statistic (June 4,1997), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://vancouver-webpages.com/META/bycount.shtml">
META attributes by count</weblink>, <it>Vancouver Webpages</it>, retrieved June 3, 2007</entry>
<entry id="2">
Danny Sullivan (October 1, 2002), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://searchenginewatch.com/showPage.html?page=2165061">
Death Of A Meta Tag</weblink>, <it>SearchEngineWatch.com</it>, retrieved June 03, 2007</entry>
<entry id="3">
Rand Fishkin (April 2, 2007), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.seomoz.org/article/search-ranking-factors">
Search Engine Ranking Factors V2</weblink>, <it>SEOmoz.org</it>, retrieved June 3, 2007</entry>
<entry id="4">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="109824361" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adviser wordnetid="109774266" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/6240607.xml">
Danny Sullivan</link></adviser>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</authority>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://searchenginewatch.com/showPage.html?page=2167931">
How To Use HTML Meta Tags</weblink>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/2582836.xml">
Search Engine Watch</link>, December 5, 2002</entry>
<entry id="5">
1 Website Designer <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.1websitedesigner.com/Language_Metatags.html">
Using language metatags in websites</weblink> February 19, 2008</entry>
<entry id="6">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="109824361" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adviser wordnetid="109774266" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/10533054.xml">
Vanessa Fox</link></adviser>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</authority>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.com/2007/03/using-robots-meta-tag.html">
Using the robots meta tag</weblink>, Official Google Webmaster Central Blog, 3/05/2007</entry>
<entry id="7">
Danny Sullivan (March 5, 2007),<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://searchengineland.com/070305-204850.php">
Meta Robots Tag 101: Blocking Spiders, Cached Pages &amp; More</weblink>, <it>SearchEngineLand.com</it>, retrieved June 3, 2007</entry>
<entry id="8">
Betsy Aoki (May 22, 2006), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blogs.msdn.com/livesearch/archive/2006/05/22/603917.aspx">
Opting Out of Open Directory Listings for Webmasters</weblink>, <it>Live Search Blog</it>, retrieved June 3, 2007</entry>
<entry id="9">
Vanessa Fox (July 13, 2006), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sitemaps.blogspot.com/2006/07/more-control-over-page-snippets.html">
More control over page snippets</weblink>, <it>Inside Google Sitemaps</it>, retrieved June 3, 2007</entry>
<entry id="10">
Yahoo! Search (October 24, 2006), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ysearchblog.com/archives/000368.html">
Yahoo! Search Weather Update and Support for 'NOODP'</weblink>, <it>Yahoo! Search Blog</it>, retrieved June 3, 2007</entry>
<entry id="11">
Yahoo! Search (February 28, 2007), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ysearchblog.com/archives/000418.html">
Yahoo! Search Support for 'NOYDIR' Meta Tags and Weather Update</weblink>, <it>Yahoo! Search Blog</it>, retrieved June 3, 2007</entry>
<entry id="12">
Yahoo! Search (May 02, 2007), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ysearchblog.com/archives/000444.html">
Introducing Robots-Nocontent for Page Sections</weblink>, <it>Yahoo! Search Blog</it>, retrieved June 3, 2007</entry>
<entry id="13">
Journal of Internet Cataloging, Volume 5(1), 2002</entry>
<entry id="14">
W3C Recommendation (May 5, 1999), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/WAI-WEBCONTENT-19990505/#gl-movement">
Web Content Accessibility Guidelines 1.0 - Guideline 7</weblink>. <it>W3.org</it>, retrieved September 28, 2007</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/187946.xml">
Search engine optimization</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Exclusion standards</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/101673.xml">
Robots exclusion standard</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/20556.xml">
Meta tags</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/3766084.xml">
nofollow</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Related marketing topics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/1618177.xml">
Internet marketing</link>&nbsp;• <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/703758.xml">
Affiliate marketing</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/1101759.xml">
E-mail marketing</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/646645.xml">
Display advertising</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/2475872.xml">
Web analytics</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Search marketing related topics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../074/2111074.xml">
Search engine marketing</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/6559316.xml">
Social media optimization</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/15883470.xml">
Online identity management</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/501170.xml">
Paid inclusion</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1027207.xml">
Pay per click (PPC)</link>&nbsp;• <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/286747.xml">
Google bomb</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Search engine spam</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/43651.xml">
Spamdexing</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/2696619.xml">
Web scraping</link>&nbsp;• <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/3152572.xml">
Scraper site</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/270213.xml">
Link farm</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/14489292.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Free+for+all+linking%22])">
Free for all linking</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Linking</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/7065490.xml">
Off-page optimization</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/14489292.xml">
Methods of website linking</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/1395433.xml">
Link exchange</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/580494.xml">
Backlink</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/2789866.xml">
Landing page</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/11170029.xml">
IP delivery</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/11996827.xml">
Landing page optimization</link>&nbsp;• <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/7059064.xml">
Human search engine</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/1015600.xml">
Stop words</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/14484974.xml">
Poison words</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
