<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:31:08[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Memex</title>
<id>20636</id>
<revision>
<id>241806303</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-29T17:04:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Thijs!bot</username>
<id>1392310</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Classification systems</category>
<category>History of human-computer interaction</category>
<category>History of computing</category>
<category>Multimodal interaction</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For the Software Company, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/19373038.xml">
Memex Technology Limited</link>.<p>

The <b>memex</b> (a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/16823212.xml">
portmanteau</link> of "memory extender") is the name given by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/32767.xml">
Vannevar Bush</link></scientist>
</person>
 to the theoretical proto-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/13460.xml">
hypertext</link> computer system he proposed in his 1945 <it><magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/149743.xml">
The Atlantic Monthly</link></magazine>
</it> article <it><product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/18915928.xml">
As We May Think</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</it>.  The memex has influenced the development of subsequential <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/13460.xml">
hypertext</link> and intellect augmenting computer systems.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Details</st>

<ss1>
<st>
A proto-hypertext system</st>
<p>

In Bush's 1945 paper, he describes a memex as an electromechanical device that an individual could use to read a large self-contained research library, and add or follow associative trails of links and notes created by that individual, or recorded by other researchers.</p>
<p>

The technology used would have been a combination of electromechanical controls and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/2842268.xml">
microfilm</link> cameras and readers, all integrated into a large desk.  Most of the microfilm library would have been contained within the desk, but the user could add or remove microfilm reels at will.  </p>
<p>

The vision of the memex predates, but is credited as the inspiration for the first practical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/13460.xml">
hypertext</link> systems of the 1960's. Bush describes the memex and other visions of <it><product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/18915928.xml">
As We May Think</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</it> as projections of technology known in the 1930's and 1940's - in the spirit of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<novelist wordnetid="110363573" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/15770.xml">
Jules Verne</link></novelist>
</writer>
</person>
 or <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<inventor wordnetid="110214637" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/18598148.xml">
Arthur C. Clarke</link></writer>
</inventor>
</person>
's  1945 proposal to orbit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/11869902.xml">
geosynchronous satellite</link>s for global telecommunication. The memex proposed by Bush would create <it>trails</it> of links connecting sequences of microfilm frames, rather than links in the modern sense where a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/49547.xml">
hyperlink</link> connects a single word, phrase or picture within a document and a local or remote destination.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Associative trails</st>
<p>

An associative trail as conceived by Bush would be a way to create a new <it>linear</it> sequence of microfilm frames across any arbitrary sequence of microfilm frames by creating a chained sequence of links in the way just described, along with personal comments and <it>side trails</it>.  The closest analogy with the modern Web browser would be to create a list of bookmarks pointing to articles relevant to a topic, and then to have some mechanism for automatically scrolling through the articles (for example, use <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 to search for a keyword, obtain a list of matches, and then use "open in new tab" in your browser and visit each tab sequentially). Modern hypertext systems with word and phrase-level linking offer more sophistication in connecting relevant information, but until the rise of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/32851.xml">
wiki</link> and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/222034.xml">
social software</link> models, modern hypertext systems have rarely followed Bush in providing individuals with the ability to create personal trails and share them with colleagues - or publish them widely.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other features</st>
<p>

The memex would have features other than linking. The user could record new information on microfilm, by taking photos from paper or from a touch-sensitive translucent screen. A user could "... insert a comment of his own, either linking it into the main trail or joining it by a side trail to a particular item. ... Thus he builds a trail of his interest through the maze of materials available to him."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> A user could also create a copy of an interesting trail (containing references and personal annotations) and "... pass it to his friend for insertion in his own memex, there to be linked into the more general trail."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> As observers like Tim Oren have pointed out, the memex could be considered to be a microfilm-based precursor to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18457137.xml">
personal computer</link>.  The September 10, 1945 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/187479.xml">
Life magazine</link> article showed the first illustrations of what the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sloan.stanford.edu/MouseSite/Secondary.html">
memex desk</weblink>
could look like, as well as illustrations of a head-mounted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/52648.xml">
camera</link>, which a scientist could wear while doing experiments, and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/44365.xml">
typewriter</link> capable of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/1032254.xml">
voice recognition</link> and of reading text by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/42799.xml">
speech synthesis</link>. Taken together, these memex machines were probably the earliest practical description of what we would call today the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/405363.xml">
Office of the future</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Extending, storing and consulting the record of the species</st>
<p>

Bush's vision for the memex extended far beyond a mechanism which might augment the research of one individual working in isolation. In Bush's vision the ability to connect, annotate and share both published works and personal trails would profoundly change the process by which the "world's record" is created and used:</p>
<p>

Wholly new forms of encyclopedias will appear, ready made with a mesh of associative trails running through them, ready to be dropped into the memex and there amplified. The lawyer has at his touch the associated opinions and decisions of his whole experience, and of the experience of friends and authorities. The patent attorney has on call the millions of issued patents, with familiar trails to every point of his client's interest. The physician, puzzled by a patient's reactions, strikes the trail established in studying an earlier similar case, and runs rapidly through analogous case histories, with side references to the classics for the pertinent anatomy and histology. ... </p>
<p>

The historian, with a vast chronological account of a people, parallels it with a skip trail which stops only on the salient items, and can follow at any time contemporary trails which lead him all over civilization at a particular epoch. There is a new profession of trail blazers, those who find delight in the task of establishing useful trails through the enormous mass of the common record. The inheritance from the master becomes, not only his additions to the world's record, but for his disciples the entire scaffolding by which they were erected. -- <it><product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/18915928.xml">
As We May Think</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</it> </p>
<p>

Bush states that "technical difficulties of all sorts have been ignored," but that, "also ignored are means as yet unknown which may come any day to accelerate technical progress as violently as did the advent of the thermionic tube." Indeed, anyone who stops to consider the performance consequences of trail following - let alone link-directed pointer-chasing - over a microfilm library of near universal scope should quickly come to the conclusion that microfilm is no more appropriate a technology for implementing AWMT's vision than <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<novelist wordnetid="110363573" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/15770.xml">
Jules Verne</link></novelist>
</writer>
</person>
's cannon is an appropriate technology for sending astronauts to the Moon. In both cases the vision may be more significant than the specific technology used to describe it. See <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/3134035.xml">
Michael Buckland</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
's conclusion: "Bush's contributions in this area were twofold: (i) A significant engineering achievement by the team under his leadership in building a truly rapid prototype microfilm selector, and (ii) a speculative article, 'As We May Think,' which, through its skillful writing and the social prestige of its author, has had an immediate and lasting effect in stimulating others." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

In "Memex: Getting Back on the Trail"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>, Tim Oren argues that Bush's original vision expressed in AWMT describes a "... private device into which public encyclopedia's and colleague's trails might be inserted to be joined with the owner's own work." </p>
<p>

However, in Bush's manuscript draft of "Memex II" of 1959 (also published in <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>), Bush says, "Professional societies will no longer print papers..." and states that individuals will either order sets of papers to come on tape - complete with photographs and diagrams - or download 'facsimiles' by telephone. Each society would maintain a 'master memex' containing all papers, references, tables "intimately interconnected by trails, so that one may follow a detailed matter from paper to paper, going back through the classics, recording criticism in the margins."</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Missing features: search and metadata</st>
<p>

The AWMT paper did not describe any automatic search, nor any universal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> scheme such as a standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/18328.xml">
library classification</link> or a hypertext element set like the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/8742.xml">
Dublin core</link></format>
</information>
</message>
.  Instead, when the user made an entry, such as a new or annotated manuscript, typescript or image, he was expected to index and describe it in his personal code book.  By consulting his code book, the user could retrace annotated and generated entries.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>

<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/3134035.xml">
Michael Buckland</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, in an article published in 1992, suggested that the memex was severely flawed because Bush did not thoroughly understand <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/149354.xml">
information science</link> and had a low opinion of indices and classification schemes: "Bush thought that the creation of arbitrary associations between individual records was the basis of memory, so he wanted 'memo(ory-)ex', or 'Memex instead of index'. The result was a personalized, but superficial and inherently self-defeating design."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> </p>
<p>

One must note that Buckland was writing at the very infancy of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
world wide web</link> which was first introduced in 1991 and not widely experienced until 1993.  At introduction, the web was predominantly link based (associational).  Classification and indexing efforts followed, with automatic indexing in the form of search engines quickly gaining prominence over classification efforts, while both remained complementary to links.  Whether Buckland would not have applied this same denigration of Memex equally to the world wide web as it flourished in its early years is unclear.  While it has since become clear that an index (search engine) is the most expedient entre into unfamiliar subject matter, associational links have remained an effective navigational method for obtaining broad or deep coverage of a subject area under study.  In the Internet era, links are typically incorporated during authorship, while indices are almost always mechanical.  Bush's unwillingness to place greater prominence on indices might have stemmed from his inability to visualize a near-term mechanical process for their creation, rather than a failure to recognize their utility once obtained.  </p>
<p>

Buckland also states that Bush's vision should be viewed from the historical perspective of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/2842268.xml">
microfilm</link> technology developed <it>prior</it> to 1945 rather than based on the power and versatility of digital computer technology developed <it>after</it> 1945. Buckland summarizes the very advanced pre-World War II development of microfilm based rapid retrieval devices, specifically the microfilm based workstation proposed by <link>
Leonard Townsend</link> in 1938 and the microfilm and photoelectronic based selector, patented by <link>
Emmanuel Goldberg</link> in 1931. Buckland states: "The literature on documentation in the 1930s was as preoccupied with microfilm technology as it is now with computer technology and for the same reason, each being the most promising information retrieval technology of the time." Buckland notes that Bush directed creation of a photoelectronic microfilm 'rapid selector' at MIT in 1938-1940 using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../454/1055454.xml">
stroboscope</link> technology pioneered by his colleague <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/14466.xml">
Harold Edgerton</link>. Buckland suggests that Bush and his team may not have been aware of Goldberg's earlier work when they built their 1938-1940 prototype, but that IBM researchers and Bush's Eastman Kodak Research Laboratory sponsor certainly were. Buckland concludes: "We speculate that Bush did not independently originate the notion of an electronic microfilm selector, although that was possible. It is not surprising that the same invention sometimes occurs independently and more or less simultaneously when a need is present and the technology becomes ripe."</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Legacy</st>

<p>

This idea directly influenced computer pioneers <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/254150.xml">
J.C.R. Licklider</link> (see his 1960 paper <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/3948917.xml">
Man-Computer Symbiosis</link></it>), <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/8081.xml">
Douglas Engelbart</link></scientist>
</person>
 (see his 1962 report <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/3948917.xml">
Augmenting Human Intellect</link></it>), and also led to <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/31550.xml">
Ted Nelson</link></scientist>
</person>
's groundbreaking work in concepts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/287801.xml">
hypermedia</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/13460.xml">
hypertext</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

<it>As We May Think</it> also predicted many kinds of technology invented after its publication in addition to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/13460.xml">
hypertext</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18457137.xml">
personal computers</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>, the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/29468.xml">
speech recognition</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/248723.xml">
online encyclopedia</link>s such as <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/5043734.xml">
Wikipedia</link></web_site>
: "Wholly new forms of encyclopedias will appear, ready-made with a mesh of associative trails running through them, ready to be dropped into the memex and there amplified."</p>
<p>

Bush's influence is still evident in research laboratories of today in both <expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<interior_designer wordnetid="110210648" confidence="0.8">
<pioneer wordnetid="110434725" confidence="0.8">
<specialist wordnetid="110631941" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<employee wordnetid="110053808" confidence="0.8">
<originator wordnetid="110383816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/349136.xml">
Gordon Bell</link></originator>
</employee>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</creator>
</associate>
</engineer>
</colleague>
</specialist>
</pioneer>
</interior_designer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</peer>
</expert>
's project, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/4473862.xml">
MyLifeBits</link> (from <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<military_unit wordnetid="108198398" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<division wordnetid="108213205" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<army_unit wordnetid="108190754" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/2163522.xml">
Microsoft Research</link></research_worker>
</army_unit>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</division>
</person>
</military_unit>
</physical_entity>
) as well as <link>
Richard Furuta</link> and <link>
Frank Shipman</link>'s <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csdl.tamu.edu/walden/">
Walden's Paths</weblink> project (from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/29927.xml">
Texas A&amp;M University</link></ranking>
</university>
).  Both projects have implemented <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/638889.xml">
path</link>-based systems reminiscent of the Memex.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/18915928.xml">
As We May Think</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/148257.xml">
Project Xanadu</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/3585614.xml">
Mundaneum</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/4473862.xml">
MyLifeBits</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>People:</b></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/32767.xml">
Vannevar Bush</link></scientist>
</person>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/8081.xml">
Douglas Engelbart</link></scientist>
</person>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/254150.xml">
J.C.R. Licklider</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/31550.xml">
Ted Nelson</link></scientist>
</person>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/1445265.xml">
Paul Otlet</link></academician>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<pioneer wordnetid="110434725" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<originator wordnetid="110383816" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/2117158.xml">
Andries van Dam</link></associate>
</creator>
</originator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</pioneer>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Ideas:</b></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link>
external memory</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/287801.xml">
hypermedia</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/13460.xml">
hypertext</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/3948917.xml">
intelligence amplification</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/405363.xml">
office of the future</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/194507/bush">
"As We May Think"</weblink> - The original article from the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/149743.xml">
Atlantic Monthly</link></it> archives</entry>
<entry id="2">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/3134035.xml">
Buckland, Michael K.</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 "Emanuel Goldberg, Electronic Document Retrieval, And Vannevar Bush's Memex". Journal of the American Society for Information Science 43, no. 4 (May 1992): 284–294</entry>
<entry id="3">
Nyce, James M.; Kahn, Paul (eds.) "From Memex to Hypertext: Vannevar Bush and the Mind's Machine". San Diego, London (...) 1991. [A reprint of all of Bush's texts regarding Memex accompanied by related Sources and Studies]</entry>
<entry id="4">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/336994.xml">
Engines of Creation</link></book>
 (1986) by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/16769.xml">
K. Eric Drexler</link></person>
.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/194507/bush">
"As We May Think"</weblink> - The original article from the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/149743.xml">
Atlantic Monthly</link></it> archives</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://graphics.cs.brown.edu/html/info/vannevar_bush.html">
"As We May Think - A Celebration of Vannevar Bush's 1945 Vision"</weblink>, at Brown University</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.livinginternet.com/i/ii_bush.htm">
Vannevar Bush and Memex</weblink> &ndash; Living Internet</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
