<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:21:34[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108058098">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>StatSoft</title>
<id>2063524</id>
<revision>
<id>212359629</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-14T14:45:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Kbdankbot</username>
<id>6505923</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Companies based in Tulsa, Oklahoma</category>
<category>Software companies of the United States</category>
<category>Companies established in 1984</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>StatSoft, Inc.</b> is one of the largest providers of <link>
analytic software</link> worldwide. StatSoft's flagship product line is the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/2079997.xml">
STATISTICA</link></software>
 suite of analytics software products. STATISTICA provides a comprehensive array of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/2720954.xml">
data analysis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/759312.xml">
data management</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/3461736.xml">
data visualization</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/42253.xml">
data mining</link> procedures. It includes a wide selection of predictive modeling, clustering, classification, and exploratory techniques in one <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/81196.xml">
software platform</link>. StatSoft is also the largest manufacturer of enterprise-wide quality-control and improvement software systems in the world, and the only company capable of supporting its QC products worldwide. <p>

StatSoft’s software products are used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/920548.xml">
mission critical</link> manufacturing applications, in regulated, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/11632.xml">
FDA</link>-controlled industries, and as a foundation of corporate-wide <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/222448.xml">
Six Sigma</link></method>
</know-how>
 initiatives. StatSoft’s products are also used to help achieve compliance with <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link>
CFR</link></publication>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
 Part 11 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/67031.xml">
Sarbanes-Oxley</link> (SOX) regulations.  STATISTICA has achieved an unprecedented record of recognition from both users and expert reviewers since its first Windows release in 1993, being ranked the highest in every review by an independent third party.</p>

<sec>
<st>
StatSoft's products</st>

<p>

<b><it>STATISTICA</it></b><b> Enterprise:</b>  The Enterprise line of STATISTICA products is designed for multi-user, collaborative analytic applications. These STATISTICA products contain the same suite of analytic capabilities as the STATISTICA Desktop applications. Those analytic procedures are deployed on a server and are designed for simultaneous use by tens or hundreds of users. STATISTICA provides a Windows client, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/33173.xml">
Web browser</link> client, for full access to STATISTICA capabilities and reports through an industry-standard Web browser, and deployment options for thin-client access to STATISTICA across a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/38140.xml">
Wide Area Network</link> (WAN).</p>
<p>

<b><it>WebSTATISTICA</it></b><b>:</b>  The WebSTATISTICA Server system is offered as a complete solution that includes the analytic functionality of the respective selected STATISTICA product or any combination of STATISTICA products. This system makes the functionality of any of the STATISTICA family of products available anywhere by any workstation equipped with an industry-standard Web browser. Thus, WebSTATISTICA Server applications add new possibilities and applications to the entire line of STATISTICA Data Analysis, Data Mining, and Quality Control/Six Sigma software.</p>
<p>

<b>Data Mining:</b> Each of the products in the STATISTICA Data Mining suite offers an easy-to-use, icon-based user interface. It features a selection of automated and ready-to-deploy data mining solutions for a wide variety of business applications. At the same time, STATISTICA is customizable and can be tailored to meet very specific analysis requirements through its open architecture.</p>
<p>

This collection of data mining and machine learning algorithms includes, among many others: Support Vector Machines, EM and k-Means Clustering, Classification &amp; Regression Trees, Generalized Additive Models, Independent Component Analysis, Stochastic Gradient Boosted Trees, Ensembles of Neural Networks, Automatic Feature Selection, MARSplines, CHAID Trees, Nearest Neighbor Methods, Association Rules, and Random Forests.</p>
<p>

STATISTICA Desktop:  The STATISTICA  Desktop line of products is designed for deployment on a single workstation. STATISTICA  spreadsheets, configurations and macros are all stored on the User's local workstation as a stand-alone application. STATISTICA  includes not only general purpose statistical, graphical, and analytic data management procedures, but also comprehensive implementations of specialized methods for data analysis (e.g., data mining, business, social sciences, biomedical research, or engineering applications). All analytic tools offered in the STATISTICA  line of software are available as part of an integrated package.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Company overview </st>

<p>

StatSoft, Inc. is a closely held corporation with headquarters in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/150969.xml">
Tulsa</link>, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/22489.xml">
Oklahoma</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
USA</link>. StatSoft offices are located in 20 countries on all continents, including: Germany (StatSoft GmbH), France (StatSoft France), the United Kingdom (StatSoft Ltd.), Poland (StatSoft Polska Sp. z o.o.), Italy (StatSoft Italia, srl), Sweden (StatSoft Scandinavia AB), the Netherlands (StatSoft Benelux BV), Iberian Peninsula - Spain and Portugal (StatSoft Iberica Lda.), Russia (StatSoft Russia), Taiwan/China (StatSoft Taiwan), Japan (StatSoft Japan, Inc.), Korea (StatSoft Korea), Brazil (StatSoft South America), South Africa (StatSoft Southern Africa), Australia (StatSoft Pacific Pty Ltd.), Czech Republic (StatSoft Czech Republic s.r.o.), Israel (StatSoft Israel Ltd.), Hungary (StatSoft Hungary Ltd.), Singapore (StatSoft Singapore), Switzerland (StatSoft Switzerland), Bulgaria (StatSoft Bulgaria Ltd.), and India (StatSoft India Pvt. Ltd.).</p>
<p>

StatSoft’s software is available in Chinese, Czech, English, French, German, Italian, Japanese, Polish, Russian, and other languages.  Documentation is available in Arabic, Chinese, Czech, English, French, German, Hungarian, Italian, Japanese, Korean, Polish, Portuguese, Russian, Spanish, and other languages.</p>
<p>

Data analysis software from StatSoft is used at most major universities, research institutes, corporations, and manufacturing facilities in more than 60 countries. 
StatSoft products are distributed by all major US and international software distributors, and they are available from value-added resellers, consulting firms, and university computer stores. Student versions of STATISTICA (and related textbooks) are distributed directly by StatSoft offices around the world.</p>
<p>

StatSoft’s STATISTICA line of software is available in single-user versions (for individual end-users), in the form of network or concurrent multi-user packages, and as enterprise fully Web-enabled systems (with extensive groupware functionality) integrated with a data warehouse. The exact number of users of StatSoft products is difficult to determine but can be estimated at more than 600,000 users worldwide (universities/research institutions: 30%; corporations/manufacturing facilities: 60%; government agencies: 10%).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Company history </st>

<p>

<b>1980s:</b> The company was established in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/34578.xml">
1984</link> as a partnership of a group of university professors and scientists. Although their research interests were in different areas of quantitative data analysis, they had one thing in common: In order to analyze data from their own research, they each had to develop custom statistical procedures, which were either not available on the market or available only in command-driven, inflexible, and tedious-to-use mainframe (or mainframe-like) programs. The company started with only five employees; its first products (PsychoStat-2 and PsychoStat-3, designed mainly for natural and social scientists) included menu-driven libraries of flexible statistical procedures integrated with data management. </p>
<p>

StatSoft started to grow rapidly. In 1985, StatSoft released StatFast, which was the first statistics package released for the newly introduced Apple Macintosh. The program offered a selection of basic statistics and graphs integrated with a data editor and could run even on a 128k Macintosh with a single floppy drive.</p>
<p>

The demand for StatSoft products overseas also grew rapidly. In 1988, StatSoft of Europe, the first StatSoft foreign sales office, was opened in Hamburg, Germany [(later incorporated as: StatSoft (Europe) GmbH)]. </p>
<p>

<b>1990s:</b> The first (DOS) version of STATISTICA (a new, graphically oriented line of statistics software) was released in March 1991. In 1992, The Macintosh version of STATISTICA repeated the success of its DOS counterpart.  The results of a survey of a random sample of 1,000 readers of MacWORLD placed it on the list of the best products in its class (MacWORLD's "World-Class Award" survey).</p>
<p>

The initial release of STATISTICA for Windows (4.0) in 1993 was followed by releases of 4.5, 5.0, 5.1, '97 Edition, and '98 Edition.  </p>
<p>

<b>2000s:</b> STATISTICA 6 was released in 2001.  STATISTICA 6 was based on the <link>
 COM</link> architecture and technologies such as multithreading and support for distributed processing for large enterprise installations.  This release included built-in Visual Basic scripting that gives programmers access to all of the program’s functionality.  
STATISTICA 7 was released in 2004.   Its product line features a comprehensive selection of technologies, solutions, and integration services, including:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Data analysis tools for virtually any application, including validated installations for the FDA-regulated industries</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Integrated, server-centric analytic applications for all categories of analysts (from advanced R&amp;D statisticians to occasional users and consumers of simple reports)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Comprehensive applications for predictive and exploratory <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/42253.xml">
data mining</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/318439.xml">
text mining</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Quality control and improvement applications including a broad selection of tools for implementation of Six Sigma initiatives, "predictive QC", and "QC mining"</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Document management systems</link> (21 CFR Part 11, and Sarbanes-Oxley (SOX) compliant) fully integrated with analytic solutions</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

All these categories of applications are built on highly scalable kernels, and they are based on a cutting edge distributed / parallel processing technology that divides the processing load of computationally intensive applications across multiple servers over the web. This supercomputer-like architecture is capable of delivering astounding performance using even very inexpensive computer hardware. </p>
<p>

<b>Present:</b> STATISTICA 8 was released in 2007.  StatSoft continues to grow and spend more than 30% of its revenues on Research and Development.  StatSoft is a leading provider of enterprise systems for a broad array of analytic applications, and the only provider of fully web-enabled, comprehensive analytic systems where a complete array of analytic tools can be accessed via thin Client (an Internet Browser) from any computer in the world as long as it is connected to the Internet. StatSoft is also the leader in the area of "intelligent" (predictive) systems for monitoring and improving quality.  StatSoft is currently the largest company in the world that offers QC systems for the enterprise, supported by full-service offices in 20 overseas locations.</p>
<p>

StatSoft enterprise solutions have now been validated in mission-critical applications at world leading companies, and in a variety of industries including the manufacturing, chemical, and pharmaceutical sectors of the economy, and many other industries. Some of the largest multinational corporations have now standardized on StatSoft solutions and integrated them deep inside the most sensitive components of their computer infrastructures. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 StatSoft’s services </st>

<p>

StatSoft's professional services groups provide a range of services to complement the STATISTICA software. StatSoft provides software integration and customization services, development of custom Web applications based on WebSTATISTICA Server technology, as well as installation of a general-purpose Web Server system.  StatSoft also offers deployment of data mining solutions designed to work with specific <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/7990.xml">
data warehouses</link> and solve particular ranges of problems.  Additionally, statistical consulting services are available.
StatSoft offers both introductory and advanced training courses in major cities in the United States and overseas. StatSoft's training classes provide hands-on experience with its line of software products as well as an introduction to real-world example applications. 
StatSoft, through its Technical Services group, provides software validation services as part of the deployment of STATISTICA applications. These services include requirement gathering and documentation, validation planning, installation qualification, operational qualification, and performance qualification. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.statsoft.com/">
StatSoft's official website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</company>
</article>
