<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:16:03[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<software  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106566077">
<header>
<title>STATISTICA</title>
<id>2079997</id>
<revision>
<id>219712777</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-16T15:14:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Wordsoup</username>
<id>6615045</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Windows-only software</category>
<category>Statistical software</category>
<category>Windows software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Software</name>
<parameters>
<genre>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/21506.xml">
numerical analysis</link></genre>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.statsoft.com/">
www.statsoft.com</weblink></website>
<latest_release_version>
8.0</latest_release_version>
<developer>
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/2063524.xml">
StatSoft</link></institution>
</company>
</developer>
<name>
STATISTICA</name>
<latest_release_date>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link></latest_release_date>
<license>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/18934886.xml">
Proprietary software</link></license>
<operating_system>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link></operating_system>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>STATISTICA</b> is a statistics and analytics software package developed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/2063524.xml">
StatSoft, Inc.</link> STATISTICA provides a selection of data analysis, data management, data mining, and data visualization procedures. Features of the software include basic and multivariate statistical analysis, quality control modules, neural networks, and a collection of data mining techniques.  All of these tools are provided in an open architecture with a single software platform.
<sec>
<st>
User Interface</st>
<p>

<it>STATISTICA</it> product categories include Enterprise (for use across a site or organization), Web-Based (for use with a server and web browser), Concurrent and Standard Network Desktop, and Single-User Desktop. <it>STATISTICA</it> has an interactive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
 graphical user interface</link> with customizable menus and toolbars. <it>STATISTICA</it> also has an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
 API</link>-based interface that allows all of the program's functions to be callable from other applications such as <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/6097382.xml">
Visual Basic</link></programming_language>
, <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/72038.xml">
C++</link></programming_language>
, and <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
 Java</link></request>
</message>
, and internally callable from the built-in <it>STATISTICA</it> Visual Basic user interface.</p>
<p>

There are three basic channels to which you can direct all analysis results spreadsheets and graphs:  workbooks, reports, and standalone windows.  Workbooks and reports are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/93497.xml">
 Active X</link> document containers, which means they can hold all native <it>STATISTICA</it> documents as well as other types of Active X documents, including <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/20268.xml">
Microsoft Excel</link></format>
</software>
 spreadsheets and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/20287.xml">
Microsoft Word</link></software>
 documents.  Workbooks contain two panels: a navigation tree on the left and a document viewer on the right that allows the user to view the document that is selected on the left.  Reports display a series of spreadsheets, graphs, or other objects sequentially in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/33236.xml">
word processor</link> style document.  Workbooks have a file extension of .stw and reports have a file extension of .str.  </p>
<p>

Data files are typically displayed in spreadsheets.  The basic form of the spreadsheet is a two-dimensional table arranged as cases (rows) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/32818.xml">
variables</link> (columns). <it>STATISTICA</it> spreadsheets have a <link>
file extension</link> of .sta.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Analytic Techniques</st>
<p>

<it>STATISTICA</it> contains several main groups of analytic techniques, which can be accessed from the Statistica <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/2399348.xml">
menu bar</link>.  The software provides options for common <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/28651.xml">
 basic statistics</link>, multivariate techniques, and advanced linear/nonlinear models.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/41613.xml">
 Quality control </link> techniques include quality control charts and process analysis.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/9541.xml">
Design of Experiments</link> module provides an interface for setting up and analyzing experiment data sets.  Other main types of analyses include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/1729542.xml">
Neural Networks</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/42253.xml">
Data Mining</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Graphics</st>
<p>

<it>STATISTICA</it> includes analytic and exploratory graphs in addition to standard 2- and 3-dimensional graphs.  The graphics technology provides a collection of brushing techniques, which allows for investigation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/160951.xml">
outliers</link> and exploratory data analysis.  Brushing actions include interactive labeling, marking, and exclusion of selected data points.  The appearance of each graph can be customized, and the graph can be saved in several graphics file formats, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPG</link>, <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/24306.xml">
PNG</link></format>
, <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/81673.xml">
 Windows metafile</link></format>
 (WMF), device-independent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/250336.xml">
Windows bitmap</link> (BMP), and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/145479.xml">
Encapsulated Postscript</link> (EPS) files.  <it>STATISTICA</it> graphs are Active-X objects that can be embedded into compatible documents, such as Excel or Word documents, where they can be edited by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/1418946.xml">
double clicking</link> on them.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Statistica Visual Basic Environment</st>
<p>

The <it>STATISTICA</it> Visual Basic environment includes a text editor, debugging tools, and an Object Browser to aide the user in selecting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/7392.xml">
 classes</link>, functions, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/5999262.xml">
 properties</link> for manually creating or editing <it>STATISTICA</it> Visual Basic <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/20560.xml">
macros</link></concept>
</idea>
.  The software also provides three options for creating macros automatically. Analysis Macros record the settings and output options chosen for a particular analysis.  A Master Macro can record a series of analyses.  A Keyboard Macro records the actual series of keystrokes that a user enters via the keyboard.  </p>
<p>

<b>Importing data with STATISTICA</b>
STATISTICA includes a facility to import text based data files.  With this mechanism STATISTICA helps to bridge the gap of being able to get your data into the software.  This is useful for the end-user who logs their own data.  It is also useful for bringing in data that has been exported from another software package in a common textual format.  STATISTICA provides two interfaces for textual importing; largely because the interfaces would become too cluttered if they were combined.  These interfaces handle fixed width text files and variable width text files.  More importantly, STATISTICA's import facility is based on smart, sophisticated parsing that the end-user has good control over.  If the data being imported were viewed like an object, then the user would tell STATISTICA what characters, or sequence of characters to expect to cause a line of data to be defined.  In the same way, the end-user would tell STATISTICA what characters, or sequence of characters to expect to cause a break in data points.  The import facility also allows you to tell the system what to use as a decimal point, what to use as string delimiters, and what to use as escape sequence.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sarbanes-Oxley Compliance</st>
<p>

<it>STATISTICA</it> provides tools that assist with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/67031.xml">
Sarbanes-Oxley Act</link> compliance.  The software integrates with the Statistica <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/71608.xml">
Document management system</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/6824243.xml">
Comparison of statistical packages</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.statsoft.com">
Statistica Homepage</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</software>
</article>
