<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:32:31[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Manicure</title>
<id>212495</id>
<revision>
<id>244017778</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T23:25:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Arakunem</username>
<id>5154376</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Body modification</category>
<category>Nail care</category>
<category>Massage</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="BothHand.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Long, manicured nails are a fashion statement.
</caption>
</image>

A <b>manicure</b> is a cosmetic beauty treatment for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/397986.xml">
fingernail</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/19166474.xml">
hand</link>s performed either at home or by a nail technician.  A manicure treatment can be just for the hands or nails, or can be for both. A common manicure found is the filing, shaping of the nails and the application of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/1033672.xml">
polish</link>. There are also manicure services that are specialties for the hands and feet. For the hands, the soaking of a softening substance and the application of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/4642616.xml">
lotion</link> is a common specialty. Another common specialty is applying a similar treatment to the feet and toenails.  This is called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/429711.xml">
pedicure</link>.  The word "manicure" derives from <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/17730.xml">
Latin</link></language>
: <it>manus</it> for "hand," <it>cura</it>  for "care."<p>

In addition to the filing, polishing, and painting of fingernails, a manicure may also include the application of artificial nail tips, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/173283.xml">
acrylic</link>s or artificial nail gels. Some manicures can include the painting of pictures or designs on the nails or applying small <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/367681.xml">
decal</link>s or imitation <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/12806.xml">
jewel</link>s.</p>
<p>

In many areas, manicurists are licensed and follow regulation. Since skin is manipulated and is sometimes trimmed, there is a certain risk of spreading <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/37220.xml">
infection</link> when tools are used across many people and, therefore, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../729/184729.xml">
sanitation</link> is a serious issue.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Manicures began 5000 years ago. In India, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/18581411.xml">
henna</link> was used for manicure. The term mehendi, used synonymously for henna, derives from the Sanskrit mehandika.  Much of the modern revival of henna derives from its popularity in India. 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/292405.xml">
Cixi</link>, the Dowager Empress of China, was known to keep very long naturally-grown nails.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

French manicures are manicures designed to resemble a natural nail, and are characterized by natural pink base nails with white tips. The tips of the nail are painted white while the rest of the nail is polished in a pink or a suitable nude shade. French manicures may have originated in 18th-century Paris and were popular in the 1920s and 1930s. The style is chosen because it is very simple and give nails a natural and clean look. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Ex-servicewomen_learning_manicure_techniques.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Ex-servicewomen learning manicure techniques, 1945
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Fashion nails</st>
<p>

In the late 20th century, artificial nails for women became widely popular. The artificial nails are not a replacement, but an extension for natural nails. There are two main approaches to creating artificial nails&mdash;<it>tips</it> and <it>forms</it>. Tips are made of lightweight plastic plates that are "nail" shaped. They are glued on the end of the natural nail and  acrylic is then applied over the entire nail. Forms are fitted over the nail and then an artificial nail is molded out of acrylic and the form is removed and then properly shaped and buffed to a shine. There are several popular techniques that can be used to create longer better looking nail enhancements. One popular material commonly called "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/173283.xml">
acrylics</link>" is a mixture of a polymer powder and a liquid monomer (e.g.<link>
ethylmethacrylate</link>). The mixture starts to harden in 30&ndash;40 seconds after application and continues to cure to final hardness typically for more than an hour. Powder and liquid acrylics can be removed in 20 minutes using a variety of solvents (usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/1795597.xml">
acetone</link> is used). Another material, commonly called "UV gel", (in correct chemical terms a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/23001.xml">
polymer</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/58890.xml">
resin</link>) hardens under <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/31990.xml">
ultraviolet light</link>. Depending on brand these can show a broader variety of quality and properties (flexibility, strength, etc.) but may be more expensive. They generally cannot be removed by organic solvents, but only be removed by filing (or left to grow out with the natural nail). Another popular alternative to acrylic or gel preparations are Fiberglass or Silk wraps. They are done by cutting pieces of actual fiberglass or silk fabric to fit on the surface of the nail or tip  and then it is sealed down with a resin or glue. These are a possible alternative for those who are allergic to chemicals used in the acrylic or gel process. Other materials can be used, as well as combinations of them. There are also temporary, cheaper flexible tips that can be quickly glued at home without help from a professional. Acrylic nail powders are available in a variety of colours and can use "special effects" such as contours, sparkles and the very popular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/212495.xml">
French Manicure</link> (pink and white appearance).
<image location="right" width="150px" src="Frenchmanicurewiki.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Example of a French Manicure
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

These fashion trends are not without risks, as residues of acrylic resins have been known to lead to redness, swelling, pain and even severe allergic reactions. The nail can <link>
separate from the nail bed</link>, and if the nail root becomes damaged, the replacement can be permanently deformed. As well, nail glue is poisonous if accidentally swallowed and a few nail polishes and removers contain toxic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/63847.xml">
formaldehyde</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/1795597.xml">
acetone</link>.</p>
<p>

An alternative to acrylic nails is to harden your natural nail by using a fluoride treatment.  Fluoride claims to harden your nails just as it hardens your teeth.  However, some fluoride nail treatments contain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/69079.xml">
Ammonium</link> <ion wordnetid="109315159" confidence="0.8">
<particle wordnetid="109386422" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="109224911" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<anion wordnetid="109197815" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/7287845.xml">
Hexafluorophosphate</link></anion>
</natural_object>
</body>
</particle>
</ion>
 rather than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/8042115.xml">
Stannous fluoride</link>, which is the type of fluoride normally used in toothpaste.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Paraffin treatments </st>
<p>

The hands can be dipped in melted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../006/24006.xml">
paraffin</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/58256.xml">
wax</link> for softening and moisturizing. Paraffin wax is used because it can be heated to temperatures of over 100 degrees, without burning or injuring the hand. The intense heat allows for deeper absorption of emollients and essential oils. The wax is usually infused with various botanical ingredients such as Aloe vera, chamomile, tea tree oil, and azulene. Fruit waxes such as peach, apple and strawberry are often used in salons. </p>
<p>

Occasionally, lotion is rubbed on the hand before submersion into the paraffin bath. The hand is usually dipped more than once to allow a thicker wax coat to form, making the coating stay warm for longer and less likely to break or tear prematurely.  After the hands have been dipped in the wax, they are wrapped in either plastic or aluminum foil, or a special type of plastic bag or glove then covered with towel or special mitten to retain warmth. The hands are left for a few minutes before the paraffin is cooled and dried.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Hot oil manicure</st>
<p>

A hot oil manicure is a specific type of manicure that cleans the cuticles and softens them with oil.  It works well for dry skin and nails that are brittle as it improves both by leaving them soft and pliable. Types of oils that can be used are mineral oil, olive oil or commercial preparation in an
electric heater.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The standard manicure Process</st>
<p>

A manicurist prepares for a customer by ensuring that the working area and tools are sanitized and conveniently located and there is proper <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/188386.xml">
lighting</link>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Common manicure tools and supplies</st>

<p>

Tools:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bowl of warm water or fingerbath</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/193688.xml">
Nail clipper</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cuticle knife and clippers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cuticle pusher/Hoof stick </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nail file/emery board, buffer, scissors and brush</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Orange Stick </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Supplies:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cuticle remover * this is caustic and MUST be rinsed off the skin after use, oil and cream</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Massage lotion</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/1033672.xml">
Nail polish</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Base coat polish &amp; ridge filler polish</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Color varnish</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Top coat or sealant</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nail bindi stick-on jewels</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Nail polish remover</link> or nail polish remover wipes</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hand cream</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sanitizing spray/towels</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cotton balls/pads</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hand towels</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<spatial_property wordnetid="105062748" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="105064037" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/2324119.xml">
Squoval</link></shape>
</property>
</spatial_property>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bcc.cuny.edu/History/His10/Course/topic5.htm">
CUNY: The History of the Modern World: Imperialism</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
Turner, Janice&#32;(2005-10-22).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/weekend/story/0,,1596384,00.html">
Dirty young men</weblink>", Guardian Unlimited.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-20</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
