<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:31:40[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Ownership</title>
<id>213897</id>
<revision>
<id>242061533</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T19:28:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mark1512</username>
<id>560387</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Legal terms</category>
<category>Property</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For ownership of articles in Wikipedia, see .
"Own" redirects here. For the television channel, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/16980185.xml">
OWN</link>.

<p>

<b>Ownership</b> is the state or fact of exclusive rights and control over <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/23626.xml">
property</link>, which may be an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/24695.xml">
object</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/873600.xml">
land/real estate</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/14724.xml">
intellectual property</link> (arguably) or some other kind of property. It is embodied in an ownership right also referred to as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/226179.xml">
title</link>.</p>
<p>

Ownership is the key building block in the development of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/5416.xml">
capitalist</link> socio-economic system. The concept of ownership has existed for thousands of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../341/34341.xml">
years</link> and in all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/19159508.xml">
cultures</link>. Over the millennia, however, and across cultures what is considered eligible to be property and how that property is regarded culturally is very different. Ownership is the basis for many other concepts that form the foundations of ancient and modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/37235.xml">
societies</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/8983183.xml">
money</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/29678.xml">
trade</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../835/152835.xml">
debt</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/4695.xml">
bankruptcy</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/5785.xml">
criminality</link> of theft and private vs. public property.</p>
<p>

The process and mechanics of ownership are fairly complex since one can gain, transfer and lose ownership of property in a number of ways. To acquire property one can purchase it with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/8983183.xml">
money</link>, trade it for other property, receive it as a gift, steal it, find it, make it or homestead it. One can transfer or lose ownership of property by selling it for money, exchanging it for other property, giving it as a gift, being robbed of it, misplacing it, or having it stripped from one's ownership through legal means such as eviction, foreclosure and seizure. Ownership is self-propagating in that if an object is owned by someone, any additional goods produced by using that object will also be owned by the same person. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Types of owners</st>

<ss1>
<st>
In person</st>
<p>

Individuals may own property directly. In some societies only adult men may own property; in other societies (such as the <link>
Haudenosaunee</link>), property is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/84024.xml">
matrilinear</link> and passed on from mother to the son. In most societies both men and women can own property with no restrictions and limitationss at all.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Structured Ownership Entities</st>
<p>

Throughout history, nations (or governments) and religions have owned property. These entities exist primarily for other purposes than to own or operate property, hence they may have no clear rules regarding the disposition of their property.</p>
<p>

To own and operate property, structures (often known today as legal entities) have been created in many societies throughout history. The differences in how they deal with members' rights is a key factor in determining their type. Each type has advantages and disadvantages derived from their means of recognizing or disregarding (rewarding or not), contributions of financial capital or personal effort. </p>
<p>

Cooperatives, corporations, trusts, partnerships, condominium associations are only some of the many varied types of structured ownership; each type has many subtypes. Legal advantages or restrictions on various types of structured ownership have existed in many societies past and present. To govern how assets are to be used, shared or treated, rules and regulations may be legally imposed or internally adopted or decreed.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Liability for the Group or for Others in the Group</st>
<p>

Ownership implies responsibility, for actions regarding the property. A "legal shield" is said to exist if the entity's legal liabilities do not get redistributed among the entity's owners or members. An application of this, to limit ownership risks, is to form a new entity to purchase, own and operate each property. Since the entity is separate and distinct from others, if a problem occurs which leads to a massive liability, the individual is protected from losing more than the value of that one property. Many other properties are protected, when owned by other distinct entities.</p>
<p>

In the loosest sense of group ownership, a lack of legal framework, rules and regulations may mean that group ownership of property places every member in a position of responsibility (liability) for the actions of each other member. A structured group duly constituted as an entity under law may still not protect members from being personally liable for each others' actions. Court decisions against the entity itself may give rise to unlimited personal liability for each and every member. An example of this situation is a professional partnership (e.g. law practice) in some jurisdictions. Thus, being a partner or owner in a group may give little advantage in terms of share ownership while producing a lot of risk to the partner, owner or participant.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Sharing Gains</st>
<p>

At the end of each financial year, accounting rules determine a surplus or profit, which may be retained inside the entity or distributed among owners according to the initial setup intent when the entity was created.</p>
<p>

Entities <it>with a member focus</it> will give financial surplus back to members according to the volume of financial activity that the participating member generated for the entity. Examples of this are producer cooperatives, buyer cooperatives and participating whole life policyholders in both mutual and share-capital insurance companies.</p>
<p>

Entities<it> with share voting rights that depend on financial capital</it> distribute surplus among shareholders without regard to any other contribution to the entity. Depending on internal rules and regulations, certain classes of shares have the right to receive increases in financial "dividends" while other classes do not. After many years the increase over time is substantial if the business is profitable. Examples of this are common shares and preferred shares in private or publicly listed share capital corporations.</p>
<p>

Entities <it>with a focus on providing service in perpetuam</it> do not distribute financial surplus; they must retain it. It will then serve as a cushion against losses or as a means to finance growth activities. Examples of this are not-for-profit entities: they are allowed to make profits, but are not permitted to give any of it back to members except by way of discounts in the future on new transactions.</p>
<p>

Depending on the charter at the foundation of the entity, and depending on the legal framework under which the entity was created, the form of ownership is determined once and for all time. To change it requires significant work in terms of communicating with stakeholders (member-owners, governments, etc) and acquiring their approval. Whatever structural constraints or disadvantages exist at the creation thus remain an integral part of the entity. Common in for instance New York City, Hamburg and Berlin in Germany is a form of real estate ownership known as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/89313.xml">
cooperative</link> (also co-operative or co-op, in German Wohnungsgenossenschaft - apartment co-operative) which relies heavily on internal rules of operation instead of the legal framework governing condominium associations. These "co-ops", owning the building for the mutual benefit of its members, can ultimately perform most of the functions of a legally constituted condominium, i.e. restricting use appropriately and containing financial liabilities to within tolerable levels. To change their structure now that they are up and operating would require significant effort to achieve acceptance among members and various levels of government.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Sharing Use</st>
<p>

The owning entity makes rules governing use of property; each property may comprise areas that are made available to any and every member of the group to use. When the group is the entire nation, the same principle is in effect whether the property is small (e.g. picnic rest stops along highways) or large such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/21818.xml">
national parks</link>, highways, ports, and publicly owned buildings. Smaller examples of shared use include common areas such as lobbies, entrance hallways and passages to adjacent buildings.</p>
<p>

One disadvantage of communal ownership, known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/30802.xml">
Tragedy of the Commons</link>, occurs where unlimited unrestricted and unregulated access to a resource (e.g. pasture land) destroys the resource because of over-exploitation. The benefits of exploitation accrue to individuals immediately, while the costs of policing or enforcing appropriate use, and the losses dues to overexploitation, are distributed among many, and are only visible to these gradually.</p>
<p>

In an ideal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/9209651.xml">
communist</link> nation the means of production of goods would be owned communally by all people of that nation; the original thinkers did not specify rules and regulations.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Types of property</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Personal property</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/24695.xml">
Personal property</link></it>
</indent>
<b>Personal property</b> is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/23626.xml">
property</link>. In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/5254.xml">
common law</link> systems personal property may also be called <b>chattels</b>. It is distinguished from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/26277.xml">
real property</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/63089.xml">
real estate</link>. In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/1048798.xml">
civil law</link> systems personal property is often called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/24695.xml">
movable property</link> or movables - any property that can be moved from one location or another. This term is in distinction with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/2202294.xml">
immovable property</link> or immovables, such as land and buildings.</p>
<p>

Personal property may be classified in a variety of ways, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/580039.xml">
good</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/8983183.xml">
money</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/1160722.xml">
negotiable instrument</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/42162.xml">
securities</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/299146.xml">
intangible assets</link> including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/2975713.xml">
choses in action</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Land ownership</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/63089.xml">
Real estate</link></it>
</indent>
Real estate or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/2202294.xml">
immovable property</link> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
legal</link> term (in some jurisdictions) that encompasses land along with anything permanently affixed to the land, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/45995.xml">
building</link>s. Real estate (immovable property) is often considered synonymous with <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/26277.xml">
real property</link></b> (also sometimes called <it>realty</it>), in contrast with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/24695.xml">
personal property</link> (also sometimes called <it>chattel</it> or <it>personalty</it>). However, for technical purposes, some people prefer to distinguish real estate, referring to the land and fixtures themselves, from real property, referring to ownership rights over real estate. The terms <it>real estate</it> and <it>real property</it> are used primarily in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/5254.xml">
common law</link>, while <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/1048798.xml">
civil law</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/16392.xml">
jurisdiction</link>s refer instead to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/2202294.xml">
immovable property</link>.</p>
<p>

In law, the word real means relating to a thing (from Latin res, matter or thing), as distinguished from a person. Thus the law broadly distinguishes between [real property] (land and anything affixed to it) and [personal property] (everything else, e.g., clothing, furniture, money). The conceptual difference was between immovable property, which would transfer title along with the land, and movable property, which a person would retain title to. (The word is not derived from the notion of land having historically been "royal" property. The word royal — and its Spanish cognate real — come from the unrelated Latin word rex, meaning king.)</p>
<p>

With the development of private <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/23626.xml">
property</link> ownership, real estate has become a major area of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
business</link>.</p>
<p>

Ownership is passed when one party asks for another party's property under all circumstances.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Corporations and legal entities</st>
<p>

An individual or group of individuals can own corporations and other legal entities. A <b>legal entity</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
legal</link> construct through which the law allows a group of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/361406.xml">
natural person</link>s to act as if it were an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/14593.xml">
individual</link> for certain purposes. Some companies and entities are owned privately by the individuals who registered them with the government while other companies are owned publicly.</p>
<p>

Some duly incorporated entities may not be owned by individuals nor by other entities; they exist without being owned once they are created. Not being owned, they cannot be bought and sold. Mutual life insurance companies, credit unions, and cooperatives are examples of this. No person can purchase the company, as their ownership is not legally available for sale, neither as shares nor as a single whole.</p>
<p>

A a publicly listed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/4918223.xml">
company</link>, known as a <b>public company</b>, is owned by any member of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/307834.xml">
public</link> who wishes to purchase stock in that company rather than by a relatively few individuals. A company that is owned by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/146081.xml">
stockholders</link> who are members of the general public and trade <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/867877.xml">
shares</link> publicly, often through a listing on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/28168.xml">
stock exchange</link>. Ownership is open to anyone who has the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/8983183.xml">
money</link> and inclination to buy shares in the company. Owners, however, are generally classified in three groups. Those with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/1536355.xml">
5% Ownership</link>s of the stock usually hold significant sway over the company. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/226597.xml">
Mutual Fund</link>s and regular institutions can also own the stock; if they own enough, can are considered as part of the 5% ownership category. They usually are differentiated from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/1499655.xml">
privately held companies</link> where the shares are held by a small group of individuals often members of one or a small group of families or otherwise related individuals (or other companies). For a discussion of the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
British</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 and <island wordnetid="109316454" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/147575.xml">
Irish</link></island>
 variant of this type of company, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/25109.xml">
public limited company</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Intellectual property</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/14724.xml">
Intellectual property</link></it>
</indent>
Intellectual (IP) property refers to a legal entitlement which sometimes attaches to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/230946.xml">
expressed form</link> of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/161999.xml">
idea</link>, or to some other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/299146.xml">
intangible</link> subject matter. This legal entitlement generally enables its holder to exercise <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/18935410.xml">
exclusive right</link>s of use in relation to the subject matter of the IP. The term <it>intellectual property</it> reflects the idea that this subject matter is the product of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/19378.xml">
mind</link> or the intellect, and that IP rights may be protected at law in the same way as any other form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/23626.xml">
property</link>.</p>
<p>

Intellectual property laws confer a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/1178306.xml">
bundle</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/18935410.xml">
exclusive right</link>s in relation to the particular form or manner in which ideas or information are expressed or manifested, and not in relation to the ideas or concepts themselves (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/230946.xml">
idea-expression divide</link>). It is therefore important to note that the term "intellectual property" denotes the specific legal rights which authors, inventors and other IP holders may hold and exercise, and not the intellectual work itself.</p>
<p>

Intellectual property laws are designed to protect different forms of intangible subject matter, although in some cases there is a degree of overlap.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/5278.xml">
copyright</link> may subsist in creative and artistic works (eg. books, movies, music, paintings, photographs and software), giving a copyright holder the exclusive right to control reproduction or adaptation of such works for a certain period of time.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/23273.xml">
patent</link> may be granted in relation to an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/44312.xml">
invention</link> that is new, useful and not simply an obvious advancement over what existed when the application was filed. A patent gives the holder an exclusive right to commercially exploit the invention for a certain period of time (typically 20 years from the filing date of a patent application).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/18935023.xml">
trademark</link> is a distinctive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/562907.xml">
sign</link> which is used to distinguish the products or services of one <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
business</link> from those of another business.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/225179.xml">
industrial design right</link> protects the form of appearance, style or design of an industrial object (eg. spare parts, furniture or textiles).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/29960.xml">
trade secret</link> (also known as "confidential information") is an item of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/353859.xml">
confidential</link> information concerning the commercial practices or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/166148.xml">
proprietary</link> knowledge of a business.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Patents, trademarks and designs fall into a particular subset of intellectual property known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/14724.xml">
industrial property</link>.</p>
<p>

Like other forms of property, intellectual property (or rather the exclusive rights which subsist in the IP) can be transferred (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/10698861.xml">
with</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/50021.xml">
without</link> consideration) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/40412.xml">
license</link>d to third parties. In some jurisdictions it may also be possible to use intellectual property as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/42162.xml">
security</link> for a loan.</p>
<p>

The basic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/153324.xml">
public policy</link> rationale for the protection of intellectual property is that IP laws facilitate and encourage disclosure of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/118450.xml">
innovation</link> into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link> for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/312085.xml">
common good</link>, by granting authors and inventors exclusive rights to exploit their works and invention for a limited period.</p>
<p>

However, various schools of thought are critical of the very concept of intellectual property, and some characterise IP as <it>intellectual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/153023.xml">
protectionism</link></it>. There is ongoing debate as to whether IP laws truly operate to confer the stated public benefits, and whether the protection they are said to provide is appropriate in the context of innovation derived from such things as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/3373310.xml">
traditional knowledge</link> and folklore, and patents for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/76266.xml">
software</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/1678619.xml">
business methods</link>. Manifestations of this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/7283.xml">
controversy</link> can be seen in the way different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/16392.xml">
jurisdiction</link>s decide whether to grant intellectual property protection in relation to subject matter of this kind, and the <grouping wordnetid="101012360" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<categorization wordnetid="101012712" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/267394.xml">
North-South divide</link></categorization>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</grouping>
 on issues of the role and scope of intellectual property laws.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Chattel slavery</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/27992.xml">
Chattel slavery</link></it>
</indent>
The living <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/54176.xml">
human body</link> is, in most modern societies, considered something which cannot be the property of anyone but the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/219599.xml">
person</link> whose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/3788.xml">
body</link> it is. This is in contradistinction to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/27992.xml">
chattel slavery</link>. Chattel slavery is a type of slavery defined as the absolute legal ownership of a person or persons, including the legal right to buy and sell them. The slaves do not have the freedom to live life as they choose, but as they are instructed by their owners, and their rights may be either severely limited or nonexistent. In most countries, chattel slaves were considered as movable property. </p>
<p>

Slavery is currently illegal in every country around the world, however, up until the 19th century slavery and ownership of people had existed in one form or another in nearly every society on earth. Notwithstanding the illegality according to codes of law, slavery still exists in various forms today.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Social Views of Ownership</st>
<p>

In modern Western popular culture some people (principally among the far <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/18499.xml">
political left</link>) believe that exclusive ownership of property underlies much social injustice, and facilitates tyranny and oppression on an individual and societal scale. Others (principally among the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/56522.xml">
political right</link>) consider the striving to achieve greater ownership of wealth as the driving factor behind human technological advancement and increasing standards of living.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Vedantic view</st>
<p>

The Brahiminist theology called Vedanta believes that the root of ownership is the feeling that one is separate from the rest of the universe. Given this understanding, one disconnects oneself from the universe, and then attempts to reconnect with objects through a relationship which is called ownership. Vedanta believes that the feeling of ownership is an illusion, which remains with oneself as long as one considers oneself as separate from the Universe. When one understands the fundamental reality that there is only one entity called the Universe, there is no need for ownership and one gets rid of this illusion.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ownership Issues in Politics</st>
<p>

<speech wordnetid="107109196" confidence="0.8">
<saying wordnetid="107151380" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<word wordnetid="106286395" confidence="0.8">
<motto wordnetid="107152259" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<neologism wordnetid="106294441" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/1300394.xml">
Ownership society</link></language_unit>
</neologism>
</part>
</motto>
</word>
</auditory_communication>
</saying>
</speech>
 is a political slogan used by United States President George W. Bush to promote a series of policies aimed to increase the control of individual citizens over health care and social security payments and policies. Critics have claimed that slogan hid an agenda that sought to implement tax cuts and curtail the government's role in health care and retirement saving.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controversies over the Universality of Ownership</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Native America</st>
<p>

A modern myth is that some societies, notably <ethnic_group wordnetid="107967382" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../217/21217.xml">
Native American</link></ethnic_group>
 ones, appeared to exist without the concept of personal ownership. Members of a society would feel free to take any objects they had need of, and expect them to be taken by others.  Recently, however, researchers have started to question just how collectivist Native American societies really were. Citing earlier studies done by anthropologists and historians "who were able to interview tribal members who had lived in pre-reservation Indian society," they argue that in fact, "most if not all North American indigenous peoples had a strong belief in individual property rights and ownership." <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.perc.org/perc.php?id=802">
http://www.perc.org/perc.php?id=802</weblink> These researchers further assert that Native American collectivism is a myth originating from the first encounters with tribes who, because of their hunting-orientation "did not view land as an important asset", and indeed, did not have a private property system with regards to land. The collectivist myth was initially propagated by reporters and politicians who never actually had contact with Native Americans and then made into a reality by the collectivist property rights system forced on Indians by the 1934 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/55752.xml">
Indian Reorganization Act</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wiktionary-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wiktionary
</caption>
</image>

Look up <it>, </it>'<b><it> in <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/156658.xml">
Wiktionary</link></web_site>
, the free dictionary.</it></b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/2377056.xml">
Cadastre</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<speech wordnetid="107109196" confidence="0.8">
<saying wordnetid="107151380" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<word wordnetid="106286395" confidence="0.8">
<motto wordnetid="107152259" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<neologism wordnetid="106294441" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/1300394.xml">
Ownership society</link></language_unit>
</neologism>
</part>
</motto>
</word>
</auditory_communication>
</saying>
</speech>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/22105.xml">
Public ownership</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
