<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:20:33[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<identifier  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107270601">
<header>
<title>Bates numbering</title>
<id>2147092</id>
<revision>
<id>236177505</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-04T05:23:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Eastlaw</username>
<id>1046972</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Universal identifiers</category>
<category>Legal documents</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Bates numbering</b> (also known as <b>Bates stamping</b> or <b>Bates coding</b>) is used in the legal, medical, and business fields to place identifying numbers and/or date/time-marks  on images and documents as they are scanned or processed (for example, during the discovery stage of preparations for trial or identifying business receipts).
Bates Stamping can be used to mark and identify images with copyrights by putting a company name, logo and/or legal copyright on them. This process provides identification, protection, and auto-increment numbering of the images.<p>

Bates numbering is commonly used as an organizational method to label and identify legal documents.  During the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../205/490205.xml">
discovery</link> phase of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/113258.xml">
litigation</link>, a large number of documents might necessitate the use of unique identifiers for each page of each document for reference and retrieval.  <b>Bates numbering</b> (named for the Bates automatic numbering machine), assigns an arbitrary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/3444411.xml">
unique identifier</link> to each page.  Such "numbering" may be solely numeric or may contain a combination of letters and numbers (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/4009786.xml">
alphanumeric</link>).  There is no standard method for numbering documents.  Examples of Bates numbers schemes used in tobacco cases may be found <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tobacco.health.usyd.edu.au/site/gateway/docs/pdf/Bates.pdf">
here</weblink>.</p>
<p>

Manual Bates stamping uses a self inking stamp with numbered wheels (5, 6, and 7-wheeled models are common) that automatically increment each time the stamp is pressed down on a page (some stamps allow for duplicate documents by only incrementing after two or more presses).  Today, preprinted, self-adhesive labels are common as is electronic document discovery (EDD) software that can electronically "stamp" documents stored as computer files by superimposing numbers onto them.</p>
<p>

The Bates Automatic Numbering Machine was patented in 1891-93 by the Bates Manufacturing Company of Edison, NJ.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.earlyofficemuseum.com/stamps.htm">
Date, Time, Number &amp; Name Stamps</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</identifier>
</article>
