<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:25:49[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Copayment</title>
<id>2151313</id>
<revision>
<id>213518243</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-19T18:24:23Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Seraphim Whipp</username>
<id>3369647</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Insurance terms</category>
<category>Health economics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>copayment</b>, or <b>copay</b>, is a capped contribution defined in the policy and paid by an insured person each time a medical service is accessed. It must be paid before any policy benefit is payable by an insurance company. Copayments do not usually contribute towards any policy out-of-pocket maximums. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
Insurance</link> companies use copayments to share health care costs to prevent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/175590.xml">
moral hazard</link>.  Though the copay is often only a small portion of the actual cost of the medical service, it is thought to prevent people from seeking medical care that may not be necessary (eg: an infection by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/92693.xml">
common cold</link>), which can result in substantial savings for insurance companies. The underlying philosophy is that with no copay, the perception is that medical care is "free" and then is used more often. <p>

However, a copay may also discourage people from seeking necessary medical care. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/1191433.xml">
RAND Health Insurance Experiment</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> a landmark study performed in the 1980s, demonstrated that cost sharing reduced <it>appropriate</it> and necessary office visits and preventive care as well as inappropriate visits, with adverse effects on visual acuity,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/77432.xml">
blood pressure</link> control,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> and survival among high-risk patients.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Medication copayments have also been associated with reduced use of necessary and appropriate medications for chronic conditions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

In a 2007 meta-analysis, RAND researchers published a review of the literature on cost sharing between 1985 and 2006. They concluded: </p>

<p>

<table style="border-collapse:collapse; border-style:none; background-color:transparent;" align="center" class="cquote2">
<row>
<col style="color:#B2B7F2;font-size:40px;font-family:serif;font-weight:bold;text-align:left;padding:10px 10px;" width="20" valign="top">
“</col>
<col style="padding:4px 10px;" valign="top">
Increased cost sharing is associated with lower rates of drug treatment, worse adherence among existing users, and more frequent discontinuation of therapy. For each 10% increase in cost sharing, prescription drug spending decreases by 2% to 6%, depending on class of drug and condition of the patient. The reduction in use associated with a benefit cap, which limits either the coverage amount or the number of covered prescriptions, is consistent with other cost-sharing features. For some chronic conditions, higher cost sharing is associated with increased use of medical services, at least for patients with congestive heart failure, lipid disorders, diabetes, and schizophrenia. While low-income groups may be more sensitive to increased cost sharing, there is little evidence to support this contention.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></col>
<col style="color:#B2B7F2;font-size:40px;font-family:serif;font-weight:bold;text-align:right;padding:10px 10px;" width="20" valign="bottom">
”</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www2.ups.edu/humanresources/2006_benefits/Benefits2006-FAQ.htm#co-payments">
What is the difference between co</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
Lohr KN, Brook RH, Kamberg CJ, et al. Use of medical care in the Rand Health Insurance Experiment: diagnosis- and service-specific analyses in a randomized controlled trial. Med Care 1986;24:S1-S87.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Lurie N, Kamberg CJ, Brook RH, Keeler EB, Newhouse JP. How free care improved vision in the health insurance experiment. Am J Public Health 1989;79:640-642. [Erratum, J Public Health 1989;79:1677.]</entry>
<entry id="4">
Keeler EB, Brook RH, Goldberg GA, Kamberg CJ, Newhouse JP. How free care reduced hypertension in the health insurance experiment. JAMA 1985;254:1926-1931.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Brook RH, Ware JE Jr, Rogers WH, et al. Does free care improve adults' health? Results from a randomized controlled trial. N Engl J Med 1983;309:1426-1434.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Drug copayment and adherence in chronic heart failure: effect on cost and outcomes. Cole JA et al, Pharmacotherapy 2006 Aug;26(8):1157-64.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Impact of two sequential drug cost-sharing policies on the use of inhaled medications in older patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or asthma. Dormuth CR et al, Clin Ther 2006 Jun;28(6):964-78; discussion 962-3.</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/short/298/1/61">
http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/short/298/1/61</weblink> Dana P. Goldman, Geoffrey F. Joyce, Yuhui Zheng, Prescription Drug Cost Sharing: Associations With Medication and Medical Utilization and Spending and Health,, JAMA. 2007;298:61-69. </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/2044841.xml">
Coinsurance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/636959.xml">
Deductible</link></entry>
</list>
</p>





</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
