<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:30:55[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Nutrition</title>
<id>21525</id>
<revision>
<id>244620399</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T19:07:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Finlay McWalter</username>
<id>22619</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Health sciences</category>
<category>Food science</category>
<category>Applied sciences</category>
<category>Self-care</category>
<category>Health</category>
<category>Nutrition</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Nutrition_label.gif" type="thumb">
<caption>

The "Nutrition Facts" table indicates the amounts of nutrients which experts recommend you limit or consume in adequate amounts.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Nutrition</b> (also called <b>nourishment</b> or <b>aliment</b>) is the provision, to cells and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/19653842.xml">
organism</link>s, of the materials necessary (in the form of food) to support <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/18393.xml">
life</link>. Many common health problems can be prevented or alleviated with good nutrition. </p>
<p>

The <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/639924.xml">
diet</link></it> of an organism refers to what it eats. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/439999.xml">
Dietitian</link>s are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/6142110.xml">
health professional</link>s who specialize in human nutrition, meal planning, economics, preparation, and so on. They are trained to provide safe, evidence-based dietary advice and management to individuals (in health and disease), as well as to institutions.</p>
<p>

Poor diet can have an injurious impact on health, causing deficiency diseases such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/28266.xml">
scurvy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/217881.xml">
beriberi</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/16994.xml">
kwashiorkor</link>; health-threatening conditions like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/56435.xml">
obesity</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/54439.xml">
metabolic syndrome</link>, and such common chronic systemic diseases as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/512662.xml">
cardiovascular disease</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/44677.xml">
diabetes</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/22461.xml">
osteoporosis</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>
 
Nutritional science investigates the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/20374.xml">
metabolic</link> and physiological responses of the body to diet. With advances in the fields of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/19200.xml">
molecular biology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/3954.xml">
biochemistry</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/12266.xml">
genetics</link>, the study of nutrition is increasingly concerned 
with metabolism and metabolic pathways, the sequences of biochemical steps through which the many substances of living things change from one form to another. </p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/54176.xml">
human body</link> contains <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/144412.xml">
chemical compounds</link>, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/33306.xml">
water</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/5932.xml">
carbohydrate</link>s (sugar, starch, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/140558.xml">
fiber</link>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acids</link> (in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
proteins</link>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acids</link> (in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/17940.xml">
lipids</link>), and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/21496.xml">
nucleic acids</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
DNA</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/25758.xml">
RNA</link>). These compounds, in turn, consist of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/5659.xml">
elements</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/5299.xml">
carbon</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/13255.xml">
hydrogen</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/22303.xml">
oxygen</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/21175.xml">
nitrogen</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/23318.xml">
phosphorus</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/5668.xml">
calcium</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/14734.xml">
iron</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/34420.xml">
zinc</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/18909.xml">
magnesium</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/19051.xml">
manganese</link>, and so on. All of these chemical compounds and elements occur in various forms and combinations (e.g. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/13311.xml">
hormones</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/32512.xml">
vitamins</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/24505.xml">
phospholipids</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/1966606.xml">
hydroxyapatite</link>), both in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/54176.xml">
human body</link> and in organisms (e.g. plants, animals) that humans eat.</p>
<p>

The human body consists of elements and compounds ingested, digested, absorbed, and circulated through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/3997.xml">
blood</link>stream. Except in the unborn fetus, it is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/165423.xml">
digestive system</link> which carries out the first steps in feeding the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/4230.xml">
cell</link>s of the body. In a typical adult, about seven liters of digestive juices enter the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/3432531.xml">
lumen</link> of the digestive tract. They break <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/5993.xml">
chemical bonds</link> in ingested molecules and modulate their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/350042.xml">
conformation</link>s and energy states. Though some molecules are absorbed into the bloodstream unchanged, digestive processes release them from the matrix of foods in which they occur. Unabsorbed matter is secreted in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/11550.xml">
feces</link>.</p>
<p>

Studies of nutritional status must take into account the state of the body before and after experiments, as well as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/9722260.xml">
chemical</link> composition of the diet and the products of excretion. Comparing the food to the waste can help determine the specific compounds and elements absorbed in the body. Their effects may only be discernible after an extended period of time, during which all food and waste must be analyzed. The number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/32818.xml">
variables</link> involved in such <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/59861.xml">
experiment</link>s is high, making nutritional studies time-consuming and expensive, which explains why the science of human nutrition is still slowly evolving.</p>
<p>

In general, eating a wide variety of fresh, whole (unprocessed), foods has proven favourable compared to monotonous diets based on processed foods. In particular, the consumption of whole plant foods slows digestion and provides higher amounts, and a more favourable balance, of essential nutrients per <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/6423.xml">
Calorie</link>, resulting in better management of cell growth, maintenance, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/20369.xml">
mitosis</link> (cell division), as well as better regulation of appetite and blood sugar. Regularly scheduled meals (every few hours) have also proven more wholesome than infrequent, haphazard ones.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Nutrients </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/66575.xml">
Nutrient</link></it>
</indent>

There are seven major classes of nutrients: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/5932.xml">
carbohydrates</link> (saccharides), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
fat</link>s (triglycerides), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/140558.xml">
fiber</link> (cellulose), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/235195.xml">
minerals</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
proteins</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/32512.xml">
vitamins</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/33306.xml">
water</link>.</p>
<p>

These nutrient classes can be generally grouped into the categories of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/66575.xml">
macronutrients</link> (needed in relatively large amounts), and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/1148672.xml">
micronutrients</link> (needed in smaller quantities). The macronutrients are carbohydrates, fats, fiber, proteins and water. The other nutrient classes are micronutrients.</p>
<p>

The macronutrients (excluding fiber and water) provide <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/1369210.xml">
energy</link>, which is measured in kilocalories, often called "Calories" and written with a capital C to distinguish individual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/6423.xml">
calorie</link>s. Carbohydrates and proteins provide four (4) Calories of energy per gram, while fats provide nine (9) Calories per gram.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Vitamins, minerals, fiber, and water do not provide energy, but are necessary for other reasons.</p>
<p>

Molecules of carbohydrates and fats consist of carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen atoms. Carbohydrates may be simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/19583.xml">
monomer</link>s (glucose, fructose, galactose), or large polymers <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/23978.xml">
polysaccharides</link> (starch). Fats are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/56525.xml">
triglyceride</link>s, made of various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link> monomers bound to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/172732.xml">
glycerol</link>. Some fatty acids are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/105948.xml">
essential</link>, but not all. Protein molecules contain nitrogen atoms in addition to the elements of carbohydrates and fats. The nitrogen-containing monomers of protein, called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acids</link>, fulfill many roles other than energy metabolism, and when they are used as fuel, getting rid of the nitrogen places a burden on the kidneys. Similar to fatty acids, certain amino acids are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/102213.xml">
essential</link>.</p>
<p>

Other micronutrients not categorized above include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
antioxidants</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/472231.xml">
phytochemicals</link>.</p>
<p>

Most foods contain a mix of some or all of the nutrient classes. Some nutrients are required on a regular basis, while others are needed less frequently. Poor health can be caused by an imbalance of nutrients, whether an excess or a deficiency.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Carbohydrates</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/5932.xml">
Carbohydrate</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Calories/gram: 4</b>
<image location="right" width="150px" src="ToastsAsCheapFoodPerCalorie.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A pack of toasted bread is a cheap, high nutrient (usually unbalanced ie deficient in essential minerals and vitamins, because of removal of grain bran) food source (which also has a long shelf life).
</caption>
</image>

Carbohydrates may be classified as monosaccharides, disaccharides, or polysaccharides by the number of monomer (sugar) units they contain. They are found in large proportion in foods such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/36979.xml">
rice</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/90267.xml">
noodles</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/36969.xml">
bread</link> and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/6700.xml">
grain</link>-based products.
Monosaccharides contain 1 sugar unit, disaccharides contain 2, and polysaccharides contain 3 or more. Polysaccharides are often referred to as complex carbohydrates because they are long chains of sugar units, whereas monosaccharides and disaccharides are 
simpler. The difference is important because complex carbohydrates take longer to digest and absorb since their sugar units are processed one-by-one off the ends of the chains; the spike in blood sugar levels caused by substantial amounts of simple sugars is thought to be at least part of the cause of increased heart and vascular disease associated with high simple sugar consumption. Simple carbohydrates are absorbed quickly and thus raise blood sugar levels more rapidly.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fat</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
Fat</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Calories/gram: 9</b></p>
<p>

Fats are composed of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>s (long carbon/hydrogen chains) bonded to a glycerol; they are typically found as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/56525.xml">
triglyceride</link>s (three fatty acids attached to one glycerol backbone). Certain fatty acids are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/105948.xml">
essential</link>. Fats may be classified as saturated or unsaturated. Saturated fats have all of their carbon atoms bonded to hydrogen atoms, whereas unsaturated fats have some of their carbon atoms double-bonded in place of a hydrogen atom. In humans, multiple studies have shown that unsaturated fats are to be preferred for health reasons, particularly mono-unsaturated fats. Saturated fats, typically from animal sources, are next, while 'trans' fats are to be avoided; they have been banned in several locations (eg, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/645042.xml">
New York City</link></village>
). Saturated and trans fats are typically solid at room temperature (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/46183.xml">
butter</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/18621997.xml">
lard</link>), while unsaturated fats are typically liquids (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/295711.xml">
flaxseed oil</link>). Unsaturated fats may be further classified as monounsaturated (one double-bond) or polyunsaturated (many double-bonds). Trans fats are saturated fats but are typically created from unsaturated fat by adding the extra hydrogen atoms in an industrial process called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/235968.xml">
hydrogenation</link>; they are also called hydrogenated fat. They are very rare in nature, but have properties useful in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/602960.xml">
food processing</link> industry.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Essential fatty acids </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/105948.xml">
Essential fatty acids</link></it>
</indent>

Most <b>fatty</b> acids are non-essential, meaning the body can produce them as needed from other fats and some energy. However, in humans, at least two fatty acids are essential and must be consumed in the diet. An appropriate balance of essential fatty acids - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/22594.xml">
omega-3</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/681218.xml">
omega-6</link> fatty acids - has been discovered to be important in reducing risk of some chronic diseases and conditions. Both of these "omega" long-chain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/264748.xml">
polyunsaturated fatty acids</link> are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/529723.xml">
substrates</link> for a class of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/631312.xml">
eicosanoids</link> known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/92336.xml">
prostaglandins</link> which have uses throughout the human body; they are in some respects, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/13311.xml">
hormone</link>s. The omega-3 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/1593775.xml">
eicosapentaenoic acid</link> (EPA) (which can be made in the human body from the omega-3 essential fatty acid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/153316.xml">
alpha-linolenic acid</link> (LNA), or taken in through marine food sources), serves as a building block for series 3 prostaglandins (e.g. weakly-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/70425.xml">
inflammation</link> PGE3). The omega-6 dihomo-gamma-linolenic acid (DGLA) serves as a building block for series 1 prostaglandins (e.g. anti-inflammatory PGE1), whereas arachidonic acid (AA) serves as a building block for series 2 prostaglandins (e.g. pro-inflammatory PGE 2). Both DGLA and AA can be made from the omega-6 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/880497.xml">
linoleic acid</link> (LA) in the human body, or can be taken in directly through food. An appropriately balanced intake of omega-3 and omega-6 partly determines the relative production of different prostaglandins, which partly explains the importance of omega-3/omega-6 balance for cardiovascular health. In industrialised societies, people typically consume large amounts of processed vegetable oils that have reduced amounts of the essential fatty acids along with a too high ratio of omega-6 fatty acids relative to omega-3 fatty acids.</p>
<p>

The conversion rate of omega-6 DGLA to AA largely determines the production of the respective prostaglandins PGE1 and PGE2. Omega-3 EPA prevents AA from being released from membranes, thereby skewing prostaglandin balance away from pro-inflammatory PGE2 made from AA toward anti-inflammatory PGE1 made from DGLA. Moreover, the conversion (desaturation) of DGLA to AA is controlled by the enzyme <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/4074428.xml">
delta-5-desaturase</link>, which in turn is controlled by hormones such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/14895.xml">
insulin</link> (up-regulation) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../953/249953.xml">
glucagon</link> (down-regulation). Because the amount and type of glucose and starch )plus some amino acid types) in food affect insulin, glucagon and other hormones, not only the amount of omega-3 versus omega-6 eaten but also the general composition of the diet, are implicated in general health regarding the essential fatty acids, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/70425.xml">
inflammation</link> (e.g. immune function) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/20369.xml">
mitosis</link> (i.e. cell division).</p>
<p>

Good sources of essential fatty acids are most vegetables, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/51253.xml">
nut</link>s/seeds and marine oils,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> including: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/4699587.xml">
fish</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/38869.xml">
flax seed</link> oils, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/62784.xml">
soy bean</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/3131476.xml">
pumpkin seed</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/58706.xml">
sunflower seed</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/165140.xml">
walnut</link>s.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Fiber </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/66554.xml">
Dietary fiber</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Calories/gram:  4</b></p>
<p>

Fiber is a carbohydrate that is incompletely absorbed in humans and some animals.  Like all carbohydrates, it contains four calories per gram, but due to its limited absorption, it contributes fewer calories.  Dietary fiber consists mainly of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/6911.xml">
cellulose</link>, a large carbohydrate polymer, that is indigestible because humans do not have enzymes to digest it. There are two subcategories: soluble and insoluble fiber. The first dissolves in water; the second does not.  Whole grains, fruits (especially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/56884.xml">
plum</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/62345.xml">
prune</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/57893.xml">
fig</link>s), and vegetables are rich in dietary fiber.  Fiber is important to digestive health and is thought to reduce the risk of colon cancer.  It can benefit both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/168509.xml">
constipation</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/53951.xml">
diarrhea</link>.  Fibers provide bulk to the intestinal contents, and  insoluble fiber stimulates <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/156932.xml">
peristalsis</link>, the rhythmic muscular contractions passing along the digestive tract).  Soluble fibers, especially those with high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18963754.xml">
viscosity</link>, absorb water to form a gel that slows the movement of food through the intestines.  Fiber, especially that in whole grains, may help lessen insulin spikes and reduce the risk of diabetes.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Protein</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/6531493.xml">
Protein in nutrition</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Calories/gram: 4</b></p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="LemonChicken2.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Most <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/18940.xml">
meats</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/5741239.xml">
chicken</link> contain all the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/102213.xml">
essential amino acids</link> needed for humans.
</caption>
</image>

Proteins are the basis of animal body structures (eg, muscles, skin, hair etc.). They are composed of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acids</link>, sometimes many thousands, which are characterized by inclusion of nitrogen and sometimes sulphur. The body requires amino acids to produce new body protein (protein retention) and to replace damaged proteins (maintenance). Amino acids not needed are discarded, typically in the urine. In animals, amino acid requirements are classified in terms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/102213.xml">
essential</link> (an animal cannot produce them internally) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/102213.xml">
non-essential</link> (the animal can produce them from other nitrogen containing compounds) amino acids. Humans use about 20 amino acids, and about ten are essential in this sense. Consuming a diet that contains adequate amounts of essential (but also non-essential) amino acids is particularly important for growing, pregnant, nursing, or injured animals, all of whom have a particularly high requirement. Protein nutrition which contains the essential amino acids is a complete protein source, one missing one or more is called incomplete. It's possible to combine two incomplete protein sources (eg, rice and beans) to make a complete protein source. Dietary sources of protein include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/18940.xml">
meat</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/19371045.xml">
tofu</link> and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/62784.xml">
soy</link>-products, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/19196010.xml">
eggs</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/6700.xml">
grain</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/305286.xml">
legume</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/8097.xml">
dairy product</link>s such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/19714.xml">
milk</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/11749910.xml">
cheese</link>. A few amino acids from protein can be converted into glucose and used for fuel through a process called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/248671.xml">
gluconeogenesis</link>. The remaining amino acids are discarded.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Minerals</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/235195.xml">
Dietary mineral</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Calories/gram: 0</b></p>
<p>

Dietary minerals are the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/5659.xml">
chemical element</link>s required by living organisms, other than the four elements <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/5299.xml">
carbon</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/13255.xml">
hydrogen</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/21175.xml">
nitrogen</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/22303.xml">
oxygen</link> which are present in common <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/22208.xml">
organic molecules</link>. The term "mineral" is archaic, since the intent of the definition is to describe ions, not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/144412.xml">
chemical compound</link>s or actual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/19053.xml">
mineral</link>s. Some dietitians recommend that these heavier elements should be supplied by ingesting specific foods (that are enriched in the element(s) of interest), compounds, and sometimes including even minerals, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/44731.xml">
calcium carbonate</link>. Sometimes these "minerals" come from natural sources such as ground <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/133824.xml">
oyster</link> shells. Sometimes minerals are added to the diet separately from food, such as mineral supplements, the most famous being iodine in "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/1232890.xml">
iodized salt</link>".</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Macrominerals</st>

<p>

A variety of elements are required to support the biochemical processes, many play a role as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/48336.xml">
electrolyte</link>s or in a structural role.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> In human nutrition, the dietary bulk "mineral elements" (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/396054.xml">
RDA</link> &amp;gt; 200 mg/day) are in alphabetical order (parenthetical comments on folk medicine perspective):
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/5668.xml">
Calcium</link> (for muscle and digestive system health, builds bone, neutralizes acidity, clears toxins, helps blood stream)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/66269.xml">
Chloride</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/18909.xml">
Magnesium</link> required for processing ATP and related reactions (health, builds bone, causes strong peristalsis, increases flexibility, increases alkalinity)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/23318.xml">
Phosphorus</link> required component of bones (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/140627.xml">
apatite</link>) and energy processing and many other functions (bone mineralization)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/23055.xml">
Potassium</link> required <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/48336.xml">
electrolyte</link> (heart and nerves health)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/26826.xml">
Sodium</link> electrolyte</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/27127.xml">
Sulfur</link> for three essential amino acids and many proteins and cofactors (skin, hair, nails, liver, and pancreas health)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Trace minerals</st>

<p>

A variety of elements are required in trace amounts, unusually because they play a role in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/5914.xml">
catalysis</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/9257.xml">
enzymes</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Some trace mineral elements (RDA  200 mg/day) are (alphabetical order):</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ium/6th_millennium.xml">
Cobalt</link> required for biosynthesis of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/14538619.xml">
vitamin B12</link> family of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/81654.xml">
coenzyme</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/125293.xml">
Copper</link> required component of many redox enzymes, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/96842.xml">
cytochrome c oxidase</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/5669.xml">
Chromium</link> required for sugar metabolism</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/14750.xml">
Iodine</link> required for the biosynthesis of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/144893.xml">
thyroxin</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/14734.xml">
Iron</link> required for many proteins and enzymes, notably <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/13483.xml">
hemoglobin</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/19051.xml">
Manganese</link> (processing of oxygen)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/19052.xml">
Molybdenum</link> required for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/97644.xml">
xanthine oxidase</link> and related oxidases</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/21274.xml">
Nickel</link> present in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/169123.xml">
urease</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/27117.xml">
Selenium</link>  required for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/92532.xml">
peroxidase</link> (antioxidant proteins)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/32431.xml">
Vanadium</link> (There is no established RDA for vanadium. No specific biochemical function has been identified for it in humans, although vanadium is found in lower organisms.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/34420.xml">
Zinc</link> required for several enzymes such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/5574263.xml">
carboxypeptidase</link>, <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<enzyme wordnetid="114732946" confidence="0.8">
<compound wordnetid="114818238" confidence="0.8">
<protein wordnetid="114728724" confidence="0.8">
<macromolecule wordnetid="114944888" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<activator wordnetid="114723079" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<organic_compound wordnetid="114727670" confidence="0.8">
<molecule wordnetid="114682133" confidence="0.8">
<catalyst wordnetid="114723628" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/89198.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22In_humans%22])">
liver alcohol dehydrogenase</link></material>
</catalyst>
</molecule>
</organic_compound>
</part>
</activator>
</chemical>
</macromolecule>
</protein>
</compound>
</enzyme>
</substance>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/434826.xml">
carbonic anhydrase</link>.  Zinc is pervasive.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Iodine is required in larger quantities than the other trace minerals in this list and is sometimes classified with the bulk minerals.  Sodium is not generally found in dietary supplements, despite being needed in large quantities, because the ion is very common in food.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Vitamins</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/32512.xml">
Vitamin</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Calories/gram: 0</b></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/235195.xml">
Mineral</link> and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/32512.xml">
vitamin</link> deficiency or excess may result in disease conditions such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/12265.xml">
goitre</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/28266.xml">
scurvy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/22461.xml">
osteoporosis</link>, impaired <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/14958.xml">
immune system</link>, disorders of cell <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/20374.xml">
metabolism</link>, certain forms of cancer, symptoms of premature <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/16413778.xml">
aging</link>, and poor <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
psychological health</link> (including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/56825.xml">
eating disorders</link>), among many others.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

As of 2005, twelve vitamins and about the same number of minerals are recognized as "essential nutrients", meaning that they must be consumed and absorbed&mdash;or, in the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/54106.xml">
vitamin D</link>, alternatively synthesized in the skin via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/31990.xml">
UVB radiation</link> to prevent deficiency symptoms and possibly death. Certain vitamin-like substances found in foods, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/271056.xml">
carnitine</link>, have also been found essential to survival and health, but these are not strictly "essential" to eat because the human body can produce them from other compounds. Moreover, thousands of different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/472231.xml">
phytochemicals</link> have recently been discovered in food (particularly in fresh vegetables), which may have desirable properties including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
antioxidant</link> activity (see below). Other essential nutrients include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/102213.xml">
essential amino acid</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/158799.xml">
choline</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/105948.xml">
essential fatty acid</link>s.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Water </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="TapWater-china.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A manual water <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/23617.xml">
pump</link> in China
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/198725.xml">
Drinking water</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Calories/gram: 0</b></p>
<p>

About 70% of the non-fat mass of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/682482.xml">
human</link> body is made of water. To function properly, the body requires between one and seven <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../094/18094.xml">
liter</link>s of water per <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/8376.xml">
day</link> to avoid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/155056.xml">
dehydration</link>; the precise amount depends on the level of activity, temperature, humidity, and other factors.  With physical exertion and heat exposure, water loss will increase and daily fluid needs may increase as well.</p>
<p>

It is not clear how much water intake is needed by healthy people, although some experts assert that 8–10 glasses of water (approximately 2 liters) daily is the minimum to maintain proper hydration.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> The notion that a person should consume eight glasses of water per day cannot be traced back to a scientific source.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> The effect of water intake on weight loss and on constipation is also still unclear.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> Original recommendation for water intake in 1945 by the <link>
Food and Nutrition Board</link> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/501503.xml">
National Research Council</link> read: "An ordinary standard for diverse persons is 1 milliliter for each calorie of food. Most of this quantity is contained in prepared foods."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> The latest dietary reference intake report by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/37638.xml">
United States National Research Council</link> in general recommended (including food sources): 2.7 liters of water total for women and 3.7 liters for men.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Specifically, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1771587.xml">
pregnant</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/19347033.xml">
breastfeeding</link> women need additional fluids to stay hydrated. According to the <institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<academy wordnetid="108279298" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/431259.xml">
Institute of Medicine</link></academy>
</institution>
&mdash;who recommend that, on average, women consume 2.2 litres and men 3.0 litres&mdash;this is recommended to be 2.4 litres (approx. 9 cups) for pregnant women and 3 litres (approx. 12.5 cups) for breastfeeding women since an especially large amount of fluid is lost during nursing.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> </p>
<p>

For those who have healthy kidneys, it is rather difficult to drink too much water, but (especially in warm humid weather and while exercising) it is dangerous to drink too little. People can drink far more water than necessary while exercising, however, putting them at risk of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/1140141.xml">
water intoxication</link>, which can be fatal. In particular large amounts of de-ionized water are dangerous.</p>
<p>

Normally, about 20 percent of water intake comes in food, while the rest comes from drinking water and assorted beverages (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/6868.xml">
caffeinated</link> included). Water is excreted from the body in multiple forms; including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/3938382.xml">
urine</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/11550.xml">
feces</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/77538.xml">
sweat</link>ing, and by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/89547.xml">
water vapor</link> in the exhaled breath.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Other nutrients </st>

<p>

<b>Calories/gram: 0</b></p>
<p>

Other micronutrients include antioxidants and phytochemicals. These substances are generally more recent discoveries which: have not yet been recognized as vitamins; are still under investigation; or contribute to health but are not necessary for life. Phytochemicals may act as antioxidants, but not all phytochemicals are antioxidants.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Antioxidants </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
Antioxidant</link></it>
</indent>

Antioxidants are a recent discovery. As cellular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/20374.xml">
metabolism</link>/energy production requires oxygen, potentially damaging (e.g. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/19702.xml">
mutation</link> causing) compounds known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/235028.xml">
free radicals</link> can form. Most of these are oxidizers 9ie, (acceptors of electrons) and some react very strongly. For normal cellular maintenance, growth, and division, these free radicals must be sufficiently neutralized by antioxidant compounds. Some are produced by the human body with adequate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/10940802.xml">
precursors</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/81625.xml">
glutathione</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/32509.xml">
Vitamin C</link> )and those that the body cannot produce may only be obtained through the diet through direct sources (Vitamin C in humans, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/54114.xml">
Vitamin A</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/32541.xml">
Vitamin K</link>) or produced by the body from other compounds (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/579219.xml">
Beta-carotene</link> converted to Vitamin A by the body, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/54106.xml">
Vitamin D</link> synthesized from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/6437.xml">
cholesterol</link> by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/27979.xml">
sunlight</link>). Phytochemicals (<it>Section Below</it>) and their subgroup polyphenols are the majority of antioxidants; about 4,000 are known.  Different antioxidants are now known to function in a cooperative network, e.g. vitamin C can reactivate free radical-containing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/81625.xml">
glutathione</link> or vitamin E by accepting the free radical itself, and so on. Some antioxidants are more effective than others at neutralizing different free radicals. Some cannot neutralize certain free radicals. Some cannot be present in certain areas of free radical development (Vitamin A is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/596745.xml">
fat-soluble</link> and protects fat areas, Vitamin C is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/33306.xml">
water</link> soluble and protects those areas). When interacting with a free radical, some antioxidants produce a different free radical compound that is less dangerous or more dangerous than the previous compound. Having a variety of antioxidants allows any byproducts to be safely dealt with by more efficient antioxidants in neutralizing a free radical's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/4024.xml">
butterfly effect</link>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Phytochemicals </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/472231.xml">
Phytochemical</link></it>
</indent>

<image width="200px" src="Blackberry_fruits10.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>

A growing area of interest is the effect upon human health of trace chemicals, collectively called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/472231.xml">
phytochemicals</link>.  These nutrients are typically found in edible plants, especially colorful fruits and vegetables, but also other organisms including seafood, algae, and fungi. The effects of phytochemicals increasingly survive rigorous testing by prominent health organizations.  One of the principal classes of phytochemicals are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/5538293.xml">
polyphenol antioxidant</link>s, chemicals which are known to provide certain health benefits to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/7256.xml">
cardiovascular system</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/14958.xml">
immune system</link>.  These chemicals are known to down-regulate the formation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/640697.xml">
reactive oxygen species</link>, key chemicals in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/512662.xml">
cardiovascular disease</link>.</p>
<p>

Perhaps the most rigorously tested phytochemical is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/2752172.xml">
zeaxanthin</link>, a yellow-pigmented carotenoid present in many yellow and orange fruits and vegetables. Repeated studies have shown a strong correlation between ingestion of zeaxanthin and the prevention and treatment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/895033.xml">
age-related macular degeneration</link> (AMD).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> Less rigorous studies have proposed a correlation between zeaxanthin intake and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/88931.xml">
cataracts</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> A second carotenoid, lutein, has also been shown to lower the risk of contracting AMD. Both compounds have been observed to collect in the retina when ingested orally, and they serve to protect the rods and cones against the destructive effects of light.</p>
<p>

Another carotenoid, beta-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/8720014.xml">
cryptoxanthin</link>, appears to protect against chronic joint inflammatory diseases, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/1776.xml">
arthritis</link>. While the association between serum blood levels of beta-cryptoxanthin and substantially decreased joint disease has been established, neither a convincing mechanism for such protection nor a cause-and-effect have been rigorously studied.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> Similarly, a red phytochemical, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/18735.xml">
lycopene</link>, has substantial credible evidence of negative association with development of prostate cancer.</p>
<p>

The correlations between the ingestion of some phytochemicals and the prevention of disease are, in some cases, enormous in magnitude.</p>
<p>

Even when the evidence is obtained, translating it to practical dietary advice can be difficult and counter-intuitive. Lutein, for example, occurs in many yellow and orange fruits and vegetables and protects the eyes against various diseases. However, it does not protect the eye nearly as well as zeaxanthin, and the presence of lutein in the retina will prevent zeaxanthin uptake. Additionally, evidence has shown that the lutein present in egg yolk is more readily absorbed than the lutein from vegetable sources, possibly because of fat solubility.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> At the most basic level, the question "should you eat eggs?" is complex to the point of dismay, including misperceptions about the health effects of cholesterol in egg yolk, and its saturated fat content.</p>
<p>

As another example, lycopene is prevalent in tomatoes (and actually is the chemical that gives tomatoes their red color). It is more highly concentrated, however, in processed tomato products such as commercial pasta sauce, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/3671251.xml">
tomato soup</link>, than in fresh "healthy" tomatoes. Yet, such sauces tend to have high amounts of salt, sugar, other substances a person may wish or even need to avoid. </p>
<p>

The following table presents phytochemical groups and common sources, arranged by family: 
<table class="wikitable">
<header>
Family</header>
<header>
Sources</header>
<header>
Possible Benefits</header>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/292340.xml">
flavonoid</link>s</col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/52948.xml">
berries</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/13296.xml">
herbs</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/5791492.xml">
vegetables</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/32961.xml">
wine</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/12436.xml">
grapes</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/29969.xml">
tea</link></col>
<col>
general <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
antioxidant</link>, oxidation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/51521.xml">
LDL</link>s, prevention of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/188288.xml">
arteriosclerosis</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/69276.xml">
heart disease</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/1931422.xml">
isoflavone</link>s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/912933.xml">
phytoestrogens</link>)</col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/62784.xml">
soy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/1900302.xml">
red clover</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/57866.xml">
kudzu root</link></col>
<col>
general <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
antioxidant</link>, prevention of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/188288.xml">
arteriosclerosis</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/69276.xml">
heart disease</link>, easing symptoms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/49611.xml">
menopause</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer prevention</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/377230.xml">
isothiocyanate</link>s</col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/4175726.xml">
cruciferous vegetables</link></col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer prevention</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/5901148.xml">
monoterpene</link>s</col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/52136.xml">
citrus</link> peels, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/281028.xml">
essential oil</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/13296.xml">
herbs</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/26897.xml">
spices</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/23208.xml">
green plants</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/202899.xml">
atmosphere</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer prevention</link>, treating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/287531.xml">
gallstones</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/1959215.xml">
organosulfur compounds</link></col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/5395.xml">
chives</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/50469.xml">
garlic</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/51258.xml">
onion</link>s</col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer prevention</link>, lowered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/51521.xml">
LDL</link>s, assistance to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/14958.xml">
immune system</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/591668.xml">
saponin</link>s</col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/4487.xml">
bean</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/6700.xml">
cereal</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/13296.xml">
herbs</link></col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/513039.xml">
Hypercholesterolemia</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/78226.xml">
Hyperglycemia</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
Antioxidant</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer prevention</link>, 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/726241.xml">
Anti-inflammatory</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/57421.xml">
capsaicinoid</link>s</col>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/74225.xml">
all <it>capiscum</it> (chile) peppers</link></col>
<col>
topical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/417111.xml">
pain relief</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer prevention</link>, cancer cell <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
apoptosis</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Intestinal bacterial flora</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/3135637.xml">
Gut flora</link></it>
</indent>
It is now also known that animal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/61343.xml">
intestine</link>s contain a large population of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/3135637.xml">
gut flora</link>. In humans, these include species such as <it><microorganism wordnetid="101326291" confidence="0.8">
<bacteria wordnetid="101348530" confidence="0.8">
<anaerobe wordnetid="101327028" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/4350782.xml">
Bacteroides</link></anaerobe>
</bacteria>
</microorganism>
</it>, <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/3991575.xml">
L. acidophilus</link></it> and <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. coli</link></it>, among many others. They are essential to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/165423.xml">
digestion</link>, and are also affected by the food we eat.  Bacteria in the gut perform many important functions for humans, including breaking down and aiding in the absorption of otherwise indigestible food; stimulating cell growth; repressing the growth of harmful bacteria, training the immune system to respond only to pathogens; producing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/14538619.xml">
vitamin B12</link>, and defending against some infectious diseases.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Balanced diet</st>
<p>

Balanced diet is a diet which consists of all the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/529854.xml">
essential nutrient</link>s in a required proportion .</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Junk food</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/64083.xml">
Junk food</link> is a slang name for food items containing limited nutritional value.  It includes food high in salts, fats, sugar, calories, and low nutrient content.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Sports nutrition </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/6112487.xml">
Sports nutrition</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Protein</st>
<p>

The protein requirements of athletes, once the source of great controversy, has settled into a current consensus.  Sedentary people and recreational athletes<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> have similar protein requirements, about 1 gram of protein per kilogram of body mass. These needs are easily met by a balanced diet containing about 70 grams of protein for a 70 kg (150 pound) man or 60 grams of protein for a 60 kg (130 pound) woman.</p>
<p>

People who exercise at greater intensity, and especially those whose activity grows muscle bulk, have significantly higher protein requirements.  According to <it>Clinical Sports Nutrition</it> (see footnote above), active athletes playing power sports (such as football), those engaged in muscle-development training, and elite endurance athletes, all require approximately 2 grams of protein per day per kilogram of body weight, roughly double that of a sedentary persons.  Older athletes seeking primarily to maintain developed muscle mass require 2 to 3 g per day per kg. </p>
<p>

Protein intake in excess of that required to build muscle (and other) tissue is broken-down by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/248671.xml">
gluconeogenesis</link> to be used as energy.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Water and salts</st>
<p>

Water is one of the most important nutrients in your sports diet. It helps eliminate food waste products in your body, regulates body temperature during activity, helps digest, is involved in converting food into energy and helps lubricate joints<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref>. Athletes should drink as much water as they comfortably can. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref>
Maintaining hydration during periods of physical exertion is key to peak performance. While drinking too much water during activities can lead to physical discomfort, dehydration in excess of 2% of body mass (by weight) markedly hinders athletic performance. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> Some studies have shown that an athlete that drinks before they feel thirsty stays cooler and performs better than one who drinks on thirst cues, although recent studies of such races as the Boston Marathon have indicated that this recommendation can lead to the problem of overhydration. Additional carbohydrates and protein before, during, and after exercise increase time to exhaustion as well as speed recovery. Dosage is based on work performed, lean body mass, and environmental factors, especially ambient temperature and humidity.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Carbohydrates</st>
<p>

The main fuel used by the body during exercise is carbohydrates, which is stored in muscle as glycogen- a form of sugar.  During exercise, muscle glycogen reserves can be used up, especially when activities last longer than 90 min. Because the amount of glycogen stored in the body is limited, it is important for athletes to replace glycogen by consuming a diet high in carbohydrates.  Meeting energy needs can help improve performance during the sport, as well as improve overall strength and endurance.
There are different kinds of carbohydrates--simple or refined, and unrefined.  A typical American consumes about 50% of their carbohydrates as simple sugars, which are added to foods as opposed to sugars that come naturally in fruits and vegetables.  These simple sugars come in large amounts in sodas and fast food.  Over the course of a year, the average American consumes 54 gallons of soft drinks, which contain the highest amount of added sugars.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>  Even though carbohydrates are necessary for humans to function, they are not all equally healthful.  When machinery has been used to remove bits of high fiber, the carbohydrates are refined.  These are the carbohydrates found in white bread and fast food.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Longevity</st>


<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/1581671.xml">
Healthy diet</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Whole plant food diet</st>

<p>

Heart disease, cancer, obesity, and diabetes are commonly called "Western" diseases because these maladies were once rarely seen in developing countries.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/3809742.xml">
One study in China</link> found some regions had essentially no cancer or heart disease, while in other areas they reflected "up to a 100-fold increase" coincident with diets that were found to be entirely plant-based to heavily animal-based, respectively.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref>  In contrast, diseases of affluence like cancer and heart disease are common throughout the United States.  Adjusted for age and exercise, large regional clusters of people in China rarely suffered from these "Western" diseases possibly because their diets are rich in vegetables, fruits and whole grains.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref></p>
<p>

The United Healthcare/Pacificare nutrition guideline recommends a whole plant food diet, and recommends using protein only as a condiment with meals.  A <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/21550.xml">
National Geographic</link></it> cover article from November, 2005, entitled <it>The Secrets of Living Longer</it>, also recommends a whole plant food diet. The article is a lifestyle survey of three populations, <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/29376.xml">
Sardinia</link></region>
ns, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/22477.xml">
Okinawa</link>ns, and <denomination wordnetid="108146782" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/28632.xml">
Adventist</link></denomination>
s, who generally display longevity and "suffer a fraction of the diseases that commonly kill people in other parts of the developed world, and enjoy more healthy years of life. In sum, they offer three sets of 'best practices' to emulate.  The rest is up to you." In common with all three groups is to "Eat fruits, vegetables, and whole grains."</p>
<p>

The <it>National Geographic</it> article noted that an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/46174.xml">
NIH</link> funded study of 34,000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/28632.xml">
Seventh-day Adventist</link>s between 1976 and 1988 "...found that the Adventists' habit of consuming beans, soy milk, tomatoes, and other fruits lowered their risk of developing certain cancers.  It also suggested that eating whole grain bread, drinking five glasses of water a day, and, most surprisingly, consuming four servings of nuts a week reduced their risk of heart disease."</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The French "paradox"</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/319138.xml">
French paradox</link></it>
</indent>
It has been discovered that people living in France live longer. Even though they consume more saturated fats than Americans, the rate of heart disease is lower in France than in North America.  A number of explanations have been suggested:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reduced consumption of processed carbohydrate and other junk foods;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ethnic genetic differences allowing the body to be harmed less by fats;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Regular consumption of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/32961.xml">
red wine</link>; or</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Living in the South requires the body to produce less heat, allowing a slower, and therefore healthier, metabolic rate. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 More active lifestyles involving plenty of daily exercise, especially walking; the French are much less dependent on cars than Americans are.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Higher consumption of artificially produced trans-fats by Americans, which has been shown to have greater lipoprotein impacts per gram than saturated fat.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

However, a growing number of French health researchers doubt the theory that the French are healthier than other populations. Statistics collected by the WHO from 1990-2000 show that the incidence of heart disease in France may have been underestimated and in fact be similar to that of neighboring countries.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Malnutrition </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/258979.xml">
Malnutrition</link></it>
</indent>

Malnutrition refers to insufficient, excessive, or imbalanced consumption of nutrients. In developed countries, the diseases of malnutrition are most often associated with nutritional imbalances or excessive consumption.
Although there are more people in the world who are malnourished due to excessive consumption, according to the United Nations <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/33583.xml">
World Health Organization</link></organization>
, the real challenge in developing nations today, more than starvation, is combating insufficient nutrition — the lack of nutrients necessary for the growth and maintenance of vital functions. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Illnesses caused by improper nutrient consumption</st>
<p>

<table class="wikitable" bgcolor="black">
<row>
<header>
NUTRIENTS</header>
<header>
DEFICIENCY</header>
<header>
EXCESS</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/6423.xml">
Calories</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/215891.xml">
Starvation</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/56435.xml">
Obesity</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/44677.xml">
diabetes mellitus</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/512662.xml">
Cardiovascular disease</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/19919.xml">
Simple carbohydrates</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/556521.xml">
Marasmus</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/215891.xml">
starvation</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/44677.xml">
diabetes mellitus</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/23978.xml">
Complex carbohydrates</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/556521.xml">
Marasmus</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/215891.xml">
starvation</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/56435.xml">
Obesity</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/264746.xml">
Saturated fat</link> / <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/263487.xml">
trans fat</link></col>
<col>
none</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/512662.xml">
Cardiovascular disease</link>,</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/264748.xml">
Unsaturated fat</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/3099997.xml">
Rabbit starvation</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/56435.xml">
Obesity</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/6437.xml">
Cholesterol</link></col>
<col>
none</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/512662.xml">
Cardiovascular disease</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
Protein</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/556521.xml">
Marasmus</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/537792.xml">
Ketoacidosis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/3099997.xml">
Rabbit starvation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/284027.xml">
kidney disease</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/26826.xml">
Sodium</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/190961.xml">
hyponatremia</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/996303.xml">
Hypernatremia</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/77432.xml">
hypertension</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/14734.xml">
Iron</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/83537.xml">
Anemia</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/71491.xml">
Hepatitis C</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/37060.xml">
cirrhosis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/69276.xml">
heart disease</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/14750.xml">
Iodine</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/12265.xml">
Goiter</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/65845.xml">
hypothyroidism</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/14750.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Toxicity+of+iodine+%22])">
 Iodine Toxicity</link>(goiter, hypothyroidism)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/54114.xml">
Vitamin A</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/1434577.xml">
Xerophthalmia</link>and Night Blindness</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/2941264.xml">
Hypervitaminosis A</link>(cirrhosis, hair loss, birth defects)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Vitamin B1</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/217881.xml">
Beri-Beri</link></col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/26229.xml">
 Vitamin B2 </link></col>
<col>
Cracking of skin and Corneal Unclearation</col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/37996.xml">
Niacin</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/355776.xml">
Pellagra</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/1231986.xml">
dyspepsia</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/5562.xml">
cardiac arrhythmias</link>, birth defects</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/14538619.xml">
 Vitamin B12 </link></col>
<col>
Pernicious Anemia</col>

</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/32509.xml">
Vitamin C</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/28266.xml">
Scurvy</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/53951.xml">
diarrhea</link> causing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/155056.xml">
dehydration</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/54106.xml">
Vitamin D</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/25987.xml">
Rickets</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/2941266.xml">
Hypervitaminosis D</link>(dehydration, vomiting, constipation)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/54104.xml">
Vitamin E</link></col>

<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../588/14410588.xml">
Hypervitaminosis E</link>(anticoagulant: excessive bleeding)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/32541.xml">
Vitamin K</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/146315.xml">
Hemorrhage</link></col>

</row>
</table>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Mental agility </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/685457.xml">
Nootropic</link></it>
</indent>

Research indicates that improving the awareness of nutritious meal choices and establishing long-term habits of healthy eating has a positive effect on a cognitive and spatial memory capacity, potentially increasing a student's potential to process and retain academic information.</p>
<p>

Some organizations have begun working with teachers, policymakers, and managed foodservice contractors to mandate improved nutritional content and increased nutritional resources in school cafeterias from primary to university level institutions.  Health and nutrition have been proven to have close links with overall educational success (Behrman, 1996). Currently less than 10% of American college students report that they eat the recommended five servings of fruit and vegetables daily.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref>  Better nutrition has been shown to have an impact on both cognitive and spatial memory performance; a study showed those with higher blood sugar levels performed better on certain memory tests.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref>  In another study, those who consumed yogurt performed better on thinking tasks when compared to those who consumed caffeine free diet soda or confections.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> Nutritional deficiencies have been shown to have a negative effect on learning behavior in mice as far back as 1951.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

"Better learning performance is associated with diet induced effects on learning and memory ability".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref>
</indent>

The "nutrition-learning nexus" demonstrates the correlation between diet and learning and has application in a higher education setting. </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

"We find that better nourished children perform significantly better in school, partly because they enter school earlier and thus have more time to learn but mostly because of greater learning productivity per year of schooling."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

91% of college students feel that they are in good health while only 7% eat their recommended daily allowance of fruits and vegetables.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref> 
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Nutritional education is an effective and workable model in a higher education setting.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

More "engaged" learning models that encompass nutrition is an idea that is picking up steam at all levels of the learning cycle.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref>
</indent>

There is limited research available that directly links a student's Grade Point Average (G.P.A.) to their overall nutritional health.  Additional substantive data is needed to prove beyond a shadow of a doubt that overall intellectual health is closely linked to a person's diet, rather than just another <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/39834.xml">
correlation fallacy</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Mental disorders </st>
<p>

Nutritional supplement treatment may be appropriate for major <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/8389.xml">
depression</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/4531.xml">
bipolar disorder</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/27790.xml">
schizophrenia</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/54393.xml">
obsessive compulsive disorder</link>, the four most common mental disorders in developed countries.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Cancer </st>

<p>

Cancer is now common in developing countries.  According a study by the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/1855289.xml">
International Agency for Research on Cancer</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
, "In the developing world, cancers of the liver, stomach and esophagus were more common, often linked to consumption of carcinogenic preserved foods, such as smoked or salted food, and parasitic infections that attack organs."  Lung cancer rates are rising rapidly in poorer nations because of increased use of tobacco.  Developed countries "tended to have cancers linked to affluence or a 'Western lifestyle' – cancers of the colon, rectum, breast and prostate – that can be caused by obesity, lack of exercise, diet and age."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Metabolic syndrome </st>

<p>

Several lines of evidence indicate lifestyle-induced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/1609070.xml">
hyperinsulinemia</link> and reduced insulin function (i.e. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/54448.xml">
insulin resistance</link>) as a decisive factor in many disease states. For example, hyperinsulinemia and insulin resistance are strongly linked to chronic inflammation, which in turn is strongly linked to a variety of adverse developments such as arterial microinjuries and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/183058.xml">
clot</link> formation (i.e. heart disease) and exaggerated cell division (i.e. cancer). Hyperinsulinemia and insulin resistance (the so-called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/54439.xml">
metabolic syndrome</link>) are characterized by a combination of abdominal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/56435.xml">
obesity</link>, elevated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/289406.xml">
blood sugar</link>, elevated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/56558.xml">
blood pressure</link>, elevated blood <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/56525.xml">
triglycerides</link>, and reduced HDL <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/6437.xml">
cholesterol</link>. The negative impact of hyperinsulinemia on prostaglandin PGE1/PGE2 balance may be significant.</p>
<p>

The state of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/56435.xml">
obesity</link> clearly contributes to insulin resistance, which in turn can cause <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/154502.xml">
type 2 diabetes</link>. Virtually all obese and most type 2 diabetic individuals have marked insulin resistance. Although the association between overweight and insulin resistance is clear, the exact (likely multifarious) causes of insulin resistance remain less clear. Importantly, it has been demonstrated that appropriate exercise, more regular food intake and reducing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/1074264.xml">
glycemic load</link> (see below) all can reverse insulin resistance in overweight individuals (and thereby lower blood sugar levels in those who have type 2 diabetes).</p>
<p>

Obesity can unfavourably alter hormonal and metabolic status via resistance to the hormone <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/214938.xml">
leptin</link>, and a vicious cycle may occur in which insulin/leptin resistance and obesity aggravate one another. The vicious cycle is putatively fuelled by continuously high insulin/leptin stimulation and fat storage, as a result of high intake of strongly insulin/leptin stimulating foods and energy. Both insulin and leptin normally function as satiety signals to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/58685.xml">
hypothalamus</link> in the brain; however, insulin/leptin resistance may reduce this signal and therefore allow continued overfeeding despite large body fat stores. In addition, reduced leptin signalling to the brain may reduce leptin's normal effect to maintain an appropriately high metabolic rate.</p>
<p>

There is a debate about how and to what extent different dietary factors&mdash; such as intake of processed carbohydrates, total protein, fat, and carbohydrate intake, intake of saturated and trans fatty acids, and low intake of vitamins/minerals&mdash;contribute to the development of insulin and leptin resistance. In any case, analogous to the way modern man-made pollution may potentially overwhelm the environment's ability to maintain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/13980.xml">
homeostasis</link>, the recent explosive introduction of high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/404226.xml">
glycemic index</link> and processed foods into the human diet may potentially overwhelm the body's ability to maintain homeostasis and health (as evidenced by the metabolic syndrome epidemic).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Hyponatremia </st>

<p>

Excess water intake, without replenishment of sodium and potassium salts, leads to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/190961.xml">
hyponatremia</link>, which can further lead to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/1140141.xml">
water intoxication</link> at more dangerous levels.  A well-publicized case occurred in 2007, when Jennifer Strange died while participating in a water-drinking contest.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2237%22])">37</ref> More usually, the condition occurs in long-distance endurance events (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/49132.xml">
marathon</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/31524.xml">
triathlon</link> competition and training) and causes gradual mental dulling, headache, drowsiness, weakness,  and confusion; extreme cases may result in coma, convulsions, and death.  The primary damage comes from swelling of the brain, caused by increased osmosis as blood salinity decreases.
Effective fluid replacement techniques include Water aid stations during running/cycling races, trainers providing water during team games such as Soccer and devices such as Camel Baks which can provide water for a person without making it too hard to drink the water.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Processed foods </st>


<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/602960.xml">
Food processing</link></it>
</indent>

Since the <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/14914.xml">
Industrial Revolution</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
 some two hundred years ago, the food processing industry has invented many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/29816.xml">
technologies</link> that both help keep foods fresh longer and alter the fresh state of food as they appear in nature. Cooling is the primary technology used to maintain freshness, whereas many more technologies have been invented to allow foods to last longer without becoming spoiled. These latter technologies include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/23311.xml">
pasteurisation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/251401.xml">
autoclavation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/3128803.xml">
drying</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/26842.xml">
salting</link>, and separation of various components, and all appear to alter the original nutritional contents of food. Pasteurisation and autoclavation (heating techniques) have no doubt improved the safety of many common foods, preventing epidemics of bacterial infection. But some of the (new) food processing technologies undoubtedly have downfalls as well.</p>
<p>

Modern separation techniques such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/2163062.xml">
milling</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/286021.xml">
centrifugation</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/238029.xml">
pressing</link> have enabled upconcentration of particular components of food, yielding flour, oils, juices and so on, and even separate fatty acids, amino acids, vitamins, and minerals. Inevitably, such large scale upconcentration changes the nutritional content of food, saving certain nutrients while removing others. Heating techniques may also reduce food's content of many heat-labile nutrients such as certain vitamins and phytochemicals, and possibly other yet to be discovered substances.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2238%22])">38</ref> Because of reduced nutritional value, processed foods are often 'enriched' or 'fortified' with some of the most critical nutrients (usually certain vitamins) that were lost during processing. Nonetheless, processed foods tend to have an inferior nutritional profile compared to whole, fresh foods, regarding content of both sugar and high GI starches, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/23055.xml">
potassium</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/26826.xml">
sodium</link>, vitamins, fibre, and of intact, unoxidized (essential) fatty acids. In addition,
processed foods often contain potentially harmful substances such as oxidized fats and trans fatty acids.</p>
<p>

A dramatic example of the effect of food processing on a population's health is the history of epidemics of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/217881.xml">
beri-beri</link> in people subsisting on polished rice. Removing the outer layer of rice by polishing it removes with it the essential vitamin <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/30500.xml">
thiamine</link>, causing beri-beri. Another example is the development of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/28266.xml">
scurvy</link> among infants in the late 1800s in the United States. It turned out that the vast majority of sufferers were being fed milk that had been heat-treated (as suggested by <link>
Pasteur</link>) to control bacterial disease. Pasteurisation was effective against bacteria, but it destroyed the vitamin C.</p>
<p>

As mentioned, lifestyle- and obesity-related diseases are becoming increasingly prevalent all around the world. There is little doubt that the increasingly widespread application of some modern food processing technologies has contributed to this development. The food processing industry is a major part of modern economy, and as such it is influential in political decisions (e.g. nutritional recommendations, agricultural subsidising). In any known profit-driven economy, health considerations are hardly a priority; effective production of cheap foods with a long shelf-life is more the trend. In general, whole, fresh foods have a relatively short shelf-life and are less profitable to produce and sell than are more processed foods. Thus the consumer is left with the choice between more expensive but nutritionally superior whole, fresh foods, and cheap, usually nutritionally inferior processed foods. Because processed foods are often cheaper, more convenient (in both purchasing, storage, and preparation), and more available, the consumption of nutritionally inferior foods has been increasing throughout the world along with many nutrition-related health complications.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Advice and guidance </st>

<ss1>
<st>
Governmental policies</st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="MyPyramid1.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

The updated <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/70896.xml">
USDA</link></agency>
 <solid wordnetid="113860793" confidence="0.8">
<pyramid wordnetid="113914837" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<polyhedron wordnetid="113883885" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/1764517.xml">
food pyramid</link></polyhedron>
</shape>
</pyramid>
</solid>
, published in 2005, is a general nutrition guide for recommended <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/10646.xml">
food</link> consumption for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/682482.xml">
humans</link>.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

In the US, "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dietitian">
dietitians</weblink>". are registered (RD) or licensed (LD) with the Commission for Dietetic Registration and the American Dietetic Association, and are only able to use the title "dietitian," as described by the business and professions codes of each respective state, when they have met specific educational and experiential prerequisites and passed a national registration or licensure examination, respectively. In California, registered dietitions must abide by the "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/cgi-bin/displaycode?section=bpc&amp;group=02001-03000&amp;file=2585-2586.8">
Business and Professions Code of Section 2585-2586.8</weblink>".Anyone may call themselves a nutritionist, including unqualified personnel, as this term is unregulated. Some states, such as the State of Florida, have begun to include the title "nutritionist" in state licensure requirements. Most governments provide guidance on nutrition, and some also impose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/245529.xml">
mandatory disclosure/labeling</link> requirements for processed food manufacturers and restaurants to assist consumers in complying with such guidance. </p>
<p>

In the US, nutritional standards and recommendations are established jointly by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/70896.xml">
US Department of Agriculture</link>and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/311814.xml">
US Department of Health and Human Services</link>. Dietary and physical activity guidelines from the USDA are presented in the concept of a <solid wordnetid="113860793" confidence="0.8">
<pyramid wordnetid="113914837" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<polyhedron wordnetid="113883885" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/1764517.xml">
food pyramid</link></polyhedron>
</shape>
</pyramid>
</solid>
, which superseded the Four Food Groups. The Senate committee currently responsible for oversight of the USDA is the <it>Agriculture, Nutrition and Forestry Committee</it>. Committee hearings are often televised on <channel wordnetid="106259898" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/77799.xml">
C-SPAN</link></channel>
 as seen here.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/58250.xml">
U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</link> provides a sample week-long menu which fulfills the nutritional recommendations of the government.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mypyramid.gov/downloads/sample_menu.pdf">
http://www.mypyramid.gov/downloads/sample_menu.pdf</weblink> </p>
<p>

<work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<solid wordnetid="113860793" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<pyramid wordnetid="113914837" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<polyhedron wordnetid="113883885" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/3875589.xml">
Canada's Food Guide</link></publication>
</polyhedron>
</shape>
</pyramid>
</artifact>
</creation>
</solid>
</product>
</work>
 is another governmental recommendation.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Teaching</st>
<p>

Nutrition is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/205075.xml">
taught</link> in schools in many countries. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/275187.xml">
England and Wales</link> the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/852223.xml">
Personal and Social Education</link> and Food Technology curricula include nutrition, stressing the importance of a balanced diet and teaching how to read nutrition labels on packaging.  In many schools a Nutrition class will fall within the Family and Consumer Science or Health departments.  In some American schools, students are required to take a certain number of FCS or Health related classes.  Nutrition is offered at many schools, and if it is not a class of its own, nutrition is included in other FCS or Health classes such as: Life Skills, Independent Living, Single Survival, Freshmen Connection, Health etc.  In many Nutrition classes, students learn about the food groups, the food pyramid, Daily Recommended Allowances, calories, vitamins, minerals, malnutrition, physical activity, healthy food choices and how to live a healthy life.</p>
<p>

A 1985 US <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/501503.xml">
National Research Council</link> report entitled <it>Nutrition Education in US Medical Schools</it> concluded that nutrition education in medical schools was inadequate.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref> Only 20% of the schools surveyed taught nutrition as a separate, required course. A 2006 survey found that this number had risen to 30%.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Humans have evolved as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/159403.xml">
omnivorous</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/210098.xml">
hunter-gatherer</link>s over the past 250,000 years. The diet of early modern humans varied significantly depending on location and climate. The diet in the tropics tended to be based more heavily on plant foods, while the diet at higher latitudes tended more towards animal products. Analysis of postcranial and cranial remains of humans and animals from the Neolithic, along with detailed bone modification studies have shown that cannibalism was also prevalent among prehistoric humans.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2241%22])">41</ref></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/627.xml">
Agriculture</link> developed about 10,000 years ago in multiple locations throughout the world, providing grains such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/36858.xml">
wheat</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/36979.xml">
rice</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/20397.xml">
maize</link>, with staples such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/36969.xml">
bread</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/23871.xml">
pasta</link>. Farming also provided milk and dairy products, and sharply increased the availability of meats and the diversity of vegetables. The importance of food purity was recognized when bulk storage led to infestation and contamination risks. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/5355.xml">
Cooking</link> developed as an often ritualistic activity, due to efficiency and reliability concerns requiring adherence to strict recipes and procedures, and in response to demands for food purity and consistency.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Antiquity through 1900</st>

<p>

The first recorded nutritional experiment is found in the Bible's <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/4333.xml">
Book of Daniel</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
. Daniel and his friends were captured by the king of <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/19720404.xml">
Babylon</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</tract>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</site>
 during an invasion of Israel. Selected as court servants, they were to share in the king's fine foods and wine. But they objected, preferring vegetables (<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/42715.xml">
pulses</link></material>
</part>
</food>
</substance>
</substance>
) and water in accordance with their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/15913.xml">
Jewish</link> dietary restrictions. The king's chief steward reluctantly agreed to a trial. Daniel and his friends received their diet for 10 days and were then compared to the king's men. Appearing healthier, they were allowed to continue with their diet.</p>
<p>

In around 475 BC, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/1737.xml">
Anaxagoras</link></person>
 stated that food is absorbed by the human body and therefore contained "homeomerics" (generative components), thereby deducing the existence of nutrients.  Around 400 BC, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/13486.xml">
Hippocrates</link></doctor>
</person>
 said, "Let food be your medicine and medicine be your food."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2243%22])">43</ref></p>
<p>

In the 1500s, scientist and artist <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/18079.xml">
Leonardo da Vinci</link></artist>
</person>
 compared <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/20374.xml">
metabolism</link> to a burning candle.  In 1747, Dr. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<medical_practitioner wordnetid="110305802" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<health_professional wordnetid="110165109" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/19098559.xml">
James Lind</link></associate>
</doctor>
</professional>
</adult>
</health_professional>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</medical_practitioner>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
, a physician in the British navy, performed the first <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/26700.xml">
scientific</link> nutrition experiment, discovering that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/261456.xml">
lime</link> juice saved sailors who had been at sea for years from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/28266.xml">
scurvy</link>, a deadly and painful bleeding disorder. The discovery was ignored for forty years, after which British sailors became known as "limeys." The essential <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/32509.xml">
vitamin C</link> within lime juice would not be identified by scientists until the 1930s.</p>
<p>

Around 1770, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/1822.xml">
Antoine Lavoisier</link></person>
, the "Father of Nutrition and Chemistry" discovered the details of metabolism, demonstrating that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/66313.xml">
oxidation</link> of food is the source of body heat.  In 1790, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/5504634.xml">
George Fordyce</link></person>
 recognized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/5668.xml">
calcium</link> as necessary for fowl survival.  In the early 1800s, the elements <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/5299.xml">
carbon</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/21175.xml">
nitrogen</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/13255.xml">
hydrogen</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/22303.xml">
oxygen</link> were recognized as the primary components of food, and methods to measure their proportions were developed.</p>
<p>

In 1816, <link>
François Magendie</link> discovered that dogs fed only <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/5932.xml">
carbohydrates</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
fat</link> lost their body <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link> and died in a few weeks, but dogs also fed protein survived, identifying protein as an essential dietary component.  In 1840, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/16024.xml">
Justus Liebig</link> discovered the chemical makeup of carbohydrates (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/27712.xml">
sugar</link>s), fats (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>s) and proteins (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link>s.)  In the 1860s, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/376949.xml">
Claude Bernard</link></scientist>
 discovered that body fat can be synthesized from carbohydrate and protein, showing that the energy in blood <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/12950.xml">
glucose</link> can be stored as fat or as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/168986.xml">
glycogen</link>.</p>
<p>

In the early 1880s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/4190274.xml">
Kanehiro Takaki</link> observed that Japanese sailors (whose diets consisted almost entirely of white rice) developed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/217881.xml">
beriberi</link> (or endemic neuritis, a disease causing heart problems and paralysis) but British sailors and Japanese naval officers did not. Adding various types of vegetables and meats to the diets of Japanese sailors prevented the disease.</p>
<p>

In 1896, Baumann observed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/14750.xml">
iodine</link> in thyroid glands.  In 1897, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/240829.xml">
Christiaan Eijkman</link></scientist>
 worked with natives of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/69336.xml">
Java</link>, who also suffered from beriberi. Eijkman observed that chickens fed the native diet of white rice developed the symptoms of beriberi, but remained healthy when fed unprocessed brown rice with the outer bran intact. Eijkman cured the natives by feeding them brown rice, discovering that food can cure disease. Over two decades later, nutritionists learned that the outer rice bran contains vitamin B1, also known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/30500.xml">
thiamine</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
1900 through present</st>

<p>

In the early 1900s, <link>
Carl Von Voit</link> and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/5882960.xml">
Max Rubner</link></scientist>
 independently measured <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/6423.xml">
caloric</link> energy expenditure in different species of animals, applying principles of physics in nutrition.  In 1906, Wilcock and Hopkins showed that the amino acid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/58358.xml">
tryptophan</link> was necessary for the survival of rats.  He fed them a special mixture of food containing all the nutrients he believed were essential for survival, but the rats died. A second group of rats to which he also fed fed an amount of milk containing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/32512.xml">
vitamins</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2244%22])">44</ref> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/675837.xml">
Gowland Hopkins</link> recognized "accessory food factors" other than calories, protein and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/235195.xml">
minerals</link>, as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../203/22203.xml">
organic</link> materials essential to health but which the body cannot synthesize.  In 1907, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/1328375.xml">
Stephen M. Babcock</link> and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biochemist wordnetid="109854915" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<chemist wordnetid="109913824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/7365015.xml">
Edwin B. Hart</link></chemist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biochemist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 conducted the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/7365355.xml">
single-grain experiment</link>. This experiment runs through 1911.</p>
<p>

In 1912, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/39760.xml">
Casimir Funk</link></scientist>
</person>
 coined the term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/32512.xml">
vitamin</link>, a vital factor in the diet, from the words "vital" and "amine," because these unknown substances preventing scurvy, beriberi, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/355776.xml">
pellagra</link>, were thought then to be derived from ammonia.  The vitamins were studied in the first half of the twentieth century. </p>
<p>

In 1913, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biochemist wordnetid="109854915" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<chemist wordnetid="109913824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/6000868.xml">
Elmer McCollum</link></chemist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biochemist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 discovered the first vitamins, fat soluble <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/54114.xml">
vitamin A</link>, and water soluble <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/457926.xml">
vitamin B</link> (in 1915; now known to be a complex of several water-soluble vitamins) and names <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/32509.xml">
vitamin C</link> as the then-unknown substance preventing scurvy.  <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../595/10468595.xml">
Lafayette Mendel</link></scientist>
 and Thomas Osborne also perform pioneering work on vitamin A and B. In 1919, Sir <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/495323.xml">
Edward Mellanby</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 incorrectly identified <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/25987.xml">
rickets</link> as a vitamin A deficiency, because he could cure it in dogs with cod liver oil.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2245%22])">45</ref> In 1922, McCollum destroyed the vitamin A in cod liver oil but finds it still cures rickets, naming <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/54106.xml">
vitamin D</link>  Also in 1922, H.M. Evans and L.S. Bishop discover <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/54105.xml">
vitamin E</link> as essential for rat pregnancy, originally calling it "food factor X" until 1925.</p>
<p>

In 1925, Hart discovered that trace amounts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/125293.xml">
copper</link> are necessary for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/14734.xml">
iron</link> absorption.  In 1927, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/749670.xml">
Adolf Otto Reinhold Windaus</link></scientist>
 synthesized vitamin D, for which he won the <award wordnetid="106696483" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/21201.xml">
Nobel Prize</link></award>
 in Chemistry in 1928. In 1928, <link>
Albert Szent-Györgyi</link> isolated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
ascorbic acid</link>, and in 1932 proves that it is vitamin C by preventing scurvy. In 1935 he synthesizes it, and in 1937 he wins a Nobel Prize for his efforts. Szent-Györgyi concurrently elucidates much of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/6818.xml">
citric acid cycle</link>.</p>
<p>

In the 1930s, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/922751.xml">
William Cumming Rose</link></scientist>
 identified <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/102213.xml">
essential amino acid</link>s, necessary protein components which the body cannot synthesize.  In 1935, Underwood and Marston independently discover the necessity of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ium/6th_millennium.xml">
cobalt</link>.  In 1936, <link>
Eugene Floyd Dubois</link> showed that work and school performance are related to caloric intake. In 1938, <link>
Erhard Fernholz</link> discovered the chemical structure of vitamin E. It was synthesised by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/1233728.xml">
Paul Karrer</link></scientist>
.</p>
<p>

In 1940, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/1279880.xml">
rationing in the United Kingdom during and after World War II</link> took place according to nutritional principles drawn up by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../069/10261069.xml">
Elsie Widdowson</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and others. In 1941, the first <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/396054.xml">
Recommended Dietary Allowance</link>s (RDAs) were established by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/37638.xml">
National Research Council</link>.</p>
<p>

In 1992, The U.S. Department of Agriculture introduced the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/208092.xml">
Food Guide Pyramid</link>.  In 2002, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/551771.xml">
Natural Justice</link> study showed a relation between nutrition and violent behavior.  In 2005, a study found that obesity may be caused by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/455651.xml">
adenovirus</link> in addition to bad nutrition.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2246%22])">46</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <it>Main list: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/7371778.xml">
List of basic nutrition topics</link></it>
</indent>

<table style="background-color: transparent; width: {[[:Template:Width]]}">
<row>
<col align="{{}}" width="33%" valign="{[[:Template:Valign]]}">
<b>Biology:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/165423.xml">
Digestion</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/9257.xml">
Enzyme</link></entry>
</list>
<p>

<b> Dangers of poor nutrition</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/321847.xml">
Deficiency</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/103558.xml">
Avitaminosis</link> is a deficiency of vitamins.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/3812008.xml">
Boron deficiency (medicine)</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/3011649.xml">
Chromium deficiency</link></disease>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/158402.xml">
Iron deficiency (medicine)</link></disease>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/2025028.xml">
Iodine deficiency</link></disease>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/3029057.xml">
Magnesium deficiency (medicine)</link></disease>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/44677.xml">
Diabetes</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/56825.xml">
Eating disorders</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/497424.xml">
Illnesses related to poor nutrition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/258979.xml">
Malnutrition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/56435.xml">
Obesity</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/4572582.xml">
Childhood obesity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/215891.xml">
Starvation</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/10646.xml">
Food</link>:</b>
<indent level="1">

 <it>
Food (portal)</it>
</indent>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <solid wordnetid="113860793" confidence="0.8">
<pyramid wordnetid="113914837" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<polyhedron wordnetid="113883885" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/4602377.xml">
5 A Day</link></polyhedron>
</shape>
</pyramid>
</solid>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<solid wordnetid="113860793" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<pyramid wordnetid="113914837" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<polyhedron wordnetid="113883885" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/3875589.xml">
Canada's Food Guide</link></publication>
</polyhedron>
</shape>
</pyramid>
</artifact>
</creation>
</solid>
</product>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Fast Food</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/2953473.xml">
Food groups</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <solid wordnetid="113860793" confidence="0.8">
<pyramid wordnetid="113914837" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<polyhedron wordnetid="113883885" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/208092.xml">
Food guide pyramid</link></polyhedron>
</shape>
</pyramid>
</solid>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/1130760.xml">
Food supplements</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/10843.xml">
Fruit</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/1014424.xml">
Functional food</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/6700.xml">
Grain</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/64083.xml">
Junk Food</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/18940.xml">
Meat</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/5791492.xml">
Vegetable</link>s</entry>
</list>
</p>
</col>
<col align="{{}}" width="33%" valign="{[[:Template:Valign]]}"><p>

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/1581671.xml">
Healthy diet</link>: </b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/8460.xml">
Dieting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/212818.xml">
Eating</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <solid wordnetid="113860793" confidence="0.8">
<pyramid wordnetid="113914837" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<polyhedron wordnetid="113883885" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/1055458.xml">
Healthy eating pyramid</link></polyhedron>
</shape>
</pyramid>
</solid>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/13115986.xml">
Nutritional rating systems</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/929794.xml">
Physicians Committee for Responsible Medicine</link> (PCRM)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/3809742.xml">
The China Study</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Lists:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/84252.xml">
Diets (list)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/5193078.xml">
List of food additives</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/497424.xml">
List of illnesses related to poor nutrition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/5919257.xml">
List of life extension related topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../067/815067.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Nutrition%22])">
List of publications in nutrition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/7566037.xml">
List of unrefined sweeteners</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/66575.xml">
Nutrient</link>s:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/5932.xml">
Carbohydrate</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/235195.xml">
Dietary mineral</link>s</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/235195.xml">
Essential mineral</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/104444.xml">
Dietary supplement</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/16865984.xml">
Evolution of dietary antioxidants</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/529854.xml">
Essential nutrient</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
Fat</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/105948.xml">
Essential fatty acid</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/66575.xml">
Macronutrient</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/1148672.xml">
Micronutrient</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/685457.xml">
Nootropic</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/1221381.xml">
Nutraceutical</link>s</entry>
</list>
</p>
</col>
<col align="{{}}" width="50%" valign="{[[:Template:Valign]]}"><p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/472231.xml">
Phytochemicals</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
Protein</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/5978246.xml">
Complete protein</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/102213.xml">
Essential amino acid</link>s</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/7092020.xml">
Incomplete protein</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/7092020.xml">
Protein combining</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/6531493.xml">
Protein in nutrition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/32512.xml">
Vitamin</link>s</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/3261719.xml">
Megavitamin therapy</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/9651482.xml">
Vitamin C megadosage</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Profession:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/439999.xml">
Dietitian</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/771326.xml">
Nutritionist</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Tools:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/13295189.xml">
Nutrition scale</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Organizations:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/3088926.xml">
American Dietetic Association</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nutrition.org">
American Society for Nutrition</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/915755.xml">
British Dietetic Association</link></union>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Related topics</b></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/80381.xml">
Health</link></it>
</indent>
* <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/973095.xml">
Auxology</link>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/189037.xml">
Exercise</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/6057429.xml">
General Fitness Training</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 
Health (portal)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/183290.xml">
Life extension</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <pseudoscience wordnetid="105778954" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/327995.xml">
Orthomolecular medicine</link></pseudoscience>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/432986.xml">
Physical fitness</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Galdston, I., <it>Human Nutrition Historic and Scientific</it> (New York: International Universities Press, 1960)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mahan, L.K. and Escott-Stump, S. eds. (2000) <it>Krause's Food, Nutrition, and Diet Therapy.</it> 10th ed. (Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders Harcourt Brace)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Thiollet, J-P, <it>Vitamines &amp; minéraux</it> (Paris, Anagramme, 2001)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Walter C. Willett and Meir J. Stampfer. 2003. Rebuilding the Food Pyramid. <it>Scientific American</it> January 2003.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Berg J, Tymoczko JL, Stryer L&#32;(2002). Biochemistry, 5th ed.,&#32;San Francisco:&#32;W. H. Freeman,&#32;page 603. ISBN 0716746840.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite id="CITEREFBarker2002" style="font-style:normal">Barker, Helen M.&#32;(2002),&#32;<it>Nutrition and dietetics for health care</it>, Edinburgh: Churchill Livingstone, pp. 17, ISBN 0443070210, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/883885.xml">
OCLC</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://worldcat.org/oclc/48917971">
48917971</weblink></cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
Nelson, D. L.; Cox, M. M. "Lehninger, Principles of Biochemistry" 3rd Ed. Worth Publishing: New York, 2000. ISBN 1-57259-153-6.</entry>
<entry id="4">
D. E. C. Corbridge "Phosphorus: An Outline of its Chemistry, Biochemistry, and Technology" 5th Edition Elsevier: Amsterdam 1995. ISBN 0-444-89307-5.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Lippard, S. J. and Berg, J. M., Principles of Bioinorganic Chemistry, University Science Books: Mill Valley, CA, 1994.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Shils <it>et al.</it> (2005) <it>Modern Nutrition in Health and Disease</it>, Lippincott Williams and Wilkins. ISBN 0-7817-4133-5.</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/health/healthy_living/nutrition/drinks_water.shtml">
Healthy Water Living</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ajpregu.physiology.org/cgi/content/full/283/5/R993">
"Drink at least eight glasses of water a day." Really? Is there scientific evidence for "8 × 8"?</weblink> by Heinz Valdin, Department of Physiology, Dartmouth Medical School, Lebanon, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/21134.xml">
New Hampshire</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.factsmart.org/h2o/h2o.htm">
Drinking Water - How Much?</weblink>, Factsmart.org web site and references within</entry>
<entry id="10">
Food and Nutrition Board, National Academy of Sciences. Recommended Dietary Allowances, revised 1945. National Research Council, Reprint and Circular Series, No. 122, 1945 (Aug), p. 3-18.</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iom.edu/report.asp?id=18495">
Dietary Reference Intakes: Water, Potassium, Sodium, Chloride, and Sulfate</weblink>, Food and Nutrition Board</entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/water/NU00283">
Water: How much should you drink every day? - MayoClinic.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
Seddon JM <it>et al.</it> JAMA. 1994; 272: 1413-1420; Schepens Eye Institute/Harvard Medical School, Nov. 11, 2003. See http://www.mdsupport.org/library/zeaxanthin.html.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Lyle, B. J., J. A. Mares-Perlman, <it>et al.</it> (1999). "Antioxidant intake and risk of incident age-related nuclear cataracts in the Beaver Dam Eye Study." Am J Epidemiol 149(9): 801-9; Yeum, K. J., A. Taylor, <it>et al.</it> (1995). "Measurement of carotenoids, retinoids, and tocopherols in human lenses." Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 36(13): 2756-61; Chasan-Taber, L., W. C. Willett, <it>et al.</it> (1999). "A prospective study of carotenoid and vitamin A intakes and risk of cataract extraction in US women." Am J Clin Nutr 70(4): 509-16; Brown, L., E. B. Rimm, <it>et al.</it> (1999). "A prospective study of carotenoid intake and risk of cataract extraction in US men." Am J Clin Nutr 70(4): 517-24.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Am J Clin Nutr, Vol. 82, No. 2, 451-455, August, 2005 (inflammatory polyarthritis); Am J Epidemiology 2006 163(1).</entry>
<entry id="17">
Note that some isoflavone studies have linked isoflavones to increased cancer risk.</entry>
<entry id="16">
Am J Clin Nutr, Vol. 70, No. 2, 247-251, August 1999.</entry>
<entry id="19">
The definition of recreational athlete here is taken from Burke and Deakin's <it>Clinical Sports Nutrition</it>(3rd Edition, McGraw-Hill Australia Pty Ltd, 2006 ): people exercising two to three hours a week at less than 55% maximum VO2 uptake.</entry>
<entry id="18">
Monoterpenes are enormously widespread among green plant life (including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/633.xml">
algae</link>). Many plants, notably coniferous trees, emit beneficial monoterpenes into the atmosphere.</entry>
<entry id="21">
William D. McArdle, Frank I. Katch, Victor L. Katch. Exercise Physiology: Energy, Nutrition, and Human Performance.  Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="20">
It is recommended to  consume about 16 ounces of water up to two hours before an event. Then try to drink about 8-12 ounces more about 10 minutes before your competition or workout.  Ideally, you should try to drink 8-10 ounces of water for every 15-20 minutes of strenuous exercise.  Fluids lost by sweating need to be replaced. Good recovery fluids include water, juices, low-fat milk, smoothies and sports drinks. Always drink as much water as you comfortably can and don’t wait until you are thirsty before you drink liquids.</entry>
<entry id="23">
Campbell T., Campbell T. The China Study, Dallas: Benella Books, 2005</entry>
<entry id="22">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/health/healthy_living/nutrition/basics_carbos.shtml">
BBC - Health - Healthy living - Bread, cereals and potatoes</weblink></entry>
<entry id="25">
Ducimetière, Pierre.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/320/7229/249/a">
Rates of coronary events are similar in France and southern Europe</weblink>".&#32;  BMJ. </entry>
<entry id="24">
Ducimetière, Pierre.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://circ.ahajournals.org/cgi/reprint/115/16/2231">
Understanding the Complexity of Trans Fatty Acid Reduction in the American Diet</weblink>".&#32;  BMJ.</entry>
<entry id="27">
Benton, D., &amp; Sargent, J. (1992/7). Breakfast, blood glucose and memory. Biological Psychology, 33(2-3), 207-210. </entry>
<entry id="26">
American College Health Association. (2007) American College Health Association national college health assessment spring 2006 reference group data report (abridged). Journal of American College Health, 55(4), 195-206.</entry>
<entry id="29">
Whitley, J., O'Dell, B., &amp; Hogan, A. (1951). Effect of diet on maze learning in second-generation rats. folic acid deficiency. Journal of Nutrition, 45(1), 153. </entry>
<entry id="28">
Kanarek, R. B., &amp; Swinney, D. (1990/2). Effects of food snacks on cognitive performance in male college students. Appetite, 14(1), 15-27.</entry>
<entry id="31">
Glewwe, P., Jacoby, H., &amp; King, E. (2001). Early childhood nutrition and academic achievement: A longitudinal analysis. Journal of Public Economics, 81(3), 345-368.</entry>
<entry id="30">
Umezawa, M., Kogishi, K., Tojo, H., Yoshimura, S., Seriu, N., Ohta, A., et al. (1999). High-linoleate and high-alpha-linolenate diets affect learning ability and natural behavior in SAMR1 mice. The Journal of Nutrition, 129(2), 431-437.</entry>
<entry id="34">
Duster, T., &amp; Waters, A. (2006). Engaged learning across the curriculum: The vertical integration of food for thought. Liberal Education, 92(2), 42.</entry>
<entry id="35">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Lakhan SE, Vieira KF&#32;(2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nutritionj.com/content/7/1/2">
Nutritional therapies for mental disorders</weblink>". <it>Nutr J</it>&#32;<b>7</b>: 2. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186%2F1475-2891-7-2">
10.1186/1475-2891-7-2</weblink>. PMID 18208598.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="32">
Managed food service contractors react quickly to the demands of their clients achievement: A longitudinal analysis. Journal of Public Economics, 81(3), 345-368.</entry>
<entry id="33">
Guernsey, L. (1993). Many colleges clear their tables of steak, substitute fruit and pasta. Chronicle of Higher Education, 39(26), A30.</entry>
<entry id="38">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Morris, Audrey; Audia Barnett, Olive-Jean Burrows&#32;(2004).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.paho.org/English/CFNI/cfni-caj37No304-art-3.pdf">
Effect of Processing on Nutrient Content of Foods</weblink>"&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link>). <it>CAJANUS</it>&#32;<b>37</b>&#32;(3): pp. 160–164. Retrieved on <link>
2006-10-26</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="39">
Commission on Life Sciences. (1985). <it>Nutrition Education in US Medical Schools</it>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=597&amp;page=4">
 p. 4</weblink>. National Academies Press.</entry>
<entry id="36">
Coren, Michael&#32;(<link>
2005-03-10</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnn.com/2005/HEALTH/03/09/cancer.study/index.html">
Study: Cancer no longer rare in poorer countries</weblink>".&#32;  <channel wordnetid="106259898" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/62028.xml">
CNN</link></channel>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="37">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/6263029.stm">
BBC NEWS | Magazine |Why is too much water dangerous?</weblink></entry>
<entry id="42">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rcw.raiuniversity.edu/biotechnology/MScBioinformatics/generalnutrition/lecture-notes/lecture-01.pdf">
History of the Study of Nutrition in Western Culture</weblink> (copy at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rain.org/homeschool/nutrition-history-in-western-culture.html">
http://www.rain.org/homeschool/nutrition-history-in-western-culture.html</weblink>)</entry>
<entry id="43">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/328/7433/0-g">
"Let food by thy medicine...</weblink>  Richard Smith, <it>BMJ  2004;328 (24 January),</it>, Accessed May 2008</entry>
<entry id="40">
Adams KM et al. (2006). <it>Status of nutrition education in medical schools</it>. Am J Clin Nutr. <b>83</b>(suppl):941S-4S.</entry>
<entry id="41">
Paola Villa, et al. "Cannibalism in the Neolithic" <it>Science</it> <b>233</b> July 1986.</entry>
<entry id="46">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/854584.stm">
"Can a virus make you fat?"</weblink> at <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<announcement wordnetid="106746580" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106748466" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/1139893.xml">
BBC News</link></program>
</announcement>
</message>
</statement>
; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scienceblog.com/cms/contagious_obesity_identifying_the_human_adenoviruses_that_may_make_us_fat_9901">
"Contagious obesity? Identifying the human adenoviruses that may make us fat"</weblink> at <link>
Science Blog</link></entry>
<entry id="44">
Heinemann 2e Biology Activity Manual by Judith Brotherton and Kate Mundie)</entry>
<entry id="45">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.beyonddiscovery.org/content/view.txt.asp?a=414">
Unraveling the Enigma of Vitamin D</weblink> - a paper funded by the <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<academy wordnetid="108279298" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/46510.xml">
United States National Academy of Sciences</link></academy>
</geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</region>
</site>
</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/nutrition/topics/dietnutrition_and_chronicdiseases/en/">
Diet, Nutrition and the prevention of chronic diseases</weblink> by a Joint <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/33583.xml">
WHO</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/11107.xml">
FAO</link> Expert consultation (2003) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nal.usda.gov/fnic/foodcomp/Bulletins/faq.html">
United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) Frequently asked questions</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foodsec.org/DL/dlintro_en.asp">
Nutritional Status Assessment and Analysis - e-learning from FAO</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.folkszone.com/">
Health, Nutrition and Fitness</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Databases and search engines </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nutritiondata.com/">
Nutrition Data</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lexolino.de/c,kultur_alltagskultur_gesundheit_ern%E4hrung_n%E4hrwerttabellen">
German Nutrition Data with fast search on www.lexolion.de</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nal.usda.gov/fnic/foodcomp/search/">
USDA National Nutrient Database for Standard Reference</weblink> Search By Food</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ars.usda.gov/Services/docs.htm?docid=13726">
USDA National Nutrient Database for Standard Reference Nutrient Lists</weblink> Search By Nutrient</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Governmental agencies and intergovernmental bodies </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unsystem.org/scn/">
UN Standing Committee on Nutrition</weblink> - In English, French and Portuguese</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Portal.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Food&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/252137.xml">
Food science</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</field>
</region>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/679350.xml">
Allergy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/7888444.xml">
Chemistry</link>&nbsp;·  <knowledge_domain wordnetid="105999266" confidence="0.8">
<discipline wordnetid="105996646" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/1515853.xml">
Engineering</link></discipline>
</knowledge_domain>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/3867443.xml">
Law</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/7073591.xml">
Microbiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/7920832.xml">
Packaging</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/602960.xml">
Processing</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/216150.xml">
Quality</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/1728007.xml">
Foodservice (catering)</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/1636646.xml">
Technology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
Nutrition</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/216192.xml">
Product development</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../209/2581209.xml">
Sensory analysis</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/6185334.xml">
discrimination testing</link>)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/3426171.xml">
Superfood</link></p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/50643.xml">
Health science</link> &amp;gt; <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/2603832.xml">
Allied health professions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/1742971.xml">
Athletic training</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/1050386.xml">
Audiology</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/7738.xml">
Chiropractic</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/8005.xml">
Dentistry</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/1560270.xml">
Dental hygiene</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/439999.xml">
Dietetics</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/76988.xml">
Electrocardiographic technicians</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/52975.xml">
Emergency medical services</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/590920.xml">
Hemodialysis technicians</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/43945.xml">
Massage therapy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/2243764.xml">
Medical assistant</link>s •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/202584.xml">
Medical physics</link> •
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/3770891.xml">
Medical technologist</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 •
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/3940866.xml">
Medical transcription</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 •
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/217662.xml">
Music therapy</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/347838.xml">
Nuclear medicine technology</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
Nutrition</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/334037.xml">
Occupational therapy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/181226.xml">
Optometry</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/297350.xml">
Pharmacy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/234819.xml">
Phlebotomy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/2447242.xml">
Orthotics</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/72750.xml">
Prosthetics</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/24022.xml">
Physical therapy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/594086.xml">
Podiatry</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
Psychology</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/463734.xml">
Public health</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/26350.xml">
Radiation therapy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/95807.xml">
Radiography</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/5399622.xml">
Radiologic technologist</link> •
<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<treatment wordnetid="100658082" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<care wordnetid="100654885" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/48614.xml">
Respiratory therapy</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</care>
</event>
</treatment>
</work>
 •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/7032057.xml">
Speech and language pathology</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/146717.xml">
Social work</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/143357.xml">
Ultrasonography</link></p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
