<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:20:12[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Dedicated hosting service</title>
<id>2199995</id>
<revision>
<id>244541511</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T09:47:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Zzuuzz</username>
<id>365454</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Servers</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>


<p>

<table class="infobox">

<row>
<header style="background:#dddddd;">
 Types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/3701714.xml">
Internet hosting service</link></header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Full-featured hosting services</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/555304.xml">
Virtual private server</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/2199995.xml">
Dedicated hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/47000.xml">
Colocation centre</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/157465.xml">
Web hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/1809185.xml">
Free hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/2455746.xml">
Shared hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/2540216.xml">
Clustered hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/951411.xml">
Reseller hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/19558636.xml">
FFmpeg hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Application-specific</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/2053065.xml">
Blog hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/8953579.xml">
Guild hosting</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/2263424.xml">
Image hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/4923012.xml">
Video hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/3705755.xml">
Wiki farm</link>s</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/309945.xml">
Application hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/19577322.xml">
Social network hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/1693035.xml">
File hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/1754950.xml">
Remote backup service</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/3505526.xml">
Game server hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/3701683.xml">
DNS hosting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/3701751.xml">
E-mail hosting</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>

A <b>dedicated hosting service</b>, <b>dedicated server</b>, or <b>managed hosting service</b> is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/3701714.xml">
Internet hosting</link> where the client leases an entire server not shared with anyone.  This is more flexible than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/2455746.xml">
shared hosting</link>, as organizations have full control over the server(s), including choice of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/13615.xml">
hardware</link>, etc.  Server administration can usually be provided by the hosting company as an add-on service. In some cases a dedicated server can offer less overhead and a larger <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/3440956.xml">
return on investment</link>. Dedicated servers are most often housed in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/579730.xml">
data centers</link>, similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/47000.xml">
colocation facilities</link>, providing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/2736308.xml">
redundant power</link> sources and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/57169.xml">
HVAC</link> systems.  In contrast to collocation, the server hardware is owned by the provider and in some cases they will provide support for your operating system or applications.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Operating system support</st>

<p>

Availability, price and employee familiarity often determines which operating systems are offered on dedicated servers. Variations of <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating systems</link>) are often included at no charge to the customer. Commercial operating systems include Microsoft Windows Server, provided through a special program called Microsoft SPLA. Red Hat Enterprise is a commercial version of Linux offered to hosting providers on a monthly fee basis. The monthly fee provides OS updates through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/296877.xml">
Red Hat Network</link> using an application called up2date. Other operating systems are available from the open source community at no charge. These include <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/998890.xml">
CentOS</link></O>
, <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/9951070.xml">
Fedora Core</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
, <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/8242.xml">
Debian</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
, and many other Linux distributions or BSD systems <platform wordnetid="103961939" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<surface wordnetid="104362025" confidence="0.8">
<horizontal_surface wordnetid="103536348" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/7580554.xml">
FreeBSD</link></horizontal_surface>
</surface>
</artifact>
</platform>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/21495.xml">
NetBSD</link>, <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/18949571.xml">
OpenBSD</link></O>
.</p>
<p>

Support for any of the operating systems above typically depends on the level of management offered with a particular dedicated server plan. Operating system support may include updates to the core system in order to acquire the latest security fixes, patches, and system-wide vulnerability resolutions. Updates to core operating systems include kernel upgrades, service packs, application updates, and security patches that keep server secure and safe. Operating system updates and support relieves the burden of server management from the dedicated server owner.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Bandwidth and connectivity</st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/15612827.xml">
Bandwidth</link> refers to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/272290.xml">
data transfer rate</link> or the amount of data that can be carried from one point to another in a given time period (usually a second) and is often represented in bits (of data) per second (bit/s). For example, visitors to your server, web site, or applications utilize bandwidth as the traffic moves from your server to the Internet and vice versa. Connectivity refers to the “access providers” that supply bandwidth, or data transfer rate, through various connection points across a network or footprint to one or multiple data centers where dedicated servers are housed.</p>
<p>

Bandwidth measurements are defined (per <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/30322.xml">
telecom</link> standards) as the following:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

First – 95th (measured using average <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/3364.xml">
bit</link>s and speed of transfer)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Second – Unmetered (measured in speed or bits)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Third – Total Transfer (measured in bytes transferred)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>95th Method:</b> Line Speed, billed on the 95th percentile, average or peak usage, refers to the speed in which data flows from the server or device. The measurement can be compared to mph (Miles Per Hour), or how fast something travels. Line Speed is measured using bits per second, kilobits per second, megabits per second, and gigabits per second.</p>
<p>

<b>Unmetered Method:</b> The second bandwidth measurement is Unmetered service where providers cap or control the “top line” speed for a server. Top line speed in unmetered bandwidth is the total Mbit/s allocated to the server and configured on the switch level. For example, if you purchase 10 Mbit/s unmetered bandwidth, the top line speed would be 10 Mbit/s. 10 Mbit/s would result in the provider controlling the speed transfers take place while providing the ability for the dedicated server owner to not be charged with bandwidth overages. Unmetered bandwidth services usually incur an additional charge. </p>
<p>

<b>Total Transfer Method:</b> Some providers will calculate the Total Transfer, the measurement of actual data leaving and coming from the server, measured in bytes. Measurement between providers varies and includes one of the following equations:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Method 1: IN TRAFFIC + OUT TRAFFIC = TOTAL TRANSFER</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Method 2: IN TRAFFIC = TOTAL TRANSFER</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Method 3: OUT TRAFFIC = TOTAL TRANSFER</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

One of the reasons people choose to outsource dedicated servers is the availability of high powered networks from multiple providers. As dedicated server providers utilize massive amounts of bandwidth, they are able to secure lower volume based pricing to include a multi-provider blend of bandwidth. To achieve the same type of network without a multi-provider blend of bandwidth, a large investment in core routers, long term contracts, and expensive monthly bills would need to be in place. The expenses needed to develop a network without a multi-provider blend of bandwidth does not make sense economically for hosting providers.</p>
<p>

Many dedicated server providers include a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/775021.xml">
service level agreement</link> based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/4122592.xml">
network</link> uptime. Some dedicated server hosting providers offer a 100% uptime guarantee on their network. By securing multiple vendors for connectivity and using redundant hardware, providers are able to guarantee higher uptimes; usually between 99-100% uptime if they are a higher quality provider. One aspect of higher quality providers is they are mostly likely <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/641227.xml">
multi-homed</link> across multiple quality uplink providers, which in turn, provides significant redundancy in the event one goes down in addition to potentially improved routes to destinations.</p>
<p>

Bandwidth consumption over the last several years has shifted from a per megabit usage model to a per gigabyte usage model. Bandwidth was traditionally measured in line speed access that included the ability to purchase needed megabits at a given monthly cost. As the shared hosting model developed, the trend towards gigabyte or total bytes transferred, replaced the megabit line speed model so dedicated server providers started offering per gigabyte.</p>
<p>

Prominent players in the dedicated server market offer large amounts of bandwidth ranging from 500 gigabytes to 3000 gigabytes using the “overselling” model. It is not uncommon for major players to provide dedicated servers with 1Terabyte (TB) of bandwidth or higher. Usage models based on the byte level measurement usually include a given amount of bandwidth with each server and a price per gigabyte after a certain threshold has been reached. Expect to pay additional fees for bandwidth overage usage. For example, if a dedicated server has been given 3000 gigabytes of bandwidth per month and the customer uses 5000 gigabytes of bandwidth within the billing period, the additional 2000 gigabytes of bandwidth will be invoiced as bandwidth overage. Each provider has a different model for billing. As of yet, no industry standards have been set.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Management</st>

<p>

To date, no industry standards have been set to clearly define the management role of dedicated server providers. What this means is that each provider will use industry standard terms, but each provider will define them differently. For some dedicated server providers, fully managed is defined as having a web based control panel while other providers define it as having dedicated system engineers readily available to handle all server and network related functions of the dedicated server provider. </p>
<p>

Server management can include some or all of the following:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
Operating system</link> updates</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Application updates</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/7092174.xml">
Server monitoring</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/41710.xml">
Simple Network Management Protocol</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 hardware monitoring</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Application monitoring</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Technical support</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1362296.xml">
Firewall</link> services</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/268622.xml">
Antivirus</link> updates</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/2186788.xml">
Security audits</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/39776.xml">
DDoS</link> protection and mitigation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Intrusion detection</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/533867.xml">
Backup</link>s and restoration</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Disaster recovery</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/3701683.xml">
DNS hosting service</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../118/61118.xml">
Load balancing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Database administration</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Performance tuning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Software installation and configuration</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

User management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Programming consultation</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Dedicated hosting server providers define their level of management based on the services they provide. In comparison, fully managed could equal self managed from provider to provider.    </p>
<p>

Administrative maintenance of the operating system, often including upgrades, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/475153.xml">
security patches</link>, and sometimes even <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/458986.xml">
daemon</link> updates are included. Differing levels of management may include adding users, domains, daemon configuration, or even custom programming.</p>
<p>

Dedicated server hosting providers may provide the following types of server managed support:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fully Managed - Includes monitoring, software updates, reboots, security patches and operating system upgrades. Customers are completely hands-off.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Managed - Includes medium level of management, monitoring, updates, and a limited amount of support. Customers may perform specific tasks.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Self Managed - Includes regular monitoring and some maintenance. Customers provide most operations and tasks on dedicated server.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Unmanaged - Little to no involvement from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/1613082.xml">
service provider</link>. Customers provide all maintenance, upgrades, patches, and security. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Note:</b> The provider will continue to maintain security on the network regardless of support level.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Security</st>
<p>

Dedicated hosting server providers utilize extreme security measures to ensure the safety of data stored on their network of servers. Providers will often deploy various software programs for scanning systems and networks for obtrusive invaders, spammers, hackers, and other harmful problems such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/59791.xml">
Trojans</link>, worms, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/729586.xml">
eggdrops</link> and crashers (Sending multiple connections). <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link> use different software for security protection.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Software</st>


<p>

Providers often bill for dedicated servers on a fixed monthly price to include specific software packages. Over the years, software vendors realized the significant market opportunity to bundle their software with dedicated servers. They have since started introducing pricing models that allow dedicated hosting providers the ability to purchase and resell software based on reduced monthly fees.</p>
<p>

Microsoft offers software licenses through a program called the Service Provider License Agreement. The SPLA model provides use of Microsoft products through a monthly user or processor based fee. SPLA software includes the Windows Operating System, Microsoft SQL Server, Microsoft Exchange Server, Microsoft SharePoint and shoutcast hosting, and many other server based products.</p>
<p>

Dedicated Server Providers usually offer the ability to select the software you want installed on a dedicated server. Depending on the overall usage of the server, this will include your choice of operating system, database, and specific applications. Servers can be customized and tailored specific to the customer’s needs and requirements.    </p>
<p>

Other software applications available are specialized web hosting specific programs called control panels. Control panel software is an all inclusive set of software applications, server applications, and automation tools that can be installed on a dedicated server. Control panels include integration into web servers, database applications, programming languages, application deployment, server administration tasks, and include the ability to automate tasks via a web based front end.</p>
<p>

Most dedicated servers are packaged with a control panel. Control panels are often confused with management tools, but these control panels are actually web based automation tools created to help automate the process of web site creation and server management. Control panels should not be confused with a full server management solution by a dedicated hosting provider.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Limitations</st>
<p>

Many providers do not allow <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/14730.xml">
IRC</link></group>
</community>
</gathering>
</social_group>
 (bots, clients or daemons). This is due to rogue IRC users triggering <link>
DDoS</link> attacks against the provider, which may overwhelm their networks, lowering service quality for all customers.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/5710507.xml">
Adult content</link> is disallowed by many providers as it may either be of questionable legality or consume large amounts of bandwidth.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Extra features</st>
<p>

Useful features for dedicated servers may be included, or cost additional monthly fees:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Serial Console or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/1153898.xml">
KVM/IP</link> - this is used to gain access to a server if for some reason the user is unable to get in via normal means (e.g. <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/28814.xml">
ssh</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
), and permits a server to be recovered from boot-time configuration faults, such as filesystem recovery.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Automated restore of OS - an automated system can be used to restore the server to its original configuration.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Remote Backup Space - ssh/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/53289.xml">
FTP</link> space to backup data stored on the server.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/374636.xml">
ColdFusion</link></software>
 (MX) - ColdFusion is the rapid server scripting environment for creating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/1141591.xml">
Rich Internet Applications</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/13989994.xml">
SQL Server</link></software>
 - Server dedicated to hosting Microsoft SQL databases and typically incurs additional hosting fees.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Oracle - Server dedicated to hosting Oracle databases and typically incurs additional hosting fees.</entry>
</list>

</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>



</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dmoz.org/Computers/Internet/Web_Design_and_Development/Hosting/">
Website hosting services</weblink> at the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<subsidiary_company wordnetid="108003935" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18949501.xml">
Open Directory Project</link></institution>
</subsidiary_company>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</property>
</undertaking>
</company>
</event>
</possession>
</work>
</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
