<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:31:04[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<model  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="110324560">
<consequence  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="111410625">
<header>
<title>Network effect</title>
<id>22053</id>
<revision>
<id>243874266</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T12:29:56Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rl</username>
<id>10481</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles needing additional references from March 2008</category>
<category>Networks</category>
<category>Transport economics</category>
<category>Economics effects</category>
<category>Business models</category>
<category>Monopoly (economics)</category>
<category>Articles needing additional references from May 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Network_effect.png">
</image>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/9223.xml">
economics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
business</link>, a <b>network effect</b> (also called <b>network externality</b>) is the effect that one user of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/580039.xml">
good</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/181586.xml">
service</link> has on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/4095185.xml">
value</link> of that product to other users.<p>

The classic example is the telephone. The more people own telephones, the more valuable the telephone is to each owner. This creates a positive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/61193.xml">
externality</link> because a user may purchase their phone without intending to create value for other users, but does so in any case.</p>
<p>

The expression "network effect" is applied most commonly to positive network externalities as in the case of the telephone. Negative network externalities can also occur, where more users make a product less valuable, but are more commonly referred to as "congestion" (as in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/234226.xml">
traffic congestion</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/430522.xml">
network congestion</link>).</p>
<p>

Over time, positive network effects can create a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/171323.xml">
bandwagon effect</link> as the network becomes more valuable and more people join, in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/213354.xml">
positive feedback</link> loop.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Origins </st>

<p>

Network effects were a central theme in the arguments of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/751063.xml">
Theodore Vail</link>, the first post patent president of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/1417711.xml">
Bell Telephone</link>, in gaining a monopoly on telephone services.  In 1908, when he presented the concept in Bell's annual report, there were over 4000 local and regional telephone exchanges, most of which were eventually merged into the Bell System.  The economics of network effects were presented in a paper by Bell employee N. Lytkins in 1917, where the term network externality was used.</p>
<p>

Network effects were more recently popularized by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/289616.xml">
Robert Metcalfe</link></scientist>
, the founder of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/9499.xml">
Ethernet</link>. In selling the product, Metcalfe argued that customers needed Ethernet cards to grow above a certain critical mass if they were to reap the benefits of their network. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

According to Metcalfe, the rationale behind the sale of networking cards was that (1) the cost of cards was proportional to the number of cards installed, but (2) the value of the network was proportional to the square of the number of users. This was expressed algebraically as having a cost of "N", and a value of "N^2". While the actual numbers behind this definition were never firm, the concept allowed customers to share access to expensive resources like disk drives and printers, send e-mail, and access the internet.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Benefits </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This section needs additional  for .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Network_effect&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding . Unsourced material may be and removed. <it>(March 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

Network effects become significant after a certain subscription percentage has been achieved, called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/8015055.xml">
critical mass</link>. At the critical mass point, the value obtained from the good or service is greater than or equal to the price paid for the good or service. As the value of the good is determined by the user base, this implies that after a certain number of people have subscribed to the service or purchased the good, additional people will subscribe to the service or purchase the good due to the positive utility<b>:</b>price ratio.</p>
<p>

A key business concern must then be how to attract users prior to reaching critical mass. One way is to rely on extrinsic motivation, such as a payment, a fee waiver, or a request for friends to sign up. A more natural strategy is to build a system that has enough value <it>without</it> network effects, at least to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/242495.xml">
early adopters</link>. Then, as the number of users increases, the system becomes even more valuable and is able to attract a wider user base. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/1545771.xml">
Joshua Schachter</link></scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 has explained that he built <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/950308.xml">
Del.icio.us</link></web_site>
 along these lines - he built an online system where he could keep bookmarks for himself, such that even if no other user joined, it would still be valuable to him.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> It was relatively easy to build up a user base from zero because early adopters found enough value in the system outside of the network aspects. The same could be said for many other successful websites which derive value from network effects, e.g. <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/1178458.xml">
Flickr</link></web_site>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/1270655.xml">
MySpace</link></company>
.</p>
<p>

Beyond critical mass, the increasing number of subscribers generally cannot continue indefinitely.  After a certain point, most networks become either congested or saturated, stopping future uptake.  Congestion occurs due to overuse.  The applicable analogy is that of a telephone network.  While the number of users is below the congestion point, each additional user adds additional value to every other customer.  However, at some point the addition of an extra user exceeds the capacity of the existing system.  After this point, each additional user decreases the value obtained by every other user.  In practical terms, each additional user increases the total system <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/41323.xml">
load</link>, leading to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/349973.xml">
busy signal</link>s, the inability to get a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/162228.xml">
dial tone</link>, and poor <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/638229.xml">
customer support</link>.  The next critical point is where the value obtained again equals the price paid.  The network will cease to grow at this point, and the system must be enlarged.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/40949.xml">
congestion</link> point may be larger than the market size.  New <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/24107.xml">
Peer-to-peer</link> technological models may always defy congestion.  Peer-to-Peer systems, or "P2P," are networks designed to distribute load among their user pool. This theoretically allows true P2P networks to scale indefinitely.  The P2P based telephony service <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/424589.xml">
Skype</link></software>
 benefits greatly from this effect.  But <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/359644.xml">
market saturation</link> will still occur.</p>
<p>

Network effects are commonly mistaken for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/10517.xml">
economies of scale</link>, which result from business size rather than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/41285.xml">
interoperability</link> (see also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/21143.xml">
natural monopoly</link>).  To help clarify the distinction, people speak of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/2969016.xml">
demand side</link> vs. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/174607.xml">
supply side</link> economies of scale.  Classical economies of scale are on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/12594.xml">
production</link> side, while network effects arise on the demand side. Network effects are also mistaken for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/234138.xml">
economies of scope</link>.</p>
<p>

The network effect has a lot of similarities with the description of phenomenon in reinforcing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/213354.xml">
positive feedback</link> loops description of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/153208.xml">
system dynamics</link> (Sterman 2000). System dynamics could be used as a modeling method to describe such phenomenon such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/242029.xml">
word of mouth</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/6837693.xml">
Bass model</link> of marketing.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Business examples</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Financial exchanges</st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/28168.xml">
Stock exchange</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/243931.xml">
derivatives exchanges</link> feature a network effect.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/56121.xml">
Market liquidity</link> is a major determinant of transaction cost in the sale or purchase of a security, as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/1056980.xml">
bid-ask spread</link> exists between the price at which a purchase can be done versus the price at which the sale of the same security can be done.  As the number of buyers and sellers on an exchange increases, liquidity increases, and transaction costs decrease.  This then attracts a larger number of buyers and sellers to the exchange. See, for example, the work of Steve Wunsch (1999).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

The network advantage of financial exchanges is apparent in the difficulty that startup exchanges have in dislodging a dominant exchange.  For example, the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/429110.xml">
Chicago Board of Trade</link></company>
 has retained overwhelming dominance of trading in US <link>
Treasury Bond</link> futures despite the startup of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/1351428.xml">
Eurex</link> US trading of identical futures contracts.  Similarly, the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/351631.xml">
Chicago Mercantile Exchange</link></company>
 has maintained a dominance in trading of Eurobond interest rate futures despite a challenge from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/336834.xml">
Euronext.Liffe</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Software</st>
<p>

There are very strong network effects operating in the market for widely used computer software.  </p>
<p>

Take for example <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/20288.xml">
Microsoft Office</link></software>
.  For many people choosing an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/291070.xml">
office suite</link>, prime considerations include how valuable having learned that office suite will prove to potential <link>
employer</link>s, and how well the software interoperates with other users.  That is, since learning to use an office suite takes many hours, they want to invest that time learning the office suite that will make them most attractive to potential employers (or consulting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/7818.xml">
client</link>s, etc), and they also want to be able to share documents. (Additionally, an example of an indirect network effect in this case is the notable similarity in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/45249.xml">
user-interface</link>s and operability menus of most new software - since that similarity directly translates into less time spent learning new environments, therefore potentially greater acceptance and adoption of those products.)</p>
<p>

Similarly, finding already-trained <link>
employee</link>s is a big concern for employers when deciding which office suite to purchase or standardize on.  The lack of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/81193.xml">
cross-platform</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/45249.xml">
user-interface</link> standards results in a situation in which one firm is in control of almost 100% of the market.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> is a further example of network effect.  The most-vaunted advantage of Windows, and that most publicised by Microsoft, is that Windows is compatible with the widest range of hardware and software.  Although this claim was justified at some point of time, it was in reality the result of network effect: hardware and software manufacturers ensure that their products are compatible with Windows in order to have access to the large market of Windows users.  Thus, Windows is popular because it is well supported, but is well supported because it is popular. 
However, network effects need not lead to market dominance by one firm, when there are standards which allow multiple firms to interoperate, thus allowing the network externalities to benefit the entire market.  This is true for the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/34198.xml">
x86</link>-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18457137.xml">
personal computer</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/13615.xml">
hardware</link>, in which there are extremely strong market pressures to interoperate with pre-existing standards, but in which no one firm dominates in the market.  The same holds true for the market for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/1394709.xml">
long-distance telephone service</link> within the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
.  In fact, the existence of these types of networks discourages dominance of the market by one company, as it creates pressures which work against one company attempting to establish a proprietary protocol or to even distinguish itself by means of product differentiation.</p>
<p>

In cases in which the relevant communication protocols or interfaces are closed standards the network effect can give the company controlling those standards monopoly power. The <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
 corporation is widely seen by computer professionals as maintaining its monopoly through these means. One observed method Microsoft uses to put the network effect to its advantage is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/18934464.xml">
embrace and extend</link> (derisively called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/18934464.xml">
embrace, extend, and extinguish</link>).</p>
<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<subsidiary_company wordnetid="108003935" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/598311.xml">
Mirabilis</link></institution>
</subsidiary_company>
</company>
 is an <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/9282173.xml">
Israel</link></country>
i start-up which pioneered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/55951.xml">
instant messaging</link> (IM) and was bought by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/1397.xml">
America Online</link></company>
. By giving away their <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/15167.xml">
ICQ</link></software>
 product <link>
for free</link> and preventing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/41285.xml">
interoperability</link> between their client <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> and other products, they were able to temporarily dominate the market for instant messaging. Because of the network effect, new IM users gained much more value by choosing to use the Mirabilis system (and join its large network of users) than they would using a competing system. As was typical for that era, the company never made any attempt to generate profits from their dominant position before selling the company.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Web sites</st>

<p>

Many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
web site</link>s also feature a network effect. One example is web marketplaces and exchanges, in that the value of the marketplace to a new user is proportional to the number of other users in the market.  For example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/130495.xml">
eBay</link> would not be a particularly useful site if <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/62912.xml">
auction</link>s were not competitive. However, as the number of users grows on eBay, auctions grow more competitive, pushing up the prices of bids on items. This makes it more worthwhile to sell on eBay and brings more sellers onto eBay, which drives prices down again as this increases supply, while bringing more people onto eBay because there are more things being sold that people want. Essentially, as the number of users of eBay grows, prices fall and supply increases, and more and more people find the site to be useful.</p>
<p>

The collaborative encyclopedia <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/5043734.xml">
Wikipedia</link></web_site>
 also benefits from a network effect. The theory goes that as the number of editors grows, the quality of information on the website improves, encouraging more users to turn to it as a source of information; some of the new users in turn become editors, continuing the process.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/2041117.xml">
Social networking</link> websites are also good examples. The more people register onto a social networking website, the more useful the website is to its registrants.</p>
<p>

By contrast, the value of a news site is primarily proportional to the quality of the articles, not to the number of other people using the site.  Similarly, the first generation of search sites experienced little network effect, as the value of the site was based on the value of the search results.  This allowed <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 to win users away from <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo!</link></company>
 without much trouble, once users believed that Google's search results were superior.  Some commentators mistook the value of the Yahoo! brand (which does increase as more people know of it) for a network effect protecting its advertising business.</p>
<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/264303.xml">
Alexa Internet</link></company>
 uses a technology that tracks users' surfing patterns; thus Alexa's Related Sites results improve as more users use the technology. Alexa's network relies heavily on a small number of browser software relationships, which makes the network more vulnerable to competition.</p>
<p>

Google has also attempted to create a network effect in its advertising business with its Google AdSense service.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/736238.xml">
Google AdSense</link> places ads on many small sites, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/33645.xml">
blog</link>s, using Google technology to determine which ads are relevant to which blogs.  Thus, the service appears to aim to serve as an exchange (or ad network) for matching many advertisers with many small sites (such as blogs).  In general, the more blogs Google AdSense can reach, the more advertisers it will attract, making it the most attractive option for more blogs, and so on, making the network more valuable for all participants.</p>
<p>

Network effects were used as justification for some of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/3682503.xml">
dot-com</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/65533.xml">
business model</link>s in the late 1990s. These firms operated under the belief that when a new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/3736784.xml">
market</link> comes into being which contains strong network effects, firms should care more about growing their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/8012445.xml">
market share</link> than about becoming <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/18487619.xml">
profit</link>able.  This was believed because market share will determine which firm can set technical and marketing standards and thus determine the basis of future <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/181592.xml">
competition</link>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Technology lifecycle </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This section needs additional  for .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Network_effect&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding . Unsourced material may be and removed. <it>(May 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


If some existing technology or company whose benefits are largely based on network effects starts to lose market share against a challenger such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/47886.xml">
disruptive technology</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/227018.xml">
open standards</link> based competition, the benefits of network effects will reduce for the incumbent, and increase for the challenger. </p>
<p>

In this model, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/7027865.xml">
tipping point</link> is eventually reached at which the network effects of the challenger dominate those of the former incumbent, and the incumbent is forced into an accelerating decline, whilst the challenger takes over the incumbent's former position.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Lock-in </st>
<p>
 
Not surprisingly network economics became a hot topic after the diffusion of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> across <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/351220.xml">
academia</link>. Most people know only of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/65776.xml">
Metcalfe's law</link> as part of network effects. Network effects are notorious for causing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/146180.xml">
vendor lock-in</link> with the most-cited examples being <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
 products and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/25213.xml">
qwerty</link> keyboard. </p>
<p>

Network effects are a source of, but distinct from, lock-in. Lock-in can result from network effects, and network effects generate increasing returns that are associated with lock-in. However, the presence of a network effect does not guarantee that lock-in will result. For example, if the network is open there is no issue of lock-in.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Types of network effects </st>
<p>

There are two kinds of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/4095185.xml">
economic value</link> to be concerned about when thinking of network effects: </p>
<p>

Inherent — I value from using the product
Network — I value from you using the product</p>
<p>

Network value itself can be direct or indirect. </p>
<p>

Direct network value is an immediate result of other users adopting the same system.  Some examples of this are fax machines and email.</p>
<p>

Indirect is a secondary result of many people using the same system. For example, complementary goods are cheaper or more available  when many people adopt a standard. Toner may be cheaper for widely used printers.  An example of this is that Windows and Linux can be seen as competing not for users, but for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/179683.xml">
software developer</link>s, as shown by 
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.si.umich.edu/tprc/papers/2005/487/Two-sided.pdf">
Nicholas Economides and Evangelos Katsamakas</weblink>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Negative and positive network effects</st>

<p>

Positive network effects are obvious. More people means more interaction. <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/5043734.xml">
Wikipedia</link></web_site>
 itself depends on positive network effects. Negative network effects beyond lock-in also exist. </p>
<p>

Negative network effects result from resource limits. Consider the connection that overloads the freeway — or the competition for bandwidth. In fact, the automobile and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/9499.xml">
ethernet</link> congestion examples illustrate that there can be threshold limits. In this case, the n+1 person begins to decrease the value of a network if additional resources are not provided.</p>
<p>

The result is that in some networks there is an exclusion value. This is clear to anyone who has considered problems of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authentication</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/296356.xml">
trust</link> on the modern internet.</p>
<p>

Another negative network effect is provider complacency. The absence of viable competitors in a successful network can cause a provider to restrict resources, consider fee increases, or otherwise create an environment contrary to the users' benefit. These situations are typically accompanied by vocal complaints from the users. (In a competitive environment the users would simply change vendors rather than complain.) </p>
<p>

Classic examples are the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/50591.xml">
United States Postal Service</link></company>
 or telephone companies during the 1960s and 1970s. More recent examples include <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/130495.xml">
Ebay</link>'s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/297359.xml">
auction site</link>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/39229.xml">
Open system (computing)</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/227018.xml">
Open standard</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../906/262906.xml">
Open format</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<disapproval wordnetid="106709533" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<criticism wordnetid="106710546" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/146180.xml">
Vendor lock-in</link></criticism>
</method>
</disapproval>
</know-how>
</message>
</technique>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/728760.xml">
Path dependence</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/65776.xml">
Metcalfe's law</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/64333.xml">
Reed's law</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/188578.xml">
Betamax</link></medium>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/7169432.xml">
Two-sided market</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../953/235953.xml">
Technology lifecycle</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<scheme wordnetid="105905348" confidence="0.8">
<plan wordnetid="105898568" confidence="0.8">
<plan_of_action wordnetid="105902545" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/65533.xml">
Business model</link></plan_of_action>
</plan>
</scheme>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/171323.xml">
Bandwagon effect</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<consequence wordnetid="111410625" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/561237.xml">
Cluster effect</link></consequence>
</phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/1385393.xml">
The Long Tail</link></group>
</collection>
</law>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/251755.xml">
List of management topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
Graph Theory</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
Semantic Web</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <social_science wordnetid="106143154" confidence="0.8">
<knowledge_domain wordnetid="105999266" confidence="0.8">
<economics wordnetid="106149484" confidence="0.8">
<discipline wordnetid="105996646" confidence="0.8">
<science wordnetid="105999797" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/1169924.xml">
Returns to scale</link></science>
</discipline>
</economics>
</knowledge_domain>
</social_science>
 (increasing returns)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.forbes.com/forbes/2007/0507/052.html">
It's All In Your Head - Forbes.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.technologyreview.com/tr35/Profile.aspx?Cand=T&amp;TRID=432">
TR35 2006 Young Innovator: Joshua Schachter, 32 (Del.icio.us [Yahoo</weblink>)]"&#32;&#32;(2006). <it>Technology Review</it>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-20</link>.&#32;“"For a system to be successful, the users of the system have to perceive that it's directly valuable to them," Schachter says. "If you need scale in order to create value, it's hard to get scale, because there's little incentive for the first people to use the product. Ideally, the system should be useful for user number one."”</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
Wunsch, Steve (1999). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stevewunsch.com/maydaymayday.htm">
Mayday, Mayday</weblink>"</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nuff.ox.ac.uk/users/klemperer/Farrell_KlempererWP.pdf">
Coordination and Lock-In: Competition with Switching Costs and Network Effects</weblink>, Joseph Farrell and Paul Klemperer.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.utdallas.edu/~liebowit/palgrave/network.html">
Network Externalities (Effects)</weblink>, S. J. Liebowitz, Stephen E. Margolis.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://oz.stern.nyu.edu/io/network.html">
An Overview of Network Effects</weblink>, Arun Sundararajan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stern.nyu.edu/networks/">
The Economics of Networks</weblink>, Nicholas Economides.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</consequence>
</model>
</article>
