<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:32:36[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Inferior vena cava filter</title>
<id>2267902</id>
<revision>
<id>233751642</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-23T15:48:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cydebot</username>
<id>1215485</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> radiology</category>
<category> medical treatments</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

An <b>inferior vena cava filter</b>, also <b>IVC filter</b> a type of vascular filter, is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medical</link> device that is implanted into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/242146.xml">
inferior vena cava</link> to prevent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/207165.xml">
pulmonary emboli</link> (PEs). 
<image location="right" width="300px" src="Mar07_090.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Inferior vena cava filter - Gunther Tulip.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
</caption>
</image>

IVC filters are used in case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/464811.xml">
contraindication</link> to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/178212.xml">
anticoagulation</link>, failure of anticoagulation or complication to anticoagulation in patients who have a venous thromboembolic disease or in prophylactic use for patients with a high risk of pulmonary embolism.
<sec>
<st>
Placement</st>

<p>

IVC filters are placed endovascularly, meaning that they are inserted via the blood vessels.  Historically, IVC filters were placed surgically, but as designs changed they could  be placed via the groin through a thin tube or catheter.  With modern filters which can be compressed into much thinner <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/291838.xml">
catheter</link>s, however, access to the venous system can be obtained either via the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/2072649.xml">
femoral vein</link> (the large vein in the groin),the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/1516228.xml">
internal jugular vein</link> (the large vein in the neck.) or via the arm veins with one design.  Choice of route depends mainly on the amount and location of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/183058.xml">
blood clot</link> within the venous system.  To place the filter, a catheter is guided into the IVC using fluoroscopic guidance, then the filter is pushed through the catheter and deployed into the desired location, usually just below the junction of the IVC and the lowest <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/1580594.xml">
renal vein</link>.</p>
<p>

Review of prior cross-sectional imaging or a venogram of the IVC is performed before deploying the filter to assess for potential anatomic variations, thrombi within the IVC, or areas of stenoses, as well as to estimate the diameter of the IVC.  The size of the IVC may affect which filter is deployed, as some (such as the Birds Nest) are approved to accommodate larger cavas.  There are situations where the filter is placed above the renal veins (e.g. pregnant patients or women of childbearing age, renal or gonadal vein thromboses, etc.).  Also, if there is duplication of the IVC, the filter is placed above the confluence of the two IVCs or a filter can be placed within each IVC.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Indications for use</st>

<p>

Most filters are placed for the following reasons. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Failure of anticoagulation</b>; eg development of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) or pulmonary emboli (PE) despite adequate anticoagulation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Contraindications to anticoagulation</b>; eg a patient at risk of PE who has another condition that puts them at risk of bleeding, such as a recent bleed into the brain, or a patient about to undergo major surgery</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Large clots</b> in the vena cava or iliac veins</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Patients at high risk</b> of having a PE</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Retrieval</st>

<p>

Most IVC filters are permanent, but some filters are now available that are "retrievable."  Retrievable filters are fitted with some sort of device (that varies from model to model) that allows them to be pulled back into a catheter (technically a "sheath") and removed from the body, often through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/1283378.xml">
Jugular vein</link>.  Previously, filters that had been in the IVC for less than three weeks were considered suitable to attempt retrieval, as filters that have been in place longer might have been overgrown by cells from the IVC wall and there was an increased risk of IVC injury if the filter is dislodged. Newer designs, and developments in techniques mean that some filters can now be left in for prolonged periods and retrievals after a year are now being reported. This would include the ALN, Option, Tulip and Celect filters.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
IVC filter brands</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 B Braun Tempofilter IVC filter (retrievable)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 B Braun VenaTech LGM IVC filter (no longer sold)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 B Braun VenaTech LP IVC filter</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bard G2 IVC (retrievable, unlimited indwell time)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bard Recovery IVC filter (retrievable) (no longer sold) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Boston Greenfield IVC filter</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cook Birds Nest IVC filter</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cook Celect IVC filter (not approved for retrieval in the US)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cook Gunther Tulip IVC filter (retrievable)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cordis OptEase IVC filter (retrievable, 23 day indwell time)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cordis TrapEase IVC filter</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mobin-Uddin Umbrella IVC filter (no longer sold) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ALN IVC filter (retrievable)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rex Medical Option IVC filter (retrievable) (in clinical trials) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Simon Nitinol IVC filter</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Gunther Tulip IVC Filter. Cook Medical. URL: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cookmedical.com/di/di_front/images/dif_bu1.jpg">
http://www.cookmedical.com/di/di_front/images/dif_bu1.jpg</weblink>. Accessed on: November 24, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="2">
OptEase Retreivable Vena Cava Filter: http://www.jnjgateway.com/home.jhtml?loc=USENG&amp;page=viewContent&amp;contentId=09008b9880388ef7&amp;parentId=09008b9880388ef7</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/207165.xml">
Pulmonary embolism</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/570153.xml">
Deep vein thrombosis</link></disease>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emedicine.com/radio/topic762.htm">
IVC filters</weblink> - emedicine.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://chorus.rad.mcw.edu/doc/02068.html">
IVC filters</weblink> - Medical College of Wisconsin</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gpnotebook.co.uk/cache/74121255.htm">
IVC filter</weblink> - GPnotebook.co.uk</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://patients.uptodate.com/topic.asp?file=vascular/4809">
Inferior vena caval filters</weblink> - UpToDate.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.americanheritage.com/articles/magazine/it/2006/1/2006_1_34.shtml">
history of Lazar Greenfield and his filter</weblink> - Invention &amp; Technology</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bostonscientific.com/med_specialty/deviceDetail.jsp?task=tskBasicDevice.jsp&amp;sectionId=4&amp;relId=3,126,127,128&amp;deviceId=12003">
Greenfield filter</weblink> - a popular IVC filter from <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/1313984.xml">
Boston Scientific</link></company>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
