<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:33:24[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<family  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108078020">
<header>
<title>Scale-free network</title>
<id>227155</id>
<revision>
<id>244044437</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T01:51:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mdd</username>
<id>113850</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Graph families</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>scale-free network</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/1704711.xml">
network</link> whose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/2129782.xml">
degree distribution</link> follows a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/24522.xml">
power law</link>, at least asymptotically.  That is, the fraction <it>P</it>(<it>k</it>) of nodes in the network having <it>k</it> connections to other nodes goes for large values of <it>k</it> as <it>P</it>(<it>k</it>) ~ <it>k</it>−<it>γ</it> where <it>γ</it> is a constant whose value is typically in the range 2max is the maximum value of <it>s</it>(<it>h</it>) for <it>h</it> in the set of all graphs with an identical degree distribution to <it>g</it>.  This gives a metric between 0 and 1, such that graphs with low <it>S</it>(<it>g</it>) are "scale-rich", and graphs with <it>S</it>(<it>g</it>) close to 1 are "scale-free".  This definition captures the notion of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/28782.xml">
self-similarity</link> implied in the name "scale-free".
<sec>
<st>
Characteristics and examples </st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="400px" src="Scale-free_network_sample.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Random network (a) and scale-free network (b). In the scale-free network, the larger hubs are highlighted.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

As with all systems characterized by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/24522.xml">
power law</link> distribution, the most notable characteristic in a scale-free network is the relative commonness of vertices with a degree that greatly exceeds the average. The highest-degree nodes are often called "hubs", and are thought to serve specific purposes in their networks, although this depends greatly on the domain.</p>
<p>

The power law distribution highly influences the network topology. It turns out that the major hubs are closely followed by smaller ones. These ones, in turn, are followed by other nodes with an even smaller degree and so on. This hierarchy allows for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../729/2573729.xml">
fault tolerant</link> behavior. Since failures occur at random and the vast majority of nodes are those with small degree, the likelihood that a hub would be affected is almost negligible. Even if such event occurs, the network will not lose its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/87141.xml">
connectedness</link>, which is guaranteed by the remaining hubs. On the other hand, if we choose a few major hubs and take them out of the network, it simply falls apart and is turned into a set of rather isolated graphs. Thus hubs are both the strength of scale-free networks and their <parlance wordnetid="107081177" confidence="0.8">
<formulation wordnetid="107069948" confidence="0.8">
<expressive_style wordnetid="107066659" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/380175.xml">
Achilles' heel</link></expressive_style>
</formulation>
</parlance>
.</p>
<p>

Another important characteristic of scale-free networks is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/1457636.xml">
clustering coefficient</link> distribution, which decreases as the node degree increases. This distribution also follows a power law. That means that the low-degree nodes belong to very dense sub-graphs and those sub-graphs are connected to each other through hubs.  Consider a social network in which nodes are people and links are acquaintance relationships between people. It is easy to see that people tend to form communities, i.e., small groups in which everyone knows everyone (one can think of such community as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/85816.xml">
complete graph</link>). In addition, the members of a community also have a few acquaintance relationships to people outside that community. Some people, however, are so related to other people (e.g., celebrities, politicians) that they are connected to a large number of communities. Those people may be considered the hubs responsible for the small world phenomenon.</p>
<p>

At present, the more specific characteristics of scale-free networks can only be discussed in either the context of the generative mechanism used to create them, or the context of a particular real-world network thought to be scale-free. For instance, networks generated by preferential attachment typically place the high-degree vertices in the middle of the network, connecting them together to form a core, with progressively lower-degree nodes making up the regions between the core and the periphery. Many interesting results are known for this subclass of scale-free networks. For instance, the random removal of even a large fraction of vertices impacts the overall connectedness of the network very little, suggesting that such topologies could be useful for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/592687.xml">
security</link>, while targeted attacks destroys the connectedness very quickly. Other scale-free networks, which place the high-degree vertices at the periphery, do not exhibit these properties; notably, the structure of the Internet is more like this latter kind of network than the kind built by preferential attachment. Indeed, many of the results about scale-free networks have been claimed to apply to the Internet, but are disputed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/2917851.xml">
Internet researchers</link> and engineers.</p>
<p>

As with most disordered networks, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/1457254.xml">
small world network</link> model, the average distance between two vertices in the network is very small relative to a highly ordered network such as a lattice. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/1457636.xml">
clustering coefficient</link> of scale-free networks can vary significantly depending on other topological details, and there are now generative mechanisms that allow one to create such networks that have a high density of triangles.</p>
<p>

It is interesting that Cohen and Havlin proved that uncorrelated power-law graph having 2&nbsp;&nbsp;γ&nbsp;&nbsp;3 will also have ultrasmall diameter <it>d</it> ~ ln&nbsp;ln&nbsp;<it>N</it>. So from the practical point of view, the diameter of a growing scale-free network might be considered almost constant.</p>
<p>

Although many real-world networks are thought to be scale-free, the evidence remains inconclusive, primarily because the generative mechanisms proposed have not been rigorously validated against the real-world data. As such, it is too early to rule out alternative hypotheses. A few examples of networks claimed to be scale-free include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
Social network</link>s, including collaboration networks. An example that has been studied extensively is <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/43607.xml">
the collaboration of movie actors in films</link></network>
</psychological_feature>
</group>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</system>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
Protein</link>-Protein interaction networks.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sexual partners in humans, which affects the dispersal of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/19019270.xml">
sexually transmitted disease</link>s.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Many kinds of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/4122592.xml">
computer network</link>s, including the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/29109.xml">
Semantic networks</link>. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Generative models</st>

<p>

These scale-free networks do not arise by chance alone. <link>
Erdős</link> and Rényi (1960) studied a model of growth for graphs in which, at each step, two nodes are chosen uniformly at random and a link is inserted between them. The properties of these <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/358477.xml">
random graph</link>s are not consistent with the properties observed in scale-free networks, and therefore a model for this growth process is needed.  </p>
<p>

The scale-free properties of the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
Web</link></invention>
 have been studied, and its distribution of links is very close to a power law, because there are a few Web sites with huge numbers of links, which
benefit from a good placement in search engines and an established presence
on the Web. Those sites are the ones that attract more of the new links. This has been called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/21143.xml">
winner takes all</link> phenomenon.  </p>
<p>

The mostly widely known generative model for a subset of scale-free networks is Barabási and Albert's (1999) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/6047029.xml">
rich get richer</link> generative model in which each new Web page creates links to existing Web pages with a probability distribution which is not uniform, but
proportional to the current in-degree of Web pages. This model was originally discovered by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/1234272.xml">
Derek J. de Solla Price</link></scholar>
</historian>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 in 1965 under the term <b>cumulative advantage</b>, but did not reach popularity until Barabási rediscovered the results under its current name (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/8286726.xml">
BA Model</link>). According to this process, a page with many in-links will attract more in-links than a
regular page. This generates a power-law but the resulting graph differs
from the actual Web graph in other properties such as the presence of small
tightly connected communities. More general models and networks characteristics have been proposed and studied (for a review see the book by Dorogovtsev and <link>
Mendes</link>).</p>
<p>

A different generative model is the <b>copy</b> model studied by Kumar et al. (2000),
in which new nodes choose an existent node at random and copy a fraction of the links of the existent node. This also
generates a power law.</p>
<p>

However, if we look at communities of interests in a specific topic, discarding the major hubs of the Web, the distribution of links is no longer a power law but resembles more a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/21462.xml">
normal distribution</link>, as observed by Pennock et al. (2002) in the communities of the home pages of universities, public companies, newspapers and scientists.  Based on these observations, they propose a generative model that mixes preferential attachment with a baseline probability of gaining a link.</p>
<p>

The growth of the networks (adding new nodes) is not a necessary condition for creating a scale-free topology. Dangalchev (2004) gives examples of generating static scale-free networks. Another possibility (Caldarelli et al. 2002) is to consider the structure as static and draw a link between vertices according to a particular property of the two vertices involved. Once specified the statistical distribution for these vertices properties (fitnesses), it turns out that in some circumstances also static networks develop scale-free properties.</p>
<p>

Recently, Manev and Manev (Med. Hypotheses, 2005) proposed that small world networks may be operative in adult brain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/740746.xml">
neurogenesis</link>. Adult neurogenesis has been observed in mammalian brains, including those of humans, but a question remains: how do new neurons become functional in the adult brain? It is proposed that the random addition of only a few new neurons functions as a maintenance system for the brain's "small-world" networks. Randomly added to an orderly network, new links enhance signal propagation speed and synchronizability. Newly generated neurons are ideally suited to become such links: they are immature, form more new connections compared to mature ones, and their number but not their precise location may be maintained by continuous proliferation and dying off. Similarly, it is envisaged that the treatment of brain pathologies by cell transplantation would also create new random links in small-world networks and that even a small number of successfully incorporated new neurons may be functionally important.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/6554098.xml">
Social-circles network model</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 - a more generalized generative model for many "real-world networks" of which the scale-free network is a special case</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/358477.xml">
Random graph</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Albert R. and Barabási A.-L., <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nd.edu/~networks/Publication%20Categories/publications.htm#anchor-allpub0001">
"Statistical mechanics of complex networks"</weblink>, Rev. Mod. Phys. 74, 47–97 (2002).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Amaral, LAN, Scala, A., Barthelemy, M., Stanley, HE., <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0001458">
"Classes of behavior of small-world networks"</weblink>. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (USA) 97:11149-11152 (2000).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Barabási, Albert-László <it>Linked: How Everything is Connected to Everything Else</it>, 2004 ISBN 0-452-28439-2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Barabási, Albert-László <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nd.edu/~networks/Publication%20Categories/01%20Review%20Articles/ScaleFree_Scientific%20Ameri%20288,%2060-69%20(2003).pdf">
"Scale-Free Networks"</weblink>. <it>Scientific American</it>, 288:60-69, May 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Barabási, Albert-László and Albert, Réka. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/9910332">
"Emergence of scaling in random networks"</weblink>. <it>Science</it>, 286:509-512, October 15, 1999.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dan Braha and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/9251395.xml">
Yaneer Bar-Yam</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://necsi.org/affiliates/braha/Topology--of--Large--Scale--Design--PRE69.pdf">
Topology of Large-Scale Engineering Problem-Solving Networks</weblink>" Phys. Rev. E 69, 016113 (2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caldarelli G. "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Physics/Mathematicalphysics/~~/dmlldz11c2EmY2k9OTc4MDE5OTIxMTUxNw==">
 Scale-Free Networks"</weblink> Oxford University Press, Oxford (2007).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Caldarelli G., Capocci A., De Los Rios P., Muñoz M.A., <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0207366">
"Scale-free networks from varying vertex intrinsic fitness"</weblink> Physical Review Letters 89, 258702 (2002).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dangalchev, Ch., <it>Generation models for scale-free networks</it>,  Physica A, 338,(2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dorogovtsev, S.N. and Mendes, J.F.F., <it>Evolution of Networks: from biological networks to the Internet and WWW</it>, Oxford University Press, 2003, ISBN 0-19-851590-1</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dorogovtsev, S.N. and Mendes, J.F.F. and Samukhin, A.N., "Structure of Growing Networks: Exact Solution of the Barabási--Albert's Model", Phys. Rev. Lett. 85, 4633 (2000) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dorogovtsev, S.N. and Mendes, J.F.F., Evolution of networks, Advances in Physics 51, 1079-1187 (2002)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Erdős, P. and Rényi, A. <it>Random graphs</it>. Publication of the Mathematical Institute of the Hungarian Academy of Science, 5, pages 17-61, 1960.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Faloutsos, M., Faloutsos, P. and Faloutsos, C., <it>On power-law relationships of the internet topology</it> Comp. Comm. rev. 29, 251, 1999.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Li, L., Alderson, D., Tanaka, R., Doyle, J.C., Willinger, W., <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0501169">
Towards a Theory of Scale-Free Graphs: Definition, Properties, and Implications (Extended Version)</weblink>. Internet Mathematics, 2005. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kumar, R., Raghavan, P., Rajagopalan, S., Sivakumar, D., Tomkins, A., and Upfal, E.:  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.brown.edu/research/webagent/focs-2000.pdf">
Stochastic models for the web graph</weblink>. In Proceedings of the 41st Annual Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS), pages 57-65, Redondo Beach, CA, USA. IEEE CS Press, 2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Manev R., Manev H.; Med. Hypotheses 2005;64(1):114-7 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15533625&amp;query_hl=26">
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15533625&amp;query_hl=26</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Matlis, Jan. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.computerworld.com/networkingtopics/networking/story/0,10801,75539,00.html">
 Scale-Free Networks</weblink>.  ComputerWorld. November 4, 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Newman, Mark E. J. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0303516">
The structure and function of complex networks</weblink>, 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pastor-Satorras, R.,Vespignani, A.,"Evolution and Structure of the Internet: A Statistical Physics Approach",Cambridge University Press, 2004, ISBN 0521826985</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Pennock, D. M., Flake, G. W., Lawrence, S., Glover, E. J., and Giles, C. L.: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.modelingtheweb.com/">
Winners don't take all: Characterizing the competition for links on the web</weblink>. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 99(8):5207-5211, 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Robb, John.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas/2004/05/scalefree_terro.html">
Scale-Free Networks and Terrorism</weblink>, 2004.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Keller, E.F. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/cgi-bin/abstract/112092785/ABSTRACT">
Revisiting "scale-free" networks</weblink>, BioEssays 27(10) 1060-1068, 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

R. N. Onody and P. A. de Castro, <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/cond-mat/0409609">
Complex Network Study of Brazilian Soccer Player</weblink></it>,  Phys. Rev. E 70, 037103 (2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Reuven Cohen, Shlomo Havlin, "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0205476">
Scale-Free Networks are Ultrasmall</weblink>" Phys. Rev. Lett. 90, 058701 (2003)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
  <cite style="font-style:normal">Steyvers, Mark; Joshua B. Tenenbaum&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.leaonline.com/doi/abs/10.1207/s15516709cog2901_3">
The Large-Scale Structure of Semantic Networks: Statistical Analyses and a Model of Semantic Growth</weblink>". <it>Cognitive Science</it>&#32;<b>29</b>&#32;(1): 41–78. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1207%2Fs15516709cog2901_3">
10.1207/s15516709cog2901_3</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</family>
</article>
