<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:28:52[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<type  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105840188">
<header>
<title>Whole life insurance</title>
<id>2282039</id>
<revision>
<id>240932766</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-25T16:44:07Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mohonu</username>
<id>3843455</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Types of insurance</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Whole Life Insurance</b>, or <b>Whole of Life Assurance</b> (in the Commonwealth), is a life insurance policy that remains in force for the insured's <it>whole life</it> and requires (in most cases) premiums to be paid every year into the policy.
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

All life insurance was originally term insurance. However, because term life insurance only pays a claim upon death within the stated term, most term insurance policy holders became upset over the idea that they could be paying premiums for 20 or 30 years and then wind up with nothing to show for it.</p>
<p>

In response to market pressures, actuaries conceived of an insurance policy with level premium payments that were higher than traditional term insurance contracts. These contracts would offer a "cash value", which was designed to be a cash reserve that would build up against the known claim - the death benefit. These policies would also credit interest to the cash value account and upon maturity of the contract (usually at age 95 or 100), the cash value would equal the death benefit.</p>
<p>

This produced a benefit to both the policy owner and the insurance company. By guaranteeing the death benefit and the cash value, the policy owner was assured that insurance coverage would be in force when the insured died. The insurance company benefited because with every premium payment made, the net amount at risk, and thus the cost of insurance, was reduced.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Types</st>
<p>

There are several types of whole life insurance policies.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> <link>
New York State</link> defines six traditional forms: non-participating (aka "non par"), participating, indeterminate premium, economic, limited pay, and single premium.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  A newer type is known generally as interest sensitive whole life.  Other jurisdictions may classify them differently, and not all companies offer all types.  It should be noted that there are as many types of insurance policies as can be written in their contracts while staying within the law's guidelines.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Non-Participating</st>
<p>

All values related to the policy (death benefits, cash surrender values, premiums) are usually determined at policy issue, for the life of the contract, and usually cannot be altered after issue. </p>
<p>

This means that the insurance company assumes all risk of future performance versus the actuaries' estimates. If future claims are underestimated, the insurance company makes up the difference.  On the other hand, if the actuaries' estimates on future death claims are high, the insurance company will retain the difference.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Participating</st>
<p>

In a <link>
participating policy</link> (also <it>par</it> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
USA</link>, and known as a <it>with-profits policy</it> in the <link>
Commonwealth</link>), the insurance company shares the excess profits (variously called <it>dividends</it> or <it>refunds</it> in the USA, <it>bonus</it> in  the Commonwealth) with the policyholder.  The greater the success of the company's performance, the greater the dividend.  For a <link>
mutual life insurance</link> company, participation also implies a degree of ownership of the mutuality.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Indeterminate Premium</st>
<p>

Similar to non-participating, except that the premium may vary year to year.  However, the premium will never exceed the maximum premium guaranteed in the policy.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Economic</st>
<p>

A blending of participating and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/661096.xml">
term life insurance</link>, wherein a part of the dividends is used to purchase additional term insurance. This can generally yield a higher death benefit, at a cost to long term cash value. In some policy years the dividends may be below projections, causing the death benefit in those years to decrease.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Limited Pay</st>
<p>

Similar to a participating policy, but instead of paying annual premiums for life, they are only due for a certain number of years, such as 20.  The policy may also be set up to be fully paid up at a certain age, such as 65 or 80.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>  The policy itself continues for the life of the insured.  These policies would typically cost more up front, since the insurance company needs to build up sufficient cash value within the policy during the payment years to fund the policy for the remainder of the insured's life.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Single Premium</st>
<p>

A form of limited pay, where the pay period is a single large payment up front.  These policies typically have fees during early policy years should the policyholder cash it in.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Interest Sensitive </st>
<p>

This type is fairly new, and is also known as either <it>excess interest</it> or <it>current assumption</it> whole life.  The policies are a mixture of traditional whole life and <link>
 universal life</link>. Instead of using dividends to augment <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/3385753.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Guaranteed+cash+value+%22])">
guaranteed cash value</link> accumulation, the interest on the policy's cash value varies with current market conditions.  Like whole life, death benefit remains constant for life.  Like universal life, the premium payment might vary, but not above the maximum premium guaranteed within the policy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Requirements </st>
<p>

Whole life insurance typically requires that the owner pay premiums for the life of the policy.  There are some arrangements that let the policy be "paid up",  which means that no further payments are ever required, in as few as 5 years, or with even a single large premium.  Typically if the payor doesn't make a large premium payment at the outset of the life insurance contract, then he is not allowed to begin making them later in the contract life.  In contrast,  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/979677.xml">
Universal life insurance</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 generally allows more flexibility in premium payment.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Guarantees </st>
<p>

The company generally will guarantee that the policy's cash values will increase regardless of the performance of the company or its experience with death claims (again compared to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/979677.xml">
universal life insurance</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/633515.xml">
variable universal life insurance</link> which can increase the costs and decrease the cash values of the policy).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Liquidity</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/3385753.xml">
Cash value</link>s are considered liquid enough to be used for investment capital, but only if the owner is financially healthy enough to continue making premium payments.  Cash value access is tax free up to the point of total premiums paid, and the rest may be accessed tax free in the form of policy loans.  If the policy lapses, taxes would be due on outstanding loans.  If the insured dies, death benefit is reduced by the amount of any outstanding loan balance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

Internal rates of return for participating policies may be much better than universal life and interest sensitive whole life because their cash values are invested in the money market and bonds, while par whole life cash values are invested in the life insurance company and its general account, which may be in real estate and the stock market.  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/633515.xml">
Variable universal life insurance</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 may outperform whole life because the owner can direct investments in sub-accounts that may do better.  If an owner desires a conservative position for his cash values, par whole life is indicated.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa5346/is_200109/ai_n21477882/print">
Life insurance: Dispelling illusions</weblink>".&#32;  The CPA Journal&#32;(Sept. 2001).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-24</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.twintierfinancial.com/the_uncommon_cents/2008/03/life-insurance.html">
Life Insurance Basics - It's Not As Bad As You Think</weblink>".&#32;  David C. Lewis, RFA&#32;(March  2008).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-24</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ins.state.ny.us/consumer/life/cli_basic.htm">
Basic Types of Policies</weblink>"&#32;(html).&#32;  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ins.state.ny.us/">
New York State Insurance Department</weblink>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Alexander B. Grannis, Chair.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://assembly.state.ny.us/Reports/Ins/199803/insureport.html#t08">
The Feeling's Not Mutual</weblink>"&#32;(html).&#32;  New York State Assembly.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.abi.org.uk/Display/default.asp?Menu_ID=1140&amp;Menu_All=1,946,1140&amp;Child_ID=413#Whole">
A Guide to Life Insurance</weblink>"&#32;(html).&#32;  The Association of British Insurers.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-16</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.life-line.org/build/glossary_c/index.php?pt=glossaryc&amp;m=blank#cur">
glossary</weblink>"&#32;(html).&#32;  Life and Health Insurance Foundation for Education.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.assetprotectionbook.com/whole_life.htm">
Whole Life Insurance</weblink>"&#32;(html).&#32;  The Asset Protection Book.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-17</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/383367.xml">
Life insurance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/527415.xml">
Permanent life insurance</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/661096.xml">
Term life insurance</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.inheritancenetwork.org/life-insurance/life-insurance-comparison.php">
Chart Comparing Different Types of Life Insurance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iii.org/individuals/life/">
Learn About Life Insurance</weblink> - Insurance Information Institute Life Insurance Learning Center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.life-line.org">
The Life and Health Insurance Foundation for Education</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eh.net/encyclopedia/?article=murphy.life.insurance.us">
A History of Life Insurance in the United States through World War I</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ins.state.il.us/Consumer/SlaveryReporting.nsf/summaryreport?OpenPage">
Illinois Department of Financial &amp; Professional Regulation, Division of Insurance, Slavery Era Policies Report August 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.naifa.org/about/ethics.cfm">
Code of Ethics, National Association of Insurance and Financial Advisors</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>












</sec>
</bdy>
</type>
</article>
