<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:34:11[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<social_event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107288639">
<contest  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107456188">
<game  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100456199">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<header>
<title>Axis &amp; Allies (2004 video game)</title>
<id>2295738</id>
<revision>
<id>238526117</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-15T06:15:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>WinterSpw</username>
<id>2881121</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>2004 video games</category>
<category>Real-time strategy video games</category>
<category>Computer wargames</category>
<category>World War II video games</category>
<category>Windows games</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox VG</name>
<parameters>

<image width="256px" src="Axis_&amp;_Allies_(2004)_Coverart.jpg">
</image>
<genre>
<genre wordnetid="105845332" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/77251.xml">
Real-time strategy</link></kind>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</genre>
</genre>
<platforms>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link></platforms>
<requirements>
Windows 98/SE/Me/2000/XP operating system, Pentium III 1.5 GHz processor, 256 MB <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/25847.xml">
RAM</link>, 1.4 GB free hard disk space, 64 MB compliant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/426408.xml">
SVGA</link> with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/6961053.xml">
Hardware T&amp;L</link> video card, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/8506.xml">
DirectX</link></software>
 version 9.0c or higher, 56 kbit/s/Cable/DSL Internet connection</requirements>
<publisher>
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
Atari</link></company>
</publisher>
<released>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/21461.xml">
November 2</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link></released>
<input>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/18842281.xml">
Keyboard</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/7056.xml">
mouse</link></input>
<title>
Axis &amp; Allies (2004 video game)</title>
<developer>
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/1372745.xml">
TimeGate Studios</link></company>
</developer>
<modes>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/497340.xml">
Single player</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/350680.xml">
Multiplayer</link></modes>
<media>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/6429.xml">
Compact Disc</link></media>
<ratings>
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/169836.xml">
ESRB</link></company>
: Teen (T)</ratings>
</parameters>
</template>


<b><it>Axis &amp; Allies</it></b> (abbreviated to A&amp;A), also called <b><it>Axis &amp; Allies RTS</it></b>, is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/77251.xml">
real-time strategy</link> <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
World War II</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/1336512.xml">
computer game</link> developed by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/1372745.xml">
TimeGate Studios</link></company>
 and published by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
Atari</link></company>
. The game was released on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/21461.xml">
November 2</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> It is based on the popular board game <game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/173475.xml">
Axis &amp; Allies</link></game>
 from <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/7576369.xml">
Milton Bradley</link></person>
 and also on TimeGate's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/2965507.xml">
Kohan series</link>. It is set in the years just after Japan and the United States had entered into the war.<p>

The game incorporates two gameplay modes: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/77251.xml">
real-time</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/123428.xml">
turn-based</link> modes. However, turn-based gameplay is only present in WWII mode, and thus gameplay is mainly focused on the real-time strategy genre.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Gameplay</st>
<p>

<it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> allows the player to assume the role of a military general of one of the five <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/427646.xml">
superpowers</link> of World War II: the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
Great Britain</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/21212.xml">
Germany</link></country>
, <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/26779.xml">
Russia</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/183897.xml">
Japan</link></country>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The five nations have military units corresponding to that of their nationality, and each general of the five nations have unique special operations, such as using a carpet bomb or deploying a secret agent.</p>
<p>

The primary objective of gameplay is to destroy the opposing enemy military forces, although some campaigns and maps will require other objectives to be completed first, such as capturing certain cities or defending a specific area, in order to achieve victory. <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> also has a "City Control" percentage toggle option that can be enabled, in which the winner of the battle goes to the first side/team to capture a set percentage of cities on the map.</p>
<p>

Gameplay supports up to eight players in a single battle in both singleplayer and multiplayer.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Resources</st>
<p>

<it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> focuses on the production of three major resources: money, ammo, and oil.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Money is obtained from a constant flow of revenue received from a Corps Hq, Division Hqs, and cities. Unlike money, both the resources of ammo and oil can be obtained from just about any building. Money is used to purchase units and technologies, while ammo and oil are used for unit upkeep.</p>
<p>

If the upkeep of either ammo or oil are not met, a player's monetary income will be reduced. If the upkeep of ammo and oil worsens, a drain of money can occur (a negative income). At this point, if there is no more money to be drained away, unsupplied regiments on the map will slowly receive damage until they are either destroyed or the upkeep is repaired.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Structures</st>
<p>

There are various types of structures in the game. Each nation has the same types of structures of each other, but they have their own unique decor specific to that nation.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Corps Hq</st>
<p>

In any battle, the player usually starts out with a Corps Hq building. The Corps Hq is the backbone to the player's military and economy, as it is the only building where all of the player's building trucks will be deployed from. Sometimes however, only battleships and/or carriers will be given to the player at the start of the game. In this situation, the player would first need to launch and unpack a Corps Hq truck from a battleship onto nearby land, and then continue deploying other trucks from the Corps Hq. These trucks can then be unpacked into makeshift buildings and structures to create a military base.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Division Hqs</st>
<p>

Division Hqs are perhaps the most important buildings in the game. Almost all military regiments are deployed from Division Hqs, and they are the only buildings that can generate income aside from the Corps Hq and cities. There are four types of Division Hqs: Infantry, Airborne, Mechanized, and Armor.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Support buildings</st>
<p>

Support buildings are the buildings that allow further technologies to be researched, aside from the Corps Hq and the Airfield, and one of the three is required to be unpacked before specific regiments are able to be deployed. There are only three support buildings: the Engineer Brigade, the Motor Pool, and the Artillery Brigade.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Airfields</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/185235.xml">
Airfields</link> are structures that produce two types of aircraft: fighters and bombers. They consist of one hangar that can hold up to four <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/10929.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22World+War+II%22])">
fighter planes</link> and two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/3446.xml">
bomber planes</link> for deploying bombing runs and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/146911.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Airborne+reconnaissance%22])">
air reconnaissance</link>. In order to deploy an Airfield though, the player must first have unpacked an Engineer Brigade, Motor Pool, and Artillery Brigade on the map. The Airfield is also the most expensive structure that can be purchased in the game, costing up to $400 in money.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Depots</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/1398444.xml">
Depots</link> are buildings used to boost ammo and oil production as well as to extend supply lines. There are three types of depots: Supply depots, Ammo depots, and Oil depots. Unlike ammo and oil depots, supply depots don't count towards the building limit.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Bunkers</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../205/92205.xml">
Bunkers</link> are a type of base defense against enemy opposition. They are immobile defensive structures that can only be constructed by Engineer Regiments. There are three types of bunkers: Machine gun bunkers, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/146640.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22World+War+II%22])">
Anti-Aircraft bunkers</link>, and <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/4971053.xml">
Artillery bunkers</link></instrument>
</device>
</weapon>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
. In addition to being able to build bunkers, Engineer Regiments can also repair damaged buildings and structures.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Miscellaneous structures</st>
<p>

Some structures can only appear in the campaign battles of the game and in player-made maps. One of these structures include the unique D-Day bunkers that are present in the "Invasion of Normandy" campaign battle. These D-Day bunkers have health points but cannot be destroyed; they are like cities and can be captured by a player, but only when its health points are reduced down to 'one'. Other "special structures" in the game include searchlights seen in the "Fall of Berlin" battle and special Japanese anti-aircraft, artillery, and machine gun bunkers seen in the "Battle of Iwo Jima".</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Units</st>
<p>

All military units in the game can be controlled by the player. There are several categories of military units: regiments, naval units, and aircraft.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Regiments</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/166653.xml">
Regiments</link> are the main fighting forces in <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it>. These regiments are comprised of different individual fighting units, ranging from 5-9 units in one regiment, and are produced from Infantry Hqs, Airborne Hqs, Mechanized Hqs, and Armor Hqs. They require different amounts of ammo and/or oil to maintain. Regiments are categorized into four different categories: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/15068.xml">
Infantry</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/58478.xml">
Airborne</link>, <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/826034.xml">
Mechanized</link></invention>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/29970.xml">
Armor</link>. The units that make up the regiments can be of various types (e.g. The Mechanized Infantry Regiment is made up of 1 officer/scout truck, 4 infantry units, 1 machine gunner, 1 light tank, and 2 halftracks). Also, these units are always in formation, whether in assault mode, aggressive mode, or passive mode. The units in each regiment also have different values and characteristics in their attack, defense, and health.</p>
<p>

Regiments gain experience points by participating in battles. Accumulation of experience points can earn a regiment field promotions, which is awarded in three stages: Regular, Veteran, and Elite. Each promotion strengthens the regiment in offense, defense, health, and morale. In addition, experience points gained by regiments also adds up towards a player's Special Operations experience.</p>
<p>

In <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it>, there is a unique characteristic that all regiments have, called 'morale'. During a battle, a regiment's morale slowly drains away, and when the regiment runs low on morale, it would rout back to a nearby area that is clear of enemies all on its own. During a rout, the player cannot control the regiment or its movement until the rout has ended. However, if the regiment's morale is totally depleted, the regiment would have the "exhausted" effect on it and would rout to a complete stop. It would halt in that area to regain its morale back before the regiment can move again.</p>
<p>

After experiencing combat, a regiment might be wounded and be low on health. As long as the regiment is not under enemy fire, in a zone of supply, and is attached to a Division Hq, it will automatically replenish and regain back the units that the regiment had lost in the battle and heal any injured units back to 100% health.</p>
<p>

The most powerful units are tanks, which have an increased defensive bonus that makes heavy tanks from all countries (except Japan, which has no heavy tank regiment) practically immune to rifle fire from infantry. The most powerful tank unit in the game comes from Germany, which is the <weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/188053.xml">
King Tiger</link></weapon>
.</p>
<p>

Each nation has at least two units that are unique to them. For example, Germany has the King Tiger tanks and the <automaton wordnetid="102761392" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<mechanism wordnetid="103738472" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/5750271.xml">
Goliath tracked mine</link></instrument>
</mechanism>
</device>
</weapon>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</automaton>
 while Russia has the <weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/16959.xml">
Katyusha rocket launcher</link></weapon>
 and conscript infantry.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Naval units</st>
<p>

The naval units of <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> include: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/251531.xml">
Battleships</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
Carriers</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/539716.xml">
Landing craft</link>. Battleships and carriers are the two main naval units of <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> that are sometimes given to the player at the start of a campaign if the mission requires the movement of armies across a body of water. Battleships yield heavy <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/1763383.xml">
gun turrets</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/146640.xml">
anti-aircraft guns</link> for shore <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/1392353.xml">
bombardment</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/146640.xml">
air defense</link>. Aircraft carriers consist of a hangar of fighters and bombers for initiating air strikes and air reconnaissance on the enemy. Landing craft are boat units deployed from a battleship that can transport infantry regiments or a Corps Hq truck to nearby land. There are also special battleships called "Marine battleships" that deploy <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<military_unit wordnetid="108198398" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/17349325.xml">
Marine</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</military_unit>
</work>
 regiments instead of regular infantry regiments, which cost more than the normal infantry but do slightly more damage. These special regiments are only available to players using the United States, and appear in the last two campaign battles, "The Battle of Iwo Jima" and "The Invasion of Okinawa", as well as custom maps.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Aircraft</st>
<p>

The aircraft of <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> include: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/10929.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22World+War+II%22])">
Fighter aircraft</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/3446.xml">
Bombers</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/2375692.xml">
Transport planes</link>. Fighter aircraft and bombers are the two main aircraft of <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> and are deployed from airfields and carriers. Fighter aircraft are mainly used for reconnaissance flights, air defense, and bomber escorts. Bomber aircraft are mainly used for bombing enemy regiments and structures. Transport planes are used for deploying and carrying paratrooper regiments or supplies purchased from Special Operations.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Technology</st>
<p>

In <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it>, technologies are upgrades that can only be purchased and researched in five buildings: the Corps Hq, the Engineer Brigade, the Motor Pool, the Artillery Brigade, and the Airfield. Technologies can improve and upgrade particular type(s) of units with a better value in attack, defense, health, speed, attack speed, morale, cost, and/or line of sight. Other technologies give a resource or income boost to the economy, while some are required to be researched to enable the deployment of the most advanced regiments in the game.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Special Operations</st>
<p>

Each general in <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> has his own unique set of four Special Operations that the player can use to employ to the battlefield (each general has the Corps Reorganization ability, so they really only have just three unique Special Operations). Special Operations are the special abilities of each general, and they have a tremendous impact on a battle if used correctly. Some Special Operations provide bonuses to the attack, defense, health, and/or speed of specific types of units, i.e. "Mechanical Reliability" increases the health of vehicles by 20%. Other Special Operations help reduce unit costs, while some provide additional resources to the player, i.e. "Military Surplus" provides additional revenue generation by Hqs. Special Operations are purchased with Special Operations experience points, which are accumulated at a constant rate, but the rate temporarily increases when a player's military forces are attacking the enemy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

The most expensive Special Operations to use are called "bombs", which deal splash damage inside an area of effect. There are four unique "bombs" that appear in the game: "Kamikaze", "Carpet Bombing", "V-1 Rocket", and "Atomic Bomb". The most powerful of these four "bombs" is the "Atomic Bomb", wielded by Admiral Nimitz, as it not only has an immensely destructive blast, it also leaves a health-draining radiation in its wake.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Generals</st>
<p>

There are 20 playable generals in the game, 4 for each nation:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 United States: <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/206221.xml">
Henry H. Arnold</link></person>
, <soldier wordnetid="110622053" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/8182.xml">
Dwight D. Eisenhower</link></person>
</president>
</soldier>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/54324.xml">
Chester W. Nimitz</link></person>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/42090.xml">
George S. Patton</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Great Britain: <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/3873.xml">
Bernard Montgomery</link></person>
, <governor_general wordnetid="110140597" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/10292.xml">
Louis Mountbatten</link></governor_general>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/201680.xml">
Archibald Wavell</link></person>
, <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<commissioned_officer wordnetid="109942970" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<governor wordnetid="110140314" confidence="0.8">
<lieutenant wordnetid="110259348" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<general wordnetid="110123844" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.8">
<commissioned_military_officer wordnetid="109943239" confidence="0.8">
<companion wordnetid="109945905" confidence="0.8">
<general_officer wordnetid="110125786" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<friend wordnetid="110112591" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/1648310.xml">
Reginald Wingate</link></friend>
</scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</worker>
</leader>
</general_officer>
</companion>
</commissioned_military_officer>
</politician>
</military_officer>
</general>
</serviceman>
</lieutenant>
</governor>
</intellectual>
</commissioned_officer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Soviet Union: <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/580776.xml">
Vasily Chuikov</link></person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/864824.xml">
Ivan Konev</link></person>
, <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<disbeliever wordnetid="110015897" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<hero wordnetid="110325013" confidence="0.8">
<preserver wordnetid="110466918" confidence="0.8">
<communist wordnetid="109945319" confidence="0.8">
<socialist wordnetid="110618848" confidence="0.8">
<politician wordnetid="110450303" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<lawman wordnetid="110249459" confidence="0.8">
<official wordnetid="110372373" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<defender wordnetid="109614684" confidence="0.8">
<atheist wordnetid="109820044" confidence="0.8">
<nonreligious_person wordnetid="109625789" confidence="0.8">
<marshal wordnetid="110295951" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/890263.xml">
Konstantin Rokossovsky</link></marshal>
</nonreligious_person>
</atheist>
</defender>
</causal_agent>
</official>
</lawman>
</worker>
</leader>
</politician>
</socialist>
</communist>
</preserver>
</hero>
</person>
</disbeliever>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/38888.xml">
Georgy Zhukov</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Germany: <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/200385.xml">
Albert Kesselring</link></person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/180727.xml">
Erich von Manstein</link></person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/9516.xml">
Erwin Rommel</link></person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/161133.xml">
Gerd von Rundstedt</link></person>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Japan: <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/589455.xml">
Tadamichi Kuribayashi</link></person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/15408.xml">
Isoroku Yamamoto</link></person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/758526.xml">
Gunichi Mikawa</link></person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/195975.xml">
Chuichi Nagumo</link></person>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Singleplayer</st>
<p>

There are three modes for singleplayer gameplay: Custom Battle, Campaign, and World War II.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Custom battle</st>
<p>

Custom battles are basically normal real-time strategy battles played with the computer. In a custom battle, the player will always start out with a single Corps Hq building, some bunker defenses, and a supply depot truck. In the staging room before the battle, the player can choose what type of map to play on, what and how many land features will be present on the map, how much money and experience points each player will start out with, along with other options.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
WWII mode</st>
<p>

WWII mode resembles a computer variant of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/173475.xml">
Axis &amp; Allies board game</link>. It is played mainly as a  <genre wordnetid="105845332" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/123428.xml">
turn-based</link></kind>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</genre>
 game, but it can also incorporate the <genre wordnetid="105845332" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/77251.xml">
RTS</link></kind>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</genre>
 mode into it.</p>
<p>

At the start, the player assumes the role of a nation and general. Once the game launches, there will be a brief video and speech given to the player telling about his/her nation's current status in the war. The player is then taken onto a flat, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/655865.xml">
panoramic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/771916.xml">
map of the world</link>. Here, the player can purchase <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/15068.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Modern%22])">
infantry</link> units, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/20282.xml">
mechanized</link> units, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/29970.xml">
armor</link> units, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/600792.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22World+War+II%22])">
air support</link> from their home country and move them across the map in turns to engage enemy armies and territories. In contrast to the Axis &amp; Allies board game, the player can only attack one territory per turn and does not build naval and air support directly on the board, but rather, during an RTS battle resolution.</p>
<p>

In attacking or defending from enemy forces, the player receives an option to either go into an RTS game to try and defeat the opposing enemy in real-time, or to let the computer compute the chances of victory for the player. The outcome of a real-time strategy resolution is entirely based on a player's skill, while computerized battle resolution is a random roll based on a direct comparison between the attacker's and the defender's quantity of forces situated in the territory.</p>
<p>

If an attacker defeats an opposing army in a territory, the weakest regiment of the defeated army is destroyed and the rest of the army retreats to a nearby allied country. If the opposing army is completely surrounded, unable to retreat to nearby allied territory, then the army is destroyed. However, if the defender is the victor, then the weakest regiment of the attacker's army is destroyed and the rest of the army retreats back to the territory from which they initiated the battle. If a unit moves into a neutral territory or an abandoned enemy territory, it will automatically capture that territory the next turn.</p>
<p>

There are only two major aspects of WWII mode: money and researches. Money is obtained by capturing and holding territories and is used to purchase military units and researches. Each territory generates a different amount of money each turn; thus wealthier territories are more important in value. Researches are also an important factor of gameplay. Purchasing researches increases the chance of victory in computerized battle resolutions, and it also allows the player to have the technology already researched in an RTS battle.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Campaigns</st>
<p>

In Campaign mode, the player is thrust into a series of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/1414884.xml">
World War II campaign battles</link> for either the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/43507.xml">
Axis Powers</link> (Germany and Japan) or the <alliance wordnetid="114418822" confidence="0.8">
<politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<union wordnetid="114418395" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<coalition wordnetid="114418662" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/2198844.xml">
Allied Nations</link></coalition>
</social_relation>
</state>
</union>
</politics>
</alliance>
 (United States, Great Britain, and Russia). There are a total of 24 challenging missions included in Campaign mode: 12 Allied campaigns and 12 Axis campaigns. There are also 8 cinematics shown throughout the campaigns.</p>
<p>

<table cellpadding="10" border="2" cellspacing="1">
<caption>
<b>List of <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it></b><b> Campaigns</b></caption>
<row style="background-color: #ccc">
<header scope="row">
Allied Campaigns</header>
<header scope="row">
Axis Campaigns</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 
Cinematic: Moscow Counteroffensive
<indent level="1">

1. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/4987.xml">
Battle of El Alamein</link>
</indent>
:2. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/60026.xml">
Battle of Guadalcanal</link>
<indent level="1">

3. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/4284.xml">
Battle of Stalingrad</link></conflict>

</indent>
:4. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/33102.xml">
Battle of Kursk</link></conflict>

<indent level="1">

5. <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<operation wordnetid="114008806" confidence="0.8">
<battle wordnetid="100953559" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="114006945" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/33088.xml">
Road to Rome</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</action>
</state>
</event>
</battle>
</operation>
</group_action>
</military_action>

</indent>
Cinematic: Operation Overlord: D-Day
<indent level="1">

6. 
</indent>
:7. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/483468.xml">
Normandy Breakout</link></conflict>

<indent level="1">

8. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/56433.xml">
Operation Market Garden</link></conflict>

</indent>
:9. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/57998.xml">
Battle of the Bulge</link></conflict>

Cinematic: Bombing of Berlin
<indent level="1">

10. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/291145.xml">
Fall of Berlin</link></conflict>

</indent>
:11. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/60027.xml">
Battle of Iwo Jima</link></conflict>

<indent level="1">

12. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/4986.xml">
Invasion of Okinawa</link>Cinematic: Victory in Japan</indent>
</col>
<col>
 
Cinematic: Invasion of France
<indent level="1">

1. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/149773.xml">
Airdrop on Crete</link></conflict>

</indent>
:2. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/4987.xml">
Battle of El Alamein</link>
<indent level="1">

3. Battle of Suez Canal
</indent>
:4. Battle of Stalingrad
<indent level="1">

5. <operation wordnetid="100955060" confidence="0.8">
<penetration wordnetid="100975452" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<invasion wordnetid="100976531" confidence="0.8">
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/3054379.xml">
Invasion of Australia</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</invasion>
</event>
</penetration>
</operation>

</indent>
:6. Battle of Kursk
<indent level="1">

7. Defense of Normandy
</indent>
:8. <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/22338.xml">
Operation Sealion</link></conflict>
Cinematic: Fall of London
<indent level="1">

9. Invasion of India
</indent>
:10. The Burning of Moscow
Cinematic: Collapse of Russia
<indent level="1">

11. Assault on Midway
</indent>
:12. Invasion of Hawaii
Cinematic: Cold War in the Pacific</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Synopsis</st>
<p>

Playing as the Allies, history goes the way it should, with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/15714415.xml">
Battle of Normandy</link> sealing Germany's fate and the capture of <volcanic_crater wordnetid="109472413" confidence="0.8">
<land wordnetid="109334396" confidence="0.8">
<geological_formation wordnetid="109287968" confidence="0.8">
<caldera wordnetid="109231117" confidence="0.8">
<island wordnetid="109316454" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/175905.xml">
Iwo Jima</link></island>
</caldera>
</geological_formation>
</land>
</volcanic_crater>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/22477.xml">
Okinawa</link> sealing Japan's. The campaigns interchange between the armies of Great Britain, Russia, and the United States of America as time progresses throughout the years of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/34614.xml">
1939</link>-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/34624.xml">
1945</link>.</p>
<p>

Playing as the Axis incorporates a change in history, beginning with a tactical German victory at Crete. Rommel and his <military_unit wordnetid="108198398" confidence="0.8">
<unit_of_measurement wordnetid="113583724" confidence="0.8">
<definite_quantity wordnetid="113576101" confidence="0.8">
<army_unit wordnetid="108190754" confidence="0.8">
<corps wordnetid="108212527" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/158208.xml">
Afrika Korps</link></corps>
</army_unit>
</definite_quantity>
</unit_of_measurement>
</military_unit>
 push the British all the way back through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/29323.xml">
Suez Canal</link>. With the fuel-rich Middle East in German hands, Germany wins the decisive <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/4284.xml">
Battle of Stalingrad</link></conflict>
 and the following year, the endlessly supplied <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/216047.xml">
Panzer</link> units crush the Russians at Kursk. Meanwhile in the Pacific, Japan manages an invasion of Australia, leaving the Americans without a staging area in the Pacific. The Battle of Normandy still happens, but this time the Germans' counterattack is successful. The failed invasion at Normandy not only prevented the Allies from opening a new front in the war, it also oversaw Germany's plans to invade Great Britain. Led by Rundstedt and Rommel (who successfully stopped the Allies at Normandy together), <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/22338.xml">
Operation Sealion</link></conflict>
 proved to be a success, forcing the British to surrender.</p>
<p>

While Germany deals with partisan resistance, Japan invades India to crush the last of the British forces under the command of Wingate. With Great Britain defeated, Germany is able to turn its attention back to Stalin and the Soviet Union. Japanese advance units under General Kuribayashi and German Panzer divisions under Field Marshal Manstein surround Moscow, but the battle for control of the city turns into a three way brawl with German and Japanese units each vying for control of the city. The battle ends in a German victory. By now, the United States of America is the only Allied nation left to challenge the Axis. With the defeat of British and Australian forces, Japan quickly eliminates the last remaining ships of the American fleet and captures <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<safety wordnetid="108643933" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/19250.xml">
Midway</link></district>
</geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</area>
</safety>
</region>
</site>
, and later <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/13270.xml">
Hawaii</link></symbol>
. With American naval forces crippled beyond repair, the Allies lose their chances of defeating the Axis Powers and America settles into a new <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/2276358.xml">
Cold War</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
 with Japan in the Pacific and Nazi Germany in Europe.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Multiplayer</st>
<p>

Players online either play in custom team battles or on official/player-created maps. A maximum of 12 players is allowed to join a single game, but only a maximum of 8 players is allowed to actually play. A fast computer with a fast Internet connection is greatly recommended for a smooth gameplay experience online. Additionally, players online can observe games, save multiplayer films, host rooms and games, and make friends and add them to their buddy lists.</p>
<p>

There is a simple ranking system for <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> multiplayer gameplay, based on the number of games played:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

0 games - No rank</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

1-49 games - Rank of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/161405.xml">
Lieutenant</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

50-249 games - Rank of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/166852.xml">
Captain</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

250-499 games - Rank of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/201920.xml">
Major</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

500-999 games - Rank of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/199023.xml">
Colonel</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

1000+ games - Rank of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/148537.xml">
General</link></entry>
</list>

Player statistics are recorded and shown in their profiles.</p>
<p>

Many online players use more strategic and tactical levels of gameplay than those used only in singleplayer against the AI. Online gameplay can be played through a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/17739.xml">
local area network</link> (LAN) connection or through the Internet.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Online gameplay requires an account to be made via <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/1008271.xml">
GameSpy</link></web_site>
. Online play is supported by GameSpy.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Map editor</st>
<p>

The <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> map editor lets players create their own maps to play in both singleplayer and multiplayer mode.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Players are able to create their own military maps, including choice of scenery, choice of gameplay, cutscenes, storylines, and military objectives.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Reception</st>
<p>

According to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/990329.xml">
Gamespot</link>, the average score received from its users comes in at a 7.4, while the average score received from gaming critics is a 6.7.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Reviewers were varied in their personal opinions on the game, with some saying that the game was fantastic and exciting, and others saying that the game was not to their expectations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Demo</st>
<p>

There is a free playable demo for <it>Axis &amp; Allies</it> that features two tutorial missions, the Battle of Stalingrad single-player mission, and the random map generator for single-player and multiplayer games for up to four players.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/173475.xml">
Axis &amp; Allies board game</link></game>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/5311290.xml">
Axis &amp; Allies (1998 video game)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References and notes</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gamespot.com/pc/strategy/axisalliesrts/index.html">
Axis &amp; Allies for PC - Axis &amp; Allies PC Game - Axis &amp; Allies Computer Game</weblink>".&#32;<it>Axis &amp; Allies description</it>.&#32;  Gamespot&#32;(June 2007).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-06-10</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.timegate.com/aa/">
TimeGate Studios - Axis &amp; Allies</weblink>".&#32;<it>TimeGate Info on Axis &amp; Allies</it>.&#32;  TimeGate Studios&#32;(May 2007).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pc.ign.com/articles/563/563069p1.html">
IGN: Axis &amp; Allies Review</weblink>".&#32;<it>Axis &amp; Allies(PC) review</it>.&#32;  Butts, Steve&#32;(May 2007).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gameplanet.co.nz/mag.dyn/Reviews/2830.html">
Gameplanet - Reviews - Axis &amp; Allies</weblink>".&#32;<it>Axis &amp; Allies game review</it>.&#32;  Gunn, Mike, staff writer&#32;(November 2004).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Special Operations experience points increase at a constant rate of 1 pt./sec, but the rate booms when military units gain experience participating in skirmishes against the enemy.</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xgpgaming.com/content.php?category=DeskPC&amp;type=review&amp;id=956">
XGP Gaming: Review</weblink>".&#32;  Hadley, David&#32;(May 2007).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gamespot.com/pc/strategy/axisalliesrts/review.html?mode=web">
Axis &amp; Allies for PC Reviews - PC Axis &amp; Allies Reviews</weblink>"&#32;(2004-11-02).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gamespot.com/pc/strategy/axisalliesrts/download_6109779.html?page=1&amp;tag=result;title;0">
Axis &amp; Allies Demo for PC Download at GameSpot</weblink>"&#32;(2004-10-06).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-10-29</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Official</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.atari.com/axisandallies/languages.php#/">
Official website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.timegate.com/aa/">
TimeGate official website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Forums</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.timegate.com/forum/forumdisplay.php?f=25">
TimeGate Studios</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/forumdisplay.php?f=324">
Atari</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Other</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.triplethreatclan.com/">
Community website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://axisallies.strategyplanet.gamespy.com/">
Strategy planet</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</entity>
</event>
</article>
