<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:26:05[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<part  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113809207">
<header>
<title>Cyclocomputer</title>
<id>2316561</id>
<revision>
<id>209882792</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-03T11:03:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Shirt58</username>
<id>1607861</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Bicycle parts</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Cyclocomputer.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A basic cyclocomputer showing speed and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/72877.xml">
Odometer</link> readings.
</caption>
</image>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Cyclocomputer_sensor.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A wired <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/317969.xml">
reed switch</link> sensor with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/170836.xml">
spoke</link> mounted magnet.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

A <b>cyclocomputer</b> is a device mounted on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/3973.xml">
bicycle</link> that calculates and displays trip information, similar to the instruments in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/725797.xml">
dashboard</link> of a car. The computer with display, or <it>head unit</it>, usually is attached to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/11742482.xml">
handlebar</link> for easy viewing.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Basic operation</st>

<ss1>
<st>
The head</st>
<p>

A basic cyclocomputer may display the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/576681.xml">
current speed</link>, maximum speed, trip distance, trip time, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/72877.xml">
total distance traveled</link>, and the current time. More advanced models also may display <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/59211.xml">
altitude</link>, incline (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/889183.xml">
inclinometer</link>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/304942.xml">
heart rate</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/19572300.xml">
temperature</link> as well as offer additional functions such as average speed, pedaling <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/2781887.xml">
cadence</link>, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/956704.xml">
stopwatch</link> and even <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
GPS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 navigation. They have become useful accessories in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/5931.xml">
bicycling</link> as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/26853.xml">
sport</link> and as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/25381.xml">
recreational</link> activity.</p>
<p>

The display is usually implemented with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/17932.xml">
liquid crystal display</link>, and it may show one or more values at once. Many current models display one value, such as current speed, with large numbers, and another number that the user may select, such as time, distance, average speed, etc., with small numbers.</p>
<p>

The head usually has one or more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/1508243.xml">
buttons</link> that the user can push to switch the value(s) displayed, reset values such as time and trip distance, <part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/2316561.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Calibration%22])">
calibrate</link></part>
 the unit, and on some units, turn on a back light for the display.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The sensor</st>
<p>

A magnet is attached to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/170836.xml">
spoke</link> of either the front or rear <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/195144.xml">
wheel</link>. A sensor based either on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/14307.xml">
Hall effect</link>, or on a magnetic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/317969.xml">
reed switch</link>, is attached to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/919697.xml">
fork</link> or the rear of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/195134.xml">
frame</link>. The sensor detects when the magnet passes once per rotation of the wheel. Alternatively, a sensor may be attached to the wheel hub. Distance is determined by counting the number of rotations, which translates into the number of wheel circumferences passed. Speed is calculated from distance against lapsed time period. To measure cadence, a magnet is mounted to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/261323.xml">
crankarm</link>, and a sensor mounted to the frame.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Transmission</st>
<p>

Some models use a wired connection between the sensor and the head unit. Other cyclocomputers, e.g. used by competitive cyclists, transmit the data wirelessly from the sensor/transmitter to the head unit.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Calibration</st>
<p>

Once a new computer is installed, it usually requires proper configuration. This normally includes selecting distance units (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/50510.xml">
kilometers</link> vs. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/19159.xml">
mile</link>s) and the circumference of the wheel. Since the sensor measures wheel rotation, different wheel sizes will translate to different measures of speed and distance for a given number of rotations.</p>
<p>

For true accuracy, however, the bicycle (with the set cyclocomputer) must be ridden by the intended rider over an accurately measured distance. The computer's reading is then compared with the known distance and any necessary corrections made.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Additional information</st>
<p>

Besides variables calculated from the rotating wheels or crank, cyclocomputers can display other information</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Gearing</st>
<p>

For integrated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/2564375.xml">
shifters</link> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/856983.xml">
racing bicycle</link>s, the gear can be read by the computer: Shimano's Flight Deck and Campagnolo's ErgoBrain work with their respective systems to detect the gearing. This allows indirect measurement of cadence. These systems do not have sensors on the crankset or cassette to determine what gear the bicycle is in. They work exclusively with the shifters, which may result in misleading information. Instead of knowing what gear the bicycle is in, they rely on sensing when the cyclist changes gears using sensors in the shifters. If the gear change doesn't actually happen, or the computer's sensors are too sensitive (eg: when braking with STI-style shifters), the information displayed is not accurate.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Performance</st>
<p>

With additional sensors, other performance measurements are available:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/1296864.xml">
heart rate monitor</link> can be integrated into the computer, using a chest strap sensor.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/4038302.xml">
power meter</link></part>
 measures <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/24236.xml">
power</link> output in watts, using a torque sensor in the bottom bracket or rear hub.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Environment</st>
<p>

Some models also have sensors built into the head that measure and display environmental parameters such as temperature and altitude.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>



<ss2>
<st>
tags:</st>




</ss2>
</sec>
</bdy>
</part>
</article>
