<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:36:45[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Deterministic encryption</title>
<id>2343703</id>
<revision>
<id>43835900</id>
<timestamp>2006-03-15T03:35:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dmharvey</username>
<id>277018</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cryptography</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>deterministic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> scheme</b> (as opposed to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/1051442.xml">
probabilistic encryption</link> scheme) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/506383.xml">
cryptosystem</link> which always produces the same <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
ciphertext</link> for a given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/157935.xml">
plaintext</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
key</link>, even over separate executions of the encryption algorithm.  Examples of deterministic encryption algorithms include the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/25385.xml">
RSA</link> cryptosystem (without encryption padding), and many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/4594.xml">
block cipher</link>s when used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/160202.xml">
ECB mode</link> or with  a constant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/105971.xml">
initialization vector</link>.<p>

Deterministic encryption can leak information to an eavesdropper, who may recognize known ciphertexts.  For example, when an adversary learns that a given ciphertext corresponds to some interesting message, she learns something every time that ciphertext is transmitted.  To gain information about the meaning of various ciphertexts, an adversary might perform a statistical analysis of messages transmitted over an encrypted channel, or attempt to correlate ciphertexts with observed actions (e.g., noting that a given ciphertext is always received immediately before a submarine dives).  This concern is particularly serious in the case of <link>
public key cryptography</link>, where any party can  encrypt chosen messages using a public encryption key.  In this case, the adversary can build a large "dictionary" of useful plaintext/ciphertext pairs, then observe the encrypted channel for matching ciphertexts.</p>
<p>

To counter this problem, cryptographers proposed the notion of "randomized" or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/1051442.xml">
probabilistic encryption</link>.  Under these schemes, a given plaintext can encrypt to one of a very large set of possible ciphertexts, chosen randomly during the encryption process.  Under sufficiently strong security guarantees the attacks proposed above become infeasible, as the adversary will be unable to correlate any two encryptions of the same message, or correlate a message to its ciphertext, even given access to the public encryption key.  This guarantee is known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/960585.xml">
semantic security</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/15352.xml">
indistinguishability</link>, and has several definitions depending on the assumed capabilities of the attacker (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/960585.xml">
semantic security</link>).</p>

</bdy>
</article>
