<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:36:13[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Corporate governance</title>
<id>235657</id>
<revision>
<id>243394750</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T10:06:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Vandalismterminator</username>
<id>8008622</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Corporate governance</category>
<category>Management</category>
<category>Corporations law</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Corporate governance</b> is the set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/4746766.xml">
process</link>es, customs, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/375091.xml">
policies</link>, laws and institutions affecting the way a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/7485.xml">
corporation</link> is directed, administered or controlled. Corporate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/652849.xml">
governance</link> also includes the relationships among the many stakeholders involved and the goals for which the corporation is governed. The principal stakeholders are the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/146081.xml">
shareholder</link>s, management and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/4822.xml">
board of directors</link>. Other stakeholders include employees, suppliers, customers, banks and other lenders, regulators, the environment and the community at large.<p>

Corporate governance is a multi-faceted subject.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> An important theme of corporate governance is to ensure the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/161973.xml">
accountability</link> of certain individuals in an organization through mechanisms that try to reduce or eliminate the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/730742.xml">
principal-agent problem</link>. A related but separate thread of discussions focus on the impact of a corporate governance system in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/241232.xml">
economic efficiency</link>, with a strong emphasis on shareholders welfare. There are yet other aspects to the corporate governance subject, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/1792799.xml">
stakeholder view</link> and the corporate governance models around the world (see section 9 below).</p>
<p>

There has been renewed interest in the corporate governance practices of modern corporations since 2001, particularly due to the high-profile collapses of a number of large U.S. firms such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/10166.xml">
Enron Corporation</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/59869.xml">
Worldcom</link>. In 2002, the US federal government passed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/67031.xml">
Sarbanes-Oxley Act</link>, intending to restore public confidence in corporate governance.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Definition</st>
<p>

In <b>A Board Culture of Corporate Governance</b> business author Gabrielle O'Donovan defines corporate governance as 'an internal system encompassing policies, processes and people, which serves the needs of shareholders and other stakeholders, by directing and controlling management activities with good business savvy, objectivity and integrity.  Sound corporate governance is reliant on external marketplace commitment and legislation, plus a healthy board culture which safeguards policies and processes'.  </p>
<p>

O'Donovan goes on to say that 'the perceived quality of a company's corporate governance can influence its share price as well as the cost of raising capital.  Quality is determined by the financial markets, legislation and other external market forces plus the international organisational environment; how policies and processes are implemented and how people are led.  External forces are, to a large extent, outside the circle of control of any board.  The internal environment is quite a different matter, and offers companies the opportunity to differentiate from competitors through their board culture.  To date, too much of corporate governance debate has centred on legislative policy, to deter fraudulent activities and transparency policy which misleads executives to treat the symptoms and not the cause.'<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

It is a system of structuring, operating and controlling a company with a view to achieve long term strategic goals to satisfy shareholders, creditors, employees, customers and suppliers, and complying with the legal and regulatory requirements, apart from meeting environmental and local community needs.</p>
<p>

Report of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/439958.xml">
SEBI</link> committee (India) on Corporate Governance defines corporate governance as  the acceptance by management of the inalienable rights of shareholders as the true owners of the corporation and of their own role as trustees on behalf of the shareholders. It is about commitment to values, about ethical business conduct and about making a distinction between personal  &amp; corporate funds in the management of a company.” The definition is drawn from the Gandhian principle of trusteeship and the Directive Principles of the Indian Constitution. Corporate Governance is viewed as ethics and a moral duty.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>
  	 		
In the 19th century, state corporation laws enhanced the rights of corporate boards to govern without unanimous consent of shareholders in exchange for statutory benefits like appraisal rights, to make corporate governance more efficient. Since that time, and because most large publicly traded corporations in the US are incorporated under corporate administration friendly Delaware law, and because the US's wealth has been increasingly securitized into various corporate entities and institutions, the rights of individual owners and shareholders have become increasingly derivative and dissipated. The concerns of shareholders over administration pay and stock losses periodically has led to more frequent calls for corporate governance reforms. </p>
<p>

In the 20th century in the immediate aftermath of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/157649.xml">
Wall Street Crash</link> of 1929 legal scholars such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/2621472.xml">
Adolf Augustus Berle</link>, Edwin Dodd, and Gardiner C. Means pondered on the changing role of the modern corporation in society. Berle and Means' monograph "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/13249958.xml">
The Modern Corporation and Private Property</link>" (1932, Macmillan) continues to have a profound influence on the conception of corporate governance in scholarly debates today.  </p>
<p>

From the Chicago school of economics, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/26354.xml">
Ronald Coase</link></scientist>
's "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/83030.xml">
The Nature of the Firm</link>" (1937) introduced the notion of transaction costs into the understanding of why firms are founded and how they continue to behave. Fifty years later, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/301227.xml">
Eugene Fama</link></scientist>
 and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/3070181.xml">
Michael Jensen</link></scientist>
's "The Separation of Ownership and Control" (1983, Journal of Law and Economics) firmly established <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/730742.xml">
agency theory</link> as a way of understanding corporate governance: the firm is seen as a series of contracts. Agency theory's dominance was highlighted in a 1989 article by Kathleen Eisenhardt (Academy of Management Review). 	 </p>
<p>

US expansion after <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
World War II</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
 through the emergence of multinational corporations saw the establishment of the managerial class. Accordingly, the following <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/18998741.xml">
Harvard Business School</link></university>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/19881.xml">
management</link> professors published influential monographs studying their prominence: Myles Mace (entrepreneurship), <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/902349.xml">
Alfred D. Chandler, Jr.</link></person>
 (business history), Jay Lorsch (organizational behavior) and Elizabeth MacIver (organizational behavior). According to Lorsch and MacIver "many large corporations have dominant control over business affairs without sufficient accountability or monitoring by their board of directors." 	 </p>
<p>

Since the late 1970’s, corporate governance has been the subject of significant debate in the U.S.  and around the globe. Bold, broad efforts to reform corporate governance have been driven, in part, by the needs and desires of shareowners to exercise their rights of corporate ownership and to increase the value of their shares and, therefore, wealth. Over the past three decades, corporate directors’ duties have expanded greatly beyond their traditional legal responsibility of duty of loyalty to the corporation and its shareowners.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

In the first half of the 1990s, the issue of corporate governance in the U.S. received considerable press attention due to the wave of CEO dismissals (e.g.: <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/18622259.xml">
IBM</link></company>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/57627.xml">
Kodak</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/225721.xml">
Honeywell</link></company>
) by their boards. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/1246170.xml">
CALPERS</link> led a wave of <it>institutional</it> shareholder activism (something only very rarely seen before), as a way of ensuring that corporate value would not be destroyed by the now traditionally cozy relationships between the CEO and the board of directors (e.g., by the unrestrained issuance of stock options, not infrequently <gossip wordnetid="107223170" confidence="0.8">
<scandal wordnetid="107223811" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<informing wordnetid="107212190" confidence="0.8">
<report wordnetid="107217924" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/6098471.xml">
back dated</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</report>
</informing>
</event>
</scandal>
</gossip>
). </p>
<p>

In 1997, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../233/262233.xml">
East Asian Financial Crisis</link> saw the economies of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/30128.xml">
Thailand</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/14579.xml">
Indonesia</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/27019.xml">
South Korea</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/3607937.xml">
Malaysia</link></country>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/23440.xml">
The Philippines</link> severely affected by the exit of foreign capital after property assets collapsed. The lack of corporate governance mechanisms in these countries highlighted the weaknesses of the institutions in their economies. </p>
<p>

In the early 2000s, the massive bankruptcies (and criminal malfeasance) of <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/10166.xml">
Enron</link></company>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/59869.xml">
Worldcom</link>, as well as lesser corporate debacles, such as <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A39143-2004Jul9.html">
Adelphia Communications</weblink>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/1397.xml">
AOL</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/38797.xml">
Arthur Andersen</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/62414.xml">
Global Crossing</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/451755.xml">
Tyco</link></company>
, and, more recently, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/293544.xml">
Fannie Mae</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/1121653.xml">
Freddie Mac</link></company>
, led to increased shareholder and governmental interest in corporate governance. This is reflected in the passage of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/67031.xml">
Sarbanes-Oxley Act</link> of 2002.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nhbar.org/publications/archives/display-journal-issue.asp?id=13">
http://www.nhbar.org/publications/archives/display-journal-issue.asp?id=13</weblink> </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Impact of Corporate Governance</st>
<p>
 	 
The positive effect of good corporate governance on different stakeholders ultimately is a strengthened economy, and hence good corporate governance is a tool for socio-economic development.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> After East Asian economies collapsed in the late 20th century, the World Bank's president warned those countries, that for sustainable development, corporate governance has to be good. Economic health of a nation depends substantially on how sound and ethical businesses are.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Role of Institutional Investors</st>
<p>
 	 
Many years ago, worldwide, buyers and sellers of corporation stocks were <it>individual</it> investors, such as wealthy businessmen or families, who often had a vested, personal and emotional interest in the corporations whose shares they owned. Over time, markets have become largely <it>institutionalized</it>: buyers and sellers are largely institutions (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/43615.xml">
pension fund</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
insurance companies</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/226597.xml">
mutual fund</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/14412.xml">
hedge funds</link>, investor groups, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/19360669.xml">
bank</link>s). </p>
<p>

The rise of the institutional investor has brought with it some increase of professional diligence which has tended to improve regulation of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/52328.xml">
stock market</link> (but not necessarily in the interest of the small investor or even of the naïve institutions, of which there are many). Note that this process occurred simultaneously with the direct growth of individuals investing <it>indirectly</it> in the market (for example individuals have twice as much money in mutual funds as they do in bank accounts). However this growth occurred primarily by way of individuals turning over their funds to 'professionals' to manage, such as in mutual funds. In this way, the majority of investment now is described as "institutional investment" even though the vast majority of the funds are for the benefit of individual investors.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/1249554.xml">
Program trading</link>, the hallmark of institutional trading, is averaging over 60% a day in 2007.</p>
<p>

Unfortunately, there has been a concurrent lapse in the oversight of large corporations, which are now almost all owned by large institutions. The <link>
Board of Directors</link> of large corporations used to be chosen by the principal shareholders, who usually had an emotional as well as monetary investment in the company (think Ford), and the Board diligently kept an eye on the company and its principal executives (they usually hired and fired the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/24110.xml">
President</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/52234.xml">
Chief executive officer</link>— CEO). </p>
<p>

Nowadays, if the owning institutions don't like what the President/CEO is doing and they feel that firing them will likely be costly (think "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/811144.xml">
golden handshake</link>") and/or time consuming, they will simply sell out their interest. The Board is now mostly <it>chosen</it> by the President/CEO, and may be made up primarily of their friends and associates, such as officers of the corporation or business colleagues. Since the (institutional) shareholders rarely object, the President/CEO generally takes the Chair of the Board position for his/herself (which makes it much more difficult for the institutional owners to "fire" him/her). Occasionally, but rarely, institutional investors support <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/12557456.xml">
shareholder resolutions</link> on such matters as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/19283891.xml">
executive pay</link> and <link>
anti-takeover</link> measures. </p>
<p>

Finally, the largest pools of invested money (such as the mutual fund 'Vanguard 500', or the largest investment management firm for corporations, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/26824.xml">
State Street Corp.</link>) are designed simply to invest in a very large number of different companies with sufficient <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/56121.xml">
liquidity</link>, based on the idea that this strategy will largely eliminate individual company <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/2460491.xml">
financial</link> or other risk and, therefore, these investors have even less interest in a particular company's governance. </p>
<p>

Since the marked rise in the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/234240.xml">
transactions</link> from the 1990s, both individual and professional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/2785607.xml">
stock investors</link> around the world have emerged as a potential new kind of major (short term) force in the direct or indirect ownership of corporations and in the markets: the casual participant. Even as the purchase of individual shares in any one corporation by individual investors diminishes, the sale of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/9135.xml">
derivatives</link> (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/538170.xml">
exchange-traded fund</link>s (ETFs), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/47423.xml">
Stock market index</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/9272073.xml">
options</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://invest-faq.com/articles/deriv-option-basics.html">
http://invest-faq.com/articles/deriv-option-basics.html</weblink>, etc.) has soared. So, the interests of most investors are now increasingly rarely tied to the fortunes of individual corporations. 	 </p>
<p>

But, the ownership of stocks in markets around the world varies; for example, the majority of the shares in the Japanese market are held by financial companies and industrial corporations (there is a large and deliberate amount of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.moneyglossary.com/?w=Cross-holdings">
cross-holding</weblink> among Japanese <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/17467.xml">
keiretsu</link> corporations and within S. Korean <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/338409.xml">
chaebol</link> 'groups') <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asianresearch.org/articles/1397.html">
http://www.asianresearch.org/articles/1397.html</weblink>, whereas stock in the USA or the UK and Europe are much more broadly owned, often still by large individual investors.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Parties to corporate governance</st>
<p>

Parties involved in corporate governance include the regulatory body (e.g. the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/52234.xml">
Chief Executive Officer</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/4822.xml">
board of directors</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/19881.xml">
management</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/146081.xml">
shareholder</link>s). Other stakeholders who take part include suppliers, employees, creditors, customers and the community at large.</p>
<p>

In corporations, the shareholder delegates decision rights to the manager to act in the principal's best interests. This separation of ownership from control implies a loss of effective control by shareholders over managerial decisions. Partly as a result of this separation between the two parties, a system of corporate governance controls is implemented to assist in aligning the incentives of managers with those of shareholders. With the significant increase in equity holdings of investors, there has been an opportunity for a reversal of the separation of ownership and control problems because ownership is not so diffuse.</p>
<p>

A board of directors often plays a key role in corporate governance. It is their responsibility to endorse the organisation's strategy, develop directional policy, appoint, supervise and remunerate senior executives and to ensure accountability of the organisation to its owners and authorities.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/5635339.xml">
Company Secretary</link>, known as a Corporate Secretary in the US and often referred to as a Chartered Secretary if qualified by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/2509939.xml">
Institute of Chartered Secretaries and Administrators</link> (ICSA), is a high ranking professional who is trained to uphold the highest standards of corporate governance, effective operations, compliance and administration. </p>
<p>

All parties to corporate governance have an interest, whether direct or indirect, in the effective performance of the organisation. Directors, workers and management receive salaries, benefits and reputation, while shareholders receive capital return. Customers receive goods and services; suppliers receive compensation for their goods or services. In return these individuals provide value in the form of natural, human, social and other forms of capital.</p>
<p>

A key factor in an individual's decision to participate in an organisation e.g. through providing financial capital and trust that they will receive a fair share of the organisational returns. If some parties are receiving more than their fair return then participants may choose to not continue participating leading to organizational collapse.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Principles</st>
<p>

Key elements of good corporate governance principles include honesty, trust and integrity, openness, performance orientation, responsibility and accountability, mutual respect, and commitment to the organization.</p>
<p>

Of importance is how directors and management develop a model of governance that aligns the values of the corporate participants and then evaluate this model periodically for its effectiveness. In particular, senior executives should conduct themselves honestly and ethically, especially concerning actual or apparent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/236850.xml">
conflicts of interest</link>, and disclosure in financial reports.</p>
<p>

Commonly accepted principles of corporate governance include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Rights and equitable treatment of shareholders</b>: Organizations should respect the rights of shareholders and help shareholders to exercise those rights. They can help shareholders exercise their rights by effectively communicating information that is understandable and accessible and encouraging shareholders to participate in general meetings.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Interests of other stakeholders</b>: Organizations should recognize that they have legal and other obligations to all legitimate stakeholders.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Role and responsibilities of the board</b>: The board needs a range of skills and understanding to be able to deal with various business issues and have the ability to review and challenge management performance. It needs to be of sufficient size and have an appropriate level of commitment to fulfill its responsibilities and duties. There are issues about the appropriate mix of executive and non-executive directors. The key roles of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/3452243.xml">
chairperson</link> and CEO should not be held by the same person.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Integrity and ethical behaviour</b>: Ethical and responsible decision making is not only important for public relations, but it is also a necessary element in risk management and avoiding lawsuits.  Organizations should develop a code of conduct for their directors and executives that promotes ethical and responsible decision making. It is important to understand, though, that reliance by a company on the integrity and ethics of individuals is bound to eventual failure. Because of this, many organizations establish <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/7720374.xml">
Compliance and Ethics Programs</link> to minimize the risk that the firm steps outside of ethical and legal boundaries.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Disclosure and transparency</b>: Organizations should clarify and make publicly known the roles and responsibilities of board and management to provide shareholders with a level of accountability. They should also implement procedures to independently verify and safeguard the integrity of the company's financial reporting. Disclosure of material matters concerning the organization should be timely and balanced to ensure that all investors have access to clear, factual information.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Issues involving corporate governance principles include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

internal controls and the independence of the entity's auditors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

oversight and management of risk</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

oversight of the preparation of the entity's financial statements</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

review of the compensation arrangements for the chief executive officer and other senior executives</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the resources made available to directors in carrying out their duties</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

the way in which individuals are nominated for positions on the board</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/41930.xml">
dividend</link> policy</entry>
</list>

" Corporate Governance" despite some feeble attempts from various quarters has remained ambiguous and often misunderstood phrase. For  Quite some time it was confined to only corporate management. It is not so. it is something much broader for it must include a fair, efficient and transparent administration to meet certain well defined objectives. Corporate governance also must go beyond law. The quantity, quality and frequency of financial  and managerial disclosure, the degree and extent to which the board of Director (BOD) exercise their trustee responsibilities and the commitment to run transparent organization- these should evolve due to interplay of many factors and the role played  by more progressive elements within the corporate sector. In India, a strident demand for evolving a code of good practices by the corporate themselves is emerging.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mechanisms and controls</st>
<p>

Corporate governance mechanisms and controls are designed to reduce the inefficiencies that arise from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/175590.xml">
moral hazard</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/309452.xml">
adverse selection</link>. For example, to monitor managers' behaviour, an independent third party (the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/224700.xml">
auditor</link>) attests the accuracy of information provided by management to investors. An ideal control system should regulate both motivation and ability.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Internal corporate governance controls</st>
<p>

Internal corporate governance controls monitor activities and then take corrective action to accomplish organisational goals. Examples include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Monitoring by the board of directors</b>: The board of directors, with its legal authority to hire, fire and compensate top management, safeguards invested capital. Regular board meetings allow potential problems to be identified, discussed and avoided. Whilst non-executive directors are thought to be more independent, they may not always result in more effective corporate governance and may not increase performance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Different board structures are optimal for different firms. Moreover, the ability of the board to monitor the firm's executives is a function of its access to information. Executive directors possess superior knowledge of the decision-making process and therefore evaluate top management on the basis of the quality of its decisions that lead to financial performance outcomes, <it>ex ante</it>. It could be argued, therefore, that executive directors look beyond the financial criteria.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Remuneration</b>: Performance-based remuneration is designed to relate some proportion of salary to individual performance. It may be in the form of cash or non-cash payments such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/866243.xml">
share</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/9272073.xml">
share option</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/43613.xml">
superannuation</link> or other benefits. Such incentive schemes, however, are reactive in the sense that they provide no mechanism for preventing mistakes or opportunistic behaviour, and can elicit myopic behaviour.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
External corporate governance controls</st>
<p>

External corporate governance controls encompass the controls external stakeholders exercise over the organisation. Examples include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

competition</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

debt covenants</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

demand for and assessment of performance information (especially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/93755.xml">
financial statements</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

government regulations</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

managerial labour market</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

media pressure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

takeovers</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Systemic problems of corporate governance</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Demand for information: A barrier to shareholders using good information is the cost of processing it, especially to a small shareholder. The traditional answer to this problem is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/164602.xml">
efficient market hypothesis</link> (in finance, the efficient market hypothesis (EMH) asserts that financial markets are efficient), which suggests that the shareholder will free ride on the judgements of larger professional investors. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Monitoring costs: In order to influence the directors, the shareholders must combine with others to form a significant voting group which can pose a real threat of carrying resolutions or appointing directors at a general meeting.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Supply of accounting information: Financial accounts form a crucial link in enabling providers of finance to monitor directors. Imperfections in the financial reporting process will cause imperfections in the effectiveness of corporate governance. This should, ideally, be corrected by the working of the external auditing process.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Role of the accountant</st>
<p>

Financial reporting is a crucial element necessary for the corporate governance system to function effectively. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/58216.xml">
Accountant</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/224700.xml">
auditor</link>s are the primary providers of information to capital market participants. The directors of the company should be entitled to expect that management prepare the financial information in compliance with statutory and ethical obligations, and rely on auditors' competence.</p>
<p>

Current accounting practice allows a degree of choice of method in determining the method of measurement, criteria for recognition, and even the definition of the accounting entity. The exercise of this choice to improve apparent performance (popularly known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/63072.xml">
creative accounting</link>) imposes extra information costs on users. In the extreme, it can involve non-disclosure of information.</p>
<p>

One area of concern is whether the accounting firm acts as both the independent auditor and management consultant to the firm they are auditing. This may result in a conflict of interest which places the integrity of financial reports in doubt due to client pressure to appease management. The power of the corporate client to initiate and terminate management consulting services and, more fundamentally, to select and dismiss accounting firms contradicts the concept of an independent auditor.  Changes enacted in the United States in the form of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act (in response to the Enron situation as noted below) prohibit accounting firms from providing both auditing and management consulting services. Similar provisions are in place under clause 49 of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/439958.xml">
SEBI</link> Act in India.</p>
<p>

The Enron collapse is an example of misleading financial reporting. Enron concealed huge losses by creating illusions that a third party was contractually obliged to pay the amount of any losses. However, the third party was an entity in which Enron had a substantial economic stake. In discussions of accounting practices with <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/38797.xml">
Arthur Andersen</link></company>
, the partner in charge of auditing, views inevitably led to the client prevailing.</p>
<p>

However, good financial reporting is not a sufficient condition for the effectiveness of corporate governance if users don't process it, or if the informed user is unable to exercise a monitoring role due to high costs (see <it>Systemic problems of corporate governance</it> above).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Regulation</st>

<p>

<table style=" margin:0 0 1.0em 1.0em; text-align:center; line-height:1.4em; font-size:88%;  " cellpadding="0" class="infobox  " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.2em; padding-left:0.4em; none; padding-bottom:0.4em; border:0;" class="">
<image width="100px" src="Scale_of_justice_2.svg">
<caption>

Scales of justice
</caption>
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding:0.1em 0.4em 0.2em; line-height:1.1em; font-size:145%; font-weight:bold; none; padding:0.4em; background:#66ccff; border:0;" class="">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/6762.xml">
Companies law</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style=" padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  padding:0; border:0; line-height:0.4em;">
&nbsp;</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style=" padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  padding-bottom:0;">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/4918223.xml">
Company</link>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
Business</link> <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/668326.xml">
Sole proprietorship</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style=" padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  padding:0 0.2em; line-height:1.2em;">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/222783.xml">
Partnership</link>
(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/1730791.xml">
General</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/1548943.xml">
Limited</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/662415.xml">
LLP</link>)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="  padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  ">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/7485.xml">
Corporation</link>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/89313.xml">
Cooperative</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.2em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; font-weight:bold;  padding:0.2em 0.4em; background:#66ccff; ">
United States</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.1em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  ">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/2461099.xml">
S corporation</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>

&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/3081289.xml">
C corporation</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/283083.xml">
LLC</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/3017183.xml">
LLLP</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/7440406.xml">
Series LLC</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/8933.xml">
Delaware corporation</link> <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/5554743.xml">
Nevada corporation</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 <volition wordnetid="105652593" confidence="0.8">
<faculty wordnetid="105650329" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/4707507.xml">
Massachusetts business trust</link></faculty>
</volition>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.2em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; font-weight:bold;  padding:0.2em 0.4em; background:#66ccff; ">
UK&nbsp;/ Ireland&nbsp;/ Commonwealth</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.1em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  padding:0.2em 0.2em 0; line-height:1.2em;">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/538325.xml">
Limited company</link>
(<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/7458596.xml">
by shares</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/10087470.xml">
by guarantee</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/25109.xml">
Public</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/1988278.xml">
Proprietary</link>)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style=" padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  ">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/2157113.xml">
Community interest company</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.2em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; font-weight:bold;  padding:0.2em 0.4em; background:#66ccff; ">
European Union&nbsp;/ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/95363.xml">
EEA</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.1em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  ">
<law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/9922.xml">
SE</link></kind>
</group>
</type>
</collection>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</law>

&nbsp;·  <law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/414769.xml">
SCE</link></kind>
</group>
</type>
</collection>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</law>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/18133244.xml">
SPE</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/4502719.xml">
EEIG</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.2em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; font-weight:bold;  padding:0.2em 0.4em; background:#66ccff; ">
Elsewhere</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.1em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  ">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/2696668.xml">
AB</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>

&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/944240.xml">
AG</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/5005536.xml">
ANS</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../335/8346335.xml">
A/S</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/3636476.xml">
AS</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <link>
GmbH</link> <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/3469273.xml">
K.K.</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/1418141.xml">
N.V.</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <link>
OY</link>&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/162297.xml">
S.A.</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/1690376.xml">
<it>more''</it></link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.2em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; font-weight:bold;  padding:0.2em 0.4em; background:#66ccff; ">
Doctrines</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.1em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  padding-bottom:0;">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/235657.xml">
Corporate governance</link>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/1138182.xml">
Limited liability</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/1161827.xml">
Ultra vires</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/1171036.xml">
Business judgment rule</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/12734024.xml">
Internal affairs doctrine</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style=" padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  padding:0 0.2em; line-height:1.1em;">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../209/2189209.xml">
De facto corporation and
corporation by estoppel</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style=" padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  ">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/1549333.xml">
Piercing the corporate veil</link>
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/951394.xml">
Rochdale Principles</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.2em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; font-weight:bold;  padding:0.2em 0.4em; background:#66ccff; ">
Related areas</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding-top:0.1em; padding-right:0.4em; padding-bottom:0.4em; padding-left:0.4em; none;  ">
<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/19280537.xml">
Contract</link>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/76381.xml">
Civil procedure</link></b></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="border-top:1px solid #aaa;"></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<ss1>
<st>
Rules versus principles</st>
<p>

Rules are typically thought to be simpler to follow than principles, demarcating a clear line between acceptable and unacceptable behaviour. Rules also reduce discretion on the part of individual managers or auditors.</p>
<p>

In practice rules can be more complex than principles. They may be ill-equipped to deal with new types of transactions not covered by the code. Moreover, even if clear rules are followed, one can still find a way to circumvent their underlying purpose - this is harder to achieve if one is bound by a broader principle.</p>
<p>

Principles on the other hand is a form of self regulation. It allows the sector to determine what standards are acceptable or unacceptable. It also pre-empts  over zealous legislations that might not be practical.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Enforcement</st>
<p>

Enforcement can affect the overall credibility of a regulatory system. They both deter bad actors and level the competitive playing field. Nevertheless, greater enforcement is not always better, for taken too far it can dampen valuable risk-taking. In practice, however, this is largely a theoretical, as opposed to a real, risk.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Action Beyond Obligation</st>
<p>

Enlightened boards regard their mission as helping management lead the company. They are more likely to be supportive of the senior management team. Because enlightened directors strongly believe that it is their duty to involve themselves in an intellectual analysis of how
the company should move forward into the future, most of the time, the enlightened board is aligned on the critically important issues facing the company.</p>
<p>

Unlike traditional boards, enlightened boards do not feel hampered by the rules and regulations of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act. Unlike standard boards that aim to comply with regulations, enlightened boards regard compliance with regulations as merely a baseline for board performance. Enlightened directors go far beyond merely meeting the requirements on a checklist. They do not need Sarbanes-Oxley to mandate that they protect values and ethics or monitor CEO performance. </p>
<p>

At the same time, enlightened directors recognize that it is not their role to be involved in the day-to-day operations of the corporation. They lead by example. Overall, what most distinguishes enlightened directors from traditional and standard directors is the passionate obligation they feel to engage in the day-to-day challenges and strategizing of the company. Enlightened boards can be found in very large, complex companies, as well as smaller companies.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Corporate governance models around the world</st>
<p>

Although the US model of corporate governance is the most notorious, there is a considerable variation in corporate governance models around the world. The intricated shareholding structures of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/17467.xml">
keiretsu</link>s in Japan, the heavy presence of banks in the equity of German firms, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/338409.xml">
chaebol</link>s in South Korea and many others are examples of arrangements which try to respond to the same corporate governance challenges as in the US.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Anglo-American Model</st>
<p>

There are many different models of corporate governance around the world. These differ according to the variety of capitalism in which they are embedded. The liberal model that is common in Anglo-American countries tends to give priority to the interests of shareholders. The coordinated model that one finds in Continental Europe and Japan also recognizes the interests of workers, managers, suppliers, customers, and the community. Both models have distinct competitive advantages, but in different ways. The liberal model of corporate governance encourages radical innovation and cost competition, whereas the coordinated model of corporate governance facilitates incremental innovation and quality competition. However, there are important differences between the U.S. recent approach to governance issues and what has happened in the U.K..</p>
<p>

In the United States, a corporation is governed by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/4822.xml">
board of directors</link>, which has the power to choose an executive officer, usually known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/52234.xml">
chief executive officer</link>.  The CEO has broad power to manage the corporation on a daily basis, but needs to get board approval for certain major actions, such as hiring his/her immediate subordinates, raising money, acquiring another company, major capital expansions, or other expensive projects.  Other duties of the board may include policy setting, decision making, monitoring management's performance, or corporate control.</p>
<p>

The board of directors is nominally selected by and responsible to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/146081.xml">
shareholder</link>s, but the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/521384.xml">
bylaw</link>s of many companies make it difficult for all but the largest shareholders to have any influence over the makeup of the board; normally, individual shareholders are not offered a choice of board nominees among which to choose, but are merely asked to rubberstamp the nominees of the sitting board. Perverse incentives have pervaded many corporate boards in the developed world, with board members beholden to the chief executive whose actions they are intended to oversee. Frequently, members of the boards of directors are CEOs of other corporations, which some<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> see as a conflict of interest. </p>
<p>

The U.K. has pioneered a flexible model of regulation of corporate governance, known as the "comply or explain" code of governance. This is a principle based code that lists a dozen of recommended practices, such as the separation of CEO and Chairman of the Board, the introduction of a time limit for CEOs' contracts, the introduction of a minimum number of non-executives Directors, of independent directors, the designation of a senior non executive director, the formation and composition of remuneration, audit and nomination committees. Publicly listed companies in the U.K. have to either apply those principles or, if they choose not to, to explain in a designated part of their annual reports why they decided not to do so. The monitoring of those explanations is left to shareholders themselves. The tenet of the Code is that one size does not fit all in matters of corporate governance and that instead of a statuary regime like the Sarbanes-Oxley Act in the U.S., it is best to leave some flexibility to companies so that they can make choices most adapted to their circumstances. If they have good reasons to deviate from the sound rule, they should be able to convincingly explain those to their shareholders.</p>
<p>

The code has been in place since 1993 and has had drastic effects on the way firms are governed in the U.K. A study by Arcot, Bruno and Faure-Grimaud from the Financial Markets Group at the London School of Economics shows that in 1993, about 10% of the UK companies member of the FTSE 350 were compliants on all dimensions while they were more than 60% in 2003. The same success was not achieved when looking at the explanation part for non compliant companies. Many deviations are simply not explained and a large majority of explanations fail to identify specific circumstances justifying those deviations. Still, the overall view is that the U.K.'s system works fairly well and in fact is often branded as a benchmark, followed by several countries.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Non Anglo-American Model</st>
<p>

In East Asian countries, family-owned companies dominate. A study by Claessens, Djankov and Lang (2000) investigated the top 15 families in East Asian countries and found that they dominated listed corporate assets. In countries such as Pakistan, Indonesia and the Philippines, the top 15 families controlled over 50% of publicly owned corporations through a system of family cross-holdings, thus dominating the capital markets. Family-owned companies also dominate the Latin model of corporate governance, that is companies in Mexico, Italy, Spain, France (to a certain extent), Brazil, Argentina, and other countries in South America.</p>
<p>

Europe and Asia exemplify the insider system: Shareholder and stakeholder 
• a small number of listed companies, 
• an illiquid capital market where ownership and control are not frequently traded 
• high concentration of shareholding in the hands of corporations, institutions, families or government 
• the insider model uses a system of interlocking networks and committees.</p>
<p>

At the same time that developing countries are undergoing a process of economic growth and transformation, they are also experiencing a revolution in the business and political relationships that characterize their private and public sectors. Establishing good corporate governance practices is essential to sustaining long-term development and growth as these countries move from closed, market-unfriendly, undemocratic systems towards open, market-friendly, democratic systems. Good corporate governance systems will allow organizations to realize their maximum productivity and efficiency, minimize corruption and abuse of power, and provide a system of managerial accountability.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> These goals are equally important for both private corporations and government bodies.</p>
<p>

Because of the implicit relationship between private interests and the larger government, good corporate governance practices are essential to establishing good governance at the national level in developing countries.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> A number of ties the keep the public and private sectors closely linked. On one hand, judiciary and regulatory bodies as well as legislatures play a role in corporate management and oversight. At the same time cartels and large corporate interests use their size to exert not only economic, but also political power. These two sectors are so intertwined that a country cannot significantly change one without simultaneously instituting changes in the other.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> </p>
<p>

According to Nicolas Meisel, there are four priorities which developing countries should concentrate on while experimenting with new forms of corporate and public governance. The first is to focus on improving the quality of information and increasing the speed at which it is created and distributed to the public. Good communication is important to the functioning of any organization. The second is to allow individual actors more autonomy while at the same time maintaining or increasing accountability. Thirdly, if a hierarchical organization used to orient private activities toward the general interest, new countervailing powers should be encouraged to fill this role. Finally, the part the state plays and how government officials are selected must be considered if a developing economy is to achieve sustainable growth. This may involve making it easier for newcomers with new ideas incumbents who may hold to older, possibly outdated, models.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Codes and guidelines</st>
<p>

Corporate governance principles and codes have been developed in different countries and issued from stock exchanges, corporations, institutional investors, or associations (institutes) of directors and managers with the support of governments and international organizations. As a rule, compliance with these governance recommendations is not mandated by law, although the codes linked to stock exchange <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/28168.xml">
listing requirements</link> may have a coercive effect.</p>
<p>

For example, companies quoted on the London and Toronto Stock Exchanges formally need not follow the recommendations of their respective national codes. However, they must disclose whether they follow the recommendations in those documents and, where not, they should provide explanations concerning divergent practices. Such disclosure requirements exert a significant pressure on listed companies for compliance.</p>
<p>

In the United States, companies are primarily regulated by the state in which they incorporate though they are also regulated by the federal government and, if they are public, by their stock exchange.  The highest number of companies are incorporated in Delaware, including more than half of the Fortune 500.  This is due to Delaware's generally business-friendly corporate legal environment and the existence of a state court dedicated solely to business issues (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://courts.delaware.gov/chancery">
Delaware Court of Chancery</weblink>).</p>
<p>

Most states' corporate law generally follow the American Bar Association's <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.abanet.org/buslaw/library/onlinepublications/mbca2002.pdf">
Model Business Corporation Act</weblink>.  While Delaware does not follow the Act, it still considers its provisions and several prominent Delaware justices, including former Delaware Supreme Court Chief Justice <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weil.com/wgm/pages/Controller.jsp?z=l&amp;sz=p&amp;db=common/firmdir.ns5&amp;d=684D35E8C17F94D485256EAD000BBE60&amp;v=0&amp;f=New%20York">
E. Norman Veasey,</weblink> participate on ABA committees.</p>
<p>

One issue that has been raised since the Disney decision<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> in 2005 is the degree to which companies manage their governance responsibilities; in other words, do they merely try to supersede the legal threshold, or should they create governance guidelines that ascend to the level of best practice.  For example, the guidelines issued by associations of directors (see Section 3 above), corporate managers and individual companies tend to be wholly voluntary. For example, The GM Board Guidelines reflect the company’s efforts to improve its own governance capacity. Such documents, however, may have a wider multiplying effect prompting other companies to adopt similar documents and standards of best practice.</p>
<p>

One of the most influential guidelines has been the 1999 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/493793.xml">
OECD</link> Principles of Corporate Governance. This was revised in 2004. The OECD remains a proponent of corporate governance principles throughout the world.</p>
<p>

Building on the work of the OECD, other international organisations, private sector associations and more than 20 national corporate governance codes, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/31769.xml">
United Nations</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/16568514.xml">
Intergovernmental Working Group of Experts on International Standards of Accounting and Reporting (ISAR)</link> has produced voluntary <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unctad.org/en/docs/iteteb20063_en.pdf">
Guidance on Good Practices in Corporate Governance Disclosure.</weblink> This internationally agreed<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> benchmark consists of more than fifty distinct disclosure items across five broad categories:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Auditing</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Board and management structure and process</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Corporate responsibility and compliance</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Financial transparency and information disclosure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ownership structure and exercise of control rights</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The World Business Council for Sustainable Development <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/863398.xml">
WBCSD</link> has done work on corporate governance, particularly on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wbcsd.org/includes/getTarget.asp?type=p&amp;id=MTE0OA&amp;doOpen=1&amp;ClickMenu=LeftMenu">
accountability and reporting</weblink>, and in 2004 created an <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wbcsd.org/Plugins/DocSearch/details.asp?DocTypeId=25&amp;ObjectId=MTIwNjg">
Issue Management Tool: Strategic challenges for business in the use of corporate responsibility codes, standards, and frameworks</weblink>.This document aims to provide general information, a "snap-shot" of the landscape and a perspective from a think-tank/professional association on a few key codes, standards and frameworks relevant to the sustainability agenda.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Corporate governance and firm performance</st>
<p>

In its 'Global Investor Opinion Survey' of over 200 institutional investors first undertaken in 2000 and updated in 2002, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/642328.xml">
McKinsey</link> found that 80% of the respondents would pay a premium for well-governed companies. They defined a well-governed company as one that had mostly out-side directors, who had no management ties, undertook formal evaluation of its directors, and was responsive to investors' requests for information on governance issues. The size of the premium varied by market, from 11% for Canadian companies to around 40% for companies where the regulatory backdrop was least certain (those in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/19291.xml">
Morocco</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/8087628.xml">
Egypt</link></country>
 and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/25391.xml">
Russia</link></country>
).</p>
<p>

Other studies have linked broad perceptions of the quality of companies to superior share price performance. In a study of five year cumulative returns of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/172717.xml">
Fortune Magazine</link>'s survey of 'most admired firms', Antunovich et al found that those "most admired" had an average return of 125%, whilst the 'least admired' firms returned 80%. In a separate study <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/945157.xml">
Business Week</link> enlisted institutional investors and 'experts' to assist in differentiating between boards with good and bad governance and found that companies with the highest rankings had the highest financial returns.</p>
<p>

On the other hand, research into the relationship between specific corporate governance controls and firm performance has been mixed and often weak. The following examples are illustrative.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Board composition</st>
<p>

Some researchers have found support for the relationship between frequency of meetings and profitability. Others have found a negative relationship between the proportion of external directors and firm performance, while others found no relationship between external board membership and performance. In a recent paper Bagahat and Black found that companies with more independent boards do not perform better than other companies. It is unlikely that board composition has a direct impact on firm performance.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Remuneration/Compensation</st>
<p>

The results of previous research on the relationship between firm performance and executive compensation have failed to find consistent and significant relationships between executives' remuneration and firm performance. Low average levels of pay-performance alignment do not necessarily imply that this form of governance control is inefficient. Not all firms experience the same levels of agency conflict, and external and internal monitoring devices may be more effective for some than for others.</p>
<p>

Some researchers have found that the largest CEO performance incentives came from ownership of the firm's shares, while other researchers found that the relationship between share ownership and firm performance was dependent on the level of ownership. The results suggest that increases in ownership above 20% cause management to become more entrenched, and less interested in the welfare of their shareholders.</p>
<p>

Some argue that firm performance is positively associated with share <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/9272073.xml">
option</link> plans and that these plans direct managers' energies and extend their decision horizons toward the long-term, rather than the short-term, performance of the company.  However, that point of view came under substantial criticism circa in the wake of various security scandals including mutual fund timing episodes and, in particular, the backdating of option grants as documented by University of Iowa academic Erik Lie and reported by James Blander and Charles Forelle of the Wall Street Journal.  </p>
<p>

Even before the negative influence on public opinion caused by the 2006 backdating scandal, use of options faced various criticisms.  A particularly forceful and long running argument concerned the interaction of executive options with corporate stock repurchase programs.  Numerous authorities (including U.S. Federal Reserve Board economist Weisbenner) determined options may be employed in concert with stock buybacks in a manner contrary to shareholder interests.  These authors argued that, in part, corporate stock buybacks for U.S. Standard &amp; Poors 500 companies surged to a $500 billion annual rate in late 2006 because of the impact of options.  A compendium of academic works on the option/buyback issue is included in the study <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=927111">
<it>Scandal''</it></weblink>by author <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ssrn.com/author=665434">
M. Gumport</weblink> issued in 2006.  </p>
<p>

A combination of accounting changes and governance issues led options to become a less popular means of remuneration as 2006 progressed, and various alternative implementations of buybacks surfaced to challenge the dominance of "open market" cash buybacks as the preferred means of implementing a share repurchase plan.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/1651029.xml">
Agency cost</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/730742.xml">
Agency Theory</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../335/1291335.xml">
Basel II</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/4770.xml">
Business ethics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/528210.xml">
Cadbury Report</link></publication>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/13229344.xml">
Certified Business Manager</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/7720374.xml">
Compliance and Ethics Programs</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/2714483.xml">
Corporate behaviour</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/7407976.xml">
Corporate benefit</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<problem wordnetid="114410605" confidence="0.8">
<difficulty wordnetid="114408086" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/178754.xml">
Corporate crime</link></difficulty>
</problem>
</state>
</issue>
</condition>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/1651052.xml">
Corporate Law Economic Reform Program</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/398356.xml">
Corporate Social Responsibility</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/7485.xml">
Corporation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/1068428.xml">
Foreign Corrupt Practices Act</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/811148.xml">
Golden Parachute</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/652849.xml">
Governance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/1557851.xml">
Institutional fund management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/3615245.xml">
King I</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/3615280.xml">
King II</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/1348555.xml">
Legal origins theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/26404.xml">
Risk management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/67031.xml">
Sarbanes-Oxley Act</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/16909251.xml">
Say on pay</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/1792799.xml">
Stakeholder theory</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/56119.xml">
Takeover</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/56117.xml">
poison pill</link>s</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
For a good overview of the different theoretical perspectives on corporate governance see Chapter 15 of Dignam, A and Lowry, J (2006) Company Law, Oxford University Press ISBN-13: 978-0-19-928936-3 </entry>
<entry id="2">
Corporate Governance International Journal, "A Board Culture of Corporate Governance, Vol 6 Issue 3 (2003)</entry>
<entry id="3">
 Crawford, Curtis J. (2007). The Reform of Corporate Governance: Major Trends in the U.S. Corporate Boardroom, 1977-1997. doctoral dissertation, Capella University.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xceo.net/about_us/crawford_dissertation.php">
http://www.xceo.net/about_us/crawford_dissertation.php</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=955289">
SSRN-Good Corporate Governance: An Instrument for Wealth Maximisation by Vrajlal Sapovadia</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
Bhagat &amp; Black, "The Uncertain Relationship Between Board Composition and Firm Performance", 54 Business Lawyer)</entry>
<entry id="6">
National Association of Corporate Directors (NACD)  – Directors Monthly, 
“Enlightened Boards: Action Beyond Obligation”, Vol. 31Number 12 (2007), Pg 13. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xceo.net/admin/files/events/Crawford.Directors_Monthly.Dec07_final.pdf">
http://www.xceo.net/admin/files/events/Crawford.Directors_Monthly.Dec07_final.pdf</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://theyrule.net">
Theyrule.net</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
Business for Development: Fostering the Private Sector. OECD Development Centre. Paris: OECD Publications, 2007 (149-152).</entry>
<entry id="9">
Nicolas Meisel, Governance Culture and Development (Paris: OECD Publishing, 2004) SourceOECD, 27 July 2007  (12).</entry>
<entry id="10">
Corporate Governance in Development: The Experiences of Brazil, Chile, India, and South Africa. ed. Charles P. Oman. OECD Development Centre and CIPE, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="11">
Nicolas Meisel, Governance Culture and Development (Paris: OECD Publishing, 2004) SourceOECD, 27 July 2007  (120).</entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.akingump.com/docs/publication/795.pdf">
The Disney Decision of 2005 and the precedent it sets for corporate governance and fiduciary responsibility, Kuckreja, Akin Gump, Aug 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unctad.org/en/docs/c2isard31_en.pdf">
TD/B/COM.2/ISAR/31</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unctad.org/Templates/Page.asp?intItemID=2920&amp;lang=1">
UNCTAD.ORG &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Corporate Governance Disclosure</weblink></entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fmg.lse.ac.uk/publications/searchdetail.php?pubid=1&amp;wsid=1&amp;wpdid=1308">
Arcot, Sridhar, Bruno, Valentina and Antoine Faure-Grimaud, "Corporate Governance in the U.K.: is the comply-or-explain working?" (December 2005). FMG CG Working Paper 001.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Becht, Marco, Patrick Bolton, Ailsa Röell, "Corporate Governance and Control" (October 2002; updated August 2004). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=343461">
ECGI - Finance Working Paper No. 02/2002.</weblink>     </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Brickley, James A., William S. Klug and Jerold L. Zimmerman, <it>Managerial Economics &amp; Organizational Architecture,</it> ISBN</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/2981884.xml">
Cadbury, Sir Adrian</link>, "The Code of Best Practice", Report of the Committee on the Financial Aspects of Corporate Governance, Gee and Co Ltd, 1992. Available online from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ecgi.org/codes">
http://www.ecgi.org/codes</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/2981884.xml">
Cadbury, Sir Adrian</link>, "Corporate Governance: Brussels", Instituut voor Bestuurders, Brussels, 1996.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Claessens, Stijn, Djankov, Simeon &amp; Lang, Larry H.P. (2000) The Separation of Ownership and Control in East Asian Corporations, Journal of Financial Economics, 58: 81-112</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/566075.xml">
Clarke, Thomas</link> (ed.) (2004) <it>"Theories of Corporate Governance: The Philosophical Foundations of Corporate Governance,"</it> London and New York: Routledge, ISBN-X</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/566075.xml">
Clarke, Thomas</link> (ed.) (2004) <it>"Critical Perspectives on Business and Management: 5 Volume Series on Corporate Governance - Genesis, Anglo-American, European, Asian and Contemporary Corporate Governance"</it> London and New York: Routledge, ISBN</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/566075.xml">
Clarke, Thomas</link> &amp; dela Rama, Marie (eds.) (2006) <it>"Corporate Governance and Globalization"</it> London and Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE, ISBN</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Colley, J., Doyle, J., Logan, G., Stettinius, W., <it>What is Corporate Governance ?</it> (McGraw-Hill, December 2004) ISBN</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Crawford, C. J. (2007).  Compliance &amp; conviction: the evolution of enlightened corporate governance. Santa Clara, Calif: XCEO.  ISBN 0-976-90190-9  9780976901914</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/455555.xml">
Easterbrook, Frank H.</link> and Daniel R. Fischel, <it>The Economic Structure of Corporate Law,</it> ISBN</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Erturk, Ismail, Froud, Julie, Johal, Sukhdev and Williams, Karel (2004) <it>Corporate Governance and Disappointment</it> Review of International Political Economy, 11 (4): 677-713.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Garrett, Allison, "Themes and Variations: The Convergence of Corporate Governance Practices in Major World Markets," 32 Denv. J. Int’l L. &amp; Pol’y).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Holton, Glyn A (2006). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.contingencyanalysis.com/home/papers/suffrage.pdf">
Investor Suffrage Movement</weblink>, Financial Analysits Journal, 62 (6), 15–20.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Monks, Robert A.G. and Minow, Nell, <it>Corporate Governance</it> (Blackwell 2004) ISBN</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Monks, Robert A.G. and Minow, Nell, <it>Power and Accountability</it> (HarperBusiness 1991), full text available <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thecorporatelibrary.com/power/contents.html">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nyssa.org/Template.cfm?Section=corp_gov_com&amp;Template=/TaggedPage/TaggedPageDisplay.cfm&amp;TPLID=3&amp;ContentID=499">
New York Society of Securities Analysts, 2003, Corporate Governance Handbook, </weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/493793.xml">
OECD</link> (1999, 2004) <it>Principles of Corporate Governance</it> Paris: OECD)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Özekmekçi, Abdullah, Mert (2004) "The Correlation between Corporate Governance and Public Relations", Istanbul Bilgi University.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sapovadia, Vrajlal K., "Critical Analysis of Accounting Standards Vis-À-Vis Corporate Governance Practice in India" (January 2007). Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=712461</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Whittington, G. "Corporate Governance and the Regulation of Financial Reporting", <it>Accounting and Business Research</it>, Vol. 2, 1993, Corporate Governance Special Issue, pp. 311-319.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

World Business Council for Sustainable Development <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/863398.xml">
WBCSD</link> (2004) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wbcsd.org/Plugins/DocSearch/details.asp?DocTypeId=25&amp;ObjectId=MTIwNjg">
<it>Issue Management Tool: Strategic challenges for business in the use of corporate responsibility codes, standards, and frameworks''</it></weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=1103644">
 A Comparative Bibliography: Regulatory Competition on Corporate Law</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.law.stanford.edu/program/centers/rcfcg/">
  Arthur and Toni Rembe Rock Center for Corporate Governance at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/26977.xml">
Stanford University</link></university>
</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cipd.co.uk/subjects/corpstrtgy/corpgov/">
Chartered Institute of Personnel and Development (CIPD) resources on corporate governance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boardmember.com/board-governance-series-1/new-releases/">
The Board Governance Series from <it>Corporate Board Member</it> magazine</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://millstein.som.yale.edu/">
The Millstein Center for Corporate Governance and Performance at the <school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<graduate_school wordnetid="108282696" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<business_school wordnetid="108281812" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/1948177.xml">
Yale School of Management</link></institution>
</business_school>
</educational_institution>
</graduate_school>
</school>
</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rru.worldbank.org/GovernanceReports/">
World Bank Corporate Governance Reports</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gcgf.org/">
Global Corporate Governance Forum</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iod.com/corporategovernance">
www.iod.com/corporategovernance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nacdonline.org">
 National Association of Corporate Directors</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style="background:white;;" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/5681.xml">
Corporate title</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
s</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:right;;" class="navbox-group">
Titles</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/3671237.xml">
Chief accounting officer</link> &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/3561800.xml">
Chief administrative officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/2920684.xml">
Chief analytics officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/14481403.xml">
Chief channel officer</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../780/9487780.xml">
Chief compliance officer</link> &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/5520362.xml">
Chief communications officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/2513827.xml">
Chief data officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/52234.xml">
Chief executive officer</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/80007.xml">
Chief financial officer</link> &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/153852.xml">
Chief information officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/4591961.xml">
Chief information security officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/2336130.xml">
Chief knowledge officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/13000456.xml">
Chief learning officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/6589530.xml">
Chief legal officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/1046550.xml">
Chief marketing officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/3863834.xml">
Chief networking officer</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/343044.xml">
Chief operating officer</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/9339281.xml">
Chief procurement officer</link> &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/1993537.xml">
Chief risk officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/11057154.xml">
Chief science officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/15640458.xml">
Chief strategy officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/579193.xml">
Chief technical officer</link></military_officer>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</engineer>
</worker>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/2113615.xml">
Chief visionary officer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:right;;" class="navbox-group">
See also</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/4822.xml">
Board of directors</link> &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<word wordnetid="106286395" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<neologism wordnetid="106294441" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/3452243.xml">
Chairman of the board</link></language_unit>
</activity>
</neologism>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</part>
</word>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/235657.xml">
Corporate governance</link> &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/1744532.xml">
Creative director</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/19283891.xml">
Executive compensation</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/2051602.xml">
Executive director</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/1014322.xml">
Fiduciary</link> &nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<lawyer wordnetid="110249950" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/1838138.xml">
General counsel</link></activity>
</lawyer>
</professional>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</adult>
</causal_agent>
</event>
</occupation>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 &nbsp;·  <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/2320612.xml">
Management team</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/1328935.xml">
Managing director</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/2945529.xml">
Non-executive director</link>  &nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/17212818.xml">
Corner office</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</head>
</causal_agent>
</administrator>
</leader>
</event>
</occupation>
</person>
</executive>
</physical_entity>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
