<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:29:53[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<structure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105726345">
<arrangement  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105726596">
<distribution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105729036">
<header>
<title>CHAOS (Linux distribution)</title>
<id>2383255</id>
<revision>
<id>242807293</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T19:13:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Drbreznjev</username>
<id>147354</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Linux distributions</category>
<category>Live CD</category>
<category>Distributed computing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>infobox OS</name>
<parameters>
<ui>
text (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/4547.xml">
bash</link>)</ui>
<screenshot>
<image width="250px" src="CHAOS_1-6_Welcome.png">
</image>
</screenshot>
<website>
http://midnightcode.org/projects/chaos/</website>
<latest_release_version>
1.6</latest_release_version>
<caption>
CHAOS-1.6 Boot Welcome Screen</caption>
<latest_release_date>
April 2005]]</latest_release_date>
<kernel_type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/20825.xml">
Monolithic kernel</link></kernel_type>
<working_state>
Current<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></working_state>
<developer>
Midnight Code / Ian Latter</developer>
<family>
<O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
</family>
<name>
CHAOS</name>
<source_model>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
Open source</link></source_model>
<license>
Various</license>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>CHAOS</b> is a small (6Mbyte) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/18212.xml">
Linux distribution</link> designed for creating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/168704.xml">
ad hoc</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/18949896.xml">
computer cluster</link>s. CHAOS is a <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/331137.xml">
Live CD</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
 which fits on a single business card sized <recording wordnetid="104063868" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<sound_recording wordnetid="104262678" confidence="0.8">
<memory_device wordnetid="103744840" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<phonograph_record wordnetid="103924069" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/18959902.xml">
CD-ROM</link></medium>
</phonograph_record>
</device>
</memory_device>
</sound_recording>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</recording>
. This tiny disc will <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml">
boot</link> any <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/24668.xml">
i586</link> class <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/49803.xml">
PC</link> (that supports CD booting), into 
a working <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/582146.xml">
openMosix</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/998116.xml">
node</link>, without disturbing (or even touching) the contents of any local hard disk. Designed for large-scale ad hoc clusters, once booted, CHAOS runs from memory allowing the CD to be used on the next node (and allowing for automated rebooting into the host <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>). CHAOS aims to be the most compact, secure and straight-forward openMosix cluster platform available.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
About</st>

<ss1>
<st>
What it is</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="225px" src="CHAOS-six-node-openMosix-no-load.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A six node CHAOS/openMosix cluster: The mosmon view with no load
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

CHAOS is built around the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link> project openMosix created by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<computer_user wordnetid="109951274" confidence="0.8">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/1356243.xml">
Moshe Bar</link></causal_agent>
</engineer>
</programmer>
</computer_user>
</person>
</physical_entity>
. openMosix, itself, is a piece of software that is added to the <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/50394.xml">
kernel</link>, to allow many Linux computers to work together as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/622962.xml">
Single System Image</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/622962.xml">
SSI</link>)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> type cluster.</p>
<p>

CHAOS creates a basic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/998116.xml">
node</link> in an openMosix cluster, and is typically not deployed on its own; cluster builders will use feature rich Linux distributions (such as <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/8094135.xml">
Quantian</link></O>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/616408.xml">
ClusterKnoppix</link>) as a "head node" in a cluster to provide their application software, while the CHAOS distribution runs on "drone nodes" to provide "dumb power" to the cluster.</p>
<p>

While this deployment model suits the typical cluster builder, openMosix is a peer-based cluster, consisting of only one type of node. All openMosix nodes are inherently equal and each can be, simultaneously, parent and child.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
How it works</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="225px" src="CHAOS-six-node-openMosix-one-load.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A six node CHAOS/openMosix cluster: The mosmon view with one process' load, launched from node two
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

As each new node is booted it will locate one cluster node, then negotiate its entry into the cluster. If the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/14921.xml">
IP address</link> of a node is not supplied to the booting node, it will multicast for one. The first responding node will be used as the point of negotiation. The local CHAOS node initiates an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/43342.xml">
IPSEC</link> tunnel to the elected negotiation node using a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/4934057.xml">
pre-shared key</link>. If the tunnel fails to establish, the new node is unable to join the cluster. With the tunnel established the new node requests a copy of the openMosix cluster map from the negotiating cluster node. The new node then repeats this process with every node in the cluster map; establishing an IPSEC tunnel, validating the cluster map, then moving on. In this way, every node is interconnected with every other node by "n-1" IPSEC tunnel connections. All openMosix cluster communications are then said to be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authenticate</link>d and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encrypted</link> via the CHAOS <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/81196.xml">
platform</link>.</p>
<p>

Once an openMosix cluster is established on the CHAOS platform, openMosix can operate as if it were on any Linux platform. Any node can launch a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/4746766.xml">
process</link> and have that process migrate to the node with the best performance <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/7261.xml">
characteristics</link> for executing that particular process. The openMosix environment has the "mosmon" utility to display the performance of the entire cluster, from any node. The image series on the right shows a six node openMosix cluster running on the CHAOS platform.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Why it was built</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="225px" src="CHAOS-six-node-openMosix-four-load.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A six node CHAOS/openMosix cluster: The mosmon view with four process' load, launched from node two
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

CHAOS was developed to utilise idle <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/52742.xml">
desktop computer</link> resources to perform pro-active <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/103127.xml">
brute-force</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/5715.xml">
cryptanalysis</link> against given password hashes. A brute-force attack, as its name suggests, requires an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/5340837.xml">
adversary</link> to employ a mammoth work effort into the resolution of a cryptographic problem. Typically, this is an exhaustive search of a particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/1499824.xml">
key-space</link>. For example, resolving the password for three upper-case alpha characters would require exploring the key-space for: AAA, AAB, AAC ... ZZX, ZZY, ZZZ.</p>
<p>

In order to reduce the time required to search the key-space, portions of the work effort can be farmed out idle resources. As opposed to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/2403284.xml">
rainbow tables</link> this technique allows CHAOS to perform brute-force attacks against irregular or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/701756.xml">
salted</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithms</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Security assessed by</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="225px" src="CHAOS-six-node-openMosix-nine-load.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A six node CHAOS/openMosix cluster: The mosmon view with nine process' load, launched from node two
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The tool used to provide the cryptographic tests was <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/208250.xml">
John the Ripper</link></software>
 (<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/208250.xml">
JtR</link></software>
). JtR was scaled by using named pipes to funnel a controlled <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/7931.xml">
dictionary</link> (a set of keys to try) into an arbitrary number of JtR clients. Each client would take one key, encrypt it, and test it against a local copy of the hash(es). John the Ripper on CHAOS differed from <link>
Cisillia</link> as it facilitated dictionary based brute-force attacks across a large number of algorithms, rather than an entire key-space driven brute-force attack across one or two algorithms.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Security provided by</st>
<p>

CHAOS was the first openMosix distribution to provide <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/43342.xml">
IPSEC</link> and IP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1362296.xml">
packet filtering</link> to the cluster node, enabling <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authentication</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> for inter-node communications, and enabling packet filtering to prevent non-cluster devices from accessing the vulnerable openMosix communications ports.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> These security controls allowed the cluster builder to utilise desktop computers in semi-trusted networks with minimal risk to cluster integrity, thus increasing the number of resources available for inclusion within the cluster.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<ss1>
<st>
2003: The creation of CHAOS</st>

<p>

The project started as tool development work for the IT Security group at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/19735.xml">
Macquarie University</link></university>
 in 2003, with an initial team that included Rob Dartnell, Ian Latter and Ty Miller. There was a need to demonstrate the weakness in one particular application's security via its one hashed, network transmitted, password. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/582146.xml">
openMosix</link> cluster software, at that time, was available via a number of Linux distributions, but these were neither secure<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> nor dynamic enough to support the campus PC environment that the cluster software was to be deployed into.</p>
<p>

The CHAOS distribution was created to fill this need, and was developed under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GPL</link> to allow the openMosix community members to benefit from the security enhancements employed around the openMosix software (the clustering technology that is added to the Linux kernel). Security improvements made by the team included <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/43342.xml">
IPSEC</link> tunnels for all cluster communications, state aware <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1362296.xml">
packet filtering</link> for each node, a tiny <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> image which allowed for <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/432253.xml">
PXE</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 booting to remote PC memory, zero-touch cluster creation, etc.</p>
<p>

The original CHAOS project page was at http://itsecurity.mq.edu.au/chaos/ - this page is no longer available.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
2004: CHAOS, CoSMoS and team departure</st>
<p>

A presentation was made to the Australian Unix Users Group (AUUG) Security Symposium in February 2004<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> at about two thirds of the way through CHAOS' initial two year development cycle.</p>
<p>

In mid to late 2004 CHAOS was adapted to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/594286.xml">
Cooperative Linux</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/594286.xml">
coLinux</link>) framework, allowing openMosix to run as a node on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> PC for the first time. This was significant as there was now the ability to run ad-hoc clusters <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/422855.xml">
24x7</link>, and not just out of business hours. The version of CHAOS created for coLinux was dubbed CosMos (Chaos-OS on <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
-OS) and was also released under the GPL, complete with Windows installer software.</p>
<p>

Later that year work stalled on CHAOS and CosMos when the IT Security team broke up to work for various organisations. Development halted for most of the six months beginning Q4 2004.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
2005: Relocation and public dissemination</st>
<p>

There was renewed interest in CHAOS development when both Ian and Ty began work at <link>
Pure Hacking</link> in Q2 2005. Pure Hacking could identify a need with the resource that CHAOS provided and offered to sponsor further CHAOS development so that it could remain under the GPL. A package updated version of CHAOS was released at that stage, but Pure Hacking provided no additional development time, leaving the project to grind to a halt again. CHAOS was "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/18933122.xml">
Slashdotted</link>"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> during this time, due to the press that came from Pure Hacking's sponsorship announcement.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Unfortunately, Pure Hacking were unable to provide the time needed to develop or maintain CHAOS. Version 1.6 of CHAOS,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> the only version released in Q1-3 of 2005, was released from development work performed in private time.</p>
<p>

In Q4 2005 Ian added CHAOS to the midnightcode.org<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> web site (at the location advertised when leaving the University in 2004)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> - in the hope of better maintaining the project. Improvements desperately needed include code and protocol clean ups, better enterprise management support, operational documentation, and simpler integration with the supporting openMosix distributions (<O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/8094135.xml">
Quantian</link></O>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/616408.xml">
ClusterKnoppix</link>).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
2006-2007: Redevelopment</st>
<p>

Many of the code clean-up issues (focused on Init and Tyd, particularly) will be resolved with the integration of the Midnight Code libraries. While currently being developed these libraries already provide better program execution, configuration control, network interface manipulation and status management than those currently in CHAOS.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Fun Facts</st>

<p>

There are two key quotes that were used on the original web site, and have since been used in various articles:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CHAOS is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/37153.xml">
supercomputer</link> for your <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/653173.xml">
wallet</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CHAOS was a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/508401.xml">
groovy</link> word that ended in OS</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

There were two unfortunate cases of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/44429.xml">
irony</link> in the history of the CHAOS distribution:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The addition of cluster security was ironic, given the purpose of the cluster was ultimately to provide a resource that would facilitate an attack against application security via large-scale cryptographic hash attacks.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The application that was to be assessed - the original purpose for CHAOS - utilised a proprietary encryption algorithm for its password hash; the exact algorithm was never found. Thus CHAOS was unable to be used to assess its intended <belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<doctrine wordnetid="105943300" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/3050114.xml">
target</link></doctrine>
</belief>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

During the initial two year development cycle, CHAOS developed a character that grew from its informal development roots. This character revealed itself in a number of ways:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tyd</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tyd is pronounced "tie-dee" (like "tidy")</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tyd was named after the protocol architect Ty Miller, when it became obvious that dynamically establishing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/20407.xml">
multicast</link> tunnels to forward the openMosix autodiscovery multicast packets across 256 routed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/101416.xml">
VLAN</link>s was not going to be feasible. The algorithm that Ty developed to create multicast tunnels using "mrouted" became the algorithm used by Tyd to negotiate unicast autodiscovery.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 TNP</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The proprietary protocol used by Tyd was called the "Terrence and Phillip" protocol (TNP) - an accidental misspelling of the Canadian <series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<evaluation wordnetid="105736149" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/27977.xml">
South Park</link></evaluation>
</series>
 characters, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/178903.xml">
Terrance and Phillip</link>.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tyd communicated with the TNP protocol on port 3278/TCP which spelt <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/3585479.xml">
FART</link> on most mobile phone <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/275222.xml">
key pads</link>.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Other than usable data, the entire TNP protocol was derived from Terrance and Phillip sound files found on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>. The greeting transaction between two nodes is the client query "let's look for treasure!" followed by the server response "yes, let's look for treasure!".</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Logo</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The original CHAOS logo was an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/1884.xml">
ASCII art</link> representation of <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.8">
<imaginary_being wordnetid="109483738" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/92134.xml">
Eric Cartman</link></imaginary_being>
</fictional_character>
, from South Park.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Code comments</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 tyd.c: "how many printf's must a man print out, before he is truly a man.." </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 testapp.c: "incrementing counters is like walking to the moon its slow, and if you don't stop, you'll crash."</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Free_Software_Portal_Logo.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Free software&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/620709.xml">
List of Linux distributions</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/331137.xml">
Live CD</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/8111362.xml">
List of Live CDs</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/582146.xml">
openMosix</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://openmosix.sourceforge.net/instant_openmosix_clusters.html">
openMosix: Instant openMosix</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://openmosix.sourceforge.net/#What">
openMosix: What is openMosix?</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://xforce.iss.net/xforce/xfdb/8927">
ISS vulnerability: mosix-malformed-packet-dos (8927)</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.auug.org.au/events/2004/security/">
AUUG Security Symposium: 20 February 2004 - Canberra</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://linux.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/04/08/0552204">
Slashdot: Linux Distro turns PCs into Night-time Clusters</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zdnet.com.au/news/software/0,2000061733,39187301,00.htm">
ZDNet Australia: Linux distro turns PCs into supercomputers</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.purehacking.com/chaos/">
Pure Hacking: CHAOS/openMosix Linux Cluster Distribution</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="8">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.midnightcode.org/projects/chaos/">
Midnight Code: Project Chaos / CosMos (The Great Systems)</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="9">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://72.14.235.104/search?q=cache:KmINNlG2PDIJ:itsecurity.mq.edu.au/chaos/about/index.htm+CHAOS+move+midnightcode.org&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=1">
IT Security: CHAOS - About the distribution</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="10">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.midnightcode.org/projects/libmidnightcode/">
Midnight Code: Project libMidnightCode (Once Written, Twice Linked)</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on June 30, 2007.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.midnightcode.org/projects/chaos/">
CHAOS homepage at Midnight Code</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.purehacking.com/chaos/">
CHAOS-1.6 at Pure Hacking</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.midnightcode.org/papers/White%20Paper%20-%20Security%20and%20openMosix.pdf">
Securely deploying SSI cluster technology over untrusted networking infrastructure</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.midnightcode.org/papers/How%20To%20-%20Heterogeneous%20Clusters.pdf">
Running ClusterKnoppix as a master node to a CHAOS drone army</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wired.com/news/infostructure/0,1377,67220,00.html">
Wired News: Linux Distribution Tames CHAOS</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://linux.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/04/08/0552204">
Slashdot: Linux Distro turns PCs into Night-time Clusters</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zdnet.com.au/news/software/0,2000061733,39187301,00.htm">
ZDNet Australia: Linux distro turns PCs into supercomputers</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/library/l-clustknop.html">
IBM DeveloperWorks: Craft a load-balancing cluster with ClusterKnoppix</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/library/l-colinux/">
IBM DeveloperWorks: Build a heterogeneous cluster with coLinux and openMosix</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.antionline.org/showthread.php?s=fe02aa3a8aaa4db0509d0c46706dbcf6&amp;t=260223">
AntiOnline: How To Make a Password Cracking Cluster</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bofh.be/clusterknoppix/">
ClusterKnoppix</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dirk.eddelbuettel.com/quantian.html">
Quantian</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openwall.com/john/">
John the Ripper</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.citefa.gov.ar/si6/cisilia.htm">
Proyecto Cisilia</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/18212.xml">
Linux distribution</link>s</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/674891.xml">
Arch Linux</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/998890.xml">
CentOS</link></O>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/8242.xml">
Debian</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/9951070.xml">
Fedora</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/94419.xml">
Gentoo</link></O>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/19368.xml">
Mandriva Linux</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/556778.xml">
Red Hat Enterprise Linux</link></O>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/28290.xml">
Slackware</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/7612875.xml">
SUSE</link>&nbsp;·  <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/990298.xml">
Ubuntu</link></O>
&nbsp;·  <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/620709.xml">
more…</link>''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
</article>
