<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:32:50[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Project management</title>
<id>24042</id>
<revision>
<id>244574215</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T14:33:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Pinkadelica</username>
<id>4754643</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Project management</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Project Management</b> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/242710.xml">
discipline</link> of planning, organizing, and managing resources to bring about the successful completion of specific project goals and objectives.  A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/160483.xml">
project</link> is a finite endeavor (having specific start and completion dates) undertaken to create a unique product or service which brings about beneficial change or added value.  This finite characteristic of projects stands in sharp contrast to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/4746766.xml">
process</link>es, or operations, which are permanent or semi-permanent functional work to repetitively produce the same product or service.  In practice, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/19881.xml">
management</link> of these two systems is often found to be quite different, and as such requires the development of distinct technical skills and the adoption of separate management philosophy, which is the subject of this article.<p>

The primary challenge of project management is to achieve all of the project goals and objectives while adhering to classic project constraints&mdash;usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/868833.xml">
scope</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/12115455.xml">
quality</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/30012.xml">
time</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/377116.xml">
budget</link>. The secondary&mdash;and more ambitious&mdash;challenge is to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/43476.xml">
optimize</link> the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/267428.xml">
allocation</link> and integration of inputs necessary to meet pre-defined objectives.  A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/160483.xml">
project</link> is a carefully defined set of activities that use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/11231.xml">
resources</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/8983183.xml">
money</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/3488351.xml">
people</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/249474.xml">
material</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/9649.xml">
energy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/27667.xml">
space</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/2015849.xml">
provisions</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/5177.xml">
communication</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/232495.xml">
motivation</link>, etc.) to achieve the project goals and objectives.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History of project management</st>
<p>

As a discipline, project management developed from different fields of application including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/239038.xml">
construction</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/9251.xml">
engineering</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/228105.xml">
defense</link>.  In the United States, the forefather of project management is <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/401230.xml">
Henry Gantt</link></scientist>
</person>
, called the father of planning and control techniques, who is famously known for his use of the <chart wordnetid="106999802" confidence="0.8">
<visual_communication wordnetid="106873252" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/223160.xml">
Gantt chart</link></visual_communication>
</chart>
 as a project management tool, for being an associate of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<management_consultant wordnetid="110289338" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/204995.xml">
Frederick Winslow Taylor</link></management_consultant>
</person>
's theories of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/389401.xml">
scientific management</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, and for his study of the work and management of Navy ship building.  His work is the forerunner to many modern project management tools including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/33598.xml">
work breakdown structure</link> (WBS) and resource allocation.</p>
<p>

The 1950s marked the beginning of the modern project management era.  Again, in the United States, prior to the 1950s, projects were managed on an ad hoc basis using mostly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/223160.xml">
Gantt Chart</link>s, and informal techniques and tools. At that time, two mathematical project scheduling models were developed: (1) the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/206886.xml">
Program Evaluation and Review Technique</link>" or PERT, developed by Booz-Allen &amp; Hamilton as part of the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/32083.xml">
United States Navy</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
's (in conjunction with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/50042.xml">
Lockheed Corporation</link>) <link>
Polaris missile</link> submarine program<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>; and (2) the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/5939406.xml">
Critical Path Method</link>" (CPM) developed in a joint venture by both <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/201829.xml">
DuPont Corporation</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/352337.xml">
Remington Rand Corporation</link></institution>
</company>
 for managing plant maintenance projects.  These mathematical techniques quickly spread into many private enterprises.</p>
<p>

At the same time, technology for project cost estimating, cost management, and engineering economics was evolving, with pioneering work by Hans Lang and others. In 1956, the American Association of Cost Engineers (now <body wordnetid="105216365" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/7181677.xml">
AACE International</link></group>
</natural_object>
</society>
</social_group>
</body>
; the Association for the Advancement of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/14283013.xml">
Cost Engineering</link>) was formed by early practitioners of project management and the associated specialties of planning and scheduling, cost estimating, and cost/schedule control (project control). AACE has continued its pioneering work and in 2006 released the first ever integrated process for portfolio, program and project management (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/14311364.xml">
Total Cost Management</link> Framework).</p>
<p>

In 1969, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/903856.xml">
Project Management Institute</link> (PMI) was formed to serve the interest of the project management industry.  The premise of PMI is that the tools and techniques of project management are common even among the widespread application of projects from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/1875574.xml">
software industry</link> to the construction industry.  In 1981, the PMI Board of Directors authorized the development of what has become <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/203637.xml">
A Guide to the Project Management Body of Knowledge</link></it> (PMBOK Guide), containing the standards and guidelines of practice that are widely used throughout the profession. The <link>
International Project Management Association</link> (IPMA), founded in Europe in 1967, has undergone a similar development and instituted the IPMA Competence Baseline (ICB). The focus of the ICB also begins with knowledge as a foundation, and adds considerations about relevant experience, interpersonal skills, and competence. Both organizations are now participating in the development of an ISO project management standard.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Definitions</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/203637.xml">
PMBOK</link> (Project Management -- Body of Knowledge as defined by the Project Management Institute &mdash; PMI):"<it>Project management is the application of knowledge, skills, tools and techniques to project activities to meet project requirements.</it>"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/353674.xml">
PRINCE2</link> project management methodology: "<it>The planning, monitoring and control of all aspects of the project and the motivation of all those involved in it to achieve the project objectives on time and to the specified cost, quality and performance.</it>"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 PROJECT: A <it>temporary</it> endeavor with a finite completion date undertaken to create a unique product or service. Projects bring form or function to ideas or needs.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DIN 69901 (Deutsches Institut für Normung - German Organization for Standardization): "<it>Project management is the complete set of tasks, techniques, tools applied during project execution</it>"</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Job description</st>
<p>

Project management is quite often the province and responsibility of an individual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/239050.xml">
project manager</link>. This individual seldom participates directly in the activities that produce the end result, but rather strives to maintain the progress and productive mutual interaction of various parties in such a way that overall risk of failure is reduced.</p>
<p>

A project manager is often a client representative and has to determine and implement the exact needs of the client, based on knowledge of the firm they are representing. The ability to adapt to the various internal procedures of the contracting party, and to form close links with the nominated representatives, is essential in ensuring that the key issues of cost, time, quality, and above all, client satisfaction, can be realized.</p>
<p>

In whatever field, a successful project manager must be able to envision the entire project from start to finish and to have the ability to ensure that this vision is realized.</p>
<p>

Any type of product or service — Pharmaceuticals, buildings, vehicles, electronics, computer software, financial services, etc. — may have its implementation overseen by a project manager and its operations by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/3377544.xml">
product manager</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The traditional triple constraints</st>

<p>

Like any human undertaking, projects need to be performed and delivered under certain constraints. Traditionally, these constraints have been listed as "scope," "time," and "cost" (Chatfield, Carl.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/project/HA102354821033.aspx">
A short course in project management</weblink>", Microsoft.&nbsp;). These are also referred to as the "Project Management Triangle," where each side represents a constraint.  One side of the triangle cannot be changed without affecting the others. A further refinement of the constraints separates product "quality" or "performance" from scope, and turns quality into a fourth constraint.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="The_triad_constraints.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The Project Management Triangle
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The time constraint refers to the amount of time available to complete a project. The cost constraint refers to the budgeted amount available for the project.  The scope constraint refers to what must be done to produce the project's end result.  These three constraints are often competing constraints: increased scope typically means increased time and increased cost, a tight time constraint could mean increased costs and reduced scope, and a tight budget could mean increased time and reduced scope. </p>
<p>

The discipline of project management is about providing the tools and techniques that enable the project team (not just the project manager) to organize their work to meet these constraints.  </p>
<p>

Another approach to project management is to consider the three constraints as finance, time and human resources. If you need to finish a job in a shorter time, you can throw more people at the problem, which in turn will raise the cost of the project, unless by doing this task quicker we will reduce costs elsewhere in the project by an equal amount.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Time</st>
<p>

For analytical purposes, the time required to produce a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/10933184.xml">
deliverable</link> is estimated using several techniques. One method is to identify tasks needed to produce the deliverables documented in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/33598.xml">
work breakdown structure</link> or WBS. The work effort for each task is estimated and those estimates are rolled up into the final deliverable estimate. </p>
<p>

The tasks are also prioritized, dependencies between tasks are identified, and this information is documented in a project schedule. The dependencies between the tasks can affect the length of the overall project (dependency constrained), as can the availability of resources (resource constrained). Time is not considered a cost nor a resource since the project manager cannot control the rate at which it is expended.  This makes it different from all other resources and cost categories.  It should be remembered that no effort expended will have any higher quality than that of the effort- expenders.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Cost</st>
<p>

Cost to develop a project depends on several variables including (chiefly): resource costs, labor rates, material rates, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/26404.xml">
risk management</link> (i.e.<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/14339638.xml">
cost contingency</link>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/9728.xml">
Earned value management</link>, plant (buildings, machines, etc.), equipment, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/6282752.xml">
cost escalation</link>, indirect costs, and profit. But beyond this basic accounting approach to fixed and variable costs, the economic cost that must be considered includes worker skill and productivity which is calculated by variation to project cost estimates.  This is important when companies hire temporary or contract employees or outsource work.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Scope</st>
<p>

Requirements specified to achieve the end result. The overall definition of what the project is supposed to accomplish, and a specific description of what the end result should be or accomplish.  A major component of scope is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/12115455.xml">
quality</link> of the final product.  The amount of time put into individual tasks determines the overall quality of the project. Some tasks may require a given amount of time to complete adequately, but given more time could be completed exceptionally. Over the course of a large project, quality can have a significant impact on time and cost (or vice versa).</p>
<p>

Together, these three constraints have given rise to the phrase "On Time, On Spec, On Budget." In this case, the term "scope" is substituted with "spec(ification)."</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Project management activities</st>
<p>

Project management is composed of several different types of activities such as:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Analysis and design of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/342713.xml">
objectives</link> and events</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/75500.xml">
Planning</link> the work according to the objectives</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Assessing and controlling risk (or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/26404.xml">
Risk Management</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/172504.xml">
Estimating</link> resources</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Allocation of resources</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Organizing the work</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Acquiring human and material resources</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Assigning tasks</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Directing activities</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Controlling project execution</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Tracking and reporting progress (<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/237494.xml">
Management information system</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Analyzing the results based on the facts achieved</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Defining the products of the project</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Forecasting future trends in the project</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/1614268.xml">
Quality Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Issues management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Issue solving</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Defect prevention</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Identifying, managing &amp; controlling changes</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Project closure (and project debrief)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Communicating to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/985467.xml">
stakeholders</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Increasing / decreasing a company's workers</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Project objectives</st>
<p>

Project <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/342713.xml">
objectives</link> define target status at the end of the project, reaching of which is considered necessary for the achievement of planned benefits.  They can be formulated as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/556981.xml">
S.M.A.R.T.</link></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Specific,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Measurable (or at least evaluable) achievement,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Achievable (recently Acceptable is used regularly as well),</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Realistic (given the current state of organizational resources) and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Time terminated (bounded).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The evaluation (measurement) occurs at the project closure. However a continuous guard on the project progress should be kept by monitoring and evaluating.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Project management artifacts</st>
<p>

The following documents serve to clarify objectives and deliverables and to align sponsors, clients, and project team's expectations.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/10617603.xml">
Project Charter</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Preliminary Scope Statement&nbsp;/ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/1211371.xml">
Statement of work</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/1511035.xml">
Business case</link>&nbsp;/ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/1609224.xml">
Feasibility Study</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/2305841.xml">
Scope Statement</link>&nbsp;/ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/7146530.xml">
Terms of reference</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9554239.xml">
Project management plan</link>&nbsp;/ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/3368157.xml">
Project Initiation Document</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/33598.xml">
Work Breakdown Structure</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/962908.xml">
Change Control</link> Plan</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/1503668.xml">
Risk Management Plan</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link>
Risk Breakdown Structure</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link>
Communications Plan</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link>
Governance Model</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/6521362.xml">
Risk Register</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link>
Issue Log</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/5593083.xml">
Action Item List</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</wordnet>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</message>
</database>
</lexical_database>
</examination>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1044927.xml">
Resource Management Plan</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/400459.xml">
Project Schedule</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link>
Project Status Report</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/3181673.xml">
Responsibility assignment matrix</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link>
Database of lessons learned</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/5838705.xml">
Stakeholder Analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/71608.xml">
Document Management</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

These documents are normally hosted on a shared resource (i.e., intranet web page) and are available for review by the project's stakeholders (except for the Stakeholder Analysis, since this document comprises personal information regarding certain stakeholders. Only the Project Manager has access to this analysis).  Changes or updates to these documents are explicitly outlined in the project's configuration management (or change control plan).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Project control variables</st>
<p>

Project Management tries to gain control over variables such as risk:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/25617.xml">
Risk</link> : Potential points of failure: Most negative risks (or potential failures) can be overcome or resolved, given enough planning capabilities, time, and resources. According to some definitions (including PMBOK Third Edition) risk can also be categorized as "positive--" meaning that there is a potential opportunity, e.g., complete the project faster than expected.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Customers (either internal or external project sponsors) and external organizations (such as government agencies and regulators) can dictate the extent of three variables: time, cost, and scope.  The remaining variable (risk) is managed by the project team, ideally based on solid estimation and response planning techniques.  Through a negotiation process among project stakeholders, an agreement defines the final objectives, in terms of time, cost, scope, and risk, usually in the form of a charter or contract.</p>
<p>

To properly control these variables a good project manager has a depth of knowledge and experience in these four areas (time, cost, scope, and risk), and in six other areas as well: integration, communication, human resources, quality assurance, schedule development, and procurement.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Approaches</st>
<p>

There are several approaches that can be taken to managing project activities including agile, interactive, incremental, and phased approaches.</p>
<p>

Regardless of the approach employed, careful consideration needs to be given to clarify surrounding project objectives, goals, and importantly, the roles and responsibilities of all participants and stakeholders.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 The traditional approach </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="600px" src="Project_Management_(phases).png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Typical development phases of a project
</caption>
</image>

A traditional phased approach identifies a sequence of steps to be completed.  In the <b>traditional approach</b>, we can distinguish 5 components of a project (4 stages plus control) in the development of a project:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

project initiation stage;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/75500.xml">
project planning</link> or design stage;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

project execution or production stage;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

project monitoring and controlling systems;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

project completion stage.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Not all the projects will visit every stage as projects can be terminated before they reach completion.  Some projects probably don't have the planning and/or the monitoring.  Some projects will go through steps 2, 3 and 4 multiple times.</p>
<p>

Many industries utilize variations on these stages.  For example, in bricks and mortar architectural design, projects typically progress through stages like Pre-Planning, Conceptual Design, Schematic Design, Design Development, Construction Drawings (or Contract Documents), and Construction Administration.  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/248932.xml">
software development</link>, this approach is often known as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/33980.xml">
waterfall development</link>", i.e., one series of tasks after another in linear sequence. In software development many organizations have adapted the Rational Unified Process (RUP) to fit this methodology, although RUP does not require or explicitly recommend this practice.  Waterfall development can work for small tightly defined projects, but for larger projects of undefined or unknowable scope, it is less suited. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/10302338.xml">
Cone of Uncertainty</link> explains some of this as the planning made on the initial phase of the project suffers from a high degree of uncertainty. This becomes specially true as software development is often the realization of a new or novel product, this method has been widely accepted as ineffective for software projects where requirements are largely unknowable up front and susceptible to change.  While the names may differ from industry to industry, the actual stages typically follow common steps to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/1467948.xml">
problem solving</link> — "defining the problem, weighing options, choosing a path, implementation and evaluation."</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/233624.xml">
Rational Unified Process</link> </st>
<p>

The Rational Unified Process (RUP) is an iterative software development process framework created by the Rational Software Corporation, a division of IBM since 2003.
RUP is not a single concrete prescriptive process, but rather an adaptable process framework, intended to be tailored by the development organizations and software project teams that will select the elements of the process that are appropriate for their needs. The following are phases of RUP, which align to business activities intended to drive successful delivery and deployment of projects. It also provides the taxonomy for blue printing and producing enterprise architecture artifacts across its different domains. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Inception - Identify the initial scope of the project, a potential architecture for the system, and obtain initial project funding and stakeholder acceptance.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Elaboration - Prove the architecture of the system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Construction - Build working software on a regular, incremental basis which meets the highest-priority needs of project stakeholders.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Transition - Validate and deploy the system into the production environment</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The open source version of RUP is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/5564511.xml">
OpenUP</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Temporary organization sequencing concepts </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Action-based entrepreneurship</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Fragmentation for commitment-building</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Planned isolation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Institutionalised termination</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Critical Chain </st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/183373.xml">
Critical chain</link> is the application of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/203932.xml">
Theory of Constraints</link> (TOC) to projects. The goal is to increase the rate of throughput (or completion rates) of projects in an organization. Applying the first three of the five focusing steps of TOC, the system constraint for all projects is identified as resources. To exploit the constraint, tasks on the critical chain are given priority over all other activities. Finally, projects are planned and managed to ensure that the critical chain tasks are ready to start as soon as the needed resources are available, subordinating all other resources to the critical chain.</p>
<p>

For specific projects, the project plan should undergo <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/8756738.xml">
Resource Leveling</link>, and the longest sequence of resource-constrained tasks is identified as the critical chain. In multi-project environments, resource leveling should be performed across projects. However, it is often enough to identify (or simply select) a single "drum" resource—a resource that acts as a constraint across projects—and stagger projects based on the availability of that single resource.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Extreme Project Management </st>
<p>

In critical studies of project management, it has been noted that several of these fundamentally <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/206886.xml">
PERT</link>-based models are not well suited for the multi-project company environment of today. Most of them are aimed at very large-scale, one-time, non-routine projects, and nowadays all kinds of management are expressed in terms of projects. Using complex models for "projects" (or rather "tasks") spanning a few weeks has been proven to cause unnecessary costs and low maneuverability in several cases. Instead, project management experts try to identify different "lightweight" models, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/639009.xml">
Agile Project Management</link> methods including <belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<doctrine wordnetid="105943300" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/10352.xml">
Extreme Programming</link></doctrine>
</belief>
 for software development and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/4743665.xml">
Scrum</link> techniques. The generalization of Extreme Programming to other kinds of projects is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/829803.xml">
extreme project management</link>, which may be used in combination with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1674621.xml">
process modeling</link> and management principles of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/2186768.xml">
human interaction management</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Event chain methodology </st>
<p>

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/10061279.xml">
Event chain methodology</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 is the next advance beyond <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/5939406.xml">
critical path method</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/183373.xml">
critical chain</link> project management. </p>
<p>

Event chain methodology is an uncertainty modeling and schedule network analysis technique that is focused on identifying and managing events and event chains that affect project schedules. Event chain methodology helps to mitigate the negative impact of psychological heuristics and biases, as well as to allow for easy modeling of uncertainties in the project schedules.
Event chain methodology is based on the following major principles. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Probabilistic moment of risk: An activity (task) in most real life processes is not a continuous uniform process. Tasks are affected by external events, which can occur at some point in the middle of the task. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Event chains: Events can cause other events, which will create event chains. These event chains can significantly affect the course of the project. Quantitative analysis is used to determine a cumulative effect of these event chains on the project schedule. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Critical events or event chains: The single events or the event chains that have the most potential to affect the projects are the “critical events” or “critical chains of events.” They can be determined by the analysis. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Project tracking with events: If a project is partially completed and data about the project duration, cost, and events occurred is available, it is possible to refine information about future potential events and helps to forecast future project performance. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Event chain visualization: Events and event chains can be visualized using <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/12936739.xml">
event chain diagrams</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 on a <chart wordnetid="106999802" confidence="0.8">
<visual_communication wordnetid="106873252" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/223160.xml">
Gantt chart</link></visual_communication>
</chart>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Process-based management</st>
<p>

Also furthering the concept of project control is the incorporation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/876008.xml">
process-based management</link>. This area has been driven by the use of Maturity models such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/1288948.xml">
CMMI</link> (Capability Maturity Model Integration) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/894924.xml">
ISO/IEC15504</link> (SPICE - Software Process Improvement and Capability Determination), which have been far more successful.</p>
<p>

Agile project management approaches based on the principles of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/2186768.xml">
human interaction management</link> are founded on a process view of human collaboration.  This contrasts sharply with traditional approach.  In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/639009.xml">
agile software development</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/3550295.xml">
flexible product development</link> approach, the project is seen as a series of relatively small tasks conceived and executed as the situation demands in an adaptive manner, rather than as a completely pre-planned process.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Project systems </st>
<p>

As mentioned above, traditionally, project development includes five elements: control systems and four stages.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Project control systems</st>
<p>

Project control is that element of a project that keeps it on-track, on-time, and within budget. Project control begins early in the project with planning and ends late in the project with  post-implementation review, having a thorough involvement of each step in the process.  Each project should be assessed for the appropriate level of control needed: too much control is too time consuming, too little control is very risky.  If project control is not implemented correctly, the cost to the business should be clarified in terms of errors, fixes, and additional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/224700.xml">
audit</link> fees.</p>
<p>

Control systems are needed for cost, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/25617.xml">
risk</link>, quality, communication, time, change, procurement, and human resources.  In addition, auditors should consider how important the projects are to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/93755.xml">
financial statements</link>, how reliant the stakeholders are on controls, and how many controls exist.  Auditors should review the development process and procedures for how they are implemented.  The process of development and the quality of the final product may also be assessed if needed or requested.  A business may want the auditing firm to be involved throughout the process to catch problems earlier on so that they can be fixed more easily.  An auditor can serve as a controls <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/542306.xml">
consultant</link> as part of the development team or as an independent auditor as part of an audit.  </p>
<p>

Businesses sometimes use formal systems development processes.  These help assure that systems are developed successfully.  A formal process is more effective in creating strong controls, and auditors should review this process to confirm that it is well designed and is followed in practice.  A good formal systems development plan outlines: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/29607.xml">
strategy</link> to align development with the organization’s broader objectives</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Standards for new systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Project management policies for timing and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/377116.xml">
budgeting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Procedures describing the process</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Project development stages</st>
<p>

Regardless of the methodology used, the project development process will have the same major stages: initiation, planning or development, production or execution, maintenance and controlling, and closing.  </p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Initiation </st>
<p>

The initiation stage determines the nature and scope of the development.  If this stage is not performed well, it is unlikely that the project will be successful in meeting the business’s needs.  The key project controls needed here are an understanding of the business environment and making sure that all necessary controls are incorporated into the project.  Any deficiencies should be reported and a recommendation should be made to fix them.  </p>
<p>

The initiation stage should include a cohesive plan that encompasses the following areas:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Study analyzing the business needs in measurable goals.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Review of the current operations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Conceptual design of the operation of the final product.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Equipment requirement.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/651604.xml">
Financial analysis</link> of the costs and benefits including a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/377116.xml">
budget</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Select stake holders, including users, and support personnel for the project.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Project charter including costs, tasks, deliverables, and schedule.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Planning and design </st>
<p>

After the initiation stage, the system is designed.  Occasionally, a small prototype of the final product is built and tested. Testing is generally performed by a combination of testers and end users, and can occur after the prototype is built or concurrently.  Controls should be in place that ensure that the final product will meet the specifications of the project charter.  The results of the design stage should include a product design that:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Satisfies the project sponsor, end user, and business requirements.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Functions as it was intended.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Can be produced within quality standards.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Can be produced within time and budget constraints.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Executing </st>
<p>

Executing consists of the processes used to complete the work defined in the project management plan to accomplish the project's requirements. Execution process involves coordinating people and resources, as well as integrating and performing the activities of the project in accordance with the project management plan. The deliverables are produced as outputs from the processes performed as defined in the project management plan.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Monitoring and Controlling </st>
<p>

Monitoring and Controlling consists of those processes performed to observe project execution so that potential problems can be identified in a timely manner and corrective action can be taken, when necessary, to control the execution of the project. The key benefit is that project performance is observed and measured regularly to identify variances from the project management plan. 
<image location="right" width="300px" src="Project_Management_(project_control).png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Monitoring and Controlling cycle
</caption>
</image>

Monitoring and Controlling includes:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Measuring the ongoing project activities (<it>where we are</it>);</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Monitoring the project variables (cost, effort, ...) against the project management plan and the project performance baseline (<it>where we should be</it>);</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Identify corrective actions to properly address issues and risks (<it>How can we get on track again</it>);</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Influencing the factors that could circumvent integrated change control so only approved changes are implemented</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In multi-phase projects, the Monitoring and Controlling process also provides feedback between project phases, in order to implement corrective or preventive actions to bring the project into compliance with the project management plan.</p>
<p>

Project Maintenance is an ongoing process, and it includes:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Continuing support of end users</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Correction of errors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Updates of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> over time</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In this stage, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/224700.xml">
auditor</link>s should pay attention to how effectively and quickly user problems are resolved.</p>
<p>

Over the course of any construction project, the work scope changes. Change is a normal and expected part of the construction process. Changes can be the result of necessary design modifications, differing site conditions, material availability, contractor-requested changes, value engineering and impacts from third parties, to name a few. Beyond executing the change in the field, the change normally needs to be documented to show what was actually constructed. Hence, the owner usually requires a final record to show all changes or, more specifically, any change that modifies the tangible portions of the finished work. The record is made on the contract documents – usually, but not necessarily limited to, the design drawings. The end
product of this effort is what the industry terms as-built drawings, or more simply, “asbuilts.” The requirement for providing them is a norm in construction contracts.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Closing </st>
<p>

Closing includes the formal acceptance of the project and the ending thereof.  Administrative activities include the archiving of the files and documenting lessons learned. 
Closing phase consist of two parts:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Close project: to finalize all activities across all of the process groups to formally close the project or a project phase</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Contract closure: necessary for completing and settling each contract, including the resolution of any open items, and closing each contract applicable to the project or a project phase.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Project management tools </st>
<p>

Project management tools include
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Financial tools</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cause and effect charts</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Online Project Health Check tool (Ph-Check tool)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/206886.xml">
PERT charts</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <chart wordnetid="106999802" confidence="0.8">
<visual_communication wordnetid="106873252" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/223160.xml">
Gantt chart</link></visual_communication>
</chart>
s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/12936739.xml">
Event Chain Diagrams</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/962858.xml">
RACI diagram</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/6392749.xml">
Run chart</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Project Cycle Optimisation (PCO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/13076799.xml">
Participatory Impact Pathways Analysis</link> (An approach for developing common understanding and consensus amongst project participants and stakeholders as to how the project will achieve its goal)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Also see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/2265048.xml">
List of project management software</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
International standards</st>
<p>

There have been several attempts to develop project management <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/27065.xml">
standard</link>s, such as:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/203637.xml">
A Guide to the Project Management Body of Knowledge</link></it> (<it>PMBOK Guide</it>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/353674.xml">
PRINCE2</link> (<it>PRojects IN Controlled Environments</it>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/1256194.xml">
V-Modell</link> (German project management method)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/4558016.xml">
HERMES method</link> (The Swiss general project management method, selected for use in Luxembourg and international organisations)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/5679193.xml">
Organizational Project Management Maturity Model</link></it> (<it>OPM3</it>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/14934.xml">
International Organisation for Standardisation</link> Founded 1947</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/147042.xml">
ISO 9000</link>: a family of standards for quality management systems.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/208022.xml">
ISO 10006</link>:2003, <it>Quality management systems &mdash; Guidelines for quality management in projects''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/27011.xml">
Software Engineering Institute</link></association>
</institute>
: <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/7492.xml">
Capability Maturity Model</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/14311364.xml">
Total Cost Management</link> Framework</it> (AACE International's process for Portfolio, Program and Project Management) (ref:<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/14283013.xml">
Cost Engineering</link>)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<table width="100%" class="multicol" border="0">
<row>
<col width="48%" valign="top" bgcolor="transparent">
<table >
<row>
<col>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19278728.xml">
Architectural engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/4016107.xml">
Commonware</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/2026112.xml">
Construction management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/239038.xml">
Construction software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/6832338.xml">
Cost overrun</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/14283013.xml">
Cost engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/3218985.xml">
Dependency Structure Matrix</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/9728.xml">
Earned value management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/3550295.xml">
Flexible project management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Functionality, mission and scope <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/682709.xml">
creep</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/652849.xml">
Governance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/257247.xml">
Human Interaction Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/400309.xml">
List of project management topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/6742061.xml">
Megaprojects</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/6389422.xml">
Megaprojects and risk</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<inclination wordnetid="106196584" confidence="0.8">
<bias wordnetid="106201908" confidence="0.8">
<partiality wordnetid="106201136" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/7224456.xml">
Optimism bias</link></partiality>
</bias>
</inclination>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<inclination wordnetid="106196584" confidence="0.8">
<bias wordnetid="106201908" confidence="0.8">
<partiality wordnetid="106201136" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/903029.xml">
Planning fallacy</link></partiality>
</bias>
</inclination>
</entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
<col width="1%" class="multicol-gutter"></col>
<col width="48%" valign="top" bgcolor="transparent">
<table >
<row>
<col>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/2851105.xml">
Portfolio management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/1040968.xml">
Project+</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/912142.xml">
Project accounting</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/5463866.xml">
Project governance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/282626.xml">
Program management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/206011.xml">
Project management software</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/2265048.xml">
List of project management software</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/7217055.xml">
Project workforce management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/6181775.xml">
Process architecture</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/15212186.xml">
Reference class forecasting</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/8756738.xml">
Resource Leveling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/222448.xml">
Six Sigma</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/4016710.xml">
Software project management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/7146530.xml">
Terms of reference</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/31340.xml">
The Mythical Man-Month</link></book>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/1235285.xml">
Timesheet</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://principles-of-scientific-management.blogspot.com/">
The Principles of Scientific Management</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boozallen.com/about/history/history_5">
Booz Allen Hamilton - History of Booz Allen 1950s</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
http://www.pmi.org/info/PP_OPM3ExecGuide.pdf</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ruleworks.co.uk/cgi-bin/TUaz.exe?Guide=Prince2&amp;XL=P&amp;t=PRINCE2%20Knowledgebase">
The PRINCE2 Guide - A to Z, FAQ and 1000+ Exam Questions</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Literature </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Aguanno-2005" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Aguanno, Kevin&#32;(2005). Managing Agile Projects.&#32;Oshawa, ON:&#32;Multi-Media Publications Inc.. ISBN 1-895186-11-0.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Baars-2006" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Baars, Wouter&#32;(2006). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.projectmanagement-training.net/project_management.html">
Project Management Handbook (open source)</weblink>, version 1.1,&#32;Edita-KNAW. ISBN 90 6984 496 6.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Berkun-2005" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Berkun, Scott&#32;(2005). Art of Project Management.&#32;Cambridge, MA:&#32;O'Reilly Media. ISBN 0-596-00786-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Brooks-1995" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Brooks, Fred&#32;(1995). The Mythical Man-Month, 20th Anniversary Edition,&#32;Adison Wesley. ISBN 0-201-83595-9.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Comninos D &amp;-2002" style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(2002). The Practice of Project Management - a guide to the business-focused approach.&#32;Kogan Page. ISBN 0-7494-3694-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Heerkens-2001" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Heerkens, Gary&#32;(2001). Project Management (The Briefcase Book Series).&#32;McGraw-Hill. ISBN 0-07-137952-5.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-International Project Management Association-2006" style="font-style:normal" class="book">International Project Management Association&#32;(2006). ICB - IPMA Competence Baseline, Version 3.0,&#32;IPMA. ISBN 0 9553213 0 1.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Kerzner-2003" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Kerzner, Harold&#32;(2003). Project Management: A Systems Approach to Planning, Scheduling, and Controlling, 8th Ed.,&#32;Wiley. ISBN 0-471-22577-0.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Chamoun-2006" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Chamoun, Yamal&#32;(2006). Professional Project Management, THE GUIDE, 1st.Edition,&#32;Monterrey, NL MEXICO:&#32;McGraw Hill. ISBN 970-10-5922-0.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Lewis-2002" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Lewis, James&#32;(2002). Fundamentals of Project Management, 2nd ed.,&#32;American Management Association. ISBN 0-8144-7132-3.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Meredith, Jack R. and Mantel, Samuel J.&#32;(2002). Project Management : A Managerial Approach, 5th ed.,&#32;Wiley. ISBN 0-471-07323-7.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Project Management Institute&#32;(2003). A Guide To The Project Management Body Of Knowledge, 3rd ed.,&#32;Project Management Institute. ISBN 1-930699-45-X.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Stellman, Andrew and Greene, Jennifer&#32;(2005). Applied Software Project Management.&#32;Cambridge, MA:&#32;O'Reilly Media. ISBN 0-596-00948-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Thayer, Richard H. and Yourdon, Edward&#32;(2000). Software Engineering Project Management, 2nd Ed.,&#32;Wiley-IEEE Computer Society Press. ISBN 0-8186-8000-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Whitty-2005" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Whitty, S. Jonathan&#32;(2005). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://espace.library.uq.edu.au/eserv.php?pid=UQ:8801&amp;dsID=sjw_ijpm_05.pdf">
A Memetic Paradigm of Project Management</weblink>.&#32;International Journal of Project Management, 23 (8) 575-583.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Whitty, S.J. and Schulz, M.F.&#32;(2007). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://espace.library.uq.edu.au/eserv.php?pid=UQ:11452&amp;dsID=sjw_mfs_ijpm_07.pdf">
The impact of Puritan ideology on aspects of project management</weblink>.&#32;International Journal of Project Management, 25 (1) 10-20.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Pettee-2005" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Pettee, Stephen R.&#32;(2005). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://primeedge.com/Asbuilt_news/as-built.pdf">
As-builts – Problems &amp; Proposed Solutions</weblink>.&#32;Construction Management Association of America.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Verzuh-2005" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Verzuh, Eric&#32;(2005). The Fast Forward MBA in Project Management, 2nd,&#32;Wiley. ISBN 0-471-69284-0 (pbk.).</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Woolf-2007" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Woolf, Murray&#32;(2007). Faster Construction Projects with CPM Scheduling, 1st,&#32;McGraw-Hill. ISBN 978-0-07-148660-6.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pmi.org/">
The Project Management Institute</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ipma.ch/">
IPMA - The International Project Management Association</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aipm.com.au/">
The Australian Institute of Project Management</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
