<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:35:15[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<rule  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105846932">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<procedure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101023820">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<algorithm  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105847438">
<header>
<title>Federated search</title>
<id>2421086</id>
<revision>
<id>243984105</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T20:43:10Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>JakobVoss</username>
<id>7276173</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Internet search algorithms</category>
<category>All articles with unsourced statements</category>
<category>Information retrieval</category>
<category>Articles with unsourced statements since June 2008</category>
<category>Internet terminology</category>
<category>Search engine optimization</category>
<category>Searching</category>
<category>Distributed computing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is missing  or needs .</b>
Using helps guard against copyright violations and factual inaccuracies. <it>(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<b>Federated search</b> is the simultaneous search of multiple online <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/4629929.xml">
database</link>s and is an emerging feature of automated, Web-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/17727.xml">
library</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
information retrieval</link> systems. It is also often referred to as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/54293.xml">
portal</link>, as opposed to simply a Web-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Purpose</st>
<p>

As described by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www2.hawaii.edu/~jacso/">
Peter Jacso</weblink> (2004), federated searching consists of (1) transforming a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/679390.xml">
query</link> and broadcasting it to a group of disparate databases with the appropriate syntax, (2) merging the results collected from the databases, (3) presenting them in a succinct and unified format with minimal duplication, and (4) providing a means, performed either automatically or by the portal user, to sort the merged result set. In traditional search engines such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
, only sources that have been indexed by the search engine’s crawler technology can be searched, retrieved and accessed. The large volume of documents housed in databases is not open to traditional Internet search engines because of limitations in crawler technology.  Federated searching resolves this issue by the technique described above and makes these <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/454403.xml">
deep Web</link> documents searchable without having to visit each database individually.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Process </st>
<p>

Federated search <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/5783.xml">
computer program</link>s allow users to search multiple information sources with a single query from a single user interface. The user enters a search query in the portal interface’s search box and the query is sent to every individual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> in the portal or federated search list. Access details for the individual databases must be preset in the portal by its owner. Federated search systems either rely upon vendors to create commercial portal systems, or they rely upon government or other organizations to provide open access portals.  How federated search is implemented depends upon which of the two types of organizations is providing the portal.</p>
<p>

Federated search portals, either commercial or open access, generally search public access <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/4629929.xml">
bibliographic databases</link>, public access Web-based library catalogues (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../953/465953.xml">
OPAC</link>s), Web-based search engines like <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 and/or open-access, government-operated or corporate data collections. These individual information sources send back to the portal's interface a list of results from the search query. The user can review this hit list.  Some portals will merely <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/971731.xml">
screen scrape</link> the actual database results and not directly allow a user to enter the information source's application. More sophisticated ones will de-dupe the results list by merging and removing duplicates. There are additional features available in many portals, but the basic idea is the same: to improve the accuracy and relevance of individual searches as well as reduce the amount of time required to search for resources.</p>
<p>

This process allows federated search some key advantages when compared with existing crawler-based search engines.  Federated search need not place any requirements or burdens on owners of the individual information sources, other than handling increased traffic.  Federated searches are inherently as current as the individual information sources, as they are searched in real time.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Implementation</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="256px" src="Federated-search-en.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

architecture of a federated search engine
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

One application of federated searching is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/548297.xml">
metasearch engine</link>; however, this is not a complete solution as many documents are not currently indexed. This is known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/454403.xml">
deep Web</link> or invisible Web. Many more information sources are not yet stored in electronic form. <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/1520204.xml">
Google Scholar</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 is an example of a project trying to address this.</p>
<p>

When the search vocabulary or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/82871.xml">
data model</link> of the search system is different from the data model of one or more of the foreign target systems the query must be translated into each of the foreign target systems.  This can be done using simple data-element translation or may require <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/2994894.xml">
semantic translation</link>.</p>
<p>

A challenge faced in the implementation of federated search engines is scalability, i.e. the performance of the site as the number of information sources comprising the federated search engine increase. One federated search engine that has begun to address this issue is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/16358354.xml">
WorldWideScience</link>, hosted by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/62866.xml">
U.S. Department of Energy</link>'s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/1705633.xml">
Office of Scientific and Technical Information</link>.  WorldWideScience <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> is composed of more than 40 information sources, several of which are federated search portals themselves.  One such portal is Science.gov <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> which itself federates more than 30 information sources representing most of the R&amp;D output of the U.S. Federal government.  Science.gov returns its highest ranked results to WorldWideScience, which then merges and ranks these results with the search returned by the other information sources that comprise WorldWideScience.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> This approach of cascaded federated search enables large number of information sources to be searched via a single query.</p>
<p>

Another application <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/12417558.xml">
Sesam</link></software>
 running in both Norway and Sweden has been built on top of an open sourced platform specialised for federated search solutions. Sesat,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>, an acronym for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/12417558.xml">
Sesam Search Application Toolkit</link>, is a platform that provides much of the framework and functionality required for handling parallel and pipelined searches and displaying them elegantly in a user interface, allowing engineers to focus on the index/database configuration tuning.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/548297.xml">
Metasearch engine</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/7438834.xml">
Funnelback</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/2351677.xml">
Aggregator</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worldwidescience.org">
WorldWideScience</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.science.gov">
Science.gov</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.science.gov">
Science.gov</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sesat.no">
Sesat</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</article>
