<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:35:28[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<disorder  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114052403">
<condition  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113920835">
<state  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100024720">
<physical_condition  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114034177">
<header>
<title>Sluggish cognitive tempo</title>
<id>2424129</id>
<revision>
<id>242168615</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T04:44:26Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Neurological disorders</category>
<category>Educational psychology</category>
<category>Special education</category>
<category>Childhood psychiatric disorders</category>
<category>Attention</category>
<category>Psychiatry</category>
<category>Attention disorders</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Sluggish Cognitive Tempo</b> (SCT) is an unformalized descriptive term which is used to better identify what appears to be a homogeneous sub-subgroup within the formal subgroup <disorder wordnetid="114052403" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/4081458.xml">
ADHD predominantly inattentive</link></physical_condition>
</state>
</condition>
</disorder>
 (ADHD-I or ADHD-PI) classification in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/8498.xml">
Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, fourth edition</link>.  It has been roughly estimated that the SCT population may make up 30-50% of the ADHD-PI population. <p>

In many ways, those who have an SCT profile have the opposite symptoms of those with classic ADHD: Instead of being <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/1338380.xml">
hyperactive</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/8386509.xml">
extroverted</link>, obtrusive, and risk takers, those with SCT are passive, daydreamy, shy, and "HYPO"-active in both a mental and physical way. They also don't have the same risk factors and outcomes. Their demeanor is sluggish, as if "in a fog" and logically they also process information more slowly. A key behavioural characteristic of those with SCT symptoms is that they are more likely to appear to be lacking motivation. They lack energy to deal with mundane tasks and will consequently seek things that are mentally stimulating because of their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/532199.xml">
underaroused state</link>. Those with SCT symptoms show a qualitatively different kind of attention deficit that is more typical of a true information input-output problem, such as memory retrieval and active <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/33912.xml">
working memory</link>. Conversely, those with the other two subtypes of ADHD are characteristically excessively energetic and have no difficulty processing information.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>

<sec>
<st>
Diagnosis</st>
<p>

Since the symptoms of SCT are not recognized in any standard medical manuals, those who have significant SCT symptoms would likely receive an ADHD/PI diagnosis. Currently the APA is considering the inclusion of SCT in the DSM-V, which is scheduled to be released in 2012.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Causes</st>
<p>

Like ADHD, those with SCT symptoms have a condition that appears to be genetic in nature. Far less is known about this group yet the impairments seem to indicate the prefrontal cortex region of the brain and difficulties with working memory. The 7-repeat allele polymorphism of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/1998759.xml">
DRD4</link> gene is also linked more strongly to this group than to ADHD/C and ADHD/PHI subgroups.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

It is thought that SCT, ADHD-PI, and ADHD are due to variations in the availability of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/48548.xml">
dopamine</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/9903342.xml">
norepinephrine</link>, and/or the efficiency of the large chemical structures of the specific receptors and re-uptake receptors. This would explain the efficacy of stimulants such as amphetamines on the treatment of ADHD and SCT.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Treatment</st>
<p>

Up to 90% of children with ADHD respond well to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/205878.xml">
methylphenidate</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/205878.xml">
Ritalin</link>) at medium-to-high doses<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>, however, a sizable percentage of children with ADHD-PI do not gain much benefit from Ritalin, and when they do benefit, it is at a much lower dose. Tests in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/5755911.xml">
lab rat</link>s have demonstrated that low doses of Ritalin can increase norepinephrine levels.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

Those with ADHD-PI often respond well to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/26th_century.xml">
amphetamines</link>, such as the prescription medication <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/649100.xml">
Adderall</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> While methylphenidate and amphetamines have many similar effects on patients (both inhibit reuptake of the neurotransmitters dopamine and norepinephrine, for example), amphetamines also promote release of those neurotransmitters. This positive effect appears to support the hypothesis that SCT is related to neurotransmitter deficiencies.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Prognosis</st>
<p>

ADHD is a developmental disorder, meaning that certain traits will be delayed in the ADHD individual. These traits can and usually will develop in people with ADHD, but just at a much slower rate than the average person. With ADHD, it has been estimated that this lag could be as high as thirty to forty percent in the development of certain skill sets, such as selective attention. Symptoms of ADHD are often seen by the time a child enters preschool. Those with SCT symptoms typically show a later onset of symptoms in comparison to ADHD. They have greater difficulty with academic tasks and far fewer social difficulties when compared to those with combo and hyperactive ADHD.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Selective attention difficulties of those with SCT manifests itself academically, in that they are prone to making more mistakes while working. Those with classic ADHD do not have this difficulty. Those with SCT have difficulty with verbal retrieval from long term memory, but may have greater visual spatial capabilities. They have deficits in working memory which has been described as the ability to keep multiple things in mind for manipulation, while simultaneously keeping this information free from internal distraction. Consequently, mental skills such as calculation, reading, and abstract reasoning are often more challenging for those with SCT. They also have a more disorganized thought process, a greater degree of sloppiness, and lose things more easily. They tend to have a greater degree of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/217631.xml">
comorbid</link> learning disabilities. Instead of having greater difficulty selecting and filtering sensory input, as is in the case of SCT, people with other types of ADHD have problems with inhibition.</p>
<p>

Studies indicate that comorbid psychiatric problems are more often of the internalizing variety with SCT, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/922.xml">
anxiety</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/840273.xml">
depression</link>, and social withdrawal. Their typical shy nature and slow response time has often been misinterpreted as aloofness or disinterest by others. In social group interactions, those with SCT may be ignored. Those with the other types of ADHD are more likely to be rejected in social situations, because of more intrusive or aggressive behavior. Those with classic ADHD also show externalizing problems such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/256038.xml">
substance abuse</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/2849297.xml">
oppositional-defiant disorder</link>, and, to a lesser degree, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../209/159209.xml">
conduct disorder</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Prevention</st>
<p>

There is no known way to prevent ADHD/PI. Some studies indicate an association between mothers who smoke during pregnancy and a higher rate of ADHD in their children.  Avoiding smoking, alcohol, and drugs during pregnancy may help reduce the risk of developing ADHD or similar behaviour in offspring.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History of the term SCT and its relationship to the DSM</st>
<p>

Sluggishness, drowsiness, and daydreaming were the characteristics listed in the DSM-III (in use from 1980-1987) that were to also be present in the diagnosis of Attention Deficit Disorder (ADD) without Hyperactivity. In a study looking at these symptoms (Lahey et al., 1988) the authors stated, "these symptoms were statistically extracted as a distinct factor", coined, Sluggish Cognitive Tempo. The Sluggish Tempo factor was found to correlate significantly to the Inattention factor, but only when Hyperactivity-Impulsivity symptoms were absent. </p>
<p>

Sluggish Cognitive Tempo symptoms were removed from the Inattention symptom list in 1988 because of poor negative predictive power for the inattentive subgroup, and because DSM contributors and editors wanted the inattentive symptoms to be identical for all ADHD subgroups. The presence of the SCT symptoms tended to predict inattention, but the absence of these symptoms did not predict the absence of inattention.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> This analysis did not take into account the possibility  that the SCT symptoms could help predict a distinct grouping within the ADHD/PI subgroup and that the ADHD/PI subgrouping could be heterogeneous in nature.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> </p>
<p>

In the DSM-IV, with its new classification of symptoms for predominately inattentive ADHD, 50 to 70% of those with a ADHD-PI diagnosis have subclinical levels of hyperactivity-impulsiveness symptoms. People with ADHD combined type (ADHD-C) and predominantly hyperactive–impulsive type (ADHD-PHI) may outgrow some, or most of their hyperactive symptoms during or after childhood, while inattentive symptoms typically remain into adulthood. In contrast, those with SCT have had only inattentive features from a young age with little to no history of hyperactivity-impulsiveness. Dr. Russell Barkley has proposed that the DSM-IV designation of ADHD-PI be used only for those displaying purely inattentive symptoms and that those who have had a history of <it>any</it> hyperactivity be designated as ADHD combined subtype. Currently, one can have a few hyperactive symptoms and still receive a diagnosis ADHD-PI. Others believe that SCT should be classified as a new separate disorder when the DSM is next updated.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Relationship to dysexecutive syndrome</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/3704475.xml">
Executive system</link> of the human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/3717.xml">
brain</link> coordinates actions and strategies for everyday tasks. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/16218170.xml">
Dysexecutive syndrome</link> is defined as  "cluster of impairments generally associated with damage to the frontal lobes of the brain" which includes "difficulties with high-level tasks such as planning, organising, initiating, monitoring and adapting behaviour."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> </p>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<chair wordnetid="103001627" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<furnishing wordnetid="103405265" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="104161981" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<furniture wordnetid="103405725" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/6127220.xml">
Adele Diamond</link></psychologist>
</furniture>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</seat>
</furnishing>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</person>
</chair>
</physical_entity>
 has recently postulated that the core cognitive deficit of those with ADHD-PI (ADD), is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/33912.xml">
working memory</link>, or, as she coined in her recent paper on the subject, "childhood-onset dysexecutive syndrome". She states:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Instructional methods that place heavy demands on working memory will disproportionately disadvantage individuals with ADD".</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "language problems often co-occur with ADD, and it is suggested that part of the reason might be that linguistic tasks, especially verbal ones, tax working memory so heavily. Spatial and artistic skills, however, are often preserved or superior in individuals with ADD."</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "The working memory deficit in many children with ADD is accompanied by markedly slowed reaction times, a characteristic that covaries with poorer working memory in general". </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Individuals with ADD have difficulty maintaining a sufficiently high level of motivation to complete a task...They go looking for something else to do or think about because they are bored...to remedy a general lower arousal level.."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/64976.xml">
Attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder</link></disease>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <disorder wordnetid="114052403" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/4081458.xml">
ADHD predominantly inattentive</link></physical_condition>
</state>
</condition>
</disorder>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/1295947.xml">
Dysthymia</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/65845.xml">
Hypothyroidism</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.schwablearning.org/articles.aspx?r=54">
Dr. Russell Barkley: AD/HD Theory, Diagnosis, &amp; Treatment Summary</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
 Diamond, Adele <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1474811">
Attention-deficit disorder (attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder without hyperactivity): A neurobiologically and behaviorally distinct disorder from attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (with hyperactivity)</weblink> <it>Development and Psychopathology</it> 17: 807-825 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/31796.xml">
Cambridge University</link> Press (2005)</entry>
<entry id="3">
Diamond, Adele, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1474811">
"Attention-deficit disorder (attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder without hyperactivity): A neurobiologically and behaviorally distinct disorder from attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (with hyperactivity)"</weblink>, (2006)</entry>
<entry id="4">
Diamond, 2006</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ninds.nih.gov/disorders/adhd/adhd.htm">
NINDS Attention Deficit-Hyperactivity Disorder Information Page</weblink> Oppositional and socially aggressive behavior is seen in 40-70 percent of children at this age.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Barkley, Russell <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.continuingedcourses.net/active/courses/course003.php">
Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder: Nature, Course, Outcomes, and Comorbidity</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1093/clipsy.8.4.463">
Blackwell Synergy - Clin Psychol Sci &amp; Pract, Volume 8 Issue 4 Page 463-488, December 2001 (Article Abstract)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=11411783&amp;dopt=Abstract">
Symptom properties as a function of ADHD type: an ...[J Abnorm Child Psychol. 2001&#93; - PubMed Result</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
http://www.dwp.gov.uk/advisers/joped/vol5/no2_sum_03_test_review_2.pdf</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.continuingedcourses.net/active/courses/course003.php">
ADHD: Nature, Course, Outcomes, and Comorbidity by Russell A. Barkley, Ph.D.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1474811">
Attention-deficit disorder (attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder without hyperactivity): A neurobiologically and behaviorally distinct disorder from attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (with hyperactivity) by ADELE DIAMOND</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.schwablearning.org/articles.asp?r=54">
Dr. Russell Barkley on ADHD.</weblink> ( SCT is mentioned in the second section of the lecture notes entitled: "is Inattentive ADHD really another disorder")</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chadd.org/AM/Template.cfm?Section=Attention_Magazine&amp;Template=/CM/ContentDisplay.cfm&amp;ContentID=3347.">
An interview with Richard Milich entitled, "Lost in the shuffle - the inattentive child without hyperactivity"</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1093/clipsy.8.4.463">
ADHD Combined and ADHD Predominantly Inattentive Type are Distinct and unrelated disorders by Milich et al</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</physical_condition>
</state>
</condition>
</disorder>
</article>
