<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:37:46[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<standard  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107260623">
<header>
<title>Advanced Configuration and Power Interface</title>
<id>2432697</id>
<revision>
<id>244208837</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T20:06:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>FreeRangeFrog</username>
<id>8043052</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cleanup from section</category>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>All articles needing copy edit</category>
<category>Open standards</category>
<category>Wikify from September 2008</category>
<category>Application programming interfaces</category>
<category>Articles to be expanded since July 2008</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing copy edit from June 2008</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
<category>All articles to be expanded</category>
<category>BIOS</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it has <b>insufficient  .</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="30px" src="Acap.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  for  grammar, style, cohesion, tone or spelling.</b>
You can assist by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Advanced_Configuration_and_Power_Interface&amp;action=edit">
editing it</weblink> now. A how-to is available.<it>&nbsp;(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


The <b>Advanced Configuration and Power Interface</b> (<b>ACPI</b>) specification, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/227018.xml">
open industry standard</link> first released in December 1996 (developed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/13973.xml">
HP</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/14617.xml">
Intel</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/3031470.xml">
Phoenix</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/59703.xml">
Toshiba</link></company>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/102490.xml">
Dell</link>), defines common interfaces for hardware recognition, motherboard and device configuration and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/273703.xml">
power management</link>. According to its specification,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> "ACPI is the key element in Operating System-directed configuration and Power Management (OSPM)."</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/6699491.xml">
 latest</link> revision of the ACPI specification, 3.0b, appeared on October 10, 2006.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>

<p>

The most widely recognized element of the standard, power management has seen a major improvement.</p>
<p>

Previously, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/3130.xml">
Advanced Power Management</link> model (APM) assigned power management control almost exclusively to the <generic wordnetid="107899976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/Form_4473.xml">
BIOS</link></generic>
, which greatly limited the functionality of the OS in controlling power consumption.</p>
<p>

Currently, ACPI brings power management features previously only available in portable computers (such as laptops) to Desktops, Workstations and Servers. For example, systems may be put into extremely low power consumption states. These are the "sleep" and "hibernate" settings available on most Desktops. The Sleep and Hibernate states can wake the system by moving the mouse, pressing a key on the keyboard, receiving a message from another computer (if connected to a LAN) or critical system errors.</p>
<p>

Some vendors such as ASUS and Compaq have provided other special keys to bring the system back to full functionality.&#91;&#93;</p>
<p>

Now if ACPI is implemented in the BIOS and other system hardware, it may be invoked (triggered) by the operating system.</p>
<p>

Windows 98 was the first Microsoft OS to support ACPI. FreeBSD v5.0 was the first UNIX OS to support ACPI. Linux, NetBSD and OpenBSD all have at least some support for ACPI.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 States </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Global states </st>
<p>

The ACPI specification defines the following seven states (so-called global states) which an ACPI-compliant computer system can be in:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>G0</b> (<b>S0</b>) <it>Working</it>: the normal working state of the computer — the operating system and applications are running. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/5218.xml">
CPU</link>(s) execute instructions. Within this state (i.e., without entering G1 <it>Sleeping</it>), it is possible for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/5218.xml">
CPU</link>(s) and devices like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard drive</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/11014498.xml">
DVD drive</link>s, etc. to be repeatedly put into and come back from low-energy states, called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Processor+states%22])">
<it>C0</it>–<it>C</it>n</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Device+states%22])">
<it>D0</it>–<it>D3''</it></link>. (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/198584.xml">
Laptop</link>s, for example, routinely power down all currently unused devices when running on battery; some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/52742.xml">
desktops</link> also do this to reduce noise.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>G1</b> <it>Sleeping</it> subdivides into the four states S1 through S4. The time needed to bring the system from here back into G0 <it>Working</it> (<it>wake-latency</it> time) is shortest for S1, short for S2 and S3, and not so short for S4.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <b>S1</b>: the most power-hungry of sleep-modes. All processor caches are flushed, and the CPU(s) stop executing instructions. Power to the CPU(s) and RAM is maintained; devices that do not indicate they must remain on may be powered down. This mode is often referred to as <it>Power On Standby</it> or simply POS, particularly in BIOS configuration screens. Some newer machines do not support S1; older machines are more likely to support S1 than S3.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <b>S2</b>: a deeper sleep-state than S1, where the CPU is powered off; however, it is not commonly implemented.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <b>S3</b>: known as <it>Suspend to RAM</it> (STR) in the BIOS, <it>Standby</it> in versions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link> through <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/33879.xml">
Windows XP</link></version>
 and in some varieties of <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
, <it>Sleep</it> in <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>, although the ACPI specification mentions only the terms <it>S3</it> and <it>Sleep</it>. In this state, main memory (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/25847.xml">
RAM</link>) is still powered, although it is almost the only component that is. Since the state of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> and all applications, open documents, etc. lies all in main memory, the user can resume work exactly where they left off—the main memory content when the computer comes back from S3 is the same as when it was put into S3. (The specification mentions that S3 is rather similar to S2, only that some more components are powered down in S3.) S3 has two advantages over S4; the computer is faster to resume than to reboot, secondly if any running applications (opened documents, etc) have private information in them, this will not be written to the disk. However, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/6829.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Disk+buffer%22])">
disk caches</link> may be flushed to prevent data corruption in case the system doesn't wake up e.g. due to power failure.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <b>S4</b>: <it>Hibernation</it> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link>, <it>Safe Sleep</it> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>, also known as <it>Suspend to disk</it>, although the ACPI specification mentions only the term <it>S4</it> (<it>main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/3220132.xml">
Hibernate (OS feature)</link></it>). In this state, all content of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/25847.xml">
main memory</link> is saved to non-volatile memory such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard drive</link>, preserving the state of the operating system, all applications, open documents etc. That means that after coming back from S4, the user can resume work where it was left off in much the same way as with S3. The difference between S4 and S3, apart from the added time of moving the main memory content to disk and back, is that a power loss of a computer in S3 makes it lose all data in main memory, including all unsaved documents, while a computer in S4 is unaffected. S4 is quite different from the other <it>S</it> states and actually resembles G2 <it>Soft Off</it> and G3 <it>Mechanical Off</it> more than it resembles S1–S3. A system that's in S4 can also be put in G3 (<it>Mechanical Off</it>) and still keep its S4 save state information, so that it can resume the operating state after getting back power.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>G2</b> (<b>S5</b>) <it>Soft Off</it>-- <it>G2</it>, <it>S5</it>, and <it>Soft Off</it> are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/67396.xml">
synonym</link>s. G2 is almost the same as G3 <it>Mechanical Off</it>, but some components remain powered so the computer can "wake" from input from the keyboard, clock, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/1557503.xml">
 modem</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/33958.xml">
LAN</link>, or <bus wordnetid="102924116" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/32073.xml">
USB</link></bus>
 device.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> This state equates to G3 <it>Mechanical Off</it> in that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml">
boot procedure</link> must be run to bring the system from G2 to G0 <it>Working</it>. G3 <it>Mechanical Off</it> is entered only when a power loss occurs, whereas G2 is initiated by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> (typically because the user issued a shutdown command in some way). The computer is not safe for disassembly in the G2 state due to the components that remain powered. It is advisable to unplug a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/52742.xml">
desktop computer</link> and wait 20 seconds prior to disassembly; although internal drives are usually not powered, the (<connection wordnetid="103091374" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/3266317.xml">
PS2</link></connection>
) keyboard, USB ports, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/19945.xml">
mainboard</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/75022.xml">
expansion card</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/7578564.xml">
power supply</link> may remain powered, even if the computer is not used to wake from input to these devices.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>G3</b> <it>Mechanical Off</it>: The computer's power consumption approaches close to zero, to the point that the power cord can be removed and the system is safe for disassembly (typically, only the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/535191.xml">
real-time clock</link> is running off its own small battery). The computer falls into this state when a power loss occurs, e.g. in case of a power outage. Once power is restored, a full <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml">
boot procedure</link> is necessary to bring the system from G3 to G0 <it>Working</it>.</entry>
</list>

Furthermore, a state <it>Legacy</it> is defined as the state when an operating system runs which does not support ACPI. In this state, the hardware and power are not managed via ACPI, effectively disabling ACPI.</p>
<p>

(Reference: ACPI specification 3.0b is linked to under <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22External+links%22])">
External links</link>, section 7.3.4)</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Device states </st>
<p>

The device states <it>D0</it>-<it>D3</it> are device-dependent:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 D0 <it>Fully-On</it> is the operating state.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 D1 and D2 are intermediate power-states whose definition varies by device.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 D3 <it>Off</it> has the device powered off and unresponsive to its bus.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Processor states </st>
<p>

The CPU power states <it>C0</it>-<it>C3</it> are defined as follows:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C0 is the operating state.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C1 (often known as <it>Halt</it>) is a state where the processor is not executing instructions, but can return to an executing state essentially instantaneously. Some processors, such as the <chip wordnetid="103020034" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<microprocessor wordnetid="103760310" confidence="0.8">
<conductor wordnetid="103088707" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<semiconductor_device wordnetid="104171831" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/165228.xml">
Pentium 4</link></semiconductor_device>
</device>
</conductor>
</microprocessor>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</chip>
, also support an Enhanced C1 state (C1E) for lower power consumption.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C2 (often known as <it>Stop-Clock</it>) is a state where the processor maintains all software-visible state, but may take longer to wake up.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C3 (often known as <it>Sleep</it>) is a state where the processor does not need to keep its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/6829.xml">
cache</link> coherent, but maintains other state. Some processors have variations on the C3 state (Deep Sleep, Deeper Sleep, etc.) that differ in how long it takes to wake the processor.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Performance states </st>
<p>

While a device or processor operates (D0 and C0, respectively), it can be in one of several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/2160626.xml">
power-performance states</link>. These states are implementation-dependent, but P0 is always the highest-performance state, with P1 to P<it>n</it> being successively lower-performance states, up to an implementation-specific limit of <it>n</it> no greater than 16.</p>
<p>

P-states have become known as <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/2234797.xml">
SpeedStep</link></commodity>
</merchandise>
</artifact>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/14617.xml">
Intel</link> processors, <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/861612.xml">
PowerNow!</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 or <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/1883225.xml">
Cool'n'Quiet</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 in <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
AMD</link></company>
 processors and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/12255055.xml">
PowerSaver</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/450868.xml">
VIA</link> processors.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 ACPI Tables </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Advanced_Configuration_and_Power_Interface&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


Operating-systems use these tables to get information about hardware.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

RSDP (Root System Description Pointer)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

RSDT (Root System Description Table)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

DSDT (Differentiated System Description Table)</entry>
</list>

It is a part of the ACPI specification and it supplies configuration information about a base system.</p>
<p>

The DSDT comprises a system description table header, followed by a definition block. The definition block is encoded using ACPI Machine Language (AML), and unlike other definition blocks on the system, the DSDT definition block can not be unloaded, as it provides the basic ACPI namespace scope that all other dynamic definition blocks can later add onto.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

XSDT (Extended System Description Table)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

FADT (Fixed ACPI Description Table)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

FACS (Firmware ACPI Control Structure)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

SBST (Smart Battery Table)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

ECDT (Embedded Controller Boot Resources Table)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

MADT (Multiple APIC Description Table)</entry>
</list>

Different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/3253403.xml">
APIC</link> models exist. This table is used to identify the model and provide the starting point (pointers to other tables/structures) that implements it.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

SRAT (System Resource Affinity Table)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Operating-systems aware of NUMA (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/40643.xml">
Non-Uniform Memory Access</link>) use this table to allocate local memory to local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/45303.xml">
threads</link> on NUMA systems, e.g. on multi processor <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/165237.xml">
AMD Opteron</link> systems. For a real <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/40643.xml">
NUMA</link> system, "Node Interleave" in Opteron BIOSes has to be disabled, accordingly "SRAT" has to be enabled. Furthermore the operating system itself has to support NUMA as well. So far all x64 Windows Systems and Linux systems with a NUMA aware <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/50394.xml">
kernel</link> are NUMA capable.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

SLIT (System Locality Distance Information Table)</entry>
</list>

This optional SLIT (System Locality Information Table) describes the distances between all processors, memory controllers, and host bridges. Each module gets associated with specific locality (could tie with the _PXM) which will be equivalent to an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/50318.xml">
SMP</link> node. The table will give units of distance between nodes. The units of distance will be relative to the SMP or intra-node distance. SMP distances will arbitrarily have a value of 10. There is a field in the table called Localities. Localities is the number of localities in the SLIT. It is an unsigned 64-bit integer. The locality indices for each locality range from 0 to Localities-1. The SLIT can be viewed as a matrix of distances, with row i of the matrix indicating the distance from locality i to every locality (including itself). Each table entry is a 1-byte unsigned integer. To get the distance from locality i to locality j, read the i*(Localities) + j entry in the matrix. Except for the distances from a locality to itself, each distance is stored twice in the matrix.
What this means is that the diagonal elements of the matrix, the distances from a locality to itself, which are the SMP distances, are all given a value of 10. The distances for the non-diagonal elements are scaled to be relative to the SMP distance, so, for example, if the distance from locality i to locality j is 2.4 times the SMP distance, a value of 24 would be stored in table entry i*(localities)+ j and in j*(localities)+ i. If one locality is unreachable from another, a value of 255 (0xFF) will be stored in that table entry. A value of 0 has no meaning, and is reserved. Values 1 through 9 are also reserved. This will enable the operating system to enhance its ability to process the locality information to increase its performance on a NUMA system.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

SLIC (Software Licensing Description Table)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/69922.xml">
OEM</link> versions of <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
 use this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/6699491.xml">
 newly-released</link> table for activation by Royalty OEMs in order for the end-user to not have problems with activating, called SLP 2.0, or System-Locked Preinstallation 2.0. For activation to work, clients obtained through the OEM channels that have an ACPI_SLIC table in the system BIOS are required to have a valid Windows marker in the same ACPI_SLIC table. The appearance of the Windows marker is important for volume license customers who are planning to use Windows Vista volume-licensed media to re-image or upgrade OEM through the re-imaging rights provided in their volume license agreement. Not having the appropriate BIOS marker results in an error or errors on these systems and prevents them from activating.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

SSDT (Secondary System Descriptor Table)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Criticism </st>


<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that some of the information in this article's  be merged into other sections to achieve a . ()</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The complex and lengthy ACPI specification (over 600 pages long) contains multiple components, including declarative tables, an imperative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/89997.xml">
bytecode</link>, and specific hardware components. Concerns have been repeatedly raised<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> that an implementation of ACPI has to run complex, untrusted and potentially buggy bytecode with full privileges, thus potentially making any system that implements ACPI unstable and/or insecure.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Where hardware does not conform to ACPI, but claims to do so, the software interoperating with that hardware is faced with a dilemma: either it can be written to be ACPI-compliant, thus risking problems with the not-entirely-compliant hardware, or it can deviate from the ACPI standard to accommodate the hardware quirks. That, however, is generally seen as undesirable from a software-engineering point of view, since the software would potentially have to be adapted for and tested with arbitrarily large numbers of hardware devices, which is precisely what standards such as ACPI are intended to avoid. Additionally, availability of compatible software does not provide the hardware manufacturer with an incentive to repair their compliance. This is a constant debate between "standards purists" and advocates of software that "simply works" with as much hardware as possible.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 ACPI Component Architecture (ACPICA) </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="36px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Advanced_Configuration_and_Power_Interface&amp;action=edit">
improve this section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(July 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


The ACPI Component Architecture (ACPICA) is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link> reference implementation of ACPI.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="100949134" confidence="0.8">
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<technology wordnetid="100949619" confidence="0.8">
<profession wordnetid="100609953" confidence="0.8">
<use wordnetid="100947128" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1661475.xml">
Green computing</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</device>
</event>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</machine>
</use>
</profession>
</technology>
</occupation>
</application>
</computer>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<key wordnetid="103613294" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/4133075.xml">
Power management keys</link></key>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/1557503.xml">
Wake-on-Ring</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acpi.info/spec.htm">
ACPI</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kananov.com/notes/s3">
Aram Kananov » How To: ACPI Suspend to RAM on Dell Latitude D800 with Fedora Core 3</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/942962">
You receive an error message when you try to activate Windows Vista on a computer that was obtained from an OEM</weblink>".&#32;  Microsoft&#32;(2007-11-02).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-04</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lwn.net/2001/0704/kernel.php3">
LWN - Kernel</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acpica.org/">
ACPICA</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acpi.info/">
ACPI home page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://developer.intel.com/technology/iapc/acpi/downloads.htm">
Intel's ACPI Component Architecture</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lesswatts.org/projects/acpi/">
ACPI for Linux</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/man.cgi?query=acpi&amp;format=html">
ACPI for FreeBSD</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.advogato.org/article/913.html">
How Linux Suspend and Resume works in the ACPI age</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hardwaresecrets.com/article/611">
Everything You Need to Know About the CPU C-States Power Saving Modes</weblink></entry>
</list>

<it>This article was originally based on material from the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<wordbook wordnetid="106418693" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<dictionary wordnetid="106418901" confidence="0.8">
<reference_book wordnetid="106417598" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/11324.xml">
Free On-line Dictionary of Computing</link></publication>
</reference_book>
</dictionary>
</book>
</wordbook>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
, which is  under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/18938782.xml">
GFDL</link>.</it></p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</standard>
</article>
