<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:36:41[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>United States Waiver of Inadmissibility</title>
<id>2445442</id>
<revision>
<id>243363324</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T05:08:04Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Regina17</username>
<id>8013466</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Immigration to the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

An <b>Application for Waiver of Grounds of Inadmissibility</b> is an application for legal entry to the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 made by an individual who is otherwise inadmissible on one or more grounds. The application is submitted to the consular office, U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services office or immigration court considering the immigrant visa or adjustment of status application.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.
<sec>
<st>
Otherwise Inadmissible persons</st>

<p>

Persons may be inadmissible to the United States for any one of the grounds for excludability listed below. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://travel.state.gov/visa/frvi/ineligibilities/ineligibilities_1364.html">
http://travel.state.gov/visa/frvi/ineligibilities/ineligibilities_1364.html</weblink></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Health Related Grounds</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Communicable diseases of public health significance.  This currently includes Class A Tuberculosis, HIV, Chancroid, Gonorrhea, Granuloma inguinale, Lymphogranuloma venerum, Syphilis, Leprosy or any other communicable disease as determined by the U.S. Secretary of Health and Human Services<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.  Individuals diagnosed with these ilnesses may apply for a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility on Form I-601.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Physical or Mental Disorders and Associated Harmful Behaviors<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Criminal and Related Violations</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Crimes involving moral turpitude (other than a purely political offense)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A controlled substance violation according to the laws and regulations of any country as long as it relates to a single offense of simple possession of 30 grams or less of marijuana<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Two or more criminal convictions when the total sentence was five years or more<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Prostitutes and commercialized vice</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Criminals involved in serious criminal activity who have received immunity from prosecution</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Security and Related Violations</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

spies, saboteurs or terrorists</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

persons whose entry would endanger U.S. foreign policy</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

voluntary members of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/9209651.xml">
Communist</link> or other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/30439.xml">
totalitarian</link> parties</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/18404036.xml">
Nazi</link>s</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Illegal Entrants and Immigration Violators</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There are several circumstances under which illegal entrants and immigration violators may apply for a Waiver of Inadmissibility:</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Persons who enter the U.S. without being admitted or paroled at a port of entry (EWI -   Entry Without Inspection) or who overstay a valid visa begin to accrue unlawful presence after the illegal entry, or the period of authorized stay expires.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If the applicant is inadmissible because they have been unlawfully present in the United States for more than 180 days (3-year bar) or one year (10-year bar) and have voluntarily left the United States (including voluntary departure), they may apply for a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility on Form I-601.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Persons who knowingly or wilfully made misrepresentations or committed fraud in order to obtain an immigration benefit or benefit under the INA, may apply for a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility on Form I-601.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Persons previously deported or given expedited removal must also file Form I-212, Application for Permission to Reapply for Admission (if eligible).</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Persons unlawfully present in the United States for an aggregate period of one (1) year who have exited the United States and re-entered without inspection (EWI) are not eligible to file Form I-601 to waive their unlawful presence.</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Falsely Claiming U.S. Citizenship</st>

<p>

NO WAIVER is available to an alien who has falsely claimed that they are a U.S. citizen (after September 30, 1996)[4] to obtain a benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act, Federal or State law. As a result, these individuals are permanently inadmissible and cannot file for a Waiver of Inadmissibility on Form I-601.[5]</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Miscellaneous Grounds</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

practicing polygamists</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

guardians accompanying helpless aliens</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

International child abductors and relatives supporting abductors</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Requirements for Approval of a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility by Ground of Inadmissibility: </st>

<p>

<b>Unlawful Presence (3/10 Year Bar)</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If the applicant is inadmissible because they have been unlawfully present in the United States for more than 180 days (3-year bar) or one year (10-year bar), they may apply for a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility on Form I-601.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>It is important to note that an applicant MAY NOT BE ELIGIBLE to apply for this waiver of inadmissibility if they were unlawfully present in the United States for more than one year, left the United States, then returned without being admitted or paroled (EWI).</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The applicant must establish that their U.S. citizen or legal permanent resident <b>spouse, parent, or the K visa petitioner</b> would suffer <b>extreme hardship</b> if the application were denied.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There are special instructions for TPS and VAWA self-petitioners applying for a waiver of this ground of inadmissibility.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Criminal Grounds</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The applicant may apply for a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibilty on Form I-601 if they have been found to be inadmissible for: (1) a crime involving moral turpitude (other than a purely political offense); (2) a controlled substance violation according to the laws and regulations of any country as long as it relates to a single offense of simple possession of 30 grams or less of marijuana; (3) two or more convictions (other than purely political ones), for which the combined sentences of confinement were five years or more; (4) prostitution; (5) unlawful commercialized vice whether or not related to prostitution; or (6) being an alien involved in serious criminal activity, who has asserted immunity from prosecution. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The applicant must establish that they are inadmissible only because of participation in prostitution (including having procured others for prostitution or having received the proceeds of prostitution), but that they have been rehabilitated and their admission will not be contrary to the national welfare, safety or security of the United States<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink>; <b>OR</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 At least 15 years have passed since the activity or even that made the applicant inadmissible, they have been rehabilitated and that their admission to the United States (or issuance of the immigrant visa) will not be contrary to the national welfare, safety or security of the United States <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink>; <b>OR</b> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The applicant's qualifying U.S. citizen or legal permanent resident <b>spouse, son, daughter, parent or K visa petitioner</b> would experience <b>extreme hardship</b> if the appplicant were denied admission; <b>OR</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The applicant is an approved VAWA (Violence Against Women Act) self-petitioner.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Immigration Fraud or Misrepresentation</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If the applicant is inadmissible because they have sought to procure an immigration benefit by fraud or misrepresenting a material fact[INA Section 212(a)(6)(C)(i)], they may apply for a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility on Form I-601.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The applicant must demonstrate that their qualifying U.S. citizen or legal permanent resident <b>spouse, parent or the K visa petitioner would experience</b> <b>extreme hardship</b> if the applicant were denied admission <b>OR</b> the applicant is a VAWA self-petitioner and the <b>applicant, their U.S. citizen or legal permanent resident parent or child</b> would experience <b>extreme hardship</b> if the applicant were denied admission to the U.S.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Health Related Grounds of Inadmissibility</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An applicant's petition may be approved if they are the <b>spouse, parent, unmarried son or daughter, or the minor unmarried lawfully adopted child of a U.S. citizen or legal permanent resident, or of an alien who has been issued an immigrant visa, or the fiance(e) of a U.S. citizen or the finace(e)'s child</b>; OR if they are a <b>VAWA self-petitioner</b>.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Please note that there are additional application requirements for individuals who are inadmissible due to diagnosis with Class A Tuberculosis, HIV, or a "Physical or Mental Disorder and Associated Harmful Behavior"</b>.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Immigrant Membership in a Totalitarian Party</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If the applicant is inadmissible because they were a member of, or affiliated with, the Communist or any other totalitarian party, they may apply for a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility on Form I-601.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A waiver may be granted for humanitarian purposes, to assure family unity, or when it is in the public interest if the applicant is the <b>parent, spouse, son, daughter, brother or sister of a U.S. citizen, OR a spouse, son or daughter of a lawful permanent resident, OR the fiance(e) of a U.S. citizen.</b><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink>  The applicant must also not be deemed a threat to the security of the United States.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink> </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Alien Smuggling</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If the applicant is inadmissible because they have engaged in alien smuggling<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>, they may apply for a Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility on Form I-601 <b>ONLY IF</b> they have encouraged,induced, assisted, abetted or aided an individual who at the time of the action was their spouse, parent, son or daughter (and no other individual) to enter the United States in violation of the law.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink>  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Also, the applicant must be either: (1) a legal permanent resident who temporarily proceeded abroad, not under an order of removal, and who is otherwise admissible to the U.S. as a returning resident; or (2) seeking admission or adjustment of status as an immediate relative, a first, second or third preference immigrant, or as the fiance(e) (or his or her children) of a U.S. citizen.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf">
http://www.uscis.gov/files/form/I-601instr.pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A waiver under this section may be granted for humanitarian reasons, to assure family unity, or when it is otherwise in the public interest.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Procedures</st>

<p>

Applicants may download Form I-601, Application for Waiver of Ground of Inadmissibility from the USCIS website <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uscis.gov/portal/site/uscis/menuitem.eb1d4c2a3e5b9ac89243c6a7543f6d1a/?vgnextoid=db029c7755cb9010VgnVCM10000045f3d6a1RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=db029c7755cb9010VgnVCM10000045f3d6a1RCRD">
http://www.uscis.gov/portal/site/uscis/menuitem.eb1d4c2a3e5b9ac89243c6a7543f6d1a/?vgnextoid=db029c7755cb9010VgnVCM10000045f3d6a1RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=db029c7755cb9010VgnVCM10000045f3d6a1RCRD</weblink>.  Depending on whether an applicant is applying for an Immigrant Visa or Adjustment of Status, Form I-601 may be filed at the consular office, U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services office or immigration court considering the immigrant visa or adjustment of status application.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>  Issues surrounding waivers of grounds of inadmissibility may be complex (including eligibility issues) and it is generally advisable to consult an attorney.  The filing fee for Form I-601 is currently $545.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.visalaw.com/03apr1/2apr103.html">
The ABCs of Immigration</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.visa-us.com/inadmis.htm">
Visa to U.S.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://uswaiver.blogspot.com">
A Canadian's pursuit to acquire a US Waiver (I-194)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thomasimmigration.com">
Immigration Waivers</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
