<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:38:45[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<worker  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109632518">
<laborer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110241300">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<workman  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110791221">
<stevedore  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110655169">
<employee  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110053808">
<header>
<title>XOSL</title>
<id>2451142</id>
<revision>
<id>239279952</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-18T13:55:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Robertsmith6</username>
<id>6542025</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from July 2008</category>
<category>Boot loaders</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is written like .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=XOSL&amp;action=edit">
rewrite this article</weblink> from a . For <b>blatant</b> advertising that would require a fundamental rewrite to become encyclopedic, use  to mark for .&nbsp;<it>(July 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>xOSL</b>(meaning E<b>x</b>tended <b>O</b>perating <b>S</b>ystem <b>L</b>oader) is the name of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml">
bootloader</link>, which is a program product class that launches operating systems from a bootable device such as a hard disk or floppy drive. The letters are an acronym that stand for eXtended Operating System Loader. xOSL was originally developed by <link>
Geurt Vos</link>.
<sec>
<st>
Basic Appeal</st>

<p>

xOSL provides a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
graphical user interface</link> which allows the user to set up and boot a computer into any of 24 different operating systems. xOSL is nondenominational bootloader, owing allegiance to no system in particular, and booting them all equally well.</p>
<p>

The xOSL interface installs and uninstalls easily. The xOSL program poses very little risk of permanent damage to existing data. Removing the program can be accomplished with the DOS command fdisk /MBR, which returns the disk to its origianl boot configuration. Generally Xosl resides on it own fat32 patrtition requiring less thn 2mb, and it does not intermingle with other data.</p>
<p>

The xOSL solution is highly portable (less than 1mB) and incorporates asily navigable menu boxes and interfaces. The program requires very little time to configure.</p>
<p>

note-
The 24 system limititation is imposed by the physical space available on the operating system menu. Theoretically, the program could support an infinite number of operating systems. By 'chainloading' the bootloader, users have reported booting vastly more operating systems than the program is claimed to support. (http://www.tprthai.net/xosl.htm)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<p>

xOSL is free software released under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GPL</link> license. The project was actively developed by Geurt Vos between 1999 and 2001 and spanned four major revisions and two minor revisions after its initial creation. </p>
<p>

From its origin in xOSL version 1.0.0, xOSL underwent major changes in ver. 1.1.0, 1.1.1, 1.1.2 and 1.1.3. These revisions were significant departures from one another, and introduced new features to the program. These features ranged from drastic user interface improvements to improved compatibility on diverse hardware platforms.</p>
<p>

xOSL ver. 1.1.4 and 1.1.5 only introduced improvements to existing functionality and repaired features that should have been functional in their predecessors. Although their improvements were subtle, they did serve to stabilize a developing protocol, and are the most polished revisions of the original to date.</p>
<p>

The project lapsed into a dormant state and was abandoned by its original developer from 2001-2007. xOSL remained available for download and use throughout this period.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Survivability</st>

<p>

Despite the lack of active product development, an enthusiastic community of xOSL users began exchanging ideas and product results through the use of <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/330541.xml">
Yahoo! Groups</link></web_site>
 and other support sites on the internet. These groups became the foundation of the 'xOSL Culture.'  The xOSL groups assisted fellow members with advice and accomplishments through the use of xOSL. The original xOSL site was mirrored in multiple locations after its removal by <link>
Mikhail Ranish</link>.</p>
<p>

The cult-like devotion to xOSL gave credibility to the idea that the future development of xOSL was an inevetability. Other bootloaders such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/924564.xml">
Lilo</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/74194.xml">
Grub</link> performed effectively, but xOSL survived as time passed without development support or a marketing platform of any kind.</p>
<p>

Very few enhancements to the original product occurred during this time, most of them being fairly inconsequential. One such enhancement gave the user the ability to change wallpapers and the image displayed at startup, and like most other revisions, it did not add a great deal to the program in terms of core functionality.</p>
<p>

Other revisions included the translation of xOSL into several different languages, including German, Czech and French, among others.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
xOSL2</st>

<p>

Responding to the demand for an updated xOSL, <link>
John Marlowe</link> has continued the development of the product under the XOSL2 title.</p>
<p>

The product boasts that it has added CD support, when in fact the original xOSL incorporated installation from a CD device. Visually and functionally, the product is basically unchanged, except for a startup screen that bears the xOSL2 logo instead of the classic xOSL logo.  No major enhancements were introduced, except a streamlined CD install process. At this time, development of xOSL2 may be discontinued.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Compatible Formats</st>

<p>

Currently xOSL is capable of booting operating systems from a variety of format types. These include, and may not be lmited to-</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link>-</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/53045.xml">
FAT12</link>  (File Allocation Table)
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/53045.xml">
FAT16</link>
<link>
FAT32</link>
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/39184.xml">
NTFS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 (New Technology File System)</p>
<p>

<O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
-</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/202801.xml">
EXT2</link>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/39195.xml">
EXT3</link>
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/39183.xml">
ReiserFS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Conclusions</st>

<p>

Other reasons for the success of xOSL include its compact size. Its primary location is in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/55389.xml">
MBR</link> where it references items on the physical hard drive for its GUI and other features. As long a drive is formated in FAT32, xOSL does not require additional partitioning. The FAT32 drive on which xOSL resides does not need to be the first partition of the drive.</p>
<p>

Other features include-</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Graphical User Interface </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Full windowing system with mouse and keyboard support </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Resolutions up to 1600x1200 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Configurable mouse speed </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A set of color schemes </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Several color adjustment options </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Password protected boot configuration and settings </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Restart/Reboot/Shutdown</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Booting Features</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Up to 24 boot items </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Microsoft file system partition hiding support </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Storing additional keys before booting </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Activate partitions (one per system or one per HD) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Automatic booting (with timeout) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Auto boot last operating system </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Password protection per boot item </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Boot master boot record on any drive </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Boot DOS/Windows 9x on any drive </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hotkey per boot item </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Support for hard disks larger than 8Gb </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Coexists with virtually any other boot manager </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Runs Ranish Partition Manager 2.38 beta 1.91 (ver 1.1.5 and above)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Master boot record virus protection</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The continued development of xOSL is almost entirely dependent on individual user contributions and community participation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www2.arnes.si/~fkomar/xosl.org/home.html">
XOSL Hq</weblink>(Official site)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/xosl/">
XOSL Users Group at Yahoo</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www2.arnes.si/~fkomar/xosl.org/">
XOSL Historical Archive from 2000</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.multibooters.co.uk/managers.html">
xOSL and Windows Vista</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ranish.com/part/xosl.htm">
XOSL Mirror at www.ranish.com</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://slashdot.org/articles/02/09/26/1225200.shtml">
37 Operating Systems on 1 PC using XOSL</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/xosl2/">
xOSL2 Sourceforge Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jakub.horky.net/xosl/">
Czech Translation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tprthai.net/xosl.htm">
xOSL: A Test Project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.goodells.net/multiboot/">
Understanding MultiBooting by Dan Goodell</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</employee>
</stevedore>
</workman>
</causal_agent>
</laborer>
</worker>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
