<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:35:26[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Hair care</title>
<id>2494084</id>
<revision>
<id>244423407</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T18:59:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SDC</username>
<id>181435</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>hairdressing</category>
<category>Hygiene</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<p>

<b>Hair care</b> is an overall term for parts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/147020.xml">
hygiene</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/440024.xml">
cosmetology</link> involving the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/14313.xml">
hair</link> on the human head. Hair care will differ according to one's hair type and according to various processes that can be applied to hair. All hair is not the same; indeed, hair is a manifestation of human diversity.</p>
<p>

In this article, 'Hair care' is taken to mean <b>care of hair on the human head</b>, but mention should be made of process and services which impact hair on other parts of the body. This includes men‘s and women’s facial, pubic, and other body hair, which may be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/439075.xml">
dyed</link>, trimmed, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/155154.xml">
shaved</link>, plucked, or otherwise removed with treatments such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/219757.xml">
waxing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/1685248.xml">
sugaring</link>, and threading. These services are offered in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/400904.xml">
salon</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/146779.xml">
barber shop</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/4219967.xml">
day spa</link>s, and products are available commercially for home use. Laser hair removal and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/142375.xml">
electrolysis</link> are also available, though these are provided (in the US) by licensed professionals in medical offices or specialty spas. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Hair cleaning and conditioning</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Biological processes and hygiene</st>
<p>

Care of the hair and care of the scalp skin may appear separate, but are actually intertwined because hair grows from beneath the skin.  The living parts of hair (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/464073.xml">
hair follicle</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/6036367.xml">
hair root</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/14252668.xml">
root sheath</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/464075.xml">
sebaceous gland</link>) are beneath the skin, while the actual hair shaft which emerges (the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/18952748.xml">
cuticle</link> which covers the cortex and medulla) has no living processes.  <b>Damage</b> or changes made to the visible hair shaft cannot be repaired by a biological process, though much can be done to manage hair and ensure that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/18952748.xml">
cuticle</link> remains intact.  (For more information on the biological processes involved in hair production, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/14313.xml">
Hair</link>.)</p>
<p>

<b>Scalp skin</b>, just as any other skin on the body, must be kept healthy to ensure a healthy body and healthy hair production.  If the scalp is not cleaned regularly, by the removal of dead skin cells, toxins released through the skin or external hazards (such as bacteria, viruses, and chemicals) may create a breeding ground for infection.  However, not all scalp disorders are a result of bacterial infections.  Some arise inexplicably, and often only the symptoms can be treated for management of the condition (example: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/393023.xml">
dandruff</link>).  There are also bacteria that can affect the hair itself, but in MEDC's (More Economically Developed Countries), this is much rarer.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/243916.xml">
Head lice</link> is probably the most common hair and scalp ailment world-wide.  Head lice can be removed with great attention to detail, and studies show it is not necessarily associated with poor hygiene.  (Indeed, even well-to-do households can experience head lice.  More recent studies reveal that head lice actually thrive in clean hair.)  In this way, <b>hair washing</b> as a term may be a bit misleading, as what is necessary in healthy hair production and maintenance is often simply cleaning the surface of the scalp skin, the way the skin all over the body requires cleaning for good hygiene.  </p>
<p>

The <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/464075.xml">
sebaceous gland</link>s</b> in human skin produce <b>sebum</b>, which is composed primarily of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>s.  Sebum acts to protect hair and skin, and can inhibit the growth of microorganisms on the skin.  Sebum contributes to the skin’s slightly acidic natural <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/24530.xml">
pH</link></b> somewhere between 5 and 6.8 on the pH spectrum.  This oily substance gives hair moisture and shine as it travels naturally down the hair shaft, and serves as a protective substance preventing the hair from drying out or absorbing excessive amounts of external substances.  Sebum is also distributed down the hair shaft “mechanically” by brushing and combing.  When sebum is present in excess, the roots of the hair can appear oily, greasy, generally darker than normal, and the hair may stick together.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hair cleaning</st>
<p>

To combat this appearance of “dirty” hair, and to remove actual dirt and other contaminants and external substances like sweat, the hair may be <b>washed</b>.  Often hair is washed as part of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/477822.xml">
shower</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/730219.xml">
bathing</link> with a specialized soap called <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/18842002.xml">
shampoo</link></b>.  Those with damaged or curly hair, or sensitive scalps, may benefit from cleansing with a light <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/887815.xml">
Hair conditioner</link>, instead.  However, this requires that only water-soluble products are applied to the hair and scalp.</p>
<p>

Shampoo is helped by warm temperature water, which helps open the cuticle of the hair and release any oils or other substances beneath.  Pure water has a pH of 7, and when shampoo has removed the slightly acidic sebum from the hair, the pH on the surface of the scalp is raised.  Freshly shampooed hair can feel tangled or rough, and hair which is left to dry after a shampoo only can be excessively dry and coarse.  To smooth the hair, <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/887815.xml">
Conditioner</link></b> is often used.  Conditioners may employ ingredients of an acidic nature to balance the hair and scalp pH.  Many modern conditioners also contain plant oils or synthetic ingredients such as plastics to coat the hair shaft and smooth it out.  Acidic rinses or chemical conditioners can help with hair detangling and manageability, which helps prevent damage.</p>
<p>

The sebaceous glands increase or reduce their secretions in order to maintain proper skin protection and pH.  When the skin is regularly stripped of its natural sebum, the sebaceous glands respond with an overproduction.  People observe that they “must” wash their hair, for example, once every other day, otherwise their hair becomes oily; however, their sebaceous glands have simply adapted to their <b>hygienic cycle</b>. Changes to the hygienic cycle result in changes to sebum secretion.  </p>
<p>

Modern shampoos and conditioners are not necessary to maintain clean and healthy hair, and indeed, many cultures do not have these products at all.  Different methods are available for those people who wish to return to this “natural” hair state, where healthy hair can be maintained with scalp massage, water-only washes, or using cleaning agents very rarely.  Natural baseline sebum secretion varies by individual, and returning the scalp to this state takes time.  This process may often include using cleaning agents, but is generally geared towards leaving the sebum on the scalp and hair for as long as possible to reacclimatize the scalp to producing less sebum.  This process may not be for everyone, as some who try this method never reach a point where they feel their hair can be clean for any extended period of time without washing with conventional shampoo.  </p>
<p>

Using <b>cold water</b> as a final rinse can help close the scales of the cuticle, and can help constrict the openings of the sebaceous glands to help moderate sebum production.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Western cleaning products and methods</st>
<p>

A more alkaline rated (meaning a high pH) shampoo is stronger and harsher to one's hair.  This can mean that the hair will be left dry and brittle.   Shampoos containing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/54536.xml">
citric</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/172474.xml">
lactic</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/188378.xml">
phosphoric acid</link> are most likely balanced.  Oily hair might require a more acidic pH shampoo.  
Anti dandruff shampoos have been implicated in irritation of the scalp, and an increase in the production of dandruff. Anti dandruff shampoos may be available Over the counter or on prescription, based on the strength of the medicine. Dandruff, despite common belief, is more often related to too much, or an issue somehow with, sebum production and not dry scalp skin.  Not all flakes are dandruff, and only a qualified physician can determine not only that one indeed does have dandruff; but also, what type of dandruff one may have.  If one is experiencing redness of the scalp skin, bumps on the scalp skin, and any weeping from sores and/or bleeding in addition to flakes, professional medical diagnosis should be sought.</p>
<p>

Conditioner choice is greatly dependent upon hair type and hair status, such as colored, permed, dry, and the like.  Commercial conditioners contain a variety of ingredients such as plant oils, pro-vitamins, acidic compounds, plastics, stabilizers, thickeners, emulsifiers, and fragrances.</p>
<p>

Conditioners may sometimes add weight to hair, creating an adverse effect in the shampooing/conditioning process.  Some conditioners, especially those containing a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/65827.xml">
silicone</link> compound, may coat the hair and lead to build up on the hair, making it dull, and lead to harsher shampoo use; in a sense, an endless cycle of shampooing and conditioning.  When used correctly, however, conditioners are helpful in temporarily coating the hair to increase shine and ease tangles.  </p>
<p>

<b>Buildup</b> is when the hair has a sticky or gummy feel, the conditioner choice seems to work less well, or the hair may be more prone to tangling.  Buildup occurs when the minerals from water and/or products are not rinsed away during shampooing. A <b>clarifying shampoo</b> may be required to remove it.  Clarifying removes all things on the surface of the hair strands, essentially leaving the hair without moisture. Failure of conditioning as part of a clarifying hair wash process may lead to excessive drying of hair. </p>
<p>

Viable <b>natural ways to condition the hair</b> include rinses with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/38437.xml">
lemon</link> juice, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/48198.xml">
lime</link> juice, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/32762.xml">
vinegar</link>. The use of acid rinses may assist those who have itchy scalps, depending on the cause for the itchiness.  Hair which is lacking sebum may also be softened using plant oils such as olive oil and coconut oil.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Washing</st>
<p>

There are various ways to shampoo hair, and selection of a method is determined by one's hair type and available resources.</p>
<p>

The most common method of hair washing is shampooing followed by conditioning. If one is a daily hair washer, then a repeating of the hair shampoo application may not be necessary.  However, if one waits a day or more between hair washings, then the first shampoo may only break up the surface tension of sebum, and a second shampoo application to the scalp hair may be necessary to thoroughly remove the sebum.  The second application is not necessary to apply to any hair length.</p>
<p>

To help lift any scaly skin, detritis, and sebum, especially for those who suffer from scalp skin ailments, very gently scratching the surface of the skin with a small fine toothed comb may help to loosen and lift grime and dead skin cells before a hair wash, helping to have a cleaner scalp skin after a hair wash. </p>
<p>

Microfiber towels that help absorb the water from hair faster than conventional towels are available on the market.  These are particularly helpful for those with very thick hair that may otherwise take a while to dry, especially if air drying.</p>
<p>

Washing hair with shampoo and conditioner should used moderately. Washing with shampoo and conditioner more than 3 times a week may dry hair, making it "frizzy."</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Physical styling</st>
<p>

<b><link>
Hair dressing</link></b> processes (and resulting care requirements) may often be associated with the female gender, but hair care and dressing is also associated with males.  Many males benefit from improved care, especially considering that males also color (music industry, to cover gray) and enjoy alternative shapes and hair styles.</p>
<p>

For many, hair care means a visit to a professional stylist.  Hair styling is a major world industry, from the salon to products to advertising and even magazines on the subject.  Indeed, the topic is displayed and discussed in various online <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/294813.xml">
discussion forum</link>s.  Hair dressing may include cuts, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/439093.xml">
weave</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/439075.xml">
coloring</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/2460120.xml">
extensions</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/1085388.xml">
perm</link>s, permanent relaxers, curling and any other form of styling or texturing. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Length and trimming</st>
<p>

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/52401.xml">
Haircut</link>s</b> or hair <b>trimming</b> often involves creating a specific shape and form, and maintaining such sculpture.  Haircuts can also be used to define a hemline along the ends and edges of longer lengths.  Hair cutting may include shaving the head, in which case scalp skin care would be required.  In some settings, hair cutting, creating forms and shapes are an expressive art form.  Hair cutting often involves considerations of body proportions, hair density and hair type, face and head shape from all views (profile, 3/4 and 360 degree, from above and from below), overall bone structure, and pattern of how hair lies or falls.</p>
<p>

Hair shapes and various lengths are often derived from concerns regarding personal expression and aesthetics (examples: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/185438.xml">
dreadlocks</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/127168.xml">
punk hair</link>, the <link>
business haircut</link>/style, very <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/8416397.xml">
long hair</link>), religion (for example, Pentecostal faith among others), social and cultural values.  In short, hair is often a physical expression of one's sense of self, of a desire to present oneself to and amongst a community, of social status and roles, and of cultural values.  Such expression often involves adding ornaments to the hair, or partial or full hair coverings (such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/381921.xml">
Kippa</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/68301.xml">
Hijab</link>, or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/275955.xml">
Turban</link>).</p>
<p>

Although trimming may beautify hair by removing <b>damaged</b> or <b>split ends</b>, cutting does not promote faster growth. Nor does trimming remove all damage throughout the hair.  Damage can occur anywhere in any length of hair, depending on overall care it is given and any processes that are applied.  Trimming at regular intervals is only necessary for maintaining formed shapes, usually.  Hair grows at the same rate regardless, and the rate is largely a matter of heredity and hormones.  There exist ways to trim hair oneself as outlined in places on the internet and hair care reading materials. </p>
<p>

Wet hair stretches rather significantly in length.  Curly hair will unfurl a fair amount when fully wet, and different areas of the hair may have a larger degree of curl or different direction of curl than others.  Thus, cutting curly hair while wet may result in uneven lines or unexpected results with regard to actual length.  Further, curly hair, in particular, once dry, might appear visually to have an uneven line depending on how the curl coils back up. Lorraine Massey, author of <it>Curly Girl,</it> specializes in the care of curly hair types, and has designed a specific method for trimming curly hair to avoid these problems.  The reason stylists like working with wet hair may be related to weight.  Wet hair is heavier and may be easier to manage in a cut/style situation since the hair remains in place thus holding a line and making it easier for the stylist to create a form.  </p>
<p>

If a chemical process is being applied to the hair, it must be wetted.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Detangling: brushing and combing</st>
<p>

The point of <b>detangling</b> is to organize hair, usually in the same direction, and eliminate knots, snarles, tangles, and any hairs that have shed naturally.  </p>
<p>

There are all manner of <b>detangling tools</b> from very fine toothed combs to very wide toothed combs and picks, and available in a wide variety of price ranges.  <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/518238.xml">
Combs</link></b> come in all shapes and sizes and all manner of materials including plastics, wood and horn.  Mold seams, splintering wood, and peeling lacquers can all grasp hair and pull, or otherwise stress or cause harm to the outer protective layer of hair, the cuticle.  Similarly, brushes also come in all sizes and shapes. There are also a variety of brushes in various paddle shapes.  Most benefit from using some form of a wide tooth comb for detangling. Detangling with a wide tooth comb represents the gentlest way to detangle hair.  Most physicians advise against sharing hair care instruments like combs and clips, to prevent spreading hair conditions like dandruff and head lice.  </p>
<p>

The old notion that <b>100 brush strokes a day</b> produces beautiful hair is somewhat false. Too much brushing may injure the hair, especially with brushes that pull the hair or scratch the scalp. It remains a possibility that the dictum of 100 strokes a day derives from the era when Boar Bristle Brushes were more commonly used, well before the invention of plastics and a time when more organic materials were used to create hair care tools.  Usually in conjunction with the idea of 100 strokes a day was the suggestion that hair will 'shine' and be 'soft' to the touch.  That said, a person skilled at brushing without hurting the folicules can brush down the natural oils to the ends of the hair fibers, thus entending the natural protection of skin oil. Notice that if the skin has been depleted of oils by shampooing, this won't work.</p>
<p>

Stages of Hair Growth:</p>
<p>

There are three phases to the <b>cycle of hair growth</b>:  growth, loss/shed, rest, regrowth.  It is natural to observe a significant amount of hair shedding during detangling or washing, but any changes or drastic increase in the rate of shedding may signal a health or nutritional problem.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Drying</st>
<p>

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/986413.xml">
Hair dryers</link></b> speed the drying process of hair by passing air, which is usually heated, over the wet hair shaft, accelerating the rate of water evaporation.  </p>
<p>

<b>Excess heat</b> may overly dry the hair, increasing the incidence of splitting or other damage.  Sparing use of hair dryers or use at lower temperatures may reduce this risk.  Hair dryer diffusers can be used to diffuse the stream of air flow so it is weaker but covers a larger area of the hair.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Curling and straightening</st>
<p>

Styling tools may include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/908032.xml">
Hair iron</link>s (including flat and curling irons), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/986413.xml">
hair dryer</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/572393.xml">
Hairbrush</link>es (both flat and round), <link>
hair roller</link>s, diffusers and various types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/254938.xml">
scissors</link>.  </p>
<p>

Hair dressing might also include the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/52401.xml">
product</link> to add texture, shine, curl, volume or hold to a particular style.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Braiding and “up-dos”</st>
<p>

Tight or frequent <b>braiding</b> may pull at the hair roots and cause <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/1888305.xml">
traction alopecia</link>. Rubber bands with metal clasps or tight clips, which bend the hair shaft at extreme angles, can also have the same effect. </p>
<p>

<b>Headaches</b> can occur when there is stress on the hair follicle. For example, hair drawn in a direction other than its natural growth pattern (hair types come out of the hair follicle in particular patterns for curly, body, straight; and also, hair grows in a pattern about the head so that it hangs or forms the way it does for humans).  If hair, like braiding, is pinned too tightly, or the whole updo slips causing pulling on the hair in the follicle at the hair root are other scenarios that can cause aggravation to the hair follicle and result in headaches.  This is because there is a system of capillaries and even veins that feed into the hair follicle, which is what nourishes the follicle to grow hair.  If the hair follicle is aggravated, the capillaries are in turn aggravated and in this way a headache can arise. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Styling products</st>
<p>

Styling products aside from shampoo and conditioner are many and varied.  Leave-in conditioner, conditioning treatments, mousse, gels, lotions, waxes, creams, serums, oils, and sprays are used to change the texture or shape of the hair, or to hold it in place in a certain style.  Applied properly, most styling products will not damage the hair apart from drying it out; most styling products contain alcohols, which can dissolve oils.  Many hair products contain chemicals which can cause build-up, resulting in dull hair or a change in perceived texture.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Wigs</st>
<p>

Care of human or other natural hair <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/233763.xml">
wigs</link> is similar to care of a normal head of hair in that the wig can be brushed, styled, and kept clean using haircare products. Wig hair can be more delicate than normal head hair in that it does not have its own supply of moisture (sebum), and any stress or damage to the hair may not be immediately noticed since the hairs are not directly attached to nerve endings in the scalp.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Functional and decorative ornaments</st>
<p>

There are many options to adorn and arrange the hair.  Hairpins, clasps, barrettes, headbands, ribbons, rubber bands (or "pony tails"), scrunchies, and combs can be used to achieve a variety of styles.  There are also many decorative ornaments that, while they may have clasps to affix them to the hair, are used solely for appearance and do not aid in keeping the hair in place.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Chemical alteration</st>
<p>

Chemical alterations like perming, coloring can be carried out to change the perceived quality and texture of hair. Most of these are temporary alterations, however, permanent alterations are also possible.</p>
<p>

Chemical alteration of hair only affects the hair above the scalp; unless the hair roots are damaged, new hair will grow in with natural color and texture. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Hair coloring</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/439075.xml">
Hair coloring</link> is the process of adding pigment to or removing pigment from the hair shaft.  Hair coloring processes may be referred to as dyeing or bleaching, depending on whether you are adding or removing pigment.</p>
<p>

Temporary hair tints simply coat the shaft with pigments which later wash off.</p>
<p>

Most permanent color changes require that the cuticle of the hair be opened so the color change can take place within the cuticle.  This process, which uses chemicals to alter the structure of the hair, can damage the cuticle or internal structure of the hair, leaving it dry, weak, or prone to breakage.  After the hair processing, the cuticle may not fully close, which results in coarse hair or an accelerated loss of pigment.  Generally, the lighter the chosen colour from one's initial hair color, the more damaged it may be.  Other options for applying color to hair besides chemical dyes include the use of such herbs as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/18581411.xml">
henna</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/15250.xml">
indigo</link>, or choosing ammonia-free solutions.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Perms and chemical straightening</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/1085388.xml">
Perms</link> and relaxation using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/2128879.xml">
relaxer</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/2296956.xml">
thermal reconditioning</link> involve chemical alteration of the internal structure of the hair in order to affect its curliness or straightness. 
Hair that has been subjected to the use of a permanent is weaker due to the application of chemicals, and should be treated gently and with greater care than hair that isn't chemically altered.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Environmental factors</st>
<p>

Minerals in water can affect hair.</p>
<p>

<b>Calcium</b> causes hair to feel dry and lack shine and volume. It can prevent the proper processing of color, highlights, perms or relaxer/straighteners and can cause a perm to appear relaxed. Calcium builds up on the scalp causing flaking of the scalp, giving the appearance of dandruff. Calcium can choke the hair at the mouth of the follicle causing the hair to break off, then coating the scalp, blocking further new hair growth. </p>
<p>

<b>Iron</b> can cause water to have a red or rusty hue.  Iron leaves hair feeling dry, brittle and weighted down. It causes lack of shine and can cause dark hair to tint darker and blonde hair to turn orange. Iron can inhibit the proper processing of perms, color, highlights, and relaxers/straighteners </p>
<p>

<b>Copper</b> discolors hair causing blonde hair to turn green and dark hair to tint darker. Copper can weigh hair down and cause dryness, and can inhibit the proper processing of perms, color, highlights, and relaxers/straighteners. </p>
<p>

<b>Magnesium</b> causes hair to lack shine, feel dry, appear weighted down therefore lacking volume, and can inhibit the proper processing of perms, color, highlights, and relaxers/straighteners. </p>
<p>

<b>Silica</b> causes many of the same effects on the hair as calcium. It causes hair to feel dry, lack volume, and can cause dandruff-like symptoms of flaking. Build-up of silica can choke the hair follicle causing hair to fall out. </p>
<p>

<b>Lead</b> can cause the hair to feel dry. Lead can prevent the proper processing of perms, color, highlights, and relaxers/straighteners. </p>
<p>

These minerals can be found in <b>well water</b>. Domestic well water is ground water. The source of ground water is rain passing through aquifers, which are layers of minerals. The acidity (pH below 7) of the rain increases the volume of minerals dissolved as the water passes through.  The majority of ground (well) water is hard. The level of calcium that is found naturally from the ground determines the hardness of water. While calcium is the element that determines hardness of water, there are many other elements in well water that affect hair, scalp and skin.  
To improve the hair health and further prevent issues with dryness and buildup, people can use a <b>shower head filter</b> that will remove the minerals found in most city waters. However, hard water minerals and the sanitizing agents like Chlorine and Chloramine can also deposit in or on the hair, building up over time.  The chemical and mineral content of water varies by geography. Filtering water through very fine mesh cloth may help to remove larger deposits in the water.  Many enjoy collecting rain water, although acid rain is an increasing issue in many parts of the world.</p>
<p>

Treatment for well water and hard water conditions are available in a variety of products, such as demineralizing shampoos and conditioners.</p>
<p>

Those who swim in <b>chlorinated or salt sea water</b> may benefit from first wetting the hair entirely and then applying conditioner to completely swell the entire hair shaft. Swimmers may also benefit from products on the market that remove chlorine after swimming in pool water.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Special considerations for hair types</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Children’s or superfine hair</st>
<p>

<b>Children’s hair</b> is often a problem because it is supremely fine and may be difficult to care for because of its nearly downy softness and fluffiness.  Up until the age of 7-10, this fine hair will remain about the head.</p>
<p>

Children’s hair is different from adult hair in texture, density, and likely also color, body and so on.  Hair's traits change over time as humans physically develop, and even age.  Like the rest of the human body, (example, teeth), hair has different stages of development spanning the full lifetime from birth to death.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Very curly hair</st>
<p>

<b>Very curly hair</b> (such as <b>African hair</b>) requires unique care of its own.</p>
<p>

Hair that is very curly often does not require detangling. But sometimes curly hair does tangle and the person that has the curly hair has to get the tangles out very painfully.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Long hair</st>
<p>

Many industries have requirements for hair being contained to prevent worker injury.  This likely includes those working in food services, construction, utilities, and machine shops of various sorts. Of course, many professions do require containing the hair for reasons of public health, and a prime example is the food industry.  Many sports may require similar constraints for reasons of safety to keep hair out of eyes and blocking one's view, and to prevent being caught in sports equipment or trees and shrubs, or matted hair in severe weather conditions or water.  This would include not allowing hair to fly loose on the backs of motorcycles and open-topped sports cars for longer tresses.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Delicate skin</st>
<p>
 
Scalp skin of <b>babies</b> and <b>the elderly</b> are similar in that the sebaceous gland production is less because of less hormones in the body.  As part of most hair follicles, there is a sebaceous gland that secretes sebum, a waxy ester, which helps to maintain the acid mantle (scalp skin health/balance) and provide a coating on the skin that keeps it supple and moist. The sebum builds overly, generally somewhere between every other day to every third day for average adults.  Very elderly may be able to wait closer to depending on sebum production and volume of hair.  Teenagers, because of hormones, often require daily washing of the hair.   Sebum also imparts a protective coating to hair strands.  Daily washing will remove the sebum daily and incite, potentially, an increase in sebum production since the skin has mechanisms for discerning the scalp skin is lacking sufficient moisture.  However, in forms of scalp disorders, this may not be the case.  For babies and elderly, the sebaceous gland production is not at peak and so daily washing is not typically necessary.  If daily washing is conducted this can actually lead to dry, itchy scalp skin scenarios that are irritating. Not all itchy scalps are related to overly dry scalp skin. Hair texture changes every seven years, with the changing levels of hormones produced.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Treatment of damage</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Split ends</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/7721905.xml">
Split ends</link>, known formally as <it>trichoptilosis</it>, happen when the protective cuticle has been stripped away from the ends of hair fibers.</p>
<p>

This condition involves a longitudinal splitting of the hair fiber.  Any chemical or physical trauma, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/19593167.xml">
heat</link>, that weathers the hair may eventually lead to split ends.  Typically, the damaged hair fiber splits into two or three strands and the split may be two to three centimeters in length. Split ends are most often observed in long hair but also occur in short hair that is not in good condition.  </p>
<p>

As hair grows, the natural protective oils of the scalp can fail to reach the ends of the hair.  The ends are considered old once they reach about 10 centimeters since they have had long exposure to the sun, gone through many shampoos and may have been overheated by hair dryers and hot irons.  This all results in dry, brittle ends which are prone to splitting.  Infrequent trims and lack of hydrating treatments can intensify this condition.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Breakage and other damage</st>
<p>

Hair can be damaged by chemical exposure and at times by excessive perming and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/13859564.xml">
straightening</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Infections and skin disorders</st>
<p>

When hair behaves in an unusual way, or a scalp skin disorder arises, it is often necessary to visit not only a qualified physician, but sometimes a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/74553.xml">
dermatologist</link>, or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/2683298.xml">
trichologist</link>.  Conditions that require this type of professional help include, but are not limited to, forms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/200129.xml">
alopecia</link>, hair pulling/picking, hair that sticks straight out, black dots on the hair, and rashes or burns resulting from chemical processes.</p>
<p>

There are a number of disorders that are particular to the scalp.  Symptoms may include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 bumps, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 lumps, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 chafes, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 weeping or bleeding,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 clumpy flakes that do not easily slough off the scalp skin, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 caking skin buildup that appears white or another color than one's natural skin tone, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 excessive itchiness that doesn't go away with a few hair wash, redness of scalp skin, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 patches of thinning, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 clumps of hair falling out, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 shedding,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 pus-like drainage,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 abnormal odor,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/393023.xml">
dandruff</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Any of these symptoms may indicate a need for professional assistance from a dermatologist or trichologist for diagnosis.  </p>
<p>

Scalp skin can suffer from infestations of mites, lice, infections of the follicles or fungus.  There could be allergic reactions to ingredients in chemical preparations applied to the hair, even ingredients from shampoo or conditioners.  Common concerns surrounding dandruff (often associated with excessive sebum); psoriasis, eczema, or seborrheic dermatitus.  </p>
<p>

An odor that persists for a few weeks despite regular hair washing may be an indication of a health problem on the scalp skin. </p>
<p>

Not all flakes are dandruff.  For example, some can merely be product buildup on the scalp skin.   This could result from the common practice of applying conditioner to scalp skin without washing.  This would dry upon the scalp skin and flake off, appearing like dandruff and even causing itchiness, but have no health effects whatsoever.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hormone changes and imbalances</st>
<p>

There are <b>various reasons for hair loss,</b> most commonly hormonal issues.  Fluctuations in hormones will often show in the hair.  Not all hair loss is related to what is known as male pattern baldness, and indeed, women can suffer from baldness just as men do.  This includes women experiencing what's referred to as male pattern baldness. There exist on the markets formulas for addressing this specific cause of lack of hair growth yet typically they require around three months of consistence use for results to begin to appear.  Cessation may also mean that gained growth may dissipate.</p>
<p>

Particularly among women, thyroid disease is one of the more under-diagnosed health concerns.  Hair falling out in clumps is one symptom of a set of symptoms that may indicate a thyroid concern. In many gynecological exams a blood screen for thyroid is now a common protocol. Thyroid often shows up first in the behavior of the hair.</p>
<p>

During pregnancy and breast feeding, the normal and natural shedding process is typically suspended (starting around month three because it takes a while for the body to recognize and reset for the hormonal shifts the body goes through) for the period of gestation and extended longer if one breast feeds (this includes pumping for breast milk).  Upon cessation of either of these, it typically takes around two months for the hormones to shift again to the normal hormonal settings, and hair shedding can increase exponentially, for approximately 3-6 months until hair returns to its normal volume.  It is commonly noticed that hair seems thicker and shinier, even, during pregnancy and breast feeding in response to the influx of shifting hormones. It is not unusual also for hair color to change, or hair structure to change (e.g., straighter hair, curlier hair).  These changes can occur more often than people may realize yet isn't often reported.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
General hair loss</st>
<p>

Some choose to <b>shave their hair</b> off entirely, while still others may have an illness (such as a form of cancer--note that not every form of cancer or cancer treatment necessarily means one will lose their hair) that caused hair loss or lead to a decision to shave the head.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Preventative action – nutrition</st>
<p>

As stated earlier, major factors for healthy hair of any type remains both genetics and health.  A well understood factor to optimum health is <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
nutrition</link></b>, and this element remains true for hair health.  The living part of hair is under the scalp skin where the hair root is housed in the hair follicle.  The entire follicle and root are fed by a vein, and blood carries nutrients to the follicle/root.  Any time an individual has any kind of health concern from stress, trauma, medications of various sorts, chronic medical conditions or medical conditions that come and then wane, heavy metals in waters and food, smoking etc. these and more can affect the hair, its growth, and its appearance.</p>
<p>

Generally, eating a full diet that contains protein, fruits, vegetables, grains, and even an appropriate amount of fat is important (several vitamins and minerals require fat in order to be delivered or absorbed by the body).  Any deficiency will typically show first in the hair, perhaps even before it is diagnosed.  For example, even a mild case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/83537.xml">
anemia</link> can cause shedding and hair loss. Vitamins that are good for hair include the B complex, especially biotin.</p>
<p>

When the body is under strain, it reprioritizes its processes.  For example, the vital organs will be attended to first, meaning that healthy, oxygenated blood may not feed into the hair follicle, resulting in less healthy hair or a decline in growth rate.  While not all hair growth issues stem from malnutrition, it is a valuable symptom in diagnosis.</p>
<p>

Scalp hair grows, on average, at a rate of about half an inch per month, and shampoos or vitamins have not been shown to noticeably change this rate. Hair growth rate also depends upon what phase in the cycle of hair growth one is actually in; there are three phases.  The speed of hair growth varies based upon <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/12266.xml">
genetics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../076/38076.xml">
gender</link>, age, hormones, and may be reduced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/66575.xml">
nutrient</link> deficiency (i.e.,  anorexia, anemia, zinc deficiency) and hormonal fluctuations (i.e., menopause, polycystic ovaries, thyroid disease). </p>
<p>

<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
The World of Hair, A Scientific Companion by Dr. John Gray, Macmillan Press Limited, 1977, pp. 23-24.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/2831247.xml">
Hair washing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/18842002.xml">
Shampoo</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/887815.xml">
Hair conditioner</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/439075.xml">
Hair coloring</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/908000.xml">
Hair gel</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/908017.xml">
Hair mousse</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
