<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:37:55[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Surplus note</title>
<id>2545982</id>
<revision>
<id>206064964</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-16T17:55:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jspellos</username>
<id>4646078</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from November 2006</category>
<category>Corporate finance</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Surplus_note&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Surplus+note%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(November 2006)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

 
A <b>Surplus note</b> is a bond-like instrument issued by an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
insurance company</link>. These <link>
securities</link> are subordinated obligations, and fall at the very bottom of the operating insurance company's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/5187.xml">
capital</link> structure. They are issued primarily by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/2619109.xml">
mutual insurance</link> companies, which are not public and owned instead by their policy holders. Surplus notes are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../835/152835.xml">
debt</link>-like in that they pay a coupon and have a finite maturity. However, in many cases, state insurance regulators have allowed insurance companies to classify the capital raised via surplus notes as “surplus” (which is the statutory equivalent of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/68804.xml">
equity</link>), because surplus note holders are last in line to make a claim on the company's assets in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/58838.xml">
default</link> scenario, much like where equity holders reside in a public company. The motivation for mutual companies to issue these instruments was to raise surplus (or equity) in response to new risk-based capital guidelines developed in the early 1990s. Because mutual companies are owned by policyholders, not shareholders, there was no alternative method to raise surplus or equity. While surplus note holders have last claim on the assets of the operating insurance company, it is important to realize that this claim is at the operating company level, which is still ahead of holding company obligations.
</p>
</bdy>
</article>
