<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:48:01[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Computational overhead</title>
<id>2554671</id>
<revision>
<id>244503160</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T03:18:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Kdakin</username>
<id>1684452</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Theoretical computer science</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link>, <b>overhead</b> is generally considered any combination of excess or indirect computation time, memory, bandwidth, or other resources that are required to be utilized or expended to enable a particular goal.  It is a special case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/2554772.xml">
engineering overhead</link>.For example, an algorithm which caches frequent results for quick retrieval has the overhead of maintaining the memory to store the cached results. In terms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/145128.xml">
Algorithmic efficiency</link>, overhead is often the terms which are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/3469503.xml">
asymptotically</link> irrelevant. 
<sec>
<st>
Example</st>
<p>

Consider two algorithms based on input length <it>n</it>: algorithm <it>A</it>, which takes <math>n^2</math> operations, and algorithm <it>B</it>, which takes <math>4n+7</math> operations.  On short inputs such as <math>n=5</math> or less, algorithm <it>A</it> is more efficient. Algorithm <it>B</it> is said to have overhead which constitutes the 4 extra operations for each input length and 7 additional operations (overhead may be used to describe all or any part of the additional operations). However, when the input is large, say <math>n=6</math> or more, algorithm <it>B</it> is much more efficient. Overhead may also be used to decide whether or not to include features in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/27010.xml">
software engineering</link>. If developing for an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/46630.xml">
embedded system</link>, a feature that has a high memory overhead may not be included.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/145128.xml">
Algorithmic efficiency</link></p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
