<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:49:24[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Los Angeles County Department of Public Works</title>
<id>2582492</id>
<revision>
<id>234970768</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-29T11:50:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>JHunterJ</username>
<id>842922</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Los Angeles County, California</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="clear: right; margin-bottom: .5em; float: right; padding: .5em 0 .8em 1.4em; background: none; width: auto;" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>
__TOC__</col>
</row>
</table>
<p>

The <b>Los Angeles County Department of Public Works</b> (LACDPW) is responsible for the construction and operation of <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/79734.xml">
Los Angeles County's</link></county>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/25897.xml">
road</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/537481.xml">
building safety</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/1365111.xml">
sewerage</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/50482.xml">
flood</link> control. DPW also operates <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/163395.xml">
traffic signals</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/92529.xml">
intelligent transportation systems</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/198725.xml">
drinking water</link> systems in certain communities, operates five <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/37575.xml">
airports</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/1218564.xml">
paratransit</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/4146.xml">
fixed route</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/23894.xml">
public transport</link>, administers various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/3407706.xml">
environment</link> programs, issues various permits for activities in the public roadway, and has a Department Emergency Operations Center that works in conjunction with the County Emergency Operations Center operated by the Sheriff's Department.</p>
<p>

Services are provided primarily to the unincorporated county with some services provided to contract cities. Flood control and watershed management services are provided to all of the county except the <geological_formation wordnetid="109287968" confidence="0.8">
<valley wordnetid="109468604" confidence="0.8">
<natural_depression wordnetid="109366017" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/501515.xml">
Antelope Valley</link></natural_depression>
</valley>
</geological_formation>
. The Department of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/323158.xml">
Public Works</link> is the largest municipal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/323158.xml">
public works</link> agency in the country, employs over 3,500 people, and has a budget in excess of one billion dollars.</p>
<p>

As part of its flood control and water supply responsibilities, the Department of Public Works has 15 major <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/51518.xml">
dam</link>s and 27 spreading grounds in the county. <obstruction wordnetid="103839993" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<barrier wordnetid="102796623" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<dam wordnetid="103160309" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/1828111.xml">
Pacoima Dam</link></dam>
</artifact>
</barrier>
</structure>
</obstruction>
 is one of the largest and survived the Northridge earthquake in 1994 when it was momentarily weightless.</p>
<p>

Water from the dams is released into channels and some is diverted into spreading basins where it percolates into the ground and recharges the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/262927.xml">
groundwater</link>. The surface water is not used directly as it requires more cleaning than groundwater. Near the coast, the department has constructed sea water barriers that use injection wells to create a fresh water barrier to prevent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/255244.xml">
salt water</link> intrusion from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/18842359.xml">
ocean</link> into the groundwater.</p>
<p>

The DPW is a leader in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/191162.xml">
watershed</link> management. It provides storm drain education programs, publishes and enforces best management practices for activities that may affect the watershed, and manages watersheds to provide a balance between flood control, recreation, and protecting the natural environment.</p>
<p>

The first director was Thomas A. Tidemanson, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/291251.xml">
P.E.</link>  After his retirement, the Alhambra, California headquarters building was named for him.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Vision: The national leader in customer satisfaction and employee excellence</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mission: Enhance our communities through responsive and effective public works services</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Values: Safety, Professionalism, Integrety, Respect, Innovation, The environment</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
Recent Public Works accomplishments</st>
<p>

Opening of the East Los Angeles County Hall Building - On January 31, 2007, Los Angeles County Supervisor Gloria Molina (1st District) dedicated East L.A.’s own “City Hall.”  As a thriving unincorporated community, East Los Angeles has long awaited for its own full service civic facility.  The new County Hall will serve as East L.A.’s “City Hall”— bringing County services closer to the community.  The County Hall is a significant milestone of the ELA Civic Center project, initiated in 1999, to establish a central location where the local community can easily access County services.  County Hall services include the First District Community Office, the Public Works Building and Safety Counter, the Department of Consumer Affairs, the Department of Parks and Recreation, the Department of Regional Planning, and other permitting agencies such as the Health Department and the Fire Department. </p>
<p>

Los Angeles County Flood Control District Opens Historic LA River Wetlands Project – On May 8, 2008, County of Los Angeles Supervisor Don Knabe (4th District) was joined by City of Long Beach Mayor Bob Foster to open the Dominguez Gap Wetlands in Long Beach. The $7 million treatment wetlands and spreading grounds project is the latest in a series of regional, multi-benefit projects implemented by the Los Angeles County Flood Control District, including the Sun Valley Park and Tuxford Green projects in the Sun Valley Watershed and the Tujunga Wash Greenway and River Restoration project in the San Fernando Valley’s Valley Glen community. </p>
<p>

The wetlands project is one of the top five demonstration projects of the Los Angeles River Master Plan. </p>
<p>

The wetlands project is the first of its kind in the Los Angeles County region. It maintains the integrity of flood protection along the urban lower reaches of the river, while introducing new water quality elements, groundwater recharge, restoration of native habitat, pedestrian and equestrian trails, environmental education, and river bike trail enhancements.</p>
<p>

The project encompasses extensive renovation of two preexisting Flood Control District spreading grounds, located along both sides of the Los Angeles River between Del Amo Blvd. and the 405 Freeway.</p>
<p>

State Official Award $25 Million to Southland Water Projects – On July 25, 2008, Lester Snow, director of the State Department of Water Resources, presented a $25 million mock-check to County of Los Angeles Supervisor Yvonne B. Burke and local officials from water supply and water treatment agencies, municipalities, and non-governmental organizations throughout the greater Los Angeles county region. The $25 million will help fund 14 water-related projects dispersed throughout Los Angeles County. State and local </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

The department was formed in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/34846.xml">
1985</link> in a consolidation of the county Road Department, the Flood Control District (in charge of dams, spreading grounds, and channels), and the County Engineer (in charge of building safety, land survey, waterworks).</p>
<p>

For 25 years, the County Engineer Department was housed in the historic Higgins Building, a 10-story <property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<manner wordnetid="104928903" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/440475.xml">
Beaux-Arts style</link></manner>
</property>
 commercial building that was designed and built by noted architect Arthur L. Haley and engineer Albert Carey Martin in 1910, at the corner of Second and Main Streets in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<vicinity wordnetid="108641113" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<section wordnetid="108648322" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/425280.xml">
Downtown Los Angeles</link></section>
</district>
</location>
</area>
</vicinity>
</region>
. After "overseeing construction projects large and small from one of the city's strongest buildings, the county determined that the department needed more modern quarters and pulled up stakes in 1977," according to the Los Angeles City Planning Department, which designated the building as the Historic-Cultural Monument #873.</p>
<p>

In 1977, the County Engineer Department moved to the corner of 5th Street and Vermont Ave., Los Angeles until the merge of the three departments. At that time the department was called the Department of County Engineer-Facilities.</p>
<p>

For years, the Flood Control District and the County Road Department were headquartered in buildings at Alcazar Street in East Los Angeles by the Los Angeles County General Hospital.</p>
<p>

Major divisions of the Public Works Department were located at various locations in Los Angeles city for a number of years, until the 12-story glass building in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../595/107595.xml">
Alhambra, California</link></village>
 was purchased and refurbished. This tallest structure in Alhambra was formerly the western headquarters of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/277858.xml">
Sears, Roebuck and Company</link>, where some fixture units still bear the label "Sears". The steel frames were strengthened in 2006 after it was learned from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/267024.xml">
Northridge earthquake</link> that the welded joints were not adequate to withstand a major earthquake.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Major Divisions</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Architectural and Engineering Division – designs various buildings and facilities for other county departments</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Aviation Division – operates the five general aviation airports: <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/2057856.xml">
Fox Field</link></airport>
 (<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/107649.xml">
Lancaster</link></village>
), <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/5460673.xml">
Brackett Field</link></airport>
 (<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/107646.xml">
La Verne</link></village>
), <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/2189873.xml">
Whiteman Airport</link></airport>
 (<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<vicinity wordnetid="108641113" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<section wordnetid="108648322" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/435298.xml">
Pacoima</link></section>
</group>
</community>
</gathering>
</location>
</area>
</social_group>
</vicinity>
</region>
), <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/2055901.xml">
Compton/Woodley Airport</link></airport>
 (<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/107615.xml">
Compton</link></village>
), and <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/5460336.xml">
El Monte Airport</link></airport>
 (<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/107629.xml">
El Monte</link></village>
)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Building and Safety Division – regulates constructions on private properties</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Construction Division – issues permits for constructions on public right-of-ways</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Design Division - designs departmental facilities </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Flood Control Maintenance Division – operates and maintains dams, open channels, storm drains, debris basins, check dams and pumping plants </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Geotechnical and Materials Engineering Division - Ensures proper land development from geology and soils engineering to subdivision mapping standards. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Land Development Division - regulates the developments in private lands</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Project Management Division – manages capital project constructions for the County</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Road Maintenance Division – maintains the various streets and roads in the unincorporated portions of the County</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sewer Maintenance Division – operates and maintains sewers, pumping stations and sewage treatment plants</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Survey Division – provides survey services, maintains public land/survey records</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Traffic and Lighting Division – handles the traffic controls and lights on the streets of the unincorporated portions of the County</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Waste Management Division - regulates the waste management programs</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Water Resources Division - handles water conservation, and operates and maintains three seawater barriers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Watershed Management Division - handles multipurpose watershed projects and the National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System Permit Program</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Waterworks Division – provides water services</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controversies</st>

<p>

In 1988, the Department issued a demolition permit for tear down the historic <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<theater wordnetid="104417809" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/17334609.xml">
Golden Gate Theater</link></theater>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/357982.xml">
East Los Angeles</link>. Demolition commenced before officials led by then County Supervisor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<member wordnetid="110307234" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<council_member wordnetid="109944763" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/3047130.xml">
Ed Edelman</link></associate>
</council_member>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</member>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 halted the work with a stop-work order.  Demolition crews had already begun to dismantle the walls when Edelman, then Los Angeles City Councilwoman <politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/1007884.xml">
Gloria Molina</link></politician>
, sheriff's deputies and more than 50 concerned community members showed up at the site to ensure the demolition work was halted.  Edelman blamed a "foul-up" in the Public Works Department for issuing the demolition permit and assured the gathered crowd that heads were going to roll and that he would "try and stop this damn demolition before it happens."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Eaton Wash Reservoir</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Penelope McMillan&#32;(1988-03-17).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/58856326.html?dids=58856326:58856326&amp;FMT=FT&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Mar+17%2C+1988&amp;author=PENELOPE+McMILLAN&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;desc=Curtain+Call+for+a+Landmark+Theater">
Curtain Call for a Landmark Theater</weblink>", Los Angeles Times.&nbsp; "Demolition crews had swept onto the site at the corner of Whittier and Atlantic boulevards Tuesday and Wednesday, and began to dismantle some walls. But they were halted by a stop-work order obtained from the county Public Works Department through the efforts of Supervisor Ed Edelman."
</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dpw.lacounty.gov">
Los Angeles County Department of Public Works web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.LAAG.us">
Lakewood Accountability Action Group</weblink> A group of County Residents that lives in Lakewood California (within Supervisor Knabe's district) and often assists cyclists and others with getting the LA County Dept. of Public Works to repair and or fix issues with the San Gabriel River Bike Path.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";background:Green;color:#F2d1d3;" class="navbox-title">
<county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/79734.xml">
 County of Los Angeles</link></county>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:#AAAAAA;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/1007427.xml">
Board of Supervisors</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/1007884.xml">
Gloria Molina, 1st Dist.</link></politician>
&nbsp;· <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/1259804.xml">
Yvonne Brathwaite Burke, 2nd Dist.</link></person>
&nbsp;· <politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/3047173.xml">
Zev Yaroslavsky, 3rd Dist.</link></politician>
&nbsp;· <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../087/5610087.xml">
Don Knabe, 4th Dist.</link></causal_agent>
</leader>
</person>
</politician>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;· <politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/5609708.xml">
Michael D. Antonovich, 5th Dist.</link></politician>
</col>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 0px 0px 2px;" rowspan="5">
<image width="100px" src="California_County_of_Los_Angeles.png">
<caption>

A very basic map of Los Angeles County
</caption>
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:#AAAAAA;;" class="navbox-group">
Departments</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/14458757.xml">
CEO</link></head>
</causal_agent>
</administrator>
</leader>
</person>
</executive>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/3999091.xml">
Coroner</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/2209685.xml">
District Attorney</link>&nbsp;· <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<government_department wordnetid="108119821" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<fire_department wordnetid="108121117" confidence="0.8">
<local_department wordnetid="108120384" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/2202063.xml">
Fire</link></local_department>
</fire_department>
</department>
</government_department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
&nbsp;· <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/4339495.xml">
Health Services</link></network>
</group>
</system>
&nbsp;· <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/10576290.xml">
Probation</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
&nbsp;· <library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/2101557.xml">
Public Library</link></library>
&nbsp;· <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/5105592.xml">
Public Safety</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/2582492.xml">
Public Works</link>&nbsp;· <law_enforcement_agency wordnetid="108348815" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/359083.xml">
Sheriff's</link></law_enforcement_agency>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";text-align:center;background:#AAAAAA;;" class="navbox-group">
Others</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;text-align:center;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link>
Arboretum and Botanic Garden</link>&nbsp;· <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<arboretum wordnetid="102733075" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/747014.xml">
Descanso Gardens</link></arboretum>
</facility>
</artifact>
&nbsp;· <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/10588771.xml">
Harbor-UCLA Medical Center</link></hospital>
&nbsp;· <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/298509.xml">
La Brea Tar Pits</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</landmark>
</point>
</position>
</region>
</site>
 &nbsp;· <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/1338390.xml">
LAC-USC General Hospital</link></hospital>
&nbsp;· <link>
LAC Sheriff's Air Rescue 5</link>&nbsp;· <public_transit wordnetid="104018951" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/359028.xml">
LACMTA</link></public_transit>
&nbsp;· <link>
Martin L. King Jr.-Harbor Hospital</link>&nbsp;· <link>
Museum of Art</link>&nbsp;· <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/481584.xml">
Music Center</link></location>
</area>
</landmark>
</point>
</center>
</position>
</region>
&nbsp;· <museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/2171864.xml">
Natural History Museum</link></museum>
&nbsp;· <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/10588986.xml">
Olive View-UCLA Medical Center</link></hospital>
&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/3556206.xml">
Seal</link>&nbsp;· <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<arboretum wordnetid="102733075" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/1672727.xml">
South Coast Botanic Garden</link></arboretum>
</facility>
</artifact>
&nbsp;· <link>
Sheriff's Dept. Officers Killed in Line of Duty</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../729/2909729.xml">
Whittier Narrows</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
