<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:49:48[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<word  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106286395">
<part  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113809207">
<neologism  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106294441">
<language_unit  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106284225">
<header>
<title>Statistical murder</title>
<id>2591118</id>
<revision>
<id>207523315</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-23T03:30:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Chris the speller</username>
<id>525927</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Decision theory</category>
<category>Political neologisms</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

When a business or regulator uses limited funds to take an action that saves a limited number of lives, instead of an alternative action that would save more lives, this decision is sometimes called <b>statistical murder</b>.  This phrase is currently primarily a term of political advocacy, used to draw attention to unwise decision making that either is not the most effective available or is potentially even harmful.<p>

This phrase is a diffuse <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/153907.xml">
neologism</link>.  The phrase originated in the early 1990s with Professor John D. Gresham, a tenured professor of policy and decision sciences  at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18426501.xml">
Harvard University</link></university>
's school of Public Health and director of the Harvard Center for Risk Analysis.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hcra.harvard.edu/">
http://www.hcra.harvard.edu/</weblink>  This phrase appears in the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/851295.xml">
Congressional Record</link></publication>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
 in February, 1995 where he is quoted thus "John Graham, a Harvard professor, who said, 'Sound science means saving the most lives and achieving the most ecological protection with our scarce budgets. Without sound science, we are engaging in a form of "statistical murder," where we squander our resources on phantom risks when our families continue to be endangered by real risks."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  In 2001 he was appointed the head of the U.S. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/1461279.xml">
Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/44030.xml">
Office of Management and Budget</link> by <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/3414021.xml">
George W. Bush</link></businessperson>
</person>
</president>
, making him the top regulator for the United States.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  Because the analysis underlying the term was controversial among those interested in U.S. government policy, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/2610287.xml">
senate confirmation</link> process for nomination made the term more widely known.</p>
<p>

To show that something is statistical murder requires that a <link>
comparative risk analysis</link> be done on the available alternatives.  This is akin to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/374583.xml">
cost-benefit analysis</link> but does not entail the translation of lives and health into dollars.  However, if other types of benefits are to also be evaluated, the comparative risk analysis approach is not viable, so a cost-benefit analysis must be done.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Additionally, the concept implies that the inefficiently spent resources could in fact be transferred to a more effective alternative.  This requires that regulators and policy makers with budgetary authority at least allow such transfers and preferably use cost-benefit analysis to plan the budgeting.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  This was not the practice at the time the phrase was coined, and has not yet become standard practice in the U.S.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Criticism of concept</st>
<p>

Some people object to the required analysis because they believe it is always wrong to put a financial value on human life.  They would have no objection to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/219072.xml">
risk assessment</link> because it only measures lives lost.  However, with this limitation it also cannot value any effects other than the number of human lives lost - including non-fatal human diseases, effects on non-human species, and effects on human activities and enjoyment.</p>
<p>

It is quite possible to make errors in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistics</link> used to do the analysis, and in 2002 Richard Parker, a law professor at the University of Connecticut, argued that all the widely published studies suffered from unacceptable flaws.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

An alternative view, taken by some policy analysts, is that it is not sufficient to look solely at outcomes, but also at feelings.  If a risk is perceived to be significant, but is in fact insignificant, it may nonetheless be appropriate to respond in some way to that risk.  Proponents of this view suggest using an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/736803.xml">
expected utility</link> calculation instead.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.house.gov/mica/fs022795.htm">
Support Moratorium on Regulatory Rule Making Decisions</weblink>".&#32;<it>Congressional Record, February 27, 1995</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-05-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.economist.com/surveys/displaystory.cfm?story_id=2347855">
The price of prudence</weblink>".&#32;<it>The Economist</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-05-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Heinzerling, Lisa and Ackerman, Fred&#32;(2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ase.tufts.edu/gdae/publications/C-B%20pamphlet%20final.pdf">
Pricing the Priceless: Cost-Benefit Analysis of Environmental Protection</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;<it>Title of Complete Work</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-05-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Graham, John D.&#32;(1995).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncpa.org/congress/pdf/s_192.pdf">
Comparing Opportunities to Reduce Health Risks: Toxin Control, Medicine and Injury Prevention</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;<it>Comparing Opportunities to Reduce Health Risks: Toxin Control, Medicine and Injury Prevention</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-05-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Parker, Richard W.&#32;(2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ombwatch.org/regs/2002/parker.aba.pdf">
Grading the Government: How Reliable are the Tests?</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;<it>Grading the Government: How Reliable are the Tests?</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-05-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Salonie, Francois and Treach, Nicolas&#32;(2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://repositories.cdlib.org/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1024&amp;context=ucsbecon">
Regulating an Agent with Different Beliefs</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;<it>Regulating an Agent with Different Beliefs</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-05-13</link>. (Link is a draft.  Final form published in 2003.)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</language_unit>
</neologism>
</part>
</word>
</article>
