<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:44:47[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Macromolecular docking</title>
<id>2606518</id>
<revision>
<id>239229012</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-18T09:08:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Zargulon</username>
<id>359432</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Protein structure</category>
<category>Molecular modelling</category>
<category>Molecular physics</category>
<category>Bioinformatics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

Macromolecular docking is the computational modelling of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/996278.xml">
molecular structure</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/7304.xml">
complexes</link> formed by two or more interacting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/106231.xml">
biological macromolecule</link>s. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
Protein</link>-protein complexes are the most commonly attempted targets, followed increasingly by protein-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/21496.xml">
nucleic acid</link> complexes.<p>

The term "docking" originated in the late 1970s, with a more restricted meaning; then, "docking" meant refining a model of a complex structure by optimizing the separation between the interactors but keeping their relative orientations fixed. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Introduction</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biological</link> roles of most proteins, as characterized by which other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/2161878.xml">
macromolecules they interact with</link>, are known at best incompletely. Even those proteins which participate in a well-studied <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/5652450.xml">
biological process</link> (<it>e.g.</it>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/6818.xml">
Krebs cycle</link>) may have unexpected interaction partners or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/10013669.xml">
function</link>s which are unrelated to that process. Moreover, vast numbers of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/4635854.xml">
"hypothetical" proteins</link> have been emerging as part of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/12388.xml">
genomic</link> revolution of the late 1990s, proteins which, apart from their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/1107659.xml">
amino acid sequence</link>, are a complete mystery. </p>
<p>

In cases of known protein-protein interactions, other questions arise. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/12437.xml">
Genetic disease</link>s are known to be caused by misfolded or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/19702.xml">
mutated</link> proteins (<it>e.g.</it>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/50601.xml">
cystic fibrosis</link>), and there is a desire to understand what, if any, anomalous protein-protein interactions a given mutation can cause. In the distant future, proteins may be designed to perform biological functions, and a determination of the potential interactions of such proteins will be essential.</p>
<p>

For any given set of proteins, the following questions may be of interest, from the point of view of technology or natural history:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Do these proteins bind <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/15187.xml">
in vivo</link></it>?</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

If they do bind:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 What is the spatial configuration which they adopt in their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/696912.xml">
bound state</link>?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 How strong or weak is their interaction?</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

If they do not bind, can they be made to bind by inducing a mutation?</p>
<p>

Protein-protein docking is ultimately envisaged to address all these issues. Furthermore, since docking methods can be based on purely <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/22939.xml">
physical</link> principles, even proteins of unknown function (or which have been studied relatively little) may be docked. The only prerequisite is that their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/996278.xml">
molecular structure</link> has been either determined experimentally, or can be estimated by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/306769.xml">
protein structure prediction</link> technique.  </p>
<p>

Protein-nucleic acid interactions feature prominently in the living cell. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/31474.xml">
Transcription factors</link>, which regulate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/159266.xml">
gene expression</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/23648.xml">
polymerase</link>s, which <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/5914.xml">
catalyse</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/214469.xml">
replication</link>, are composed of proteins, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/12438.xml">
genetic material</link> they interact with is composed of nucleic acids. Modeling protein-nucleic acid complexes presents some unique challenges, as described below.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

In the 1970's, complex modelling revolved around manually identifying features on the surfaces of of the interactors, and interpreting the consequences for binding, function and activity; any computer programmes were typically used at the end of the modelling process, to discriminate between the relatively few configurations which remained after all the heuristic constraints had been imposed. The first use of computers was in a study on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/13483.xml">
hemoglobin</link> interaction in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/28657.xml">
sickle-cell</link> fibres<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. This was followed in 1978 by work on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/30652.xml">
trypsin</link>-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/4628609.xml">
BPTI</link> complex<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. Computers discriminated between good and bad models using a scoring function which rewarded large interface area, and pairs of molecules in contact but not occupying the same space. The computer used a simplified representation of the interacting proteins, with one interaction centre for each residue. Favorable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/368328.xml">
electrostatic</link> interactions, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/13609.xml">
hydrogen bonds</link>, were identified by hand.</p>

<p>

Towards the beginning of the 1990's, more structures of complexes were determined, and available computational power had increased substantially. With the emergence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link>, the focus moved towards developing generalized techniques which could be applied to an arbitrary set of complexes at acceptable computational cost. The new methods were envisaged to apply even in the absence of phylogenetic or experimental clues; any specific prior knowledge could still be introduced at the stage of choosing between the highest ranking output models, or be framed as input if the algorithm catered for it.
1992 saw the publication of the correlation method<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>, an algorithm which used the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/11512.xml">
fast Fourier transform</link> to give a vastly improved scalability for evaluating coarse shape complementarity on rigid-body models. This was extended in 1997 to cover coarse electrostatics<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>.</p>
<p>

In 1996 the results of the first blind trial were published<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>, in which six research groups attempted to predict the complexed structure of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/4609.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22TEM+beta-lactamases+(class+A)%22])">
TEM-1 Beta-lactamase</link> with Beta-lactamase inhibitor protein (BLIP). The exercise brought into focus the necessity of accommodating conformational change and the difficulty of discriminating between conformers. It also served as the prototype for the CAPRI assessment series, which debuted in 2001.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Rigid-body docking <it>vs</it>. flexible docking</st>
<p>

If the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/996278.xml">
bond angles, bond lengths and torsion angles</link> of the components are not modified at any stage of complex generation, it is known as <it>rigid body docking</it>. A subject of speculation is whether or not rigid-body docking is sufficiently good for most docking. When substantial conformational change occurs within the components at the time of complex formation, rigid-body docking is inadequate. However, scoring all possible conformational changes is prohibitively expensive in computer time. Docking procedures which permit conformational change, or <it>flexible docking</it> procedures, must intelligently select small subset of possible conformational changes for consideration.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods</st>
<p>

Successful docking requires two criteria:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Generating a set configurations which reliably includes at least one nearly correct one.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Reliably distinguishing nearly correct configurations from the others.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

For many interactions, the binding site is known on one or more of the proteins to be docked. This is the case for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
antibodies</link> and for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/582189.xml">
competitive inhibitor</link>s. In other cases, a binding site may be strongly suggested by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/19599.xml">
mutagenic</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/23962.xml">
phylogenetic</link> evidence. Configurations where the proteins interpenetrate severely may also be ruled out <it>a priori</it>. </p>
<p>

After making exclusions based on prior knowledge or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/28756.xml">
stereochemical</link> clash, the remaining space of possible complexed structures must be sampled exhaustively, evenly and with a sufficient coverage to guarantee a near hit. Each configuration must be scored with a measure that is capable of ranking a nearly correct structure above at least 100,000 alternatives.  This is a computationally intensive task, and a variety of strategies have been developed.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Reciprocal space methods</st>
<p>

Each of the proteins may be represented as a simple cubic lattice. Then, for the class of scores which are discrete <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../519/7519.xml">
convolution</link>s, configurations related to each other by translation of one protein by an exact lattice vector can all be scored almost simultaneously by applying the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/53268.xml">
convolution theorem</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. It is possible to construct reasonable, if approximate, convolution-like scoring functions representing both stereochemical and electrostatic fitness. </p>
<p>

Reciprocal space methods have been used extensively for their ability to evaluate enormous numbers of configurations. They lose their speed advantage if torsional changes are introduced. Another drawback is that it is impossible to make efficient use of prior knowledge. The question also remains whether convolutions are too limited a class of scoring function to identify the best complex reliably.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Monte Carlo methods</st>
<p>

In <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/56098.xml">
Monte Carlo</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
, an initial configuration is refined by taking random steps which are accepted or rejected based on their induced improvement in score (see the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/56107.xml">
Metropolis criterion</link>), until a certain number of steps have been tried. The assumption is that convergence to the best structure should occur from a large class of initial configurations, only one of which needs to be considered. Initial configurations may be sampled coarsely, and much computation time can be saved. Because of the difficulty of finding a scoring function which is both highly discriminating for the correct configuration and also converges to the correct configuration from a distance, the use of two levels of refinement, with different scoring functions, has been proposed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Torsion can be introduced naturally to Monte Carlo as an additional property of each random move.</p>
<p>

Monte Carlo methods are not guaranteed to search exhaustively, so that the best configuration may be missed even using a scoring function which would in theory identify it. How severe a problem this is for docking has not been firmly established. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Selecting the docked complex structure</st>
<p>

To find a score which forms a consistent basis for selecting the best configuration, studies are carried out on a standard benchmark <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/2606518.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Benchmark%22])">
(see below)</link> of protein-protein interaction cases. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/11044649.xml">
Scoring functions</link> are assessed on the rank they assign to the best structure (ideally the best structure should be ranked 1), and on their coverage (the proportion of the benchmark cases for which they achieve an acceptable result).
Types of scores studied include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
Heuristic</link> scores based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
residue</link> contacts.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Shape complementarity of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/5799825.xml">
molecular surface</link>s ("stereochemistry").</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Free energies, estimated using parameters from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/547400.xml">
molecular mechanics</link> <power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<influence wordnetid="105194151" confidence="0.8">
<force wordnetid="105194578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/2916615.xml">
force field</link></force>
</influence>
</power>
s such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/314653.xml">
CHARMM</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/307123.xml">
AMBER</link>. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Phylogenetic desirability of the interacting regions. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Clustering coefficients.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

It is usual to create hybrid scores by combining one or more categories above in a weighted sum whose weights are optimized on cases from the benchmark. To avoid bias, the benchmark cases used to optimize the weights must not overlap with the cases used to make the final test of the score.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Benchmark</st>
<p>

A benchmark of 84 protein-protein interactions with known complexed structures has been developed for testing docking methods.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> The set is chosen to cover a wide range of interaction types, and to avoid repeated features, such as the profile of interactors' structural families according to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/746131.xml">
SCOP</link> database. Benchmark elements are classified into three levels of difficulty (the most difficult containing the largest change in backbone conformation). The protein-protein docking benchmark contains examples of enzyme-inhibitor, antigen-antibody and homomultimeric complexes.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The CAPRI assessment</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/17451531.xml">
Critical Assessment of PRediction of Interactions</link></it>
</indent>
The Critical Assessment of PRediction of Interactions<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> is an ongoing series of events in which researchers throughout the community try to dock the same proteins, as provided by the assessors. Rounds take place approximately every 6 months. Each round contains between one and six target protein-protein complexes whose structures have been recently determined experimentally. The coordinates and are held privately by the assessors, with the cooperation of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/29400.xml">
structural biologist</link>s who determined them. The assessment of submissions is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/277248.xml">
double blind</link>. </p>
<p>

CAPRI attracts a high level of participation (37 groups participated worldwide in round seven) and a high level of interest from the biological community in general. Although CAPRI results are of little statistical significance owing to the small number of targets in each round, the role of CAPRI in stimulating discourse is significant. (The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/461517.xml">
CASP</link> assessment is a similar exercise in the field of protein structure prediction).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Deciding whether a complex actually occurs in nature and measuring its affinity</st>
<p>

A reliable method for affinity prediction has the potential to transform biochemistry and cell biology. Though a distant prospect, affinity prediction may be considered as the ultimate achievement in protein-protein docking.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Protein-protein docking and molecular docking</st>
<p>

The field of protein-protein docking is highly computationally oriented, and it shares approaches with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/2292623.xml">
small-molecule docking</link>. Proteins complexed with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/21505.xml">
polynucleotide</link> molecules are widely studied using similar or identical approaches to protein-protein docking, although if the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/21505.xml">
nucleotide</link> molecule is small enough, the case may be framed as a small-molecule docking problem. See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/11044649.xml">
Scoring functions for docking</link> and <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/11044599.xml">
Searching the conformational space for docking</link></method>
</know-how>
 for more information.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Levinthal C, Wodak SJ, Kahn P, Dadivanian AK&#32;(1975).&#32;"Hemoglobin Interactions in Sickle Cell Fibers: I. Theoretical Approaches to the Molecular Contacts". <it>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</it>&#32;<b>72</b>&#32;(4): 1330. PMID 1055409.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Wodak SJ, Janin J&#32;(1978).&#32;"Computer Analysis of Protein-Protein Interactions". <it>Journal of Molecular Biology</it>&#32;<b>124</b>&#32;(2): 323-42. PMID 712840.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal"><president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/1006658.xml">
Katchalski-Katzir E</link></president>
, Shariv I, Eisenstein M, Friesem AA, Aflalo C, Vakser IA&#32;(1992).&#32;"Molecular surface recognition: determination of geometric fit between proteins and their ligands by correlation techniques". <it>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</it>&#32;<b>89</b>&#32;(6): 2195–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073%2Fpnas.89.6.2195">
10.1073/pnas.89.6.2195</weblink>. PMID 1549581.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
}"&amp;gt;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Macromolecular_docking#endnote_">
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Macromolecular_docking#endnote_</weblink>}" name="{}"&amp;gt;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Macromolecular_docking#endnote_">
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Macromolecular_docking#endnote_</weblink>}" class="citation"&amp;gt;Gabb HA, Jackson RM, Sternberg MJ,  <it>Modelling protein docking using shape complementarity, electrostatics and biochemical information</it>,  ,  {16 April 2009}.</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Strynadka NC, Eisenstein M, Katchalski-Katzir E, Shoichet BK, Kuntz ID, Abagyan R, Totrov M, Janin J, Cherfils J, Zimmerman F, Olson A, Duncan B, Rao M, Jackson R, Sternberg M, James MN&#32;(1996).&#32;"Molecular Docking Programs Successfully Predict the Binding of a Beta-lactamase Inhibitory Protein to TEM-1 Beta-Lactamase". <it>Nature Structural Biology</it>&#32;<b>3</b>&#32;(3): 233-9. PMID 8605624.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gray JJ, Moughon S, Wang C, Schueler-Furman O, Kuhlman B, Rohl CA, Baker D&#32;(2003).&#32;"Protein-protein docking with simultaneous optimization of rigid-body displacement and side-chain conformations". <it>J. Mol. Biol.</it>&#32;<b>331</b>&#32;(1): 281–99. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0022-2836%2803%2900670-3">
10.1016/S0022-2836(03)00670-3</weblink>. PMID 12875852.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Mintseris J, Wiehe K, Pierce B, Anderson R, Chen R, Janin J, Weng Z&#32;(2005).&#32;"Protein-Protein Docking Benchmark 2.0: an update". <it>Proteins</it>&#32;<b>60</b>&#32;(2): 214–6. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2Fprot.20560">
10.1002/prot.20560</weblink>. PMID 15981264.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Janin J, Henrick K, Moult J, Eyck LT, Sternberg MJ, Vajda S, Vakser I, Wodak SJ&#32;(2003).&#32;"CAPRI: a Critical Assessment of PRedicted Interactions". <it>Proteins</it>&#32;<b>52</b>&#32;(1): 2–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2Fprot.10381">
10.1002/prot.10381</weblink>. PMID 12784359.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#e7dcc3" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
Proteins</link>: key <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/2634439.xml">
methods</link>of study</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/59861.xml">
Experiment</link>al</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/542744.xml">
Protein purification</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/143533.xml">
Green fluorescent protein</link> - <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/174030.xml">
Western blot</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 - <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/507330.xml">
Protein immunostaining</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/1076110.xml">
Protein sequencing</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <chemical_analysis wordnetid="100646833" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/12582.xml">
Gel electrophoresis</link></chemical_analysis>
/<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/589968.xml">
Protein electrophoresis</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</method>
</experiment>
</know-how>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
</technique>
 - <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<assay wordnetid="105738625" confidence="0.8">
<classification wordnetid="105732756" confidence="0.8">
<basic_cognitive_process wordnetid="105701944" confidence="0.8">
<appraisal wordnetid="105733583" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/1799688.xml">
Protein immunoprecipitation</link></appraisal>
</basic_cognitive_process>
</classification>
</assay>
</process>
 - <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/1983032.xml">
Peptide mass fingerprinting</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/306769.xml">
Protein structure prediction</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/2606518.xml">
Protein-protein docking</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/474908.xml">
Protein structural alignment</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/7786535.xml">
Protein ontology</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/4350008.xml">
Protein-protein interaction prediction</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/496309.xml">
Assay</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/2634856.xml">
Enzyme assay</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/1098915.xml">
Protein assay</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</method>
</experiment>
</know-how>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/3599041.xml">
Secretion assay</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
