<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:47:37[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Online counseling</title>
<id>2632136</id>
<revision>
<id>241859723</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-29T21:04:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Badagnani</username>
<id>308437</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Internet culture</category>
<category>mental health</category>
<category>psychotherapy</category>
<category>Counseling</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<b>Online counseling</b> generally refers to the provision of professional mental health services concerns via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
internet</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/5177.xml">
communication</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/29816.xml">
technology</link>. Often called e-therapy, etherapy, e-counseling, online therapy, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/143215.xml">
coaching</link>, services are typically offered via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
email</link>, real-time <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/40390.xml">
chat</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/274116.xml">
video conferencing</link>.  Some clients use online counseling in conjunction with traditional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/24931.xml">
psychotherapy</link>, and others use it as an occasional check-in tool for their lives.</p>
<p>

Some argue that the heightened anonymity of online counseling promotes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/1211114.xml">
transference</link> in the client, and is therefore ideal for psychodynamic therapy approaches.  Likewise, it is ostensibly less suitable for body-based forms of therapy such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/1369306.xml">
Bioenergetics</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Benefits </st>

<p>

Clients typically seek out online counseling services for the same reasons that people seek professional help through traditional channels.  However, online counseling may be especially appealing for individuals who are unable or unwilling to see a mental health professional in person.  For example, it is potential resource for clients who are home-bound (such as the elderly or infirm) or who reside in rural areas far from a therapist's office.  Also assists those with have fear of exposing their feelings.  For example, a person with grief and loss issues, may be fearful of crying in front of another person.  Online counseling can also be an option for individuals who suffer from a particular problem and wish to work with a hard-to-find expert in that issue.  </p>
<p>

Convenience is the most-often cited reason why people use online counseling services.  It can be convenient for clients and counselors alike, and participants may engage in the counseling process from the comfort of their homes or offices, at times that are most convenient for them. Schedules are often tight.  Online therapy allows client to send an email at 3am or schedule a phone conference at 8am.  This is very helpful to many clients.</p>
<p>

Confidentiality is another oft-cited benefit.  Many people are uncomfortable talking about their personal problems while in the physical presence of another, and may be more likely to disclose when they cannot be seen.  This effect is called disinhibition.  Thus, online counseling may allow for more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/25009.xml">
privacy</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/353859.xml">
confidentiality</link> that traditional counseling (provided that participants take technical precautions like email <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link>, etc.  </p>
<p>

Online counseling is often touted as being less expensive then traditional in-person sessions, because both client and therapist can take their time with their responses instead of having to think quickly within a typical 30 to 45-minute traditional session (in "asynchronous" email work). Online chat sessions may also be priced lower than face-to-face (F2F) work because net-based counselors may not have the overhead costs needed to maintain an office. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Difficulties </st>

<p>

A major challenge for online counseling and because there are verbal cues (or verbal behavior), signs and signals given by a client to a therapist that are missed in online counseling.  Many online counselors offer the option of phone counseling or video conferencing during the chat.  This enables both parties to pick up on some of the missed cues.</p>
<p>

Some argue that online counseling may, for some individuals, feed into their tendency to avoid "in office" interactions when what would benefit them most would be to be in the actual physical presence of a healing professional. In some instances this "distanced" interaction can be coupled with the presence of a professional who wishes (for whatever reason) to maintain a distance from the intimacy of "in office" interactions. When both of the above situations exist, it is unlikely to result in an effective therapeutic outcome.</p>
<p>

Another major challenge is professionalism and security.  Many people can hang a virtual shingle and offer to do online counseling.</p>
<p>

Another disadvantage is that communication on the Internet may be more vulnerable to interception than face-to-face counseling.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Research</st>

<p>

A 2005 <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/7955325.xml">
University of Toronto</link></university>
 study showed female users of a Canadian online counseling service outnumbered males four to one.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/13139134.xml">
List of counseling topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/1158739.xml">
ISMHO</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
AAOP.com</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes </st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.news.utoronto.ca/bin6/051011-1731.asp">
University of Toronto - News@UofT - Online counselling comes of age (Oct 11/05)</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="CITEREFKrausZackStricker2004">Kraus, R.; J. Zack&#32;&amp; G. Stricker&#32;(2004), written at San Diego, California,&#32;<it>Online Counseling: A Handbook for Mental Health Professionals</it>, Elsevier Academic Press</cite></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://construct.haifa.ac.il/~azy/refthrp.htm">
list of research references related to online counseling</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://counsellingresource.com/papers/online-practice/index.html">
"9 Observations About the Practice and Process of Online Therapy"</weblink> - Draws on an evidence base of over 700,000 words of email-based counselling and therapy</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://MyLiveTherapist.com">
MyLiveTherapist.com</weblink> - Hundreds of counselors! Available 24/7 by Chat, Email, Phone.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mytherapist.com">
MyTherapist.com</weblink> - Secure online therapy and counseling services</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.onlinecounselingtherapy.com">
Online counseling and therapy service</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.onlinecounseling.co.za">
Local and International online counseling and online therapy</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
