<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:42:34[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Social welfare in Japan</title>
<id>2634705</id>
<revision>
<id>220480993</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-20T01:58:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Andycjp</username>
<id>55014</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Japanese society</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Social welfare</b>, assistance for the ill or otherwise disabled and for the old, has long been provided in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/15573.xml">
Japan</link> by both the government and private companies. Beginning in the 1920s, the government enacted a series of welfare programs, based mainly on European models, to provide medical care and financial support. Government expenditures for all forms of social welfare increased from 6% of the national income in the early 1970s, to 18% in 1989. The mixture of public and private funding have created complex pension and insurance systems. But a much older tradition calls for support within the family and the local community, and this is one of the reasons why Japanese society is the way it is.<p>

The futures of Japan's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/80381.xml">
health</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/3332250.xml">
welfare</link> systems are being shaped by the rapid aging of the population (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/2630744.xml">
Elderly people in Japan</link>). <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/490201.xml">
Medical insurance</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/261925.xml">
health care</link> for the elderly, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/463734.xml">
public health</link> expenses constituted about 60% of social welfare and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/27691.xml">
social security</link> costs in 1975, while government <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/43613.xml">
pension</link>s accounted for 20%. By the early 1980s, pensions accounted for nearly 50% of social welfare and social security expenditures because people were living longer after retirement. A fourfold increase in workers' individual contributions was projected by the twenty-first century.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Pension system</st>

<p>

In Japan, pension system is very complex. There are three types of pensions arranged by the government and corporate organizations.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

An elementary part:Providing minimal benefits. A <b><link>
basic pension</link></b>（premium is fixed amount）</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

A secondary part:Providing benefits, based on income until retirements. <b><link>
Employees Pension Insurance</link></b>、a <b><link>
Mutual Aid Pension</link></b>（A premium is a fixed percentage of monthly income）</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

A third part:Company Pensions（An Employees' Pension Fund, Tax-qualified Pension Plan. A premium depends on organizations）</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

After becoming an insured person of an employees' pension plan or a mutual-aid pension, a people are also regarded as an insured person of a basic pension automatically.</p>
<p>

<table border="1">
<caption>
<b>National pension plan</b></caption>
<row align="center">
<header>
A secondary part</header>
<col colspan="2">
&nbsp;</col>
<col>
<link>
Employees Pension Insurance</link></col>
<col>
<link>
National Public Service Mutual Aid Pension</link></col>
<col>
<link>
Local Public Service Mutual Aid Pension</link></col>
<col>
<link>
Private School Teachers and Employees Mutual Aid Pension</link></col>
</row>
<row align="center">
<header>
An elementary part</header>
<col colspan="6">
<link>
The National Pension Fund</link>（A basic pension）</col>
</row>
<row align="center">
<header>
Insured persons</header>
<col>
Employers、unemployed persons and part time &amp; casual workers or equivalents Salaried employees who do not meet necessary conditions  for members of an employees' pension plan</col>
<col>
Spouses of categoryⅡinsured persons</col>
<col>
Company employees</col>
<col colspan="3">
Public employees</col>
</row>
<row align="center">
<header>
&nbsp;</header>
<col>
CategoryⅠinsured persons</col>
<col>
Category Ⅲ insured persons</col>
<col colspan="4">
CategoryⅡinsured persons</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<table border="1">
<caption>
<b>Other pension plan</b></caption>
<row>
<header rowspan="2">
Individual type</header>
<col>
<link>
Worker's property accumulation promotion system</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Personal type <link>
defined contribution pension plan</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<header rowspan="7">
Corporate type</header>
<col>
<link>
Defined benefit pension plans</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link>
Employees' pension funds</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link>
Tax-qualified Pension Plans</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Defined contribution pension plans</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link>
Retirement mutual aid pensions for small sized businesses</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Retirement mutual aid pensions for specific small sized businesses</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

A major revision in the public pension system in 1986 unified several former plans into the single <link>
Employee Pension Insurance Plan</link>. In addition to merging the former plans, the 1986 reform attempted to reduce benefits to hold down increases in worker contribution rates. It also established the right of women who did not work outside the home to pension benefits of their own, not only as a dependent of a worker. Everyone aged between twenty and sixty was a compulsory member of this Employee Pension Insurance Plan.</p>
<p>

Despite complaints that these pensions amounted to little more than "spending money," an increasing number of people planning for their retirement counted on them as an important source of income. Benefits increased so that the basic monthly pension was about US$420 in 1987, with future payments adjusted to the consumer price index. Forty percent of elderly households in 1985 depended on various types of annuities and pensions as their only sources of income.</p>
<p>

Some people are also eligible for <link>
corporate retirement allowance</link>s. About 90% of firms with thirty or more employees gave retirement allowances in the late 1980s, frequently as lump sum payments but increasingly in the form of annuities.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Public assistance</st>
<p>

Japan also has <link>
public assistance program</link>s benefiting about 1% of the population. About 33% of recipients are elderly people, 45% were households with sick or disabled members, and 14% are fatherless families, and 8% are in other categories.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/1550826.xml">
Social Insurance</link></st>
<p>

Companies in Japan are responsible for enrolling their employees in various social insurance Social Insurance (,,  Shakai Hoken ) systems, including health insurance, employee pension insurance, employment insurance, and workers' accident compensation insurance. The employer covers all costs for workers' accident compensation insurance, but payments to the other systems are shared by both employer and employee.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/18862.xml">
Minimum wage</link></st>
<p>

The <link>
Minimum Wage Law</link>, introduced in 1947 but not enacted until 1959, was designed to protect low-income workers. Minimum wage levels have been determined, according to both region and industry, by special councils composed of government, labor, and employment representatives. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/1327943.xml">
Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare (Japan)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/2634919.xml">
Health care in Japan</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/2826173.xml">
Social education in Japan</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/2630744.xml">
Elderly people in Japan</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>This article contains material from the <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<report wordnetid="107218470" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/207691.xml">
Library of Congress Country Studies</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</report>
</document>
, which are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/195149.xml">
United States government</link> publications in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link>.</it> - <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/jptoc.html">
Japan</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sia.go.jp/e/index.html">
Social Insurance Agency</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/english/index.html">
Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
