<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:39:50[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Superuser</title>
<id>264209</id>
<revision>
<id>243725335</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T20:02:10Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cmerritt run</username>
<id>7673644</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Operating system security</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since August 2008</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>System administration</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="150px" src="Merge-arrows.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrows
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  with . ()</col>
</row>
</table>


On many computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>s, the <b>superuser</b>, or <b>root</b>, is a special <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/16301990.xml">
user account</link> used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/154985.xml">
system administration</link>. The "Super User" in enterprise programs (SAP, Oracle) often refers to an individual who is an expert in a module or process within the enterprise system.<p>

Many older operating systems on computers intended for personal and home use, including <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/20027.xml">
MS-DOS</link></O>
 and <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/454486.xml">
Windows 9x</link></O>
, do not have the concept of multiple accounts and thus have no separate administrative account; anyone using the system has full privileges. Separation of administrative privileges from normal user privileges makes an operating system more resistant to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/18994196.xml">
viruses</link> and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/20901.xml">
malware</link>, and the lack of this separation in these operating systems has been cited as one major source of their insecurity.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Unix and Unix-like</st>

<p>

In <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
-style computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating systems</link>, <b>root</b> is the conventional name of the user who has all rights or permissions in all modes (single- or multi-user). Alternative names include <b>baron</b> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/4801.xml">
BeOS</link>  and <b>avatar</b> on some Unix variants.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/1223807.xml">
BSD</link> often provides a <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/1553581.xml">
toor</link></b> ("root" backwards) account in addition to a root account for better usability while performing administrative tasks. The root user can do many things an ordinary user cannot, such as changing the ownership of files and binding to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/4971331.xml">
ports</link> numbered below 1024.</p>
<p>

It is never good practice for anyone to use root as their normal user account, since simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/1057428.xml">
typographical error</link>s in entering commands can cause major damage to the system. It is advisable to create a normal user account instead and then use the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/459280.xml">
su</link> command to switch when necessary. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/1008028.xml">
sudo</link> utility can also be used instead to allow a measure of graduated access.</p>
<p>

Many operating systems, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link> and some <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 distributions, allow administrator accounts which provide greater access while shielding the user from most of the pitfalls of full root access. In some cases, the root account is disabled by default, and must be specifically enabled. In a few systems, such as <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/24226.xml">
Plan 9</link></O>
, there is no superuser at all.</p>
<p>

Software defects which allow a user to "gain root" (to execute with superuser privileges code supplied by that user) are a major <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
computer security</link> issue, and the fixing of such software is a major part of maintaining a secure system. One common way of gaining root is to cause a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/4373.xml">
buffer overflow</link> in a program already running with superuser privileges. This is often avoided in modern operating systems by running critical services, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/170697.xml">
httpd</link>, under a unique limited account. A related term is <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/223942.xml">
rootkit</link></it>, using root privileges to conceal certain data from the system administrator.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Windows NT</st>

<p>

In <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/33438.xml">
Windows NT</link></family>
 and later systems derived from it (<version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/33941.xml">
Windows 2000</link></version>
, <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/33879.xml">
Windows XP</link></version>
, <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/208068.xml">
Windows Server 2003</link></version>
 and <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
), there may or may not be a <it>superuser</it>. By default, there is a <it>superuser</it> named <b>Administrator</b>, although it is not an exact analogue of the <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
 <b>root</b> superuser account. <b>Administrator</b> does not have all the privileges of <b>root</b> because some superuser privileges are assigned to the <b>Local System</b> account in <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/33438.xml">
Windows NT</link></family>
. The Local System account can be accessed by the user by making Task Scheduler start a command prompt, which is then launched as Local System (the account Task Scheduler runs on), allowing you to run anything as Local System.</p>


<p>

In <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
 or later, you can use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/4359671.xml">
User Account Control</link> to run a process with elevated privileges (for example, by right-clicking (Windows 2000 users must hold the SHIFT key while right-clicking) on the program and selecting <it>Run as administrator</it>). In earlier version of Windows, the command <it>runas</it> fulfils this task (see <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/resources/documentation/windows/xp/all/proddocs/en-us/runas.mspx">
Microsoft's documentation for runas</weblink> for more details).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
SAP &amp; Oracle</st>

<p>

SAP and Oracle are well known enterprise systems which often require a complex set of training in order to learn.  Because of this, and also to encourage engagement with the systems, many companies have created a "Super User Model" (also called Power User, Champion) in order to take regular users and raise them to a level of leadership within the system.  Doing this accomplishes three objectives<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>:</p>
<p>

1.	More engaged use of the system as there is a personal face assigned to champion the system and make acceptance of the technology less challenging.</p>
<p>

2.	A significant time and cost reduction as companies are not seeking or hiring new or temporary resources for the purposes of developing and/or delivering documentation, training, and support.</p>
<p>

3.	ROI or proof of concept of the SAP investment should be more easily achieved as users are directly involved, thereby using the system invested in, which benefits the company overall.</p>
<p>

Extensive research has been done specifically with the Super User Model in SAP, specifically in regards to the role they take in training and supporting end users.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../124/6541124.xml">
nobody (username)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/3468701.xml">
Power user</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Sap super user</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.insiteobjects.com/papers/Super">
User.pdf Super User Whitepaper</weblink>, The Super User Model in SAP</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.insiteobjects.com/webisodes/episode2.html">
The SAP Super User - Video Summary</weblink>, The Super User Model in SAP - Video by Insite Objects</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.linfo.org/root.html">
root Definition</weblink> - by The Linux Information Project (LINFO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ubit.buffalo.edu/linux/ublinux4/superuser.php">
Superuser Privileges</weblink> - Linux: UBLinux 4 (GNU)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://developer.apple.com/internet/security/securityintro.html">
An Introduction to Mac OS X Security</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-questions/2005-September/098410.html">
Discussion on origin of Charlie Root at pipermail</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
