<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:40:57[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Cost-effectiveness analysis</title>
<id>265128</id>
<revision>
<id>235296055</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-31T01:41:56Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Fizzy</username>
<id>552650</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Costs</category>
<category>Health economics</category>
<category>Public health</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Cost-effectiveness analysis</b> (CEA) is a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/6639133.xml">
economic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/651604.xml">
analysis</link> that compares the relative expenditure (costs) and outcomes (effects) of two or more courses of action. Cost-effectiveness analysis is often used where a full cost-benefit analysis is inappropriate e.g. the problem is to determine how best to comply with a legal requirement. 
<sec>
<st>
CEA in Infrastructure Asset Management</st>

<p>

Cost-effectiveness analysis is commonly used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/17039178.xml">
Infrastructure Asset Management</link> instead of a full <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/374583.xml">
cost-benefit analysis</link> where the objective is to sustain the existing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/17054388.xml">
standard of service</link>. The replacement or refurbishment of an existing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/17039178.xml">
Infrastructure Asset</link> is a good example of this. 
In effect, the benefits side of the equation is held constant at some pre-determined standard of service, and various options for providing that standard of service are then compared, with the least-cost method identified as the preferred option.</p>
<p>

The use of CEA is supported by the benefits identified in the Asset Management Plan where the whole-life cost is also detailed. As such, an indicative benefit-cost ratio is contained within the Asset Management Plan - allowing individual assets to be justified as part of a system of assets. This provides a framework for the safe use of CEA for individual assets.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
CEA in pharmacoeconomics</st>

<p>

In the context of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/6989424.xml">
pharmacoeconomics</link>, the cost-effectiveness of a therapeutic or preventive intervention is the ratio of the cost of the intervention to a relevant measure of its effect. Cost refers to the resource expended for the intervention, usually measured in monetary terms such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/8100.xml">
dollar</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/270673.xml">
pounds</link>. The measure of effects depends on the intervention being considered. Examples include the number of people cured of a disease, the mm Hg reduction in diastolic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/56558.xml">
blood pressure</link> and the number of symptom-free days experienced by a patient. The selection of the appropriate effect measure should be based on clinical judgment in the context of the intervention being considered.</p>
<p>

A special case of CEA is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/1393154.xml">
cost-utility analysis</link>, where the effects are measured in terms of years of full health lived, using a measure such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/1393169.xml">
quality-adjusted life years</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/4144577.xml">
disability-adjusted life years</link>.</p>
<p>

Cost-effectiveness is typically expressed as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/265132.xml">
incremental cost-effectiveness ratio</link> (ICER),  the ratio of change in costs to the change in effects. </p>
<p>

A complete compilation of cost-utility analyses in the peer reviewed medical literature is available at the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tufts-nemc.org/CEARegistry">
CEA Registry Website</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/374583.xml">
Cost-benefit analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/6832338.xml">
Cost overrun</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/4420584.stm">
Why some drugs are not worth it</weblink> BBC report</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/choice/en/">
World Health Organization - CHOICE CHoosing Interventions that are Cost Effective</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ispor.co.googlepages.com">
ISPOR-CO, The Colombian Chapter of The International Society for Pharmacoeconomics and Outcomes Research</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>





</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
