<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:40:12[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<merchandise  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103748886">
<header>
<title>Cutting fluid</title>
<id>266412</id>
<revision>
<id>243944328</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T18:04:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Wizard191</username>
<id>935746</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Petroleum products</category>
<category>Lubricants</category>
<category>Coolants</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="Makino-S33-MachiningCenter-example.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Thin-wall milling of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/904.xml">
aluminum</link> using a water-based cutting fluid on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/2389550.xml">
milling cutter</link>.
</caption>
</image>

<b>Cutting fluids</b> are various fluids that are used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/365765.xml">
machining</link> to cool and lubricate the cutting tool. There are various kinds of cutting fluids, which include oils, oil-water <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/10290.xml">
emulsion</link>s, pastes, gels, and mists. They may be made from petroleum distillates, animal fats, plant oils, or other raw ingredients. Depending on context and on which type of cutting fluid is being considered, it may be referred to as <b>cutting fluid</b>, <b>cutting oil</b>, <b>cutting compound</b>, <b>coolant</b>, or <b>lubricant</b>.<p>

Every kind of machining (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/1860095.xml">
turning</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/3064915.xml">
boring</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/900867.xml">
drilling</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/266425.xml">
milling</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/838061.xml">
broaching</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/1179028.xml">
grinding</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/401753.xml">
sawing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/266430.xml">
shaping</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/6086634.xml">
planing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/1000136.xml">
reaming</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/270174.xml">
tapping</link>) can potentially benefit from one kind of cutting fluid or another, depending on workpiece material. (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/132784.xml">
Cast iron</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/3292.xml">
brass</link> are usually machined dry. Interrupted cuts such as milling with carbide cutters are usually recommended to be used dry due to damage to the cutters caused by thermoshock.)</p>
<p>

The properties that are sought after in a good cutting fluid are the ability to: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 keep the workpiece at a stable temperature (critical when working to close <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/522062.xml">
tolerance</link>s). Very warm is OK, but extremely hot or alternating hot-and-cold should be avoided.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 maximize the life of the cutting tip by lubricating the working edge and reducing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/15604614.xml">
tip welding</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ensure safety for the people handling it (toxicity, bacteria, fungi) and for the environment upon disposal.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 prevent rust on machine parts and cutters.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Mechanisms of action </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Cooling </st>
<p>

Metal cutting operations involve generation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/19593167.xml">
heat</link> due to friction between the tool and the pieces and due to energy lost deforming the material. The surrounding air alone is a rather poor coolant for the cutting tool, because the rate of heat transfer is low. Ambient-air cooling is adequate for light cuts with periods of rest in between, such as are typical in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/91191.xml">
maintenance, repair and operations</link> (MRO) work or hobbyist contexts. However, for heavy cuts and constant use, such as in production work, more heat is produced per time period than ambient-air cooling can remove. It is not acceptable to introduce long idle periods into the cycle time to allow the air-cooling of the tool to "catch up" when the heat-removal can instead be accomplished with a flood of liquid, which can "keep up" with the heat generation.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Lubrication at the tool-chip interface </st>
<p>

Besides cooling, the other way that cutting fluids aid the cutting process is by lubricating the interface between the tool's cutting edge and the chip. By preventing friction at this interface, some of the heat generation is prevented. This lubrication also helps prevent the chip from being welded onto the tool, which interferes with subsequent cutting.</p>
<p>

<component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<addition wordnetid="102679415" confidence="0.8">
<additive wordnetid="102679788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/3155791.xml">
EP additive</link></additive>
</addition>
</part>
</component>
s are often added to cutting fluids.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Delivery methods </st>

<p>

Every conceivable method of applying cutting fluid (flooding, spraying, dripping, misting, etc.) can be used, with the best choice depending on the application and the equipment available. For many metalcutting applications the ideal would be high-pressure, high-volume pumping to force a stream of fluid directly into the tool-chip interface, with walls around the machine to contain the splatter and a sump to catch, filter, and recirculate the fluid. This type of system is commonly employed, especially in manufacturing. It is often not a practical option for MRO or hobbyist metalcutting, where smaller, simpler machine tools are used. Fortunately it is also not necessary in those applications, where heavy cuts, aggressive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/1527151.xml">
speeds and feeds</link>, and constant, all-day cutting are not vital.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Types of cutting fluid </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Liquids </st>

<p>

There are generally three types of liquids: mineral, semi-synthetic, and synthetic. Semi-synthetic and synthetic cutting fluids try to blend the best properties of oil into the best properties of water. They basically achieve this by allowing oil to emulsify into water. Some of these properties are: rust inhibition, tolerance of a wide range of water hardness (maintain pH stability around 9 to 10), ability to work with many metals, resist thermal breakdown, and environmental safety.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Water is a great conductor of heat but has drawbacks as a cutting fluid. It boils easily, promotes rusting of machine parts, and does not lubricate well. Therefore, other ingredients are necessary to create an optimal cutting fluid.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/19053.xml">
Mineral</link> coolants, which are petroleum-based, began in the late 1800s. They vary from the thick, dark, sulfur-rich cutting oils used in heavy industry to light, clear oils.</p>
<p>

Semi-synthetic coolants are an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/10290.xml">
emulsion</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/2563234.xml">
microemulsion</link> of water with mineral oil. They began in the 1930s. A typical CNC usually uses emulsified coolant. One way to understand it is to think of "pots-and-pans dishwater". It is a fair amount of oil emulsified into a larger amount of water using a detergent. Therefore it is roughly analogous to your dishwater after you have washed the vegetable oil off your pans (although more oily and less soapy).</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/446403.xml">
Synthetic</link> coolants originated in the late 1950s and are usually water-based.</p>
<p>

A hand-held <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/4088449.xml">
refractometer</link> is used to determine the mix ratio (also called strength) of water soluble coolants to verify effectiveness.  Numerous other test equipment are used to determine such things as acidity, and amount of conductivity.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Pastes or gels </st>

<p>

Cutting fluid may also take the form of a paste or gel when used for some applications, in particular hand operations such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/205126.xml">
drill</link>ing and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/270174.xml">
tapping</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Mists </st>

<p>

Some cutting fluids are used in mist (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/57763.xml">
aerosol</link>) form and some of them are used in drilling aluminium</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Other fluids used (present and past) </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Present </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/16992.xml">
Kerosene</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/15434.xml">
rubbing alcohol</link>, and <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/3866564.xml">
3-In-One Oil</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
 often give good results when working on aluminium.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/18621997.xml">
Lard</link> is suitable for general machining and also press tool work.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/212419.xml">
Mineral oil</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/354181.xml">
WD-40</link></institution>
</characteristic>
</hallmark>
</company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/41026.xml">
Dielectric</link> fluid is the cutting fluid used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/75485.xml">
Electrical discharge machines</link> (EDMs). It is usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/1268562.xml">
deionized water</link> or a high-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/286681.xml">
flash-point</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/16992.xml">
kerosene</link>. Intense heat is generated by the cutting action of the electrode (or wire) and the fluid is used to stabilise the temperature of the workpiece, along with flushing any eroded particles from the immediate work area. The dielectric fluid is nonconductive.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Liquid- (water- or petroleum oil-) cooled water tables are used with the plasma arc cutting (PAC) process.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Past </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 19th-century machining practice, it was not uncommon to use plain water. This was simply a practical expedient to keep the cutter cool, regardless of whether it provided any lubrication at the cutting edge–chip interface. When one considers that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/685784.xml">
high-speed steel</link> (HSS) had not been developed yet, the need to cool the tool becomes all the more apparent. (HSS retains its hardness at high temperatures; other carbon tool steels do not.) An improvement was soda water, which better inhibited the rusting of machine slides. These options are generally not used today because better options are available.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lard was very popular in the past. It is used less often today, because of the wide variety of other options, but it is still a fine option.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Old machine shop training texts speak of using <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<chemical_agent wordnetid="114779550" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<coloring_material wordnetid="114984973" confidence="0.8">
<oxidant wordnetid="114780040" confidence="0.8">
<mineral wordnetid="114662574" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="114778436" confidence="0.8">
<pigment wordnetid="114989820" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/1830570.xml">
red lead</link></material>
</pigment>
</agent>
</part>
</causal_agent>
</mineral>
</oxidant>
</coloring_material>
</substance>
</substance>
</chemical_agent>
</physical_entity>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/15679439.xml">
white lead</link>, often mixed into lard or lard oil. This practice is obsolete. Lead is a health hazard, and excellent non-lead-containing options are available.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 From the mid-20th century to the 1990s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/302493.xml">
1,1,1-trichloroethane</link> was used as an additive to make some cutting fluids more effective. In shop-floor slang it was referred to as "one-one-one". It has been phased out because of its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/44183.xml">
ozone-depleting</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/7251.xml">
CNS</link>-depressing properties.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Safety concerns (toxicity, bacteria, fungi) </st>

<p>

Cutting fluids have been associated with skin rashes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/2221241.xml">
dermatitis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/197010.xml">
esophagitis</link>, lung disease, and cancer. These problems result from either toxicity or bacterial or fungal contamination.</p>
<p>

Metalworking fluids often contain substances such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/216223.xml">
biocide</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../812/2120812.xml">
corrosion inhibitors</link>, metal fines, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/1655171.xml">
tramp oils</link>, and biological contaminants. Inhalation of cutting fluid aerosols may cause irritation of the throat, nose, and lungs and has been associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/302753.xml">
chronic bronchitis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/44905.xml">
asthma</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/2303500.xml">
hypersensitivity pneumonitis</link> (HP), and worsening of pre-existing respiratory problems. Skin exposure may result from touching contaminated surfaces, handling parts and equipment, splashing fluids, and aerosol mist settling on the skin. Skin contact with cutting fluids may cause allergic contact dermatitis, irritant contact dermatitis, and occupational ("oil") acne.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> </p>
<p>

Safer formulations provide a natural resistance to tramp oils allowing improved filtration separation without removing the base additive package. Ventilation, splash guards on machines, and personal protective equipment can mitigate hazards related to cutting fluids.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/9028799.xml">
Bacteria</link>l growth is predominant in semi-synthetic and synthetic fluids. Tramp oil along with human hair or skin oil are some of the debris during cutting which accumulates and forms a layer on the top of the liquid, anaerobic bacteria proliferate due to a number of factors. An early sign of the need for replacement is the "Monday-morning smell" (due to lack of usage from Friday to Monday). <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/65555.xml">
Antiseptic</link>s are sometimes added to the fluid to kill bacteria. Such use must be balanced against whether the antiseptics will harm the cutting performance, workers' health, or the environment. Maintaining as low a fluid temperature as practical will slow the growth of microorganisms.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Environmental impact </st>

<p>

Old, used cutting fluid must be disposed of when it is fetid or when it is chemically degraded and has lost its performance. As with used motor oil or other wastes, its impact on the environment should be mitigated. Legislation and regulation specify how this mitigation should be achieved. Enforcement is the most challenging aspect. Modern cutting fluid disposal may involve techniques such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/368389.xml">
ultrafiltration</link> using polymeric or ceramic membranes which concentrates the suspended and emulsified oil phase.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/1826695.xml">
Coolant</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<addition wordnetid="102679415" confidence="0.8">
<additive wordnetid="102679788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/3155791.xml">
EP additive</link></additive>
</addition>
</part>
</component>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../069/18069.xml">
Lubricants</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/266443.xml">
Metalworking</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
OSHA (1999). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.osha.gov/SLTC/metalworkingfluids/metalworkingfluids_manual.html">
Metalworking Fluids: Safety and Health Best Practices Manual</weblink>. Salt Lake City: U.S. Department of Labor, Occupational Safety and Health Administration.</entry>
<entry id="2">
NIOSH (2007). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/hhe/reports/pdfs/2005-0227-3049.pdf">
Health hazard evaluation and technical assistance report: HETA 005-0227-3049</weblink>, Diamond Chain Company, Indianapolis, Indiana.</entry>
<entry id="3">
 NIOSH (1998). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/98-102.html">
Criteria for a recommended standard: occupational exposure to metalworking fluids</weblink>. Cincinnati, OH: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health. DHHS (NIOSH) Pub. No. 98-102.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</merchandise>
</article>
