<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:41:49[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Scale (social sciences)</title>
<id>268973</id>
<revision>
<id>238431758</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-14T20:35:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>J. Spencer</username>
<id>568400</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Social sciences methodology</category>
<category>Market research</category>
<category>Psychometrics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In the social sciences, <b>scaling</b> is the process of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/19022.xml">
measuring</link> or ordering entities with respect to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/861437.xml">
quantitative</link> attributes or traits. For example, a scaling technique might involve estimating individuals' levels of extraversion, or the perceived quality of products. Certain methods of scaling permit estimation of magnitudes on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/360892.xml">
continuum</link>, while other methods provide only for relative ordering of the entities.<p>

See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
level of measurement</link> for an account of qualitatively different kinds of measurement scales.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Comparative and noncomparative scaling </st>

<p>

With <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
comparative scaling</link>, the items are directly compared with each other (example : Do you prefer <beverage wordnetid="107881800" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/24573.xml">
Pepsi</link></beverage>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/6690.xml">
Coke</link>?). In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
noncomparative scaling</link> each item is scaled independently of the others (example : How do you feel about Coke?).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Composite measures</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/268973.xml">
Composite measure</link>s of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/32818.xml">
variable</link>s are created by combining two or more separate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/307139.xml">
empirical</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/434104.xml">
indicators</link> into a single measure. Composite measures measure complex concepts more adequately than single indicators, extend the range of scores available and are more efficient at handling multiple items.</p>
<p>

In addition to scales, there are two other types of composite measures. Indexes are similar to scales except multiple indicators of a variable are combined into a single measure. The index of consumer confidence, for example, is a combination of several measures of consumer attitudes. A <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/312707.xml">
typology</link></b> is similar to an index except the variable is measured at the nominal level.</p>
<p>

Indexes are constructed by accumulating scores assigned to individual attributes, while scales are constructed through the assignment of scores to patterns of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/40738.xml">
attribute</link>s.</p>
<p>

While indexes and scales provide measures of a single <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/8398.xml">
dimension</link>, typologies are often employed to examine the intersection of two or more dimensions. Typologies are very useful analytical tools and can be easily used as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/437701.xml">
independent variable</link>s, although since they are not unidimensional it is difficult to use them as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/437701.xml">
dependent variable</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Data types</st>
<p>

The type of information collected can influence scale construction. Different types of information  are measured in different ways.  See in particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
level of measurement</link>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Some data are measured at the <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
nominal level</link></b>. That is, any numbers used are mere labels : they express no mathematical properties. Examples are SKU inventory codes and UPC bar codes. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Some data are measured at the <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
ordinal level</link></b>. Numbers indicate the relative position of items, but not the magnitude of difference. An example is a preference ranking. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Some data are measured at the <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
interval level</link></b>. Numbers indicate the magnitude of difference between items, but there is no absolute zero point. Examples are attitude scales and opinion scales. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Some data are measured at the <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
ratio level</link></b>. Numbers indicate magnitude of difference and there is a fixed zero point. Ratios can be calculated. Examples include: age, income, price, costs, sales revenue, sales volume, and market share.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Scale construction decisions</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

What level of data is involved (nominal, ordinal, interval, or ratio)?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

What will the results be used for? </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Should you use a scale, index, or typology?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

What types of statistical analysis would be useful?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Should you use a comparative scale or a noncomparative scale?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

How many scale divisions or categories should be used (1 to 10; 1 to 7; -3 to +3)?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Should there be an odd or even number of divisions? (Odd gives neutral center value; even forces respondents to take a non-neutral position.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

What should the nature and descriptiveness of the scale labels be?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

What should the physical form or layout of the scale be? (graphic, simple linear, vertical, horizontal)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Should a response be forced or be left optional?</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Comparative scaling techniques</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/4395832.xml">
Pairwise comparison</link> scale - a respondent is presented with two items at a time and asked to select one (example : Do you prefer Pepsi or Coke?). This is an ordinal level technique when a measurement model is not applied. Krus and Kennedy (1977) elaborated the paired comparison scaling within their domain-referenced model. The Bradley-Terry-Luce (BTL) model (Bradley and Terry, 1952; Luce, 1959) can be applied in order to derive measurements provided the data derived from paired comparisons possess an appropriate structure. Thurstone's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/2251120.xml">
Law of comparative judgment</link> can also be applied in such contexts.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/2161615.xml">
Rasch model</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 scaling - respondents interact with items and comparisons are inferred between items from the responses to obtain scale values. Respondents are subsequently also scaled based on their responses to items given the item scale values. The Rasch model has a close relation to the BTL model.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
Rank-order scale</link></b> - a respondent is presented with several items simultaneously and asked to rank them (example : Rate the following advertisements from 1 to 10.). This is an ordinal level technique.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
Constant sum scale</link></b> - a respondent is given a constant sum of money, script, credits, or points and asked to allocate these to various items (example : If you had 100 Yen to spend on food products, how much would you spend on product A, on product B, on product C, etc.). This is an ordinal level technique.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/2973694.xml">
Bogardus social distance scale</link></b> - measures the degree to which a person is willing to associate with a class or type of people. It asks how willing the respondent is to make various associations. The results are reduced to a single score on a scale. There are also non-comparative versions of this scale.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
Q-Sort scale</link></b> - Up to 140 items are sorted into groups based a rank-order procedure. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/1058531.xml">
Guttman scale</link></b> - This is a procedure to determine whether a set of items can be rank-ordered on a unidimensional scale. It utilizes the intensity structure among several indicators of a given variable. Statements are listed in order of importance. The rating is scaled by summing all responses until the first negative response in the list. The Guttman scale is related to Rasch measurement; specifically, Rasch models bring the Guttman approach within a probabilistic framework.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Non-comparative scaling techniques</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
Continuous rating scale</link></b> (also called the graphic rating scale) - respondents rate items by placing a mark on a line. The line is usually labeled at each end. There are sometimes a series of numbers, called scale points, (say, from zero to 100) under the line. Scoring and codification is difficult.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/454402.xml">
Likert scale</link></method>
</know-how>
</b> - Respondents are asked to indicate the amount of agreement or disagreement (from strongly agree to strongly disagree) on a five- or seven-point scale. The same format is used for multiple questions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/3984567.xml">
Phrase completion scales</link></b> - Respondents are asked to complete a phrase on an 11-point response scale in which 0 represents the absence of the theoretical construct and 10 represents the theorized maximum amount of the construct being measured. The same basic format is used for multiple questions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/2208004.xml">
Semantic differential scale</link></b> - Respondents are asked to rate on a 7 point scale an item on various attributes. Each attribute requires a scale with bipolar terminal labels.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
Stapel scale</link></b> - This is a unipolar ten-point rating scale. It ranges from +5 to -5 and has no neutral zero point. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/770661.xml">
Thurstone scale</link></b> - This is a scaling technique that incorporates the intensity structure among indicators.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link>
Mathematically derived scale</link></b> - Researchers infer respondents’ evaluations mathematically. Two examples are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/398786.xml">
multi dimensional scaling</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/253701.xml">
conjoint analysis</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Scale evaluation</st>
<p>

Scales should be tested for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/239138.xml">
reliability</link>, generalizability, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/239140.xml">
validity</link>. Generalizability is the ability to make inferences from a sample to the population, given the scale you have selected. Reliability is the extent to which a scale will produce consistent results. Test-retest reliability checks how similar the results are if the research is repeated under similar circumstances. Alternative forms reliability checks how similar the results are if the research is repeated using different forms of the scale. Internal consistency reliability checks how well the individual measures included in the scale are converted into a composite measure.</p>
<p>

Scales and indexes have to be validated. Internal validation checks the relation between the individual measures included in the scale, and the composite scale itself. External validation checks the relation between the composite scale and other indicators of the variable, indicators not included in the scale. Content validation (also called face validity) checks how well the scale measures what is supposed to measure. Criterion validation checks how meaningful the scale criteria are relative to other possible criteria. Construct validation checks what underlying construct is being measured. There are three variants of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/794342.xml">
construct validity</link>. They are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/6235098.xml">
convergent validity</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/6235137.xml">
discriminant validity</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/6229750.xml">
nomological validity</link> (Campbell and Fiske, 1959; Krus and Ney, 1978). The coefficient of reproducibility indicates how well the data from the individual measures included in the scale can be reconstructed from the composite scale.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bradley, R.A. &amp; Terry, M.E. (1952): <it>Rank analysis of incomplete block designs, I. the method of paired comparisons</it>. Biometrika, 39, 324-345.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Campbell, D. T. &amp; Fiske, D. W. (1959) Convergent and discriminant validation by the multitrait-multimethod matrix. <it>Psychological Bulletin,</it>  56, 81-105.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Hodge, D. R. &amp; Gillespie, D. F. (2003). Phrase Completions: An alternative to Likert scales. Social Work Research, 27(1), 45-55.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Hodge, D. R. &amp; Gillespie, D. F. (2005). Phrase Completion Scales. In K. Kempf-Leonard (Editor). Encyclopedia of Social Measurement. (Vol. 3, pp. 53-62). San Diego: Academic Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Krus, D. J. &amp; Kennedy, P. H. (1977) Normal scaling of dominance matrices: The domain-referenced model. <it>Educational and Psychological Measurement,</it> 37, 189-193 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.visualstatistics.net/Scaling/Domain%20Referenced%20Scaling/Domain-Referenced%20Scaling.htm">
(Request reprint).</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Krus, D. J. &amp; Ney, R. G. (1978) Convergent and discriminant validity in item analysis. <it>Educational and Psychological Measurement,</it> 38, 135-137 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.visualstatistics.net/Statistics/Item%20Analysis%20CD%20Validity/Item%20Analysis%20CD%20Validity.htm">
(Request reprint).</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Luce, R.D. (1959): <it>Individual Choice Behaviours: A Theoretical Analysis</it>. New York: J. Wiley.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/5216974.xml">
Rating scale</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/821148.xml">
Level of measurement</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/373212.xml">
Social research</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/59252.xml">
Marketing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/196086.xml">
Marketing research</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/274035.xml">
Quantitative marketing research</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</field>
</region>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Lists of related topics</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/251751.xml">
List of marketing topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/251755.xml">
List of management topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/90075.xml">
List of economics topics</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
