<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:55:58[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Applications of randomness</title>
<id>2714990</id>
<revision>
<id>176717454</id>
<timestamp>2007-12-09T05:44:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mild Bill Hiccup</username>
<id>5202324</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Randomness</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
Randomness</link></it>
</indent>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
Randomness</link> has many uses in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/11921.xml">
gambling</link>,  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/8691.xml">
divination</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
cryptography</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/752.xml">
art</link>, etc.<p>

Note that these uses may have different requirements when it comes to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/2551773.xml">
statistical randomness</link> or unpredictability, which in turn leads to different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/65462.xml">
randomization</link> methods. For example, applications in cryptography have strict requirements, whereas other uses (such as generating a "quote of the day") don't need more than "shallow" randomness.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Early uses </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Games </st>

<p>

Unpredictable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
random</link> numbers were first investigated in the context of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/11921.xml">
gambling</link>, and many randomizing devices such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/8244.xml">
dice</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/23189.xml">
shuffling playing cards</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/26487.xml">
roulette</link> wheels, were first developed for use in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/53481.xml">
games of chance</link>. Fairly produced random numbers are vital to electronic gambling and ways of creating them are sometimes regulated by governmental gaming commissions.</p>
<p>

Modern electronic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/5215.xml">
casino</link> games contain often one or more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/2736939.xml">
random number generator</link>s that decide the outcome of a trial in the game.  Even in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/29229.xml">
slot machine</link>s, where mechanical reels appear to spin randomly, the reels are actually spinning for entertainment value and eventually stop exactly where the machine's software decided they would stop when the handle was first pulled. (It has been alleged that some gaming machines' software is deliberately biased to prevent true randomness, in the interests of maximizing their owners' revenue -- this sort of allegation is why state <link>
gaming inspector</link>s exist.)</p>
<p>

Random draws are often used to make a decision where no rational or fair basis exists for making a deterministic decision, or to make unpredictable moves.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Divination </st>

<p>

Many ancient cultures saw random events in nature as signs from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/5042765.xml">
god</link>s. Still today, much of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/8691.xml">
divination</link> is based on the observation of random processes.</p>
<p>

Random numbers are often used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/23754.xml">
parapsychology</link> as a test of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/40253.xml">
precognition</link>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Political Use </st>

<ss1>
<st>
Athenian Democracy</st>

<p>

Fifth Century BC <link>
Athenian Democracy</link> developed out of a notion of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/7590455.xml">
isonomia</link> (equality of political rights), and random selection was the principal way of achieving this fairness<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. Greek "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/7959.xml">
Democracy</link>" (literally meaning rule by the people) was literally run by the people: the administration was in the hands of committees <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/41912.xml">
allotted</link> from the people. Although it may seem strange to those used to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/9282116.xml">
Liberal Democracy</link> the Athenian Greeks considered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/9457.xml">
elections</link> to be undemocratic<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. This was because citizens chosen on merit or popularity contradicted the democratic principle of equality of all citizenry. In addition, allotment prevented the corrupt practise of buying votes as no one could know who would be selected as a magistrate or to sit on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/44720.xml">
Jury</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Modern Use</st>
<p>

Allotment is today restricted mainly to the selection of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/44720.xml">
juror</link>s in Anglo-Saxon legal systems like the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1048927.xml">
UK</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
US</link>. Proposals have been made for its use in government such as a new constitution for Iraq <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sortition.org.uk">
http://www.sortition.org.uk</weblink> and various proposals for Upper Houses chosen by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/41912.xml">
allotment</link> (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/3371414.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Allotment/Sortition%22])">
Lords Reform</link>)</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Science </st>
<p>

Random numbers have uses in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/22939.xml">
physics</link> (such as <link>
noise resonance</link> studies), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/9251.xml">
engineering</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/43476.xml">
operations research</link>.  Many methods of statistical analysis, such as the <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/3763850.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Bootstrap%22])">
bootstrap</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</method>
</experiment>
</know-how>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 method, require random numbers.  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/56098.xml">
Monte Carlo method</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
s in physics and computer science require random numbers to function.  </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Statistical sampling </st>

<p>

<link>
Statistical practice</link> is based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/27579.xml">
statistical theory</link> which, itself is founded on the concept of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
randomness</link>. Many elements of statistical practice depend on the emulation of randomness through random numbers. Where those random numbers fall short of the conceptual ideal of randomness any subsequent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistical</link> analysis may suffer from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/1086930.xml">
systematic bias</link>. Elements of statistical practice that depend on randomness include: choosing a representative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/27586.xml">
sample</link>, disguising the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/2193391.xml">
protocol</link> of a study from a participant (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/163180.xml">
randomized controlled trial</link>) and <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/56098.xml">
Monte Carlo</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 simulation.</p>
<p>

These applications are useful in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/224700.xml">
auditing</link> (for determining samples - such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/842201.xml">
invoice</link>s) and <link>
experimental design</link> (for example in the creation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/277248.xml">
double-blind trials</link>).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Analysis </st>

<p>

Many experiments in physics rely on a statistical analysis of their output.  For example, an experiment might collect <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/34197.xml">
X-ray</link>s from an astronomical source and then analyze the result for periodic signals.  Since random noise can be expected to appear to have very faint periodic signals embedded in it, statistical analysis is required to determine the likelihood that a given signal actually represents a genuine signal.  Testing such analysis methods requires the generation of random numbers.  If the statistical method is extremely sensitive to patterns in the data (such as those used to search for binary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/1227284.xml">
pulsar</link>s) then very large amounts of data with no recognizable pattern are needed.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Simulation </st>

<p>

In many scientific and engineering fields, computer simulations of real phenomena are essential to understanding.  When the real phenomena are affected by unpredictable processes, such as radio noise or day-to-day weather, these processes must be simulated using random or pseudo-random numbers.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/2736939.xml">
Random number generator</link>s were originally constructed to carry out computer simulation of physical phenomena, specifically the simulation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/879282.xml">
neutron transport</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/22054.xml">
nuclear fission</link>. </p>
<p>

Pseudo-random numbers are frequently used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/43444.xml">
simulation</link> of statistical events, a very simple example being the outcome of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/494410.xml">
tossing a coin</link>. More complicated implications are the simulation of genetics in whole populations, or the behaviour of sub-atomic particles. Such simulation methods, often called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/47895.xml">
stochastic</link> simulation methods have many applications in computer simulation of real-world effects.</p>
<p>

Some not very rational projects such as the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/435023.xml">
Global Consciousness Project</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
 exist which monitors fluctuations in the randomness of the numbers generated by a large number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/160506.xml">
hardware random number generator</link>s in an attempt to predict the scope of an event in near future. The intent is to prove that large scale events that are about to happen build up a sort of pressure (possibly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/19595649.xml">
quantum</link>) that affects the RNGs.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Cryptography </st>
<p>

A ubiquitous use of unpredictable random numbers is in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
cryptography</link> which underlies most of the attempts to provide security in modern communications (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/353859.xml">
confidentiality</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authentication</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/9611.xml">
electronic commerce</link>, etc.). </p>
<p>

For example, if a user wants to use an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption algorithm</link>, it is best that they select a random number as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/53039.xml">
key</link>.  These numbers must be completely unguessable to anyone else.  The only way to practically manufacture such numbers is to use random numbers. If this is not done properly, security can be compromised. For example, if a simple 32 bit linear congruential pseudo-random number generator of the type supplied with most programming languages is used, then there will only be some four billion possible keys that can be produced  before the generator repeats itself. A suitably motivated adversary could simply test them all.  Even if a more sophisticated random number generator is used, its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/2503259.xml">
seed</link> might be guessed (perhaps it is the time of day when the key was generated), and then keys can be predicted.  (A vulnerability of this sort was famously discovered in an early release of <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/21863.xml">
Netscape Navigator</link></software>
, forcing the authors to quickly find a source of "more random" random numbers). Thus for this application, some truly random numbers are required.  </p>
<p>

Truly random numbers are absolutely required to be assured of the theoretical security provided by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/22210.xml">
one-time pad</link> &mdash; the only provably unbreakable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> algorithm. Furthermore, those random sequences cannot be reused and must never become available to any attacker, which implies a continuously operable generator. See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/173620.xml">
Venona</link> for an example of what happens when these requirements are violated when using a one-time pad. </p>
<p>

For cryptographic purposes, one normally assumes some upper limit on the work an adversary can do (usually this limit is astronomically sized). If one has a pseudo-random number generator whose output is "sufficiently difficult" to predict for an unknown seed (such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/49007.xml">
stream cipher</link>), one can generate true random numbers to fill the seed and then use the pseudo-random numbers in cryptographic applications.  Such random number generators are called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/182249.xml">
cryptographically secure pseudo-random number generator</link>s, and several have been implemented (for example, the /dev/urandom device available on most Unixes, the Yarrow server, and AT&amp;T Bell Labs "truerand").  As with all cryptographic software, there are subtle issues beyond those discussed here, so care is certainly indicated in actual practice. In any case, it is often impossible to avoid the need for true (i.e., hardware) random number generators.</p>
<p>

Since a requirement in cryptography is unpredictability to an attacker, <it>any</it> published random sequence is a poor choice, as are such sequences as the digits in an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/19724804.xml">
irrational number</link> such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/377456.xml">
φ</link> or even in <link>
transcendental numbers</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/23601.xml">
π</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/9633.xml">
e</link>.  Put another way, in cryptography, random bit streams need to be not only random, but also secret and hence unpredictable. Public or third-party sources of random values, or random values computed from publicly observable phenomena (weather, sports game results, stock prices), are almost never cryptographically acceptable, though often tempting and too often used by the unwary. They permit attacks that should never be allowed.</p>
<p>

Since most cryptographic applications require a few thousand <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/3364.xml">
bit</link>s at most, slow random number generators serve well&mdash;if they are actually random.  This use of random generators is important; many informed observers believe every computer should have a way to generate true random numbers.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Literature, music and art </st>

<p>

A clear example of randomness occurs in the problem of arranging items in an art exhibit.  Usually this is avoided by using a theme. As John Cage pointed out, "While there are many ways that sounds might be produced [i.e., in terms of patterns], few are attempted". Similarly, the arrangement of art in exhibits is often deliberately non-random. One case of this was Hitler's attempt to portray modern art in the worst possible light by arranging works in worst possible manner. A case can be made for trying to make art in the worst possible way; i.e., either as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/2097128.xml">
anti-art</link>, or as actually random art. </p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/8240.xml">
Dadaism</link> as well as many other movements in art and letters have attempted to deal with randomness in various forms. Often people mistake order for randomness based on lack of information; e.g., <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/16307.xml">
Jackson Pollock</link></artist>
</person>
's drip
paintings, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<painter wordnetid="110391653" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<printmaker wordnetid="110475687" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/238326.xml">
Helen Frankenthaler</link></creator>
</printmaker>
</scholar>
</artist>
</painter>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
's  abstractions (e.g., "For E.M."). Thus, in theory of art, all art is random in that it's "just paint and canvas" (the explanation of <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<painter wordnetid="110391653" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<printmaker wordnetid="110475687" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/173057.xml">
Frank Stella</link></creator>
</printmaker>
</scholar>
</artist>
</painter>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
's work).</p>
<p>

Similarly, the "unexpected" ending is part of the nature of interesting literature. A chief example of this is <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/8199.xml">
Denis Diderot</link></person>
's novel <it>Jacques le fataliste</it> (literally: <it>James the Fatalist</it>; sometimes referred to as <it>Jacques the Fatalist</it> or <it>Jacques the Servant and his Master</it>). At one point in the novel, Diderot speaks directly to the reader:</p>
<p>

Now I, as the author of this novel might have them set upon by thieves, or I might have them rest by a tree until the rain stops, but in fact they kept on walking and then near night-fall they could see the light of an inn in the distance.</p>
<p>

(not an exact quote).  Diderot was making the point that the novel (a new invention then) was in fact random (in the sense of being invented out of thin air by the author).   See also <translator wordnetid="110725280" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/311360.xml">
Eugenio Montale</link></writer>
</translator>
, <product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<genre wordnetid="105845332" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/85248.xml">
Theatre of the Absurd</link></kind>
</end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</creation>
</genre>
</product>
.</p>
<p>

Randomness in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/18839.xml">
music</link> is deemed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/23613.xml">
postmodern</link>, including <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/65954.xml">
John Cage</link></person>
's chance derived <it><part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<piece wordnetid="103932203" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/14164396.xml">
Music of Changes</link></piece>
</part>
</it>, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/158366.xml">
Iannis Xenakis</link></person>
' <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/292222.xml">
stochastic</link> music,  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/99234.xml">
aleatoric music</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/11820540.xml">
indeterminate music</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/543884.xml">
generative music</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Other uses </st>

<p>

Random numbers are also used in situations where "fairness" is approximated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/65462.xml">
randomization</link>, such as selecting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/44720.xml">
juror</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/55826.xml">
military draft lotteries</link>. In the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/4376.xml">
Book of Numbers</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
 (33:54), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/19577.xml">
Moses</link> commands the Israelites to apportion the land by lot (גורל).</p>
<p>

Other examples might be generating a "Random Quote of the Day" for a website, or determining which way a villain might move in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/1336512.xml">
computer game</link>. </p>
<p>

Weaker forms of <it>randomness</it> are also closely associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/13790.xml">
hash algorithm</link>s and in creating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/265322.xml">
amortized</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/28249.xml">
searching</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/28442.xml">
sorting algorithm</link>s.</p>
<p>

Randomness is also used in fanfiction, to describe events in stories that happen without much importance to plot, usually on purpose for humoruous reasons.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Herodotus 3.80</entry>
<entry id="2">
The Athenian Democracy in the Age of Demosthenes", <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/8373924.xml">
Mogens Herman Hansen</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, ISBN 1-85399-585-1</entry>
<entry id="3">
“it is thought to be democratic for the offices to be assigned by lot, for them to be elected is oligarchic,” [Aristotle, Politics 4.1294b]</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://random.org</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
