<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:55:58[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Neuro-fuzzy</title>
<id>2715076</id>
<revision>
<id>234855270</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-28T20:48:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Uncle G&amp;apos;s major work &amp;apos;bot</username>
<id>406717</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Artificial intelligence</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link>, <b>neuro-fuzzy</b> refers to combinations of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
artificial neural network</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/49180.xml">
fuzzy logic</link>. Neuro-fuzzy hybridization results in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/2932246.xml">
hybrid intelligent system</link> that synergizes these two techniques by combining the human-like reasoning style of fuzzy systems with the learning and connectionist structure of neural networks.  Neuro-fuzzy hybridization is widely termed as Fuzzy Neural Network (FNN) or Neuro-Fuzzy System (NFS) in the literature.  Neuro-fuzzy system (the more popular term is used henceforth) incorporates the human-like reasoning style of fuzzy systems through the use of fuzzy sets and a linguistic model consisting of a set of IF-THEN fuzzy rules. The main strength of neuro-fuzzy systems is that they are universal approximators with the ability to solicit interpretable IF-THEN rules.<p>

The strength of neuro-fuzzy systems involves two contradictory requirements in fuzzy modeling: interpretability versus accuracy. In practice, one of the two properties prevails. The neuro-fuzzy in fuzzy modeling research field is divided into two areas: linguistic fuzzy modeling that is focused on interpretability, mainly the Mamdani model; and precise fuzzy modeling that is focused on accuracy, mainly the Takagi-Sugeno-Kang (TSK) model.</p>
<p>

Although generally assumed to be the realization of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/48660.xml">
fuzzy system</link> through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/263636.xml">
connectionist</link> networks, this term is also used to describe some other configurations including:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Deriving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/16415639.xml">
fuzzy rule</link>s from trained <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/2310753.xml">
RBF</link> networks.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/49180.xml">
Fuzzy logic</link> based tuning of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/1729542.xml">
neural network</link> training parameters.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fuzzy logic criteria for increasing a network size.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Realising <link>
fuzzy membership</link> through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/39172.xml">
clustering</link> algorithms in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/233497.xml">
unsupervised learning</link> in <link>
SOM</link>s and <link>
neural networks</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Representing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/56601.xml">
fuzzification</link>, fuzzy inference and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/1035745.xml">
defuzzification</link> through multi-layers feed-forward <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/263636.xml">
connectionist</link> networks.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

It must be pointed out that interpretability of the Mamdani-type neuro-fuzzy systems can be lost. To improve the interpretability of neuro-fuzzy systems, certain measures must be taken, wherein important aspects of interpretability of neuro-fuzzy systems are also discussed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Pseudo outer-product-based fuzzy neural networks</st>
<p>

<it>Pseudo outer-product-based fuzzy neural networks ("POPFNN")</it>, are a family of neuro-fuzzy systems, that are based on the linguistic fuzzy model.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Three members of POPFNN exist in the literature:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>POPFNN-AARS(S)</b>,  which is based on the Approximate Analogical Reasoning Scheme<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>POPFNN-CRI(S)</b>, which is based on commonly accepted fuzzy Compositional Rule of Inference<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>POPFNN-TVR</b>, which is based on Truth Value Restriction</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The "POPFNN" architecture is a five-layer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/1729542.xml">
neural network</link> where the layers from 1 to 5 are called: input linguistic layer, condition layer, rule layer, consequent layer, output linguistic layer.  The fuzzification of the inputs and the defuzzification of the outputs are respectively performed by the input linguistic and output linguistic layers while the fuzzy inference is collectively performed by the rule, condition and consequence layers.</p>
<p>

The learning process of POPFNN consists of three phases:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Fuzzy membership generation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Fuzzy rule identification</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Supervised fine-tuning</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Various fuzzy membership generation <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s can be used: Learning Vector Quantization (LVQ), Fuzzy Kohonen Partitioning (FKP) or Discrete Incremental Clustering (DIC). Generally, the POP algorithm and its variant LazyPOP are used to identify the fuzzy rules.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
ANFIS</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/2932246.xml">
Hybrid intelligent system</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Y. Jin (2000). Fuzzy modeling of high-dimensional systems: Complexity reduction and interpretability improvement. IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems, 8(2), 212-221, 2000</entry>
<entry id="2">
Zhou, R. W., &amp; Quek, C. (1996). "POPFNN: A Pseudo Outer-product Based Fuzzy Neural Network". <it>Neural Networks</it>, 9(9), 1569-1581.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Quek, C., &amp; Zhou, R. W. (1999). "POPFNN-AAR(S): a pseudo outer-product based fuzzy neural network." <it>IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man and Cybernetics</it>, Part B, 29(6), 859-870.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Ang, K. K., Quek, C., &amp; Pasquier, M. (2003). "POPFNN-CRI(S): pseudo outer product based fuzzy neural network using the compositional rule of inference and singleton fuzzifier." <it>IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man and Cybernetics</it>, Part B, 33(6), 838-849.</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Abraham A., "Adaptation of Fuzzy Inference System Using Neural Learning, Fuzzy System Engineering: Theory and Practice", Nadia Nedjah et al. (Eds.), <it>Studies in Fuzziness and Soft Computing</it>, Springer Verlag Germany, ISBN 3-540-25322-X, Chapter 3, pp. 53-83, 2005. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springeronline.com/sgw/cda/frontpage/0,11855,5-40109-22-48660080-0,00.html">
information on publisher's site</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ang, K. K., &amp; Quek, C. (2005). "RSPOP: Rough Set-Based Pseudo Outer-Product Fuzzy Rule Identification Algorithm". <it>Neural Computation</it>, 17(1), 205-243.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kosko, Bart (1992). <it>Neural Networks and Fuzzy Systems: A Dynamical Systems Approach to Machine Intelligence</it>. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall. ISBN 0-13-611435-0.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lin, C.-T., &amp; Lee, C. S. G. (1996). <it>Neural Fuzzy Systems: A Neuro-Fuzzy Synergism to Intelligent Systems</it>. Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Quek, C., &amp; Zhou, R. W. (2001). "The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/149969.xml">
POP</link> learning algorithms: reducing work in identifying fuzzy rules." <it>Neural Networks</it>, 14(10), 1431-1445.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soft-computing.de/detail1.html">
A Definition of Interpretability of Fuzzy Systems</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
