<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:50:27[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Classes of supply</title>
<id>2726384</id>
<revision>
<id>238907345</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-16T23:03:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bahamut0013</username>
<id>3704212</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Military logistics</category>
<category>Military of the United States</category>
<category>Military supply</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/32212.xml">
U.S. Armed Forces</link> divides supplies into ten <b>Classes of Supply</b>.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/21133.xml">
North Atlantic Treaty Organisation</link> (NATO) uses only the first five.  
<sec>
<st>
 U.S. Armed Forces Classes of Supply </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class I - Subsistence (food), gratuitous (free) health and comfort items.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class II - Clothing, individual equipment, tentage, organizational tool sets and kits, hand tools, unclassified maps, administrative and housekeeping supplies and equipment.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class III - Petroleum, Oil and Lubricants (POL) (package and bulk): Petroleum, fuels, lubricants, hydraulic and insulating oils, preservatives, liquids and gases, bulk chemical products, coolants, deicer and antifreeze compounds, components, and additives of petroleum and chemical products, and coal.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class IV - Construction materials, including installed equipment and all fortification and barrier materials. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class V - Ammunition of all types, bombs, explosives, mines, fuzes, detonators, pyrotechnics, missiles, rockets, propellants, and associated items.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class VI - Personal demand items (such as health and hygiene products, soaps and toothpaste, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/13366106.xml">
writing material</link>, snack food, beverages, cigarettes, batteries, <link>
alcohol</link>, and cameras—nonmilitary sales items).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class VII - Major end items such as launchers, tanks, mobile machine shops, and vehicles.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class VIII - Medical material (equipment and consummables) including repair parts peculiar to medical equipment. (Class VIIIa – Medical consummable supplies not including blood &amp; blood products; Class VIIIb – Blood &amp; blood components (whole blood, platelets, plasma, packed red cells, etc).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class IX - Repair parts and components to include kits, assemblies, and subassemblies (repairable or non-repairable) required for maintenance support of all equipment.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class X - Material to support nonmilitary programs such as agriculture and economic development (not included in Classes I through IX).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Miscellaneous - Water, salvage, and captured material.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

(Source - U.S. Army Field Manual 4-0 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/2718615.xml">
Combat Service Support</link>)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 North Atlantic Treaty Organization Classes of Supply </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class I - Items of subsistence, e.g. food and forage, which are consumed by personnel or animals at an approximately uniform rate, irrespective of local changes in combat or terrain conditions. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class II - Supplies for which allowances are established by tables of organization and equipment, e.g. clothing, weapons, tools, spare parts, vehicles. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class III - Petroleum, oil and lubricants (POL) for all purposes, except for operating aircraft or for use in weapons such as flamethrowers, e.g. gasoline, fuel oil, greases, coal and coke. (Class IIIa - aviation fuel and lubricants) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class IV - Supplies for which initial issue allowances are not prescribed by approved issue tables. Normally includes fortification and construction materials, as well as additional quantities of items identical to those authorized for initial issue (Class II) such as additional vehicles. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Class V - Ammunition, explosives, and chemical agents of all types. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

(Source - NATO Logistics Handbook, 1997)</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
