<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:34:48[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<concept  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105835747">
<header>
<title>Semiconductor</title>
<id>27709</id>
<revision>
<id>244543797</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T10:10:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Horselover Frost</username>
<id>5949061</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles with unsourced statements</category>
<category>Articles with unsourced statements since March 2008</category>
<category>Semiconductors</category>
<category>Fundamental physics concepts</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>
<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is missing  or needs .</b>
Using helps guard against copyright violations and factual inaccuracies. <it>(March 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</b><p>

A <b>semiconductor</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/18993816.xml">
solid</link> material that has <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/59079.xml">
electrical conductivity</link> in between a <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/198984.xml">
conductor</link></concept>
</idea>
 and an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/15066.xml">
insulator</link>; it can vary over that wide range either permanently or dynamically.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

Semiconductors are important in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/9663.xml">
electronic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/29816.xml">
technology</link>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/40344.xml">
Semiconductor device</link>s, electronic components made of semiconductor materials, are essential in modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/189768.xml">
consumer electronics</link>, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computers</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/19644137.xml">
mobile phone</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/1247424.xml">
digital audio player</link>s.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/27114.xml">
Silicon</link> is used to create most semiconductors commercially, but dozens of other materials are used as well.</p>




<sec>
<st>
Band structure</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>For more details on this topic, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/706247.xml">
Electronic band structure</link>.</it>
</indent>

<image width="150px" src="HAtomOrbitals.png">
<caption>

 In a single H-atom an electron resides in well known orbits. Note that the orbits are called s,p,d in order of increasing circular current.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="CovalentBond.png">
<caption>

 Putting two atoms together leads to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/653183.xml">
delocalized</link> orbits across two atoms, a so called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/6246.xml">
covalent bond</link>. Due to Paulis principle in every state there is max one electron. 
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Bändermodell-Potentialtöpfe.png">
<caption>

 This can be continued with more atoms. Note: This picture unfortunately shows a metal.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Benz4.png">
<caption>

 Using 6 carbon atoms one can create molecular orbits which allow for circular current. Filling the states following Pauli's principle leads to zero net current. Current due to uneven filling needs an energy investment.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Ressauts_et_terrasses.png">
<caption>

 Proceeding in a regular fashion and create a crystal, which may after creation be cut into a tape and fused together at the ends allow for circular currents.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Si-band-schematics.PNG">
<caption>

 For this regular solid the band structure can be calculated or measured.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Electronic_band_diagram.svg">
<caption>

 Integrating over the k axis gives the bands of a semiconductor showing a full valence band and an empty conduction band. Generally stopping at the vacuum level is dumb, because some people want to calculate: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/364613.xml">
photoemission</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/2065830.xml">
inverse photoemission</link>
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Wave_packet_(no_dispersion).gif">
<caption>

 <b>After</b> the band structure is determined states can be combined to generate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/452667.xml">
wave packet</link>s. As this is analogous to wave packages in free space, the results are similar.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Diffusion_rayleigh_et_diffraction.png">
<caption>

 An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/421940.xml">
alternative description</link>, which does not really appreciate the strong Coulomb interaction, shoots free electrons into the crystal and looks at the scattering.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Semiconduttore_intrinseco.png">
<caption>

 A third <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/432181.xml">
alternative description</link> uses strongly localized unpaired electrons in chemical bonds, which looks almost like a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/2740949.xml">
Mott insulator</link>.
</caption>
</image>
</p>


<ss1>
<st>
 Explaining semiconductor energy bands </st>

<p>

There are three popular ways to describe the electronic structure of a crystal. </p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Energy level splitting due to electron energy level Pauli exclusion </st>

<p>

The first starts from single atoms. An atom has discrete energy levels.
When two atoms come close each energy level splits into an upper and a lower level, whereby they delocalize across the two atoms.
With more atoms the number of levels increases, and groups of levels form bands.
Semiconductors contain many bands. If there is a large distance between the highest occupied state and the lowest unoccupied         space, then a gap will likely remain between occupied and unoccupied bands even after band formation.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Bragg reflection in a diffuse lattice </st>

<p>

A second way starts with free electrons <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/33516.xml">
wave</link>s. When fading in an electrostatic potential due to the cores,
due to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/421940.xml">
Bragg reflection</link> some waves are reflected and cannot penetrate the bulk, that is a band gap opens.
In this description it is not clear, while the number of electrons fills up exactly all states below the gap.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Energy level splitting due to spin state Pauli exclusion</st>

<p>

A third description starts with two atoms. The split states form a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/6246.xml">
covalent bond</link>
where two electrons with spin up and spin down are mostly in between the two atoms. 
Adding more atoms now is supposed not to lead to splitting, but to more bonds.
This is the way silicon is typically drawn. The band gap is now formed by lifting one electron from the lower electron level
into the upper level. This level is known to be anti-bonding, but bulk silicon has not been seen to lose atoms as easy as electrons are
wandering through it. Also this model is most unsuitable to explain how in graded hetero-junction the band gap can vary smoothly.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Energy bands and electrical conduction</st>

<p>

Like in other solids, the electrons in semiconductors can have energies only within certain bands (ie. ranges of levels of energy) between the energy of the ground state, corresponding to electrons tightly bound to the atomic nuclei of the material, and the free electron energy, which is the energy required for an electron to escape entirely from the material. The energy bands each correspond to a large number of discrete <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/279638.xml">
quantum state</link>s of the electrons, and most of the states with low energy (closer to the nucleus) are full, up to a particular band called the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/146065.xml">
valence band</link></it>. Semiconductors and insulators are distinguished from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/19042.xml">
metals</link> because the valence band in the semiconductor materials is very nearly full under usual operating conditions, thus causing more electrons to be available in the conduction band.</p>
<p>

The ease with which electrons in a semiconductor can be excited from the valence band to the conduction band depends on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/118396.xml">
band gap</link> between the bands, and it is the size of this energy bandgap that serves as an arbitrary dividing line (roughly 4 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/9598.xml">
eV</link>) between semiconductors and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/15066.xml">
insulator</link>s. </p>
<p>

In the picture of covalent bonds, an electron moves by hopping to a neighboring bond. Because of the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/24669.xml">
Pauli exclusion principle</link></concept>
</idea>
 it has to be lifted into the higher anti-bonding state of that bond. In the picture of delocalized states, for example in one dimension that is in a wire, for every energy there is a state with electrons flowing in one direction and one state for the electrons flowing in the other. For a net current to flow some more states for one direction than for the other direction have to be occupied and for this energy is needed. For a metal this can be a very small energy in the semiconductor the next higher states lie above the band gap. Often this is stated as: full bands do not contribute to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/59079.xml">
electrical conductivity</link>. However, as the temperature of a semiconductor rises above <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/1418.xml">
absolute zero</link>, there is more energy in the semiconductor to spend on lattice vibration and — more importantly for us — on lifting some electrons into an energy states of the <it>conduction band</it>, which is the band immediately above the valence band. The current-carrying electrons in the conduction band are known as "free electrons", although they are often simply called "electrons" if context allows this usage to be clear.</p>
<p>

Electrons excited to the conduction band also leave behind <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/142534.xml">
electron hole</link>s, or unoccupied states in the valence band. Both the conduction band electrons and the valence band holes contribute to electrical conductivity. The holes themselves don't actually move, but a neighboring electron can move to fill the hole, leaving a hole at the place it has just come from, and in this way the holes appear to move, and the holes behave as if they were actual positively charged particles.</p>
<p>

One <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/6246.xml">
covalent bond</link> between neighboring atoms in the solid is ten times stronger than the binding of the single electron to the atom, so freeing the electron does not imply destruction of the crystal structure.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Holes: electron absence as a charge carrier</st>

<p>

The notion of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/142534.xml">
holes</link>, which was introduced for semiconductors, can also be applied to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/19042.xml">
metal</link>s, where the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/170165.xml">
Fermi level</link> lies <it>within</it> the conduction band. With most metals the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/14307.xml">
Hall effect</link> reveals electrons to be the charge carriers, but some metals have a mostly filled conduction band, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/14307.xml">
Hall effect</link> reveals positive charge carriers, which are not the ion-cores, but holes. Contrast this to some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/198984.xml">
conductors</link> like solutions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/1605200.xml">
salt</link>s, or plasma. In the case of a metal, only a small amount of energy is needed for the electrons to find other unoccupied states to move into, and hence for current to flow. Sometimes even in this case it may be said that a hole was left behind, to explain why the electron does not fall back to lower energies: It cannot find a hole. In the end in both materials electron-phonon scattering and defects are the dominant causes for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/61577.xml">
resistance</link>.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="360px" src="FD_e_mu.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Fermi-Dirac distribution. States with energy <math>\epsilon</math> below the Fermi energy, here <math>\mu</math>, have higher probability <math>n</math> to be occupied, and those above are less likely to be occupied. Smearing of the distribution increases with temperature.
</caption>
</image>
The energy distribution of the electrons determines which of the states are filled and which are empty. This distribution is described by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/159225.xml">
Fermi-Dirac statistics</link>. The distribution is characterized by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/19572300.xml">
temperature</link> of the electrons, and the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/170165.xml">
Fermi energy</link></it> or <it>Fermi level</it>. Under absolute zero conditions the Fermi energy can be thought of as the energy up to which available electron states are occupied. At higher temperatures, the Fermi energy is the energy at which the probability of a state being occupied has fallen to 0.5. </p>
<p>

The dependence of the electron energy distribution on temperature also explains why the conductivity of a semiconductor has a strong temperature dependency, as a semiconductor operating at lower temperatures will have fewer available free electrons and holes able to do the work. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Energy–momentum dispersion</st>

<p>

In the preceding description an important fact is ignored for the sake of simplicity: the <it>dispersion</it> of the energy. The reason that the energies of the states are broadened into a band is that the energy depends on the value of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/686036.xml">
wave vector</link>, or <it>k-vector</it>, of the electron. The k-vector, in quantum mechanics, is the representation of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/20431.xml">
momentum</link> of a particle.</p>
<p>

The dispersion relationship determines the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/156706.xml">
effective mass</link>, <math>m^{*}</math>, of electrons or holes in the semiconductor, according to the formula:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math> m^{*} = \hbar^2 \cdot \left[ {{d^2 E(k)} \over {d k^2}} \right]^{-1} </math>
</indent>

The effective mass is important as it affects many of the electrical properties of the semiconductor, such as the electron or hole <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/760994.xml">
mobility</link>, which in turn influences the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/11671.xml">
diffusivity</link></it> of the charge carriers and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/59079.xml">
electrical conductivity</link> of the semiconductor. </p>
<p>

Typically the effective mass of electrons and holes are different. This affects the relative performance of <it>p-channel</it> and <it>n-channel</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/40345.xml">
IGFET</link>s, for example (Muller &amp; Kamins 1986:427).</p>
<p>

The top of the valence band and the bottom of the conduction band might not occur at that same value of k. Materials with this situation, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/27114.xml">
silicon</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/12242.xml">
germanium</link>, are known as <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/173679.xml">
indirect bandgap</link></it> materials. Materials in which the band extrema are aligned in k, for example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/144143.xml">
gallium arsenide</link>, are called <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/173680.xml">
direct bandgap</link></it> semiconductors. Direct gap semiconductors are particularly important in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/132883.xml">
optoelectronics</link> because they are much more efficient as light emitters than indirect gap materials.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Carrier generation and recombination</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>For more details on this topic, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/2080260.xml">
Carrier generation and recombination</link>.</it>
</indent>

When <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/202522.xml">
ionizing radiation</link> strikes a semiconductor, it may excite an electron out of its energy level and consequently leave a hole. This process is known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/2080260.xml">
<it>electron–hole pair generation''</it></link>.  Electron-hole pairs are constantly generated from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/467047.xml">
thermal energy</link> as well, in the absence of any external energy source. </p>
<p>

Electron-hole pairs are also apt to recombine. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/67088.xml">
Conservation of energy</link> demands that these recombination events, in which an electron loses an amount of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/9649.xml">
energy</link> larger than the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/118396.xml">
band gap</link>, be accompanied by the emission of thermal energy (in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/85754.xml">
phonons</link>) or radiation (in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/23535.xml">
photons</link>). </p>
<p>

In some states, the generation and recombination of electron–hole pairs are in equipoise.  The number of electron-hole pairs in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/1326107.xml">
steady state</link> at a given temperature is determined by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/712450.xml">
quantum statistical mechanics</link>. The precise <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanical</link> mechanisms of generation and recombination are governed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/67088.xml">
conservation of energy</link> and <link>
conservation of momentum</link>.</p>
<p>

As the probability that electrons and holes meet together is proportional to the product of their amounts, the product is in steady state nearly constant at a given temperature, providing that there is no significant electric field (which might "flush" carriers of both types, or move them from neighbour regions containing more of them to meet together) or externally driven pair generation. The product is a function of the temperature, as the probability of getting enough thermal energy to produce a pair increases with temperature, being approximately 1/exp(band gap / kT), where k is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/53702.xml">
Boltzmann's constant</link> and T is absolute temperature.</p>
<p>

The probability of meeting is increased by carrier traps – impurities or dislocations which can trap an electron or hole and hold it until a pair is completed. Such carrier traps are sometimes purposely added to reduce the time needed to reach the steady state.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Doping </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>For more details on this topic, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/860861.xml">
Doping (semiconductor)</link>.</it>
</indent>

The property of semiconductors that makes them most useful for constructing electronic devices is that their conductivity may easily be modified by introducing impurities into their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/58690.xml">
crystal lattice</link>.  The process of adding controlled impurities to a semiconductor is known as <it>doping</it>.  The amount of impurity, or dopant, added to an <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/2245430.xml">
intrinsic</link></it> (pure) semiconductor varies its level of conductivity.  Doped semiconductors are often referred to as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/9512766.xml">
<it>extrinsic''</it></link>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Dopants</st>

<p>

The materials chosen as suitable dopants depend on the atomic properties of both the dopant and the material to be doped.  In general, dopants that produce the desired controlled changes are classified as either electron acceptors or donors.  A donor atom that activates (that is, becomes incorporated into the crystal lattice) donates weakly-bound valence electrons to the material, creating excess negative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/488140.xml">
charge carrier</link>s.  These weakly-bound electrons can move about in the crystal lattice relatively freely and can facilitate conduction in the presence of an electric field. (The donor atoms introduce some states under, but very close to the conduction band edge. Electrons at these states can be easily excited to conduction band, becoming free electrons, at room temperature.)  Conversely, an activated acceptor produces a hole. Semiconductors doped with donor impurities are called <it>n-type</it>, while those doped with acceptor impurities are known as <it>p-type</it>.  The n and p type designations indicate which charge carrier acts as the material's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/488140.xml">
majority carrier</link>.  The opposite carrier is called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/488140.xml">
minority carrier</link>, which exists due to thermal excitation at a much lower concentration compared to the majority carrier.</p>
<p>

For example, the pure semiconductor <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/27114.xml">
silicon</link> has four valence electrons. In silicon, the most common dopants are <link>
IUPAC</link> <group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/144929.xml">
group 13</link></group>
 (commonly known as <it>group III</it>) and <group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/188037.xml">
group 15</link></group>
 (commonly known as <it>group V</it>) elements.  Group 13 elements all contain three valence electrons, causing them to function as acceptors when used to dope silicon.  Group 15 elements have five valence electrons, which allows them to act as a donor.  Therefore, a silicon crystal doped with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/3755.xml">
boron</link> creates a p-type semiconductor whereas one doped with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/23318.xml">
phosphorus</link> results in an n-type material.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Carrier concentration</st>

<p>

The concentration of dopant introduced to an intrinsic semiconductor determines its concentration and indirectly affects many of its electrical properties.  The most important factor that doping directly affects is the material's carrier concentration.  In an intrinsic semiconductor under thermal equilibrium, the concentration of electrons and holes is equivalent.  That is,</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>n = p = n_i</math>
</indent>

If we have a non-intrinsic semiconductor in thermal equilibrium the relation becomes: 
<math>n0*p0 = (n_i)^2</math></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

</indent>
Where <math>n</math> is the concentration of conducting electrons, <math>p</math> is the electron hole concentration, and <math>n_i</math> is the material's intrinsic carrier concentration.  Intrinsic carrier concentration varies between materials and is dependent on temperature.  Silicon's <math>n_i</math>, for example, is roughly 1.6&amp;times;1010 cm-3 at 300 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/19593121.xml">
kelvin</link> (room temperature).</p>
<p>

In general, an increase in doping concentration affords an increase in conductivity due to the higher concentration of carriers available for conduction.  Degenerately (very highly) doped semiconductors have conductivity levels comparable to metals and are often used in modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/15150.xml">
integrated circuit</link>s as a replacement for metal.  Often superscript plus and minus symbols are used to denote relative doping concentration in semiconductors.  For example, <math>n^+</math> denotes an n-type semiconductor with a high, often degenerate, doping concentration.  Similarly, <math>p^-</math> would indicate a very lightly doped p-type material.  It is useful to note that even degenerate levels of doping imply low concentrations of impurities with respect to the base semiconductor.  In crystalline intrinsic silicon, there are approximately 5&amp;times;1022 atoms/cm³.  Doping concentration for silicon semiconductors may range anywhere from 1013 cm-3 to 1018 cm-3.  Doping concentration above about 1018 cm-3 is considered degenerate at room temperature.  Degenerately doped silicon contains a proportion of impurity to silicon in the order of parts per thousand.  This proportion may be reduced to parts per billion in very lightly doped silicon.  Typical concentration values fall somewhere in this range and are tailored to produce the desired properties in the device that the semiconductor is intended for.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Effect on band structure</st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Pn_junction_equilibrium.svg" type="thumb">
</image>

Doping a semiconductor crystal introduces allowed energy states within the band gap but very close to the energy band that corresponds with the dopant type.  In other words, donor impurities create states near the conduction band while acceptors create states near the valence band.  The gap between these energy states and the nearest energy band is usually referred to as dopant-site bonding energy or <math>E_B</math> and is relatively small.  For example, the <math>E_B</math> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/3755.xml">
boron</link> in silicon bulk is 0.045 eV, compared with silicon's band gap of about 1.12 eV.  Because <math>E_B</math> is so small, it takes little energy to ionize the dopant atoms and create free carriers in the conduction or valence bands.  Usually the thermal energy available at room temperature is sufficient to ionize most of the dopant.</p>
<p>

Dopants also have the important effect of shifting the material's Fermi level towards the energy band that corresponds with the dopant with the greatest concentration.  Since the Fermi level must remain constant in a system in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/265823.xml">
thermodynamic equilibrium</link>, stacking layers of materials with different properties leads to many useful electrical properties.  For example, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/571755.xml">
p-n junction</link>'s properties are due to the energy band bending that happens as a result of lining up the Fermi levels in contacting regions of p-type and n-type material.</p>
<p>

This effect is shown in a <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/6917139.xml">
band diagram</link></it>. The band diagram typically indicates the variation in the valence band and conduction band edges versus some spatial dimension, often denoted <it>x</it>. The Fermi energy is also usually indicated in the diagram. Sometimes the <it>intrinsic Fermi energy</it>, <it>Ei</it>, which is the Fermi level in the absence of doping, is shown. These diagrams are useful in explaining the operation of many kinds of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/40344.xml">
semiconductor device</link>s.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Preparation of semiconductor materials</st>
<p>

Semiconductors with predictable, reliable electronic properties are necessary for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/63137.xml">
mass production</link>. The level of chemical purity needed is extremely high because the presence of impurities even in very small proportions can have large effects on the properties of the material. A high degree of crystalline perfection is also required, since faults in crystal structure (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/795334.xml">
dislocation</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/1997989.xml">
twins</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/7849.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Planar+defects%22])">
stacking faults</link>) interfere with the semiconducting properties of the material. Crystalline faults are a major cause of defective semiconductor devices. The larger the crystal, the more difficult it is to achieve the necessary perfection. Current mass production processes use crystal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/335354.xml">
ingots</link> between four and twelve inches (300 mm) in diameter which are grown as cylinders and sliced into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/41860.xml">
wafer</link>s.</p>
<p>

Because of the required level of chemical purity and the perfection of the crystal structure which are needed to make semiconductor devices, special methods have been developed to produce the initial semiconductor material. A technique for achieving high purity includes growing the crystal using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/175039.xml">
Czochralski process</link>. An additional step that can be used to further increase purity is known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/171396.xml">
zone refining</link>. In zone refining, part of a solid crystal is melted. The impurities tend to concentrate in the melted region, while the desired material recrystalizes leaving the solid material more pure and with fewer crystalline faults.</p>
<p>

In manufacturing semiconductor devices involving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/662174.xml">
heterojunction</link>s between different semiconductor materials, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/3263791.xml">
lattice constant</link>, which is the length of the repeating element of the crystal structure, is important for determining the compatibility of materials.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Nuvola_apps_ksim.png">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Electronics&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/156706.xml">
Effective mass</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/706247.xml">
Electronic band structure</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Bloch waves</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/3094328.xml">
Tight-binding model</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/760994.xml">
Electron mobility</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/43597.xml">
Exciton</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/27696.xml">
Semiconductor device fabrication</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/449667.xml">
List of semiconductor materials</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/612813.xml">
Semiconductor industry</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/643769.xml">
Quantum tunneling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/40344.xml">
Semiconductor device</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/66315.xml">
Solid-state chemistry</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/61220.xml">
Spintronics</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/467183.xml">
Wide bandgap semiconductors</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
. They are used in many applications like solar cells. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/14870.xml">
International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry</link>. "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://goldbook.iupac.org/S05591.html">
semiconductor</weblink>". <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/2698988.xml">
Compendium of Chemical Terminology</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it> Internet edition.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Notes</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A. A. Balandin and K. L. Wang (2006), Handbook of Semiconductor Nanostructures and Nanodevices (5-Volume Set), American Scientific Publishers. ISBN 1-58883-073-X</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Muller-1986" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Muller, Richard S.;&#32;Theodore I. Kamins&#32;(1986). Device Electronics for Integrated Circuits, 2d,&#32;New York:&#32;Wiley. ISBN 0-471-88758-7.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book"><physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/2236445.xml">
Sze, Simon M.</link></scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
&#32;(1981). Physics of Semiconductor Devices (2nd ed.).&#32;John Wiley and Sons (WIE). ISBN 0-471-05661-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Turley, Jim&#32;(2002). The Essential Guide to Semiconductors.&#32;Prentice Hall PTR. ISBN 0-13-046404-X.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Yu, Peter Y.; Cardona, Manuel&#32;(2004). Fundamentals of Semiconductors : Physics and Materials Properties.&#32;Springer. ISBN 3-540-41323-5.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ben G. Steetman and Sanjay Kumar Banerjee (2006), Solid State Electronic Devices, Pearson Education Inc. ISBN 0-13-149726-X</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://main.semiconductorforums.com/">
Semiconductor Forum</weblink> Semiconductor Forum for VLSI Enthusiasts</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ilocus.com/commchip1q07.htm">
iLocus Report on Communications Chip Market 1Q07: Published May 2007</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.newark.com/semiconductors-prototyping">
Newark - Source for Semiconductors and Prototyping </weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://science.howstuffworks.com/diode.htm">
Howstuffworks' semiconductor page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/solids/semcn.html">
Semiconductor Concepts at Hyperphysics</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Semiconductor OneSource <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.semi1source.com/shof/">
Hall of Fame</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.semiconductorglossary.com/">
Glossary</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ece-www.colorado.edu/~bart/book/book/">
Principles of Semiconductor Devices</weblink> by Bart Van Zeghbroeck, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/289672.xml">
University of Colorado</link></university>
. An online textbook</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tpub.com/content/neets/14179/index.htm">
US Navy Electrical Engineering Training Series</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iop.org/EJ/journal/SST">
Institute of Physics "Semiconductor Science and Technology" Journal</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ioffe.rssi.ru/SVA/NSM/Semicond/index.html">
NSM-Archive</weblink> Physical Properties of Semiconductors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.semineedle.com">
Semineedle</weblink> Semiconductor Community</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.semi-directory.com">
Semi-Directory</weblink> Semiconductor resource center and industry events calendar</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
General subfields within <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/22939.xml">
physics</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/361897.xml">
Astrophysics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/48579.xml">
Atomic, molecular, and optical physics</link>&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/5387.xml">
Condensed matter physics</link></concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/226020.xml">
Dynamics</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/11034.xml">
Fluid dynamics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/29952.xml">
Thermodynamics</link>) &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/9532.xml">
Electromagnetism</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/22483.xml">
Optics</link>)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/23259.xml">
High energy physics</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/19559.xml">
Mechanics</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/19555586.xml">
Classical&nbsp;mechanics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
Quantum mechanics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/28481.xml">
Statistical mechanics</link>)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/30001.xml">
Relativity</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/26962.xml">
Special relativity</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/12024.xml">
General relativity</link>)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/25267.xml">
Quantum field theory</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/28767.xml">
Statics</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/527232.xml">
Fluid statics</link>)</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</concept>
</article>
