<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:42:48[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Predictive dialer</title>
<id>277163</id>
<revision>
<id>244529402</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T07:34:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Unara</username>
<id>7759275</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Telemarketing</category>
<category>Telephony</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>predictive dialer</b> is a computerized system that automatically dials batches of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/18790468.xml">
telephone number</link>s for connection to agents assigned to sales or other campaigns. Predictive dialers are widely used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/7243.xml">
call center</link>s.
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/179958.xml">
autodialer</link> preceded the predictive dialer. While the basic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/179958.xml">
autodialer</link> merely automatically dials telephone numbers for call center agents who are idle or waiting for a call, the predictive dialer uses a variety of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s to predict both the availability of agents and called party answers, adjusting the calling process to the number of agents it predicts will be available when the calls it places are expected to be answered.</p>
<p>

The predictive dialer monitors the answers to the calls it places, detecting how the calls it makes are answered. It discards unanswered calls, busy numbers, disconnected lines, answers from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/10826.xml">
fax machine</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/254857.xml">
answering machine</link>s and similar automated services, and only connects calls answered by people to waiting sales representatives. Thus, it frees agents from the task of manually dialing telephone numbers and subsequently listening to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/231463.xml">
ring tone</link>s, unanswered or unsuccessful calls. </p>
<p>

A predictive dialer can dramatically increase the time an agent spends on communication rather than waiting; a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/35502.xml">
2002</link> survey indicated an increase in talk time from twenty minutes in the hour to almost fifty. The system is most suitable for low quality lists and large numbers of agents; however, an unexpectedly high contact rate can overwhelm the system leading to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/2482814.xml">
call abandonment</link>.</p>
<p>

Call list is the data loaded to the dialer before commencing a campaign. The data is generally derived from a large database such as a telephone directory or similar listing from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/6968.xml">
CRM</link> software. Some predictive dialers generate call lists and report call attempts. Unsuccessful calls are often analyzed to determine if the number called needs to be called back later or needs special treatment, such as a manual or autodialed call by an agent to listen to an answer machine message.</p>
<p>

Predictive dialer systems are commonly used by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/162180.xml">
telemarketing</link> organizations involved in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/3696159.xml">
B2C</link> (business to consumer) calling as it allows their sales representatives to have much more customer contact time. Predictive dialers may also be used by market survey companies and debt collection services who need to contact and personally speak to a lot of people by telephone. More commonly predictive dialers are now being used as a quick and easy way to automate all sorts of calls which would otherwise be made manually by a call center, such as welcome calls for new customers, customer service call backs, appointment confirmations/reminders, or even for the automation of large numbers of ad hoc calls that might need to take place (such as by a taxi company, or parcel delivery service etc). </p>
<p>

They generally rely on the fact that if a person were to sit down and manually dial 1000 people, a large percentage of these calls will not result in contact with someone at the other end. Out of 1000 calls made, typically only about 25-35% would actually connect to a live person. Of the rest, a large number (often 40-60%) won't be answered at all, around 10% might be answering machines, faxes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/19443900.xml">
modem</link>s or other electronic devices, around 5% of numbers would be busy and the rest will result in network errors, or be identified as invalid numbers. For call centers that need to make large numbers of outbound calls, this represents a large problem. Typically in manual dialing environments, a given agent will spend around 80% of their time listening to the phone ring waiting to talk to someone, or dealing with invalid numbers or answering machines and only about 20% of their time actually doing what they are really there to do. By using a predictive dialer to filter out these unproductive calls and to spare the agent from having to wait for the phone to be answered each time, call centers can reverse the situation. Agents can now spend on average around 80% of their time talking to customers and only about 20% of their time waiting for the next call - a 300% increase in productivity.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Functioning</st>
<p>

The predictive dialer exhibits predictive behavior when its dialing algorithm produces more call attempts (dials) than the number of agents currently logged in and available to handle calls. The predictive dialing happens when the predictive dialer <it>dials ahead</it> of the agents becoming available or when the predictive dialer <it>matches</it> a forecast number of available agents with a forecast number of available called parties. The matching and dialing ahead perspectives provide the large increases in dial rates and agent productivity.</p>
<p>

If a system has 100 agents working on it, the dialer will dial a number of calls sometimes crudely based on a phone line to agent ratio of 1.5:1 or 2:1. This means that for each available agent, the system will dial the phone numbers of two potential customers. As these calls are made to the telephone network, the dialer will monitor each call and determine what the outcome of the call was. From 150 calls made, the system will immediately strip out any unproductive outcomes, such as busy calls (these are usually queued for automatic redial), no answers &amp; invalid numbers. Some predictive dialers incorporate "answering machine detection", which tries to determine if a live person or answering machine picked up the phone. This is one cause of the typical delays that one may experience before being connected to an agent.</p>
<p>

If not enough calls are made ahead, agents will sit idle, whereas if there are too many calls made and there are not enough agents to handle them, then the call is typically <it>dropped</it>. A sophisticated system will throttle calls more appropriately to deal with these situations.</p>
<p>

The advanced predictive dialer determines and uses many operating characteristics that it learns during the calling campaign and adjusts automatically to the behaviour of an ongoing campaign. Examples of such statistics include call connection rates (both current and average for recent past days by hour of the day), average agent connection time, geographic location dialed, etc. It uses these statistics continually to make sophisticated predictions so as to minimize agent idle time while controlling occurrences of nuisance calls, which are answered calls without the immediate benefit of available agents. An advanced predictive dialer can readily maintain the ratio of nuisance calls to answered calls at less than a fraction of one percent while still dialing ahead. However, this level of performance may require a sufficiently large critical mass of agents. Conversely, it becomes increasingly difficult to maintain a high talk time percentage with a lower number of agents without increasing dropped calls.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Silent calls</st>
<p>

Predictive dialing systems use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s to control the ratio of calls to agents. Because a dialer cannot know what proportion of its calls will connect until it has made them, it will alter its dialing rate depending on how many connections it manages to achieve. Occasionally, the system will get more live parties on call attempts than there are agents available to take those calls. Consequently, the dialer will disconnect or delay distribution of calls that cannot be distributed to an agent. This is known as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/2482814.xml">
silent call</link> or a nuisance call. The called party hears only silence when the predictive dialer does not at least play a recorded message.</p>
<p>

The experience for those who receive a predictive dialer call can be less satisfactory. There may be an appreciable period of silence before a call is routed to a sales representative. This annoys people and also gives them a chance to hang up. If no sales representative is available for a successful call, it is often disconnected. In certain countries, this disconnection is a breach of regulatory codes, and most countries now regulate limits on the number of silent calls that a company makes within a certain time frame. In the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
UK</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
USA</link>, these silent calls have caused concern and outrage amongst the public, and strict regulations now govern how these systems may be used, with threats of large fines for companies that abuse these systems. Currently, in the UK, a maximum of 3% of the calls made may be "dropped," which is why call centers have to be very careful about their procedures.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Types</st>
<p>

Predictive dialers perform the same function but the architecture and delivery methods can vary greatly between manufacturers. There are several types of predictive dialing: <it>Software</it>,  <it>Hardware</it>, <it>Smart</it>, and <it>Hosted</it> dialers. </p>
<p>

In recent years, 'mixed' type predictive dialers have emerged. These predictive dialers are based on simpler hardware, such as voice modems, and more powerful software for answering machine detection and call progress detection. The biggest advantage of this type of predictive dialers is the substantially lower cost of ownership. Another form of predictive dialer has evolved: the so-called 'smart' predictive dialer combining voice broadcasting and attendant phone agents. Hosted predictive dialing is a service provided by third party providers that connects calls via the internet to agents.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Soft dialers</st>
<p>

Software-only solutions use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/15231.xml">
ISDN</link> messaging, or a <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="105849040" confidence="0.8">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/162190.xml">
CTI</link></feature>
</property>
</concept>
</idea>
 link to provide call progress analysis for calls made. Software-only dialers are often cheaper because they do not require expensive telephony components, but may offer less functionality than more traditional 'hard dialer' solutions, particularly when it comes to detecting answering machines (AMD) and integration with other 'voice' related functions (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/2417230.xml">
voice recording</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/162186.xml">
IVR</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/29468.xml">
speech recognition</link>, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/42799.xml">
text-to-speech</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
 etc.). Typically, a software dialer is connected to an existing <point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<geographic_point wordnetid="108578706" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<workplace wordnetid="104602044" confidence="0.8">
<central wordnetid="102994858" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/24004.xml">
PBX</link></central>
</workplace>
</location>
</geographic_point>
</point>
 system via the PBX CTI link. In most cases, expensive specialized 'call classification' cards are required in the PBX for call progress analysis and answering machine detection. Open Source dialers have proven themselves in the production world and enable call centers of all sizes to lower costs. Other advantages include customization of the software suites to meet the needs on an individual basis.</p>
<p>

Pros:   
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Low cost without consideration of sunk costs of a fully-provisioned PBX</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Flexible architecture works well in multi-site and distributed environments</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Cons: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A few older PBXs will not work with a soft dialer configuration</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Higher error rates in classification of calls (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/10826.xml">
Fax</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/19443900.xml">
modem</link>, etc. have to be detected by the agent)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lower call-processing capacity</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hard dialers</st>
<p>

Hardware dialers use dedicated telephony boards to perform call progress analysis and answering machine detection. Those switches usually have two main types of connections: agent audio and external audio. The agent audio connections are usually simple T1/E1/ISDN etc. telephony spans which are connected directly to an existing PBX (although other connection types that do not require a PBX are available such as Analogue or VoIP connections). When an agent first logs in for the day, the dialer will place a call from the switch directly to the phone on the agent's desk. This open phone call between the agent and the dialer switch is then kept open for the duration of the session. The second type of connection is the external audio connection which is the connection that will be used to make outbound phone calls. These connections are typically ISDN/T1/E1 connections direct to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/468436.xml">
PSTN</link>. When an outbound call is made and answered, the call is immediately joined to an already open agent audio connection of the agent selected to take the call.   </p>
<p>

Pros:   
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fewer telephony connections required (In hard dialers external audio connections can go directly to the PSTN)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dialer typically will not need upgrading in line with PBX/CTI etc.; since standard telephony connections are the only link between the PBX and the dialer, the dialer is less affected by software changes/versions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Superior answering machine and call progress detection capability</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Remote agent capabilities - hard dialers can connect to any phone, anywhere on the PSTN. (Highly suitable for home working or remote sites)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Independent of special CTI communication and proprietary PBX protocols</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Independent of PBX (Can work with a PBX or without benefit of any PBX or ACD)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Higher capacity for handling calls (up to about 100,000 calls per hour) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Faster call switching, as both ends of the call are already in place.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Cons:   
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 More expensive than a soft dialer when the enterprise already has a PBX with spare capacity for processing calls.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Increased cost of ownership as expensive to upgrade and maintain. </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Smart predictive dialers</st>
<p>

Smart predictive dialers combine <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/179958.xml">
auto dialing</link> with voice messaging and phone agents who are prepared to handle calls initiated by the dialer. Answering machines, busy signals, and unanswered calls are processed in a manner similar to that of a normal predictive dialing system. However, when a 'live' answer is detected, the dialer plays an introductory recorded message, giving the call recipient the option to talk with an agent to complete the transaction. This message is a consistent greeting that identifies the caller, the nature of the call, and the option to speak with an agent. This process requires a more sophisticated predictive algorithm to ensure that a phone agent is available when the call recipient asks to speak with an agent.  </p>
<p>

Pros:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Call lists are pre-qualified without the need for an agent</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Call lists are processed much more quickly and efficiently</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fewer agents are required to handle far more calls</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Agents are only speaking with interested callers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Call list processing is far less expensive</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Cons:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Overall list performance may be less due to call recipient resistance to recorded messages</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Certain U.S. states do not allow recorded messaging (unless prior business relationship has been established). This may limit the use of this technique to only certain types of business or consumer campaigns in certain geographical areas.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Illegal in the UK unless you have received prior permission from the people you are calling</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hosted predictive dialers</st>
<p>

Hosted predictive dialers (aka Virtual Predictive Dialers, Web-Enabled Predictive Dialers, VoIP Predictive Dialers) use the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/2262333.xml">
Software as a Service</link> (SaaS) model to provide organizations and individuals with a predictive dialer capability. Typically, the only requirement for a firm to use a hosted predictive dialer system is a computer with an Internet connection and a telephone line for each agent. </p>
<p>

Pros:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 No required investments in computer or telephone hardware </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 No required investments in software or licenses </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Administration and support are handled by the service provider</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Links into the system are remote, enabling agents and supervisors to connect from any location</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Software updates and upgrades included. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Cons:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Service is dependent on an internet connection; when the internet goes down, so does the service</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Providers using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
VoIP</link> as their primary delivery method experience limited reliability and performance</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Often far more limited in capability than an "On Site" product.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hybrid predictive dialers</st>
<p>

Hybrid predictive dialers are basically soft dialers that rely on a hosted VOIP service for calls. Unlike soft dialers, a hybrid dialer does not connect to an existing PBX system. Instead, it connects to a VOIP service provider through internet connections.</p>
<p>

Pros:   
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 All advantages offered by soft dialers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 All advantages offered by hosted dialers</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Cons:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lower call-processing capacity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Service is dependent on an internet connection; when the internet goes down, so does the service</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/162180.xml">
Telemarketing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/1298689.xml">
Do Not Call Registry</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/375271.xml">
Dialer</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="105849040" confidence="0.8">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/162190.xml">
Computer telephony integration</link></feature>
</property>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/665239.xml">
Direct marketing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/215288.xml">
Wardialer</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
