<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:34:54[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Supply chain management</title>
<id>27995</id>
<revision>
<id>244590235</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T16:22:32Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mufka</username>
<id>2742610</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Supply chain management</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing copy edit from October 2007</category>
<category>Supply chain management terms</category>
<category>Distribution, retailing, and wholesaling</category>
<category>Management</category>
<category>All articles needing copy edit</category>
<category>Commercial item transport and distribution</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Production and manufacturing</category>
<category>Marketing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="500px" src="A_company's_supply_chain_(en).png" type="thumb">
<caption>

An illustration of a company's supply chain; the arrows stand für supplier-relationship management, internal SCM and customer-relationship management (cf. Chen/Paulraj, 2004)
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Supply chain management (SCM)</b> is the process of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/378010.xml">
planning</link>, implementing and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/491900.xml">
controlling</link> the operations of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/186493.xml">
supply chain</link> as efficiently as possible. Supply Chain Management spans all movement and storage of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/216167.xml">
raw material</link>s, work-in-process inventory, and finished goods from point-of-origin to point-of-consumption.</p>
<p>

<table style="clear: right; margin-bottom: .5em; float: right; padding: .5em 0 .8em 1.4em; background: none; width: auto;" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>
__TOC__</col>
</row>
</table>

The definition one American professional association put forward is that Supply Chain Management encompasses the planning and management of all activities involved in sourcing, procurement, conversion, and logistics management activities. Importantly, it also includes coordination and collaboration with <link>
channel partner</link>s, which can be suppliers, intermediaries, third-party service providers, and customers. In essence, Supply Chain Management integrates <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/29664.xml">
supply and demand</link> management within and across companies. More recently, the loosely coupled, self-organizing network of businesses that cooperates to provide product and service offerings has been called the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/16845449.xml">
Extended Enterprise</link></it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Supply Chain Management can also refer to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/11980289.xml">
Supply chain management software</link> which are tools or modules used in executing supply chain transactions, managing supplier relationships and controlling associated business processes. </p>
<p>

Supply chain event management (abbreviated as SCEM) is a consideration of all possible occurring events and factors that can cause a disruption in a supply chain. With SCEM possible scenarios can be created and solutions can be planned.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Supply Chain Management Problems </st>
<p>

Supply chain management must address the following problems:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/239863.xml">
Distribution</link> Network Configuration: Number, location and network missions of suppliers, production facilities, distribution centers, warehouses, cross-docks and customers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Distribution <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/29607.xml">
Strategy</link>: Including questions of operating control (centralized, decentralized or shared); delivery scheme (e.g., direct shipment, pool point shipping, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/826311.xml">
Cross docking</link>, DSD (direct store delivery), closed loop shipping); mode of transportation (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/8261759.xml">
motor carrier</link>, including truckload, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/2471085.xml">
LTL</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/1196735.xml">
parcel</link>; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/25715.xml">
railroad</link>; intermodal, including TOFC and COFC; ocean freight; airfreight); replenishment strategy (e.g., pull, push or hybrid); and transportation control (e.g., owner-operated, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/6742891.xml">
private carrier</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/40910.xml">
common carrier</link>, contract carrier, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/2105986.xml">
3PL</link>).  Trade-Offs in Logistical Activities </entry>
</list>

The above activities must be coordinated well together in order to achieve the least total logistics cost. Trade-offs exist that increase the total cost if only one of the activities is optimized. For example, full truckload (FTL) rates are more economical on a cost per pallet basis than less than truckload (LTL) shipments. If, however, a full truckload of a product is ordered to reduce transportation costs there will be an increase in inventory holding costs which may increase total logistics costs. It is therefore imperative to take a systems approach when planning logistical activities. These trade-offs are key to developing the most efficient and effective Logistics and SCM strategy.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Information: Integration of and other processes through the supply chain to share valuable information, including demand signals, forecasts, inventory, transportation, and potential collaboration etc.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/182655.xml">
Inventory</link> Management: Quantity and location of inventory including raw materials, work-in-process and finished goods.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cash-Flow: Arranging the payment terms and the methodologies for exchanging funds across entities within the supply chain.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Supply chain execution is managing and coordinating the movement of materials, information and funds across the supply chain. The flow is bi-directional.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Activities/functions </st>
<p>

Supply chain management is a cross-functional approach to manage the movement of raw materials into an organization, certain aspects of the internal processing of materials into finished goods, and then the movement of finished goods out of the organization toward the end-consumer.  As organizations strive to focus on core competencies and becoming more flexible, they have reduced their ownership of raw materials sources and distribution channels. These functions are increasingly being outsourced to other entities that can perform the activities better or more cost effectively. The effect is to increase the number of organizations involved in satisfying customer demand, while reducing management control of daily logistics operations. Less control and more supply chain partners led to the creation of supply chain management concepts. The purpose of supply chain management is to improve trust and collaboration among supply chain partners, thus improving inventory visibility and improving inventory velocity. </p>
<p>

Several models have been proposed for understanding the activities required to manage material movements across organizational and functional boundaries. SCOR is a supply chain management model promoted by the Supply Chain Management Council. Another model is the SCM Model proposed by the Global Supply Chain Forum (GSCF). Supply chain activities can be grouped into strategic, tactical, and operational levels of activities.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Strategic </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Strategic network optimization, including the number, location, and size of warehouses, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/1525255.xml">
distribution center</link>s and facilities.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Strategic partnership] with suppliers, distributors, and customers, creating communication channels for critical information and operational improvements such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/826311.xml">
cross docking</link>, direct shipping, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/2105986.xml">
third-party logistics</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/999536.xml">
Product design</link> coordination, so that new and existing products can be optimally integrated into the supply chain, load management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
Information Technology</link> infrastructure, to support supply chain operations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Where-to-make and what-to-make-or-buy decisions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Aligning overall organizational strategy with supply strategy.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Tactical </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sourcing contracts and other purchasing decisions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Production decisions, including contracting, scheduling, and planning process definition.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Inventory decisions, including quantity, location, and quality of inventory. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Transportation strategy, including frequency, routes, and contracting.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/223063.xml">
Benchmarking</link> of all operations against competitors and implementation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/805228.xml">
best practice</link>s throughout the enterprise.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Milestone payments</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Focus on customer demand.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Operational </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Daily production and distribution planning, including all nodes in the supply chain.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Production scheduling for each manufacturing facility in the supply chain (minute by minute).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Demand planning and forecasting, coordinating the demand forecast of all customers and sharing the forecast with all suppliers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sourcing planning, including current inventory and forecast demand, in collaboration with all suppliers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Inbound operations, including transportation from suppliers and receiving inventory.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Production operations, including the consumption of materials and flow of finished goods.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Outbound operations, including all fulfillment activities and transportation to customers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Order promising, accounting for all constraints in the supply chain, including all suppliers, manufacturing facilities, distribution centers, and other customers...</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Supply chain management </st>
<p>

Organizations increasingly find that they must rely on effective supply chains, or networks, to successfully compete in the global market and networked economy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> In Peter Drucker's (1998) management's new paradigms, this concept of business relationships extends beyond traditional enterprise boundaries and seeks to organize entire business processes throughout a value chain of multiple companies.</p>
<p>

During the past decades, globalization, outsourcing and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
information technology</link> have enabled many organizations, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/102490.xml">
Dell</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/13973.xml">
Hewlett Packard</link>, to successfully operate solid collaborative supply networks in which each specialized business partner focuses on only a few key strategic activities (Scott, 1993).  This inter-organizational supply network can be acknowledged as a new form of organization. However, with the complicated interactions among the players, the network structure fits neither "market" nor "hierarchy" categories (Powell, 1990). It is not clear what kind of performance impacts that different supply network structures could have on firms, and little is known about the coordination conditions and trade-offs that may exist among the players.
From a system's point of view, a complex network structure can be decomposed into individual component firms (Zhang and Dilts, 2004). Traditionally, companies in a supply network concentrate on the inputs and outputs of the processes, with little concern for the internal management working of other individual players. Therefore, the choice of an internal management control structure is known to impact local firm performance (Mintzberg, 1979).</p>
<p>

In the 21st century, there have been a few changes in business environment that have contributed to the development of supply chain networks. First, as an outcome of globalization and the proliferation of multi-national companies, joint ventures, strategic alliances and business partnerships, there were found to be significant success factors, following the earlier "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/218426.xml">
Just-In-Time</link>", "Lean Management" and "Agile Manufacturing" practices.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Second, technological changes, particularly the dramatic fall in information communication costs, which are a paramount component of transaction costs, have led to changes in coordination among the members of the supply chain network (Coase, 1998).</p>
<p>

Many researchers have recognized these kinds of supply network structures as a new organization form, using terms such as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/17467.xml">
Keiretsu</link>", "Extended Enterprise", "Virtual Corporation", "Global Production Network", and "Next Generation Manufacturing System".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> In general, such a structure can be defined as "a group of semi-independent organizations, each with their capabilities, which collaborate in ever-changing constellations to serve one or more markets in order to achieve some business goal specific to that collaboration" (Akkermans, 2001).</p>
<p>

The security management system for supply chain is described in ISO/IEC 28000 and ISO/IEC 28001 and related standards published jointly by ISO and IEC.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Developments in Supply Chain Management </st>
<p>

Six major movements can be observed in the evolution of supply chain management studies: Creation, Integration, and Globalization (Lavassani et al., 2008a), Specialization Phases One and Two, and SCM 2.0.</p>
<p>

<b>1. Creation Era</b></p>
<p>

The term supply chain management was first coined by an American industry consultant in the early 1980s. However
the concept of supply chain in management, was of great importance long before in the early 20th century, especially by the creation of the assembly line. The characteristics of this era of supply chain management include the need for large scale changes, reengineering, downsizing driven by cost reduction programs, and widespread attention to the Japanese practice of management.</p>
<p>

<b>2. Integration Era</b> </p>
<p>

This era of supply chain management studies was highlighted with the development of Electronic Data Interchange (EDI) systems in the 1960s and developed through the 1990s by the introduction of Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP) systems. This era has continued to develop into the 21st century with the expansion of internet-based collaborative systems. This era of SC evolution is characterized by both increasing value-added and cost reduction through integration. </p>
<p>

<b>3. Globalization Era</b></p>
<p>

The third movement of supply chain management development, globalization era, can be characterized by the attention towards global systems of supplier relations and the expansion of supply chain over national boundaries and into other continents. Although the use of global sources in the supply chain of organizations can be traced back to several decades ago (e.g. the oil industry), it was not until the late 1980s that a considerable number of organizations started to integrate global sources into their core business. This era is characterized by the globalization of supply chain management in organizations with the goal of increasing competitive advantage, creating more value-added, and reducing costs through global sourcing.</p>
<p>

<b>4. Specialization Era -- Phase One -- Outsourced Manufacturing and Distribution</b></p>
<p>

In the 1990s industries began to focus on “core competencies” and adopted a specialization model. Companies abandoned vertical integration, sold off non-core operations, and outsourced those functions to other companies. This changed management requirements by extending the supply chain well beyond the four walls and distributing management across specialized supply chain partnerships.</p>
<p>

This transition also refocused the fundamental perspectives of each respective organization. OEMs became brand owners that needed deep visibility into their supply base. They had to control the entire supply chain from above instead of from within. Contract manufacturers had to manage bills of material with different part numbering schemes from multiple OEMs and support customer requests for work -in-process visibility and vendor-managed inventory (VMI). </p>
<p>

The specialization model creates manufacturing and distribution networks composed of multiple, individual supply chains specific to products, suppliers, and customers who work together to design, manufacture, distribute, market, sell, and service a product. The set of partners may change according to a given market, region, or channel, resulting in a proliferation of trading partner environments, each with its own unique characteristics and demands.</p>
<p>

<b>5. Specialization Era -- Phase Two -- Supply Chain Management as a Service</b></p>
<p>

Specialization within the supply chain began in the 1980s with the inception of transportation brokerages, warehouse management, and non asset based carriers and has matured beyond transportation and logistics into aspects of supply planning, collaboration, execution and performance management.  </p>
<p>

At any given moment, market forces could demand changes within suppliers, logistics providers, locations, customers and any number of these specialized participants within  supply chain networks. This variability has significant effect on the supply chain infrastructure, from the foundation layers of establishing and managing the electronic communication between the trading partners to the more-complex requirements, including the configuration of the processes and work flows that are essential to the management of the network itself.</p>
<p>

Supply chain specialization enables companies to improve their overall competencies in the same way that outsourced manufacturing and distribution has done; it allows them to focus on their core competencies and assemble networks of best in class domain specific partners to contribute to the overall value chain itself – thus increasing overall performance and efficiency. The ability to quickly obtain and deploy this domain specific supply chain expertise without developing and maintaining an entirely unique and complex competency in house is the leading reason why supply chain specialization is gaining popularity. </p>
<p>

Outsourced technology hosting for supply chain solutions debuted in the late 1990s and has taken root in transportation and collaboration categories most dominantly.  This has progressed from the Application Service Provider (ASP) model from approximately 1998 through 2003 to the On-Demand model from approximately 2003-2006 to the Software as a Service (SaaS) model we are currently focused on today.</p>
<p>

<b>6. Supply Chain Management 2.0 (SCM 2.0)</b></p>
<p>

Building off of globalization and specialization, SCM 2.0 has been coined to describe both the changes within the supply chain itself as well as the evolution of the processes, methods and tools that manage it in this new "era".  </p>
<p>

Web 2.0 is defined as a trend in the use of the World Wide Web that is meant to increase creativity, information sharing, and collaboration among users.  At its core, the common attribute that Web 2.0 brings is it helps us navigate the vast amount of information available on the web to find what we are looking for. It is the notion of a usable pathway.  SCM 2.0 follows this notion into supply chain operations.  It is the pathway to SCM results – the combination of the processes, methodologies, tools and delivery options to guide companies to their results quickly as the complexity and speed of the supply chain increase due to the effects of  global competition, rapid price commoditization, surging oil prices, short product life cycles, expanded specialization, near/far and off shoring, and talent scarcity. </p>
<p>

SCM 2.0 leverages proven solutions designed to rapidly deliver results with the agility to quickly manage future change for continuous flexibility, value and success. This is delivered through competency networks composed of best of breed supply chain domain expertise to understand which elements, both operationally and organizationally, are the critical few that deliver the results as well as the intimate understanding of how to manage these elements to achieve desired results, finally the solutions are delivered in a variety of options as no-touch via business process outsourcing, mid-touch via managed services and software as a service (SaaS), or high touch in the traditional software deployment model.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Supply chain business process integration </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="30px" src="Acap.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  for  grammar, style, cohesion, tone or spelling.</b>
You can assist by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Supply_chain_management&amp;action=edit">
editing it</weblink> now. A how-to is available.<it>&nbsp;(October 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


Successful SCM requires a change from managing individual functions to integrating activities into key supply chain processes. An example scenario: the purchasing department places orders as requirements become appropriate. Marketing, responding to customer demand, communicates with several distributors and retailers as it attempts to satisfy this demand. Shared information between supply chain partners can only be fully leveraged through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/8642567.xml">
process integration</link>.</p>
<p>

Supply chain business process integration involves collaborative work between buyers and suppliers, joint product development, common systems and shared information. According to Lambert and Cooper (2000) operating an integrated supply chain requires continuous information flow.
However, in many companies, management has reached the conclusion that optimizing  the product flows cannot be accomplished without implementing a process approach to the business. The key supply chain processes stated by Lambert (2004) <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> are:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/6968.xml">
Customer relationship management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Customer service management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Demand management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Order fulfillment</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Manufacturing flow management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Supplier relationship management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Product development and commercialization</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Returns management</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

One could suggest other key critical supply business processes combining these processes stated by Lambert such as:</p>

<p>

Customer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/909187.xml">
service management</link>
Procurement
Product development and commercialization
Manufacturing flow management/support
Physical distribution
Outsourcing/partnerships
Performance measurement</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

a) Customer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/909187.xml">
service management</link> process:</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Customer Relationship Management concerns the relationship between the organization and its customers. Customer service provides the source of customer information. It also provides the customer with real-time information on promising dates and product availability through interfaces with the company's production and distribution operations. Successful organizations use following steps to build customer relationships:
determine mutually satisfying goals between organization and customers
establish and maintain customer rapport
produce positive feelings in the organization and the customers</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

b) Procurement process: </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Strategic plans are developed with suppliers to support the manufacturing flow management process and development of new products. In firms where operations extend globally, sourcing should be managed on a global basis. The desired outcome is a win-win relationship, where both parties benefit, and reduction times in the design cycle and product development are achieved. Also, the purchasing function develops rapid communication systems, such as electronic data interchange (EDI) and Internet linkages to transfer possible requirements more rapidly. Activities related to obtaining products and materials from outside suppliers requires performing resource planning, supply sourcing, negotiation, order placement, inbound transportation, storage, handling and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/305224.xml">
quality assurance</link>, many of which include the responsibility to coordinate with suppliers in scheduling, supply continuity, hedging, and research into new sources or programmes.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

c) Product development and commercialization: </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Here, customers and suppliers must be united into the product development process, thus to reduce time to market. As product life cycles shorten, the appropriate products must be developed and successfully launched in ever shorter time-schedules to remain competitive. According to Lambert and Cooper (2000), managers of the product development and commercialization process must:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 coordinate with customer relationship management to identify customer-articulated needs;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 select materials and suppliers in conjunction with procurement, and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 develop production technology in manufacturing flow to manufacture and integrate into the best supply chain flow for the product/market combination.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

d) Manufacturing flow management process: </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The manufacturing process is produced and supplies products to the distribution channels based on past forecasts. Manufacturing processes must be flexible to respond to market changes, and must accommodate mass customization. Orders are processes operating on a just-in-time (JIT) basis in minimum lot sizes. Also, changes in the manufacturing flow process lead to shorter cycle times, meaning improved responsiveness and efficiency of demand to customers. Activities related to planning, scheduling and supporting manufacturing operations, such as work-in-process storage, handling, transportation, and time phasing of components, inventory at manufacturing sites and maximum flexibility in the coordination of geographic and final assemblies postponement of physical distribution operations.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

e) Physical distribution: </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This concerns movement of a finished product/service to customers. In physical distribution, the customer is the final destination of a marketing channel, and the availability of the product/service is a vital part of each channel participant's marketing effort. It is also through the physical distribution process that the time and space of customer service become an integral part of marketing, thus it links a marketing channel with its customers (e.g. links manufacturers, wholesalers, retailers). </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

f) Outsourcing/partnerships: </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This is not just outsourcing the procurement of materials and components, but also outsourcing of services
that traditionally have been provided in-house. The logic of this trend is that the company will increasingly 
focus on those activities in the value chain where it has a distinctive advantage and everything else it will
outsource. This movement has been particularly evident in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/77547.xml">
logistics</link> where the provision of transport, 
warehousing and inventory control is increasingly subcontracted to specialists or logistics partners. Also, to
manage and control this network of partners and suppliers requires a blend of both central and local involvement. Hence, strategic decisions need to be taken centrally with the monitoring and control of supplier performance and day-to-day liaison with logistics partners being best managed at a local level.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

g) Performance measurement: </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Experts found a strong relationship from the largest arcs of supplier and customer integration to market share and profitability. By taking advantage of supplier capabilities and emphasizing a long-term supply chain perspective in customer relationships can be both correlated with firm performance. As logistics competency becomes a more critical factor in creating and maintaining competitive advantage, logistics measurement becomes increasingly important because the difference between profitable and unprofitable operations becomes more narrow. A.T. Kearney Consultants (1985) noted that firms engaging in comprehensive performance measurement realized improvements in overall productivity. According to experts internal measures are generally collected and analyzed by the firm including 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Cost</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Customer Service</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Productivity measures</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Asset measurement, and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Quality.</entry>
</list>

External performance measurement is examined through customer perception measures and "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/805228.xml">
best practice</link>" benchmarking, and includes 1) customer perception measurement, and 2) best practice benchmarking.
Components of Supply Chain Management are 
1. Standardization 
2. Postponement 
3. Customization</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Theories of Supply Chain Management </st>

<p>

Currently there exists a gap in the literature available in the area of supply chain management studies, on providing theoretical support for explaining the existence and the boundaries of supply chain management. Few authors such as Halldorsson, et al. (2003), Ketchen and Hult (2006) and Lavassani, et al. (2008b) had tried to provide theoretical foundations for different areas related to supply chain with employing organizational theories. These theories includes:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Resource-based view (RBV)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Transaction Cost Analysis (TCA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Knowledge-based view (KBV)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Strategic Choice Theory (SCT)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Agency theory (AT)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Institutional theory  (InT)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Systems Theory (ST)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Network Perspective (NP)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Components of Supply Chain Management Integration </st>

<p>

<b>The management components of SCM</b></p>
<p>

The SCM components are the third element of the four-square circulation framework. The level of integration and management of a business process link is a function of the number and level, ranging from low to high, of components added to the link (Ellram and Cooper, 1990; Houlihan, 1985). Consequently, adding more management components or increasing the level of each component can increase the level of integration of the business process link.
The literature on business process reengineering,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> buyer-supplier relationships,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> and SCM<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> suggests various possible components that must receive managerial attention when managing supply relationships. Lambert and Cooper (2000) identified the following components which are: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Planning and control</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Work structure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Organization structure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Product flow facility structure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Information flow facility structure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Management methods</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Power and leadership structure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Risk and reward structure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

	Culture and attitude</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

However, a more careful examination of the existing literature<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> will lead us to a more comprehensive structure of what should be the key critical supply chain components, the "branches" of the previous identified supply chain business processes, that is, what kind of relationship the components may have that are related with suppliers and customers accordingly. Bowersox and Closs states that the emphasis on cooperation represents the synergism leading to the highest level of joint achievement (Bowersox and Closs, 1996). A primary level channel participant is a business that is willing to participate in the inventory ownership responsibility or assume other aspects of financial risk, thus including primary level components (Bowersox and Closs, 1996). A secondary level participant (specialized), is a business that participates in channel relationships by performing essential services for primary participants, thus including secondary level components, which are in support of primary participants.  Third level channel participants and components that will support the primary level channel participants, and which are the fundamental branches of the secondary level components, may also be included.</p>
<p>

Consequently,  Lambert and Cooper's  framework of supply chain components does not lead us to the conclusion about what are the primary or secondary (specialized) level supply chain components (see Bowersox and Closs, 1996, p.g. 93). That is, what supply chain components should be viewed as primary or secondary, how these components should be structured in order to have a more comprehensive supply chain structure, and to examine the supply chain as an integrative one (See above sections 2.1 and 3.1).</p>
<p>

Baziotopoulos reviewed the literature to identify supply chain components.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>  Based on this study, Baziotopoulos (2004) suggests the following supply chain components:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 For <b>customer service management</b>: Includes the primary level component of customer relationship management, and secondary level components such as benchmarking and order fulfillment.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 For <b>product development and commercialization</b>: Includes the primary level component of Product Data Management (PDM), and secondary level components such as market share, customer satisfaction, profit margins, and returns to stakeholders.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 For <b>physical distribution, manufacturing support and procurement</b>: Includes the primary level component of enterprise resource planning (ERP), with secondary level components such as warehouse management, material management, manufacturing planning, personnel management, and postponement (order management).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 For <b>performance measurement</b>: Includes the primary level component of logistics performance measurement, which is correlated with the information flow facility structure within the organization. Secondary level components may include four types of measurement such as: variation, direction, decision and policy measurements. More specifically, in accordance with these secondary level components, total cost analysis (TCA), customer profitability analysis (CPA), and asset management could be concerned as well.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 For <b>outsourcing</b>: Includes the primary level component of management methods, and the strategic objectives for particular initiatives in key areas of information technology, operations, manufacturing capabilities, and logistics (secondary level components).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Reverse Supply Chain</b>
<link>
Reverse Logistics</link> is the process of planning, implementing and controlling the efficient, effective inbound flow and storage of secondary goods and related information opposite to the traditional supply chain direction for the purpose of recovering value or proper disposal.
Reverse logistics is also referred to as "Aftermarket Customer Services". 
In other words, anytime money is taken from a company's Warranty Reserve or Service Logistics budget, that is a Reverse Logistics operation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jpfarrell.blogspot.com/">
Definition of  Terms</weblink>".&#32;  A Management Consultant @ Large.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-27</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Baziotopoulos, 2004</entry>
<entry id="3">
MacDuffie and Helper, 1997; Monden, 1993; Womack and Jones, 1996; Gunasekaran, 1999</entry>
<entry id="4">
Drucker, 1998; Tapscott, 1996; Dilts, 1999</entry>
<entry id="5">
Lambert, Douglas M.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scm-institute.org">
Supply Chain Management: Processes, Partnerships, Performance</weblink>, 3rd edition, 2008.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Macneil ,1975; Williamson, 1974; Hewitt, 1994</entry>
<entry id="7">
Stevens, 1989; Ellram and Cooper, 1993; Ellram and Cooper, 1990; Houlihan, 1985</entry>
<entry id="8">
Cooper <it>et al.</it>, 1997; Lambert <it>et al.</it>,1996; Turnbull, 1990</entry>
<entry id="9">
Zhang and Dilts, 2004 ;Vickery <it>et al.</it>, 2003; Hemila, 2002; Christopher, 1998; Joyce <it>et al.</it>, 1997; Bowersox and Closs, 1996; Williamson, 1991; Courtright <it>et al.</it>, 1989; Hofstede, 1978</entry>
<entry id="10">
Stevens, 1989</entry>
<entry id="11">
Ellram and Cooper, 1993</entry>
<entry id="12">
Mills <it>et al.</it>, 2004</entry>
<entry id="13">
Lewis and Talalayevsky, 2004</entry>
<entry id="14">
Hedberg and Olhager, 2002</entry>
<entry id="15">
Hemila, 2002</entry>
<entry id="17">
Yusuf <it>et al.</it>, 2003</entry>
<entry id="16">
Vickery et.al., 2003</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Haag, S., Cummings, M., McCubbrey, D., Pinsonneault, A., &amp; Donovan, R. (2006), Management Information Systems For the Information Age (3rd Canadian Ed.), Canada: McGraw Hill Ryerson ISBN 0-072-81947-2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Halldorsson, Arni, Herbert Kotzab &amp; Tage Skjott-Larsen (2003). Inter-organizational theories behind Supply Chain Management – discussion and applications, In Seuring, Stefan et al. (eds.), Strategy and Organization in Supply Chains, Physica Verlag. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Halldorsson, A., Kotzab, H., Mikkola, J. H., Skjoett-Larsen, T. (2007). Complementary theories to supply chain management . Supply Chain Management: An International Journal, Volume 12 Issue 4 , 284-296.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Handfield and Bechtel, 2001; Prater <it>et al.</it>, 2001; Kern and Willcocks, 2000; Bowersox and Closs, 1996; Christopher, 1992; Bowersox, 1989</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kaushik K.D., &amp; Cooper, M. (2000). Industrial Marketing Management. Volume29, Issue 1 , January 2000, Pages 65-83</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ketchen Jr., G., &amp; Hult, T.M. (2006). Bridging organization theory and supply chain management: The case of best value supply chains. Journal of Operations Management, 25(2) 573-580. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Larson, P.D. and Halldorsson, A. (2004). Logistics versus supply chain management: an international survey. International Journal of Logistics: Research &amp; Application, Vol. 7, Issue 1, 17-31.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lavassani, M. K., Movahedi B., Kumar V. (2008a) Transition to B2B e-Marketplace enabled Supply Chain: Readiness Assessment and Success Factors, Information Resources Management (Conf-IRM), 2008, Niagara, Canada.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lavassani, M. K., Movahedi B., Kumar V. (2008b) HISTORICAL DEVELOPMENTS IN THEORIES OF SUPPLY CHAIN MANAGEMENT: THE CASE OF B2B E-MARKETPLACES. Administrative Science Association of Canada (ASAC), 2008, Halifax, Canada.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mentzer, J.T. et al (2001): Defining Supply Chain Management, in: Journal of Business Logistics, Vol. 22, No. 2, 2001, pp. 1-25</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Simchi-Levi D.,Kaminsky P., Simchi-levi E. (2007), Designing and Managing the Supply Chain, third edition, Mcgraw Hill</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<table style="background:transparent; width:100%;" cellpadding="0" class=" multicol" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col align="left" width="" valign="top">
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/1585223.xml">
Beer Distribution Game</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/3363545.xml">
Bullwhip effect</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/4303969.xml">
Calculating Demand Forecast Accuracy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/6061244.xml">
Customer Driven Supply Chain</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/4159592.xml">
Demand chain management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/239863.xml">
Distribution</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/264466.xml">
e-business</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/17644390.xml">
Factory Physics</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/771132.xml">
Fulfillment</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/195701.xml">
Industrial Engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/1098368.xml">
Information technology management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/18134326.xml">
Integrated business planning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/182655.xml">
Inventory management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/6718932.xml">
Liquid Logistics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <knowledge_domain wordnetid="105999266" confidence="0.8">
<discipline wordnetid="105996646" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/186164.xml">
Logistic engineering</link></discipline>
</knowledge_domain>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/77547.xml">
Logistics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/1331168.xml">
Logistics Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <concentration wordnetid="105704266" confidence="0.8">
<specialism wordnetid="105705184" confidence="0.8">
<attention wordnetid="105650579" confidence="0.8">
<faculty wordnetid="105650329" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/14865434.xml">
Logistics Officer</link></faculty>
</attention>
</specialism>
</concentration>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/237494.xml">
Management information systems</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
<col align="left" width="" valign="top">
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/59252.xml">
Marketing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/6546396.xml">
Military Supply Chain Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/1993994.xml">
Operations management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/763365.xml">
Procurement</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/6990153.xml">
Procurement outsourcing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/2101106.xml">
Reverse logistics</link></concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/909187.xml">
Service management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/484241.xml">
Strategic information system</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/11183756.xml">
Supply chain network</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/3425802.xml">
Supply Chain Security</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/186493.xml">
Supply chain</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/5180882.xml">
Supplier relationship management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/348422.xml">
Tenders</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/375528.xml">
Value chain</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/10032565.xml">
Value grid</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/565255.xml">
Vendor Managed Inventory</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/1745691.xml">
Warehouse Management System</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cio.com/article/40940">
CIO Magazine's ABCs of Supply Chain Management</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scdigest.com">
Supply Chain Digest Web Site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.interorganisational.org">
InterOrganisational: Academic Blog on Supply Chain Management</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
