<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:59:59[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<cause  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107326557">
<beginning  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107290905">
<happening  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107283608">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<origin  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107323922">
<factor  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107327805">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<header>
<title>Astrological compatibility</title>
<id>2809535</id>
<revision>
<id>244200278</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T19:27:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dmitri Lytov</username>
<id>1507888</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Technical factors of astrology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="margin: 0px 0px 1em 1em; border: 1px solid #aaaaaa; clear: both; float:right;" align="right" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="background:#BBDDFF; padding: 0px 5px 3px 5px; text-align: center;" align="center">
 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
Astrology</link></b></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <image location="center" width="120px" src="Astrologyproject.svg">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<header style="background:#b0c4de; font-size: 95%; border-top: 1px solid #aaaaaa; border-bottom: 1px solid #aaaaaa; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px;">
Background</header>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/958988.xml">
History of astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/14021.xml">
History of astronomy</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/1018868.xml">
Astrology and astronomy</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<header style="background:#b0c4de; font-size: 95%; border-top: 1px solid #aaaaaa; border-bottom: 1px solid #aaaaaa; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px;">
Traditions</header>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/5524744.xml">
Babylonian astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/8406253.xml">
Arab and Persian astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/159669.xml">
Chinese astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/8355897.xml">
Egyptian astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/5563228.xml">
Hellenistic astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link>
Indian astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/5005288.xml">
Islamic astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/405765.xml">
Sidereal astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/159668.xml">
Western astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 85%; font-weight: bold; text-align: right; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/11569981.xml">
More...</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<header style="background:#b0c4de; font-size: 95%; border-top: 1px solid #aaaaaa; border-bottom: 1px solid #aaaaaa; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px;">
 Branches of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/3740333.xml">
horoscopic astrology</link></header>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/1148848.xml">
Natal astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/587154.xml">
Electional astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/517442.xml">
Horary astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/1052019.xml">
Mundane astrology</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 85%; font-weight: bold; text-align: right; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/11569981.xml">
More...</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<header style="background:#b0c4de; border-top: 1px solid #aaaaaa; border-bottom: 1px solid #aaaaaa; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px;">
Categories</header>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 
Astrologers|Astrologers</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 
Astrological texts|Astrological texts</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe;">
 
Astrological writers|Astrological writers</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe; text-align:center; font-weight:bold;">
 
Astrology Portal</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding: 0px 5px 0px 5px; background: #edf3fe; text-align:center;"></col>
</row>
</table>
<p>

<b>Astrological compatibility,</b> (<b>synastry</b>), is the branch of astrology that studies relationships by comparing natal horoscopes.  A natal horoscope is a chart, map, or imaginary snapshot of the planets in the solar system and their positions in the zodiac at the exact time of your birth.  The signs of the Zodiac represent 12 different types of spiritual energy and purpose.  The planets in the solar system are associated with at least one but most often two signs of the zodiac. </p>
<p>

Relationships between planets, signs (types of energy) and houses (sectors of the chart)  are described in words and /or often rated in numbers to show to what degree, how, and in what ways one person is compatible or incompatible with another. The assesment is based on the patterns and distributions of energy in the respective and combined charts.</p>
<p>

Compatibility between Zodiac signs is always approached within a particular branch of astrological tradition, be it <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/159669.xml">
Chinese astrology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/159668.xml">
Western astrology</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/186462.xml">
Vedic astrology</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Compatibility in Western astrology</st>

<p>

The first concept to be understood is that the different planets correspond to different kinds of love.  Venus is the planet of affection, attraction and/or romantic love.  Venus is associated with the Zodiac sign Libra.  Mars is the planet of sex and passion   Martian love was called Eros by the Greeks. Mars is associated with the sign Aries.  The Sun which is associated with Leo is also a symbol for love. The kind of love that is mutual honor, respect and an appreciation for each other as equals. The Greek words for this type of love is perhaps Philia.  Agape is the love of God or the unconditional spiritual love that God  instructs us to have for one another(Christianity). In modern astrology Agape might be associated with the planet Neptune or Jupiter, rulers of the spiritual sign Pisces.  </p>
<p>

In a natal horoscope if someone has Venus in Pisces, that person will be “attracted to or have affection” for someone with Piscean character.  If somebody has Mars in Gemini that person may be sexually attracted to a person who has Gemini character or energy in their chart.</p>
<p>

In reality we are a mix or blend of energies as described in the natal chart. The natal chart also tells us how or the manner in which someone loves.  For example if someone has Venus in Scorpio they will have a tendency to give affection in an emotionally intense possibly mystical way. If someone has a Mars in Taurus, their erotic style of loving will be sensual and slow. </p>
<p>

Relationships are complex and many people will desire to experience a balance of all the different types of love.  They not only want affectionate love but erotic love, honor love, and spiritual love. All from  the  one partner.  A good astrologer will be able to ascertain the “love needs and abilities ” of each partner from observing patterns in each horoscope,</p>
<p>

When astrologers speak of aspects they describe the relationships between the planets or energies. Each of us have aspects or relationships between the planets in our birth (natal) charts they represent our psychological strengths, weakness, natural blessings and personal demons. In synastry or chart comparisons, aspects illustrate areas of ease and compatibility or challenge and incompatibility between the individuals studied.   </p>
<p>

Logically then the most compatible person is an astrological twin.  An astrological twin is someone who has the same planet alignments (born at the same time) and in the same place.  </p>
<p>

If compatibility can be thought of as how harmonious a relationship is, then the most compatible Aspect should be the conjunction. That is Aries is with Aries, Taurus with Taurus etc.</p>
<p>

You might think this would be true but most astrologers agree that we are put on earth to balance each others strengths and weakness or smooth out each others rough edges. Too much of even a seemingly good thing is often bland and unproductive 
And you will rarely find even the most narcissistic of people excited about the possibility of being in a relationship with themselves.  So healthy or positive synastry between two charts is about blending and complementing another’s energies to create a healthy synergy.    </p>
<p>

Consider The zodiac a circle or belt of fixed stars surrounding the solar system. These fixed stars serve as “landmarks” in the sky.  As the planets orbit the sun at their respective speeds and rhythms, when viewed from earth they appear to be in a particular constellation of the zodiac (area of the sky). Aspects have to do with the distance between planets as they travel.  Aspects are measured in degrees since they all are moving within a big circle around the sun. Each of the 12 signs of the Zodiac occupies 30 degrees of the 360 degree circle.  For example if mars is passing through the area of Virgo and Venus is traveling through Capricorn, at a certain time they will be exactly 120 degrees apart.  This aspect is called a trine.  A Trine is considered the most positive aspect or relationship because it is between similar energies and therefore easily blended.  in this example it is between the earth signs  Virgo and Capricorn.  If however Mars was in Virgo but Venus was in   Scorpio, this aspect would be a sextile  or 60 degrees apart.  They are separated by one sign or constellation between them.  The sextile is also a positive aspect because the energies complement one another  in this case  they represent the elements of earth and water which in nature need or support each other. </p>
<p>

Astrology has in common with music a base-12 cycle.  In music theory there are intervals which are more harmonious than others.  If music theory can be applied to astrology then the most harmonious to least harmonious <cause wordnetid="107326557" confidence="0.8">
<beginning wordnetid="107290905" confidence="0.8">
<happening wordnetid="107283608" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<origin wordnetid="107323922" confidence="0.8">
<factor wordnetid="107327805" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../966/179966.xml">
 aspects</link></psychological_feature>
</factor>
</origin>
</event>
</happening>
</beginning>
</cause>
 are conjunction, quincunx, sextile, square, trine, semisextile and opposition.</p>
<p>

In practice the trine and sextile are considered the most positive aspects the square (90 degrees) is the most negative, and the opposition (180 degrees) and conjunction (0 degrees) could be either bad or good depending on the kind of energies involved. An Opposition of energies can be an ongoing battle or balance. A conjunction, meaning planets standing together in the same sign, can be a beautiful blend e.g. Moon/ Venus (emotions and affections)   or frustrating Saturn/Mars (Stop and Go).  Again conjunctions can be positive aspects in a chart when they are energies that blend or complement one another’ but if they are energies that naturally oppose or antagonize each other, a conjunction is NOT a good thing. There is one exception however and that is the combination of Mars and Venus.</p>
<p>

In a compatibility chart between a man and woman when a mans Mars is conjunct (in the same position) as a woman’s Venus, this denotes a very primal and urgent attraction.  They represent the opposite energies in the zodiac and nature. Venus is the Female principle and Mars is the Male. The combination of attraction /Affection (Venus) and Passion (Mars) is the stuff of great love stories.    </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Compatibility in Indian astrology</st>

<p>

Hindu / Indian have unique system of examining compatibility based on horoscopes of the aspirant couple.  Horoscope matching is an art of the highest ingenuity of an astrologer. All the factors cannot be detailed in small space like this. The fundamental concept of matching horoscopes emanates from constellations occupied by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/19331.xml">
Moon</link> at the time of births of bride and bridegroom. Individuals inherit qualities of the birth constellation. Various constellations represent different nature in respect of their casts, animals presented by them, sex, <it>Gana</it> (God / man / demon), humour, birds ruled, primordial elements, Gotra, directions ruled, consonants and vowels, mutual harmony and repellent with certain stars, beneficence to the other stars by virtue of mutual distance etc.</p>
<p>

In addition host of other factors like, longevity of the individuals, character (sexual), widowhood, poverty, progeny, their body status, radical strengths and indications, planetary nature and afflictions, currency of major and minor periods,<it> Marakaas</it> (death inflicting planets), placement of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/14640471.xml">
Mars</link> in their nativity (Mangal Dosha), time of query, omen (<it>Shagun</it>), antidotes, propitiations, auspicious time for marriage etc. should be examined to arrive at suitable union of the couple.   </p>
<p>

Based on the birth constellations following aspects are examined <it>Varna, Vashya, Tara, Yoni, Gana, Graha Maitri, Bhakoota, Nadi, Mahendra, Vedha, Rajju, Stree Deergha, Linga, Gotra, Pakshi, Yoni, Chandra Yoga, Ayya Varga and Yujja</it> for checking compatibility. In another system, only eight of these factors are given importance and are assigned numerical values - <it>Varna</it> (1 point), <it>Vashya</it> (2 Points), <it>Tara</it> (3 points), <it>Yoni</it> (4 points), <it>Graha Maitri</it> (5 points), <it>Gana</it> (6 points), <it>Bhakoota</it> (7 points) and <it>Nadi</it> (8 points). The total of these factors adds up to 36 points and horoscope is considered to be matched if the compatibility score is more than 18. </p>
<p>

Significance of various aspects in compatibility are as follows:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Varna</it> : Grade of spiritual development, obedience </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Vashya</it> : Mutual control – friendship.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Tara</it> : Mutual beneficence-luck-auspiciousness</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Yoni</it> : Sexual aspects, affinity, urge, compatibility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Graha Maitri</it> : Psychological disposition, friendship.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Gana</it> : Nature: Dev – Manush – Raakshas</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Bhakoota</it> : Children, growth of family.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Nadi</it>: Temperaments, hereditary (astrological), affliction and death to other</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Mahendra</it> : Promotes attachments, increase in longevity.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Stree – Dergha</it> :  Service to husband.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Rajju</it> :  Felicity and duration of married life.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Vedha – Varga</it> : Mutual repellence and enmity.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Varga</it> : Mutual friendship / enmity judged from their names</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Yujja</it> :  Type of mutual love – from one side – both sides.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Based on the above aspects, mathematical computation is done to arrive at the totality of the matching. In certain cases need based matching is done and the astrologer has to use his skills in examining compatibility. It is felt essential to match the horoscopes before further marriage negotiations are done. The above system is in practice for the last two millennia.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

For astrological compatibility in Chinese astrology, see:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Theodora Lau. (1997). "Chinese Horoscopes Guide to Relationships". Publisher: Doubleday Publishing. ISBN 0-385-48640-5</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Suzanne White. (1998). Chinese Astrology: Plain and Simple. Publisher: Tuttle Publishing. ISBN 0-8048-3188-2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Suzanne White. (1998) New Astrology: A Unique Synthesis of the World's Two Great Astrological Systems: The Chinese and Western</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Theodora Lau. (1999). Handbook of Chinese Horoscopes. Publisher: HarperCollins Publishers. ISBN 0-06-273731-7</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

For astrological compatibility in western astrology, see:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Diagram Group. (2004). "The Book of the Zodiac". Publisher: Sterling Publishing Co., Inc. ISBN 1402713061 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ronald Davison. (1983). "Synastry: Understanding Human Relations Through Astrology". Publisher: Aurora Press, Inc. ISBN 0943358051 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

E. W. Neville. (1997). "Planets in Synastry: Astrological Patterns of Relationships". Publisher: Whitford Press, Inc. ISBN 0924608013 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Christine Rakela. (2004). "Love Relationship Formula: Predicting Romantic Success with Astrology ". Publisher: Llewellyn Publications, Inc. ISBN 0738704245 </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

For astrological compatibility in Indian Astrology
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gayatri Devi Vasudev (2002). "The Art of Matching Charts". Publisher: Motilal Banarasidass. ISBN 81-208-1769-9</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

H.Defouw - R.E.Svoboda(2000). "Light on Relationships: The Synastry of Indian Astrology". Publisher: </entry>
</list>

Weiser Books. ISBN 1578631483
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

V K Shridhar (2002). " HINDU ELECTIONAL ASTROLOGY". Publisher: Suvaas Publishers, 25, Friends Colony, Yamuna Nagar, 135 001 Haryana India. ISBN :81-901413-0-9. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.besttime-election.com">
http://www.besttime-election.com</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/19647869.xml">
Interpersonal compatibility</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sex-astrology.com/index.php?page=articles&amp;catid=10">
Astrological Compatibility Rules</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.planetarypositions.com/chartmatch.html">
Vedic horoscope compatibility</weblink> Application to calculate compatibility as per the Indian Astrology system mentioned above</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</psychological_feature>
</factor>
</origin>
</event>
</happening>
</beginning>
</cause>
</article>
