<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:57:39[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<know-how  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105616786">
<method  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105660268">
<header>
<title>Computer-assisted proof</title>
<id>2840305</id>
<revision>
<id>227138641</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-22T04:02:46Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Classicalecon</username>
<id>4831766</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Artificial intelligence</category>
<category>Automated theorem proving</category>
<category>Philosophy of mathematics</category>
<category>Formal methods</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>computer-assisted proof</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/82285.xml">
mathematical proof</link> that has been at least partially generated by computer.<p>

Most computer-aided proofs to date have been implementations of large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/359970.xml">
proofs-by-exhaustion</link> of a mathematical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/30977.xml">
theorem</link>. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/10949.xml">
four color theorem</link> was the first major theorem to be proved using a computer.</p>
<p>

The idea is to use the computer to perform lengthy computations, but to control the round-off and propagation errors through the interval arithmetic technique. More precisely, one reduces the computation to a sequence of  elementary operations, say (+,-,*,/); the result of an elementary operation is rounded off by the computer precision. However, one can construct an interval provided by upper and lower bounds on the result of an elementary operation. Then one proceeds by replacing numbers with intervals and  performing  elementary operations between such intervals of representable numbers.</p>
<p>

Attempts have also been made in the area of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link> research to create smaller, explicit, new proofs of mathematical theorems from the bottom up using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
machine reasoning</link> techniques such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/846509.xml">
heuristic</link> search. Such <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/2546.xml">
automated theorem prover</link>s have proved a number of new results and found new proofs for known theorems.  Additionally, some interactive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/1258607.xml">
proof assistant</link>s allow mathematicians to develop human-readable proofs which are nonetheless formally verified for correctness.  These areas do not share the controversial implications of computer-aided proofs-by-exhaustion. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Philosophical objections </st>
<p>

Computer-assisted proofs are the subject of much controversy in the mathematical world. Some mathematicians believe that lengthy computer-assisted proofs are not, in some sense, <it>real</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/82285.xml">
mathematical proof</link>s because they involve so many logical steps that they are not practically <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/270054.xml">
verifiable</link> by human beings, and that mathematicians are effectively being asked to put their trust in an empirical computational process instead of logical deduction from assumed axioms.</p>
<p>

Other mathematicians believe that lengthy computer-assisted proofs should be regarded as <it>calculations</it>, rather than <it>proofs</it>: the proof algorithm itself should be proved valid, so that its use can then be regarded as a mere "verification".  This is known as "Poincaré's principle" in the mathematical community, after a statement by <link>
Henri Poincaré</link>.  They reply to their opponents' arguments that computer-assisted proofs are subject to errors in their source programs, compilers, and hardware, can be resolved by multiple replications of the result using different programming languages, different compilers, and different computer hardware.</p>
<p>

Another possible way of verifying computer-aided proofs is to generate their reasoning steps in a machine-readable form, and then use an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/2546.xml">
automated theorem prover</link> to demonstrate their correctness. This approach of using a computer program to prove another program correct does not appeal to computer proof skeptics, who see it as adding another layer of complexity without addressing the perceived need for human understanding. </p>
<p>

Another argument against computer-aided proofs is that they lack <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/18974136.xml">
mathematical elegance</link> - that they provide no insights or new and useful concepts.  In fact, this is an argument that could be advanced against any lengthy proof by exhaustion.</p>
<p>

An additional philosophical issue raised by computer-aided proofs is whether they make mathematics into a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/159731.xml">
quasi-empirical science</link>, where the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/26833.xml">
scientific method</link> becomes more important than the application of pure reason in the area of abstract mathematical concepts. This directly relates to the argument within mathematics as to whether mathematics is based on ideas, or "merely" an exercise in formal symbol manipulation. It also raises the question whether, if according to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/23632.xml">
Platonist</link> view, all possible mathematical objects in some sense "already exist", whether computer-aided mathematics is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/2845886.xml">
observational science</link> like astronomy, rather than an experimental one like physics or chemistry. Interestingly, this controversy within mathematics is occurring at the same time as questions are being asked in the physics community about whether <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/18938115.xml">
twenty-first century</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/19594028.xml">
theoretical physics</link> is becoming too mathematical, and leaving behind its experimental roots.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/891251.xml">
As of 2005</link>, there is an emerging field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/256363.xml">
experimental mathematics</link> that is confronting this debate head-on by focusing on numerical experiments as its main tool for mathematical exploration.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/2546.xml">
Automated theorem proving</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/3189200.xml">
Symbolic mathematics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<attendant wordnetid="109821831" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<checker wordnetid="109913110" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/321157.xml">
Model checking</link></checker>
</causal_agent>
</method>
</worker>
</know-how>
</assistant>
</attendant>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/8618570.xml">
Proof checking</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/2884728.xml">
Automated reasoning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/270054.xml">
Formal verification</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/256363.xml">
Experimental mathematics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/2845886.xml">
Observational science</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/12823.xml">
Garbage in, garbage out</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lenat, D.B., (1976), AM: An artificial intelligence approach to discovery in mathematics as heuristic search, Ph.D. Thesis, STAN-CS-76-570, and Heuristic Programming Project Report HPP-76-8, Stanford University, AI Lab., Stanford, CA.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Edmund Furse; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.comp.glam.ac.uk/pages/staff/efurse/Abstracts/Why-did-AM-halt.html">
Why did AM run out of steam?</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Keith Devlin; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.maa.org/devlin/devlin_01_05.html">
Last doubts removed about the proof of the Four Color Theorem</weblink>, <it>MAA Online</it>, January 2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/07012/753384-28.stm">
Number proofs done by computer might err</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</method>
</know-how>
</article>
