<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:43:32[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<agency  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108337324">
<header>
<title>National Weather Service</title>
<id>286989</id>
<revision>
<id>244226768</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T21:31:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Src1</username>
<id>305653</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Government agencies established in 1870</category>
<category>National Weather Service</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Government agency</name>
<parameters>
<logo_width>
140px</logo_width>
<logo>
US-NationalWeatherService-Logo.svg</logo>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weather.gov">
www.weather.gov</weblink></website>
<chief1_position>
Director</chief1_position>
<jurisdiction>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/195149.xml">
Federal government of the United States</link></jurisdiction>
<agency_name>
National Weather Service</agency_name>
<headquarters>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/43485.xml">
Silver Spring</link></village>
, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/18858.xml">
Maryland</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</headquarters>
<slogan>
<it>America's National Weather Service: Protecting Lives, Livelihoods, and Your Way of Life''</it></slogan>
<parent_agency>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/37876.xml">
NOAA</link></parent_agency>
<chief1_name>
Dr. John "Jack" L. Hayes</chief1_name>
<formed>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/11361.xml">
February 9</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/34769.xml">
1870</link></formed>
</parameters>
</template>


The <b>National Weather Service</b> (<b>NWS</b>), once known as the Weather Bureau<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, is one of the six scientific agencies that make up the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/37876.xml">
National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</link> (NOAA) of the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/195149.xml">
government</link>. It is tasked with providing "weather, hydrologic, and climate forecasts and warnings for the United States, its territories, adjacent waters and ocean areas, for the protection of life and property and the enhancement of the national economy." This is done through a collection of national and regional centers, and more than 122 local weather forecast offices (WFOs). Since the NWS is a government agency, most of its products are in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/581195.xml">
public domain</link> and available free of charge.
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

The NWS, formerly known as the Weather Bureau, was founded on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/11361.xml">
February 9</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/34769.xml">
1870</link> through a joint <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
congressional</link></legislature>
 resolution signed by <post wordnetid="108624385" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/24113.xml">
President</link></post>
 <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/31752.xml">
Ulysses S. Grant</link></person>
</president>
. The mission of the NWS was "to provide for taking meteorological observations at the military stations in the interior of the continent and at other points in the States and Territories...and for giving notice on the northern (Great) Lakes and on the seacoast by magnetic telegraph and marine signals, of the approach and force of storms." The agency was placed under the <position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/44000.xml">
 Secretary of War</link></location>
</point>
</position>
 because "military discipline would probably secure the greatest promptness, regularity, and accuracy in the required observations." Within the Department of War, it was assigned to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/1682898.xml">
U.S. Army Signal Corps</link> under Brigadier General <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<commissioned_officer wordnetid="109942970" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<health_professional wordnetid="110165109" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<general wordnetid="110123844" confidence="0.8">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<commissioned_military_officer wordnetid="109943239" confidence="0.8">
<general_officer wordnetid="110125786" confidence="0.8">
<medical_practitioner wordnetid="110305802" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/917169.xml">
Albert J. Myer</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</medical_practitioner>
</general_officer>
</commissioned_military_officer>
</military_officer>
</doctor>
</general>
</professional>
</health_professional>
</adult>
</serviceman>
</person>
</commissioned_officer>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
. General Meyer gave the National Weather Service its first name: The Division of Telegrams and Reports for the Benefit of Commerce.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

The agency first became a civilian enterprise in 1890, when it became part of the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/70896.xml">
Department of Agriculture</link></agency>
; it would later be moved to the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/70243.xml">
Department of Commerce</link></agency>
 in 1940.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The first Weather Bureau <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/172851.xml">
radiosonde</link> was launched in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1645518.xml">
Massachusetts</link></country>
 in 1937, which went on to replace all routine aircraft observation within two years. The Bureau was renamed the National Weather Service in 1967, as part of the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/8783558.xml">
Environmental Science Services Administration</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
, which became the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/37876.xml">
National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</link> (NOAA) three years later with the enactment of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/531842.xml">
National Environmental Policy Act</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Forecasting</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="125px" src="NDFD-sample-max-temp.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Sample maximum temperature map from the NDFD
</caption>
</image>

The NWS issues a comprehensive package of forecast products to support a variety of users, including the general public. Although text forecasts have been the primary means of product dissemination, the NWS has been converting its forecast products to a digital, gridded format. Each of the 122 Weather Forecast Offices (WFOs) send their graphical forecasts to a national server to be compiled in the National Digital Forecast Database (NDFD). This is a collection of sensible weather elements such as: maximum and minimum temperature, humidity, cloud cover, probability of precipitation, amount of precipitation and wintry precipitation, weather type, and wind direction and speed. In addition to viewing (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weather.gov/forecasts/graphical/">
http://www.weather.gov/forecasts/graphical/</weblink>) gridded weather data via the internet, more advanced users can decode the individual grids using a "GRIB2 decoder" which can output data as shapefiles, netCDF, GrADS, float files, and comma separated variable files.  Specific points in the digital database can be accessed using an XML <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/29215.xml">
SOAP</link> service (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weather.gov/xml/">
http://www.weather.gov/xml/</weblink>). These capabilities have greatly increased the audience of NDFD data. The NWS has received some criticism from commercial weather vendors for providing graphical forecast data free of charge. They argue that such tailored forecast information compete with their own products. However, a large majority of private weather firms quickly realized its potential benefits and have flourished by using the NDFD as a tool for composing their products.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Aviation</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="NOAAPreparing.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

National Weather Service meteorologists preparing a forecast, early 20th century.
</caption>
</image>

The NWS supports the aviation community through the production of several specific forecast products. Each WFO has responsibility for the issuance of Terminal Aerodrome Forecasts (TAF) for one or more airports in their jurisdiction. TAFs are concise, coded 24-hour forecasts for a specific airport, issued every six hours with amendments as needed. As opposed to a public weather forecast, a TAF only addresses weather elements critical to aviation. These are: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/15440316.xml">
wind</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/1796418.xml">
visibility</link>, weather, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/47515.xml">
sky condition (clouds)</link>, and optional data such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/223992.xml">
wind shear</link>. The following is an example of a TAF for <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/290147.xml">
Will Rogers World Airport</link></airport>
 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/57848.xml">
Oklahoma City</link></village>
:</p>
<p>

KOKC 212350Z 220024 10006KT P6SM SCT040 BKN120
TEMPO 0001 VRB15G25KT 2SM +TSRA BKN040CB OVC070
FM0100 10007KT P6SM SCT040CB BKN060 BKN120
TEMPO 0105 2SM +TSRA BKN030CB OVC050
FM0500 07006KT 5SM SHRA BKN030CB OVC050
TEMPO 0508 3SM +TSRA OVC030CB
FM1200 03006KT P6SM -SHRA BKN025 OVC070
FM1600 05007KT P6SM BKN035 OVC100</p>
<p>

21 NWS Center Weather Service Units (CWSU) are collocated with the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/11186.xml">
Federal Aviation Administration (FAA)</link></agency>
 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/3438844.xml">
Air Route Traffic Control Centers (ARTCC)</link></location>
</area>
</center>
</region>
. Their main responsibility is to provide up-to-the-minute weather information and briefings to the Traffic Management Units and control room supervisors. Special emphasis is given to weather conditions that would be hazardous to aviation or would impede the flow of air traffic in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/13869047.xml">
National Airspace System</link>. Beside scheduled and unscheduled briefings for decision-makers in the ARTCC and other FAA facilities, CWSU meteorologists also issue two unscheduled products. The Center Weather Advisory (CWA) is an aviation weather warning for thunderstorms, icing, turbulence, and low <link>
 cloud ceilings</link> and visibilities. The Meteorological Impact Statement (MIS) is a 2-12 hour forecast for weather conditions which are expected to impact ARTCC operations.</p>
<p>

The <link>
Aviation Weather Center</link> (AWC), located in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/811487.xml">
Kansas City, MO</link>, is a central aviation-support facility operated by the National Weather Service. The AWC issues two primary products:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<informing wordnetid="107212190" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<warning wordnetid="107224151" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/3710068.xml">
AIRMET</link></speech_act>
</warning>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</informing>
</event>
 (Airmen's Meteorological Information): Information on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/2644317.xml">
icing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/154664.xml">
turbulence</link>, mountain obscuration, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/223992.xml">
low-level wind shear</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/1536627.xml">
IMC conditions</link>, and strong surface winds.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/3709962.xml">
SIGMET</link>s (Significant Meteorological Information)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Convective: Issued for an area of thunderstorms affecting an area of 3,000&nbsp;square miles (7,800&nbsp;km2) or greater, a line of thunderstorms at least 60&nbsp;nmi (110&nbsp;km) long, and/or severe or embedded thunderstorms affecting any area that are expected to last 30 minutes or longer.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Non-convective: Issued for severe or greater turbulence over a 3,000&nbsp;square miles (7,800&nbsp;km2) area, severe or greater icing over a 3,000&nbsp;square miles (7,800&nbsp;km2), or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/1536627.xml">
IMC conditions</link> over a 3,000&nbsp;square miles (7,800&nbsp;km2) area due to dust, sand, or volcanic ash.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fire Weather</st>
<p>

Catering to national, regional and local land management agencies such as the <link>
US Forest Service</link>, the NWS issues a complete Fire Weather Forecast twice daily, with updates as needed. The forecast contains weather information relevant to fire control and smoke management for the next 36-48 hours. The appropriate crews use this information to plan for staffing and equipment levels, the ability to do prescribed burns, and assess the daily fire danger. Once per day, NWS meteorologists issue a coded fire weather forecast for specific USFS observation sites that are then input into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/12874176.xml">
National Fire Danger Rating System</link> (NFDRS). This computer model outputs the daily fire danger that is then conveyed to the public in one of four ratings: low, moderate, high, extreme.</p>
<p>

The local weather office also, under a prescribed set of criteria, will determine if a Fire Weather Watch or a Red Flag Warning needs to be issued. These products alert not only the public, but other agencies that conditions are creating the potential for extreme fire behavior.</p>
<p>

On the national level, the NWS <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/536249.xml">
Storm Prediction Center</link> issues fire weather analyses for days one and two. These include large-scale areas that may experience critical fire weather conditions including the occurrence of "dry thunderstorms." These are thunderstorms, usually occurring in the western U.S., that are not accompanied by any rain due to it evaporating before reaching the surface.
<image location="right" width="135px" src="NWS-IMET-deployed.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

NWS IMET taking observations in the field
</caption>
</image>

State and Federal forestry officials sometimes request a forecast from a WFO for a specific location called a "spot forecast." Spot forecasts are used to determine whether it will be safe to ignite a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/616992.xml">
prescribed burn</link> and how to situate crews during the controlling phase. Officials send in a request, usually during the early morning, containing the position coordinates of the proposed burn, the ignition time, and other pertinent information. The WFO composes a short-term fire weather forecast for the location and sends it back to the officials, usually within an hour of receiving the request.</p>
<p>

The NWS assists officials at large wildfires or other disasters, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/1476975.xml">
HAZMAT</link> incidents, by providing on-ground support through Incident Meteorologists (IMET). IMETs are NWS forecasters specially trained to work with Incident Management Teams during severe wildfire outbreaks or other disasters requiring onsite weather support. IMETs travel quickly to the incident site and then assemble a mobile weather center capable of providing continuous meteorological support for the duration of the incident. The kit includes a cell phone, a laptop computer and communications equipment, used for gathering and displaying weather data such as satellite imagery or numerical forecast model output. Remote weather stations are also used to gather specific data for the point of interest. They often receive direct support from the local WFO during such crises. IMETS can be deployed anywhere a disaster strikes and must be capable of working long hours for weeks at a time in remote locations under rough conditions. There are approximately 60 to 70 IMETs nationally.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Public</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="Weather_Forecast_Offices.PNG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Map of regions covered by the 122 Weather Forecast Offices.
</caption>
</image>

A significant portion of NWS forecasting is directed toward the general public. Because coded products are very difficult to understand by someone not familiar with the coding, most NWS public products are written using basic meteorological terminology in a sentence format. The main public forecasts products are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Zone Forecast Product (ZFP) - text product issued by all WFOs to explicitly state expected weather conditions within each zone in their area of forecast responsibility through day seven.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Surf Zone Forecast (SRF) - a text forecast for local beaches issued by coastal WFOs, including coastal hazard information such as that pertaining to rip currents. These products are issued year-round at the Los Angeles, San Diego, and New York City offices, and seasonally at most other coastal offices.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Short Term Forecast (NOW) - a localized, event-driven product used to provide the public with detailed weather information during significant and/or fast-changing hydrometeorological conditions during the next six hours.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Area Forecast Matrices (AFM) - displays various weather parameters at 3, 6 and 12 hour intervals for areas specified in the current ZFP.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Point Forecast Matrices (PFM) - displays various weather parameters at 3, 6 and 12 hour intervals for significant cities in the WFO area of responsibility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tabular State Forecast Product (SFT) - general seven-day public forecast of hydrometeorological conditions at specific locations over a WFO's area of responsibility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Area Forecast Discussion (AFD) - a semi-technical product primarily for explaining the scientific rationale behind a forecast and to summarize current watches/warnings/advisories in effect.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

NWS forecasts are available from their website. Previously, upon clicking a location on the map, the zone forecast for that county would appear. Now that the National Digital Forecast Database is operational, the internet forecasts have become "point-and-click," with the web server instantly composing a narrative text forecast for a particular point on the grid. This capability greatly reduces discontinuities in the forecast and takes full advantage of the detail put into the forecast by NWS meteorologists.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hydrologic</st>

<p>

The NWS is the primary source for hydrologic watches, warnings, and advisories for the United States of America. Local NWS offices are responsible for issuing: Flood Watches, Flash Flood Watches, Flood Warnings, Flash Flood Warnings and Flood Advisories for their local County Warning Area. These products can and do emphasize different hydrologic issues depending on geographic area, land use, time of year, as well as other meteorological and non-meteorological factors. For example, during the early spring or late winter a Flood Warning can be issued for an ice jam that occurs on a river, while in the summer a Flood Warning will most likely be issued for excessive rainfall. For the official definition of all the NWS hydrology products, see the NWS <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nws.noaa.gov/glossary/">
glossary</weblink>.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Ahps.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

National AHPS map
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

In recent years the NWS has enhanced its dissemination of hydrologic information through the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weather.gov/ahps/">
Advanced Hydrologic Prediction Service</weblink>, more commonly referred to by the acronym (AHPS).  AHPS allows anyone to view near real time observation and forecast data for rivers, lakes and streams. AHPS also enables the NWS to provide long-range probabilistic information which can be used for long-range planning decisions.</p>
<p>

Daily river forecasts are issued by the 13 River Forecast Centers (RFC) using hydrologic models based on rainfall, soil characteristics, precipitation forecasts, and several other variables. Some RFCs, especially those in mountainous regions, also provide seasonal snow pack and peak flow forecasts.  These forecasts are used by a wide range of users, including those in agriculture, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/381399.xml">
hydroelectric dam</link> operation, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/18581463.xml">
water supply</link> resources.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Marine</st>

<p>

The NWS's mission to protect life and property and to enhance the national economy includes a suite of products for the water bodies adjacent to the U.S.. The marine forecasting program is aimed at promoting safe and efficient transportation, both commercial and recreational. NWS national centers or WFOs issue several marine products:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Coastal Waters Forecast (CWF) - a text product issued by all coastal WFOs to explicitly state expected weather conditions within their marine forecast area of responsibility through day 5. Also addresses expect wave heights.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Offshore Waters Forecast (OFF) - a text product that provides forecast and warning information to mariners who travel on the oceanic waters adjacent to the U.S. coastal waters through day 5. Issued by the Ocean Prediction Center (OPC).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 NAVTEX forecast - a text forecast issued by OPC designed to accommodate broadcast restrictions of the U.S. Coast Guard NAVTEX transmitters. The product is a combination of the CWF and OFF.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 High Seas Forecast (HSF) - routine text product issued every six hours by OPC to provide warning and forecast information to mariners who travel on the oceanic waters.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Tropical</st>

<p>

The <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<atmospheric_phenomenon wordnetid="111425580" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<natural_phenomenon wordnetid="111408559" confidence="0.8">
<storm wordnetid="111462526" confidence="0.8">
<hurricane wordnetid="111467018" confidence="0.8">
<physical_phenomenon wordnetid="111419404" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<cyclone wordnetid="111443721" confidence="0.8">
<windstorm wordnetid="111527014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/255317.xml">
National Hurricane Center</link></windstorm>
</cyclone>
</area>
</process>
</phenomenon>
</center>
</physical_phenomenon>
</hurricane>
</storm>
</natural_phenomenon>
</location>
</atmospheric_phenomenon>
</region>
</physical_entity>
 (NHC) and the Central Pacific Hurricane Center (CPHC) are responsible for monitoring tropical weather in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/698.xml">
Atlantic</link>, and central and eastern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/23070.xml">
Pacific Ocean</link>. In addition to routine outlooks and discussions, they initiate advisories and discussions on individual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/8282374.xml">
tropical cyclone</link>s, as needed. If a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/8282374.xml">
tropical cyclone</link> threatens the United States or its territories, individual WFOs begin issuing statements detailing the expected local effects. The following tropical weather products are issued by the NWS:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Routine Products</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tropical Weather Outlook (TWO)</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 Atlantic basin</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 Pacific basin</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tropical Weather Discussion (TWD)</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 Atlantic basin</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 Pacific basin</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tropical Weather Summary (TWS)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Satellite Interpretation Message (SIM)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Active Tropical Cyclone Products</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tropical/Subtropical Cyclone Public Advisory (TCP)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tropical/Subtropical Cyclone Discussion (TCD)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Tropical Cyclone Forecast/Advisory (TCM)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Strike Probabilities of Tropical Cyclone Conditions (SPF)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Local WFO Products</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Hurricane Local Statement (HLS)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Inland Tropical Storm/Hurricane Watches or Warnings (NPW)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Post-Tropical Cyclone Reports (PSH)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Climate</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/15137017.xml">
Climate Prediction Center</link> (CPC) is responsible for all of the NWS's climate-related forecasts. Their mission is to "serve the public by assessing and forecasting the impacts of short-term climate variability, emphasizing enhanced risks of weather-related extreme events, for use in mitigating losses and maximizing economic gains." Their products cover time scales from a week to seasons, extending into the future as far as technically feasible, and cover the land, the ocean, and the atmosphere, extending into the stratosphere. Most of their products cover the Contiguous U.S. and Alaska. Here is a list of the main CPC products:</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="185px" src="NOAA-CPC-seasonal-temp-outlook.gif" type="thumb">
<caption>

Sample CPC 3.5 month temperature outlook
</caption>
</image>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 3-Month Temperature and Precipitation</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Outlooks</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Discussions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1-Month Temperature and Precipitation</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Outlooks</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Discussions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 6 to 10-Day and 8 to 14-Day Products</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Temperature and Precipitation Anomaly</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Excessive Heat Outlook</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Maximum Heat Index Prediction</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 3-Month Probability of Exceedance</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Temperature</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Precipitation</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Heating and Cooling Degree Days</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hurricane Season Outlook</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Atlantic basin</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Pacific basin</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 U.S. Drought</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Outlook</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Discussion</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 International Support</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Weekly Afghan Hazards</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Weekly Africa Hazards</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Weekly Central America Hazards</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Weekly Haiti Hazards</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Additionally, Weather Forecast Offices issue daily and monthly climate reports for their area of responsibility.  These generally include recorded highs, lows and other information.  Since this data is not official until it has been quality controlled by NCDC, when these products are made available from Forecast Offices (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weather.gov/climate/">
http://www.weather.gov/climate/</weblink>) they are considered to be unofficial and preliminary and cannot be used in a court of law.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Data Acquisition</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="NWS-Mosaic-Radar-Composite.gif" type="thumb">
<caption>

A NWS composite radar image of the , composed of many regional radars.
</caption>
</image>

</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Surface Observations</st>
<p>

<it>The <information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<datum wordnetid="105816622" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Automated Surface Observing System</link></datum>
</information>
 (ASOS)</it> is a joint effort of the National Weather Service (NWS), the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA), and the Department of Defense (DOD). The ASOS serves as the nation's primary surface weather observing network. It is designed to support weather forecast activities and aviation operations and, at the same time, support the needs of the meteorological, hydrological, and climatological research communities. ASOS was especially designed for the safety of the aviation community, therefore the sites are almost always located near airport runways. The system transmits routine hourly observations along with special observations when conditions exceed preselected weather element thresholds (e.g. the visibility decreases to less than 3 miles). The basic weather elements observed are: sky condition, visibility, present weather, obstructions to vision, pressure, temperature, dewpoint, wind direction and speed, precipitation accumulation, and selected significant remarks. The coded observations are issued as <information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<datum wordnetid="105816622" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/466804.xml">
METAR</link></datum>
</information>
s and look similar to this:
METAR KNXX 121155Z 03018G29KT 1/4SM +TSSN FG VV002 M05/M07 A2957 RMK PK WND 01029/1143 SLP026
SNINCR 2/10 RCRNR T2 SET 6///// 7//// 4/010 T10561067 11022 21056 55001 PWINO PNO FZRANO</p>
<p>

Getting more information on the atmosphere, more frequently, and from more locations is the key to improving forecasts and warnings. Due to the large installation and operating costs associated with ASOS, the stations are widely spaced. Before aviation weather observing began, the <it>Cooperative Observer Program (COOP)</it> was the only means for acquiring daily weather information. This network of approximately 11,000 mostly volunteer weather observers still flourishes today, providing much of the meteorological and climatological data to the country. The program which was established in 1890 under the Organic Act, currently has a twofold mission:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Provide observational meteorological data, usually consisting of daily maximum and minimum temperatures, snowfall, and 24-hour precipitation totals, required to define the climate of the United States and to help measure long-term climate changes.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Provide observational meteorological data in near real-time to support forecast, warning and other public service programs of the NWS.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Marine Observations</st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="135px" src="NOAA-NDBC-discus-buoy.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

3-meter discus buoy located off the Southeast U.S. coast
</caption>
</image>

NWS forecasters need frequent, high-quality marine observations to examine conditions for forecast preparation and to verify their forecasts after they are produced. These observations are especially critical to the output of <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/1505381.xml">
numerical weather models</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 because large water bodies have a profound impact on the weather. Other users rely on the observations and forecasts for commercial and recreational activities. To help meet these needs, the NWS's <institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/5000703.xml">
National Data Buoy Center</link></institution>
 (NDBC) operates a network of about 90 buoys and 60 land-based coastal observing systems (C-MAN). All stations measure wind speed, direction, and gust; barometric pressure; and air temperature. In addition, all buoy stations, and some C-MAN stations, measure sea surface temperature and wave height and period. Conductivity and water current are measured at selected stations. All stations report hourly.</p>
<p>

Supplemental weather observations are acquired through the <it>United States Voluntary Observing Ship (VOS)</it> program. It is organized for the purpose of obtaining weather and oceanographic observations from transiting ships. An international program under World Meteorological Organization (WMO) marine auspices, the VOS has forty-nine countries as participants. The United States program is the largest in the world, with nearly 1,000 vessels. Observations are taken by deck officers, coded in a special format known as the "ships synoptic code", and transmitted in realtime to the NWS. They are then distributed on national and international circuits for use by meteorologists in weather forecasting, by oceanographers, ship routing services, fishermen, and many others. The observations are then forwarded for use by the National Climatic Data Center (NCDC) in Asheville, North Carolina.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Upper Air Observations</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="110px" src="Radiosonde-wx-balloon.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A radiosonde shortly after launch.
</caption>
</image>

Upper air weather data is essential for weather forecasting and research. The NWS operates 92 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/172851.xml">
radiosonde</link> locations in North America and 10 sites in the Caribbean. A small, expendable instrument package is suspended below a 2 meter (6 ft) wide balloon filled with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/13255.xml">
hydrogen</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/13256.xml">
helium</link>, then released daily at or shortly after 11 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/143276.xml">
UTC</link> and 23 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/143276.xml">
UTC</link>. As the radiosonde rises at about 300 meters/minute (1,000 ft/min), sensors on the radiosonde measure profiles of pressure, temperature, and relative humidity. These sensors are linked to a battery powered radio transmitter that sends the sensor measurements to a ground receiver. By tracking the position of the radiosonde in flight, information on wind speed and direction aloft is also obtained. The flight can last longer than two hours, and during this time the radiosonde can ascend above 35 km (115,000 ft) and drift more than 200 km (125 mi) from the release point. When the balloon has expanded beyond its elastic limit and bursts (about 6 m or 20 ft in diameter), a small parachute slows the descent of the radiosonde, minimizing the danger to lives and property.</p>
<p>

Data obtained during the flights is coded and disseminated, at which point it can be plotted on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/1268839.xml">
Skew-T</link> or Stuve diagram for analysis.</p>
<p>

In recent years, the National Weather Service has begun incorporating data from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/6158574.xml">
AMDAR</link> in its numerical models (however, the raw data is not available to the public).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Event-driven Products</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<informing wordnetid="107212190" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<warning wordnetid="107224151" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/2241482.xml">
Severe weather terminology (United States)</link></speech_act>
</warning>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</informing>
</event>
</it>
</indent>

The National Weather Service has developed a multi-tier concept for forecasting or alerting the public to all types of hazardous weather. These are:</p>
<p>

<b>Outlook</b> - A hazardous weather outlook is issued daily addressing potentially hazardous weather or hydrologic events that may occur in the next seven days. The outlook will include information about potential severe thunderstorms, heavy rain or flooding, winter weather, extremes of heat or cold, etc. It is intended to provide information to those who need considerable lead time to prepare for the event. Other outlooks are issued on an event-driven basis, such as the Flood Potential Outlook and Severe Weather Outlook.</p>
<p>

<b>Watch</b> - A watch is used when the risk of a hazardous weather or hydrologic event has increased significantly, but its occurrence, location or timing is still uncertain. It is intended to provide enough lead time so those who need to set their plans in motion can do so. A watch means that hazardous weather is possible, but not imminent. People should have a plan of action in case a storm threatens and they should listen for later information and possible warnings especially when planning travel or outdoor activities.</p>
<p>

<b>Warning</b> - A warning is issued when a hazardous weather or hydrologic event is occurring, imminent or likely. A warning means weather conditions pose a threat to life or property. People in the path of the storm need to take protective action.</p>
<p>

<b>Advisory</b> - An advisory is issued when a hazardous weather or hydrologic event is occurring, imminent or likely. Advisories are for less serious conditions than warnings, that cause significant inconvenience and if caution is not exercised, could lead to situations that may threaten life or property.</p>
<p>

<b>Special Weather Statement</b> - A special weather statement is issued when something rare or unusual is occurring. These are usually triggered by sudden changes in meteorological conditions. The statements are to be taken as warnings for residents of a specific area. The warning generally states that an area might be at risk for a slight weather danger. Not all weather statements are warnings, though. Other times, statements describe informative facts about a weather system; such as local snowfall.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Product Dissemination</st>

<p>

<it>NOAA Weather Radio All-Hazards (NWR)</it>, sometimes called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/300427.xml">
Weatheradio</link> (though this is actually a trademark of receiver manufacturer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/83376.xml">
Tandy</link>), is a special radio system that transmits weather warnings and forecasts 24 hours a day across most of the United States. The system, owned and operated by the NWS, consists of more than 900 transmitters, covering all 50 states, adjacent coastal waters, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/23041.xml">
Puerto Rico</link></country>
, the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/32135.xml">
U.S. Virgin Islands</link></country>
, and the U.S. Pacific Territories. NWR requires a special <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/15368428.xml">
radio</link> receiver or scanner capable of picking up the signal. It is broadcast on seven frequencies centered around 162 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/14121.xml">
MHz</link> in the VHF frequency band. In recent years, national emergency response agencies such as FEMA and the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/58236.xml">
Department of Homeland Security</link></agency>
 have begun to take advantage of NWR's ability to efficiently reach a large portion of the population. The system is now used to broadcast civil and natural emergency information in addition to that relating to weather.</p>
<p>

<it>NOAA Weather Wire Service (NWWS)</it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nws.noaa.gov/nwws/">
http://www.nws.noaa.gov/nwws/</weblink> is a satellite data collection and dissemination system operated by the National Weather Service. Its purpose is to provide state and federal government, commercial users, media, and private citizens with timely delivery of meteorological, hydrological, climatological, and geophysical information. All products in the NWWS datastream are prioritized, with weather and hydrologic warnings receiving the highest priority (watches are next in priority). NWWS delivers severe weather and storm warnings to users in 10 seconds or less from the time they are issued, making it the fastest delivery system available. Products are broadcast to users via the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/2424311.xml">
AMC</link></company>
-4 satellite.</p>
<p>

<it>EMWIN</it> is the <it>Emergency Managers Weather Information Network</it>, a system designed to provide the emergency management community with access to a set of NWS warnings, watches, forecasts, and other products at no recurring cost. Its can receive data via radio, internet, or a dedicated satellite dish, depending on the needs and capabilities of the user. </p>
<p>

The <it>NOAAPORT</it> broadcast system provides a one-way broadcast communication of NOAA environmental data and information in near real time to NOAA and external users. This broadcast service is implemented by a commercial provider of satellite communications utilizing C-band.</p>
<p>

The <it>Weather.gov</it> website is a data rich website operated by NWS that serves as a portal to hundreds of thousands of webpages and more than 300 different NWS websites.  From the homepage, it is possible to enter a city and state to get a local forecast page, view a rapidly updated map of active watch and warnings, and select areas related to graphical forecasts, national maps, radar displays, rivers, air quality, satellite images and climate.  Also offered are xml data feeds of active watch and warnings, ASOS observations and digital forecasts for 5x5 kilometer grids.</p>
<p>

The <it>Interactive Weather Information Network (IWIN)</it> is an internet site operated by the NWS that has been superseded by the <it>weather.gov</it> and has recently been proposed for termination. </p>
<p>

Since 1983, the NWS has provided external user access to U.S. Government obtained or derived weather information through a collection of data communication line services called the <it>Family of Services (FOS)</it>. FOS is accessible via dedicated telecommunications access lines in the Washington, D.C., area. All FOS data services are driven by the NWS Telecommunication Gateway computer systems located at NWS headquarters in Silver Spring, MD. Users may obtain any of the individual services from NWS for a one-time connection charge and an annual user fee.</p>
<p>

Every NWS office operates its own web page with access to current products and other information specific to the local area.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Technology</st>
<p>

The <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/314409.xml">
WSR-88D</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/8724.xml">
Doppler</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/675776.xml">
weather radar</link> system, also called <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/314409.xml">
NEXRAD</link></network>
</group>
</system>
, was developed by the NWS during the mid 1980s and fully deployed by the early 1990s. There are 158 such <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/25676.xml">
radar</link> sites in the United States and selected overseas locations. This technology, because of its high resolution and ability to detect intra-cloud motions, is now the cornerstone of NWS severe weather warning operations.</p>
<p>

NWS meteorologists use an advanced information processing, display, and telecommunications system called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/900144.xml">
AWIPS</link> to complete their work. These workstations allow them to easily view a multitude of weather and hydrologic information, as well as compose and disseminate products.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Organization </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 National Weather Service (NWS)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Chief Information Officer</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/1619931.xml">
National Centers for Environmental Prediction</link> (NCEP)</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 <link>
Aviation Weather Center</link> (AWC)</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/15137017.xml">
Climate Prediction Center</link> (CPC)</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/1619939.xml">
Environmental Modeling Center</link> (EMC)</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/1057897.xml">
Hydrometeorological Prediction Center</link> (HPC)</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/19163391.xml">
Ocean Prediction Center</link> (OPC)</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 NCEP Central Operations</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/2096158.xml">
Space Weather Prediction Center</link></phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>
 (SWPC)</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/536249.xml">
Storm Prediction Center</link> (SPC)</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/255317.xml">
Tropical Prediction Center</link> (TPC)</entry>
<entry level="5" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<atmospheric_phenomenon wordnetid="111425580" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<natural_phenomenon wordnetid="111408559" confidence="0.8">
<storm wordnetid="111462526" confidence="0.8">
<hurricane wordnetid="111467018" confidence="0.8">
<physical_phenomenon wordnetid="111419404" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<cyclone wordnetid="111443721" confidence="0.8">
<windstorm wordnetid="111527014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/255317.xml">
National Hurricane Center</link></windstorm>
</cyclone>
</area>
</process>
</phenomenon>
</center>
</physical_phenomenon>
</hurricane>
</storm>
</natural_phenomenon>
</location>
</atmospheric_phenomenon>
</region>
</physical_entity>
 (NHC)</entry>
<entry level="5" type="bullet">

 Tropical Analysis and Forecast Branch (TAFB)</entry>
<entry level="5" type="bullet">

 Technical Support Branch (TSB)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Chief Financial Officer</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Operational Systems</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Hydrologic Development</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Science and Technology</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 Programs and Plans</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 Meteorological Development Laboratory (MDL)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Climate, Water and Weather Services</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 6 Regions</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <image width="150px" src="NOAA-NWS-WFO.jpg">
<caption>

122 Weather Forecast Offices
</caption>
</image>
 (WFOs)</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 21 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/11600474.xml">
Center Weather Service Unit</link>s (CWSU)</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 13 River Forecast Centers (RFC)</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/1359407.xml">
Pacific Tsunami Warning Center</link></administration>
</group>
</instrumentality>
</social_group>
</artifact>
</system>
</body>
 (PTWC)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/11600512.xml">
Spaceflight Meteorology Group</link> (SMG)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controversy</st>

<p>

While generally respected as one of the premier weather organizations in the United States, the National Weather Service has been perceived by some, particularly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/3225498.xml">
libertarian</link>s and commercial weather services such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/652031.xml">
AccuWeather</link></company>
, as competing unfairly with the private sector. In 2005, Senator <senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/214873.xml">
Rick Santorum</link></senator>
 (R-PA) introduced the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/5026496.xml">
National Weather Service Duties Act of 2005</link>, a bill intended to limit the NWS's ability to provide data that could be given just as easily by commercial outlets, but at a cost. The bill was widely criticized by users of the NWS's services. The bill died in committee during the 2005 session.</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weather.gov/organization.php">
NWS Organization Tree</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <military_unit wordnetid="108198398" confidence="0.8">
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<branch wordnetid="108401248" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/1682898.xml">
Signal Corps (United States Army)</link></branch>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</military_unit>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weather.gov/pa/history/timeline.php">
Evolution of theNational Weather Service (Timeline)- Public Affairs Office - Public Affairs - NOAA's National Weather Service</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nws.noaa.gov/pa/history/index.php">
History of the NWS.</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weather.gov/pa/history/timeline.php">
Evolution of the NWS.</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nws.noaa.gov">
National Weather Service</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nws.noaa.gov/nwr/">
NOAA Weather Radio All Hazards</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hpc.ncep.noaa.gov/">
Hydrometeorological Prediction Center</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aviationweather.gov/">
Aviation Weather Center</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nhc.noaa.gov/">
National Hurricane Center</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spc.noaa.gov/">
Storm Prediction Center</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cpc.noaa.gov/">
Climate Prediction Center</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/58232.xml">
United States government agencies</link> involved in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/64919.xml">
Environmental science</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<b><agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
United States Environmental Protection Agency</link></agency>
</b></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<b><agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/70904.xml">
Department of the Interior</link></agency>
</b></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/161535.xml">
National Park Service</link></agency>
&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/75289.xml">
Fish and Wildlife Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/513237.xml">
Bureau of Indian Affairs</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/54139.xml">
Bureau of Land Management</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/1705010.xml">
Minerals Management Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/3475685.xml">
Office of Surface Mining, Reclamation, and Enforcement</link>&nbsp; <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/191640.xml">
Geological Survey</link></agency>
&nbsp; <control wordnetid="105196375" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="105196582" confidence="0.8">
<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/388065.xml">
Bureau of Reclamation</link></power>
</authority>
</control>
&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../076/706076.xml">
Office of Insular Affairs</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/37876.xml">
National Oceanic and
Atmospheric Administration</link></b></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/286989.xml">
National Weather Service</link></agency>
&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/900043.xml">
National Ocean Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/854435.xml">
National Geodetic Survey</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/37876.xml">
National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/1705106.xml">
National Marine Fisheries Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/2080106.xml">
Office of Oceanic and Atmospheric Research</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<b><agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/62866.xml">
Department of Energy</link></agency>
</b></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/10034125.xml">
Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy</link>&nbsp; <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/1704673.xml">
Energy Information Administration</link></agency>
&nbsp; <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/56976.xml">
Federal Energy Regulatory Commission</link></agency>
&nbsp; <link>
Biological and Environmental Research</link>&nbsp; <link>
Office of Environmental Management</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<b><agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/70896.xml">
Department of Agriculture</link></agency>
</b></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/503212.xml">
Farm Service Agency</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/1704694.xml">
Foreign Agricultural Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/1707092.xml">
Risk Management Agency</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/3409918.xml">
Food Safety and Inspection Service</link>&nbsp; <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/42652.xml">
Forest Service</link></agency>
&nbsp; <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/745028.xml">
Natural Resources Conservation Service</link></agency>
&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../124/1707124.xml">
Rural Business-Cooperative Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/1707148.xml">
Office of Community Development</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../203/1707203.xml">
Rural Housing Service</link> &nbsp; <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/140406.xml">
Rural Utilities Service</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/1332977.xml">
Food and Nutrition Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/1707242.xml">
Center for Nutrition Policy and Promotion</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/1706535.xml">
Agricultural Marketing Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/416918.xml">
Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/1711244.xml">
Grain Inspection, Packers and Stockyards Administration</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/251892.xml">
Agricultural Research Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/397270.xml">
Cooperative State Research, Education, and Extension Service</link>&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/1263590.xml">
Economic Research Service</link>&nbsp; <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/1705017.xml">
National Agricultural Statistics Service</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
&nbsp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/2645920.xml">
Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
National Meteorological Organisations</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Europe</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/4219738.xml">
Danish Meteorological Institute</link></agency>
</department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
&nbsp; 
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../074/3372074.xml">
Deutscher Wetterdienst</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/18060166.xml">
Instituto de Meteorologia</link></agency>
</association>
</administrative_unit>
</institute>
&nbsp; 
<link>
Mto-France</link>&nbsp; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/17974353.xml">
Meteo Swiss</link>&nbsp; 
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/319671.xml">
Met Office</link></agency>
&nbsp; 
<link>
Met ireann</link>&nbsp; 
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/9019182.xml">
Norwegian Meteorological Institute</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/4179425.xml">
Royal Netherlands Meteorological Institute (KNMI)</link></administration>
</group>
</agency>
</association>
</administrative_unit>
</social_group>
</body>
</institute>
&nbsp; 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/2014760.xml">
Finnish Meteorological Institute</link></agency>
</association>
</administrative_unit>
</institute>
&nbsp; 
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/7024760.xml">
Czech Hydrometeorological Institute</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/4062914.xml">
Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Institute</link>&nbsp; 
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/16035441.xml">
Royal Meteorological Institute</link></administration>
</group>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
</social_group>
</body>
&nbsp; 
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/8622991.xml">
Turkish State Meteorological Service</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
</p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Asia</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even"><p>

<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/2570742.xml">
Hong Kong Observatory</link></agency>
&nbsp; 
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/2178816.xml">
India Meteorological Department</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/457886.xml">
Japan Meteorological Agency</link></agency>
</location>
</administrative_unit>
</area>
</center>
</region>
&nbsp; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/3704916.xml">
Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration</link>&nbsp; 
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/5371348.xml">
Central Weather Bureau (Taiwan)</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/15540445.xml">
China Meteorological Administration</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/482814.xml">
Afghanistan Meteorological Authority</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/11957738.xml">
Pakistan Meteorological Department</link></agency>
</department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
&nbsp; 
<link>
Direco dos Servios Meteorolgicos e Geofisicos</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Americas</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/59393.xml">
Meteorological Service of Canada</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/286989.xml">
National Weather Service</link></agency>
&nbsp; 
<link>
Servicio Meteorolgico Nacional</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Oceania</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even"><p>

<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/4088114.xml">
Meteorological Service of New Zealand Limited</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/1804661.xml">
Bureau of Meteorology (Australia)</link></agency>
&nbsp; 
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/6334263.xml">
Fiji Meteorological Service</link></administration>
</group>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
</social_group>
</body>
</p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Africa</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/3596004.xml">
South African Weather Service</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp; 
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/15382029.xml">
Mozambique National Institute of Meteorology</link></administration>
</group>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
</social_group>
</body>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</agency>
</article>
