<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:59:10[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Alan Turing&apos;s Unorganized Machines</title>
<id>2873513</id>
<revision>
<id>208253354</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-26T03:18:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Alan Turing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In a far-sighted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/34612.xml">
1948</link> report <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/1208.xml">
Alan Turing</link></scientist>
</person>
 suggested that the infant human cortex was what he called an <it>unorganized machine</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. Turing defined the class of unorganized machines as largely random in their initial construction, but capable of being trained to perform particular tasks. Turing's unorganized machines were in fact very early examples of randomly-connected, binary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/1729542.xml">
neural network</link>s, and Turing claimed that these were the simplest possible model of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../944/21944.xml">
nervous system</link>. <p>

In his 1948 paper Turing defined two examples of his unorganized machines. The first were <it>A-types machines</it> - these being essentially randomly connected networks of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/510001.xml">
NAND</link> logic gates. The second were called <it>B-type machines</it>, which could be created by taking an A-type machine and replacing every inter-node connection with a structure called a <it>connection modifier</it> - which itself is made from A-type nodes. The purpose of the connection modifiers were to allow the B-type machine to undergo "appropriate interference, mimicking education" in order to organize the behaviour of the network to perform useful work. Before the term <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
genetic algorithm</link></it> was coined, Turing even proposed the use of what he called a <it>genetical search</it> to configure his <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://home.clear.net.nz/pages/cw/unorganized.htm">
unorganized machines</weblink>. Turing claimed that the behaviour of B-type machines could be very complex when the number of nodes in the network was large, and stated that the "picture of the cortex as an unorganized machine is very satisfactory from the point of view of evolution and genetics". </p>

<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Turing's 1948 paper has been re-printed as <b>Turing AM.</b> Intelligent Machinery. In: Ince DC, editor. <it>Collected works of AM Turing - Mechanical Intelligence.</it> Elsevier Science Publishers, 1992.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
