<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:03:00[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Predictive Model Markup Language</title>
<id>2876802</id>
<revision>
<id>224394339</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-08T17:38:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>AlistairMcMillan</username>
<id>49523</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Markup languages</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Predictive Model <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/285411.xml">
Markup</link> Language (PMML)</b> is an <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
XML</link></format>
-based language developed by the Data Mining Group (DMG) which provides a way for applications to define statistical and data mining models and to share models between PMML compliant applications.<p>

PMML provides applications a vendor-independent method of defining models so that proprietary issues and incompatibilities are no longer a barrier to the exchange of models between applications. It allows users to develop models within one vendor's application, and use other vendors' applications to visualize, analyze, evaluate or otherwise use the models. Previously, this was very difficult, but with PMML, the exchange of models between compliant applications is now straightforward. </p>
<p>

Since PMML is an XML based standard, the specification comes in the form of an XML Schema.</p>

<sec>
<st>
PMML Components</st>
<p>

PMML follows a very intuitive structure to describe a data mining model, be it an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
artificial neural network</link> or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/226631.xml">
logistic regression</link> model. Sequentially, it can be described by the following components:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Header</b>: contains general information about the PMML document, such as copyright information for the model, its description, and information about the application used to generate the model such as name and version. It also contains an attribute for a timestamp which can be used to specify the date of model creation. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Data Dictionary</b>: contains definitions for all the possible fields used by the model. It is in the data dictionary that a field is defined as continuous, categorical, or ordinal (attribute optype). Depending on this definition, the appropriate value ranges are then defined as well as the data type (such as, string or double). </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Model</b>: contains the definition of the data mining model. A multi-layered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/1706332.xml">
feedforward neural network</link> is the most common neural network representation in contemporary applications, given the popularity and efficacy associated with its training algorithm known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/1360091.xml">
Backpropagation</link>. Such a network is represented in PMML by a "NeuralNetwork" element which contains attributes such as:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Model Name (attribute modelName)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Function Name (attribute functionName)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Algorithm Name (attribute algorithmName)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Activation Function (attribute activationFunction)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Number of Layers (attribute numberOfLayers)</entry>
</list>

This information is then followed by three kinds of neural layers which specify the architecture of the neural network model being represented in the PMML document. These attributes are NeuralInputs, NeuralLayer, and NeuralOutputs. Besides neural networks, PMML allows for the representation of many other data mining models including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/65309.xml">
support vector machines</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/577053.xml">
association rules</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/87339.xml">
naive bayes classifier</link>, clustering models, text models, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/232602.xml">
decision trees</link>, and different regression models.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Mining Schema</b>: the mining schema lists all fields used in the model. This can be a subset of the fields as defined in the data dictionary. It contains specific information about each field, such as:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Name (attribute name): must refer to a field in the data dictionary</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Usage type (attribute usageType): defines the way a field is to be used in the model. Typical values are: active, predicted, and supplementary. Predicted fields are those whose values are predicted by the model. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Outlier Treatment (attribute outliers): defines the outlier treatment to be use. In PMML, outliers can be treated as missing values, as extreme values (based on the definition of high and low values for a particular field), or as is.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Missing Value Replacement Policy (attribute missingValueReplacement): if this attribute is specified then a missing value is automatically replaced by the given values.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Missing Value Treatment (attribute missingValueTreatment): indicates how the missing value replacement was derived (e.g. as value, mean or median).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Data Transformations</b>: transformations allow for the mapping of user data into a more desirable form to be used by the mining model. PMML defines several kinds of simple data transformations. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Normalization: map values to numbers, the input can be continuous or discrete.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Discretization: map continuous values to discrete values.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Value mapping: map discrete values to discrete values.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Functions: derive a value by applying a function to one or more parameters.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Aggregation: used to summarize or collect groups of values.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
PMML Products</st>
<p>

A range of products are being offered to produce and consume PMML:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-306.ibm.com/software/data/db2/warehouse/">
IBM DB2 Data Warehouse Edition</weblink>: produces PMML 3.0 and 3.1 for sequences only models. Consumes (scores and visualizes) PMML 3.1 and earlier.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rattle.togaware.com/">
Rattle</weblink>: Uses the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/376707.xml">
R programming language</link> to build several predictive models. It offers a PMML package to export models built in R to PMML 3.2. This package includes export support for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/65309.xml">
support vector machines</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/17903.xml">
linear regression</link>, and binary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/226631.xml">
logistic regression</link> models. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.salford-systems.com/cart.php">
Salford-Systems CART</weblink>: a decision tree system that produces PMML 3.1.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sas.com/technologies/analytics/datamining/miner/">
SAS Enterprise Miner</weblink>: produces PMML 2.1 for several mining models, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/17903.xml">
linear regression</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/226631.xml">
logistic regression</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/232602.xml">
decision trees</link>, <link>
neural networks</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/1860407.xml">
K-means</link> clustering, and associations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spss.com/spss/family.cfm">
SPSS</weblink>: produces and scores PMML 3.1. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zementis.com/adapa.htm">
Zementis ADAPA</weblink>: batch and real-time scoring of PMML 3.2 and earlier for several mining models, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/232602.xml">
decision trees</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/65309.xml">
support vector machines</link>, <link>
neural networks</link>, linear and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/226631.xml">
logistic regression</link> models.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/ig/adde?hl=en&amp;moduleurl=hosting.gmodules.com/ig/gadgets/file/115640297026242314759/converterwidget.xml">
PMML Converter</weblink> - This is an iGoogle gadget that can be used to convert a variety of PMML elements from older versions (2.1, 3.0 and 3.1) to PMML 3.2. It also validates any PMML file against the PMML schema (for older  versions as well as version 3.2).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/ig/adde?hl=en&amp;moduleurl=hosting.gmodules.com/ig/gadgets/file/115640297026242314759/adapawidget.xml">
ADAPA Predictive Analytics Engine</weblink> - Available as an iGoogle gadget or as a Service through the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/11590152.xml">
Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/15592778.xml">
ADAPA</link> engine can import several PMML models (in version 3.2). After uploading, models are available for scoring or verification. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dmg.org/v3-2/GeneralStructure.html">
PMML 3.2 Specification</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dmg.org/index.html">
Data Mining Group Home</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
