<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:43:41[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<worker  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109632518">
<laborer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110241300">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<workman  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110791221">
<stevedore  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110655169">
<employee  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110053808">
<header>
<title>GNU GRUB</title>
<id>287817</id>
<revision>
<id>242967630</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-04T14:22:44Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>RussBot</username>
<id>279219</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>System software</category>
<category>Boot loaders</category>
<category>GNU project</category>
<category>GNU project software</category>
<category>Research projects</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Software</name>
<parameters>
<genre>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml">
Bootloader</link></genre>
<screenshot>
<image width="150px" src="Grub2.png">
<caption>

Grub2.png
</caption>
</image>
</screenshot>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/">
www.gnu.org/software/grub</weblink></website>
<latest_release_version>
1.96</latest_release_version>
<developer>
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/275549.xml">
GNU Project</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</developer>
<name>
GNU GRUB</name>
<latest_release_date>
2008-02-03; 438 days ago</latest_release_date>
<caption>
a GNU GRUB logo</caption>
<license>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GNU General Public License</link></license>
</parameters>
</template>


"GRUB" redirects here. For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/74194.xml">
grub (disambiguation)</link>.

<p>

<b>GNU GRUB</b> ("GRUB" for short) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml">
boot loader</link> package from the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/275549.xml">
GNU Project</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
. GRUB is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/2484864.xml">
reference implementation</link> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/3159572.xml">
Multiboot Specification</link>, which allows a user to have several different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>s on their computer at once, and to choose which one to run when the computer starts. GRUB can be used to select from different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/50394.xml">
kernel images</link> available on a particular operating system's partitions, as well as to pass boot-time parameters to such kernels.</p>
<p>

GNU GRUB developed from a previous package called the <b>Grand Unified Bootloader</b> (a play on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/12610.xml">
grand unified theory</link>). It is predominantly used on <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/31815.xml">
Unix-like</link></family>
 systems; the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/11875.xml">
GNU operating system</link> uses GNU GRUB as its boot loader, as do most general-purpose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/18212.xml">
Linux distribution</link>s. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/46145.xml">
Solaris</link> has used GRUB as its bootloader on x86 systems since the Solaris 10 1/06 release.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Features </st>
<p>

GRUB is dynamically configurable; it loads its configuration at startup, allowing boot-time changes such as selecting different kernels or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/3137188.xml">
initial RAM disks</link>. To this end, GRUB provides a simple, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/4547.xml">
bash</link>-like, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/6707.xml">
command line interface</link> which lets users write new boot sequences.</p>
<p>

GRUB is highly portable. It supports multiple executable formats, and is geometry translation independent; while Multiboot compliant, it supports non-multiboot operating systems such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> and <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/22409.xml">
OS/2</link></O>
 via a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/5481027.xml">
chain loading</link> function. GRUB supports all commonly used Unix file systems as well as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/53045.xml">
VFAT</link> and <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/39184.xml">
NTFS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 as used by Windows, and supports <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/404839.xml">
Logical Block Address</link> (LBA) mode. GRUB allows users to view the contents of files on any supported file system. </p>
<p>

GRUB can be used with a variety of different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/45249.xml">
user interface</link>s. Most Linux distributions take advantage of GRUB's support for a graphical interface to provide a customized boot menu with a background image, and occasionally mouse support. GRUB's text interface can be set to use a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/77359.xml">
serial link</link> to provide a <link>
remote terminal</link> boot loader access.</p>
<p>

GRUB can download operating system images from a network, and can thus support disk-free systems. GRUB supports automatic decompression of OS images prior to booting from them.</p>
<p>

GRUB differs from other boot loaders by being able to communicate with a user directly via a GRUB prompt.  A GRUB prompt is the stage before GRUB loads an operating system and can be triggered at a text-mode GRUB booting screen (which is controlled by the configuration file "menu.lst" (or "grub.conf": see below)) by pressing the "c" key.  A GRUB prompt (similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/4547.xml">
bash</link>) can also be obtained by booting GRUB as a stand alone system without an operating system attached or in any GRUB installation with an operating system when the "menu.lst" file is absent.  From the GRUB prompt a user can manually select and control booting from any installed operating system by using bash-like commands.  To boot an operating system automatically, the appropriate commands are placed in a configuration file called "menu.lst" in a designated subdirectory.</p>
<p>

GRUB has a rich set of terminal commands that allow a user at the GRUB prompt to view the partition details of the hard disks, alter a partition setting, re-map the disk order temporarily, boot any user-defined configuration file and to view booting configuration of other boot loaders in file formats GRUB supports.  Thus, without prior knowledge of what is installed on a computer one can use GRUB from an external device such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/10891.xml">
floppy disk</link>, <link>
USB</link> device or a <recording wordnetid="104063868" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<sound_recording wordnetid="104262678" confidence="0.8">
<memory_device wordnetid="103744840" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<phonograph_record wordnetid="103924069" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/18959902.xml">
CD-ROM</link></medium>
</phonograph_record>
</device>
</memory_device>
</sound_recording>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</recording>
 to boot up an installed operating system.</p>
<p>

GRUB uses a scrolling screen for selection of operating systems to boot.  This means 150 or more booting choices can be controlled by GRUB with ease by adding each to the "menu.lst" configuration file, and selecting one at boot time using the arrow keys. </p>
<p>

One boot loader can boot another boot loader by <it>chainloading</it>.  GRUB uses the same two to three lines of command sequences to boot any <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/8146.xml">
DOS</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link>, <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/1223807.xml">
BSD</link> or <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/46145.xml">
Solaris</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
 system, making it very easy to work with.</p>
<p>

Although GNU GRUB can be pre-packaged or retro-built into <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/31815.xml">
Unix-like</link></family>
 operating systems, there are also specific GRUB implementations for DOS and Windows. GRUB can also be installed as a stand alone system unattached to any operating system. Its implementation requires one file for booting from a CD and two files for booting from a floppy, hard disk or a USB device.  These files are available from any Linux Live CD that supports GRUB, making it easily and freely obtainable by computer users.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Boot process </st>

<p>

When a computer is turned on, the computer's <generic wordnetid="107899976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/Form_4473.xml">
BIOS</link></generic>
 finds the primary bootable device (usually the computer's hard disk) and loads the initial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/6885679.xml">
bootstrap</link> program from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/55389.xml">
master boot record</link> (MBR), the first 512 bytes of the hard disk, and then transfers control to this code.</p>
<p>

The MBR contains GRUB stage 1. Given the small size of the MBR, Stage 1 does little more than load the next stage of GRUB (which may reside physically elsewhere on the disk). Stage 1 can either load Stage 2 directly, or it can load stage 1.5: GRUB Stage 1.5 is located in the first 30 kilobytes of hard disk immediately following the MBR. Stage 1.5 loads Stage 2. </p>
<p>

When GRUB Stage 2 receives control, it presents an interface to the user in order to select which operating system to boot. This normally takes the form of a graphical menu, although if this is not available or the user wishes further control, GRUB has its own command prompt, where the user can manually specify the boot parameters. GRUB can also be set to automatically load a particular kernel after a timeout period.</p>
<p>

Once boot options have been selected, GRUB loads the selected kernel into memory and passes control on to the kernel, which then continues to start itself. At this stage GRUB can also pass control of the boot process to another loader, using <it>chain loading</it>, for operating systems  such as Windows that do not support the Multiboot standard. In this case, copies of the other system's boot programs have been saved by GRUB; instead of a kernel, the other system is loaded as though it had been started from the MBR. This may be yet another boot manager, such as the Microsoft boot menu, allowing further selection of non-Multiboot operating systems. (This behavior is often automatic when modern Linux distributions are installed "on top of" existing Windows systems, allowing the user to retain the original operating system without modification, including systems that contain multiple versions of Windows.)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Installation </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="GRUB_screenshot.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

GRUB in non-graphical mode
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

A key feature of GRUB is that it can be installed without being attached to an operating system, however it needs a copy of a Linux image for such an installation.  Working as a stand alone system it is virtually a mini system in its own right and able to boot all the installed major operating systems by a method known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/5481027.xml">
Chain loading</link>.   </p>
<p>

Unlike <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/287810.xml">
LILO</link></software>
, there is no need to reinstall GRUB to the MBR or a partition after a change to the configuration file.</p>
<p>

In Linux, the "grub-install" command is used to install stage1 to either the MBR or a partition. GRUB's configuration file, stage2 (usually), and other files must be in a usable partition. If these files or the partition become unavailable stage1 will drop the user to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/6707.xml">
command line interface</link>.</p>
<p>

The name and disk location of the GRUB configuration file varies from system to system; for example, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/8242.xml">
Debian GNU/Linux</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/2399620.xml">
openSUSE</link> the file is stored in /boot/grub/menu.lst while <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/9951070.xml">
Fedora</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
 and <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/94419.xml">
Gentoo Linux</link></O>
 uses /boot/grub/grub.conf. Fedora also provides a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/180473.xml">
symbolic link</link> from /etc/grub.conf to /boot/grub/grub.conf for <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/287790.xml">
FHS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 compatibility reasons and other thus distros can establish symbolic links to the three locations.</p>
<p>

Instead of being installed on the system's hard disk, GRUB can be installed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/347100.xml">
removable media</link> such as an optical drive (bios access, and <pause wordnetid="115271008" confidence="0.8">
<extension wordnetid="115272382" confidence="0.8">
<time_interval wordnetid="115269513" confidence="0.8">
<delay wordnetid="115272029" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/998659.xml">
el-torito</link></delay>
</time_interval>
</extension>
</pause>
), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/10891.xml">
floppy disk</link> or <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/400414.xml">
USB flash drive</link></medium>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 in order to bring up a system which may not have or cannot boot from its own disk.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Development </st>

<p>

The most used version of GRUB is referred to as "GRUB Legacy". This version is still receiving bug fixes but no new features are being added. The GRUB developers have switched their focus to GRUB 2, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/13653181.xml">
complete rewrite</link> whose goals include making GNU GRUB cleaner, safer, more robust, more portable and more powerful. GRUB 2 started under the name <b>PUPA</b>. PUPA was supported by the <link>
Information-technology Promotion Agency</link> (IPA) in Japan. PUPA was integrated into GRUB 2 development around 2002, when the GRUB version 0.9x was renamed GRUB Legacy. When GRUB 2 is released it will bear the name GNU GRUB. As of February 2008, GRUB 2 is still in development, is not ready for production use, and is not documented.</p>
<p>

Some of the goals of the project include support for non-x86 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/81196.xml">
platforms</link>, <link>
internationalization</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/126843.xml">
localization</link>, non-ASCII characters, <link>
dynamic modules</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/66924.xml">
memory management</link>, a scripting <link>
mini-language</link>, migrating platform specific (x86) code to platform specific modules, and an object-oriented framework.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Variants </st>
<p>

Since GRUB Legacy is still the most widely used version among end users, but official development is being done on a different version, several other projects maintain their own enhancements (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/301506.xml">
forks</link>) to the GRUB Legacy code in the meantime.  These include <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.supergrubdisk.org/">
Super Grub Disk</weblink> (new commands include "setgrubdevice" and "usbshift") and [https://gna.org/projects/grub4dos/ GRUB for DOS] (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://svn.gna.org/viewcvs/grub4dos/trunk/README_GRUB4DOS.txt?view=auto">
several commands</weblink> were enhanced, including "find --set-root", "map --hook", and "cdrom").</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 GRUB editors </st>
<p>

<image width="250px" src="StartUp-Manager.png" type="thumb">
</image>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/18420309.xml">
StartUp-Manager</link> is a program that can edit many GRUB options.</p>
<p>

KGRUBEditor is a system <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
GUI</link> tool to view and edit the GRUB boot loader,  written in the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/16629.xml">
KDE</link></software>
4 libraries. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Grub Conf is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/12362.xml">
GNOME</link>2 based GRUB configuration editor. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

grub-choose-default controls the default entry in menu.lst, through a <link>
Python</link> GUI.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Under Windows if you are running <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/39194.xml">
ext2</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/39195.xml">
3</link>, then you can use Ext2IFS <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

GrubEd is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/29292.xml">
script</link> which gives users a nice GUI to alter their grub settings at the touch of (a few) buttons. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Utilities </st>
<p>

GRUB Utilities is a collection of multi platform utilities for GRUB Legacy, GRUB2 and GRUB for DOS. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brady, Pádraig.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pixelbeat.org/docs/disk/">
Details of GRUB on the PC</weblink>".&#32;  pixelbeat.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-11-22</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Okuji, Yoshinori.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/">
GNU GRUB</weblink>".&#32;  gnu.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-29</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Notes </st>



</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Free_Software_Portal_Logo.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Free software&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/2114553.xml">
bootman</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<laborer wordnetid="110241300" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<workman wordnetid="110791221" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<employee wordnetid="110053808" confidence="0.8">
<stevedore wordnetid="110655169" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/4412616.xml">
Das U-Boot</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</stevedore>
</employee>
</act>
</workman>
</undertaking>
</laborer>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</event>
</person>
</work>
</physical_entity>
 Universal Bootloader</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/4011296.xml">
elilo</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/287810.xml">
LILO</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/22091.xml">
Ncurses</link></software>
 and Ncurses package for Windows in <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/2636598.xml">
GnuWin32</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<laborer wordnetid="110241300" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<workman wordnetid="110791221" confidence="0.8">
<stevedore wordnetid="110655169" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<employee wordnetid="110053808" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/287844.xml">
NTLDR</link></employee>
</part>
</stevedore>
</workman>
</causal_agent>
</laborer>
</worker>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/3872262.xml">
SILO</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/5881986.xml">
BCD</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/2451142.xml">
xOSL</link> Extended Operating System Loader</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/">
GNU GRUB Website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/manual">
Official GNU GRUB manual</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/grub-2.en.html">
GRUB 2 Home Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lists.gnu.org/mailman/listinfo/help-grub">
Official help-grub email list</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://grub.enbug.org/FrontPage">
GRUB  wiki</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jbakshi.50webs.com/Linux_tutorial/GRUB/GNU%20GRUB%20simplified.html">
GNU GRUB (0.97) Simplified for Newbies</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pixelbeat.org/docs/disk/">
Structure at the start of a hard disk in a PC and how GRUB fits into that structure</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.supergrubdisk.org/">
Super Grub Disk</weblink>: a boot utility that can restore and repair overwritten and misconfigured GRUB installs or directly boot various operating systems. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sarovar.org/projects/grub4dos/">
GRUB4DOS</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://grub4dos.sourceforge.net/wiki/">
 Wiki</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boot-land.net/forums/?showforum=66">
Forum</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geocities.com/lode_leroy/grubinstall/">
WINGRUB: a GRUB installer for Windows</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.linuxdevcenter.com/pub/a/linux/2008/01/22/lilo-and-grub-boot-loaders-made-simple.html">
LILO and GRUB: Boot Loaders Made Simple by Judith Myerson</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/4622">
Boot with GRUB</weblink>, <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/233831.xml">
Linux Journal</link></web_site>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</product>
</magazine>
</publication>
</medium>
</machine>
</press>
</print_media>
</creation>
</computer>
</work>
 - A good tutorial</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.justlinux.com/forum/showthread.php?threadid=147959">
How to install and boot 145 OS in a PC (using GRUB)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://users.bigpond.net.au/hermanzone/p15.htm#How_to_add_Grub_to_your_USB_thumb_drive.">
How to add GRUB to your USB thumb drive.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/275549.xml">
GNU Project</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
History</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/12592.xml">
GNU Manifesto</link></medium>
</end_product>
</oeuvre>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
&nbsp;·  <group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/18949437.xml">
Free Software Foundation</link></group>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/9374064.xml">
History of free software</link></col>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 0px 0px 2px;" rowspan="9">
<image width="64px" src="Heckert_GNU_white.svg">
<caption>

GNU is not a gnu
</caption>
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Licences</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GNU General Public License</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/13073.xml">
GNU Lesser General Public License</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/6842801.xml">
Affero General Public License</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/18938782.xml">
GNU Free Documentation License</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/390406.xml">
GPL linking exception</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Software</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/11875.xml">
GNU</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/8820973.xml">
variants</link>)&nbsp;·  <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/13236.xml">
Hurd</link></software>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/12362.xml">
GNOME</link>&nbsp;·  <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/7404018.xml">
Gnuzilla</link></software>
&nbsp;·  <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<browser wordnetid="106571301" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/9937024.xml">
IceCat</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</browser>
</program>
</application>
</software>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.8">
<contestant wordnetid="109613191" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/2844806.xml">
Gnash</link></causal_agent>
</contestant>
</player>
</person>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/4547.xml">
Bash</link>&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<compiler wordnetid="109946957" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/12323.xml">
GCC</link></writer>
</causal_agent>
</compiler>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/18933234.xml">
GNU Emacs</link>&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/324364.xml">
glibc</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/940194.xml">
Coreutils</link>&nbsp;·  <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<tool wordnetid="104451818" confidence="0.8">
<implement wordnetid="103563967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/171984.xml">
Build system</link></implement>
</tool>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/774936.xml">
Other GNU packages and programs</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Public speakers</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../966/801966.xml">
Robert J. Chassell</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
Loïc Dachary</link>&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<computer_user wordnetid="109951274" confidence="0.8">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/10561686.xml">
Ricardo Galli</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</engineer>
</programmer>
</computer_user>
</person>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<disputant wordnetid="109615465" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<reformer wordnetid="110515194" confidence="0.8">
<computer_user wordnetid="109951274" confidence="0.8">
<militant wordnetid="110315837" confidence="0.8">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/1303429.xml">
Georg C. F. Greve</link></causal_agent>
</engineer>
</programmer>
</militant>
</computer_user>
</reformer>
</person>
</disputant>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<computer_user wordnetid="109951274" confidence="0.8">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/3864098.xml">
Federico Heinz</link></causal_agent>
</engineer>
</programmer>
</computer_user>
</person>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/3306645.xml">
Benjamin Mako Hill</link></research_worker>
</person>
&nbsp;·  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/1609799.xml">
Bradley M. Kuhn</link></person>
&nbsp;·  <celebrity wordnetid="109903153" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/383972.xml">
Eben Moglen</link></celebrity>
&nbsp;·  <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/3434143.xml">
Richard Stallman</link></person>
</president>
&nbsp;·  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/12284380.xml">
John Sullivan</link></person>
&nbsp;·  <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/7122587.xml">
Leonard H. Tower Jr.</link></scientist>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other topics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/501787.xml">
GNU/Linux naming controversy</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</disagreement>
</dispute>
</event>
</controversy>
&nbsp;·  <product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.8">
<show wordnetid="106619065" confidence="0.8">
<documentary wordnetid="106616806" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/186501.xml">
Revolution OS</link></psychological_feature>
</documentary>
</show>
</movie>
</social_event>
</event>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</employee>
</stevedore>
</workman>
</causal_agent>
</laborer>
</worker>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
