<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:59:26[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108435388">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<network  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108434259">
<header>
<title>Contact network</title>
<id>2878553</id>
<revision>
<id>237969355</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-12T17:17:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CanadianLinuxUser</username>
<id>6847637</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Social networks</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

A <b>contact network</b> is a minimal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link> in which people are not assumed to have any relationship other than to be able to contact each other - perhaps only to refer items of mutual interest in politics or business, that imply no longstanding collaboration or relationship or trust with each other.</p>
<p>

Study of contact networks is central to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/2861.xml">
advertising</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/59252.xml">
marketing</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/1123386.xml">
political marketing</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/24389.xml">
public relations</link> in particular, since spreads of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/254054.xml">
rumour</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/4819416.xml">
hearsay</link> are thought to follow contact networks closely.  A <link>
phone tree</link> or buddy list for instance, especially when combined with technologies such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/28207.xml">
SMS</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/287872.xml">
flash mob</link>s, are well known ways to spread requests, rumours or news. </p>
<p>

Unlike social networks, once the rumour is passed on, the ability to rein it in or restrict or qualify it may be very limited.  Members of a contact network do not in general follow up claims or issues with each other as members of social networks do (or are thought to do).</p>
<p>

Contact networks are also thought central to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/2040972.xml">
power network</link> analysis because people ally, for purposes of achieving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/147885.xml">
power (sociology)</link>, even with those with whom they have no social contact, do not like, and would otherwise not work with at all.  A <b>contact</b> is thus something less even than a "<link>
weak friend</link>" or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/161744.xml">
acquaintance</link>.  </p>
<p>

More than 200 such weak friends can exist in a true social network, but contact networks can be much larger - and are subject to such odd concepts as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/6968.xml">
customer relationship management</link>."</p>
<p>

Technologically, contact networks have tended to expand with the ease of sending and receiving people's contact information.  Some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/341419.xml">
semantic link</link> conventions such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/2917772.xml">
hCard</link> have developed to facilitate just such a spread.  Most <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/283329.xml">
Personal Information Manager</link> tools also handle contact networks easily, even if they have poor facilities for handling relationships <it>as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/2041117.xml">
social network service</link>s tend to specialize in.</it></p>
<p>

Receiving or facilitating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/459847.xml">
spam</link> is thought to be often a consequence of having many contacts, as a penetrated email account can often be used to spread much of it, without the contact necessarily complaining to the sender, as they would in a true social network.</p>


</bdy>
</network>
</group>
</system>
</article>
