<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 19:59:42[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Herb Jepko</title>
<id>2884260</id>
<revision>
<id>243227132</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T18:17:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DevorahLeah</username>
<id>5836431</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>1995 deaths</category>
<category>People from Salt Lake City, Utah</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Herb Jepko</b> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/14563107.xml">
March 20</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/34608.xml">
1931</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/20587.xml">
March 31</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/34658.xml">
1995</link>) was an influential <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/15368428.xml">
radio</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/87893.xml">
talk show</link> host in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/53837.xml">
Salt Lake City</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
  from 1964 to 1990.  He was the first radio talk show host to do a nationally syndicated, satellite-delivered program.
<sec>
<st>
Early Years</st>

<p>

According to the Arizona Department of Health Services, Herb Jepko was born in Hayden, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/5399.xml">
Colorado</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 to a single mother named Mary Irene Parke. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://genealogy.az.gov/">
http://genealogy.az.gov/</weblink> He was originally named William, but when he was adopted by Metro and Nellie Jepko of <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/106793.xml">
Prescott, Arizona</link></village>
, they renamed him Herbert Earl Jepko. Unfortunately, Metro and Nellie's marriage was not a happy one. After they divorced, Metro got custody, but he was a wounded <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/4764461.xml">
World War I</link></conflict>
 veteran, and he soon took ill. With his father unable to care for him, Herb had to spend time in foster care off and on. He attended school in Prescott, but then his father got healthy enough to take care of him again, and in 1949, they moved to <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/49121.xml">
Phoenix</link></village>
. Herb graduated high school there, and briefly attended <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/2053869.xml">
Phoenix College</link></university>
, which was then a small two-year college and is today flagship of the Maricopa Community College system. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.maricopa.edu/">
http://www.maricopa.edu/</weblink> He hoped to become a doctor, but soon ran out of money and was drafted into the Army. (1) It was during his time in the military that he discovered his life's work-- radio, working in Radio-Television Operations while serving in the <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/16772.xml">
Korean War</link></conflict>
. </p>
<p>

After completing his military service, he found work in radio at several stations around the Western United States, including KVNA in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/57554.xml">
Flagstaff</link></village>
, AZ and <radio_station wordnetid="104044119" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/574914.xml">
KFI</link></radio_station>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/18110.xml">
Los Angeles</link>. It was while he was the promotion director at KFI that he was influenced by a popular late night host named <link>
Ben Hunter</link>, whose overnight call-in program was called the Night Owl show. Hunter's work was getting a lot of positive attention, and Herb was impressed with how loyal the late-night audience was. He stayed in LA throughout the rest of the 50s, where he married Patsy Little Brown (listeners would later know her as 'Pat'). Herb, Patsy and their five children from previous marriages moved to <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/53837.xml">
Salt Lake City</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, her home town, in the early 1960s. They would later have one child together, Herb Jepko Junior (Jep or Jeppy). By all accounts, they deeply loved each other and their relationship was a strong one.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Radio Career</st>

<p>

Herb was hired by several Salt Lake City-area stations, including KCPX, where he played jazz for the late night audience; and a new station, KANN in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/270467.xml">
Ogden</link> UT, where he did the afternoon drive shift. Then, in 1962, Herb joined radio station <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/1083500.xml">
KSL</link> first doing mid-days, and then in April 1963, becoming the station's morning show disc jockey, a shift he held throughout the rest of 1963. Despite being in a very visible shift, Herb was puzzled that a powerful station like KSL (with a booming signal that could be heard in a number of states) signed off at midnight. He knew how successful Ben Hunter's show had been, and he believed there was a similar late night audience in Salt Lake City that was not being served. So he decided to do something about it. On 11 February 1964, Herb's late-night show made its debut. It was an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/1441840.xml">
open-mic</link> call-in show, initially known as "The Other Side of the Day," and later named the "Nitecaps" in a contest for a new name held among listeners early in the show's first year. By early November 1975, this show would become the first nationally <link>
syndicated</link> talk show, when the <network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/187326.xml">
Mutual Broadcasting System</link></network>
 agreed to syndicate it.</p>
<p>

Jepko's groundbreaking syndication is often cited as the pioneering kick-start for nationally broadcast talk-radio that allowed for the prominence of such hosts as <actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/301864.xml">
Larry King</link></actor>
 and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/273444.xml">
Phil Donahue</link></person>
. Ironically, when Jepko's Mutual contract was terminated on 29 May 1977, he was replaced first by Long John Nebel and Candy Jones (a husband and wife team), and then six months later (following Long John's untimely death) by Larry King. (Jepko had evidently been offered a chance to stay with Mutual if he would become more controversial and try to attract a younger audience, but he adamantly refused, feeling he had an obligation to his existing, largely rural and older listeners.) (2)</p>
<p>

"The Herb Jepko Nitecap Show" was idiosyncratic, never focusing one any single topic. Carrying a laid-back atmosphere inherent to its (then unusual) 12:00 AM - 6:00 AM time slot, the show consisted entirely of listener call-ins: any subject the listener wished to talk about, no matter how big or small, was allowed, and the only forbidden topics were politics and denominational religion. Later, as the show became more popular, callers were limited to one call every two weeks of no more than 5 minutes. Jepko would run a recording of "Tinkerbell," a music box rendition of the song "Never On Sunday," to indicate that the caller's time was done.</p>
<p>

Many of the listeners were elderly or shut-ins, or long-distance truckers, but a number were insomniacs who enjoyed hearing a friendly voice. And in a world of angry talkers, Jepko, whose listeners called him "Herbie," was known for being friendly, warm, and thoroughly non-controversial. He told an interviewer in 1965 that he hoped his show would contribute to "good will and understanding," and that his listeners would feel they were part of a family. (3)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Jepko and the Nitecaps</st>

<p>

"Nitecaps" was more than just a radio show. It was a club -- the Nitecaps International Association. Local members formed chapters, called "Nitestands." Members took Jepko's message about good will to heart, and volunteered their time to the elderly, ill, service men and women and shut-ins; Nitestands were not only for socializing with other fans of the show, but they were an opportunity to do charitable work in each local community. And sometimes, Jepko would come to town and do a live broadcast.  Additionally, Herb and Patsy sponsored an annual convention for members, giving them an opportunity to meet each other.  That sense of community was especially important, and Jepko promoted it whenever possible.  The Nitecaps show had its own magazine, called "The Wick," and its own theme song  -- written by listener Della Dame, and performed by local musician Don Ray; it can be heard here.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nitecaps.net/audioclips.htm">
http://www.nitecaps.net/audioclips.htm</weblink>.  (The song was chosen by listeners from another on-air contest of listener created songs).  Jepko also created a Nitecaps travel agency, and an insurance company, as well as compiling recipe books from recipes sent in by listeners.  In fact, any Nitecaps listener could find a variety of merchandise that was available for purchase, often marketed in the pages of the Wick. (4)</p>
<p>

Although his fans adored him and loved the show, Jepko was dropped by MBS from syndication in late May 1977. His fans were very upset and insisted that he somehow stay on the air, so Jepko cobbled together fourteen stations, including the powerful KSL, which became the new "Nitecap Radio Network." Unfotunately by this time (unlike the early 1960s), Herb had plently of late-night competition including 24-hour television, cable tv, 24-hour radio stations, and Larry King. When KSL dropped the show in late 1978, Herb continued the show on a handful of stations, eventually bankrupting his personal assets in an effort to keep going.  Several attempts were made to resurrect the program, indluding one with clear-channel WOAI in the early 1980s, but none proved successful or long-lasting.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Final Years</st>

<p>

Despite how popular he was with his fans, Jepko did not significantly profit from his work. According to a former colleague, his Nitecaps show had been financially successful, but his deal with Mutual was not to his advantage. Where he and his staff had done all the selling of commercial time on the  KSL program, the Mutual network insisted on doing the selling for the syndicated show. That would have been fine if Mutual understood how to sell late night radio, which was (and still is) largely driven by direct-response advertising (rather than ratings, or cost-per-point appeals). Unfortunately, there were problems almost immediately, resulting in on-going friction between the way Mutual wanted things done and how Jepko thought things ought to be.  Jepko ended up convinced that Mutual did not understand his unique audience. Mutual, on the other hand, faced with challenges gaining affiliate clearances for the show (only 70 or so of MBS's over 500 affiliates ever carried the show) decided Jepko's audience was too old, too rural, and not large enough to bring in a profit for the network. As Jepko perceived it, Mutual betrayed their original contract with him and gave up on the show. By the time Jepko's contract ended, Jepko had lost whatever money his original Nitecaps show had brought him. (5)</p>
<p>

In addition to losing the show he loved, he had also endured the tragedy of losing his youngest son, Herbert Earl Jr., who died of AIDS in 1992. Jepko's health sharply declined after that, and there is anecdotal evidence from former colleagues that he had a drinking problem (6), which escalated during this period of time. The cause of his death was given as "liver failure." (7)</p>
<p>

Some of his former listeners still recall him fondly as proving that a talk show could be kinder and gentler and still attract a wide audience at a time when radio was becoming more controversial and talkers more angry.</p>
<p>

Herb Jepko was posthumously inducted into the Utah Broadcaster Association's Hall of Fame in 2003, and there is an effort to establish a Memorial scholarship fund in his name at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/32097.xml">
University of Utah</link></university>
, see www.nitecaps.net link below.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Works cited</st>

<p>

(1) Hilly Rose. "But That's Not What I Called About." Chicago: Contemporary Books, 1978, p. 48.</p>
<p>

(2) Lynn Arave. "Utahn Helped Shape U.S. Radio." Deseret (Salt Lake City) Morning News, 16 February 2007.</p>
<p>

(3) James Bapis. "Utah Radio Program Rekindles Human Values, Listeners Say." Ogden (UT) Standard-Examiner, 25 July 1965, p. 16.</p>
<p>

(4) Mitch Broder. "Small-talk Show is Big Draw in Wee Hours." New York Times, 23 February 1975, p. D29.</p>
<p>

(5) Michael Keith (editor). <it>Sounds in the Night</it>. Ames IA: Iowa State University Press, 2001. (quoted material comes from pp. 96-8)</p>
<p>

(6) Keith, p.218; see also Mark Fisher. <it>Something in the Air</it>. New York: Random House, 2007. quote comes from p. 117)</p>
<p>

(7) "Herb Jepko, Friend of Insomniacs Across the Nation, Dies at Age 64." Salt Lake City (UT) Tribune, 2 April 1995, p. B3.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=6953556">
Biography at Find-A-Grave</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nitecaps.net">
 A Nitecap fan website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rwonline.com/pages/s.0106/t.14502.html">
Jepko’s Was a Gentle Voice in the Night, July 2008 article in Radio World</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
