<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:03:40[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Schopenhauer&apos;s criticism of the Kantian philosophy</title>
<id>2890279</id>
<revision>
<id>225125533</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-12T00:30:32Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Alexbot</username>
<id>5517884</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Kantianism</category>
<category>Arthur Schopenhauer</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/700.xml">
Schopenhauer</link> appended a criticism to the first volume of his <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/1313078.xml">
The World as Will and Representation</link></it>. He wanted to show <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/14631.xml">
Kant</link>'s errors so that Kant's merits would be appreciated and his achievements furthered.
<sec>
<st>
 Kant's merits </st>
<p>
 
According to Schopenhauer's essay. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/14631.xml">
Kant</link>'s three main merits are as follows: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1. The distinction of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/60931.xml">
phenomenon</link> from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/102803.xml">
thing-in-itself</link>.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/519280.xml">
intellect</link> mediates between things and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/243391.xml">
knowledge</link>.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/16143.xml">
Locke's</link></philosopher>
</person>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/7295638.xml">
primary qualities</link> result from the mind's activity, just as his secondary qualities result from receptivity at any of the five <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/43912.xml">
senses</link>.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/6679056.xml">
A priori</link></it> knowledge is separate from <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/6679056.xml">
a posteriori</link></it> knowledge.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/15428.xml">
ideal</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/43854.xml">
real</link> are diverse from each other.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/1666427.xml">
Transcendental</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/13692155.xml">
philosophy</link> goes beyond <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/44941.xml">
dogmatic</link> philosophy's "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/247304.xml">
eternal</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/29920.xml">
truth</link>s," such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/3011743.xml">
principle of contradiction</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/1137736.xml">
principle of sufficient reason</link>. It shows that those "truths" are based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/369081.xml">
necessary</link> forms of thought that exist in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/3717.xml">
brain</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2. The explanation of how the moral significance of human conduct is different from the laws that are concerned with phenomena. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The significance is directly related to the thing-in-itself, the innermost nature of the world.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

3. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/25414.xml">
Religious</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/39872.xml">
scholastic</link> philosophy is completely overthrown by the demonstration of the impossibility of proofs for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/1126522.xml">
speculative</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/30503.xml">
theology</link> and also for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/236822.xml">
rational</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
psychology</link>, or reasoned study of the soul.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Schopenhauer also said that Kant's discussion, on pages A534 to A550, of the contrast between empirical and intelligible characters is one of Kant's most profound ideas. Schopenhauer asserted that it is among the most admirable things ever said by a human.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The empirical character of a phenomenon is completely determined. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The intelligible character of a phenomenon is free. It is the thing-in-itself which is experienced as a phenomenon.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Kant's faults </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Fundamental error </st>

<ss3>
<st>
Perceptions and Concepts</st>
<p>

Kant did not distinguish between concrete,  <faculty wordnetid="105650329" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/154170.xml">
intuitive</link></faculty>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/25140.xml">
perceptual</link> knowledge of objects and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
abstract</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/3754374.xml">
discursive</link>, conceptual, knowledge of thoughts.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kant began his investigation into knowledge of perceived objects by considering indirect, reflective knowledge of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/6978.xml">
concepts</link> instead of direct, intuitive knowledge of perceptions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 For Kant, there is absolutely no knowledge of an object unless there is thought which employs abstract concepts. For him, perception is not knowledge because it is not thought. In general, Kant claimed that perception is mere <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/242682.xml">
sensation</link>. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

In accordance with Kant's claim, non-human animals would not be able to know objects. Animals would only know impressions on their sense organs, which Kant mistakenly called perception. Kant had erroneously asserted that full, perceived objects, not mere sensations, were given to the mind by the sense organs. Perception, however, according to Schopenhauer, is intellectual and is a product of the Understanding. Perception of an object does not result from the mere data of the senses. It requires the Understanding. Therefore, if animals do not have Understanding, in accordance with Kant, then they have only Sensation, which, Schopenhauer claimed, gives only raw sense data, not perceived objects. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer considered the following sentences on page A253 of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/347543.xml">
The Critique of Pure Reason</link></it> to encapsulate all of Kant's errors:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>If all thought (by means of categories) is taken away from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/10174.xml">
empirical</link> knowledge, no knowledge of any object remains, because nothing can be thought by mere intuition or perception. The simple fact that there is within me an affection of my sensibility, establishes in no way any relation of such a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/991606.xml">
representation</link> to any object.''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

On page A253, Kant stated that no knowledge of any object would remain if all thought by means of categories was removed from empirical knowledge.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer claimed that perception of an object occurs without conceptual thought.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

On page A253, Kant stated that a concept without an intuition is not empty. It still has the form of thought.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer claimed that perceived representations are the content of a concept. Without them, the concept is empty.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss3>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Secondary errors </st>

<ss2>
<st>
 Transcendental analytic </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kant asserted that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/18895.xml">
metaphysics</link> is knowledge <it>a priori</it>, or before experience. As a result, he concluded that the source of metaphysics cannot be inner or outer experience.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer claimed that metaphysics must understand inner and outer experience in order to know the world and not empty forms. Kant did not prove that the material for knowing the world is outside of the experience of the world and merely in the forms of knowledge.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant's writing was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/3237634.xml">
obscure</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant took the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/11887.xml">
Greek</link></language>
 word <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/102803.xml">
noumena</link>, which meant "that which is thought," and used it to mean "things-in-themselves." (See <philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/177582.xml">
Sextus Empiricus</link></philosopher>
, <it><link>
Outlines of Pyrrhonism</link></it>, Book I, Chapter 13: "<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/1737.xml">
Anaxagoras</link></person>
 opposed what is thought (noumena) to what appears or is perceived (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/60931.xml">
phenomena</link>).") </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kant tried to create a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/3729225.xml">
logic</link>al, overly-symmetrical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link> without reflecting on its contents.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

He didn't clearly explain the meaning of and relationships between represented objects, representing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/18930.xml">
subject</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/9302.xml">
existence</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/29920.xml">
truth</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/53472.xml">
illusion</link>, error, sensations, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/17004290.xml">
judgment</link>s, words, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/6978.xml">
concept</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/25140.xml">
perception</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/216180.xml">
understanding</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/42446.xml">
reason</link>. </entry>
</list>

</p>
<ss3>
<st>
Concepts</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Kant didn't clearly explain concepts in general:</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Concepts of the understanding (common concepts and categories).</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Concepts of Reason (Ideas of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/5042765.xml">
God</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/343296.xml">
Freedom</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/177052.xml">
Immortality</link>).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

He divided reason into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/30746.xml">
theoretical</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/95170.xml">
practical</link>, making practical reason the source of virtuous conduct.</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Idealism</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant altered his first edition to:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

suppress the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/15428.xml">
idealistic</link> assertion that objects are conditioned by the knowing subject;</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Object&ndash;in&ndash;itself/Thing&ndash;in&ndash;itself</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

claim that the <link>
spatially</link> external thing-in-itself causes sensations in the sense organs of the knowing subject.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant tried to explain how:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

a perceived object, not mere raw sensation, is given to the mind by sensibility (sensation, space, and time), and</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

how the human understanding produces an experienced object by thinking twelve categories.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant doesn't explain how something external causes sensation in a sense organ.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

He didn't explain whether the object of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/297724.xml">
experience</link> (the object of knowledge which is the result of the application of the categories) is a perceptual representation or an abstract concept. He mixed up the perceptible and the abstract so that an absurd hybrid of the two resulted.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

There is a contradiction between the object experienced by the senses and the object experienced by the understanding.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Kant claims that representation of an object occurs both</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

through reception of one or more of the five senses, and</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

through the activity of the understanding's twelve categories.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Sensation and understanding are separate and distinct abilities. Yet, for Kant, an object is known through each of them.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

This contradiction is the source of the obscurity of the Transcendental Logic.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Kant's incorrect triple distinction:</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Representation (given to one or more of the 5 senses, and to the sensibilities of space and time)</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Object that is represented (thought through the 12 categories)</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Thing-in-itself (cannot be known).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer claimed that Kant's represented object is false.  The true distinction is only between the <it>representation</it> and the <it>thing-in-itself</it>. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

For Schopenhauer, the law of causality, which relates only to the representation and not to the thing-in-itself, is the real and only form of the understanding. The other 11 categories are therefore unnecessary because there is no represented object to be thought through them.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Kant sometimes spoke of the thing-in-itself as though it was an object that caused changes in a subject's senses. Schopenhauer affirmed that the thing-in-itself was totally different from phenomena and therefore had nothing to do with causality or being an object for a subject.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Excessive fondness for symmetry:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Origin of Kant's Transcendental Logic:</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

As pure intuitions (in the Transcendental Aesthetic) were the basis of empirical intuitions,</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

pure concepts (in the Transcendental Logic) were made the basis of empirical concepts.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

As the Transcendental Aesthetic was the <it>a priori</it> basis of mathematics,</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

the Transcendental Logic was made the <it>a priori</it> basis of logic.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

After discovering empirical perception is based on two forms of <it>a priori</it> perception (space and time), Kant tried to demonstrate that empirical knowledge is based on an analogous <it>a priori</it> knowledge (categories).</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Schemata</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

He went too far when he claimed that the schemata of the pure concepts of the understanding (the categories) are analogous to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/4222874.xml">
schema</link> of empirically acquired concepts.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

A schema of empirical perception is a sketchy, imagined perception. Thus, a schema is the mere imagined form or outline, so to speak, of a real perception. It is related to an empirical abstract concept to show that the concept is not mere word-play but has indeed been based on real perceptions. These perceptions are the actual, material  content of the empirical abstract concept.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

A schema of pure concepts is supposed to be a pure perception. There is supposed to be a schema for each of the pure concepts (categories). Kant overlooked the fact that these pure concepts, being pure, have no perceptual content. They gain this content from empirical perception. Kant's schemata of pure concepts are entirely undemonstrable and are a merely arbitrary assumption.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

This demonstrates Kant's purposeful intention to find a pure, <it>a priori</it> analogical basis for every empirical, <it>a posteriori</it> mental activity.</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Judgments/Categories</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Derived all philosophical knowledge from the table of judgments. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Made the table of categories the basis for every assertion about the physical and the metaphysical.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Derived pure concepts of the understanding (categories) from reason. But the Transcendental Analytic was supposed to reference only the sensibility of the sense organs and also the mind's way of understanding objects. It was not supposed to be concerned with reason. </entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Categories of quantity were based on judgments of quantity. But these judgments relate to reason, not understanding. They involve logical inclusion or exclusion of concepts with each other, as follows:</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

Universal judgment: All A are x; Particular judgment: Some A are x; Singular judgment: This one A is x.</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

Note: The word "quantity" was poorly chosen to designate mutual relations between abstract concepts.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Categories of quality were based on judgments of quality. But these judgments also are related only to reason, not to understanding. Affirmation and denial are relations between concepts in a verbal judgment. They have nothing to do with perceptual reality for the understanding. Kant also included infinite judgments, but only for the sake of architectonic symmetry. They have no meaning in Kant's context.</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

The term "quality" was chosen because it has usually been opposed to "quantity." But here it means only affirmation and denial in a judgment.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The categorical relation (A is x) is simply the general connection of a subject concept with a predicate concept in a statement. It includes the hypothetical and disjunctive sub-relations. It also includes the judgments of quality (affirmation, negation) and judgments of quantity (inclusional relationships between concepts). Kant made separate categories from these sub-relations. He used indirect, abstract knowledge to analyze direct, perceptual knowledge.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Our certain knowledge of the physical persistence of substance, or the conservation of matter, is derived, by Kant, from the category of subsistence and inherence. But this is merely based on the connection of a linguistic subject with its predicate. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

With judgments of relation, the hypothetical judgment (if A, then B) does not correspond only to the law of causality. This judgment is also associated with three other roots of the principle of sufficient reason. Abstract reasoning does not disclose the distinction between these four kinds of ground. Knowledge from perception is required.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

reason of knowing (logical inference);</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

reason of acting (law of motivation);</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

reason of being (spatial and temporal relations, including the arithmetical sequences of numbers and the geometrical positions of points, lines, and surfaces).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Disjunctive judgments derive from the logical law of thought of the excluded middle (A is either A or not-A). This relates to reason, not to the understanding. For the purpose of symmetry, Kant asserted that the physical analog of this logical law was the category of community or reciprocal effect. However, it is the opposite, since the logical law refers to mutually exclusive predicates, not inclusive.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer asserted that there is no reciprocal effect. It is only a superfluous synonym for causality. For architectonic symmetry, Kant created a separate <it>a priori</it> function in the understanding for reciprocal effect. Actually, there is only an alternating succession of states, a chain of causes and effects.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Modal categories of possible, actual, and necessary are not special, original cognized forms. They are derived from the principle of sufficient reason (ground). </entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Possibility is a general, mental abstraction. It refers to abstract concepts, which are solely related to the ability to reason or logically infer.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

There is no difference between actuality (existence) and necessity.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Necessity is a consequence from a given ground (reason).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss3>
</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Transcendental dialectic </st>

<ss3>
<st>
Reason</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kant defined reason as the faculty or power of principles. He claimed that principles provide us with synthetical knowledge from mere concepts (A 301; B 358). However, knowledge from mere concepts, without perception, is analytical, not synthetical. Synthetical knowledge requires the combination of two concepts, plus a third thing. This third thing is pure intuition or perception, if it is <it>a priori</it>, and empirical perception, if it is <it>a posteriori</it>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 According to Kant's principle of reason, everything that is conditioned is part of a total series of conditions. The essential nature of reason tries to find something unconditioned that functions as a beginning of the series.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 But Schopenhauer claimed that the demand is only for a <it>sufficient</it> reason or ground. It extends merely to the completeness of the determinations of the nearest or next cause, not to an absolute first cause.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kant claimed that everyone's reason leads them to assume three unconditioned absolutes. These are God, the soul, and the total world. The unconditioned absolutes are symmetrically derived by Kant from three kinds of syllogism as the result of three categories of relation.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Schopenhauer stated that the soul and the total world are not unconditioned because they are supposed, by believers, to be conditioned by God.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Schopenhauer also stated that everyone's reason does not lead to these three unconditioned absolutes. Buddhists are nontheists. Only Judaism and its derivatives, Christianity and Islam, are monotheistic. Exhaustive and extensive historical research would be needed to validate Kant's claim about the universality of reason's three unconditioned absolutes.</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Ideas of reason</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kant called God, soul, and total world (cosmos) Ideas of Reason. In doing so, he appropriated Plato's word "Idea" and ambiguously changed its settled meaning. Plato's Ideas are models or standards from which copies are generated. The copies are visible objects of perception. Kant's Ideas of Reason are not accessible to knowledge of perception. They are barely understandable through abstract knowledge of concepts.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fondness for symmetry led Kant to derive, as necessary, the concept of the soul from the paralogisms of rational psychology. He did so by applying the demand for the unconditional to the concept of substance, which is the first category of relation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kant claimed that the concept of the soul arose from the concept of the final, unconditioned subject of all predicates of a thing. This was taken from the logical form of the categorical syllogism. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer asserted that subjects and predicates are logical. They are concerned only with the relation of abstract concepts in a judgment. They are not concerned with a substance, such as a soul, that contains no material basis.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Idea of the total world, cosmos, or universe was said, by Kant, to originate from the hypothetical syllogism (If A is x, then B is y; A is x; Therefore B is y). </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer said that all three Ideas (God, soul, and universe) might be derived from the hypothetical syllogism. This is because all of these Ideas are concerned with the dependence of one object on another. When no more dependencies can be imagined, then the unconditioned has been reached.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Relating the Cosmological Ideas to the Table of Categories</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Kant stated that the cosmological Ideas, with regard to the limits of the world in time and space, are determined through the category of quantity.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 Schopenhauer asserted that those Ideas are not related to that category. Quantity is only concerned with the mutual inclusion of exclusion of concepts with each other (All A are x; Some A are x; This A is x).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Kant said that the divisibility of matter occurred according to the category of quality. But quality is merely the affirmation or negation in a judgment. Schopenhauer wrote that the mechanical divisibility of matter is associated with the quantity of matter, not quality.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

All of the cosmological ideas should derive from the hypothetical form of syllogism and therefore from the principle of sufficient reason. Kant asserted that divisibility of a whole into ultimate parts was based on the principle of sufficient reason. This is because the ultimate parts are supposed to be the ground conditions and the whole is supposed to be the consequent. However, Schopenhauer claimed that divisibility is instead based on the principle of contradiction. For him, the parts and the whole are actually one. If the ultimate parts are thought away, then the whole is also thought away.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

According to Schopenhauer, the fourth antinomy is redundant. It is an unnecessary repetition of the third antinomy. This arrangement was formed for the purpose of maintaining the architectonic symmetry of the category table.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

The thesis of the third antinomy asserts the existence of the causality of freedom. This is the same as the primary cause of the world.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

The thesis of the fourth antinomy asserts the existence of an absolutely necessary Being that is the cause of the world. Kant associated this with modality because through the first cause, the contingent becomes necessary.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer calls the whole antinomy of cosmology a mere sham fight. He said that Kant only pretended that there is a necessary antinomy in reason.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

In all four antinomies, the proof of the thesis is a sophism.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The proof of each antithesis, however, is an inevitable conclusion from premisses that are derived from the absolutely certain laws of the phenomenal world.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The theses are sophisms, according to Schopenhauer.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

First Cosmological Antinomy's Thesis:</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Purports to discuss beginning of time but instead discusses end or completion of series of times.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Arbitrarily presupposes that the world is given as a whole and is therefore limited.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Second Cosmological Antinomy's Thesis:</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/43582.xml">
Begs the question</link> by presupposing that a compound is an accumulation of simple parts.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Arbitrarily assumes that all matter is compound instead of an infinitely divisible total.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Third Cosmological Antinomy's Thesis:</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Kant appeals to his principle of pure reason (reason seeks the unconditioned in a series) in order to support causality through freedom. But, according to Schopenhauer, reason seeks the latest, most recent, sufficient cause. It does not seek the most remote first cause.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Kant said that the practical concept of freedom is based on the transcendent Idea of freedom, which is an unconditioned cause. Schopenhauer argued that the recognition of freedom comes from the consciousness that the inner essence or thing-in-itself is free will.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Fourth Cosmological Antinomy's Thesis:</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

The fourth antinomy is a redundant repetition of the third antinomy. Every conditioned does not presuppose a complete series of conditions which ends with the unconditioned. Instead, every conditioned presupposes only its most recent condition.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

As a solution to the cosmological antinomy, Kant stated:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Both sides assumed that the world exists in itself. Therefore, both sides are wrong in the first and second antinomies.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Both sides assumed that reason assumes an unconditioned first cause of a series of conditions. Therefore, both sides are correct in the third and fourth antinomies.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer disagreed. He said that the solution was that the antitheses are correct in all four antinomies.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant stated that the Transcendental Ideal is a necessary idea of human reason. It is the most real, perfect, powerful entity.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer disagreed. He said that his own reason found this idea to be impossible. He was unable to think of any definite object that corresponds to the description.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The three main objects of scholastic philosophy were the soul, the world, and God. Kant tried to show how they were taken from the three possible major premisses of syllogisms.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The soul was derived from the categorical judgment (A is x) and the world was taken from the hypothetical judgment (If A is x, then B is y).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

For architectonic symmetry, God had to be derived from the remaining disjunctive judgment (A is either x or not-x).</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer said that the antique philosophers did not mention this derivation, so it can't be necessary to all human reason. Their gods were limited. World-creating gods merely gave form to pre-existing matter. Reason, according to ancient philosophers, did not obtain an idea of a perfect God or Ideal from the disjunctive syllogism.</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Kant stated that knowledge of particular things results from a continuous process of the limitation of general or universal concepts. The most universal concept would then have contained all reality in itself.</entry>
<entry level="4" type="bullet">

According to Schopenhauer, the reverse is true. Knowledge starts from the particular and is extended to the general. General concepts result from abstraction from particulars, retaining only their common element. The most universal concept would thus have the least particular content and be the emptiest.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant alleged that the three transcendent ideas are useful as regulative principles. As such, he claimed, they aid in the advancement of the knowledge of nature.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer asserted that Kant was diametrically wrong. The ideas of soul, finite world, and God are hindrances. For example, the search for a simple, immaterial, thinking soul would not be scientifically useful.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss3>
</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Ethics </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant claimed that virtue results from practical reason.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer claimed that, to the contrary, virtuous conduct has nothing to do with a rational life and may even be opposed to it, as with Machiavellian rational expediency.</entry>
</list>

</p>
<ss3>
<st>
Categorical Imperative</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

According to Schopenhauer, Kant's Categorical Imperative:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Redundantly repeats the ancient command: "don't do to another what you don't want done to you."</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Is egoistic because its universality includes the person who both gives and obeys the command.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Is cold and dead because it is to be followed without love, feeling, or inclination, but merely out of a sense of duty.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss3>
</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Power of judgment </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In the <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/347543.xml">
Critique of Pure Reason</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it>, Kant claimed that the understanding was the ability to judge. The forms of judgments were said to be the basis of the categories and all philosophy. But in his <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/549047.xml">
Critique of Judgment</link></it>, he called a new, different ability the faculty of judgment. That now resulted in four faculties: sensation, understanding, judging, and reason. Judgment was located between understanding and reason, and contained elements of both.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kant's interest in the concept of suitability or expediency resulted in his investigation regarding knowledge of beauty and knowledge of natural purposiveness.</entry>
</list>

</p>
<ss3>
<st>
Aesthetics</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

As usual, he started from abstract concepts in order to know concrete perceptions. Kant started from the abstract judgment of taste in order to investigate knowledge of beautiful objects of perception.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Kant was not concerned with beauty itself. His interest was in the question of <it>how a </it>'subjective<b> statement or judgment about beauty could be universally valid, as though it concerned an actual quality of an </b>object<b><it>.</it></b></entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Teleology</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Kant asserted that the subjective statement that nature seems to have been created with a premeditated purpose does not necessarily have objectively validity or truth.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Kant claimed that the apparently purposive, deliberate constitution of organic bodies cannot be explained from merely mechanical causes. ("...it is absurd for man even to entertain any thought ... that maybe another Newton may some day arise to make intelligible to us even the genesis of but a blade of grass from natural laws that no design has ordered [i.e., from mechanical principles].") (<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/549047.xml">
Critique of Judgment</link></it>, |75).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Schopenhauer said that Kant didn't go far enough. Schopenhauer stated that one province of nature cannot be explained from laws of any another province of nature. He listed examples of separate provinces of nature as being mechanics, chemistry, electricity, magnetism, crystallization, and organics. Kant had only asserted this regarding the organic and the mechanical.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss3>
</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Reactions to Schopenhauer</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Paul Guyer</st>
<p>

In <it>The Cambridge Companion to Schopenhauer</it>, Professor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/4876608.xml">
Paul Guyer</link></educator>
</scholar>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</person>
</philosopher>
</physical_entity>
 wrote an article titled "Schopenhauer, Kant, and the Methods of Philosophy." In it, he compared the methods of the two philosophers and in so doing, discussed Schopenhauer's Criticism.</p>
<p>

In explaining how objects are experienced, Kant used transcendental arguments. He tried to prove and explain the fundamental principles of knowledge. In so doing, he started by indirectly conceptually reflecting on the conditions that exist in the observing subject that make possible verbal judgments about objective experience.</p>
<p>

We shall therefore follow up the pure concepts to their first germs and beginnings in the human understanding....</p>
<p>

&ndash;  <cite >A66</cite></p>
<p>

In contrast, Schopenhauer's method was to start by a direct examination of perceived objects in experience, not of abstract concepts. 
...the solution of the riddle of the world is possible only through the proper connexion of outer with inner experience....</p>
<p>

&ndash;  <cite >Appendix p. 428</cite>
The fundamental principles of knowledge cannot be transcendentally explained or proved, they can only be immediately, directly known. Such principles are, for example, the permanence of substance, the law of causality, and the mutual interactive relationships between all objects in space. Abstract concepts, for Schopenhauer, are not the starting point of knowledge. They are derived from perceptions, which are the source of all knowledge of the objective world. The world is experienced in two ways: (1.) mental representations that involve space, time, and causality; (2.) our will which is known to control our body.</p>
<p>

Professor Guyer stated that Schopenhauer raised important questions regarding the possibility of Kant's transcendental arguments and proofs. However, even though Schopenhauer objected to Kant's method, he accepted many of Kant's conclusions. For example, Kant's description of experience and its relation to space, time, and causality was accepted. Also, the distinction between logical and real relations, as well as the difference between phenomena and things-in-themselves, played an important role in Schopenhauer's philosophy.</p>
<p>

In general, the article tries to show how Schopenhauer misunderstood Kant as a result of the disparity between their methods. Where Kant was analyzing the conceptual conditions that resulted in the making of verbal judgments, Schopenhauer was phenomenologically scrutinizing intuitive experience. In one case, though, it is claimed that Schopenhauer raised a very important criticism. That is his objection to Kant's assertion that a particular event can be known as being successive only if its particular cause is known. Otherwise, almost all of Schopenhauer's criticisms are attributed to his opposite way of philosophizing which starts with the examination of perceptions instead of concepts.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>The Cambridge Companion to Schopenhauer</it>, Edited by Christopher Janaway, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, ISBN 0-521-62924-1</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/1313078.xml">
The World as Will and Representation</link></it>, Arthur <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/700.xml">
Schopenhauer</link>, New York: Dover Press, Volume I, Appendix, "Criticism of the Kantian Philosophy," ISBN 0-486-21761-2</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/661863.xml">
Kantianism</link></institution>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/4222874.xml">
Schema (Kant)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/9790323.xml">
Schopenhauer's criticism of Kant's schemata</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/700.xml">
Arthur Schopenhauer</link></philosopher>
</person>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Books</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/5634430.xml">
On the Fourfold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it>&nbsp;·  <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/19097368.xml">
On Vision and Colors</link></it>&nbsp;·  <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/1313078.xml">
The World as Will and Representation</link></it>&nbsp;·  <it><product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<essay wordnetid="106409562" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/5776721.xml">
On the Freedom of the Will</link></essay>
</end_product>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</it> &nbsp;·  <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/5237738.xml">
On the Basis of Morality</link>''</it></col>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 0px 0px 2px;" rowspan="5">
<image width="50px" src="Schopenhauer.jpg">
<caption>

Arthur Schopenhauer
</caption>
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Criticism</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/2890279.xml">
Kantian philosophy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/9790323.xml">
Kant's schemata</link>&nbsp;·  <argument wordnetid="106648724" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/8854637.xml">
Proofs of the parallel postulate</link></evidence>
</indication>
</argument>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Philosophy</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/14694092.xml">
Antinatalism</link>&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/584224.xml">
Aesthetics</link></scholar>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</person>
</philosopher>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/1928747.xml">
Hedgehog's dilemma</link></relationship>
&nbsp;·  <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/13564651.xml">
The Art of Being Right</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
