<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:05:51[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<creation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103129123">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<master  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103727274">
<header>
<title>SRX Altered Banpreios</title>
<id>2932171</id>
<revision>
<id>221899722</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-26T16:21:02Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Advent child</username>
<id>1708255</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Banpresto Originals</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>SRX (Super Robot Type-X or X-Type) Altered Banpreios</b> is a fictional robot in the <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/1297946.xml">
Super Robot Wars</link></entertainer>
</psychological_feature>
</game>
</causal_agent>
</contest>
</performer>
</social_event>
</event>
</person>
</comedian>
</physical_entity>
 series. It appears as a playable unit in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/2570440.xml">
3rd Super Robot Wars Alpha</link>.
<sec>
<st>
Appearance</st>

<p>

The Banpreios is a hulking machine that is not as boxy as its predecessor, the <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/2931999.xml">
SRX</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
. The Banpreios has a large head shaped like that of <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/1422612.xml">
Banpresto's</link></company>
 logo. There is white on much of the body structure while there is a lot of blue on the upper body and arms and red on the legs. Its vents are clearly marked by being shaded in yellow. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Technical And Historical</st>

<p>

<it>For the full history of the SRX, see <link>
here</link>.</it></p>
<p>

The Banpreios is meant to be the final product of the <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/11001352.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22SRX+Development+Project%22])">
SRX Developmental Project</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
. This machine will finally allow the <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/9379474.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Tronium+Engine%22])">
Tronium Engine</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
 to be used at full capacity without the worry of it having the side effect of potentially exploding (<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/11001352.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Tronium%22])">
Tronium</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
 is a highly dangerous mineral). This way, the SRX is no longer a threat to its pilots and is an even deadlier foe in combat. Learning from the original SRX's success and mistakes, the Banpreios is allowed to become a well-developed and refined robot that brings its use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/1432865.xml">
super robot</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/496955.xml">
real robot</link> qualities to a state close to perfection.</p>
<p>

The Banpreios, like the SRX, is meant to be a combining robot that uses the R-1 Altered, R-2 Altered, and R-3 Altered. However, due to the war becoming so intense, the project is rushed and the Banpreios itself is sent out ahead of schedule. It is said in Alpha 3 the Banpreios is capable of separating, but this ability is sealed for the sake of time and to strengthen the mecha (in game terms, this is likely due to the limitations of Alpha 3's Squad System).</p>
<p>

The Banpreios is armed with a variety of weaponry and can again use the <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/2957979.xml">
R-Gun Powered</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
 as a weapon module. The pilots of the Banpreios upon rollout are <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/7994660.xml">
Raidiese F. Branstein</link></fictional_character>
 (again maintaining the output of the Tronium Engine) and <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/7750155.xml">
Mai Kobayashi</link></fictional_character>
 (who performs the T-Link Contact with the <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/9379474.xml">
T-Link</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
/<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/9379474.xml">
Uranus</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
 systems). Once they reach <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/7435960.xml">
Ryusei Date</link></fictional_character>
, he takes his place as the primary pilot of the machine. When <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/7449657.xml">
Aya Kobayashi</link></fictional_character>
 is recovered, she once again maintains the T-Link System, this time alongside her sister. With both Aya and Mai on board, Banpreios can use attacks that require "Twin Contact" with the T-Link System.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Specifications</st>
<p>

<b>Model Number:</b> SR-01 SRX ALTERED</p>
<p>

<b>Height:</b> 75.3 meters</p>
<p>

<b>Weight:</b> 431.8 tons</p>
<p>

<b>Main Power Source:</b> Tronium Engine</p>
<p>

<b>Defensive System:</b> <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/9379474.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Nendou+Field%22])">
Nendou Field</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
</p>
<p>

<b>Weapon Systems:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Telekinesis Missiles HP <it>The Banpreios unloads many missile pods that launch into a group of enemies and open up to reveal a load of small but strong explosives that spread out among the targets to damage them all while leaving any ally units in the blast area unharmed.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

High Palm Detonator <it>Learning from the SRX, it seems it is more appropriate for the arm weapons to be fast-firing beam cannons in order to save energy and perform more accurate shots. These large beam cannons are located in each palm.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gaun Genocider <it>The Banpreios fires a huge beam ray attack from its visor. The Banpresto logo sound effect can be heard when it fires and when it hits.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

T-LINK Blade Knuckle <it>The Banpreios uses psychic energy to create energy blades on both arms. It uses them to repeatedly impale/punch the target before breaking one blade off inside the target and sending it flying backwards. The blade then explodes.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Altered Full Burst <it>A coordinated attack that utilizes the Telekenesis Missiles, High Palm Detonators, and Gaun Genocider to perform an all out attack.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tenjou Tenja Nendou Musou Ken (Heaven and Earth Psychic Matchless Sword) <it>Ryusei's name for the Banpreios' ultimate sword attack. The blade-like protrusions on the feet detach and combine. They use Zol Orihalcon to create the Super Zol Orichalcon Sword. With this weapon, a devastating sword combination attack is used. The Banpreios first impales the enemy with the sword. When Ryusei issues the "Open Sword!" command, the two blades fold back, cutting the opponent in two. As a finishing strike, the blades revert back to the normal configuration and Banpreios cleaves through the enemy. This move is likely to be what was intended for the prototype's <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<master wordnetid="103727274" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/4532741.xml">
R-Sword</link></master>
</artifact>
</creation>
 module, given the similarities between the Super Zol Orichalcon Sword and the twin blades of the R-Sword.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tenjou Tenga Ichigeki Hissatsu Hou Kai (Heaven and Earth One Shot Sure Kill Cannon Improved) <it> Similar to the original the SRX, R-Gun can be used as an additional weapon. This is actually known as the HTB Cannon (Hyper Tronium Buster Cannon), where the R-Gun transforms into its Metal Genocider Mode and is used as a giant gun for the Banpreios in which power from the Tronium Engine is relayed into the R-Gun to perform a devastating attack. With the limits on the Banpreios now almost non-existent, the Tronium engine can be powered to new heights to power this attack. In this version of the attack, an additional module called</it> Ex-Gunner <it>is deployed, and docked to the rear of the R-Gun Powered, but the exact functions of this unit, aside from making the machine look more like a proper rifle, are not specified.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</master>
</artifact>
</creation>
</article>
