<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:44:30[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<communicator  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109610660">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<engineer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109615807">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<scientist  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110560637">
<writer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110794014">
<research_worker  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110523076">
<header>
<title>Avinash Kak</title>
<id>294131</id>
<revision>
<id>231634222</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-13T07:23:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Edward</username>
<id>4261</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Artificial intelligence researchers</category>
<category>American computer scientists</category>
<category>Kashmiri people</category>
<category>American engineers</category>
<category>Technology writers</category>
<category>Purdue University faculty</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Textbook writers</category>
<category>Americans of Indian descent</category>
<category>Indian Institute of Technology people</category>
<category>Indian computer scientists</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Avinash Kak</b> (also known as <b>Avi Kak</b> to his friends around the world) is a professor of Electrical and Computer Engineering at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/23757.xml">
Purdue University</link></university>
 who has done pioneering research in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/76332.xml">
image processing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/385523.xml">
tomography</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/6596.xml">
computer vision</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/23015.xml">
computer language</link>s. <p>

His research on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/172088.xml">
machine vision</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/46673.xml">
robotics</link> is based on the credo that sensory intelligence for machines must be demonstrated using real data, since practically anything can be shown to work with synthetic data. His laboratory has performed  research on sensory intelligence for the machines of the future by considering 3D object recognition, vision-guided navigation for indoor mobile robots, and task and assembly planning.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Significant Contributions to Robotics and Computer Vision </st>
<p>

With regard to the groundbreaking contributions made by Kak and his collaborators: In 1989, Chen and Kak published 3D-POLY that is still the fastest algorithm for recognizing 3D objects in depth maps.  In 1992, Kosaka and Kak published FINALE, which is considered to be a computationally efficient and highly robust approach to vision-based navigation by indoor mobile robots. In 2003, a group of researchers that included Kak developed a tool for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/743971.xml">
content-based image retrieval</link> that was demonstrated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/241717.xml">
clinical trial</link>s to markedly improve the performance of radiologists.  This remains the only clinically evaluated system for content-based image retrieval for radiologists.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Significant Contributions to Image Reconstruction Algorithms </st>

<p>

The SART algorithm (Simultaneous Algebraic Reconstruction Technique) proposed by Andersen and Kak in 1984 has had a major impact in CT imaging
applications where the projection data is limited.  As a measure of its popularity, researchers have proposed various extensions to 
SART: OS-SART, FA-SART, VW-OS-SART, SARTF, etc. Researchers have also studied how SART can best be implemented on
different parallel processing architectures. SART and its proposed extensions are used in emission CT in nuclear medicine, for dynamic CT, for holographic tomography, etc. Convergence
of the SART algorithm was theoretically established in 2004 by Ming Jiang and Ge Wang in their paper "Convergence of the simultaneous algebraic reconstruction technique (SART)" published in the IEEE Transactions on Image Processing, Vol. 12, August 2003, pp. 957-961.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Books Authored </st>

<p>

His book <b>Principles of Computerized Tomographic Imaging</b>, now re-published as a classic in <link>
Applied Mathematics</link> by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/26886.xml">
SIAM</link> (Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics), is widely used in courses dealing with modern medical imaging.  It is one of the most frequently cited books in the literature on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/1007969.xml">
image reconstruction</link>. His other co-authored book <b>Digital Picture Processing</b> is also considered to be a classic and has been one of the most widely referenced sources in literature dealing with digital <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/76332.xml">
image processing</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/6596.xml">
computer vision</link>. (The citation counts at 
Google Scholar <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?num=100&amp;hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=A.C.Kak">
http://scholar.google.com/scholar?num=100&amp;hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=A.C.Kak</weblink>          
show how frequently these classics are cited                                            
in the technical literature.)   </p>
<p>

His more recent books are a part of his <b>Object Trilogy Project</b><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cobweb.ecn.purdue.edu/~kak/trilogy.html">
http://cobweb.ecn.purdue.edu/~kak/trilogy.html</weblink> The first book of the trilogy,<b>Programming with Objects: A Comparable Presentation of Object-Oriented Programming with C++ and Java</b>, presents a comparative approach to the teaching and learning of two large object-oriented languages, <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/72038.xml">
C++</link></programming_language>
 and <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
. The second book, <b>Scripting with Objects: A Comparative Presentation of Object-Oriented Scripting with Perl and Python</b>, does the same with Perl and Python.  The last, <b>Designing with Objects</b> is presumably currently in the works.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Lost in Translation </st>

<p>

The Chinese translation of Kak's <b>Programming with Objects</b> book left out the following opening paragraph from Chapter 1.  This paragraph talks about freedom of societies.  The title of this chapter is <b>Chapter 1: Why OO Programming --- Some Parallels with Things at Large</b>.</p>

<p>

Although the answer to this question will reveal itself as you work your way through this book, at this juncture it might be useful to draw parallels between object-oriented programming (OO) and the world around us.  You are unlikely to dispute the assertion that during the last half century the following facts about societies have become amply clear: soceities function best when centralized control is kept to a minimum; when the intelligence needed for the smooth functioning of a society is as distributed as possible; when each person is sufficiently smart to know for himself or herself how to make sense of the various norms and mores of the society for the common good; and when the higher-level organizational structures, often organized in the form of hierarchies facilitate the propagation of society-nurturing messages up and down the hierarchies.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Bibliography</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Azriel Rosenfeld and Avinash Kak, <it>Digital Picture Processing</it> Academic Press(1982)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Avinash Kak and Malcolm Slaney, <it>Principles of Computerized Tomographic Imaging</it> SIAM (Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics) Press(1988)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Avinash Kak, <it>Programming With Objects: A Comparative Presentation of Object Oriented Programming with C++ and Java</it> John Wiley and Sons(2003)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

C. H. Chen and A. C. Kak, "A Robot Vision System for Recognizing 3-D Objects in Low-Order Polynomial Time," IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, pp. 1535-1563, November/December 1989</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Akio Kosaka and Avinash Kak, "Fast Vision-Guided Mobile Robot Navigation using Model-Based Reasoning and Prediction of Uncertainties," Computer Vision, Graphics, and Image Processing -- Image Understanding, pp. 271-329, November 1992.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Alex Aisen, Lynn Broderick, Helen Winter-Muram, Carla Brodley, Avinash Kak, Christina Pavlopoulou, Jennifer Dy, Chi-Ren Shyu, and Alan Marchiori, "Automated Storage and Retrieval of Thin-Section CT Images to Assist Diagnosis: System Description and Preliminary Assessment," Radiology, Vol. 228, No. 1, pp. 265-270, July 2003</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Anders Andersen and Avinash Kak, "Simultaneous Algebraic Reconstruction Technique (SART): A Superior Implementation of ART," Ultrasonic Imaging, 1984.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</research_worker>
</writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</engineer>
</entity>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
</article>
