<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:44:21[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Web of trust</title>
<id>296356</id>
<revision>
<id>241554309</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-28T16:11:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>VolkovBot</username>
<id>3035831</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia spam cleanup</category>
<category>PGP</category>
<category>Semantic Web</category>
<category>Online social networking</category>
<category>Asymmetric-key cryptosystems</category>
<category>Key management</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<indent level="1">

This page is about concept of <b>web of trust</b>. For internet security tool, see 
</indent>
In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
cryptography</link>, a <b>web of trust</b> is a concept used in <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/23080.xml">
PGP</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/38809.xml">
GnuPG</link>, and other <link>
OpenPGP</link>-compatible systems to establish the authenticity of the binding between a public key and a user. Its decentralized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/451914.xml">
grass roots</link> trust model is an alternative to the centralized trust model of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/194112.xml">
public key infrastructure</link> (PKI), which relies exclusively on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/296370.xml">
certificate authority</link> (or a hierarchy of such).  As with computer networks, there are many independent webs of trust, and any user (through their <link>
identity certificate</link>) can be a part of, and a link between, multiple webs.<p>

The web of trust concept was first put forth by PGP creator <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<disputant wordnetid="109615465" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<reformer wordnetid="110515194" confidence="0.8">
<militant wordnetid="110315837" confidence="0.8">
<cryptanalyst wordnetid="109981540" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<decoder wordnetid="109995398" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/23486.xml">
Phil Zimmermann</link></decoder>
</scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</cryptanalyst>
</militant>
</reformer>
</person>
</disputant>
</physical_entity>
 in 1992 in the manual for PGP version 2.0:
As time goes on, you will accumulate keys from other people that you may want to designate as trusted introducers.  Everyone else will each choose their own trusted introducers.  And everyone will gradually accumulate and distribute with their key a collection of certifying signatures from other people, with the expectation that anyone receiving it will trust at least one or two of the signatures.  This will cause the emergence of a decentralized fault-tolerant web of confidence for all public keys.</p>



<sec>
<st>
 Operation of a web of trust </st>
<p>

All OpenPGP-compliant implementations include a certificate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/5878091.xml">
vetting</link> scheme to assist with this; its operation has been termed a web of trust. OpenPGP identity certificates (which include public key(s) and owner information) can be digitally signed by other users who, by that act, endorse the association of that public key with the person or entity listed in the certificate.  This is commonly done at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/424764.xml">
key signing parties</link>.</p>
<p>

OpenPGP-compliant implementations also include a vote counting scheme which can be used to determine which public key &ndash; owner association a user will trust while using PGP. For instance, if three partially trusted endorsers have vouched for a certificate (and so its included public key &ndash; owner <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../588/42588.xml">
binding</link>), OR if one fully trusted endorser has done so, the association between owner and public key in that certificate will be trusted to be correct. The parameters are user-adjustable (e.g., no partials at all, or perhaps 6 partials) and can be completely bypassed if desired.</p>
<p>

The scheme is flexible, unlike most public key infrastructure designs, and leaves trust decision(s) in the hands of individual users. It is not perfect and requires both caution and intelligent supervision by users. Essentially all PKI designs are less flexible and require users to follow the trust endorsement of the PKI generated, certificate authority (CA)-signed, certificates. Intelligence is normally neither required nor allowed. These arrangements are not perfect either, and require both caution and care by users.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Contrast with typical PKI </st>
<p>

In contrast, a typical <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/296352.xml">
X.509</link></advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 PKI permits each certificate to be signed only by a single party: a certificate authority (CA). The CA's certificate may itself be signed by a different CA, all the way up to a 'self-signed' <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/296362.xml">
root certificate</link>. Root certificates must be available to those who use a lower level CA certificate and so are typically distributed widely. They are for instance, distributed with such applications as browsers and email clients. In this way <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/187813.xml">
SSL</link>/<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/187813.xml">
TLS</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
-protected Web pages, email messages, etc. can be authenticated without requiring users to manually install root certificates. Applications commonly include over one hundred root certificates from dozens of PKIs, thus by default bestowing trust throughout the hierarchy of certificates which lead back to them. Many of these root certificates were created by companies which collapsed, e.g. as the <bubble wordnetid="109229709" confidence="0.8">
<misfortune wordnetid="114475405" confidence="0.8">
<ball wordnetid="113899404" confidence="0.8">
<globule wordnetid="109289709" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920429" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<sphere wordnetid="113899200" confidence="0.8">
<round_shape wordnetid="113865483" confidence="0.8">
<catastrophe wordnetid="114476290" confidence="0.8">
<adversity wordnetid="114475661" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<fortune wordnetid="114473222" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/9021.xml">
Dot-com bubble</link></fortune>
</shape>
</adversity>
</catastrophe>
</round_shape>
</sphere>
</state>
</condition>
</globule>
</ball>
</misfortune>
</bubble>
  burst. Unless those PKIs are still properly managed the root certificates almost certainly should not be relied upon now.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Web of trust problems </st>
<p>

The OpenPGP web of trust is essentially unaffected by such things as company failures, and has continued to function with little change. However, a related problem does occur. Users, whether individuals or organizations, who lose track of a private key can no longer decrypt messages sent to them produced using the matching public key found in an OpenPGP certificate. Early PGP certificates did not include expiry dates, and those certificates had unlimited lives. Users had to prepare a signed cancellation certificate against the time when the matching private key was lost or compromised. One very prominent cryptographer is still getting messages encrypted using a public key for which he long ago lost track of the private key (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Reference-Ferguson-2003%22])">
Ferguson 2003</link>, p.333).  He can't do much with those messages except discard them after notifying the sender that they were unreadable and requesting resending with a public key for which he still has the matching private key. Later PGP, and all OpenPGP compliant certificates include expiry dates which automatically preclude such troubles (eventually) when used sensibly.  This problem can also be easily avoided by the use of "designated revokers", which were introduced in the early 1990s.  A key owner may designate a third party that has permission to revoke the key owner's key if the key owner loses his own private key and thus loses the ability to revoke his own public key.</p>
<p>

A non-technical, social, difficulty with a Web of Trust like the one built into PGP/OpenPGP type systems is that every web of trust without a central controller (eg, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/296370.xml">
CA</link>) depends on other users for trust. Those with new certificates (ie, produced in the process of generating a new key pair) will not likely be readily trusted by other users' systems, that is by those they have not personally met, until they find enough endorsements for the new certificate. This is because many other Web of Trust users will have their certificate vetting set to require one or more fully trusted endorsers of an otherwise unknown certificate (or perhaps several partial endorsers) before using the public key in that certificate to prepare messages, believe signatures, etc.</p>
<p>

Despite the wide use of OpenPGP compliant systems and easy availability of on-line multiple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/616119.xml">
key server</link>s, it is possible in practice to be unable to readily find someone (or several people) to endorse a new certificate (eg, by comparing physical identification to key owner information and then digitally signing the new certificate). Users in remote areas or undeveloped ones, for instance, may find other users scarce. And, if the other's certificate is also new (and with no or few endorsements from others), then its signature on any new certificate can offer only marginal benefit toward becoming trusted by still other parties' systems and so able to securely exchange messages with them. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/424764.xml">
Key signing parties</link> are a relatively popular mechanism to resolve this problem of finding other users who can install one's certificate in existing webs of trust by endorsing it. Websites also exist to facilitate the location of other OpenPGP users to arrange keysignings. The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gswot.org">
Gossamer Spider Web of Trust</weblink> also makes key verification easier by linking OpenPGP users via a hierarchical style web of trust where end users can benefit by coincidental or determined trust of someone who is endorsed as an introducer, or by explicitly trusting GSWoT's top-level key minimally as a level 2 introducer (the top-level key endorses level 1 introducers).</p>
<p>

The possibility of finding chains of certificates is often justified by the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/636799.xml">
small world phenomenon</link>": given two individuals, it is often possible to find a short chain of people between them such that each person in the chain knows the preceding and following links. However, such a chain is not necessarily useful: the person encrypting an email or verifying a signature not only has to find a chain of signatures from his private key to his correspondent's, but also to trust each person of the chain to be honest and competent about signing keys (that is, he has to judge whether these people are likely to honestly follow the guidelines about verifying the identity of people before signing keys). This is a much stronger constraint.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Doing the math </st>

<p>

The work of Audun Jøsang is an algebraic treatment of trust measurements and methods and calculation that attempts to capture how trust varies as it "traverses" a web of trust.  The other sites (below) contains a link to his publications.
A good one to start with might be "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unik.no/people/josang/papers/Jos1999-NDSS.pdf">
An Algebra for Assessing Trust in Certification Chains</weblink>".  Also see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/12413580.xml">
Subjective logic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/862635.xml">
Trust metric</link>.</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/176320.xml">
Virtual community</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/355054.xml">
CAcert</link> signs OpenPGP keys if you are checked through a web of trust, they also issue free X.509 certificates.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1576475.xml">
Thawte</link></trade_name>
 stopped signing OpenPGP keys many years ago and now only issues X.509 certificates.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section may contain .</b>
If you are familiar with the content of the external links, please help by removing promotional links in accordance with . ()</col>
</row>
</table>


</p>
<ss1>
<st>
 General </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rubin.ch/pgp/weboftrust.en.html">
An explanation of the PGP Web of Trust</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wim.uni-koeln.de/uploads/media/The_PGP_Trust_Model.pdf">
"The PGP Trust Model"</weblink> - by Alfarez Abdul-Rahman</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mcwg.org/mcg-mirror/cert.htm">
Overview of Certification Systems: X.509, CA, PGP and SKIP</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://email-security.net/papers/pki-pgp-ibe.htm">
Comparison Of Secure Email Technologies - X.509 / PKI, PGP, and IBE</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 PGP Key Analysis </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://keyserver.kjsl.com/~jharris/ka/">
Current key analysis reports</weblink> - maintained by Jason Harris</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bcn.boulder.co.us/~neal/pgpstat/">
PGP Web of Trust Statistics</weblink> - analysis by Neal McBurnett in 1996</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dtype.org/keyanalyze/">
Analysis of a large OpenPGP ring</weblink> - analysis by Drew Streib in 2001-2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pgp.cs.uu.nl/plot/">
Analysis of the PGP strong set</weblink> - maintained by Henk Penning</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Web of Trust statistics and tools </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lysator.liu.se/~jc/wotsap/index.html">
Wotsap - Web of trust statistics and pathfinder</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.parisc-linux.org/~willy/wot/footsie/">
The Footsie Web of Trust analysis</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://people.cs.uu.nl/henkp/henkp/pgp/">
PGP tools, pathfinder, references</weblink> from Henk P. Penning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://t-butter.de/gpg.php">
Individual key statistics</weblink> from Thomas Butter</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://xmlns.com/wot/0.1/">
Web of Trust RDF Vocabulary</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Other trust-related tools and sites </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/trust-forum/">
Trust-forum</weblink>: a project of web-based communication system that aims to include a web of trust between servers based on trust declarations between users.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mywot.com/">
WOT - Web of Trust - free internet security tool</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://moloko.itc.it/trustmetricswiki/moin.cgi/FrontPage">
Trust Metrics Evaluation Project</weblink> wiki.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/suhl/bizer/SWTSGuide/">
Semantic Web Trust and Security Resource Guide</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unik.no/people/sl/">
Subjective logic demonstrator</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://v3.espacenet.com/textdoc?IDX=WO0115002">
Web of Trust Patent, Epinions</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/467054.xml">
Epinions history</link></web_site>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks  " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#ccf;" class="navbox-title">
&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
Public-key cryptography</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<b>Algorithms:</b> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/14050287.xml">
CEILIDH</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/1564406.xml">
Cramer-Shoup</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/7903.xml">
DH</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/59470.xml">
DSA</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/3357958.xml">
ECDH</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/450525.xml">
ECDSA</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/1506894.xml">
EKE</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/59458.xml">
ElGamal encryption</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/2033473.xml">
ElGamal signature scheme</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/598608.xml">
GMR</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../076/3530076.xml">
IES</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/3200486.xml">
Lamport</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/1586447.xml">
MQV</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/481582.xml">
NTRUEncrypt</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/3513327.xml">
NTRUSign</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/480685.xml">
Paillier</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/451283.xml">
Rabin</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/25385.xml">
RSA</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/450536.xml">
Schnorr</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/2159061.xml">
SPEKE</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/1306670.xml">
SRP</link></method>
</rule>
</direction>
</know-how>
</protocol>
</message>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/2587137.xml">
STS</link></method>
</rule>
</direction>
</know-how>
</protocol>
</message>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../209/3963209.xml">
XTR</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</field>
</region>
</p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even"><p>

<b>Theory:</b> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/181334.xml">
Discrete logarithm</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../966/9966.xml">
Elliptic curve cryptography</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</field>
</region>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/1544741.xml">
RSA problem</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<b>Standardization:</b> <link>
ANS X9F1</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/549159.xml">
CRYPTREC</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/1644154.xml">
IEEE P1363</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/497430.xml">
NESSIE</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/1602099.xml">
NSA Suite B</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even"><p>

<b>Misc:</b> <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/59644.xml">
Digital signature</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/7943312.xml">
Fingerprint</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/194112.xml">
PKI</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/296356.xml">
Web of trust</link>&nbsp;&#124; 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/5749.xml">
Key size</link></p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#ccf;" class="navbox-title">
&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
Cryptography</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/520066.xml">
History of cryptography</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/5715.xml">
Cryptanalysis</link> | 
Cryptography portal | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/449585.xml">
Topics in cryptography</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/53042.xml">
Symmetric-key algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/4594.xml">
Block cipher</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/49007.xml">
Stream cipher</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
Public-key cryptography</link> | <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<primitive wordnetid="109627462" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/439526.xml">
Cryptographic hash function</link></primitive>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/567523.xml">
Message authentication code</link> | <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/182249.xml">
Random numbers</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/28733.xml">
Steganography</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<cite id="Reference-Ferguson-2003" style="font-style:normal" class="book"><physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<cryptanalyst wordnetid="109981540" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<decoder wordnetid="109995398" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/204933.xml">
Ferguson, Niels</link></decoder>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</cryptanalyst>
</person>
</physical_entity>
;&#32;Bruce Schneier&#32;(2003). Practical Cryptography.&#32;<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/537930.xml">
John Wiley &amp; Sons</link></company>
. ISBN 0471223573.</cite>&nbsp;</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
