<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:05:08[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<institute  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108407330">
<association  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108049401">
<header>
<title>Center for Information Technology</title>
<id>3005034</id>
<revision>
<id>243982960</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T20:38:04Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Warpozio</username>
<id>96257</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>National Institutes of Health</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="US-NIH-CIT-Logo.svg">
</image>

The <b>Center for Information Technology</b> (CIT) is an agency of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/195149.xml">
United States Federal Government</link>.  CIT, first established in 1964 as the Division of Computer Research and Technology (DCRT), provides the technological and computational support and services for the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/46174.xml">
NIH</link></association>
</institute>
 community.
<sec>
<st>
Mission</st>
<p>

CIT's mission is to provide, coordinate, and manage <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
information technology</link> and to advance computational science. CIT supports NIH's research and management programs with efficient, cost-effective information systems, networking services, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/30322.xml">
telecommunications</link> services. Among its activities, the CIT:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 engages in collaborative research and provides collaborative support to NIH investigators in the area of computational <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
bioscience</link>;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 provides efficient, cost-effective information systems and networking services;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 provides state-of-the-art scientific and administrative computing facilities;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 identifies new computing technologies with innovative applications to biomedical research;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 creates, purchases, and distributes software applications;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 provides NIH staff with computing information, expertise, and training;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 provides data processing and high-performance computing facilities, integrated telecommunications data networks, and services to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/58250.xml">
U.S. Department of Health and Human Service (DHHS)</link> and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/58232.xml">
Federal agencies</link>;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 serves as a data center to HHS and other Federal agencies; and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 develops, administers, and manages NIH systems and provides consulting services to NIH Institutes and Centers (ICs), in support of administrative and business applications.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1954</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

A central data processing facility was established in the <link>
Office of the Director, NIH</link>, under Dr. Harold Dorn, combining <link>
EAM</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/24420.xml">
punched card</link>) equipment and biometric expertise.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1956</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The biometric facility became the Biometrics Branch in the new Division of Research Services (DRS).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 1956</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The NIH Director established a committee on electronic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/41961.xml">
data processing</link> and computers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1958</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

NIH installed its first electronic digital computer as an experimental device.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 1960</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/219354.xml">
Surgeon General</link> approved the establishment of a Computation and Data Processing Branch in DRS.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

October 1961</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

NIH installed its first “second generation” computer.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 1963</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The NIH Director appointed a steering committee to undertake a comprehensive study of data processing activities at NIH.  The NIH steering committee recommended the establishment of a Division of Computer and Information Sciences (subsequently changed to the Division of Computer Research and Technology (DCRT), including provision for the transfer of the Computation and Data Processing Branch, DRS, to the new organization.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1964</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

DCRT was established, with James King as Interim Acting Director.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1966</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

Dr. Arnold W. Pratt was named DCRT's first Director.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 1966</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

Components of the “third-generation” computer system were installed.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 1969</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

NIH research community received the first <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/30958.xml">
time-sharing</link> computers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

June 1969</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

Minicomputers designed by the DCRT were installed in NIH laboratories.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 1979</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

An interagency agreement between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/120882.xml">
HEW</link> and <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/424408.xml">
GSA</link></agency>
 established the NIH Central Computer Utility as a Federal Data Processing Center.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 1983</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The Personal Workstation Project was founded to determine how effectively NIH personnel could use personal computers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1988</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/78379.xml">
Convex</link></institution>
</company>
 Unix-based supermini-computer was installed, and the network task group was created.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1990</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

Extensive networking (NIHnet) was installed at NIH, providing connectivity for 60 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/17739.xml">
local area network</link>s.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 1992</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

Department of Health and Human Services (DHHS) Secretary <official wordnetid="110372373" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/522709.xml">
Louis Sullivan</link></official>
, in a letter to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
Congress</link>, committed to creating a new office to improve management and coordination of NIH's information resources.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

June 1992</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The NIH Director approved creation of the Office of Information Resources Management (OIRM) in OD.  Dr. Francis W. Hartel, Ph.D. was selected as the NIH Senior IRM official and the Director of OIRM.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The Information Systems Security Officers (ISSO) committee was established to handle NIH IT security issues.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

February 1994</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

To help customers obtain computer-related information, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/13544.xml">
help desk</link> was inaugurated.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

October 1994</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

OIRM sponsored the first Internet conference on legal and policy issues related to the increased use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> resources at NIH.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 1995</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

DCRT sponsored Internet Expo Day to help NIH staff discover the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
 and its enormous potential to disseminate and exchange information.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

June 1995</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The NIH Director approved a revised charter for the Office of Information Resource Management (IRM) council and increased its role in providing management leadership on NIH-wide information technology (IT) initiatives.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

August 1995</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The first NIH electronic store was established to provide efficient acquisition of personal computers, hardware, software, and on-line components to NIH personnel.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1996</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/30322.xml">
telecommunications</link> committee was established to provide the IRM council with advice about crosscutting telecommunication issues affecting a large number of NIH staff. Issues included telephone features and services, pagers, cellular services, video <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/41783.xml">
teleconferencing</link>, remote access, audio conferencing, and switchboard operator services. Responsibilities were shared by DCRT and the Telecommunications Branch located in NIH's Office of Research Services; DCRT introduces a subscription based program for the acquisition and distribution of brand-name software to NIH and HHS personnel, with the result of significant cost reduction for software licensing.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 1996</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The IRM council established the NIH Year 2000 Work Group (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/34235.xml">
Y2K</link>) to provide NIH with leadership and direction on initiatives modifying computer systems and applications to accommodate problems related to a two-digit date field.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

June 1996</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

NIH's Computer Center was designated as a major DHHS data center.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

July 1996</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The NIH Data Warehouse, which provides a one-stop-shop graphical user interface to NIH administrative and accounting information, was introduced to NIH.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

August 1996</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The Information Technology Management Reform Act of 1996 (ITMRA, also known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/1794984.xml">
Clinger-Cohen Act</link>) became effective. ITMRA assigned overall responsibility for the acquisition and management of government IT resources to the Director, Office of Management and Budget. Additionally, ITMRA gave authority to heads of executive agencies to acquire IT resources, and directed agencies to appoint a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/153852.xml">
Chief Information Officer</link> (CIO) to provide advice to each agency on the effective management of IT investments.  NIH Director named Anthony Itteilag, NIH Deputy Director for Management, to serve as interim NIH Chief Information Officer (CIO).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 1996</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The NIH Director's leadership forum on the management of IT at NIH formed an IT Central Committee (ITCC) to provide recommendations on improving the management of NIH IT resources.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 1996</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

A final ITCC report was submitted to the NIH Director. The report recommended appointing a CIO and combining DCRT, OIRM, and TCB into a single organizational structure.  Dona R. Lenkin was appointed to serve as OIRM Acting Director and alternate NIH CIO.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1997</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

A review of NIH's administrative structure, conducted in response to a request from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/223225.xml">
Congressman</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/969282.xml">
John Porter</link> (<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/14849.xml">
Ill.</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
), was completed. The report recommended that the NIH implement the ITCC recommendations by appointing a permanent CIO and establishing a CIO organization.  NIH's first electronic magazine, LiveWire, was launched by DCRT. The on-line magazine offered easy access to key services and computer information.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

July 1997</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

DCRT introduced the NIH Human Resources Information and Benefits System (HRIBS), a Web service that gave employees easy access to personnel data, including benefits, salary, awards, leave, savings, performance and retirement.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

September 1997</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

DCRT completed consolidation of two HHS data centers --- the Program Support Center Information Technology Service and the Administration for Children and Families National Computer Center --- into the NIH Computer Center.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

October 1997</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

<post wordnetid="108624385" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/32759.xml">
Vice President</link></post>
 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<vice_president wordnetid="110751265" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/5042706.xml">
Al Gore</link></vice_president>
</person>
 awarded OIRM staff the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/5021254.xml">
National Performance Review "Hammer" Award</link> for the development of an automated security risk assessment tool for networks.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 1997</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

DCRT inaugurated SILK (Secure Internet-Linked) technology to provide Web access to enterprise data.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

February 1998</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The Center for Information Technology (CIT) was formed, combining the functions of the DCRT, the Office of Information Resources Management (OIRM), and the Telecommunications Branch.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

March 1998</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

<skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/3005345.xml">
Alan S. Graeff</link></military_officer>
</scholar>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</worker>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
 was named NIH's first Chief Information Officer (CIO) and Director of the newly formed Center for Information Technology (CIT).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

April 1998</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

CIT's OIRM sponsored an IT security conference to provide IT security officers and others with essential information for moving towards the 21st century; CIT renames its original acquisition and distribution project to the Software Distribution Project (SDP). The SDP provides software to more than 24,000 customers, including more than 80% of all personnel.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

October 1998</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The NIH IT <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/871961.xml">
Board of Governors</link> (BoG) was established to advise the NIH and the NIH CIO on NIH-wide IT management and to make recommendations on IT activities and priorities.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 1999</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

CIT completed development of the predecessor to the TELESYNERGY(TM) Medical Consultation WorkStation, a multimedia, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/234714.xml">
medical imaging</link> workstation. This system provided an electronic imaging environment, utilizing a prototype <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
Asynchronous Transfer Mode</link> (ATM) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/774446.xml">
telemedicine</link> network. The TELESYNERGY(TM) environment included a scientific workstation as the computing platform that transmits simultaneous high-resolution images to all sites participating in a medical consultation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

May 1999</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The Information Technology Management Committee (ITMC) was formed to develop and communicate recommendations and decisions at the IC level, provided a forum for building consensus across the NIH, and served as an umbrella organization to the NIH IT process management and technical committees.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

December 1999</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

NIH successfully prepared for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/34235.xml">
Year 2000</link>, thus bringing to fruition four-years of effort preparing for the largest information management project in history. The NIH strategy of aggressive renovation and validation of information systems, biomedical equipment, facilities, utilities, and telecommunications provided a smooth transition that ensured the integrity of the NIH mission.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

January 2000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

CIT joined forces with NCI in a pioneering TELESYNERGY(TM) collaboration to reach out to distant community hospitals. Patients in remote areas were now able to participate in selected NCI phase I and phase II protocols. Collaborating sites, with TELESYNERGY(TM) Systems either installed or under construction, included hospitals in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/109028.xml">
Fort Lauderdale, Florida</link></village>
; <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/151290.xml">
Wheeling, West Virginia</link></village>
; <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../046/5046.xml">
Belfast</link></site>
, Northern Ireland, United Kingdom; and <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/8504.xml">
Dublin</link></site>
, the Republic of <island wordnetid="109316454" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/147575.xml">
Ireland</link></island>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

CIT renames the Software Distribution Project (SDP) to the Information Systems Designated Procurement (iSDP) to acquire and deliver brand-name software, hardware and services to NIH and DHHS personnel. The iSDP takes advantage of large volume purchasing agreements to provide significantly discounted prices to its customers. The iSDP also saves its participants time and money by eliminating the need to search for the best information systems deals. iSDP provides major software titles, hardware and services to more than 54,000 customers, including 84 percent of DHHS personnel, and all of NIH.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2001</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The NIH Incident Response Team (IRT) was the first civilian Federal agency to receive the prestigious <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/1086289.xml">
Office of Personnel Management</link></agency>
 (OPM) Guardian Award, for exceptional contributions in ensuring the confidentiality, availability, and integrity of NIH information resources.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

Dr. John F. (Jack) Jones, Jr., joined CIT as Chief IT Architect for NIH, to focus on NIH <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/1010494.xml">
enterprise systems</link> critical to the mission of NIH and lead <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/1448049.xml">
Enterprise Architecture</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
; CIT took a leadership role in forging NIH's strategy for common services, including hosting the improved and expanded NIH <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/54293.xml">
Portal</link>. CIT supported the development and staged implementation of the NIH Portal as a single, user-friendly customizable web interface by which data and documents can be readily accessed by NIH staff and associated personnel; CIT successfully implemented the NIH Administrative Restructuring Advisory Committee (ARAC) recommendations for IT Consolidation (Phase I).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2003</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The National Institutes of Health (NIH) Information Technology Working Group (ITWG), established by the NIH Director as part of the NIH Steering Committee, provides governance and oversight on NIH IT management issues. The ITWG is advisory to the NIH Director, NIH Steering Committee, and NIH Chief Information Officer (CIO).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

As an advisory group to the NIH Director, NIH Steering Committee, and NIH CIO on IT management, the ITWG establishes governance over the five IT Domain Areas below, representing the areas where decisions need to be made at the intersection of business and information technology.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

IT Principles Domain</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

includes alignment of IT to the NIH mission of the NIH, corporate policies and oversight of the use of IT, and determination of ownership of IT initiatives</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

IT Infrastructure Strategies Domain</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

includes the IT “public utility” and secure, robust, and manageable common services</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

IT Architecture Domain</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

includes data standards and application standards</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Business Application Needs Domain</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

includes all enterprise, non-scientific administrative, grants/extramural, and Intramural IT systems</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

IT Investment and Prioritization Domain</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

includes funding mechanisms and priorities</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2004</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

CIT successfully implemented the NIH ARAC recommendations for IT Consolidation Phase II; CIT continues to implement and oversee NIH enterprise-wide applications like:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Integrated Time and Attendance System (ITAS)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 NIH Enterprise Common Services (NECS); including NIH Login and NIH Portal</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 NIH Intramural Data Base (NIDB)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Contractor Performance System (CPS)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Vulnerability Tracking System (VTS)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Human Resources Data Base (HRDB)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

November 2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

<skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/3005345.xml">
Alan S. Graeff</link></military_officer>
</scholar>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</worker>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
 leaves CIT to take a position at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/408290.xml">
National Library of Medicine</link>'s National Center for Biotechnology Information.  Dr. John F. (Jack) Jones is appointed Acting Director of CIT as well as Acting NIH Chief Information Officer</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Past Directors</st>
<p>

<table style="margin: 0 0 1em 1em; width: 50%; border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 95%" cellpadding="4" class="toccolours" border="1">
<row>
<header>
<b>Name</b></header>
<header>
<b>In Office From</b></header>
<header>
<b>To</b></header>
</row>
<row>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
James King (Acting)</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
1964</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
N/A</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Dr. Eugene Harris (Acting)</col>
<col>
N/A</col>
<col>
August 1966</col>
</row>
<row>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
Dr. Arnold W. Pratt</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
August 1966</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
May 1990</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Dr. David Rodbard</col>
<col>
November 1990</col>
<col>
April 1996</col>
</row>
<row>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
William L. Risso (Acting)</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
April 1996</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
March 1998</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/3005345.xml">
Alan S. Graeff</link></military_officer>
</scholar>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</worker>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
</col>
<col>
March 1998</col>
<col>
November 2005</col>
</row>
<row>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
Jack F. Jones (Acting)</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
November 2005</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
Present</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Past NIH CIOs</st>
<p>

<table style="margin: 0 0 1em 1em; width: 50%; border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 95%" cellpadding="4" class="toccolours" border="1">
<row>
<header>
<b>Name</b></header>
<header>
<b>In Office From</b></header>
<header>
<b>To</b></header>
</row>
<row>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
<skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/3005345.xml">
Alan S. Graeff</link></military_officer>
</scholar>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</worker>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
March 1998</col>
<col bgcolor="#cccccc">
November 2005</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Jack F. Jones (Acting)</col>
<col>
November 2005</col>
<col>
Present</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Programs</st>
<p>

CIT consists of the Office of the Director (OD), the Office of the Deputy Chief Information Officer (ODCIO), the Office of Planning, Evaluation, and Communications (OPEC), the Division of Computational Bioscience (DCB), the Division of Customer Support (DCS), the Division of Computer System Services (DCSS), the Division of Enterprise and Custom Applications (DECA), and the Division of Network Systems and Telecommunications (DNST).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Office of the Director (OD)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

John F. "Jack" Jones, PhD </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deputy Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Alfred Whitley</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Executive Officer</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Kathryn Slocum Wimsatt</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deputy CIO</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Stacy Charland (Acting)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Scientific Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Benes L. Trus, PhD (Acting)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 NIH Chief IT Architect</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Helen McCulloch Schmitz (Acting)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The Office of the Director plans, directs, coordinates, and evaluates the Center's programs, policies, and procedures and provides analysis and guidance in the development of systems for the effective use of IT techniques and equipment in support of NIH programs. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/579193.xml">
Chief Technology Officer</link> (CTO) provides advice on the computational and telecommunications needs of the NIH community and provides analysis and guidance in developing systems supporting NIH-wide IT initiatives. In addition, the CTO evaluates new technologies, provides planning guidance for CIT programs and services, and coordinates IT architectural management for the NIH.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Office of the Deputy Chief Information Officer (ODCIO)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Stacy Charland (Acting)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The Deputy Chief Information Officer advises the Chief Information Officer (CIO) on the direction and management of significant NIH IT program and policy activities under relevant Federal statutes, regulations and policies. The ODCIO also develops, implements, manages, and oversees NIH IT activities related to IT legislation, regulations, and NIH and other Federal policies:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ODCIO directs NIH's IT capital planning processes with regard to major IT investments and provides leadership to NIH ICs to enhance and strengthen their IT program management so they comply with legislative and policy requirements.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The office serves as principal NIH liaison to HHS, its OPDIVs, and other Federal agencies on IT matters.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In addition, ODCIO identifies critical IT issues and analyzes, plans, leads, and manages the implementation of special HHS or Federal initiatives as they relate to the management of NIH's IT resources.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ODCIO also collaborates with NIH managers responsible for IT-related functions, in particular, IT security. ODCIO staffs and supports NIH's Incident Response Team (IRT). The IRT serves as the focal point for IT security incidents by identifying and characterizing incidents, and providing immediate diagnostic and corrective action when appropriate.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Office of the Chief Information Technology Architect (OCITA)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Chief IT Architect</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Helen McCulloch Schmitz (Acting)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The Chief IT Architect leads the NIH Enterprise Architecture program with the mission to develop a comprehensive plan for IT support that acknowledges the need for both conforming and diverse business processes.  The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://enterprisearchitecture.nih.gov/About/Team/OCITA.htm">
Office of the Chief IT Architect (OCITA)</weblink> is the NIH Enterprise Architecture program management office and consists of a fulltime architecture staff.</p>
<p>

OCITA's central responsibility is the daily execution and management of the NIH Enterprise Architecture program and associated activities and initiatives. In this capacity, OCITA’s primary responsibilities are to:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lead the creation and renewal of architecture and standards </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lead and facilitate the IT Architecture <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://enterprisearchitecture.nih.gov/About/Approach/DomainTeamProcess.htm">
Domain Team Process</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Manage domain team memberships </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ensure NIH mission and architecture alignment </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lead assessments of evolving technologies for standards adoption or renewal </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Plan and recommend architectural migration </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Assess the current environment in specific technical areas </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Publish the architecture in the chosen format </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Conduct awareness/education sessions </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Advise in business and IT planning </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Interpret and communicate architecture issues and choices </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Advise project teams on the use of architecture </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Support projects on assessing adherence when requested </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Evaluate project requests for exceptions to architecture </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Develop recommendations for the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://enterprisearchitecture.nih.gov/About/Team/ARB.htm">
Architecture Review Board (ARB)</weblink> as the basis for decision-making </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Represent NIH architecture to the Department of Health and Human Services </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Provide enterprise architecture reviews in support of the NIH Capital Planning and Investment Control (CPIC) process</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Planning, Evaluation, and Communications Office(PECO)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director (Acting)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Jennifer Czajkowski </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The Planning, Evaluation, and Communications Office(PECO) is located in the Center for Information Technology’s (CIT) Office of the Director, Executive Office. It is the focal point for strategic business and operational planning, analysis and evaluation, as well as the central office for communications at CIT. </p>
<p>

PECO provides technical and programmatic assistance to the Director and his senior staff in all aspects of the Center’s efforts toward initiation, development, implementation, and evaluation of information technology (IT) programs on which the National Institutes of Health (NIH) relies. PECO disseminates important communication information about CIT related products and services to support and advance the mission of the NIH.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Division of Computational Bioscience (DCB)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Benes L. Trus (Acting)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deputy Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Calvin Johnson (Acting)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

DCB is a research and development organization that provides scientific and technical expertise in computational science and engineering to support biomedical research activities at the NIH:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DCB applies the concepts and technologies of computer, engineering, physical and mathematical science to biomedical applications including the areas of image processing, bioinformatics, genetic databases, structural biology, scientific visualization, medical imaging, telemedicine, signal processing, biomedical instrumentation, and biomathematics.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DCB develops computational methods and tools for solving biomedical laboratory and clinical research problems.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DCB promotes the application of high-performance computing and high-speed communications to biomedical research and provides these resources for the NIH scientific staff.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DCB evaluates the overall effectiveness of these programs and represents CIT to the national Information Technology Research and Development (IT R&amp;D) Program.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Division of Computer System Services (DCSS)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Adriane R. Burton</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deputy Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

DCSS plans, implements, operates, and supports centrally owned or administered computing resources for NIH enterprises use, ensuring interoperability among those resources and between them and other computing facilities owned by customer organizations.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DCSS promotes awareness and efficient and effective use of these computing resources by customer personnel through training, presentations, consultations, and documentation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DCSS investigates new and emerging computing requirements of customer programs. It conducts research and development to identify, evaluate, and adapt new computer architectures and technologies to meet identified customer requirements and to enhance current service offerings.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Additionally, where appropriate, DCSS manages and operates departmental computing resources for IC, Office, or Center use.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Division of Customer Support (DCS)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Chris Ohlandt</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deputy Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Jenny Czajkowski</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

DCS provides centralized, integrated computer support services to the NIH computing community:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DCS advocates customer needs to CIT management and represents services and policies to CIT's customers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It plays an active and participatory role in supporting desktop computing to the end-user in the areas of software and hardware, including internet, communications, and access technologies.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Division also coordinates and oversees CIT's Training Program for the benefit of the NIH computing community. The training program is delivered at no charge to the user.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In addition to providing a central account establishment and management service for access to CIT systems, DCS also manages the NIH-wide help desk and implements support technology tools.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Division of Enterprise and Custom Applications (DECA)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Jack Vinner (Acting)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deputy Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Jack Vinner</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

DECA supports the NIH enterprise business process through the development and management of transaction and decision-support environments for administrative and business applications of the NIH, such as procurement, budget, accounting and human resource activities, as well as systems that support extramural and intramural business processes:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Division provides complete information systems management services to the NIH including technical project management, systems analysis, programming, data integration and conversion, quality assurance, testing, and production support.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DECA also provides the NIH community with World Wide Web development, support services, and consulting services for applications development.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Division of Network Systems and Telecommunications (DNST)</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 Renitalynette K. Anderson</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deputy Director</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

DNST directs the engineering, design, implementation, and support of network infrastructure and services for the NIH wide area network (NIHnet) to facilitate the use of scientific, administrative, and other business applications:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DNST manages and directs NIH telecommunications systems and technical requirements for the NIH ICs and implements telecommunications programs to meet the needs of the NIH community.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Division researches, develops, and tests next-generation networking/ telecommunications technologies and develops and supports applications using new network technologies, such as telemedicine and video conferencing.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It provides consulting, guidance and support to the ICs, helping them to meet their network requirements.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To improve the information infrastructure on networking/telecommunications activities, DNST serves as liaison to the NIH ICs and other DHHS components.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DNST serves as a focal point for telecommunications service orders, and develops and disseminates recommended standards, policies, and procedures for the nationwide implementation and management of NIH networking and telecommunications systems.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Division also develops, implements, and supports remote access services to NIHnet, provides technical support for wireless services, and a 24-hour telephone/network support service.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources</st>
<p>

NIH Almanac - Organization - Center for Information Technology; August 2005 . That publication is not copyrighted and is in the public domain. URL: http://www.nih.gov/about/almanac/organization/CIT.htm.</p>
<p>

CIT Organization; June 2005 . That publication is not copyrighted and is in the public domain. URL: http://www.cit.nih.gov/org/default.asp</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/46174.xml">
National Institutes of Health</link></association>
</institute>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://enterprisearchitecture.nih.gov/">
NIH Enterprise Architecture</weblink>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cit.nih.gov/">
CIT home page</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://irm.cit.nih.gov/">
Office of the Deputy Chief Information Officer</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://opec.cit.nih.gov/">
Office of Planning, Evaluation, and Communications</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dcb.cit.nih.gov/">
Division of Computational Bioscience</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cit.nih.gov/nw-tc.html">
Division of Network Systems and Telecommunications</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://datacenter.cit.nih.gov/">
Division of Computer System Services</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://support.cit.nih.gov/">
Division of Customer Support</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cit.nih.gov/deca/">
Division of Enterprise and Custom Applications</weblink>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#99BBC8;" class="navbox-title">
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/46174.xml">
National Institutes of Health</link></association>
</institute>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#99BBC8;;" class="navbox-group">
Institutes</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<p>

<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../835/907835.xml">
National Cancer Institute</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/458424.xml">
National Eye Institute</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/574482.xml">
National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</link>&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/1544352.xml">
National Human Genome Research Institute</link></institution>
</association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/1545066.xml">
National Institute on Aging</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/1705096.xml">
National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/1013155.xml">
National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/539902.xml">
National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10477975.xml">
National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/1179168.xml">
National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/1705102.xml">
National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/1705064.xml">
National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../071/1705071.xml">
National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</link>&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/1487987.xml">
National Institute on Drug Abuse</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/1179171.xml">
National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/211655.xml">
National Institute of General Medical Sciences</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/455909.xml">
National Institute of Mental Health</link></agency>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/237641.xml">
National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</link>&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../087/1705087.xml">
National Institute of Nursing Research</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/408290.xml">
National Library of Medicine</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#99BBC8;;" class="navbox-group">
Centers</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<p>

<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/3005034.xml">
Center for Information Technology</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/11948970.xml">
Center for Scientific Review</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/19025629.xml">
John E. Fogarty International Center</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/391043.xml">
National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
National Center on Minority Health and Health Disparities</link>&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/9819050.xml">
National Center for Research Resources</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/8875634.xml">
Quality Assurance Review Center</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/4709222.xml">
Radiological Physics Center</link></association>
</institute>
&nbsp;· 
<link>
Warren Grant Magnuson Clinical Center</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#99BBC8;;" class="navbox-group">
Programs</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/336950.xml">
Visible Human Project</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#99BBC8;;" class="navbox-group">
Related</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<p>

<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/224130.xml">
United States Public Health Service</link></agency>
&nbsp;· 
<institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/3859111.xml">
National Institutes of Health Director's Pioneer Award</link></association>
</institute>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</association>
</institute>
</article>
