<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:35:04[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>TeX</title>
<id>30065</id>
<revision>
<id>243601779</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T06:45:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Tobias Bergemann</username>
<id>36029</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Donald Knuth</category>
<category>TeX</category>
<category>Macro programming languages</category>
<category>Desktop publishing software</category>
<category>Typesetting</category>
<category>Digital typography</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing rewrite</category>
<category>Free TeX software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>infobox software</name>
<parameters>
<genre>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/169180.xml">
Typesetting</link></genre>
<logo>
<image width="100px" src="TeX_logo.svg">
<caption>

The TeX logo
</caption>
</image>
</logo>
<website>
http://www.tug.org/</website>
<latest_release_version>
3.1415926</latest_release_version>
<developer>
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/8095.xml">
Donald Knuth</link></scientist>
</person>
</developer>
<name>
TeX</name>
<latest_release_date>
March 2008</latest_release_date>
<license>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/2404057.xml">
Permissive</link></license>
<operating_system>
<platform wordnetid="103961939" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<surface wordnetid="104362025" confidence="0.8">
<horizontal_surface wordnetid="103536348" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/81193.xml">
Cross-platform</link></horizontal_surface>
</surface>
</artifact>
</platform>
</operating_system>
</parameters>
</template>


For help displaying mathematical formulae in Wikipedia, see .
<p>

<b>TeX</b> (pronounced , as in <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/292885.xml">
Greek</link></language>
, often /ˈtɛk/ in <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English</link></language>
; written with a lowercase 'e' in imitation of the logo) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/169180.xml">
typesetting</link> system designed and mostly written by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/8095.xml">
Donald Knuth</link></scientist>
</person>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Together with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/44263.xml">
METAFONT</link> language for font description and the <font wordnetid="106825399" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/639806.xml">
Computer Modern</link></font>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/64105.xml">
typeface</link>s, it was designed with two main goals in mind: to allow anybody to produce high-quality books using a reasonable amount of effort, and to provide a system that would give the exact same results on all computers, now and in the future. Within the typesetting system, its name is formatted as TeX.</p>
<p>

TeX is considered by many to be the best way to typeset complex mathematical formulae.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> TeX is popular in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/351220.xml">
academia</link>, especially in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/22939.xml">
physics</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/5695.xml">
communities</link>.  It has largely displaced <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/30811.xml">
troff</link>, the other favored formatter, in many Unix installations, which use both for different purposes. It is now also being used for many other typesetting tasks, especially in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/18195.xml">
LaTeX</link> and other template packages.</p>
<p>

The widely-used <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/19045.xml">
MIME</link> Type for TeX is application/x-tex. TeX is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/10635.xml">
free software</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

When the first volume of Knuth's <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/31358.xml">
The Art of Computer Programming</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it> was published in 1969, it was typeset using hot metal type set by a <plant wordnetid="103956922" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<foundry wordnetid="103387653" confidence="0.8">
<factory wordnetid="103316406" confidence="0.8">
<building_complex wordnetid="102914991" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/1014735.xml">
Monotype Corporation</link></building_complex>
</factory>
</foundry>
</artifact>
</structure>
</plant>
 typecaster a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/1018892.xml">
hot metal typesetting</link> machine from the 19th century which produced a "good classic style" appreciated by Knuth. When the second edition of the second volume was published, in 1976, the whole book had to be typeset again because the Monotype technology had been largely replaced by photographic techniques, and the original fonts were no longer available.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> However, when Knuth received the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/4161853.xml">
galley proof</link>s of the new book on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/19849.xml">
30 March</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/34549.xml">
1977</link>, he found them awful.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Around that time, Knuth saw for the first time the output of a high-quality digital typesetting system, and became interested in digital typography. The disappointing galley proofs gave him the final motivation to solve the problem at hand once and for all by designing his own typesetting system. On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/19675.xml">
May 13</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/34549.xml">
1977</link>, he wrote a memo to himself describing the basic features of TeX.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

He planned to finish it on his <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/69322.xml">
sabbatical</link> in 1978, but as it happened the language was frozen only in 1989, more than ten years later. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/299674.xml">
Guy Steele</link> happened to be at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/26977.xml">
Stanford</link></university>
 during the summer of 1978, when Knuth was developing his first version of TeX.  When Steele returned to <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/18879.xml">
MIT</link></university>
 that fall, he rewrote TeX's I/O to run under the <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/298349.xml">
ITS</link></O>
 operating system. The first version of TeX was written in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/481275.xml">
SAIL programming language</link> to run on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/23628.xml">
PDP-10</link> under Stanford's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/309290.xml">
WAITS</link> operating system. For later versions of TeX, Knuth invented the concept of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/18136.xml">
literate programming</link>, a way of producing compilable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/27661.xml">
source code</link> and high quality cross-linked documentation (typeset in TeX, of course) from the same original file. The language used is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/87394.xml">
WEB</link> and produces programs in DEC PDP-10 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/23773.xml">
Pascal</link>.</p>
<p>

A new version of TeX, rewritten from scratch and called TeX82, was published in 1982. Among other changes, the original <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/59347.xml">
hyphenation</link> algorithm was replaced by a new algorithm written by <link>
Frank Liang</link>. TeX82 also uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/449736.xml">
fixed-point arithmetic</link> instead of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/11376.xml">
floating-point</link>, to ensure reproducibility of the results across different computer hardware,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> and includes a real, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/30621.xml">
Turing-complete</link> programming language, following intense lobbying by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/299674.xml">
Guy Steele</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

In 1989, Donald Knuth released new versions of TeX and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/44263.xml">
METAFONT</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> Despite his desire to keep the program stable, Knuth realised that 128&nbsp;different characters for the text input were not enough to accommodate foreign languages; the main change in version 3.0 of TeX is thus the ability to work with 8-bits inputs, allowing 256 different characters in the text input.</p>
<p>

Since version 3, TeX has used an idiosyncratic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/920901.xml">
version numbering system</link>, where updates have been indicated by adding an extra digit at the end of the decimal, so that the version number <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/3107.xml">
asymptotically</link> approaches <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/23601.xml">
π</link>. This is a reflection of the fact that TeX is now very stable, and only minor updates are anticipated. The current version of TeX is 3.1415926; it was last updated in March 2008. The design was frozen after version 3.0, and no new feature or fundamental change will be added, so all newer versions will contain only <invertebrate wordnetid="101905661" confidence="0.8">
<arthropod wordnetid="101767661" confidence="0.8">
<bug wordnetid="102236355" confidence="0.8">
<insect wordnetid="102159955" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/37085.xml">
bug</link></animal>
</insect>
</bug>
</arthropod>
</invertebrate>
 fixes. Even though Donald Knuth himself has suggested a few areas in which TeX could have been improved, he indicated that he firmly believes that having an unchanged system that will produce the same output now and in the future is more important than introducing new features. For this reason, he has stated that the "absolutely final change (to be made after my death)" will be to change the version number to π, at which point all remaining bugs will become features.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> 
Likewise, versions of METAFONT after 2.0 asymptotically approach <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/9633.xml">
e</link>, and a similar change will be applied after Knuth's death.</p>

<p>

However, since the source code of TeX is essentially in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link> (see below), other programmers are allowed (and explicitly encouraged) to improve the system, but are required to use another name to distribute the modified TeX, meaning that the source code can still evolve. For example, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/596407.xml">
Omega</link> project was developed after 1991, primarily to enhance TeX's multilingual typesetting abilities. Donald Knuth himself created “unofficial” modified versions, such as <link>
TeX-XeT</link>, which allows a user to mix texts written in left-to-right and right-to-left <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/33602.xml">
writing system</link>s in the same document.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The typesetting system</st>
<p>

TeX commands commonly start with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/174815.xml">
backslash</link> and are grouped with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../hem/Ledringhem.xml">
curly braces</link>.  However, almost all of TeX's syntactic properties can be changed on the fly which makes TeX input hard to parse by anything but TeX itself. TeX is a <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/20560.xml">
macro</link></concept>
</idea>
- and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/81251.xml">
token</link>-based language: many commands, including most user-defined ones, are expanded on the fly until only unexpandable tokens remain which get executed.  Expansion itself is practically side-effect free. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/30742.xml">
Tail recursion</link> of macros takes no memory, and if-then-else constructs are available.  This makes TeX a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/30621.xml">
Turing-complete</link> language even at expansion level.</p>
<p>

The system can be divided into four levels: in the first, characters are read from the input file and assigned a category code (sometimes called “catcode”, for short). Combinations of a backslash (really: any character of category zero) followed by letters (characters of category 11) or a single other character are replaced by a control sequence token. In this sense this stage is like lexical analysis, although it does not form numbers from digits. In the next stage, expandable control sequences (such as conditionals or defined macros) are replaced by their replacement text. The input for the third stage is then a stream of characters (including ones with special meaning) and unexpandable control sequences (typically assignments and visual commands). Here characters get assembled into a paragraph.  TeX's paragraph breaking algorithm works by optimizing breakpoints over the whole paragraph. The fourth stage breaks the vertical list of lines and other material into pages.</p>
<p>

The TeX system has precise knowledge of the sizes of all characters and symbols, and using this information, it computes the optimal arrangement of letters per line and lines per page. It then produces a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/196831.xml">
DVI</link> file (“DeVice Independent”) containing the final locations of all characters. This dvi file can be printed directly given an appropriate printer driver, or it can be converted to other formats.  Nowadays, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/17823517.xml">
PDFTeX</link> is often used which bypasses DVI generation altogether.</p>
<p>

The base TeX system understands about 300 commands, called <it>primitives</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> However, these low-level commands are rarely used directly by users, and most functionality is provided by format files (predumped memory images of TeX after large macro collections have been loaded). Knuth's original default format, which adds about 600 commands, is <link>
Plain TeX</link> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://tug.ctan.org/pub/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/lib/plain.tex">
available from CTAN</weblink>). The most widely used format is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/18195.xml">
LaTeX</link>, originally developed by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/195671.xml">
Leslie Lamport</link></scientist>
, which incorporates document styles for books, letters, slides, etc, and adds support for referencing and automatic numbering of sections and equations. Another widely used format, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/6571457.xml">
AMS-TeX</link>, is produced by the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/198822.xml">
American Mathematical Society</link></organization>
, and provides many more user-friendly commands, which can be altered by journals to fit with their house style.  Most of the features of AMS-TeX can be used in LaTeX by using the AMS “packages”.  This is then referred to as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/6571457.xml">
AMS-LaTeX</link>. Other formats include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/918538.xml">
ConTeXt</link>, used primarily for desktop publishing and written mostly by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/2020743.xml">
Hans Hagen</link> at <link>
Pragma</link>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
How TeX is run</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="LaTeX_sample.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A sample page produced using TeX with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/18195.xml">
LaTeX</link> macros.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

A sample <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/13834.xml">
Hello world program</link> in plain TeX is:
Hello, World
\end          % marks the end of the file; not shown in the final output
This might be in a file <it>myfile.tex</it>, as <it>.tex</it> is a common <link>
file extension</link> for plain TeX files.</p>
<p>

By default, everything that follows a percent sign on a line is a comment, ignored by TeX. Running TeX on this file (for example, by typing tex myfile.tex in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/71915.xml">
command line interpreter</link>, or by calling it from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
graphical user interface</link>) will create an output file called <it>myfile.dvi</it>, representing the content of the page in a <b>d</b>e<b>v</b>ice <b>i</b>ndependent format (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/196831.xml">
DVI</link>).  The results can either be printed directly from a DVI viewer or converted to a more common format such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/24080.xml">
PostScript</link> using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/463499.xml">
dvips</link> program. This was because TeX natively uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/1094512.xml">
bitmap font</link>s, which are only designed to display well at one particular size, whereas PostScript typically uses scalable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/24080.xml">
Type 1 font</link>s. It is now possible to make dvips output scalable fonts with a bit of tweaking (newer versions of Ghostscript support it). TeX variants such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/17823517.xml">
PDFTeX</link> produce PDF files directly.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Mathematical example</st>

<p>

TeX provides a text syntax for mathematical formulae. For example, the well-known <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/25175.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Quadratic+formula%22])">
quadratic formula</link> would appear as:
The quadratic formula is $-b \pm \sqrt{b^2 - 4ac} \over 2a$
\end</p>
<p>

and the output would resemble:
<indent level="1">

The quadratic formula is <math>\textstyle{-b \pm \sqrt{b^2 - 4ac} \over 2a}</math>
</indent>

The formula is printed in a way a person would write by hand, or typeset the equation. In a document, entering <it>mathematics mode</it> is done by starting with a $, then entering a formula in TeX semantics and closing again with another $. Knuth explained in a jest that he chose the dollar sign to indicate the beginning and end of mathematical mode in plain TeX because typesetting mathematics was traditionally supposed to be expensive.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> <it>Display mathematics</it> (mathematics presented centered on a new line) is similar but uses $$ instead of $. For example, the above with the quadratic formula in display math:</p>
<p>

The quadratic formula is $$-b \pm \sqrt{b^2 - 4ac} \over 2a$$
\end</p>
<p>

renders as
<indent level="1">

The quadratic formula is
</indent>
<math>-b \pm \sqrt{b^2 - 4ac} \over 2a</math></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Novel aspects</st>
<p>

The TeX software incorporates several aspects that were not available, or were of lower quality, in other typesetting programs at the time when TeX was released. Some of the innovations are based on interesting algorithms, and have led to a number of theses for Knuth's students. While some of these discoveries have now been incorporated into other typesetting programs, others, such as the rules for mathematical spacing, are still unique. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Mathematical spacing</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="280px" src="AMS_Euler_sample_math.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Mathematical text typeset using TeX and the <font wordnetid="106825399" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/1325921.xml">
AMS Euler</link></font>
 font.
</caption>
</image>

Since the primary goal of TeX was the high-quality typesetting of his book <it>The Art of Computer Programming</it>, Knuth gave a lot of attention to the choice of proper spacing rules for mathematical formulae. He took three bodies of work that he considered as standards of excellence for mathematical typography: the books typeset by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/1180080.xml">
Addison-Wesley</link>, the publisher of <it>The Art of Computer Programming</it>, in particular the work done by <link>
Hans Wolf</link>; editions of the mathematical journal <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/6860708.xml">
Acta Mathematica</link></publication>
</periodical>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it> dating from around 1910; and a copy of <it><link>
Indagationes Mathematicae</link></it>, a <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/21148.xml">
Dutch</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 mathematics journal. Knuth looked closely at these examples to derive a set of spacing rules for TeX.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> While TeX provides some basic rules and the tools needed to specify proper spacing, the exact parameters depend on the font used to typeset the formula. For example, the spacing for Knuth's <font wordnetid="106825399" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/639806.xml">
Computer Modern</link></font>
 fonts has been precisely fine-tuned over the years and is now frozen, but when other fonts, such as <font wordnetid="106825399" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/1325921.xml">
AMS Euler</link></font>
, were used by Knuth for the first time, new spacing parameters had to be defined.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hyphenation and justification</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Crystal_Clear_app_kedit.svg">
<caption>

Notepad
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>To comply with Wikipedia's , this section may need to be rewritten.</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=TeX&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink>. The may contain suggestions.</col>
</row>
</table>


In comparison with manual typesetting, the problem of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/394049.xml">
justification</link> is easy to solve with a digital system such as TeX, which, provided that good points for line breaking have been defined, can automatically spread the spaces between words to fill in the line. The problem is thus to find the set of breakpoints that will give the most pleasing result. Many line breaking algorithms use a <it>first-fit</it> approach, where the breakpoints for each line are determined one after the other, and no breakpoint is changed after it has been chosen.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> Such a system is not able to define a breakpoint depending on the effect that it will have on the following lines. In comparison, the <it>total-fit</it> line breaking algorithm used by TeX and developed by Donald Knuth and <link>
Michael Plass</link> considers <it>all</it> the possible breakpoints in a paragraph, and finds the combination of line breaks that will produce the most globally pleasing arrangement. </p>
<p>

Formally, the algorithm defines a value called <it>badness</it> associated with each possible line break; the badness is increased if the spaces on the line must stretch or shrink too much to make the line the correct width. Penalties are added if a breakpoint is particularly undesirable: for example, if a word must be hyphenated, if two lines in a row are hyphenated, or if a very loose line is immediately followed by a very tight line. The algorithm will then find the breakpoints that will minimize the sum of squares of the badness (including penalties) of the resulting lines. If the paragraph contains <math>n</math> possible breakpoints, the number of situations that must be evaluated naively is <math>2^n</math>. However, by using the method of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/125297.xml">
dynamic programming</link>, the complexity of the algorithm can be brought down to <math>O(n^2)</math> (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/44578.xml">
Big O notation</link>). Further simplifications (for example, not testing extremely unlikely breakpoints such as a hyphenation in the first word of a paragraph) lead to an efficient algorithm whose running time is almost always of order <math>n</math>. However, in general, a thesis by <link>
Michael Plass</link> shows how the page breaking problem can be <class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/39466.xml">
NP-complete</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
 because of the added complication of placing figures.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> A similar algorithm is used to determine the best way to break paragraphs across two pages, in order to avoid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/851428.xml">
widows</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/851428.xml">
orphans</link> (lines that appear alone on a page while the rest of the paragraph is on the following or preceding page). </p>
<p>

TeX's line breaking algorithm has been adopted by several other programs, such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/176323.xml">
Adobe InDesign</link></software>
 a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/54257.xml">
desktop publishing</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/454746.xml">
application</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/11875.xml">
GNU</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/10105654.xml">
fmt</link> <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/6707.xml">
command line</link> utility.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>
<p>

If no suitable line break can be found for a line, the system will try to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/59347.xml">
hyphen</link>ate a word. The original version of TeX used a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/2842189.xml">
hyphenation algorithm</link> based on a set of rules for the removal of prefixes and suffixes of words, and for deciding if it should insert a break between the two consonants in a pattern of the form <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/32693.xml">
vowel</link>&ndash;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/5641.xml">
consonant</link>&ndash;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/5641.xml">
consonant</link>&ndash;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/32693.xml">
vowel</link> (which is possible most of the time).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> TeX82 uses a new hyphenation algorithm, designed by <link>
Frank Liang</link> in 1983, to assign priorities to breakpoints in letter groups. A list of hyphenation patterns is first generated automatically from a corpus of hyphenated words (a list of 50,000 words). If TeX must find the acceptable hyphenation positions in the word <it>encyclopedia</it>, for example, it will consider all the subwords of the extended word <it>.encyclopedia.</it>, where <it>.</it> is a special marker to indicate the beginning or end of the word. The list of subwords include all the subwords of length 1 (<it>.</it>, <it>e</it>, <it>n</it>, <it>c</it>, <it>y</it>, etc), of length 2 (<it>.e</it>, <it>en</it>, <it>nc</it>, etc), etc, up to the subword of length 14, which is the word itself, including the markers. TeX will then look into its list of hyphenation patterns, and find subwords for which it has calculated the desirability of hyphenation at each position. In the case of our word, 11 such patterns can be matched, namely 
1c4l4, 1cy, 1d4i3a, 4edi, e3dia, 2i1a, ope5d, 2p2ed, 3pedi, pedia4, y1c. For each position in the word, TeX will calculate the <it>maximum value</it> obtained among all matching pattern, yielding en1cy1c4l4o3p4e5d4i3a4. Finally, the acceptable positions are those indicated by an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/143135.xml">
odd</link> number, yielding the acceptable hyphenations <it>en-cy-clo-pe-di-a</it>. This system based on subwords allows the definition of very general patterns (such as 2i1a), with low indicative numbers (either odd or even), which can then be superseded by more specific patterns (such as 1d4i3a) if necessary. These patterns find about 90% of the hyphens in the original dictionary; more importantly, they do not insert any spurious hyphen. In addition, a list of exceptions (words for which the patterns do not predict the correct hyphenation) are included with the Plain TeX format; additional ones can be specified by the user.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
METAFONT</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/44263.xml">
METAFONT</link></it>
</indent>
METAFONT, not strictly part of TeX, is a font description system which allows the designer to describe characters algorithmically. It uses <link>
Bezier curve</link>s in a fairly standard way to generate the actual characters to be displayed, but Knuth devotes lots of attention to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../087/1172087.xml">
rasterizing</link> problem on <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/25742.xml">
bitmap</link></format>
</artifact>
</structure>
</information>
</message>
ped displays. Another thesis, by <link>
John Hobby</link>, further explores this problem of digitizing “brush trajectories”. This term derives from the fact that METAFONT describes characters as having been drawn by abstract brushes (and erasers).</p>
<p>

It is possible to use TeX and LaTeX without METAFONT. Adobe PostScript (“Type 1”) fonts may be used instead. (La)TeX expects fonts to be supplied as bitmaps at specific point sizes, while PostScript is a vector (outline) description scalable over a wide range, so this does introduce some minor complications. Nonetheless, with the help of some prewritten packages, (La)TeX can be made to use PostScript fonts. Further note that “Type 1” or “T1” can refer in documentation to two very different things: the TeX T1 character encoding scheme to map byte values to glyphs, and Adobe PostScript fonts.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Macro language </st>

<p>

TeX provides an unusual macro language; the definition of a macro not only includes a list of commands but also the syntax of the call. Macros are completely integrated with a full-scale interpreted compile-time language that also guides processing. </p>
<p>

TeX's macro level of operation is lexical, but it is a built-in facility of TeX, that makes use of syntax interpretation. Comparing with most widely used <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/81971.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Lexical+pre-processors%22])">
lexical preprocessors</link> like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/625653.xml">
M4</link>, it differs slightly, as the body of a macro gets tokenized at definition time, that is, it is not completely raw text. Except for a few very special cases, this gives the same behaviour. </p>
<p>

The TeX macro language has been successfully used to extend TeX to, for instance, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/18195.xml">
LaTeX</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/918538.xml">
ConTeXt</link>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Development </st>

<p>

The original source code for the current TeX software is written in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/87394.xml">
WEB</link>, a mixture of documentation written in TeX and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/23773.xml">
Pascal</link> subset in order to ensure portability. For example, TeX does all of its dynamic allocation itself from fixed-size arrays and uses only <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/449736.xml">
fixed-point arithmetic</link> for its internal calculations.  As a result, TeX has been ported to almost all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>s, usually by using the <link>
web2c</link> program to convert the source code into <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/6021.xml">
C</link></programming_language>
 instead of directly compiling the Pascal code. </p>
<p>

Knuth has kept a very detailed log of all the bugs he has corrected and changes he has made in the program since 1982; as of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/891251.xml">
2005</link>, the list contains 419 entries, not including the version modification that should be done after his death as the final change in TeX.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> Donald Knuth offers <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<award wordnetid="106696483" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/1484627.xml">
monetary awards</link></signal>
</award>
</symbol>
 to people who find and report a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/37085.xml">
bug</link> in TeX. The award per bug started at $2.56 (one "hexadecimal dollar"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref>) and doubled every year until it was frozen at its current value of $327.68. This has not made Knuth poor, however, as there have been very few bugs claimed. In addition, people have been known to frame a check proving they found a bug in TeX instead of cashing it.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Packages</st>

<p>

TeX is usually provided in the form of an easy-to-install bundle of TeX itself along with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/44263.xml">
METAFONT</link> and all the necessary fonts, documents formats, and utilities needed to use the typesetting system. On <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
UNIX</link></family>
-compatible systems, including <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>, TeX is distributed in the form of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/6517703.xml">
teTeX</link> distribution and more recently the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/9651386.xml">
TeX Live</link></software>
 distribution. On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link>, there is the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/1204926.xml">
MiKTeX</link></software>
 distribution (enhanced by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/protext">
ProTeX</weblink> ) and the [https://xemtex.groups.foundry.supelec.fr/xemtex-web-gb-2-5.html fpTeX] distribution.</p>
<p>

Several document processing systems are based on TeX, notably <link>
jadeTeX</link>, which uses TeX as a backend for printing from <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<computer_user wordnetid="109951274" confidence="0.8">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/460690.xml">
James Clark</link></causal_agent>
</engineer>
</programmer>
</computer_user>
</person>
</physical_entity>
's <link>
DSSSL Engine</link>, the <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<editor wordnetid="110044879" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/12262817.xml">
Arbortext</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</editor>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
 publishing system, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/405902.xml">
Texinfo</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/11875.xml">
GNU</link> documentation processing system. TeX has been the official typesetting package for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/11875.xml">
GNU operating system</link> since 1984.</p>
<p>

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/1316123.xml">
XeTeX</link></software>
 is a new TeX engine that supports <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/31742.xml">
Unicode</link>. Originally making use of advanced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>-specific font technologies, it now supports <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/194776.xml">
OpenType</link></format>
 and is available on Linux and Microsoft Windows.</p>
<p>

Numerous extensions and companion programs for TeX exist, among them <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/239392.xml">
BibTeX</link></format>
</information>
</message>
 for bibliographies (distributed with LaTeX), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/17823517.xml">
pdfTeX</link>, which bypasses dvi and produces output in <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/1955.xml">
Adobe Systems</link></company>
' <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
Portable Document Format</link></format>
</language>
</information>
</message>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/596407.xml">
Omega</link>, which allows TeX to use the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/31742.xml">
Unicode</link> character set. Most TeX extensions are available for free from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/187689.xml">
CTAN</link>, the Comprehensive TeX Archive Network.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Editors</st>

<p>

The <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/167852.xml">
TeXmacs</link></software>
 text editor is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/33291.xml">
WYSIWYG</link> scientific text editor that is intended to be compatible with TeX and <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<editor wordnetid="110044879" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/18933234.xml">
Emacs</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</editor>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
. It uses Knuth's fonts, and can generate TeX output.</p>
<p>

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/166127.xml">
LyX</link></software>
 is a “What You See is What You Mean” document processor which runs on a variety of platforms including Linux, Windows (newer versions require Windows 2000 or later) or Mac OS X (using a non-native <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/25204.xml">
Qt</link> front-end).</p>
<p>

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/1316112.xml">
TeXShop</link></software>
 for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>, and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/805186.xml">
WinShell</link></software>
 for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link> are similar tools and provide integrated development environment (IDE) for working with LaTeX or TeX. For <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/16629.xml">
KDE</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/1089680.xml">
Kile</link></software>
 provides such an IDE.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/18933234.xml">
GNU Emacs</link> has various built-in and third party packages with support for TeX, the major one being <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/2607243.xml">
AUCTeX</link>.  For <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<editor wordnetid="110044879" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/32478.xml">
Vim</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</editor>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
 there is the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://vim-latex.sourceforge.net/">
Vim-LaTeX Suite</weblink>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
License</st>
<p>

Donald Knuth has indicated several times<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> that the source code of TeX has been placed into the "public domain," and he strongly encourages modifications or experimentations with this source code. However, since the code is still copyrighted, it is technically <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/10635.xml">
free</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/277663.xml">
open-source software</link> but is not in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link> in the legal sense.  In particular, since Knuth highly values the reproducibility of the output of all versions of TeX, any changed version must not be called TEX, TeX, or anything confusingly similar. To enforce this rule, any implementation of the system must pass a test suite called the <link>
TRIP test</link> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://tug.ctan.org/pub/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/tex/trip.tex">
available on CTAN</weblink>) before being allowed to be called TeX. The question of license is somewhat confused by the statements included at the beginning of the TeX source code<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref>, which indicate that “<it>all rights are reserved. Copying of this file is authorized only if (...) you make absolutely no changes to your copy</it>”. However, this restriction should be interpreted as a prohibition to change the source code <it>as long as the file is called tex.web</it>. This interpretation is confirmed later in the source code when the TRIP test is mentioned (“<it>If this program is changed, the resulting system should not be called ‘TeX’</it>”).</p>
<p>

The <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/198822.xml">
American Mathematical Society</link></organization>
 has also claimed a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/18935023.xml">
trademark</link> for TeX, which was rejected, because at the time this was tried (early 1980s), “TEX” (all caps) was registered by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/225721.xml">
Honeywell</link></company>
 for the “Text EXecutive” text processing system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Use of TeX</st>

<p>

In several technical fields, in particular computer science, mathematics and physics, TeX has become a de facto standard. Many thousands of books have been published using TeX, including books published by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/1180080.xml">
Addison-Wesley</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/73199.xml">
Cambridge University Press</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/420561.xml">
Elsevier</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/48518.xml">
Oxford University Press</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/1418949.xml">
Springer</link></institution>
</company>
. Numerous journals in these fields are produced using TeX or LaTeX, allowing authors to submit their raw manuscript written in TeX.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref></p>
<p>

While many publications in other fields, including dictionaries and legal publications, have been produced using TeX, it has not been as successful as in more technical fields, in particular because TeX was primarily designed for mathematics. When he designed TeX, Donald Knuth did not believe that a single typesetting system would fit everyone's needs; instead, he designed many hooks inside the program so that it would be possible to write extensions, and released the source code, hoping that publishers would design versions tailored to their needs. While such extensions have been created (including some by Knuth himself<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>), most people have extended TeX only using macros and it has remained a system associated with technical typesetting.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Pronouncing and writing "TeX"</st>
<p>

The name TeX is intended to be pronounced . The X is meant to represent the <W wordnetid="106833544" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/715909.xml">
Greek</link></W>
 letter <it>χ</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/166706.xml">
chi</link>). TeX is the abbreviation of <it>τέχνη</it> (ΤΕΧΝΗ – technē), Greek for both "art" and "craft", which is also the root word of <it>technical</it>.  English speakers often pronounce it /ˈtɛk/, like the first syllable of <it>technical</it>.</p>
<p>

The name is properly typeset with the "E" below the baseline and reduced spacing between the letters. This is done, as Donald Knuth mentions in his TeXBook, to distinguish ΤeΧ from other system names such as TEX, the Text EXecutive processor (developed by Honeywell Information Systems).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref> Fans like to proliferate names from the word “TeX” &mdash; such as <it>TeXnician</it> (user of TeX software), <it>TeXpert</it>, <it>TeXhacker</it> (TeX programmer), <it>TeXmaster</it> (competent TeX programmer), <it>TeXhax</it>, and <it>TeXnique</it>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Community </st>

<p>

Notable entities in the TeX community include the <association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<club wordnetid="108227214" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/2724732.xml">
TeX Users Group</link></club>
</association>
, which publishes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/2202360.xml">
TUGboat</link> and <periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/2200848.xml">
The PracTeX Journal</link></periodical>
, and <association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<club wordnetid="108227214" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/4660608.xml">
Deutschsprachige Anwendervereinigung TeX</link></club>
</association>
, a large user group in Germany.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Free_Software_Portal_Logo.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Free software&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/1571680.xml">
List of document markup languages</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/1574968.xml">
Comparison of document markup languages</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/52313.xml">
MathML</link></format>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/486362.xml">
Formula editor</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/192978.xml">
Texvc</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/2177009.xml">
PSTricks</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>This article was originally based on material from the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<wordbook wordnetid="106418693" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<dictionary wordnetid="106418901" confidence="0.8">
<reference_book wordnetid="106417598" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/11324.xml">
Free On-line Dictionary of Computing</link></publication>
</reference_book>
</dictionary>
</book>
</wordbook>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
, which is  under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/18938782.xml">
GFDL</link>.''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Donald E. Knuth. <it>The TeXbook</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/288504.xml">
Computers and Typesetting</link>, Volume A). Reading, Massachusetts: Addison-Wesley, 1984. ISBN 0-201-13448-9. The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ctan.org/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/tex/texbook.tex">
source code of the book in TeX</weblink> (and a needed set of macros <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://tug.ctan.org/pub/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/lib/manmac.tex">
ftp://tug.ctan.org/pub/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/lib/manmac.tex</weblink>) is available online on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/187689.xml">
CTAN</link>. It is provided only as an example and its use to prepare a book like The TeXbook is not allowed.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Donald E. Knuth. <it>TeX: The Program</it> (Computers and Typesetting, Volume B). Reading, Massachusetts: Addison-Wesley, 1986. ISBN 0-201-13437-3. The full source code of TeX; also available on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/187689.xml">
CTAN</link> at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://tug.ctan.org/pub/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/tex/tex.web">
ftp://tug.ctan.org/pub/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/tex/tex.web</weblink>. Being written using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/18136.xml">
literate programming</link>, it contains plenty of human-readable documentation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Donald E. Knuth. <it>Digital Typography</it> (CSLI lecture notes, no 78). Center for the Study of Language and Information, 1999. ISBN 1-57586-010-4.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Donald E. Knuth and Michael F. Plass. <it>Breaking Paragraphs Into Lines</it>, Software &mdash; Practice and Experience <b>11</b> (1981), 1119&ndash;1184. Reprinted as chapter 3 of <it>Digital Typography</it>, p. 67&ndash;155.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/195671.xml">
Leslie Lamport</link></scientist>
. <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/18195.xml">
LaTeX</link>: A Document Preparation System</it>. Addison-Wesley, Reading, Massachusetts: Addison-Wesley, 2nd. ed., 1994. ISBN 0-201-52983-1.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Franklin Mark Liang. <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/docs/liang/">
Word Hy-phen-a-tion by Com-put-er</weblink></it>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/8775.xml">
PhD</link> thesis, Department of Computer Science, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/26977.xml">
Stanford University</link></university>
, August 1983.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 M.D. Spivak. <it>The Joy of TeX</it> (2nd edition). American Mathematical Society, 1990. ISBN 0-8218-2997-1. <it>Reference on AMS-TeX</it>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Nelson H.F. Beebe. <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb25-1/beebe-2003keynote.pdf">
25 Years of TeX and METAFONT: Looking Back and Looking Forward</weblink></it>, TUGboat <b>25</b> (2004), 7&ndash;30.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Michael Vulis, <it>Modern TeX and Its Applications</it>, CRC Press, 1992. ISBN 0-8493-4431-X</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes </st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gcc.gnu.org/ml/java/1999-q2/msg00419.html">
Per Bothner (assistant of Knuth) discusses authorship</weblink>".&nbsp;"Knuth definitely wrote most of the code himself, at least for the Metafont re-write, for which I have personal knowledge.  However, some of his students (such as Michael Plass and John Hob by) did work on the algorithms used in TeX and Metafont."</entry>
<entry id="2">
Beccari, Claudio&#32;(1997).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb18-1/tb54becc.pdf">
Typesetting mathematics for science and technology according to ISO31XI</weblink>".&#32;<it>TUGboat</it>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Donald E. Knuth. <it>Digital Typography</it>. Commemorative lecture for the <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<award wordnetid="106696483" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/216053.xml">
Kyoto Prize</link></signal>
</award>
</symbol>
, <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/37652.xml">
Kyoto</link></site>
, 1996. Reprinted as chapter 1 of the book <it>Digital Typography</it>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
<it>Digital Typography</it>, p. 5. “<it>I had spent 15 years writing those books, but if they were going to look awful I didn't want to write any more.</it>”</entry>
<entry id="5">
Donald E. Knuth. <it>TEXDR.AFT</it>, chapter 24 of the book <it>Digital Typography</it>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Knuth and Plass, p. 144</entry>
<entry id="7">
Donald E. Knuth, <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://maps.aanhet.net/maps/pdf/16_15.pdf">
Knuth meets NTG members</weblink></it>, NTG: MAPS. <b>16</b> (1996), 38&ndash;49. Reprinted as <it>Questions and Answers, III</it>, chapter 33 of <it>Digital Typography</it>, p. 648.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Donald E. Knuth. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb10-3/tb25knut.pdf">
<it>The New Versions of TeX and METAFONT''</it></weblink>, TUGboat <b>10</b> (1989), 325&ndash;328; <b>11</b> (1990), 12. Reprinted as chapter 29 of <it>Digital Typography</it>.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Donald E. Knuth. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ntg.nl/maps/05/34.pdf">
<it>The future of TeX and METAFONT''</it></weblink>, NTG journal MAPS (1990), 489. Reprinted as chapter 30 of <it>Digital Typography</it>, p. 571.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Donald E. Knuth and Pierre MacKay. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb08-1/tb17knutmix.pdf">
<it>Mixing Right-to-Left Texts with Left-to-Right Texts''</it></weblink>, TUGboat <b>8</b> (1987), 14–25. Reprinted as chapter 4 of <it>Digital Typography</it>.</entry>
<entry id="11">
<it>The TeXbook</it>, p. 9.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Donald E. Knuth, <it>The TeXbook</it>, Ch. 16: Typing Math Formulas, p. 127.</entry>
<entry id="13">
Donald E. Knuth. <it>Questions and Answers II</it>, TUGboat <b>17</b> (1996), 355&ndash;367. Reprinted as chapter 32 of <it>Digital Typography</it>, p. 620.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Donald E. Knuth. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb10-1/tb23knut.pdf">
<it>Typesetting Concrete Mathematics''</it></weblink>, TUGboat <b>10</b> (1989), 31&ndash;36, 342. Reprinted as chapter 18 of <it>Digital Typography</it>.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Michael P. Barnett. <it>Computer Typesetting: Experiments and Prospects</it>. <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/5685.xml">
Cambridge</link></village>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1645518.xml">
Massachusetts</link></country>
: <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/719601.xml">
MIT Press</link></company>
, 1965.</entry>
<entry id="17">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/53256.xml">
Advogato</link></web_site>
. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.advogato.org/article/28.html">
Interview of Donald E. Knuth</weblink> (PDF file, also available in <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.advogato.org/article/28.html">
http://www.advogato.org/article/28.html</weblink>), TUGboat <b>21</b> (2000), 103&ndash;110.</entry>
<entry id="16">
Knuth and Plass</entry>
<entry id="19">
Liang, p. 3</entry>
<entry id="18">
GNU Project, <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/textutils/manual/textutils/html_node/textutils_9.html#SEC9">
GNU text utilities manual, 4.1 fmt: Reformat paragraph text</weblink></it>. 2000.</entry>
<entry id="21">
<it>The TeXbook</it>, Appendix H: Hyphenation, pp. 449&ndash;455.</entry>
<entry id="20">
Liang, PhD thesis</entry>
<entry id="23">
Donald E. Knuth, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://tug.ctan.org/pub/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/errata/errorlog.tex">
Appendix to the <it>Errors of TeX</it> paper</weblink>, available on CTAN, last modified in January 2003.</entry>
<entry id="22">
Donald E. Knuth, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://tug.ctan.org/pub/tex-archive/systems/knuth/dist/errata/tex82.bug">
List of updates to the TeX82 listing published in September 1982</weblink>, available on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/187689.xml">
CTAN</link>.</entry>
<entry id="25">
Kara Platoni, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stanfordalumni.org/news/magazine/2006/mayjun/features/knuth.html">
Love at First Byte</weblink>. Stanford Magazine, May-June 2006</entry>
<entry id="24">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sunburn.stanford.edu/~knuth/faq.html">
Frequently Asked Questions</weblink> on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sunburn.stanford.edu/~knuth/">
Don Knuth's webpage</weblink></entry>
<entry id="27">
<it>The future of TeX and METAFONT</it>, p. 572 of the book <it>Digital Typography</it>.</entry>
<entry id="26">
The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/whatis.html">
History of TeX</weblink></entry>
<entry id="29">
Donald E. Knuth, <it>TeX: The Program</it>.</entry>
<entry id="28">
Donald E. Knuth. <it>Computers and Typesettings</it> (available online split into 2 files: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb07-2/tb15gordon.pdf">
http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb07-2/tb15gordon.pdf</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb07-2/tb15knut.pdf">
http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb07-2/tb15knut.pdf</weblink>), TUGboat <b>7</b> (1986), 95–98. Reprinted as chapter 28 of <it>Digital Typography</it>, p. 560.</entry>
<entry id="31">
Beebe, p.10</entry>
<entry id="30">
<it>The TeXbook</it>, p. 1.</entry>
<entry id="34">
Donald E. Knuth. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/TUGboat/Articles/tb07-2/tb15knutlogo.pdf">
<it>The TeX Logo in Various Fonts''</it></weblink>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/2202360.xml">
TUGboat</link> <b>7</b> (1986), 101. Reprinted as chapter 6 of <it>Digital Typography</it>.</entry>
<entry id="32">
Donald E. Knuth. <it>Questions and Answers I</it>, TUGboat <b>17</b> (1996), 7–22. Reprinted as chapter 31 of <it>Digital Typography</it>, p. 598.</entry>
<entry id="33">
Donald E. Knuth. <it>Questions and Answers II</it>, TUGboat <b>17</b> (1996), 355–367. Reprinted as chapter 32 of <it>Digital Typography</it>, p. 616–617.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://refcards.com/docs/silvermanj/tex/tex-refcard-letter.pdf">
Plain TeX Quick Reference (PDF)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tex.ac.uk/cgi-bin/texfaq2html?introduction=yes">
UK TeX Users' Group FAQ</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Simon Eveson. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-users.york.ac.uk/~spe1/texnotes07.pdf">
<it>An Introduction to Mathematical Document Production Using AmSLaTeX''</it></weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tug.org/texshowcase/">
The TeX showcase</weblink> gallery of typesetting examples</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Eijkhout, Victor. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eijkhout.net/tbt/">
<it>TeX by Topic''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.gwdg.de/pub/dante/info/impatient/book.pdf">
<it>TeX for the Impatient (PDF)''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Walsh, Norman. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://makingtexwork.sourceforge.net/mtw/">
<it>Making TeX Work''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Plain TeX supported by <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/6279949.xml">
MathMagic</link></software>
 equation editor</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
