<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:44:36[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Erucic acid</title>
<id>302078</id>
<revision>
<id>242796890</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T18:21:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Aspro</username>
<id>255486</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Fatty acids</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="float: right; clear: right; margin: 0 0 1em 1em; border-collapse: collapse;" width="250px" class="toccolours" border="1">
<header colspan="2" style="width: 30%; background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;">
Erucic acid</header>
<row>
<col colspan="2" align="center" bgcolor="#ffffff">
 <image width="300px" src="Erucic_acid.png">
</image>
</col>
</row>


<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/3141503.xml">
IUPAC name</link></col>
<col>
(<it>Z</it>)-Docos-13-enoic acid</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
style="background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;" colspan="2"</header>
<header>
style="background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;" colspan="2"</header>
<col colspan="2" style="width: 30%; background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;">
 Except where noted otherwise, data are given for materials in their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/240224.xml">
standard state(at 25&nbsp;°C, 100&nbsp;kPa)</link></col>
</row>
</table>
<p>

<b>Erucic acid</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/264748.xml">
monounsaturated</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/3110439.xml">
omega-9</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>, denoted 22:1 ω-9.  It is prevalent in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/219545.xml">
rapeseed</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/59916.xml">
wallflower</link> seed, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/187774.xml">
mustard seed</link>, making up 40-50% of their oils.  Erucic acid is also known as <it>cis</it>-13-docosenoic acid and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/12528.xml">
trans isomer</link> is known as <link>
brassidic acid</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Uses </st>
<p>

It has many of the same uses as mineral oils but with the advantage that it is more readily bio-degradable. Its high tolerance to temperature makes it suitable for transmission oil.  Its ability to polymerize and dry means it can be - and is - used as a binder for oil <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/23776.xml">
paint</link>s. Erucic acid will readily form many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../203/22203.xml">
organic compounds</link>.  Adding this ability to its polymerizing characteristics makes it very suitable for use as <link>
organic matrices</link> that need to be polymeric. This makes it especially useful in the manufacture of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/10290.xml">
emulsions</link> to coat photographic films and papers. A complex cocktail of many different erucic acid compounds is commonly used in just one roll of color film. It is widely used to produce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/188678.xml">
emollient</link>s, especially for skin and healthcare products.  Like other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>s, it gets converted into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/133176.xml">
surfactant</link>s.
Erucic acid is especially valued in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/489228.xml">
tribology</link> as a superior lubricant. When used in the manufacture of plastic films in the form of erucamide, it migrates to the surfaces and so resists the sticking of each film to its neighbor.  Being a hydrocarbon of high calorific value, with a very low flash point, high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/1034567.xml">
cetane</link> rating, and good lubrication qualities, erucic acid can be a valuable component of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/81761.xml">
bio-diesel</link>.
When converted into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/13769394.xml">
behenyl alcohol</link> (CH3(CH2)21OH), erucic acid has many further uses such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/4771910.xml">
pour point</link> depressant, enabling liquids to flow at a lower temperature and silver behenate for use in photography.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Sources of  erucic acid </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="RanscombeFarmRape9919.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

The seed oil of the rape plant is rich in erucic acid.
</caption>
</image>

The name <it>erucic</it> means: of or pertaining to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/13565158.xml">
eruca</link>;  which is a genus of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/18967.xml">
flowering plant</link>s in the family <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/3794.xml">
Brassicaceae</link>. It is also the Latin for coleworth; which today, is better known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/571106.xml">
kale</link>.
Erucic acid is produced naturally (together with other fatty acids) across a great range of green plants, but especially so in members of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/106355.xml">
brassica</link> family. It is highest in some of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/219545.xml">
rapeseed</link> varieties of brassicas, kale and mustard being some of the highest, followed by Brussels spouts and broccoli. For industrial purposes, a <it>High-Erucic Acid Rapeseed</it> (HEAR) has been developed. These cultivars can yield 40% to 60% of the total oil recovered as erucic acid.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Metabolism of erucic acid  </st>
<p>

Erucic acid is broken down in the human body by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/9257.xml">
enzyme</link>s (long-chain acyl-coenzyme A (CoA)  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/81659.xml">
dehydrogenase</link>) produced in the liver, which chop it into shorter-chain fatty acids, which are, in turn, broken down. For more information on this see: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/5988464.xml">
Lipid metabolism</link>. Based on animal studies in adult pigs and piglets, it can be reasonably presumed that, in human infants that have not yet been weaned, these particular enzymes are in short supply (as the mother's milk is the normal food source during this period), although not totally absent. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>
Because of this, babies should not be given foods high in erucic acid. Before low-erucic acid oil rapeseed (LEAR &amp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/86190.xml">
Canola</link>) cultivars were developed, this situation was unlikely to present a realistic danger since erucic acid occurs in nature only along with bitter-tasting compounds that infants instinctively reject. In these new varieties, the bitterness or pungency has been considerably reduced to make it more palatable to humans and cattle; however erucic acid content is also greatly reduced well below the 2% limit on erucic acid content set by the FDA.
Studies on rats have shown that they are less able to digest vegetable fats (whether or not they contain erucic acid) than humans and pigs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Chariton et al. suggests that in rats: “Inefficient activation of erucic acid
to erucyl-CoA and a low level of activity of triglyceride lipase and enzymes of betaoxidation for erucic acid probably contribute
to the accumulation and retention of cardiac lipid.”<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Before this process was fully understood, however, there developed a misunderstanding, which continues to be repeated until this day. See below.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Health effects </st>
<p>

No negative health effects have ever been documented in humans, although it is advisable not to give un-weaned babies foods containing erucic acid for the reasons given above.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

Epidemiological studies suggest that, in regions where mustard oil is still used in a traditional manner, mustard oil may afford some protection against cardiovascular diseases. In this sense 'traditional' means that the (a) oil is used fresh and (b) vegetable fats count only as a small percentage of the total caloric intake. Whether this effect is due to the nature of erucic acid <it>per se</it> to make the blood platelets less sticky, or to the presence of a reasonably high percentage of α-linolenic acid, or to a combination of properties of fresh unrefined oil, is as yet uncertain. Care needs to be taken with such epidemiological studies in order to exclude the possibility of early deaths from other causes skewing the results. The fact that early asymptomatic coronary disease is readily detectable post mortem and is absent in the mustard oil cohorts tends to add weight to the hypothesis that mustard oil is protective. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

A four-to-one mixture of erucic acid and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/661100.xml">
oleic acid</link> constitutes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/538131.xml">
Lorenzo's oil</link>; an experimental treatment for a rare neurobiology disorder <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/52952.xml">
adrenoleukodystrophy</link>.</p>
<p>

The high percentage of erucic acid in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/746422.xml">
mustard oil</link> has led to its being banned for food use in the <economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
European Union</link></economy>
 and other countries.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Health concerns </st>
<p>

Before <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/12383.xml">
genetic engineering</link>, plant breeders were aiming to produce a less-bitter-tasting multi-purpose oil from rapeseed that would appeal to a larger market by making it more palatable for cattle and other livestock. While it was possible to breed out much of the pungent-tasting glucosinolates, one of the dominant erucic acid genes would get stripped out of the genome as well, greatly reducing its valuable erucic acid content. Studies on rats show lipodosis problems when fed high quantities of erucic acid, however, so this did not hinder saleability.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Later trials showed that rats had the same problems with other vegetable fatty acids, <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> because rats are poor at metabolising some fats.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> The plant breeding industry later changed "low erucic acid" to be its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/644044.xml">
unique selling proposition</link>  over that of its competitors.</p>
<p>

There are not many studies done on humans with erucic acid; the majority are carried out by the food science industry on animals. Animal studies failed to show negative events occurring from feeding of erucic acid, and the studies were repeated under increasingly unnatural scenarios. In one case, neonate piglets that have a limited ability to absorb these fats had their normal sow's milk replaced solely with rapeseed oil for one hundred percent of their calorific needs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> The studies showed that lipidoses suffered by the piglets proved to be only a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/434754.xml">
transient</link> effect; the liver automatically responded by increasing enzyme levels to cope with the unusual diet, and the lipidoses subsided.</p>
<p>

A recent study recorded the higher rates of lung cancer in countries with populations that cook over solid fuel <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/33550.xml">
wood</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/7906908.xml">
biomass</link> fires and stoves. The possibility of production of smoke from heated oil was also considered, and it was established that rapeseed oil, which contains erucic acid, can cause increased <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/18450.xml">
lung carcinoma</link>s through emissions under high heat. However, the report also showed a variety of cooking oils also did this at similar heats. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Cardiac concerns </st>
<p>

The levels of erucic acid in human foods are restricted, in part, over concerns that it may adversely affect heart tissue.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>
It promotes myocardial lesions in male adult rat animal models, however the same effects were not observed in female adult rats.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/158799.xml">
Choline</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/866807.xml">
inositol</link> offered some protection against this damage,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> while <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/153316.xml">
alpha-linolenic acid</link> may have aggravated it.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>
Erucic acid is preferentially absorbed in myocardium tissue<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>
but is not metabolized there.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>
<p>

However, rats may present a poor animal model to study the effects of erucic acid on heart tissue due to poor ability to metabolize the substance.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Economic Research Service, USDA (September 1996) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/publications/IUS6/ius6c.pdf">
 Crambe, Industrial Rapeseed, and Tung Provide Valuable Oils</weblink>. <it>Fats and Oils</it>, Industrial Uses; Page 18. Retrieved 2007-01-29 </entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kramer JK, Farnworth ER, Johnston KM, Wolynetz MS, Modler HW, Sauer FD&#32;(Nov 1990).&#32;"Myocardial changes in newborn piglets fed sow milk or milk replacer diets containing different levels of erucic acid". <it>Lipids</it>&#32;<b>25</b>&#32;(11): 729–37. PMID 2280677.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Farnworth ER, Wolynetz MS, Modler HW, Kramer JK, Sauer FD, Johnston KM&#32;(1994).&#32;"Backfat and carcass composition of piglets fed milk replacers containing vegetable oil compared with sow-reared piglets". <it>Reprod. Nutr. Dev.</it>&#32;<b>34</b>&#32;(1): 25–35. PMID 8129839.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hulan HW, Kramer JK, Mahadevan S, Sauer FD&#32;(Jan 1976).&#32;"Relationship between erucic acid and myocardial changes in male rats". <it>Lipids</it>&#32;<b>11</b>&#32;(1): 9–15. PMID 1250074.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kramer JK, Farnworth ER, Thompson BK, Corner AH, Trenholm HL&#32;(May 1982).&#32;"Reduction of myocardial necrosis in male albino rats by manipulation of dietary fatty acid levels". <it>Lipids</it>&#32;<b>17</b>&#32;(5): 372–82. PMID 7098776.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">de Wildt DJ, Speijers GJ&#32;(Jun 1984).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/0041-008X(84)90275-8">
Influence of dietary rapeseed oil and erucic acid upon myocardial performance and hemodynamics in rats</weblink>". <it>Toxicol. Appl. Pharmacol.</it>&#32;<b>74</b>&#32;(1): 99–108. PMID 6729825.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Charlton KM, Corner AH, Davey K, Kramer JK, Mahadevan S, Sauer FD&#32;(Jul 1975).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pmcentrez&amp;artid=1277456">
Cardiac lesions in rats fed rapeseed oils</weblink>". <it>Can. J. Comp. Med.</it>&#32;<b>39</b>&#32;(3): 261–9. PMID 1170010.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
Food Standards Australia New Zealand (June 2003) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foodstandards.gov.au/_srcfiles/Erucic%20acid%20monograph.pdf">
 Erucic acid in food</weblink> : <it>A Toxicological Review and Risk Assessment .</it> Technical report series No. 21; Page 4 paragraph 1;  ISBN  0 642 34526 0, ISSN 1448-3017</entry>
<entry id="9">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.food.gov.uk/news/newsarchive/2004/sep/erucic">
Food Standards Agency - Agency issues warning on erucic acid</weblink>"&#32;(2 September 2004).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-02</link>.</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Rastogi T, Reddy KS, Vaz M, et al&#32;(Apr 2004).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ajcn.org/cgi/content/full/79/4/582">
Diet and risk of ischemic heart disease in India</weblink>". <it>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</it>&#32;<b>79</b>&#32;(4): 582–92. PMID 15051601.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Neat CE, Thomassen MS, Osmundsen H&#32;(Apr 1981).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pmcentrez&amp;artid=1162977">
Effects of high-fat diets on hepatic fatty acid oxidation in the rat. Isolation of rat liver peroxisomes by vertical-rotor centrifugation by using a self-generated, iso-osmotic, Percoll gradient</weblink>". <it>Biochem. J.</it>&#32;<b>196</b>&#32;(1): 149–59. PMID 6272750.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kramer et al..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jn.nutrition.org/cgi/content/abstract/103/12/1696">
Growth Rate, Lipid Composition, Metabolism and Myocardial Lesions of Rats Fed Rapeseed Oils</weblink>"&#32;(pdf). <it>Journal of Nutrition</it>&#32;<b>103</b>&#32;(12): 1696. PMID 4752972. Retrieved on <link>
2007-12-10</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
S Kurt, Baan R, Grosse Y, Secretan B, (2006) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ehs.sph.berkeley.edu/krsmith/publications/2006%20pubs/Lancet-Oncology3.pdf">
Carcinogenicity of household solid fuel combustion and of high-temperature frying</weblink>. WHO International Agency for Research on Cancer Monograph Working Group. PDF 52kb. Retrieved 2007-01-29</entry>
<entry id="14">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Clandinin MT, Yamashiro S&#32;(1982).&#32;"Dietary factors affecting the incidence of dietary fat-induced myocardial lesions". <it>J. Nutr.</it>&#32;<b>112</b>&#32;(4): 825–8. PMID 7200131. Retrieved on <link>
2007-12-10</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">McCutcheon JS, Umermura T, Bhatnager MK, Walker BL&#32;(1976).&#32;"Cardiopathogenicity of rapeseed oils and oil blends differing in erucic, linoleic, and linolenic acid content". <it>Lipids</it>&#32;<b>11</b>&#32;(7): 545–52. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2FBF02532900">
10.1007/BF02532900</weblink>. PMID 948250. Retrieved on <link>
2007-12-10</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Becker W, Bruce A&#32;(1985).&#32;"Autoradiographic studies with fatty acids and some other lipids: a review". <it>Prog. Lipid Res.</it>&#32;<b>24</b>&#32;(4): 325–46. PMID 3916594. Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-03</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/538131.xml">
Lorenzo's oil</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/17940.xml">
Lipid</link>s: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>s</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/264746.xml">
Saturated</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/232345.xml">
Butyric</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/2933897.xml">
Hexanoic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/3127774.xml">
Caprylic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/2349173.xml">
Decanoic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/1598497.xml">
Lauric</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/1718038.xml">
Myristic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/542488.xml">
Palmitic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/338511.xml">
Stearic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/542531.xml">
Arachidic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/3306741.xml">
Behenic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/3306766.xml">
Lignoceric</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/22594.xml">
<it>n</it>−3 Unsaturated</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/153316.xml">
α-Linolenic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/3956140.xml">
Stearidonic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/1593775.xml">
Eicosapentaenoic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/1673318.xml">
Docosahexaenoic</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/681218.xml">
<it>n</it>−6 Unsaturated</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/880497.xml">
Linoleic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/806075.xml">
γ-Linolenic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/3950770.xml">
Dihomo-γ-linolenic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/267909.xml">
Arachidonic</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/3110439.xml">
<it>n</it>−9 Unsaturated</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/661100.xml">
Oleic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/302078.xml">
Erucic</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/15602057.xml">
Nervonic</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
