<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:45:45[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<survey  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100644503">
<header>
<title>Accessibility</title>
<id>302109</id>
<revision>
<id>241747237</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-29T11:23:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Test accessibility</category>
<category>Urban studies and planning</category>
<category>Urban design</category>
<category>Disability</category>
<category>Transportation planning</category>
<category>Ergonomics</category>
<category>Accessibility</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For Wikipedia's accessibility policy, see .
For the wider design concept, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/1158081.xml">
Universal design</link>.  For the logical notion, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/3708585.xml">
Accessibility relation</link>.
<image location="right" width="200px" src="Curitiba_10_2006_05_RIT.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Universal access is provided in <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/439002.xml">
Curitiba</link></city>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/5705446.xml">
public transport</link> system, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/3383.xml">
Brazil</link></country>
.
</caption>
</image>

<b>Accessibility</b> is a general term used to describe the degree to which a product (e.g., device, service, environment) is accessible by as many people as possible. Accessibility can be viewed as the "ability to access" the functionality, and possible benefit, of some system or entity. Accessibility is often used to focus on people with disabilities and their right of access to entities, often through use of assistive technology. Several definitions of accessibility refer directly to access-based individual rights laws and regulations. Products or services designed to meet these regulations are often termed <it>Easy Access</it> or <it>Accessible</it>.<p>

Accessibility is not to be confused with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/288276.xml">
usability</link> which is used to describe the extent to which a product (e.g., device, service, environment) can be used by specified users to achieve specified goals with effectiveness, efficiency and satisfaction in a specified context of use.</p>
<p>

Accessibility is strongly related to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/1158081.xml">
universal design</link> when the approach involves "direct access." This is about making things accessible to all people (whether they have a disability or not). However, products marketed as having benefited from a Universal Design process are often actually the same devices customized specifically for use by people with disabilities.  An alternative is to provide "indirect access" by having the entity support the use of a person's assistive technology to achieve access (e.g., screen reader).  </p>

<sec>
<st>
Disabilities</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/436022.xml">
disability rights movement</link> advocates equal access to social, political, and economic life which includes not only physical access but access to the same tools, services, organizations and facilities which we all pay for. </p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Handicapped_Accessible_sign.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

This is the internationally recognized symbol for accessibility
</caption>
</image>

While it is often used to describe facilities or amenities to assist people with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/56285.xml">
disabilities</link>, as in "wheelchair accessible", the term can extend to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/3933.xml">
Braille</link> signage, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/106369.xml">
wheelchair</link> ramps, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/19373997.xml">
elevator</link>s, audio signals at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/158478.xml">
pedestrian crossing</link>s, walkway contours, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/1192305.xml">
website design</link>, and so on. </p>
<p>

Various countries have legislation requiring physical accessibility which are (in order of enactment):
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In the US, under the <right wordnetid="105174653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/1338.xml">
Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990</link></right>
, new public and private business construction generally must be accessible. Existing private businesses are required to increase the accessibility of their facilities when making any other renovations in proportion to the cost of the other renovations.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.access-board.gov/">
The U.S. Access Board</weblink> is "A Federal Agency Committed to Accessible Design for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/1160447.xml">
People with Disabilities</link>." Many states in the US have their own disability laws.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In Australia, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/3585500.xml">
Disability Discrimination Act 1992</link> has numerous provisions for accessibility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In the UK, the <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<legal_document wordnetid="106479665" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="106532095" confidence="0.8">
<right wordnetid="105174653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/227321.xml">
Disability Discrimination Act 1995</link></right>
</act>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</legal_document>
</document>
 has numerous provisions for accessibility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In South Africa <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/15750886.xml">
The Promotion of Equality and the Prevention of Unfair Discrimination Act 2000</link> has numerous provisions for accessibility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In Ontario, Canada, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/581381.xml">
Ontarians with Disabilities Act</link> of 2001 is meant to "improve the identification, removal and prevention of barriers faced by persons with disabilities..."</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Transportation</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Curitiba_10_2006_04_RIT.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Accessibility to all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/4146.xml">
buses</link> is provided in <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/439002.xml">
Curitiba</link></city>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/5705446.xml">
public transport</link> system. <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/3383.xml">
Brazil</link></country>
.
</caption>
</image>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/18580879.xml">
transport</link>ation, accessibility refers to the ease of reaching destinations. People who are in places that are highly accessible can reach many other activities or destinations quickly, people in inaccessible places can reach many fewer places in the same amount of time.</p>
<p>

A measure that is often used is to measure accessibility in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/1096272.xml">
traffic analysis zone</link> <it>i</it> is:</p>
<p>

<math>
Accessibility_i  = \sum_j {Opportunities_j } \times f\left( {C_{ij} } \right)
</math>
where:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <math>i</math> = index of origin zones</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <math>j</math> = index of destination zones</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <math>f\left( {C_{ij} } \right)</math> = function of generalized travel cost (so that nearer or less expensive places are weighted more than farther or more expensive places).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

For a non-motorized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/2398917.xml">
mode of transport</link>, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/33509.xml">
walking</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/5931.xml">
cycling</link>, the generalized travel cost may include additional factors such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/252712.xml">
safety</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/12461.xml">
gradient</link>.</p>
<p>

Automobile accessibility also refers to ease of use by disabled people.</p>



<ss1>
<st>
 Accessibility planning </st>

<p>

In the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/548847.xml">
Department for Transport</link> have mandated that each <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/52786.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22England%22])">
local authority</link> produce an Accessibility Plan that is incorporated in their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/3078950.xml">
Local Transport Plan</link>. An Accessibility Plan sets out how each local authority plans to improve access to employment, learning, health care, food shops and other services of local importance, particularly for disadvantaged groups and areas. Accessibility targets are defined in the accessibility plans, these are often the distance or time to access services by different modes of transport including walking, cycling and public transport.</p>
<p>

Accessibility Planning was introduced as a result of the report "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/upload/assets/www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/social_exclusion_task_force/publications_1997_to_2006/making_transport_2003.pdf">
Making the Connections: Final Report on Transport and Social Exclusion</weblink>". This report was the result of research carried out by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/3229028.xml">
Social Exclusion</link> Unit.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Low floor </st>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>"Low floor" redirects here</it>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/1206834.xml">
Low-floor bus</link>&nbsp;and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/1206833.xml">
Low-floor tram</link></it>
</indent>
A significant development in transportation, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/23894.xml">
public transport</link> in particular, to achieve accessibility, is the move to "low floor" vehicles. In a low floor vehicle, access to part or all of the passenger cabin is unobstructed from one or more entrances by the presence of steps, enabling easier access for the infirm or people with <conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/1005984.xml">
push chairs</link></vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</conveyance>
. A further aspect may be that the entrance and corridors are wide enough to accommodate a wheelchair. Low floor vehicles have been developed for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/4146.xml">
bus</link>es, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/54416.xml">
trolleybus</link>es and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/30733.xml">
trams</link>.</p>
<p>

Low floor in the vehicular sense is normally combined in a conceptual meaning with normal pedestrian access from a standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/3600229.xml">
kerb</link> height. However, the accessibility of a low floor vehicle can also be utilised from slightly raising portions of kerb at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/240496.xml">
bus stop</link>s, or through use of level boarding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/333625.xml">
bus rapid transit</link> 'stations' or tram stops. The combination of access from a kerb was the technological development of the 1990s, as step free interior layouts for buses had existed in some cases for decades, with entrance steps being introduced as chassis designs and overall height regulations changed.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Housing</st>

<p>

Most existing and new housing, even in the wealthiest nations, lack basic <link>
accessibility features</link> unless the designated, immediate occupant of a home currently has a disability.   However, there are some initiatives to change typical residential practices so that new homes incorporate basic access features such as zero-step entries and door widths adequate for wheelchairs to pass through.</p>
<p>

Great Britain applies the most widespread application of home access to date. In 1999, Parliament passed Section M, an amendment to residential building regulations requiring basic access in all new homes.  ("Doors to Be Swept Away in New Rules for Builders", Rachel Kelley, <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/39127.xml">
The Times</link></newspaper>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/8353.xml">
December 5</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/34601.xml">
1997</link>.)  In the United States, the 1988 Amendments to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../071/653071.xml">
Fair Housing Act</link> added people with disabilities, as well as familial status, to the classes already protected by law from discrimination (race, color, sex, religion and country of origin).  Among the protection for people with disabilities in the 1988 Amendments are  seven construction requirements for all multifamily buildings of more than four units first occupied after <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/20198.xml">
March 13</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/34703.xml">
1991</link>.  These seven requirements are as follows:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 An accessible building entrance on an accessible route.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Accessible common and public use areas.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Doors usable by a person in a wheelchair. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Accessible route into and through the dwelling unit.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Light switches, electrical outlets, thermostats and other environmental controls in accessible locations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Reinforced walls in bathrooms for later installation of grab bars.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Usable kitchens and bathrooms.</entry>
</list>

(From Fair Housing First, a website sponsored by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development).</p>
<p>

In spite of these advancements, the housing types where most people in the United States reside --single-family homes--are not covered by the Americans with Disabilities Act, the Fair Housing Act, or any other federal law with the exception of the small percentage of publicly-funded homes impacted by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/2819491.xml">
Section 504</link> of the Rehabilitation Act.  As a result, the great majority of new single-family homes replicate the barriers in existing homes.   </p>
<p>

The broad concept of Universal Design is relevant to housing, as it is to all aspects of the built environment.   Furthermore, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/6357548.xml">
Visitability</link> movement begun by grass roots disability advocates in the 1980s focuses specifically on changing construction practices in new housing.  This movement, a network of interested people working in their locales,  works on educating, passing laws, and spurring voluntary home access initiatives with the intention that basic access become a routine part of new home construction.</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Telecommunications and IT access</st>

<p>

Another dimension of accessibility is the ability to access information and services by minimizing the barriers of distance and cost as well as the usability of the interface.  In many countries this has led to initiatives, laws and regulations that aim toward providing universal access to the internet and to phone systems at reasonable cost to citizens.</p>
<p>

Currently there are a few major movements to coordinate a set of guidelines for accessibility for the web.  The first and most well known is The <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/181070.xml">
Web Accessibility Initiative</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (WAI), which is part of the World Wide Web Consortium (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/33434.xml">
W3C</link>). This organization developed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/5291317.xml">
Web Content Accessibility Guidelines</link> (WCAG) 1.0 which explains how to make Web content accessible to people with disabilities. Web "content" generally refers to the information in a Web page or Web application, including text, images, forms, sounds, and such. (More specific definitions are available in the WCAG documents.)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

The WCAG is separated into 3 levels of compliance, A, AA and AAA.  Each level requires a stricter set of conformance guidelines, such as different versions of <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 (Transitional vs Strict) and other techniques that need to be incorporated into your code before accomplishing validation.  Online tools such as the <link>
Watchfire WebXACT</link> engine or the  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imergo.com/">
imergo Web Compliance Manager</weblink>  will allow users to submit their website and automatically run it through the WCAG guidelines and produce a report, stating whether or not they conform to each level of compliance. <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/318918.xml">
Adobe Dreamweaver</link></software>
 also offers plugins which allow web developers to test these guidelines on their work from within the program.</p>
<p>

Another source of web accessibility guidance comes from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/195149.xml">
US government</link>. Section 508 of the <link>
US Rehabilitation Act</link> is a comprehensive set of rules designed to help web designers make their sites accessible. They have also developed a website where you can take online training course for free to learn about these rules.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.section508.gov/index.cfm?FuseAction=Content&amp;ID=5">
508 Universe</weblink></p>
<p>

In general, for a website to comply with accessibility standards, they should at least have the following:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (X)HTML Validation from the W3C for the pages content</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CSS Validation from the W3C for the pages layout</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 At least WAI-AA (preferably AAA) compliance with the WAI's WCAG</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Compliance with all guidelines from Section 508 of the US Rehabilitation Act</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/2365845.xml">
Access keys</link> built into the HTML</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
Semantic</link> Web Markup</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A high contrast version of the site for individuals with low vision</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Alternative media for any multimedia used on the site (video, flash, audio, etc)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Another good idea is for websites to include a web accessibility statement on the site.  This page details the accessible status of the page, lists access keys and can display which validations have been achieved for the site as well as include their pledge for accessibility. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bostonretinalimplant.org/accessibility.php">
Example of a accessibility statement</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Meeting and Conference Access</st>
<p>

Meetings and conferences should consider the needs of all of their participants.  Checklists such as this may make it easier to identify specific needs:</p>
<p>

Mobility access:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wheelchair accessible transportation </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Reserved parking </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Barrier-free meeting rooms / restrooms / podium/speaker's platform </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Handicap accessible lodging </entry>
</list>

Hearing access: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Advance copies of papers </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

An assistive listening system </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sign language interpreters </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A quiet place to gather for social conversation (a quieter space that is still visible to others should be reserved at social events or dinners so that people who are hard of hearing may go there to talk with their colleagues.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 TTY access or Internet-based TRS </entry>
</list>

Sight access: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Large print/braille copies of the program and papers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A student volunteer to guide and describe the artwork, computer work, etc. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A tech to help with assistive devices and screen readers (e.g., JAWS reader) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gloves to touch three dimensional work (where permissible) </entry>
</list>

Other issues: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Notification if social events include flashing lights and noises (these can cause seizures, so either avoid them or announce them ahead of time).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Notices asking participants to refrain from allergy-producing problems (e.g., perfumes) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Inform food providers of food allergies (e.g., peanuts, shellfish, etc.) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Referral information for local personal care attendant agencies </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Referral information for veterinarian care for service animals </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Access to a place to rest during the day (if the conference venue is far from the lodgings)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Test accessibility</st>
<p>

With the passage of the No Child Left Behind Act of 2001, student accountability in essential content areas such as reading, mathematics, and science has become a major area of focus in educational reform. As a result, test developers have needed to create tests to ensure all students, including those with special needs (e.g., students identified with disabilities), are given the opportunity to demonstrate proficiency on state assessments. Currently, states are permitted to develop two different types of tests in addition to the standard grade-level assessments to target students with special needs. First, the alternate assessment may be used to report proficiency for up to 1% of students in a state. Second, new regulations permit the use of alternate assessments based on modified academic achievement standards to report proficiency for up to 2% of students in a state.</p>
<p>

To ensure these new tests generate results that permit valid inferences about student performance, they must be accessible to as many individuals as possible. The Test Accessibility and Modification Inventory (TAMI) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://peabody.vanderbilt.edu/tami.xml">
http://peabody.vanderbilt.edu/tami.xml</weblink> was developed for this purpose. Integrating principles of universal design, assessment accessibility, cognitive load theory, and research on item-writing and test development, the TAMI is a decision-making tool designed to facilitate a comprehensive analysis of tests and test items to enhance their accessibility for all students. The TAMI is a non-commercial instrument that has been made available to all state assessment directors and testing companies. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/653.xml">
Assistive technology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/10411026.xml">
Accessible toilets</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/11683576.xml">
Accessible tourism</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/411964.xml">
Computer accessibility</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/9606.xml">
Ergonomics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/5446467.xml">
Game accessibility</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/1994381.xml">
Music cognition</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/1994381.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Accessibility%22])">
Accessibility</link> section.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/2891308.xml">
Public Transport Accessibility Level</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/7548962.xml">
Principles of Intelligent Urbanism</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/1228878.xml">
Prevention</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/27481.xml">
Section 508 Amendment to the Rehabilitation Act of 1973</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/1158081.xml">
Universal design</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/6357548.xml">
Visitability</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/1192305.xml">
Web accessibility</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/gettingstarted/Overview.html">
WAI Resources on Introducing Web Accessibility</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 [http://www.disabledgo.info - Access guides to over 70000 venues across the UK, designed by disabled people, for disabled people</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nrac.org.uk">
National Register of Access Consultants (NRAC)</weblink> - a national register persons in the United Kingdom capable of auditing premises or designing modifications to them to raise their accessibility</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sath.org/">
Society for Accessible Travel &amp; Hospitality</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fairhousingfirst.org">
Fair Housing First</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.digitalthreads.com/rada/">
Road Access for Disabled</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marschen.se">
March for Accessibility</weblink> - Organization fighting for a Swedish equivalent to the US, UK etc. accessibility laws.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cehd.umn.edu/NCEO/OnlinePubs/Policy14.htm">
Assessment Accessibility</weblink> - National Center on Educational Outcomes</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://peabody.vanderbilt.edu/tami.xml">
Test Accessibility and Modification Inventory (TAMI)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Technology accessibility</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.afb.org/accessibility.asp">
Accessibility - American Foundation for the Blind</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eiao.net/">
EIAO - European Internet Accessibility Observatory</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.accessibility.nl/?languageId=2">
Accessibility</weblink> from the Bartiméus Accessibility Foundation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nfb.org/nfb/Technology_Center.asp?SnID=1830431469">
Technology Center</weblink> - National Federation of the Blind (U.S.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/enable/research/default.aspx">
Research Studies about Accessible Technology</weblink> - Microsoft Corporation &amp; Forrester Research, Inc.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rerc-ami.org/">
Rehab Engineering Research Center on Accessible Medical Instrumentation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/">
The Web Accessibility Initiative of the World Wide Web Consortium</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.section508.gov/index.cfm?FuseAction=Content&amp;ID=5">
Section 508 Training Online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eu4all-project.eu">
EU4ALL</weblink> - European Unified Approach for Accessible Lifelong Learning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bentoweb.info">
BenToWeb - Benchmarking Tools and Methods for the Web</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imergo.com">
 imergo Web Compliance Manager</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</survey>
</article>
