<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:44:49[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104377057">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<header>
<title>Macsyma</title>
<id>303734</id>
<revision>
<id>244255237</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T23:52:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ronz</username>
<id>7862</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Common Lisp software</category>
<category>Computer algebra systems</category>
<category>Lisp software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<b>Macsyma</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/54427.xml">
computer algebra system</link> that was originally developed from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/34655.xml">
1968</link> to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/34756.xml">
1982</link> at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/19061.xml">
MIT</link> as part of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/254147.xml">
Project MAC</link> and later marketed commercially. It was the first comprehensive symbolic mathematics system and one of the earliest <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/10136.xml">
knowledge based system</link>s; many of its ideas were later adopted by <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/49024.xml">
Mathematica</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/79099.xml">
Maple</link></software>
, and other systems.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Development</st>
<p>

The project was initiated in July, 1968 by
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://acl.ldc.upenn.edu/J/J83/J83-3008.pdf">
Carl Engelman</weblink>,
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/3974206.xml">
William A. Martin</link></person>
 (front end, expression display, polynomial arithmetic)
and
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/1929039.xml">
Joel Moses</link></associate>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 (simplifier, indefinite integration: heuristic/Risch). Bill Martin was in charge of the project until 1971, and Moses ran it for the next decade. Engelman and his staff left in 1969 to return to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/458752.xml">
The MITRE Corporation</link>.
Later major contributors to the core mathematics engine were:</p>
<p>

Yannis Avgoustis (special functions),
David Barton (algsys),
Richard Bogen (special functions),
Bill Dubuque (limits, Grobner, TriangSys, indefinite integration: Bronstein, power series, number theory, special functions, functional equations, pattern matching, sign queries),
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../484/2142484.xml">
Richard Fateman</link></associate>
</research_worker>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 (rational functions, pattern matching, arbitrary precision floating-point),
Michael Genesereth (comparison, knowledge database),
Jeff Golden (simplifier, language, system),
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/505528.xml">
R. W. Gosper</link></programmer>
</person>
 (definite summation, special functions),
Charles Karney (plotting),
John Kulp,
Ed Lafferty (ODE solution, special functions),
Stavros Macrakis (real/imaginary parts, system),
Barry Trager (algebraic integration, factoring, Grobner),
<link>
Paul Wang</link> (polynomial factorization, limits, definite integration),
David Y. Y. Yun,
Gail Zacharias (Grobner),
and
Rich Zippel (power series, polynomial factorization, number theory, combinatorics).</p>


<p>

Macsyma was written in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/47774.xml">
Maclisp</link>, and was, in some cases, a key motivator for improving that dialect of <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/18016.xml">
Lisp</link></programming_language>
 in the areas of numerical computing, efficient compilation and language design. Maclisp itself ran primarily on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/23628.xml">
PDP-6 and PDP-10</link> computers, but also on the <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/18847.xml">
Multics</link></O>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
OS</link> and on the <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<digital_computer wordnetid="103196324" confidence="0.8">
<workstation wordnetid="104603399" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/18123.xml">
Lisp Machine</link></workstation>
</digital_computer>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 architectures. Macsyma was one of the largest, if not the largest, Lisp programs of the time.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Commercialization</st>
<p>

In 1979, in response to a request from Richard Fateman, then a professor at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/31922.xml">
UC Berkeley</link></ranking>
</university>
, MIT provided a temporary license for Macsyma code. This was almost immediately brought up on the new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/32517.xml">
VAX-11/780</link> computer using a dialect of Maclisp, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/2188401.xml">
Franz Lisp</link>, written by Fateman's group. MIT reluctantly licensed versions of VAX Macsyma from Berkeley to about 50 universities, starting with Caltech, under condition that the licenses would be revoked when negotiations for a proper license were complete. Indeed this happened when the negotiation with Symbolics (see below) was complete. Symbolics was reluctant to license the VAX product, since VAX constituted competitive hardware to their own Lisp Machines and therefore suppressed the VAX software for five years. UC Berkeley also brought up copies of Macsyma on <chip wordnetid="103020034" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<microprocessor wordnetid="103760310" confidence="0.8">
<conductor wordnetid="103088707" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<semiconductor_device wordnetid="104171831" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/20270.xml">
Motorola 68000</link></semiconductor_device>
</device>
</conductor>
</microprocessor>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</chip>
-based systems, most notably <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/26980.xml">
Sun</link></institution>
</company>
 workstations. Symbolics suppressed those as well. At the same time Fateman worked to change the (now revoked) temporary license for Macsyma into something more permanent.</p>
<p>

Ultimately, the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/62866.xml">
United States Department of Energy</link></agency>
 imposed on MIT the requirement that they release a copy into the <link>
National Energy Software Center</link> (NESC) library in 1982, while allowing MIT to assert restrictions in terms of high price and no redistribution. This was intended to protect the technology transfer to Symbolics. (Such restrictions have been since lifted, 2002 or so.) This so-called DOE Macsyma had been rewritten at MIT in a pre-<programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/6068.xml">
Common Lisp</link></programming_language>
 dialect called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/7415350.xml">
NIL lisp</link>, incompletely implemented on <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/32736.xml">
VAX/VMS</link></O>
, an unpopular system in academia, where <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/18932622.xml">
Berkeley VAX Unix</link></O>
 was common. DOE Macsyma formed the basis for the much-later open source Maxima system.</p>
<p>

In 1981, Moses and Richard Pavelle, an MIT staffer and proponent of applying Macsyma to engineering and science, proposed to form a company to commercialize Macsyma. However, MIT policy prevented MIT personnel from profiting directly from MIT developments. In early 1982, Macsyma was licensed by MIT to <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/1085251.xml">
Arthur D. Little</link></company>
, Inc., which became the broker for Macsyma and soon licensed Macsyma to <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<digital_computer wordnetid="103196324" confidence="0.8">
<workstation wordnetid="104603399" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/28195.xml">
Symbolics</link></institution>
</workstation>
</digital_computer>
</machine>
</device>
</company>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 in late 1982. It appears that Symbolics was not so much interested in the code as in keeping Macsyma out of the software catalog of its competitor in the Lisp Machine business, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/1084355.xml">
LMI</link></institution>
</company>
. The business arrangement between Symbolics and Arthur D. Little required a royalty payment to ADL of 15% of Macsyma gross sales. This led to speculation on the desire of MIT and ADL to see MACSYMA prosper. The development of Macsyma continued at Symbolics despite the fact that it was seen as a diversion from the sales of <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<digital_computer wordnetid="103196324" confidence="0.8">
<workstation wordnetid="104603399" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/18123.xml">
Lisp machine</link></workstation>
</digital_computer>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
s, which Symbolics considered to be their main business. Macsyma sales and the leveraged sales of Lisp Machines reached 10% of overall sales at Symbolics within two years. Despite resistance from many in Symbolics, Macsyma was released for <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/7952.xml">
DEC</link></company>
 VAX computers and Sun workstations using Berkeley's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/2188401.xml">
Franz Lisp</link> in 1986 and 1987.</p>
<p>

However, problems in Symbolics and within the Macsyma group led to the decline of Macsyma. In the first half of 1986, Macsyma revenues were lower than in the first half of 1985, in a growing industry. Wolfram's SMP program and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/79099.xml">
Waterloo Maple</link></software>
 were growing at this time, although MACSYMA was easily superior to these other packages in symbolic math.</p>
<p>

Pavelle ran the Macsyma division at Symbolics until early 1986. In the second half of 1986 Richard Petti became the manager of the Macsyma business. Macsyma cut headcount but expanded its sales force and marketing, and focused its developers more on features that customers asked for. (For example, the Grobner algorithm developed in the 1970s at MIT was not installed in a shipping Macsyma until 1987.) In 1987, Macsyma annual revenues roughly doubled. MACSYMA became more user friendly: documentation and on-line help were reorganized and expanded; some command names were changed to be more mnemonic. Petti argued to Symbolics management that Macsyma was a 'strategic business unit' that should be funded based on its performance and potential, not based on the prospects of the main workstation business. However, Symbolics cut the Macsyma headcount after this period of sharp growth; Symbolics tried to use Macsyma as a tiny cash cow to fund the losses of the workstation business that was 30 times its size.</p>
<p>

The greatest product weakness of Macsyma was its numerical analysis. Mastering symbolic math was a herculean task; but numerical capabilities were critical to get a piece of the much larger engineering and lower-end scientific markets. At MIT Macsyma had a link to the IMSL (now <link>
Visual Numerics</link>) numerical libraries, but this link was severed when Macsyma moved to Symbolics. Lisp developers at Symbolics generally believed that numerical analysis was an old technology that was not important for Lisp applications, so they declined to invest in it. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/53734.xml">
Double precision</link> arithmetic in Macsyma (on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/49803.xml">
PC</link> version) was about six times slower than Fortran. Also Macsyma's matrices were implemented as lists of lists, which cost another factor of perhaps 5-10 in speed for key algorithms. Macsyma did not have many of the basic algorithms of numerical linear algebra, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/6243993.xml">
LU decomposition</link>.</p>
<p>

In 1987-88, the Macsyma group tried to build a PC Macsyma with <link>
Gold Hill Lisp</link>. (Earlier, Symbolics had killed its own project to build a Lisp compiler for standard computers to avoid competing with Lisp machine sales. This was a controversial move that, by some accounts, was undertaken without approval of senior management. Symbolics also declined to cooperate with Sun to make Lisp available on Sun workstations for the same reason.) Gold Hill Lisp was too unstable, and its weak architecture made it impossible for Gold Hill to eliminate the bugs. This was a crucial failure for Macsyma. It meant that Macsyma could not respond on PCs when Mathematica appeared on Apple computers in mid-1988. Macsyma appeared on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link> PCs in August 1989 using the CLOE Lisp from Symbolics. However, the Macsyma staff was too small and lacked the mix of skills needed to add the kind of graphics, notebook interface and better numerics that Mathematica had.</p>
<p>

By 1989, it was clear to Petti that Symbolics would implode due to poor product strategy, and that it would take Macsyma with it. (Some product issues: (1) Symbolics' software was designed for MIT-class software developers without enough concessions to others. (2) Symbolics' world-class software was losing share in the market due to dependence on very high-cost hardware. (3) In moving to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/32823.xml">
VLSI</link> hardware in the mid-1980s, Symbolics converted from 36-bit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/1613344.xml">
word size</link> to a 40-bit, without justification from the market for the enormous development cost of this change.) Macsyma could not assemble a buy-out team due to lack of cooperation from MIT. After keeping reasonably quiet since 1986 about the product issues, Petti tried in late 1988 to persuade Symbolics to adopt a software-only or board-level strategy; but the fourth president in four years would hear nothing of it. In 1990 Petti left Symbolics for a start-up.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Macsyma, Inc.</st>
<p>

Macsyma, Inc., was founded in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/34669.xml">
1992</link> by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/951714.xml">
Russell Noftsker</link> (chairman, who had co-founded <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<digital_computer wordnetid="103196324" confidence="0.8">
<workstation wordnetid="104603399" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/28195.xml">
Symbolics</link></institution>
</workstation>
</digital_computer>
</machine>
</device>
</company>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
) and Richard Petti (president, who had turned around Macsyma for a time at Symbolics) by raising funds and purchasing the rights to Macsyma from the ailing Symbolics. Although the market was growing fast, Macsyma sales in 1991 and early 1992 were still falling rapidly. Macsyma's market share in symbolic math software had fallen from 70% in 1987 to 1% in 1992. By 1993, market growth had slowed and the market had standardized on Mathematica and Maple. The competitors had development staffs that were 4-8 times as large as that of Macsyma Inc. throughout the 1990s.</p>
<p>

In early 1995 the company shipped Macsyma 2.0.5, with these improvements: (1) On Wester's large test of symbolic math, Macsyma 2.0.5 scored 10% better than Maple and 15% better than Mathematica. Instead of being very slow, it was on average faster than Mathematica and almost as fast as Maple. (2) Macsyma 2.0.5 had a better notebook interface than either competitor, with formatted math display, text formatting, hypertext links, and the best scientific graphics interface in the math software industry. (3) Reviewers unanimously agreed that Macsyma had the best help system in the industry (including hypertext, demos, examples, function templates, and later Mathtips natural language query). Macsyma also had greatly improved its paper documentation. (4) Although Macsyma 2.0.5 was still very slow at numerics, it had a greatly strengthened portfolio of numerical analysis and linear algebra routines. (In 1996 Macsyma added <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/1013768.xml">
LAPACK</link> which greatly increased the speed of most numerical linear algebra.) A review in <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/1467304.xml">
PC Magazine</link></magazine>
 raved about the product, saying "Macsyma is the leader in the mathematical program marketplace."</p>
<p>

This accomplishment was possible because Macsyma Inc. had more than its share of world-class developers, including Jeff Golden (for most symbolic math), Bill Gosper (for special functions, summations and other areas), Howard Cannon (VP of development, for all software), and occasional consulting from Bill Dubuque (for integration and equation solving). Other developers made major contributions in numerical analysis, graphics, and help systems.</p>
<p>

The company could not continue indefinitely to outperform staffs 4-8 times as large and reverse the market momentum. Market share did not increase above 2%, because the competitors were entrenched in all key accounts, converting to a new product is very costly in learning time, and market growth declined. Also, starting in 1992 or 1993, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/5759836.xml">
Mathsoft</link></company>
 engaged in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/187486.xml">
Pyrrhic</link> strategy of spending $10 million on direct mail at very low prices, which won much of the remaining growth in the symbolic math market, just when Macsyma Inc. was struggling to rebuild its world-class product.</p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link>, Macsyma were acquired by <link>
Tenedos LLC</link>, a holding company that previously had purchased Symbolics. The holding company has not re-released or resold Macsyma, but Macsyma continues to be distributed by Symbolics.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Available versions</st>
<p>

There is also a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GPL</link>-licensed version, called <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/95925.xml">
Maxima</link></software>
, based on the 1982 version of the DOE Macsyma, subsequently adapted for Common Lisp and enhanced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/4178.xml">
William Schelter</link>. It is under active development, and can be compiled under several <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/6068.xml">
Common Lisp</link></programming_language>
 systems. Downloadable executables for <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link> and other systems, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
graphical user interface</link>s are available. Maxima does not include any of the numerous enhancements made to the commercial version of Macsyma between 1982-1999 (at least 50 man-years of work), but includes numerous additional features and several alternative front ends. While this has resulted in some incompatibilities between Macsyma and Maxima, programs written in Common Lisp or in the Macsyma algebraic language can often be run, with only minor changes, in either system.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.math.utexas.edu/pipermail/maxima/2003/005861.html">
Richard Petti's summary of the history of commercial Macsyma</weblink> <it>(remarks on the history of Macsyma by a cofounder of Macsyma, Inc.)''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.math.utexas.edu/pipermail/maxima/2003/005884.html">
http://www.math.utexas.edu/pipermail/maxima/2003/005884.html</weblink> more from Richard Petti.''</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</article>
