<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:03:03[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Multi-track diplomacy</title>
<id>3058193</id>
<revision>
<id>243967698</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T19:36:04Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>AndrewHowse</username>
<id>1208138</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Diplomacy by genre</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The term <b>multi-track diplomacy</b> is based on the original distinction made by <link>
Joseph Montville</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/34776.xml">
1981</link> between official, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/12229.xml">
governmental</link> actions to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/412676.xml">
resolve conflicts</link> (track one) and unofficial efforts by non-governmental <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/290809.xml">
professionals</link> to resolve conflicts within and between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/28151.xml">
states</link> (track two). Later, <link>
Louise Diamond</link> coined the phrase "multi-track <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/43259.xml">
diplomacy</link>," recognizing that to lump all track two activities under one label did not capture the complexity or breadth of unofficial diplomacy.  Ambassador <link>
John W. McDonald</link> then wrote an article expanding track two into four separate tracks: conflict resolution professionals, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
business</link>, private <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/46011.xml">
citizens</link>, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/19641.xml">
media</link>. This <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/555650.xml">
framework</link>, however, still had the four unofficial tracks operating with the exclusive purpose to affect or change the direction of track one. <p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/34703.xml">
1991</link>, Diamond and McDonald expanded the number of tracks to nine. They added four new tracks: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/25414.xml">
religion</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
activism</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/25524.xml">
research</link>, training, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/9252.xml">
education</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/220050.xml">
philanthropy</link>, or the funding community. More importantly, however, they reorganized the relationship between the various tracks. Instead of putting track one at the top of the hierarchy, with all the "unofficial" tracks poised to change the direction of track one; they redesigned the diagram and connected the tracks in a circle. No one track is more important than the other, and no one track is independent from the others. They operate together as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>. Each track has its own <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/10368228.xml">
resources</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/4095460.xml">
values</link>, and approach, but since they are all linked, they can operate more powerfully when they are coordinated. </p>
<p>

The <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/91363.xml">
Arlington County, Virginia</link></county>
-based <link>
Institute for Multi-Track Diplomacy</link> uses a multi-track approach in its work by involving as many different tracks as possible when implementing projects. This way, even when doing social <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/6241951.xml">
peacebuilding</link> work, we involve people from government, media, or other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/1201650.xml">
social institutions</link> which provide a link between the structural peacebuilding and political peacebuilding processes. Just as conflict transformation and peacebuilding are understood in terms of systems change, multi-track diplomacy takes a systems approach to understanding the nature of international peacebuilding. </p>
<p>

This <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/227985.xml">
systems approach</link>, inherent in the three concepts of conflict transformation (1), peacebuilding (2) and multi-track diplomacy (3), describes (a) what needs to change about a conflict (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/11454544.xml">
conflict transformation</link>), (b) how that change is effected (peacebuilding), and (c) the actors involved and the environment in which such change takes place (multi-track diplomacy). </p>

<sec>
<st>
Expanded history of multi-track diplomacy</st>

<p>

In 1981, Joseph Montville, then a <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/31975.xml">
U.S. State Department</link></agency>
 employee, coined the phrases Track One and Track Two diplomacy in "Foreign Policy According to Freud," which appeared in <it>Foreign Policy</it> (Montville &amp; Davidson, 1981). Track One diplomacy was what <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/43259.xml">
diplomats</link> did—formal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/22083.xml">
negotiations</link> between nations conducted by professional diplomats. Track Two diplomacy referred to conflict resolution efforts by professional non-governmental conflict resolution practitioners and theorists. "Track Two has as its object the reduction or resolution of conflict, within a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/5165.xml">
country</link> or between countries, by lowering the anger or tension or fear that exists, through improved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/5177.xml">
communication</link> and a better understanding of each other’s point of view" (McDonald &amp; Bendahmane, 1987, p. 1). </p>
<p>

The efforts of these conflict resolution professionals, generally operating through <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/46539.xml">
non-governmental organizations (NGOs)</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/19725260.xml">
universities</link>, arose from the realization by diplomats and others that formal official government-to-government interactions were not necessarily the most effective methods for securing <politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/99224.xml">
international cooperation</link></social_relation>
</politics>
 or resolving differences.</p>
<p>

Track two diplomacy is unofficial, non-structured interaction. It is always open minded, often <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/336.xml">
altruistic</link>, and . . . strategically optimistic, based on best case analysis. Its underlying assumption is that actual or potential conflict can be resolved or eased by appealing to common human capabilities to respond to good will and reasonableness. Scientific and cultural exchanges are examples of track two diplomacy. The problem most <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/19280734.xml">
political liberals</link> fail to recognize is that reasonable and altruistic interaction with foreign countries cannot be an alternative to traditional track one diplomacy, with its official posturing and its underlying threat of the use of force. Both tracks are necessary for psychological reasons and both need each other. (Montville &amp; Davidson, 1981, p. 155)</p>
<p>

Montville (Montville &amp; Davidson, 1981) maintains that there are two basic processes in track two diplomacy. The first consists of facilitated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/425443.xml">
workshops</link> that bring members of conflicting groups together to develop <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/161744.xml">
personal relationships</link>, understand the conflict from the perspective of others, and develop joint strategies for solving the conflict. The second process involves working to shift public opinion: “Here the task is a psychological one which consists of reducing the sense of victimhood of the parties and rehumanizing the image of the adversary” (McDonald &amp; Bendahmane, 1987, p. 10). </p>
<p>

Methods for conducting these activities are still evolving as is the thinking around which individuals—representing various roles and functions in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/37235.xml">
society</link> and government—should be included. Montville points out that “there is no evidence that conflict resolution workshops would work for the principal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/55959.xml">
political leaders</link> themselves—perhaps because they are too tough or even impervious to the humanizing process” (McDonald &amp; Bendahmane, 1987, p. 14). Ambassador McDonald (Sep 2003 - Aug 2004)  seconds this assumption but feels that it is merely because the leaders are stuck in rigid roles and politically have less access to fluidity than individuals further removed from the top echelon of government(McDonald, Sep 2003 - Aug 2004). </p>
<p>

In 1986 Ambassador John McDonald and Diane Bendahmane (1987) produced <it>Conflict Resolution: Track Two Diplomacy</it>, a book that compiled the thoughts of several Track One and Track Two professionals confirming the need for government to support, encourage, and work with Track Two. The Department of State refused to print the book for eighteen months because the Department has a strong defensiveness regarding its right, ability, and authority to conduct conflict resolution. The book was finally published in 1987 and states that </p>
<p>

. . . the official government apparatus for analyzing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/1946540.xml">
international security</link> issues and designing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/233404.xml">
foreign policy</link> has to equip itself to support and benefit from track two diplomacy. As part of the process, <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/639389.xml">
government analysts</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</method>
</event>
</know-how>
</occupation>
 must improve their capabilities to understand how history, society, culture, and psychology interact. (Montville &amp; Davidson, 1981, p. 156-7)</p>
<p>

At a special briefing for representatives of non-governmental organizations, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/401375.xml">
U.S. Department of State’s Deputy Director</link> for Political Affairs in the Office of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/7515928.xml">
Iraq</link></country>
 presented a plea for help from NGOs (Paul Sutphin, 2004). Acting under <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/6984.xml">
Secretary Colin Powell’s</link> initiative and authority, the State Department’s Iraqi analysts explained their frustrations in conducting dialogue, developing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/451914.xml">
grassroots</link> relationships, and rebuilding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/174521.xml">
infrastructure</link>. Far from admitting that the State Department was limited in its right, ability, and authority to conduct conflict resolution, they admitted that they couldn’t build relationships or spend money fast enough to rebuild Iraq in time to appease the Iraqis and needed help to do it. This may not be the ideal situation in terms of NGO and State Department cooperation. </p>
<p>

“Further Exploration of Track Two Diplomacy” was published in 1991 as an Occasional Paper (McDonald), and as a chapter in <it>Timing the De-Escalation of International Conflicts</it> (Kriesberg &amp; Thorson, 1991). In 1996 Dr. Louise Diamond and Ambassador McDonald published <it>Multi-Track Diplomacy: A Systems Approach to Peace</it>. Since then the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
model</link> has been more robustly developed and the original second track has been expanded into nine tracks as illustrated in the logo.</p>
<p>

The Multi-Track concept is meant to convey the idea that all sectors of society are important and need to be involved, supported, listened to, and trained in a shared language of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/170594.xml">
dialogue</link>, conflict resolution, and peacebuilding in order to prevent or end violent conflict. </p>
<p>

Ambassador McDonald and the Institute for Multi-Track Diplomacy developed the following principles of multi-track diplomacy: </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Twelve principles of multi-track diplomacy</st>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Relationship—Building strong interpersonal and intergroup relations throughout the fabric of society.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Long-term commitment—Making an ongoing commitment to people and to processes that may take years to come to fruition.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Cultural <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/26859.xml">
synergy</link>—Respecting the cultural wisdom of all the parties and welcoming the creative interaction of different cultural ways.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Partnership—Modeling collaborative process by partnering with local parties and with other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/294833.xml">
institutions</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/102512.xml">
coalitions</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Multiple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/29816.xml">
technologies</link>—Utilizing a variety of technologies, as appropriate, and creating new methods, as needed, to meet the unique needs of each situation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Facilitation—Assisting parties in taking responsibility for their own dreams and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/469691.xml">
destiny</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/167703.xml">
Empowerment</link>—Helping people become empowered <principle wordnetid="105913538" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<generalization wordnetid="105913275" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/3736752.xml">
agents</link></generalization>
</idea>
</principle>
 of change and transformation within their societies.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Action research—Learning from all that we do and sharing that learning with others.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Invitation—Entering the system where there is an invitation and an open door.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/850663.xml">
Trust</link></issue>
—Building relationships of mutual trust and caring within the system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Engagement—Acknowledging that once we enter a system we become a unique part of it -- an engaged, caring, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/161973.xml">
accountable</link> partner. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Transformation—Catalyzing changes at the deepest level of beliefs, assumptions, and values, as well as behaviors and structures. (Institute for Multi-Track Diplomacy, 2004) </entry>
</list>

Multi-Track Diplomacy is essentially a step in the same direction as the evolution of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/6515385.xml">
Deep Democracy</link>. While Multi-Track Diplomacy focuses on functional <link>
social roles</link> in each of its tracks, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/6515385.xml">
Deep Democracy</link> uses concepts and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/620667.xml">
methodologies</link> from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/909765.xml">
Process Oriented Psychology</link> to further extends the discrete tracks to a broad range of roles, psychological figures, and experiences and explores the tensions and chaos that exist between them.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citizentrack.blogspot.com/2007/01/multi-track-diplomacy-study-group.html">
Multi-Track Diplomacy Study Group Consensus: Hamas and Kadima</weblink>, (University of Maryland, January 2007)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Institute for Multi-Track Diplomacy. (2004). Principles of Multi-Track Diplomacy. Retrieved 7 Dec 2003 from www.imtd.org</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kriesberg, L., &amp; Thorson, S. J. (1991). Timing the De-Escalation of International Conflicts (1st ed.). Syracuse: Syracuse University Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 McDonald, J. W. (1991). Further Exploration of Track Two Diplomacy. In Kriesberg &amp; Thorson (Eds.), Timing the De-escalation of International Conflicts. Syracuse: Syracuse Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 McDonald, J. W. (Sep 2003 - Aug 2004). Private conversations. Arlington, VA.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 McDonald, J. W., &amp; Bendahmane, D. R. (1987). Conflict Resolution: Track Two Diplomacy. Washington, DC: US Government Printing Office.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Montville, J. V., &amp; Davidson, W. D. (1981). Foreign Policy According to Freud. Foreign Policy, Winter 1981-82, 145-157.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Stone, Diane. (2004) ‘Private Authority, Scholarly Legitimacy and Political Credibility: Think Tanks and Informal Diplomacy’, in Timothy J. Sinclair (ed.) <it>Global Governance: Critical Concepts in Political Science</it>. London and New York: Routledge.  ISBN 0415276616 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Paul Sutphin. (2004). Deputy Director for Political Affairs, Office of Iraq, Bureau of Near Eastern Affairs briefing on: The Transition of Power in Iraq. 29 Jul 2004. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of State,.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
