<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:46:28[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Structural analysis</title>
<id>306543</id>
<revision>
<id>224816046</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-10T15:24:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Structural analysis</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about structural studies in engineering.&#32;&#32;For social-science usage, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/27763.xml">
Structuralism</link>.  For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/1438600.xml">
Structure (disambiguation)</link>. 
<p>

<table style="width:150px; border-collapse:collapse;" cellpadding="2" class="infobox">
<header style="background:#ccf;">
Mechanical failure modes</header>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/815969.xml">
Buckling</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/155443.xml">
Corrosion</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/681241.xml">
Creep</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/261967.xml">
Fracture</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/2325044.xml">
Impact</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/20648.xml">
Melting</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/10404914.xml">
Mechanical overload</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/3326995.xml">
Rupture</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/1394160.xml">
Thermal shock</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/366023.xml">
Wear</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/3391336.xml">
Yielding</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="text-align:center;"></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<b>Structural analysis</b> comprises the set of physical laws and mathematics required to study and predict the behavior of structures. The subjects of structural analysis are engineering artifacts whose integrity is judged largely based upon their ability to withstand loads; they commonly include buildings, bridges, aircraft, and ships.  Structural analysis incorporates the fields of mechanics and dynamics as well as the many failure theories. From a theoretical perspective the primary goal of structural analysis is the computation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/15601377.xml">
deformation</link>s, internal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/10902.xml">
force</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/228107.xml">
stress</link>es. In practice, structural analysis can be viewed more abstractly as a method to drive the engineering design process or prove the soundness of a design without a dependence on directly testing it.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Analytical Methods</st>

<p>

To perform an accurate analysis a structural engineer must determine such information as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/3633309.xml">
structural load</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/9853903.xml">
geometry</link>, support conditions, and materials properties. The results of such an analysis typically include support reactions, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/228107.xml">
stresses</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/859275.xml">
displacements</link>. This information is then compared to criteria that indicate the conditions of failure. Advanced structural analysis may examine <link>
dynamic response</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/815969.xml">
stability</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/146103.xml">
non-linear</link> behaviour.</p>
<p>

There are three approaches to the analysis: the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/277641.xml">
mechanics of materials</link> approach (also known as strength of materials), the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/301429.xml">
elasticity theory</link> approach (which is actually a special case of the more general field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/5918.xml">
continuum mechanics</link>), and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/18233581.xml">
finite element</link> approach.  The first two make use of analytical formulations which apply mostly to simple linear elastic models, lead to closed-form solutions, and can often be solved by hand.  The finite element approach is actually a numerical method for solving differential equations generated by theories of mechanics such as elasticity theory and strength of materials.  However, the finite-element method depends heavily on the processing power of computers and is more applicable to structures of arbitrary size and complexity. </p>
<p>

Regardless of approach, the formulation is based on the same three fundamental relations: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/92290.xml">
equilibrium</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/1243855.xml">
constitutive</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/40930.xml">
compatibility</link>. The solutions are approximate when any of these relations are only approximately satisfied, or only an approximation of reality.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Limitations</st>

<p>

Each method has noteworthy limitations.  The method of mechanics of materials is limited to very simple structural elements under relatively simple loading conditions.  The structural elements and loading conditions allowed, however, are sufficient to solve many useful engineering problems.  The theory of elasticity allows the solution of structural elements of general geometry under general loading conditions, in principle.  Analytical solution, however, is limited to relatively simple cases.  The solution of elasticity problems also requires the solution of a system of partial differential equations, which is considerably more mathematically demanding than the solution of mechanics of materials problems, which require at most the solution of an ordinary differential equation.  The finite element method is perhaps the most restrictive and most useful at the same time.  This method itself relies upon other structural theories (such as the other two discussed here) for equations to solve.  It does, however, make it generally possible to solve these equations, even with highly complex geometry and loading conditions, with the restriction that there is always some numerical error.  Effective and reliable use of this method requires a solid understanding of its limitations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Strength of materials methods (classical methods)</st>
<p>

The simplest of the three methods here discussed, the mechanics of materials method is available for simple structural members subject to specific loadings such as axially loaded bars, prismatic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/630099.xml">
beams</link> in a state of pure bending, and circular shafts subject to torsion.  The solutions can under certain conditions be superimposed using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/1201321.xml">
superposition principle</link> to analyze a member undergoing combined loading. Solutions for special cases exist for common structures such as thin-walled pressure vessels.</p>
<p>

For the analysis of entire systems, this approach can be used in conjunction with statics, giving rise to the <it>method of sections</it> and <it>method of joints</it> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/397263.xml">
truss</link> analysis, <engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/899063.xml">
moment distribution</link></engineer>
 for small rigid frames, and <it>portal frame</it> and <it>cantilever method</it> for large rigid frames. Except for moment distribution, which came into use in the 1930s, these methods were developed in their current forms in the second half of the nineteenth century. They are still used for small structures and for preliminary design of large structures.</p>
<p>

The solutions are based on linear isotropic infinitesimal elasticity and Euler-Bernoulli beam theory.  In other words, they contain the assumptions (among others) that the materials in question are elastic, that stress is related linearly to strain, that the material (but not the structure) behaves identically regardless of direction of the applied load, that all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/15601377.xml">
deformation</link>s are small, and that beams are long relative to their depth.  As with any simplifying assumption in engineering, the more the model strays from reality, the less useful (and more dangerous) the result.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Elasticity methods</st>
<p>

Elasticity methods are available generally for an elastic solid of any shape.  Individual members such as beams, columns, shafts, plates and shells may be modeled. The solutions are derived from the equations of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/301429.xml">
linear elasticity</link>.  The equations of elasticity are a system of 15 partial differential equations.  Due to the nature of the mathematics involved, analytical solutions may only be produced for relatively simple geometries.  For complex geometries, a numerical solution method such as the finite element method is necessary.</p>
<p>

Many of the developments in the mechanics of materials and elasticity approaches have been expounded or initiated by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<traveler wordnetid="109629752" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<exile wordnetid="110071332" confidence="0.8">
<absentee wordnetid="109757653" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/278413.xml">
Stephen Timoshenko</link></scholar>
</absentee>
</exile>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</engineer>
</traveler>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Finite element methods</st>
<p>

Finite element method models a structure as an assembly of elements or components with various forms of connection between them. Thus, a continuous system such as a plate or shell is modeled as a discrete system with a finite number of elements interconnected at finite number of nodes. The behaviour of individual elements is characterised by the element's stiffness or flexibility relation, which altogether leads to the system's stiffness or flexibility relation. To establish the element's stiffness or flexibility relation, we can use the <it>mechanics of materials</it> approach for simple one-dimensional bar elements, and the <it>elasticity approach</it> for more complex two- and three-dimensional elements. The analytical and computational development are best effected throughout by means of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19008728.xml">
matrix algebra</link>.</p>
<p>

Early applications of matrix methods were for articulated frameworks with truss, beam and column elements; later and more advanced matrix methods, referred to as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/3587096.xml">
finite element analysis</link>," model an entire structure with one-, two-, and three-dimensional elements and can be used for articulated systems together with continuous systems such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/636219.xml">
pressure vessel</link>, plates, shells, and three-dimensional solids. Commercial computer software for structural analysis typically uses matrix finite-element analysis, which can be further classified into two main approaches: the displacement or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/2841222.xml">
stiffness method</link> and the force or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/2820493.xml">
flexibility method</link>. The stiffness method is the most popular by far thanks to its ease of implementation as well as of formulation for advanced applications. The finite-element technology is now sophisticated enough to handle just about any system as long as sufficient computing power is available.  Its applicability includes, but is not limited to, linear and non-linear analysis, solid and fluid interactions, materials that are isotropic, orthotropic, or anisotropic, and external effects that are static, dynamic, and environmental factors. This, however, does not imply that the computed solution will automatically be reliable because much depends on the model and the reliability of the data input.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Time-line</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1452-1519 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/18079.xml">
Leonardo da Vinci</link></artist>
</person>
 made many contributions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1638: <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/11945.xml">
Galileo Galilei</link></scientist>
</person>
 published the book "Two New Sciences" in which he examined the failure of simple structures.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1660: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/229553.xml">
Hooke's law</link> by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/49720.xml">
Robert Hooke</link></scientist>
</person>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1687: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/14627.xml">
Issac Newton</link> published "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/48781.xml">
Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica</link>" which contains the <text wordnetid="106387980" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/55212.xml">
Newton's laws of motion</link></concept>
</idea>
</text>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1750: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/2064935.xml">
Euler-Bernoulli beam equation</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1700-1782: <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<analyst wordnetid="109790482" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/46784.xml">
Daniel Bernoulli</link></mathematician>
</writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</analyst>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
 introduced the principle of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/1211986.xml">
virtual work</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1707-1783: <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/17902.xml">
Leonhard Euler</link></scientist>
</person>
 developed the theory of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/815969.xml">
buckling</link> of columns.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1826: <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/900573.xml">
Claude-Louis Navier</link></scientist>
</person>
 published a treatise on the elastic bahaviors of structures.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1873: <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/3289085.xml">
Carlo Alberto Castigliano</link></mathematician>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
 presented his dissertation "Intorno ai sistemi elastici", which contains his <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/3289152.xml">
theorem</link> for computing displacement as partial derivative of the strain energy. This theorem includes the method of <it>least work</it> as a special case.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1936: <engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/899063.xml">
Hardy Cross</link></engineer>
' publication of the moment distribution method which was later recognized as a form of the relaxation method applicable to the problem of flow in pipe-network.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1941: <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<traveler wordnetid="109629752" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<exile wordnetid="110071332" confidence="0.8">
<inventor wordnetid="110214637" confidence="0.8">
<absentee wordnetid="109757653" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/5806759.xml">
Alexander Hrennikoff</link></creator>
</absentee>
</inventor>
</exile>
</causal_agent>
</engineer>
</traveler>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 submitted his D.Sc thesis in <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/18879.xml">
MIT</link></university>
 on the discretization of plane elasticity problems using a lattice framework.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1942: <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/715238.xml">
R. Courant</link></scientist>
 divided a domain into finite subregions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1956: J. Turner, R. W. Clough, H. C. Martin, and L. J. Topp's paper on the "Stiffness and Deflection of Complex Structures". This paper introduces the name "finite-element method" and is widely recognized as the first comprehensive treatment of the method as it is known today.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asme.org/Communities/History/Resources/Interactive_Timeline.cfm">
ASME Eyewitness Series: Finite Element Method (FEM) - Historical Timeline</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colorado.edu/engineering/CAS/Felippa.d/FelippaHome.d/Publications.d/Report.CU-CAS-00-13.pdf">
A Historical Outline of Matrix Structural Analysis: A Play in Three Acts</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Probabilistic_Assessment_of_Structures">
Probabilistic assessment of structures using Monte Carlo simulation</weblink> by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pro-eng.com">
Jan Hlavacek</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eng.fea.ru/ANSYS_LSDYNA_AviGallery.html">
FEM Applications in Structural Analysis. AVI-gallery at CompMechLab site, St.Petersburg State Polytechnical University, Russia</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
