<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:46:00[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<know-how  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105616786">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<method  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105660268">
<header>
<title>Protein structure prediction</title>
<id>306769</id>
<revision>
<id>238227472</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-13T21:48:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>ClueBot</username>
<id>4928500</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Protein structure</category>
<category>Protein methods</category>
<category>Bioinformatics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/969126.xml">
Protein structure</link> prediction</b> is one of the most important goals pursued by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/31491.xml">
theoretical chemistry</link>.  Its aim is the prediction of the three-dimensional structure of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link>s from their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link> sequences, sometimes including additional relevant information such as the structures of related proteins.  In other words, it deals with the prediction of a protein's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
tertiary structure</link> from its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/24511.xml">
primary structure</link>. Protein structure prediction is of high importance in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medicine</link> (for example, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/579414.xml">
drug design</link>) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/4502.xml">
biotechnology</link> (for example, in the design of novel <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/9257.xml">
enzymes</link>). Every two years, the performance of current methods is assessed in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/461517.xml">
CASP</link> experiment.<p>

The practical role of protein structure prediction is now more important than ever. Massive amounts of protein sequence data are produced by modern large-scale <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
DNA</link> sequencing efforts such as the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/5219699.xml">
Human Genome Project</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
. Despite community-wide efforts in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/303101.xml">
structural genomics</link>, the output of experimentally determined protein structures &mdash; typically by time-consuming and relatively expensive <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/34151.xml">
X-ray crystallography</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/3654507.xml">
NMR spectroscopy</link> &mdash; is lagging far behind the output of protein sequences.</p>
<p>

A number of factors exist that make protein structure prediction a very difficult task. The two main problems are that the number of possible protein structures is extremely large, and that the physical basis of protein structural stability is not fully understood. As a result, any protein structure prediction method needs a way to explore the space of possible structures efficiently (a search strategy), and a way to identify the most plausible structure (an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/9649.xml">
energy</link> function). </p>
<p>

In <b>comparative structure prediction</b>, the search space is pruned by the assumption that the protein in question adopts a structure that is reasonably close to the structure of at least one known protein. In <b>de novo</b> or <b>ab initio</b> structure prediction, no such assumption is made, which results in a much harder search problem. In both cases, an energy function is needed to recognize the native structure, and to guide the search for the native structure. Unfortunately, the construction of such an energy function is to a great extent an open problem.   </p>
<p>

Direct simulation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/52085.xml">
protein folding</link> in atomic detail, via methods such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/198608.xml">
molecular dynamics</link> with a suitable energy function, is typically not tractable due to the high computational cost, despite the efforts of distributed computing projects such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/413102.xml">
Folding@home</link></software>
. Therefore, most de novo structure prediction methods rely on simplified representations of the atomic structure of proteins.</p>
<p>

The above mentioned issues apply to all proteins, including well-behaving, small, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/19583.xml">
monomeric</link> proteins. In addition, for specific proteins (such as for example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/369688.xml">
multimeric proteins</link> and disordered proteins), the following issues also arise:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Some proteins require stabilisation by additional domains or binding partners to adopt their native structure. This requirement is typically unknown in advance and difficult to handle by a prediction method.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The tertiary structure of a native protein may not be readily formed without the aid of additional agents. For example, proteins known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/167632.xml">
chaperones</link> are required for some proteins to properly fold. Other proteins cannot fold properly without modifications such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/474363.xml">
glycosylation</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A particular protein may be able to assume multiple conformations depending on its chemical environment.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The biologically active conformation may not be the most <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/29952.xml">
thermodynamically</link> favorable.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Due to the increase in computer power, and especially new algorithms, much progress is being made to overcome these problems. However, routine de novo prediction of protein structures, even for small proteins, is still not achieved.</p>

<sec>
<st>
<it>Ab initio</it> protein modelling</st>

<p>

<it>Ab initio</it>- or <it>de novo</it>- protein modelling methods seek to build three-dimensional protein models "from scratch", i.e., based on physical principles rather than (directly) on previously solved structures. There are many possible procedures that either attempt to mimic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/52085.xml">
protein folding</link> or apply some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/292222.xml">
stochastic</link> method to search possible solutions (i.e., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/563854.xml">
global optimization</link> of a suitable energy function). These procedures tend to require vast computational resources, and have thus only been carried out for tiny proteins. To predict protein structure <it>de novo</it> for larger proteins will require better algorithms and larger computational resources like those afforded by either powerful supercomputers (such as <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<mainframe wordnetid="103711711" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<digital_computer wordnetid="103196324" confidence="0.8">
<supercomputer wordnetid="104358117" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/136764.xml">
Blue Gene</link></supercomputer>
</digital_computer>
</machine>
</device>
</mainframe>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/10096050.xml">
MDGRAPE-3</link>) or distributed computing (such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/413102.xml">
Folding@home</link></software>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/1363423.xml">
Human Proteome Folding Project</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/3255539.xml">
Rosetta@Home</link>). Although these computational barriers are vast, the potential benefits of structural genomics (by predicted or experimental methods) make <it>ab initio</it> structure prediction an active research field. </p>
<p>

As an intermediate step towards predicted protein structures, <link>
contact map</link> predictions have been proposed.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Comparative protein modelling</st>

<p>

Comparative protein modelling uses previously solved structures as starting points, or templates. This is effective because it appears that although the number of actual proteins is vast, there is a limited set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
tertiary</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/443318.xml">
structural motif</link>s to which most proteins belong. It has been suggested that there are only around 2000 distinct protein folds in nature, though there are many millions of different proteins. </p>
<p>

These methods may also be split into two groups:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/7026278.xml">
Homology modelling</link></b> is based on the reasonable assumption that two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/142431.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Homology+of+sequences+in+genetics%22])">
homologous</link> proteins will share very similar structures. Because a protein's fold is more evolutionarily conserved than its amino acid sequence, a target sequence can be modeled with reasonable accuracy on a very distantly related template, provided that the relationship between target and template can be discerned through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/149289.xml">
sequence alignment</link>. It has been suggested that the primary bottleneck in comparative modelling arises from difficulties in alignment rather than from errors in structure prediction given a known-good alignment.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Unsurprisingly, homology modelling is most accurate when the target and template have similar sequences.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/3135539.xml">
<b>Protein threading</b></link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> scans the amino acid sequence of an unknown structure against a database of solved structures.  In each case, a scoring function is used to assess the compatibility of the sequence to the structure, thus yielding possible three-dimensional models. This type of method is also known as <b>3D-1D fold recognition</b> due to its compatibility analysis between three-dimensional structures and linear protein sequences. This method has also given rise to methods performing an <b>inverse folding search</b> by evaluating the compatibility of a given structure with a large database of sequences, thus predicting which sequences have the potential to produce a given fold.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Side chain geometry prediction</st>
<p>

Even structure prediction methods that are reasonably accurate for the peptide backbone often get the orientation and packing of the amino acid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/1152896.xml">
side chain</link>s wrong. Methods that specifically address the problem of predicting side chain geometry include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/5310739.xml">
dead-end elimination</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/5352435.xml">
self-consistent mean field</link> method. Both discretize the continuously varying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../046/338046.xml">
dihedral angle</link>s that determine a side chain's orientation relative to the backbone into a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/1527574.xml">
rotamer</link>s with fixed dihedral angles. The methods then attempt to identify the set of rotamers that minimize the model's overall energy. Rotamers are the side chain conformations with low energy. Such methods are most useful for analyzing the protein's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/14136.xml">
hydrophobic</link> core, where side chains are more closely packed; they have more difficulty addressing the looser constraints and higher flexibility of surface residues.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Software </st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/8011876.xml">
MODELLER</link> is a popular software tool for producing homology models using methodology derived from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/3654507.xml">
NMR spectroscopy</link> data processing. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://swissmodel.expasy.org//SWISS-MODEL.html">
SwissModel</weblink> provides an automated web server for basic homology modeling. Common software tools for protein threading are <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de/hhpred">
HHpred</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://meta.bioinfo.pl/submit_wizard.pl">
bioinfo.pl</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://robetta.bakerlab.org/">
Robetta</weblink>, and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sbg.bio.ic.ac.uk/~3dpssm/">
3D-PSSM</weblink>. The basic algorithm for threading is described in<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> and is fairly straightforward to implement. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eidogen-sertanty.com/products_tip_content.html">
TIP</weblink> is a knowledgebase of STRUCTFAST<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> models and precomputed similarity relationships between sequences, structures, and binding sites.</p>
<p>

A very recent review of currently popular software for structure prediction can be found at.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> A partial list of web servers and available tools is maintained <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ncisgi.ncifcrf.gov/~ravichas/HomMod/">
here</weblink>.</p>
<p>

Several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/8501.xml">
distributed computing</link> projects concerning protein structure prediction have also been implemented, such as the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/413102.xml">
Folding@home</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/3255539.xml">
Rosetta@home</link></software>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/1363423.xml">
Human Proteome Folding Project</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/1142304.xml">
Predictor@home</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/7663689.xml">
TANPAKU</link>.</p>
<p>

The <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/17385860.xml">
Foldit</link></software>
 program seeks to investigate the pattern-recognition and puzzle-solving abilities inherent to the human mind in order to create more successful computer protein structure prediction software.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Protein-protein complexes</st>

<p>

In the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/542598.xml">
complexes of two or more proteins</link>, where the structures of the proteins are known or can be predicted with high accuracy, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/2606518.xml">
protein-protein docking</link> methods can be used to predict the structure of the complex. Information of the effect of mutations at specific sites on the affinity of the complex helps to understand the complex structure and to guide docking methods. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/7672374.xml">
Protein structure prediction software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/4350008.xml">
Protein-protein interaction prediction</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/12207850.xml">
Molecular modeling software</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Zhang Y and Skolnick J&#32;(2005).&#32;"The protein structure prediction problem could be solved using the current PDB library". <it>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</it>&#32;<b>102</b>&#32;(4): 1029–1034. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073%2Fpnas.0407152101">
10.1073/pnas.0407152101</weblink>. PMID 15653774. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15653774">
 15653774</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Bowie JU, Luthy R, Eisenberg D&#32;(1991).&#32;"A method to identify protein sequences that fold into a known three-dimensional structure". <it>Science</it>&#32;<b>253</b>&#32;(5016): 164–170. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126%2Fscience.1853201">
10.1126/science.1853201</weblink>. PMID 1853201. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=1853201">
 1853201</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Voigt CA, Gordon DB, Mayo SL&#32;(2000).&#32;"Trading accuracy for speed: A quantitative comparison of search algorithms in protein sequence design". <it>J Mol Biol</it>&#32;<b>299</b>&#32;(3): 789–803. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006%2Fjmbi.2000.3758">
10.1006/jmbi.2000.3758</weblink>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=10835284">
 10835284</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Debe DA, Danzer JF, Goddard WA, Poleksic A&#32;(2006).&#32;"STRUCTFAST: Protein sequence remote homology detection and alignment using novel dynamic programming and profile-profile scoring". <it>Proteins</it>&#32;<b>64</b>: 960–967. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2Fprot.21049">
10.1002/prot.21049</weblink>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16786595">
 16786595</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Nayeem A, Sitkoff D, Krystek S Jr&#32;(2006).&#32;"A comparative study of available software for high-accuracy homology modeling: From sequence alignments to structural models". <it>Protein Sci</it>&#32;<b>15</b>: 808–824. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1110%2Fps.051892906">
10.1110/ps.051892906</weblink>. PMID 16600967. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16600967">
 16600967</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://predictioncenter.org/">
CASP experiments home page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://speedy.embl-heidelberg.de/gtsp/flowchart2.html">
Structure Prediction Flowchart (a clickable map)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#eee8aa;" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/969126.xml">
Protein structure determination methods</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#eee8aa;;" class="navbox-group">
High resolution</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/34151.xml">
X-ray crystallography</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 | <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/3654507.xml">
NMR</link></method>
</know-how>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/1822961.xml">
Electron crystallography</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#eee8aa;;" class="navbox-group">
Medium resolution</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/2235991.xml">
Cryo-electron microscopy</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/5177435.xml">
Fiber diffraction</link> | <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/283810.xml">
Mass spectrometry</link></database>
</wordnet>
</method>
</know-how>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</technique>
 | <link>
SAXS</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#eee8aa;;" class="navbox-group">
Spectroscopic</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/3654507.xml">
NMR</link></method>
</know-how>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/92193.xml">
Circular dichroism</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/480634.xml">
Absorbance</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/11555.xml">
Fluorescence</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/6662091.xml">
Fluorescence anisotropy</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#eee8aa;;" class="navbox-group">
Translational Diffusion</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link>
Analytical ultracentrifugation</link> | <chemical_analysis wordnetid="100646833" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/97911.xml">
Size exclusion chromatography</link></chemical_analysis>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/164483.xml">
Light scattering</link> | <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/3654507.xml">
NMR</link></method>
</know-how>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#eee8aa;;" class="navbox-group">
Rotational Diffusion</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/6662091.xml">
Fluorescence anisotropy</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/6661945.xml">
Flow birefringence</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/1913887.xml">
Dielectric relaxation</link> | <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/3654507.xml">
NMR</link></method>
</know-how>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#eee8aa;;" class="navbox-group">
Chemical</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/4952672.xml">
Hydrogen-deuterium exchange</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/564361.xml">
Site-directed mutagenesis</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/6661744.xml">
Chemical modification</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#eee8aa;;" class="navbox-group">
Thermodynamic</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/6660265.xml">
Equilibrium unfolding</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#eee8aa;;" class="navbox-group">
Computational</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/306769.xml">
Protein structure prediction</link></method>
</know-how>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/2292623.xml">
Molecular docking</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";background:#eee8aa;" class="navbox-abovebelow">
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#e7dcc3" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
Proteins</link>: key <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/2634439.xml">
methods</link>of study</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/59861.xml">
Experiment</link>al</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/542744.xml">
Protein purification</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/143533.xml">
Green fluorescent protein</link> - <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/174030.xml">
Western blot</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 - <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/507330.xml">
Protein immunostaining</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/1076110.xml">
Protein sequencing</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <chemical_analysis wordnetid="100646833" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/12582.xml">
Gel electrophoresis</link></chemical_analysis>
/<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/589968.xml">
Protein electrophoresis</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</method>
</experiment>
</know-how>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
</technique>
 - <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<assay wordnetid="105738625" confidence="0.8">
<classification wordnetid="105732756" confidence="0.8">
<basic_cognitive_process wordnetid="105701944" confidence="0.8">
<appraisal wordnetid="105733583" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/1799688.xml">
Protein immunoprecipitation</link></appraisal>
</basic_cognitive_process>
</classification>
</assay>
</process>
 - <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/1983032.xml">
Peptide mass fingerprinting</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/306769.xml">
Protein structure prediction</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/2606518.xml">
Protein-protein docking</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/474908.xml">
Protein structural alignment</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/7786535.xml">
Protein ontology</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/4350008.xml">
Protein-protein interaction prediction</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/496309.xml">
Assay</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/2634856.xml">
Enzyme assay</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/1098915.xml">
Protein assay</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</method>
</experiment>
</know-how>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/3599041.xml">
Secretion assay</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</method>
</entity>
</know-how>
</article>
