<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:46:21[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108058098">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>ETA Systems</title>
<id>308007</id>
<revision>
<id>226455632</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-18T14:50:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Glass Tomato</username>
<id>1750724</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computer companies of the United States</category>
<category>Defunct computer companies of the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>ETA Systems</b> was a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/37153.xml">
supercomputer</link> company spun-off from <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/58032.xml">
Control Data Corporation</link></institution>
</company>
 (CDC) in the early 1980s in order to regain a footing in the supercomputer business. They successfully delivered an excellent machine, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/308028.xml">
ETA-10</link>, but lost money continually while doing so. CDC management eventually gave up and folded the company.
<sec>
<st>
Historical development</st>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/29103.xml">
Seymour Cray</link></scientist>
</person>
 left CDC in the early 1970s when they refused to continue funding of his <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/921048.xml">
CDC 8600</link> project. Instead they continued with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/937447.xml">
CDC STAR-100</link> while Cray went off to build the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/37171.xml">
Cray-1</link>. Cray's machine was much faster than the STAR, and soon CDC found itself pushed out of the supercomputing market.</p>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<pioneer wordnetid="110434725" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<originator wordnetid="110383816" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/184611.xml">
William Norris</link></creator>
</originator>
</head>
</causal_agent>
</administrator>
</leader>
</pioneer>
</person>
</executive>
</physical_entity>
 was convinced the only way to regain a foothold would be to spin off a division that would be free from management prodding. In order to regain some of the small-team flexibility that seemed essential to progress in the field, ETA was created in 1983 with the mandate to build a 10G<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/82930.xml">
FLOPS</link> machine by 1986.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Products</st>
<p>

ETA had only one product, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/308028.xml">
ETA-10</link>. It was essentially a modernized version of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/826507.xml">
CDC Cyber</link>-205 computer, and deliberately kept compatiblility with it. Like the Cyber series, the ETA-10 did not use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../205/58205.xml">
vector registers</link> as in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/217315.xml">
Cray</link> machines, but instead used pipelined memory operations to a high-bandwidth <link>
main memory</link>. The basic layout was a shared-memory multiprocessor with up to 8 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/5218.xml">
CPUs</link> (and up to 16 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/2470370.xml">
I/O processor</link>s), each capable of 4 double-precision or 8 single-precision operations per clock cycle.</p>
<p>

The main reason for the ETA-10's speed was the use of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/306364.xml">
liquid nitrogen</link> cooling in some models to cool the logic components. Even though it was based on then-current <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/49420.xml">
CMOS</link> technologies, the cooling allowed the CPUs to operate on a ~7ns cycle, so a fully-loaded ETA-10 was capable of about 4.5 GFLOPS. The design goal had been 10 GFLOPS, so the design was technically a failure. Two LN2-cooled models were designated <b>ETA-10F</b> and <b>ETA-10G</b>.  Two slower, lower-cost air-cooled versions, the <b>ETA-10Q</b> and <b>ETA-10P</b> (code named "Piper") were also marketed.</p>
<p>

The planned follow-on was supposed to be designated ETA-30, as in 30 GFLOPS.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Software</st>
<p>

Software for the ETA-10 line is largely regarded as a disaster. When CDC and ETA first designed the ETA architecture, they made the conscious decision not to port the CDC VSOS operating system from the earlier CDC 205.  It was felt by both the vendor, and the existing customer base (who wrongly believed that their vendor knew best), that a new OS needed to be written to extract the best performance from the hardware.  It was all "down hill" from here.  They didn't realize the fact that typical new operating systems take 10 years for major debugging.</p>
<p>

When ETA-10s initially shipped in 1986 there was no <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> for the machines. Programs had to be loaded one at a time from an attached <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/181443.xml">
Apollo Computer</link></institution>
</company>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/68181.xml">
workstation</link>, run, and then the supercomputer rebooted to run the next program. </p>
<p>

At the time <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
 was making major inroads into the supercomputing fields, but ETA decided to write their own <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/1216649.xml">
EOS</link> operating system, which wasn't ready when the first machines were delivered. An operating system based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
UNIX</link> <link>
System V</link> became available in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/34670.xml">
1988</link>, at which point it looked like the machine might finally succeed. Many sites that had refused to pay for their machines due to the low quality of EOS found ETA's UNIX completely usable and were willing to accept delivery.</p>
<p>

It is a mistake to believe that ETA's demise was based solely on operating system choice or existence.  The <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/11168.xml">
Fortran</link></programming_language>
 compiler (ftn200) had not changed from the CDC205.  This compiler retained vendor-specific programming performance features (known as the Q8* subroutine calls) in an era when supercomputer users were realizing the necessity of source code portability between architectures.  Additionally, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/40355.xml">
compiler optimizations</link> were not keeping up with existing technology as shown by the Japanese supercomputer vendors as well as the newer minisupercomputer makers and competition at <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/217315.xml">
Cray Research</link></company>
.</p>
<p>

In general, computer hardware manufacturers prior and up to that period tended to be weak on software.  Libraries and available commercial and non-commercial (soon to be called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open-source</link>) applications help an installed base of machine.  CDC was relatively weak in this area.</p>
<p>

In April 1989 CDC decided to fold ETA back into CDC, by which point 7 liquid-cooled and 27 air-cooled machines had been sold. At this point ETA had the best <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/450670.xml">
price/performance ratio</link> of any supercomputer on the market, and its initial software problems appeared to be finally sorted out. Nevertheless, shortly thereafter CDC exited the supercomputer market entirely, giving away remaining ETA machines free to high schools through the <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/1365129.xml">
SuperQuest</link></psychological_feature>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link> competition.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Naming the Firm</st>
<p>

Neil Lincoln, chief architect, asserts that ETA is not an acronym, and otherwise means nothing, not even the well known acronym of "estimated time of arrival." In point of fact, he says that he would not have named the firm that so as to dissociate it from, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/9926.xml">
ETA</link>, the Basque separatist group, or the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/84653.xml">
Eta</link></it>, the Japanese social minority (especially as Japan was considered a market), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/421433.xml">
see ETA (disambiguation)</link>. According to one of the CPU designers at ETA, Neil told a story that his son actually came up with the name - apparently a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/198674.xml">
linotype machine</link> has characters arranged in the order of frequency used in the English language (etaoin / shrdlu / cmfwyp / vbgkqj / xz) - and the first 3 letters were used.</p>
<p>

Another theory asserts the name was chosen based on the frequency of English alphabet letters due in part to the then current popularity of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<professor wordnetid="110480730" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/8758.xml">
Douglas Hofstadter</link></writer>
</professor>
</person>
's 1980 book <link>
Gödel, Escher, Bach</link> which used ETAODIN, etc., to capitalize on popularity and current hip-ness.</p>
<p>

A third, completely plausible theory, is that ETA was a successor name to the much earlier <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/77901.xml">
Engineering Research Associates</link></institution>
</company>
 ERA: Engineering Technology Associates. Norris and others have denied this.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/529029.xml">
Thomas Jefferson High School for Science and Technology</link> won one of the donated ETA-10 supercomputers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/2595401.xml">
EOS</link> was the initial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> developed by ETA Systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
 was the later, more popular operating system</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.museumwaalsdorp.nl/computer/en/eta10p.html">
Computer history TNO location The Hague/Waalsdorp: the ETA10-P</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://yarchive.net/comp/eta_peglar.html">
The ETA Saga</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</company>
</article>
