<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:45:44[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<information  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106634376">
<format  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106636806">
<header>
<title>Exchangeable image file format</title>
<id>308774</id>
<revision>
<id>243750630</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T22:07:43Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Zundark</username>
<id>70</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Graphics file formats</category>
<category>Digital photography</category>
<category>Metadata</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about a format for storing metadata in image files.&#32;&#32;For information about filename and directory structures of digital cameras, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/2920017.xml">
Design rule for Camera File system</link>.&#32;&#32;
<image location="right" width="200px" src="Exif_print_logo.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

the Exif Print Logo
</caption>
</image>

<b>Exchangeable image file format</b> (<b>Exif</b>) is a specification for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/71925.xml">
image</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/18933600.xml">
file format</link> used by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/52797.xml">
digital camera</link>s. The specification uses the existing <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPEG</link></format>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/145478.xml">
TIFF</link> Rev. 6.0, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/142535.xml">
RIFF</link> <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/34062.xml">
WAV</link></format>
 file formats, with the addition of specific <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> tags.  It is not supported in <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/63285.xml">
JPEG 2000</link></format>
, <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/24306.xml">
PNG</link></format>
, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/12702.xml">
GIF</link>.
<sec>
<st>
 Background </st>
<p>

Exif was created by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/4362053.xml">
Japan Electronic Industries Development Association</link> (JEIDA). Version 2.1 of the specification is dated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/15806.xml">
June 12</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/34647.xml">
1998</link>, and the latest, version 2.2 dated April 2002, is also known as <it>Exif Print</it>. Though the specification is not currently maintained by any industry or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/27065.xml">
standards</link> organisation, its use by camera manufacturers is nearly universal.</p>
<p>

The metadata tags defined in the Exif standard cover a broad spectrum:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Date and time information.  Digital cameras will record the current date and time and save this in the metadata.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Camera settings.  This includes static information such as the camera model and make, and information that varies with each image such as orientation, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/47474.xml">
aperture</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/166803.xml">
shutter speed</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/82269.xml">
focal length</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/1267643.xml">
metering mode</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/168568.xml">
ISO speed</link> information.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/18935353.xml">
thumbnail</link> for previewing the picture on the camera's LCD screen, in file managers, or in photo manipulation software.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Descriptions and copyright information.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Technical </st>
<p>

The Exif tag structure is taken from that of TIFF files. On several image specific properties, there is a large overlap between the tags defined in the <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/145478.xml">
TIFF</link></format>
, Exif, <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/6390226.xml">
TIFF/EP</link></format>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/2920017.xml">
DCF</link> standards. For descriptive metadata, there is an overlap between Exif and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/17188838.xml">
IPTC Information Interchange Model</link> info, which also can be embedded in a JPEG file.</p>
<p>

When Exif is employed for <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPEG</link></format>
 files, the Exif data is stored in one of JPEG's defined utility <it>Application Segments</it>, the APP1 (segment marker 0xFFE1), which in effect holds an entire TIFF file within. When Exif is employed in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/145478.xml">
TIFF</link> files (also when used as "an embedded TIFF file" mentioned earlier), the TIFF Private Tag 0x8769 defines a sub-Image File Directory (IFD) that holds the Exif specified TIFF Tags. In addition, Exif also defines a GPS sub-IFD using the TIFF Private Tag 0x8825, obviously holding location information, and a "Interoperability IFD" specified within the Exif sub-IFD, using the Exif tag 0xA005.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Geolocation </st>
<p>

The Exif format has standard tags for location information. Currently, only very few cameras, such as the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/509334.xml">
Ricoh</link></company>
 500SE, Nikon Coolpix P6000 or some higher-end mobile phones, have a built-in GPS receiver and store the location information in the Exif header when the picture is taken. For other cameras, such as Nikon D300 or Fujifilm S5Pro, a separate GPS receiver that fits into the flash connector or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/2984782.xml">
hot shoe</link> is available. Recorded GPS data can also be added to any digital photograph on a computer, either by correlating the time stamps of the photographs with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/4105326.xml">
GPS record</link> from a hand-held GPS receiver or manually using a map or mapping software, e.g. <link>
Geoseeker</link>. Photo sharing communities like <link>
locr</link> or <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/1178458.xml">
Flickr</link></web_site>
 equally allow their users to upload geotagged pictures or to add geolocation information online. The process of adding geographic information to a photograph is known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/1436748.xml">
geocoding</link>.</p>
<p>

Apple Inc. has added geotagging capabilities to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/8841749.xml">
iPhone</link>. The second generation iPhone (known as the iPhone 3G) is equipped with a GPS receiver, and uses the receiver to geotag the Exif data in photographs taken with the device. The first generation iPhone is not equipped with GPS, and uses nearby cellular phone towers to triangulate and approximate the location at which the picture was taken, which is then added to the Exif data associated with the picture.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Program support</st>
<p>

Exif data is embedded within the image file itself.  While many recent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/1794544.xml">
image manipulation programs</link> recognize and preserve Exif data when writing to a modified image, this is not the case for most older programs. Many image gallery programs also recognise Exif data and optionally display it alongside the images.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Problems</st>
<p>

Apart from not being a maintained standard, the Exif format has a number of drawbacks, mostly relating to its use of legacy file structures.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The derivation of Exif from the <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/145478.xml">
TIFF</link></format>
 file structure using offset pointers in the files means that data can be spread anywhere within a file, which means that software is likely to corrupt any pointers or corresponding data that it doesn't decode/encode. This is the reason most image editors damage or remove the Exif metadata to some extent upon saving.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The standard defines a MakerNote tag, which allows camera manufacturers to place any custom format metadata in the file. This is used increasingly by camera manufacturers to store a myriad of camera settings not listed in the Exif standard, such as shooting modes, post-processing settings, serial number, focusing modes, etc.  As this tag format is proprietary and manufacturer-specific, it can be prohibitively difficult to retrieve this information from an image (or properly preserve it when rewriting an image).  Some manufacturers encrypt portions of the information; for example, Nikon encrypts the detailed lens data in their newer MakerNote data versions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The standard only allows <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/145478.xml">
TIFF</link></format>
 or <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPEG</link></format>
 files — there is no provision for a "raw" file type which would be a direct data dump from the sensor device. This has caused camera manufacturers to invent many proprietary, incompatible "raw" file formats.  To solve this problem, Adobe developed the <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/1022571.xml">
DNG</link></format>
 format (a TIFF-based raw file format), in hopes that manufacturers would standardize on a single, raw file format.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Exif standard specifically states that color depth is always 24 bits.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> However, many modern cameras, such as the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<camera wordnetid="102942699" confidence="0.8">
<equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.8">
<photographic_equipment wordnetid="103926148" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/427549.xml">
Nikon D70</link></photographic_equipment>
</equipment>
</camera>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 which captures 36 bits of color per pixel, can capture significantly more. Since Exif/DCF files cannot represent this color depth, many manufacturers have developed proprietary, non-compatible <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/2956858.xml">
RAW image format</link>s.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Most digital cameras can also capture video — the Exif standard has no provision for video files.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Exif is very often used in images created by scanners, however the standard makes no provisions for any scanner specific information.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Photo manipulation software sometimes fails to update the embedded thumbnail after an editing operation, possibly causing the user to inadvertently publish compromising information.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Exif metadata is restricted in size to 64 kB in <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPEG</link></format>
 images because according to the specification this information must be contained within a single <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPEG</link></format>
 APP1 segment. Although the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22FlashPix+Extensions%22])">
FlashPix extensions</link> allow information to span multiple <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPEG</link></format>
 APP2 segments, these extensions are not commonly used.  This has prompted some camera manufacturers to develop non-standard techniques for storing the large preview images used by some digital cameras for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/17932.xml">
LCD</link> review. These non-standard extensions are commonly lost if a user re-saves the image using image editor software, possibly rendering the image incompatible with the original camera that created it.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is no way to record time-zone information along with the time, thus rendering the stored time ambiguous.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is no field to record readouts of a camera's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/324949.xml">
accelerometers</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/201148.xml">
inertial navigation system</link>. Such data could help to establish the relationship between the image sensor’s XYZ coordinate system and the gravity <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/292688.xml">
vector</link> (i.e., which way is down in this image). It could also establish relative camera positions or orientations in a sequence of photos.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Competitors </st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/2310624.xml">
Extensible Metadata Platform</link> (XMP) was created by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/1955.xml">
Adobe Systems</link></company>
 as a better metadata format for photography and image processing. However, it is generally unsupported in cameras.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Viewing and editing Exif data</st>


<p>

In Windows XP and later Microsoft operating systems, a subset of the Exif information may be viewed by right clicking on an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/2679981.xml">
image file</link> and clicking properties; from the properties dialog click the Summary tab.  However, this can damage certain Exif headers if changes are applied.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  Other Windows software like <link>
Exif Harvester</link> may be more reliable.</p>
<p>

On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link> 10.4 and above, this information may be viewed in the Finder by doing Get Info on a file and expanding the More Info section.</p>
<p>

On <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
 systems using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/12362.xml">
GNOME</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/68334.xml">
desktop environment</link>, a subset of Exif data can be seen by right clicking the file in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/77360.xml">
Nautilus file manager</link> and selecting properties.  In <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/16629.xml">
KDE</link></software>
, it can be seen by right clicking, selecting "Properties" and then "Meta info".  Most Unix image viewers give the full set of Exif data.</p>
<p>

There are many software tools available which allow both viewing and editing of Exif data. The <link>
Opanda IExif Viewer</link><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opanda.com/en/iexif/">
http://www.opanda.com/en/iexif/</weblink> is a free stand-alone application, and also a plug-in for MSIE and Firefox on Windows platforms, that allows examination of detailed Exif data online by right clicking on an image.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> <link>
FxIF</link> and <link>
Exif Viewer</link> are multi-platform extensions for Firefox that display Exif data in the image properties dialog. This feature is native in the web browser, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/18996620.xml">
Opera</link></software>
 under image properties.</p>
<p>

Retrieval of detailed Exif data not usually displayed by other programs can be accomplished using <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/16688584.xml">
ExifTool</link></software>
 which runs in <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/23939.xml">
Perl</link></programming_language>
, and is available for all platforms.</p>
<p>

For AmigaOS/MorphOS 'SView5' covers a lot of the previously mentioned functionality.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Example </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Konqueror_Exif_data.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>

The following table shows Exif data for a photo made with a typical digital camera. Notice that authorship and copyright information is generally not provided in the camera's output, so it must be filled in during later stages of processing.</p>
<p>

<table style="margin:auto;" class="wikitable">
<header>
Tag</header>
<header>
Value</header>
<row>
<col>
Manufacturer</col>
<col>
CASIO</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Model</col>
<col>
QV-4000</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Orientation</col>
<col>
top - left</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Software</col>
<col>
Ver1.01</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Date and Time</col>
<col>
2003:08:11 16:45:32</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
YCbCr Positioning</col>
<col>
centered</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Compression</col>
<col>
JPEG compression</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
x-Resolution</col>
<col>
72.00</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
y-Resolution</col>
<col>
72.00</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Resolution Unit</col>
<col>
Inch</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Exposure Time</col>
<col>
1/659 sec.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
FNumber</col>
<col>
f/4.0</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
ExposureProgram</col>
<col>
Normal program</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Exif Version</col>
<col>
Exif Version 2.1</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Date and Time (original)</col>
<col>
2003:08:11 16:45:32</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Date and Time (digitized)</col>
<col>
2003:08:11 16:45:32</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
ComponentsConfiguration</col>
<col>
Y Cb Cr -</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Compressed Bits per Pixel</col>
<col>
4.01</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Exposure Bias</col>
<col>
0.0</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
MaxApertureValue</col>
<col>
2.00</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Metering Mode</col>
<col>
Pattern</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Flash</col>
<col>
Flash did not fire.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Focal Length</col>
<col>
20.1 mm</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
MakerNote</col>
<col>
432 bytes unknown data</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
FlashPixVersion</col>
<col>
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/6792750.xml">
FlashPix</link></format>
</information>
</message>
Version 1.0</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Color Space</col>
<col>
sRGB</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
PixelXDimension</col>
<col>
2240</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
PixelYDimension</col>
<col>
1680</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
File Source</col>
<col>
DSC</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
InteroperabilityIndex</col>
<col>
R98</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
InteroperabilityVersion</col>
<col>
(null)</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
FlashPix extensions</st>
<p>

The Exif specification also includes a description of FPXR (FlashPix-Ready) information which may be stored in APP2 of <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPEG</link></format>
 images using a structure similar to that of a <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/6792750.xml">
FlashPix</link></format>
</information>
</message>
 file.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  These FlashPix extensions allow meta information to be preserved when converting between FPXR JPEG images and FlashPix images.  FPXR information may be found in images from some models of digital cameras by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/57627.xml">
Kodak</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/13973.xml">
Hewlett-Packard</link>.  Below is an example of the FPXR information found in a JPEG image from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/3685711.xml">
Kodak EasyShare V570</link> digital camera:</p>
<p>

<table style="margin:auto;" class="wikitable">
<header>
Tag</header>
<header>
Value</header>
<row>
<col>
Code Page</col>
<col>
1200</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Used Extension Numbers</col>
<col>
1</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Extension Name</col>
<col>
Screen nail</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Extension Class ID</col>
<col>
10000230-6FC0-11D0-BD01-00609719A180</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Extension Persistence</col>
<col>
Invalidated By Modification</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Extension Create Date</col>
<col>
2003:03:29 17:47:50</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Extension Modify Date</col>
<col>
2003:03:29 17:47:50</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Creating Application</col>
<col>
Picoss</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Extension Description</col>
<col>
Presized image for LCD display</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Storage-Stream Pathname</col>
<col>
/.Screen Nail_bd0100609719a180</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Screen Nail</col>
<col>
(124498 bytes of data containing 640x480 JPEG preview image)</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Exif audio files</st>
<p>

The Exif specification describes the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/142535.xml">
RIFF</link></format>
</information>
</message>
 file format used for <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/34062.xml">
WAV</link></format>
 audio files, and defines a number of tags for storing meta information such as artist, copyright, creation date, and more in these files.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>  The following table gives an example of Exif information found in a WAV file written by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/4933448.xml">
Pentax Optio WP</link> digital camera:</p>
<p>

<table style="margin:auto;" class="wikitable">
<header>
Tag</header>
<header>
Value</header>
<row>
<col>
Encoding</col>
<col>
Microsoft PCM</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Num Channels</col>
<col>
1</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Sample Rate</col>
<col>
7872</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Avg Bytes Per Sec</col>
<col>
7872</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Bits Per Sample</col>
<col>
8</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Date Created</col>
<col>
2005:08:08</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Exif Version</col>
<col>
0220</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Related Image File</col>
<col>
IMGP1149.JPG</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Time Created</col>
<col>
16:23:35</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Make</col>
<col>
PENTAX Corporation</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Model</col>
<col>
PENTAX Optio WP</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
MakerNote</col>
<col>
(2064 bytes of data)</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
MakerNote data</st>
<p>

The 'MakerNote' tag contains image information normally in a proprietary binary format. Some of these manufacture specific formats have been decoded:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 OZHiker: Agfa, Canon, Casio, Epson, Fujifilm, Konica/Minolta, Kyocera/Contax, Nikon, Olympus, Panasonic, Pentax/Asahi, Ricoh, Sony <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kamisaka: Canon, Casio, FujiFilm, ISL, KDDI, Konica/Minolta, Mamiya, Nikon, Panasonic, Pentax, Ricoh, Sigma, Sony, WWL<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 X3F Info: Sigma/Foveon<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/16688584.xml">
ExifTool</link></software>
: Canon, Casio, FujiFilm, JVC/Victor, Kodak, Leaf, Konica-Minolta, Nikon, Olympus/Epson, Panasonic/Leica, Pentax/Asahi, Ricoh, Sanyo, Sigma/Foveon, Sony<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Olypedia: Olympus<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/3616597.xml">
Digital photography</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/76332.xml">
Image processing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/28733.xml">
Steganography</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/2679981.xml">
Image file formats</link></format>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/6390226.xml">
Tag Image File Format / Electronic Photography</link></format>
 (TIFF/EP)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/1436748.xml">
Geocoded photo</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/2310624.xml">
eXtensible Metadata Platform</link> (XMP)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/4207958.xml">
Point of interest</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/2920017.xml">
Design rule for Camera File system</link> (DCF)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/812532.xml">
International Press Telecommunications Council</link> (IPTC)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://owl.phy.queensu.ca/~phil/exiftool/TagNames/Nikon.html#LensData01">
Nikon Tags: Nikon LensData01 Tags</weblink>".&#32;  Phil Harvey&#32;(2008-01-25).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-28</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
(JEITA CP-3451) Section 4.4.3: Pixel Composition and Sampling</entry>
<entry id="3">
Maximillian Dornseif&#32;(2004-12-17).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blogs.23.nu/disLEXia/stories/5751">
EXIF Thumbnail in JPEG images</weblink>".&#32;  disLEXia 3000 blog.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-28</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dpreview.com/news/0112/01121402nikonxpwarnings.asp">
Nikon also warn about Windows XP</weblink>".&#32;  Digital Photography Review&#32;(2001-12-14).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-28</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nikond40blog.blogspot.com/2008/02/opanda-iexif-is-professional-exif.html">
Opanda IExif is a professional Exif viewer for your D40, D40x &amp; D60 Pictures</weblink>".&#32;  Digital Photography Review&#32;(2008-02-19).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-02</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
(JEITA CP-3451) Section 4.7.2: Interoperability Structure of APP2 in Compressed Data</entry>
<entry id="7">
(JEITA CP-3451) Section 5: Exif Audio File Specification</entry>
<entry id="8">
Evan Hunter.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ozhiker.com/electronics/pjmt/jpeg_info/makernotes.html">
EXIF Makernotes - Reference Information</weblink>".&#32;  OZHiker.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-29</link>.</entry>
<entry id="9">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://homepage3.nifty.com/kamisaka/makernote">
Exif MakerNote 解析カイセキ情報</weblink>"&#32;(in Japanese).&#32;  Kamisaka.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-29</link>.</entry>
<entry id="10">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20070805234644/http://www.x3f.info/technotes/FileDocs/MakerNoteDoc.html">
SIGMA and FOVEON EXIF MakerNote Documentation</weblink>".&#32;  x3f.info.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-26</link>.</entry>
<entry id="11">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://owl.phy.queensu.ca/~phil/exiftool/TagNames">
ExifTool Tag Names</weblink>".&#32;  Phil Harvey&#32;(2008-01-18).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-29</link>.</entry>
<entry id="12">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://olypedia.de/Olympus_Makernotes">
Olympus Makernotes</weblink>"&#32;(in German).&#32;  Olypedia.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-29</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

Technical Standardization Committee on AV &amp; IT Storage Systems and Equipment&#32;(April 2002).&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.exif.org/Exif2-2.PDF">
Exchangeable Image File Format for Digital Still Cameras (JEITA CP-3451)</weblink></it>"&#32;(.PDF). &#32;Version 2.2.&#32;Japan Electronics and Information Technology Industries Association.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-28</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Exif 2.2 Specification as <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kodak.com/global/plugins/acrobat/en/service/digCam/exifStandard2.pdf">
PDF file</weblink> or as <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.digicamsoft.com/exif22/exif22/html/exif22_1.htm">
HTML</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cipa.jp/exifprint/index_e.html">
Exif Print info on Cipa site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.awaresystems.be/imaging/tiff/tifftags/privateifd/exif.html">
Exif in the TIFF Tags Directory</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.exifremover.com/">
Exif remover online tool</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</format>
</information>
</message>
</article>
