<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:14:53[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Pharmacy informatics</title>
<id>3123084</id>
<revision>
<id>238282664</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-14T03:24:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ohconfucius</username>
<id>736651</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Health care informatics</category>
<category>Information science</category>
<category>Pharmacy</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<ss1>
<st>
 Definition of Pharmacy Informatics </st>

<p>

<b>Pharmacy informatics</b>, also referred to as <b>pharmacoinformatics</b>, is the application of computers to the storage, retrieval and analysis of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/9311172.xml">
drug</link> and prescription information.  Pharmacy informaticists work with pharmacy information management systems that help the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/192605.xml">
pharmacist</link> make excellent decisions about patient drug therapies with respect to, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/490201.xml">
medical insurance</link> records, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/1099396.xml">
drug interaction</link>s, as well as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/304263.xml">
prescription</link> and patient information.</p>
<p>

Pharmacy <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/4964625.xml">
informatics</link> is the study of interactions between people, their work processes and engineered systems within <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/261925.xml">
health care</link> with a focus on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/15687473.xml">
pharmaceutical care</link> and improved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/5780856.xml">
patient safety</link>.</p>
<p>

Pharmacy informatics can be thought of as a sub-domain of the larger professional discipline of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/351581.xml">
health informatics</link>.  Some definitions of pharmacy informatics reflect this relationship to health informatics.  For example, the Health Information Management Systems Society (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/2204377.xml">
HIMSS</link>) defines pharmacy informatics as, "the scientific field that focuses on medication-related data and knowledge within the continuum of healthcare systems - including its acquisition, storage, analysis, use and dissemination - in the delivery of optimal medication-related patient care and health outcomes"</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 History and Trends in Pharmacy Informatics </st>

<p>

The application of computerized information technology to pharmacy practice, including highly specialized software and hardware, is not new.  In fact, the term pharmacy informatics is much newer than the domain it specifies.  Pharmacists, computer scientists and other specialists brought the first generation of pharmacy-specific computer technology to retail and hospital pharmacies in the 1970s through the 1990s.  </p>
<p>

A present, major trend in pharmacy informatics is to move from pharmacy-specific systems to larger, fully-integrated information systems that include pharmacy functions as a component of larger <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/1075997.xml">
clinical information system</link>s, retail prescription management systems and drug <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/186493.xml">
supply chain</link> management systems.  Another major trend is the accelerating technology diffusion of computerized provider order entry (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/2021968.xml">
CPOE</link>) for medication orders in hospitals and electronic prescribing (e-Prescribing) of prescriptions sent via networks from physician offices to retail pharmacies.</p>
<p>

Pharmacy informatics professional activity has been growing demonstrably over the past several years.  For example, the American Society of Health-System Pharmacists (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/6111318.xml">
ASHP</link>) created a new organizational section in 2006, the Section on Pharmacy Informatics and Technology (SOPIT), that is expressly, "dedicated to improving health outcomes through the use and integration of data, information, knowledge, technology, and automation in the medication-use process."  Also, the American Medical Informatics Association (AMIA, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amia.org">
http://www.amia.org</weblink>) has created a pharmacoinformatics working group to, "promote interaction among AMIA members who are interested in the intersection of technology and medication management."</p>
<p>

As a profession, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/297350.xml">
pharmacy</link> practice encompasses many different practice venues including retail, community pharmacy, hospital pharmacy practice, long-term care, mail-order and others.  This diversity of pharmacy practices is reflected by a like diversity of stakeholder groups interested in pharmacy informatics and the automation of the drug supply chain.  One group, the American Society of Automation in Pharmacy (ASAP, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asapnet.org">
http://www.asapnet.org</weblink>) is notable for its retail-oriented mission, "to assist its members in advancing the application of computer technology in the pharmacist's role as caregiver and in the efficient operation and management of a pharmacy."</p>
<p>

In the academic sphere, as of July 1, 2007, pharmacy informatics is a required component of professional pharmacy degree programs.  The latest standards from the Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acpe-accredit.org">
http://www.acpe-accredit.org</weblink>) require colleges of pharmacy to address pharmacy informatics within their curricula.  ACPE expects Doctor of Pharmacy graduates to be familiar with informatics terminology, justifications for systemic processing of data and the consequences, both advantageous and undesirable, of using technological information and communication innovations in healthcare.</p>
<p>

Pharmacy informatics practitioners put their energies toward creating standardized, high-reliability <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/76656.xml">
workflow</link>s developed through an integral approach that aligns the physical-chemical characteristics of drug products, pharmacy staff needs and requirements, work process expectations and outputs, and available information, machine and robotics technologies.  The practice of pharmacy informatics also may involve drug information analysis, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/24042.xml">
project management</link>, customer and vendor relations, communications, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/154985.xml">
system administration</link>, technical troubleshooting, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/5311.xml">
computer programming</link>, contracting and business leadership.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
  Future of Pharmacy Informatics </st>

<p>

Pharmacy informatics will likely continue to grow in its scope and importance for some time.  When, in 1999, the Institute of Medicine (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/36889.xml">
IOM</link>) published the report <product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/10577721.xml">
To Err is Human</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
, the pharmacy community was at once <it>called out</it> for allowing unsafe medication management practices to preponderate and <it>called upon</it> to dramatically improve the safety of medication use in the United States.  The Institute for Safe Medication Practices (ISMP, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ismp.org">
http://www.ismp.org</weblink>), a leading <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/5928345.xml">
patient safety organization</link>, is well positioned to advance medication safety efforts.  ISMP continues to focus on pharmacy informatics and patient information management as key areas of both promise and concern, promise that the application of new information technologies will improve patient safety and concern that the diffusion, adoption and best-practice use of medication management technologies is happening too slowly.  Time will tell if pharmacy informatics, as an area of applied <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/149354.xml">
information science</link>s and as a sub-discipline of health informatics, will indeed positively transform medication use so that patients benefit from improved safety and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/896469.xml">
efficacy</link> with respect to the medications they require.</p>

</ss1>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/2368154.xml">
Clinical decision support system</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/1123434.xml">
Diffusion of innovations</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/3597879.xml">
Inherent safety</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<asset wordnetid="105154517" confidence="0.8">
<forte wordnetid="105159225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/1075969.xml">
Nursing informatics</link></forte>
</asset>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<treatment wordnetid="100658082" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<care wordnetid="100654885" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/5780856.xml">
Patient safety</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</care>
</event>
</treatment>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/297350.xml">
Pharmacy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/8641993.xml">
Preventable medical error</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/97517.xml">
Unintended consequences</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amia.org/mbrcenter/wg/pharmi/">
American Medical Informatics Association Pharmacoinformatics Working Group</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asapnet.org/">
American Society of Automation in Pharmacy</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ashp.org/s_ashp/cat2cn.asp?CID=3966&amp;DID=6773">
ASHP Section on Pharmacy Informatics and Technology</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.himss.org/ASP/topics_pharmacyinformatics.asp">
HIMSS Pharmacy Informatics</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.slais.ubc.ca/courses/libr500/winter2000/WWW/j_leung/">
Pharmacy Informatics Introduction</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ils.unc.edu/informatics_programs/doc/Pharmacy_2006.html">
Pharmacy Informatics Training</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ajpe.org/view.asp?art=aj7106117&amp;pdf=yes/">
Implementing Pharmacy Informatics in College Curricula:  The AACP Technology in Pharmacy Education and Learning Special Interest Group</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
