<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:10:22[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<firm  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108059870">
<enterprise  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108056231">
<business  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108061042">
<publisher  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108062623">
<header>
<title>Eastern Book Company</title>
<id>3160094</id>
<revision>
<id>228327893</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-28T05:02:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>ESkog</username>
<id>88149</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Indian law</category>
<category>Publishing companies of India</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Eastern Book Company</b>, based in <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/392095.xml">
Lucknow</link></legal_power>
, is <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
's leading publisher of law books. It was established in the 1940s by two brothers, CL Malik and PL Malik.  It remains a family run enterprise.<p>

It publishes Supreme Court Cases - a law report that has become the first choice for citation in all the Courts in India.  
Its venture in electronic publishing under the <link>
SCC Online</link> suite of products has established it as the frontrunner both in terms of the legal content provided and the technology used to present the material. </p>
<p>

EBC publishes a wide range of legal commentaries, student texts, law reports and digests, and its products include pioneering works both in the print and electronic medium. With a list of over 500 authoritative and well known titles, it is well recognised for its contribution to legal literature worldwide. Our law report Supreme Court CasesTM, started in 1969 and now running into 240 volumes, is the leading law report of India with a very wide circulation, and is cited most often before the Indian Supreme Court. Due to quality and high standards adopted and maintained in Supreme Court CasesTM, today the law report has the respect and admiration of the entire legal community, including the Honorable Judges. EBC has done pioneering work, by creating a complete index/digest of the case law of the Indian Supreme Court from its inception in 1950 till date. This has appeared in the print medium and more recently, in a revolutionary form, in the electronic medium, as SCC Online's Supreme Court Case FinderTM. This Information Database and search program is a proven source for quick retrieval of case-law precedents of the Supreme Court of India.</p>

<p>

It has now tied up with the Incorporated Council of Law Reporting for England and Wales (ICLR) to reprint the Law Reports and the Weekly Law Reports in India, Pakistan, Bangladesh, Nepal, Bhutan, Myanmar, Sri Lanka and the Maldives.</p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebc.co.in">
Company Website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scconline.com">
SCC Online</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</publisher>
</business>
</enterprise>
</firm>
</article>
