<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:47:39[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network society</title>
<id>316667</id>
<revision>
<id>243619776</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T09:51:59Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>TTZnju</username>
<id>5116837</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Society</category>
<category>Digital Revolution</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The term <b>Network Society</b> was coined by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/3569806.xml">
Jan van Dijk</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 in his Dutch book <it>De Netwerkmaatschappij</it> (1991) (<it>The Network Society</it>) (1999, 2006), and by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<sociologist wordnetid="110620758" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<anarchist wordnetid="109791816" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<radical wordnetid="110503452" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/64644.xml">
Manuel Castells</link></radical>
</writer>
</anarchist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</sociologist>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 in <it>The Network Society</it>, the first part of his trilogy <it>The Information Age</it> (1996). In 1978 James Martin used the related term 'The Wired Society' indicating a society that is connected by mass- and telecommunication networks. <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/1203090.xml">
Barry Wellman</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 and the team of Roxanne Hiltz and Murray Turoff also have done work on the concept of network society.<p>

Van Dijk defines the network society as a society in which a combination of social and media networks shapes its prime mode of organization and most important structures at all levels (individual, organizational and societal). He compares this type of society to a mass society that is shaped by groups, organizations and communities ('masses') organized in physical co-presence. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Barry Wellman and Hiltz-Turoff Explore <it>The Network Society</it> Concept</st>
<p>

Wellman has studied the network society as a sociologist at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/7955325.xml">
University of Toronto</link></university>
. His first formal work was in 1973, "The Network City" with a more comprehensive theoretical statement in 1988. Since his 1979 "The Community Question", Wellman has argued that societies at any scale are best seen as networks (and "networks of networks") rather than as bounded groups in hierarchical structures.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> More recently, Wellman has contributed to the theory of social network analysis with an emphasis on individualized networks, also known as "networked individualism".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> In his studies, Wellman focuses on three main points of the network society: community, work and organizations. He states that with recent technological advances an individual's community can be socially and spatially diversified. Organizations can also benefit from the expansion of networks in that having ties with members of different organizations can help with specific issues.</p>
<p>

In 1978, Roxanne Hiltz and Murray Turoff's <it>The Network Nation</it> explicitly built on Wellman's community analysis, taking the book's title from Craven and Wellman's "The Network City". The book argued that computer supported communication could transform society. It was remarkably prescient, as it was written well before the advent of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>. Turoff and Hiltz were the progenitors of an early computer supported communication system, called EIES.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> llll Roxanne and Murray Turoff got married in 1978.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Manuel Castells and <it>The Network Society''</it></st>
<p>

According to Castells, networks constitute the new social morphology of our societies.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  When interviewed by Harry Kreisler from the University of California Berkeley, Castells said "...the definition, if you wish, in concrete terms of a network society is a society where the key social structures and activities are organized around electronically processed information networks. So it's not just about networks or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social networks</link>, because social networks have been very old forms of social organization. It's about social networks which process and manage information and are using micro-electronic based technologies."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> The diffusion of a networking logic substantially modifies the operation and outcomes in processes of production, experience, power, and culture. For Castells, networks have become the basic units of modern society. Van Dijk does not go that far; for him these units still are individuals, groups, organizations and communities, though they may increasingly be linked by networks.</p>
<p>

The network society goes further than the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/163901.xml">
information society</link> that is often proclaimed. Castells argues that it is not purely the technology that defines modern societies, but also cultural, economical and political factors that make up the network society.  Influences such as religion, cultural upbringing, political organizations, and social status all shape the network society. Societies are shaped by these factors in many ways. These influences can either raise or hinder these societies. For van Dijk, information forms the substance of contemporary society, while networks shape the organizational forms and (infra)structures of this society. </p>
<p>

The <it>Space of Flows</it> plays a central role in Castells' vision of the network society. It is a network of communications, defined by hubs where these networks crisscross. Élites in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/5391.xml">
cities</link> are not attached to a particular locality but to the space of flows.</p>
<p>

Castells puts great importance on the networks and argues that the real power is to be found within the networks rather than confined in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/5391.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Global+cities%22])">
global cities</link>. This contrasts with other theorists who rank cities hierarchically.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Jan van Dijk and <it>The Network Society''</it></st>
<p>

Van Dijk has defined the idea "network society" as a form of society increasingly organizing its relationships in media networks gradually replacing or complementing the social networks of face-to-face communication. Personal communication is replaced by digital technology.  This means that social and media networks are shaping the prime mode of organization and most important structures of modern society.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> </p>
<p>

Van Dijk's <it>The Network Society</it> describes what the network society is and what it might be like in the future.  The first conclusion of this book is that modern society is in a process of becoming a network society.  This means that on the internet interpersonal, organizational, and mass communication come together. People become linked to one another and have access to information and communication with one another constantly. Using the internet brings the “whole world” into homes and work places.  Also, when media like the internet becomes even more advanced it will gradually appear as “normal media” in the first decade of the twentieth-first century as it becomes used by larger sections of the population and by vested interests in the economy, politics and culture. It asserts that paper means of communication will become out of date, with newspapers and letters becoming ancient forms for spreading information.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Matthew Wall Smith and Recent Contributions</st>
<p>

Scholars such as Jan van Dijk and Manuel Castells researched and studied the term "network society" in earlier years. In more recent studies, scholars such as Matthew Wall Smith have done some extensive research on the subject. In Matthew Wall Smith's studies he refers to the internet as a public infrastructure rather than a marketable asset, which is how society currently views the internet. He predicts, as many others have, that in the future all forms of communication and record will be done electronically through computers. This opens the spectrum, creating and expanding the possibility for fields such as telecommunications. This expansion will boost the telecommunications industry and develop an increase in the availability of jobs in that particular field. The needs of society are constantly changing. In a world where technology expands with each day the future will revolve around computers and what we view as advanced technology in today’s world. As society expands so will the need for communication. Face to face means of communication will be replaced by technological means. Human interaction will be replaced by digital conversations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Network Society in modern life</st>
<p>

The concepts described by Jan van Dijk, Barry Wellman, Hiltz-Turoff and Manuel Castells can be seen throughout modern technology.  Web sites such as 'Facebook' and 'MySpace' are prime examples of Network Society at work. These sites allow people all over the world to communicate through digital means without face to face contact. Other means include instant messenger servers, such as AIM and IChat, and email servers, including Hotmail, Yahoo Mail, AOL Mail, and many others.  All of these web services provide means for people to communicate without personal contact.  This demonstrates how the ideas of society changing will affect the persons we communicate over time.</p>

</ss1>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/3115342.xml">
Knowledge society</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/501281.xml">
Postindustrial society</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/2041117.xml">
Social networking service</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Craven, Paul, and Barry Wellman. 1973. "The Network City." <it>Sociological Inquiry</it> 43:57-88; Wellman, Barry. 1988. "Structural Analysis: From Method and Metaphor to Theory and Substance." Pp. 19-61 in <it>Social Structures: A Network Approach</it>, edited by Barry Wellman and S.D. Berkowitz. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; Wellman, Barry. 1979: "The Community Question: The Intimate Networks of East Yorkers." <it>American Journal of Sociology</it> 84 (March): 1201-31. </entry>
<entry id="2">
 Wellman, Barry "Physical Place and Cyber Place," <it>International Journal of Urban and Regional Research</it>, 2001.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Hiltz, S. Roxanne and Murray Turoff. 1978. The Network Nation. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley.</entry>
<entry id="4">
http://books.google.com/books?id=hngg4aFtJVcC&amp;dq=manuel+castells+network+society&amp;pg=PP1&amp;ots=N83cznWst4&amp;sig=mBhRZtRgPT4Bh9XNvM0-OsHjBwc&amp;prev=http://www.google.com/search%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3Dmanuel%2Bcastells%2Bnetwork%2Bsociety%26btnG%3DGoogle%2BSearch&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=print&amp;ct=title&amp;cad=one-book-with-thumbnail#PPA500,M1</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://globetrotter.berkeley.edu/people/Castells/castells-con4.html">
Conversation with Manuel Castells, p. 4 of 6</weblink>".&#32;  Globetrotter.berkeley.edu.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-10-06</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
ICT.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gw.utwente.nl/vandijk/research/network_society/network_society_plaatje/b_book_summary.doc/">
B. Book Summary</weblink>".&#32;  Gw.utwente.nl.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-10-06</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue7_9/wallsmith/index.html">
The Network Society</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Wikibooks</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=hngg4aFtJVcC&amp;dq=manuel+castells+network+society&amp;pg=PP1&amp;ots=N83cznWst4&amp;sig=mBhRZtRgPT4Bh9XNvM0-OsHjBwc&amp;prev=http://www.google.com/search%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3Dmanuel%2Bcastells%2Bnetwork%2Bsociety%26btnG%3DGoogle%2BSearch&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=print&amp;ct=title&amp;cad=one-book-with-thumbnail#PPA500,M1">
<it>The Network Society</it> on Googlebooks</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://globetrotter.berkeley.edu/people/Castells/castells-con4.html">
Interview with Manuel Castells</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
