<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:11:11[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<child  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="109917593">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Audrey Santo</title>
<id>3179641</id>
<revision>
<id>239470407</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-19T04:33:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>American children</category>
<category>1983 births</category>
<category>People with brain injuries</category>
<category>People from Worcester, Massachusetts</category>
<category>Stigmatics</category>
<category>American Roman Catholics</category>
<category>2007 deaths</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<b>Audrey Marie Santo</b> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/8848.xml">
December 19</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/34755.xml">
1983</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/1862.xml">
April 14</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>), often referred to as <b>Little Audrey</b> by pilgrims to her home, was a young woman from <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/99312.xml">
Worcester, Massachusetts</link></village>
, United States, through whom <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/52041.xml">
miracle</link>s were said to have happened.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
</p>
<sec>
<st>
The accident</st>
<p>
 
On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/1027.xml">
August 9</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/34760.xml">
1987</link>, at the age of 3, Audrey and her brother Stephen were playing in the driveway of her grandmother's house. She fell into the swimming pool and almost drowned. She was immediately rushed to hospital. According to Audrey's mother Linda, the presiding physician prescribed too much <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/1588678.xml">
phenobarbital</link>, causing Audrey to lapse into a coma. Three weeks later, Audrey emerged from the coma into a state called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/3972731.xml">
akinetic mutism</link>; she was only able to move her eyes and fingers; she could not speak. From the beginning, many people came to pray for Audrey - not only relatives, but family friends and even strangers. The hospital was so inundated with people that Audrey was placed in a private room in the PICU. </p>
<p>

The doctors informed her mother that Audrey would have to spend the rest of her days on life support. They recommended that Audrey be placed in an extended care facility. Insisting that her daughter was fully conscious though in a "non-moving, non-speaking state," Linda took Audrey home and prepared to care for her personally.</p>
<p>

Shortly after the accident, Linda took Audrey to <link>
Međugorje</link>, a popular pilgrimage site in the then <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/297809.xml">
Yugoslavia</link></country>
, where the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/73513.xml">
Virgin Mary</link> is said to appear to six visionaries since 1981. Audrey was present at one of the alleged apparitions; she seemed to be aware, and nodded her head as if to say 'yes'. Linda states that Audrey communicated directly with the Virgin Mary and agreed to become a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/16263446.xml">
victim soul</link>. In Catholic folk-belief, one who willingly takes on the suffering of others<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The concept of a <it>Victim Soul</it> is not one that is approved by the Church<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.  Audrey subsequently went into cardiac arrest and almost died, requiring a medical evacuation back to the United States. Rather than assuming that Audrey's health simply was not up to the strain of that much travel, her mother interpreted the child's heart failure as having to do with the fact that the apparition site was close to "the biggest <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/765.xml">
abortion</link> clinic in Yugoslavia". <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Miracles claims</st>
<p>

Since her visit to Međugorje, numerous miracles were purported to have occurred in Audrey's bedroom and within the house. Her nurses reported an overpowering scent of roses in her room. At least three of these women were not Catholics at the time, but converted after witnessing the reported miracles. </p>
<p>

It has also been claimed that Audrey sometimes bore the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/39339.xml">
stigmata</link>. The claimed miracles in Audrey's home included icons weeping blood or oil, a bleeding statue of <information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<inflammation wordnetid="114336539" confidence="0.8">
<punishment wordnetid="101160342" confidence="0.8">
<appearance wordnetid="107321772" confidence="0.8">
<belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<laminitis wordnetid="114348895" confidence="0.8">
<happening wordnetid="107283608" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="105823932" confidence="0.8">
<corporal_punishment wordnetid="101161161" confidence="0.8">
<execution wordnetid="101163779" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_control wordnetid="101123598" confidence="0.8">
<deity wordnetid="109505418" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<symptom wordnetid="114299637" confidence="0.8">
<manifestation wordnetid="107323231" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/1095706.xml">
Jesus</link></manifestation>
</symptom>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</spiritual_being>
</deity>
</social_control>
</event>
</group_action>
</execution>
</corporal_punishment>
</evidence>
</happening>
</laminitis>
</belief>
</appearance>
</punishment>
</inflammation>
</information>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/2560249.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Miracles+of+the+Bleeding+Host%22])">
consecrated hosts bleeding</link>, blood appearing spontaneously in a tabernacle, oil dripping down the walls of the garage, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/73513.xml">
Virgin Mary</link> appearing in cloud formations overhead.</p>

<p>

Many miraculous healings were attributed to Audrey as well, typical of claims made about a purported <it>victim soul</it>.  The concept of a <it>victim soul</it> is a controversial, non-canonical belief <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>. that some individuals volunteer to suffer for other's sins out of their deep love for others. Many people with various diseases or injuries claim to have been cured either by visiting Audrey's house or by intercessory prayer offered by others at Audrey's house. </p>
<p>

For example, Sheryle Parolisi of <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/116752.xml">
Methuen</link></village>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1645518.xml">
Massachusetts</link></country>
, says she prayed at Audrey's bedside for the recovery of her son Joey, who had been badly injured in a motorcycle accident. She reports that, on returning home, Joey met her at the door without the crutches or cane which he had needed to help him walk since the accident. He told her that he "just had a feeling that he could walk". Medical reports comparing Joey's condition prior to and subsequent to his alleged cure are unavailable. It is also likely that he may have experienced spontaneous remission of his symptoms.</p>
<p>

Promoters of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/28436.xml">
saint</link>hood for Audrey  have alleged that while alive, Audrey baffled medical science in the following ways :
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 As of 1999, Audrey showed no <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/902762.xml">
bedsore</link>s despite having been in bed for 12 years. Either none were reported, or the assiduous care she received at home prevented them. She was arguably receiving a great deal more personal attention than she would in a medical facility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Her mechanical respirator occasionally stopped, as did the flow in her <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/681283.xml">
feeding tube</link>. Believers stated that Audrey voluntarily controlled these devices through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/24777.xml">
telekinesis</link> because she made a deliberate decision to fast for a period of time. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 She reportedly was not able to receive any solid food but was given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/9767.xml">
Holy Communion</link> hosts daily. Historically, people given to extremes of spiritual devotion are often said to exist solely on communion hosts. According to medical studies dating back to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/32798.xml">
Victorian era</link>, when fasting was considered extremely admirable, such people are usually receiving some type of normal food. In addition, today's Communion hosts readily dissolve and are extremely easy to ingest.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

During her life, Audrey's house became a pilgrimage site. The home was remodeled for this purpose and a large window installed in Audrey's bedroom so that visitors could view her as they passed by.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controversy</st>
<p>

In 1998, <it>The Washington Post</it>  had a Pittsburgh lab test a sample of the miraculous oil which purportedly oozed from the icons in Audrey's room.  Their tests revealed that the oil consisted of 80 percent corn or soybean oil, and 20 percent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/17263709.xml">
chicken fat</link>. Another sample of the miracle oil given to <series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/422220.xml">
20/20</link></series>
's <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<journalist wordnetid="110224578" confidence="0.8">
<biographer wordnetid="109855433" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/11653485.xml">
Lynn Sherr</link></biographer>
</journalist>
</scholar>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 by Linda Santo proved to be 75 percent olive oil and the remaining 25% was unidentifiable<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>.</p>
<p>

In addition, an organization calling itself <it>Apostolate of a Silent Soul, Inc.</it> which is associated with Audrey Santo provides a "price list," and sells items such as photographs of Audrey and crucifixes which had been in Audrey's room, while also soliciting donations.  This activity led to suggestions that the Santo family is marketing Audrey's condition for personal gain. As of April 16, 2009, they are still selling items such as: magnets, T-shirts, Audrey's photo, postcards, angel pins, books and CDs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

The Audrey Santo story was also featured with disapproval in an episode of <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.8">
<disbeliever wordnetid="110015897" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<libertarian wordnetid="110257524" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<thinker wordnetid="110708292" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<skeptic wordnetid="110604634" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<advocate wordnetid="109774783" confidence="0.8">
<magician wordnetid="110280674" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<atheist wordnetid="109820044" confidence="0.8">
<nonreligious_person wordnetid="109625789" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/286917.xml">
Penn &amp; Teller</link></entertainer>
</nonreligious_person>
</atheist>
</writer>
</magician>
</advocate>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</skeptic>
</communicator>
</thinker>
</actor>
</libertarian>
</intellectual>
</person>
</disbeliever>
</comedian>
</physical_entity>
's show <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/11126578.xml">
Bullshit!</link>.  Upon receiving a price list for Audrey <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../217/466217.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Promotional+gifts%22])">
swag</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> along with an "oil soaked cotton ball" presumably from Audrey's bedroom, co-host <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/348378.xml">
Penn Jillette</link></person>
, in an uncharacteristically solemn manner, suggested reciprocating by giving Linda, Audrey's mother, a conscience, as "the one she's got is clearly not working."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Roman Catholic Church's position on Audrey's alleged miracles</st>
<p>

In 1999, the Bishop of Worcester, the Most Rev. Daniel P. Reilly,  released his preliminary findings on the case. In that report, the Bishop said that "The most striking evidence of the presence of God in the Santo home is seen in the dedication of the family to Audrey" </p>
<p>

As for the purported miracles, he said " I want to underscore that any paranormal occurrences are not miraculous in and of themselves".  </p>
<p>

He also stated in regard to the claim that Audrey is a <it>Victim Soul</it>, "We must proceed quite cautiously here, since this term is not commonly used by the Church except for Christ himself who became the victim for our sins and transgressions on the cross."  The report further states that "The term "victim soul" is not an official term in the Church. It was used in some circles in the 18th and 19th century when there was a fascination with suffering and death."</p>
<p>

And with regard to the many pilgrims who pray to Audrey, he said "praying to Audrey is not acceptable in Catholic teaching." It was further states that "One should only pray for Audrey. Our faith teaches us to pray to God and to pray for the intercession of the saints. Therefore, the distribution of a "Prayer to Audrey" should cease immediately."</p>
<p>

In the case of the purported miracle oil, his report stated: "We must be careful not to identify this oil as "holy oil," which could be used to anoint a person. The Sacrament of the Anointing of the Sick, which can only be celebrated by a priest or bishop, uses oil blessed by the bishop at the Mass of Chrism, and is given to those who are seriously ill."</p>
<p>

While the Bishop's report does not confirm any of the alleged miracles and cautions against some of the beliefs being promoted, it had nothing but praise for the care Audrey is receiving from her loving family.  The bishop lauds the "excellent care the family gives to their daughter. This has manifested itself in her physical condition, for example, she has not apparently had bedsores in the eleven years she has been confined to her bed."  He celebrates their "constant love and devotion to their daughter is a miracle in the broad sense of the word. They have always recognized the human dignity of their daughter, despite the circumstances."</p>
<p>

Above quotes taken from the Diocese Issues Interim Findings on Miraculous Claims, Statement by Most Rev. Daniel P. Reilly, Bishop of Worcester<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Death and funeral</st>
<p>

Audrey Santo died from <it>cardio-respiratory failure</it> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/1862.xml">
April 14</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link> in her home.  Family, friends, and clergy were at her side.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/1519686.xml">
vigil</link> was held <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/1974.xml">
April 17</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/184798.xml">
funeral mass</link> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/1826.xml">
April 18</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>, both at <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<church wordnetid="103028079" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<place_of_worship wordnetid="103953416" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<cathedral wordnetid="102984061" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/1811501.xml">
St. Paul's Cathedral</link></cathedral>
</geographical_area>
</place_of_worship>
</tract>
</location>
</church>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
</region>
</site>
 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/99312.xml">
Worcester, MA</link></village>
. The public was allowed to attend these two events, but the burial was private.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Tench, Megan&#32;(2007-04-19).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2007/04/19/a_tearful_farewell_to_little_audrey/">
A tearful farewell to Little Audrey</weblink>".&#32;  Boston Globe.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=mzRypTpuHZAC&amp;pg=PA208&amp;ots=8paWwYhL71&amp;dq=victim+soul+catholicism&amp;sig=NJGCG3z6zWo_qJ14sYMsQ4zfaek">
Between Heaven and Earth: The Religious Worlds People Make and the Scholars Who Study Them</weblink> by Robert A. Orsi Published 2005 Princeton University Press ISBN 0691049033 Accessed May 12, 2007</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worcesterdiocese.org/audrey.html">
Diocese Issues Interim Findings on Miraculous Claims</weblink> Statement by Most Rev. Daniel P. Reilly, Bishop of Worcester</entry>
<entry id="4">
Ellen Barry, "The Strange Case of Audrey Santo". <it>Boston Phoenix</it>, December 25, 1997 - January 1, 1998, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bostonphoenix.com/archive/features/97/12/25/AUDREY_SANTO.html">
webpage found September 21, 2007</weblink>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worcesterdiocese.org/audrey.html">
Diocese Issues Interim Findings on Miraculous Claims</weblink> Statement by Most Rev. Daniel P. Reilly, Bishop of Worcester</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csicop.org/articles/19990121-audrey-santo/">
Miracles or Deception?</weblink> by Joe Nickell from CSICOP</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.littleaudreysanto.org/Item_List.htm">
Little Audrey Santo Price List</weblink> Apostolate of a Silent Soul, Inc.</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.littleaudreysanto.org/Item_List.htm">
Little Audrey Santo Price List</weblink> Apostolate of a Silent Soul, Inc.</entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sho.com/site/ptbs/prevepisodes.do?episodeid=s3/signs">
Season 3:  Signs From Heaven</weblink> Penn &amp; Teller: Bullshit! on Showtime</entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worcesterdiocese.org/audrey.html">
Diocese Issues Interim Findings on Miraculous Claims</weblink> Statement by Most Rev. Daniel P. Reilly, Bishop of Worcester</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brittonfuneralhomes.com/sitemaker/sites/britto0/obit.cgi?user=santo">
Audrey Marie Santo</weblink> Britton Funeral Homes</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.littleaudreysanto.org/">
Audrey Santo's Official Web Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bostonphoenix.com/archive/features/97/12/25/AUDREY_SANTO.html">
The Strange Case of Audrey Santo</weblink> <it>Boston Phoenix</it> article pointing up cultural influence and controversy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csicop.org/articles/19990121-audrey-santo/">
Preliminary Findings in Audrey Santo Case</weblink> Points out that the Catholic Church itself does not necessarily believe every claimed miracle.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worcesterdiocese.org/news/communications/releases/audrey.html">
Statement by the Bishop of Worcester</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.telegram.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070415/ALERT01/70415001">
Link regarding her death</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brittonfuneralhomes.com/sitemaker/sites/britto0/obit.cgi?user=santo">
Audrey Santo Obituary</weblink> from the Britton Funeral Home</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/features/santo.htm">
Tears for Audrey</weblink> 1998 <it>Washington Post</it> article on Audrey Santo</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</child>
</article>
