<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:17:19[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>IDEF1X</title>
<id>3180013</id>
<revision>
<id>243657990</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T14:21:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mdd</username>
<id>113850</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles incorporating text from public domain works of the United States Government</category>
<category>Data modeling</category>
<category>Systems analysis</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="320px" src="B_5_1_IDEF1X_Diagram.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Example of an IDEF1X Diagram.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>IDEFIX</b> (<it>Integration Definition for Information Modeling</it>) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/759422.xml">
data modeling</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/346781.xml">
language</link> for the developing of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/19558680.xml">
semantic data model</link>s. IDEF1X is used to produce a graphical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/1800596.xml">
information model</link> which represents the structure and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantics</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/18985062.xml">
information</link> within an environment or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

Use of the IDEF1X permits the construction of semantic data models which may serve to support the management of data as a resource, the integration of information systems, and the building of computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link>s. This standard is part of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/423331.xml">
IDEF</link> family of modeling languages in the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/27010.xml">
software engineering</link>, and is build on the Information Modeling Manual IDEF1. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/759422.xml">
data modeling</link> technique is used to model <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/18985040.xml">
data</link> in a standard, consistent, predictable manner in order to manage it as a resource. It can be used in projects requiring a standard means of defining and analyzing the data resources within an organization. Such projects include the incorporation of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/759422.xml">
data modeling</link> technique into a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/620667.xml">
methodology</link>, managing data as a resource, integrating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/237495.xml">
information system</link>s, and or designing computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link>s. The primary objectives of the IDEF1X standard are to ptovide: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Means for completely understanding and analyzing an organization's data resources;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Common means of representing and communicating the complexity of data;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A technique for presenting an overall view of the data required to run an enterprise;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Means for defining an application- independent view of data which can be validated by users and transformed into a physical database design; and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A technique for deriving an integrated data definition from existing data resources.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A principal objective of IDEF1X is to support <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/14841.xml">
integration</link>. The approach to integration focuses on the capture, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/19881.xml">
management</link>, and use of a single semantic definition of the data resource referred to as a “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/58267.xml">
Conceptual schema</link>.” The “conceptual schema” provides a single integrated definition of the data within an enterprise which is unbiased toward any single application of data and is independent of how the data is physically stored or accessed. The primary objective of this conceptual schema is to provide a consistent definition of the meanings and interrelationship of data which can be used to integrate, share, and manage the integrity of data. A conceptual schema must have three important characteristics. It must be: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Consistent with the infrastructure of the business and be true across all application areas.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Extendible, such that, new data can be defined without altering previously defined data.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Transformable to both the required user views and to a variety of data storage and access structures.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

The need for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/19558680.xml">
semantic data model</link>s was first recognized by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/32090.xml">
U.S. Air Force</link> in the mid-1970s as a result of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/1673666.xml">
Integrated Computer Aided Manufacturing</link> (ICAM) Program. The objective of this program was to increase manufacturing productivity through the systematic application of computer technology. The ICAM Program identified a need for better analysis and communication techniques for people involved in improving manufacturing productivity. As a result, the ICAM Program developed a series of techniques known as the IDEF (ICAM Definition) Methods which included the following: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/2361538.xml">
IDEF0</link> used to produce a “function model” which is a structured representation of the activities or processes within the environment or system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IDEF1 used to produce an “information model” which represents the structure and semantics of information within the environment or system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IDEF2 used to produce a “dynamics model”</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The initial approach to IDEF information modeling (IDEF1) was published by the ICAM program in 1981, based on current research and industry needs. The theoretical roots for this approach stemmed from the early work of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/93548.xml">
Edgar F. Codd</link></scientist>
</person>
 on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/681605.xml">
relational theory</link> and <peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<pioneer wordnetid="110434725" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<originator wordnetid="110383816" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/1041520.xml">
Peter Chen</link></scholar>
</originator>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</alumnus>
</creator>
</associate>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</pioneer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</peer>
 on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/752991.xml">
entity-relationship model</link>. The initial IDEF1 technique was based on the work of Dr. R.R. Brown and Mr. T.L. Ramey of <manufacturer wordnetid="108060446" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/335475.xml">
Hughes Aircraft</link></institution>
</business>
</enterprise>
</company>
</manufacturer>
 and Mr. D.S. Coleman of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/5046492.xml">
D. Appleton &amp; Company</link>, with critical review and influence by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/301387.xml">
Charles Bachman</link></scientist>
</person>
, <peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<pioneer wordnetid="110434725" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<originator wordnetid="110383816" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/1041520.xml">
Peter Chen</link></scholar>
</originator>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</alumnus>
</creator>
</associate>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</pioneer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</peer>
, Dr. M.A. Melkanoff, and Dr. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/19595941.xml">
G.M. Nijssen</link>. </p>
<p>

In 1983, the U.S. Air Force initiated the Integrated Information Support System (I2S2) project under the ICAM program. The objective of this project was to provide the enabling technology to logically and physically integrate a network of heterogeneous computer hardware and software. As a result of this project, and industry experience, the need for an enhanced technique for information modeling was recognized.</p>
<p>

Application within industry had led to the development in 1982 of a Logical Database Design Technique (LDDT), based on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/26220.xml">
relational model</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/752991.xml">
entity-relationship model</link> and more generalization concepts. It provided multiple levels of models and a set of graphics for representing the conceptual view of information within an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/10336.xml">
enterprise</link>. The LDDT had a high degree of overlap with IDEF1 features, introduced enhanced semantic and graphical constructs, and addressed information modeling enhancement requirements identified under the I2S2 program. Eventually a substantial subset of LDDT was combined with the methodology of IDEF1, and published by the ICAM program in 1985. This technique was called IDEF1 Extended or, simply, IDEF1X.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 IDEF1X Building blocks </st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="1_Entity_Syntax.svg">
<caption>

Entity Syntax
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="2_Example_of_a_Domain_Hierarchy.svg">
<caption>

Domain Hierarchy
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_11_Attribute_Examples.jpg">
<caption>

Attribute example
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="3_Attribute_and_Primary_Key_Syntax.svg">
<caption>

Primary Key Syntax
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Entities : The representation of a set of real or abstract things (people, objects, places, events, ideas, combination of things, etc.) that are recognized as the same type because they share the same characteristics and can participate in the same relationships.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Domains: A named set of data values (fixed, or possibly infinite in number) all of the same data type, upon which the actual value for an attribute instance is drawn. Every attribute must be defined on exactly one underlying domain. Multiple attributes may be based on the same underlying domain.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Attributes: A property or characteristic that is common to some or all of the instances of an entity. An attribute represents the use of a domain in the context of an entity. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Keys: An attribute, or combination of attributes, of an entity whose values uniquely identify each entity instance.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Primary Keys: The candidate key selected as the unique identifier of an entity.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Foreign Keys: An attribute, or combination of attributes of a child or category entity instance whose values match those in the primary key of a related parent or generic entity instance. A foreign key results from the migration of the parent or generic entities primary key through a specific connection or categorization relationship.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="4_Relationship_Cardinality_Syntax.jpg">
<caption>

Relationship Cardinality Syntax
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="5_Identifying_Relationship_Syntax.jpg">
<caption>

Identifying Relationship Syntax
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="8_Categorization_Relationship_Syntax.svg">
<caption>

Categorization Relationship Syntax
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="9_Non-Specific_Relationship_Syntax.jpg">
<caption>

Non-Specific Relationship Syntax
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Relationships: An association between two entities or between instances of the same entity.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Connection Relationships: The number of entity instances that can be associated with each other in a relationship. See Constraint, Cardinality.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Categorization Relationships: A relationship in which instances of both entities represent the same real or abstract thing. One entity (generic entity) represents the complete set of things the other (category entity) represents a sub-type or sub-classification of those things. The category entity may have one or more characteristics, or a relationship with instances of another entity not shared by all generic entity instances. Each instance of the category entity is simultaneously an instance of the generic entity.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Non-Specific Relationships: An relationship in which an instance of either entity can be related to a number of instances of the other.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 IDEF1X Topics </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 The Three Schema Approach  </st>
<p>

<image width="280px" src="A2_3_Three_schema_approach.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/19539838.xml">
three schema approach</link> .<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>
</caption>
</image>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/19539838.xml">
three-schema approach</link> in software engineering is an approach to building information systems and systems information management, that promotes the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/58267.xml">
conceptual model</link> as the key to achieving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/4780372.xml">
data integration</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/48031.xml">
schema</link> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/18869.xml">
model</link>, usually depicted by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/598669.xml">
diagram</link> and sometimes accompanied by a language description. The three-schema approach has three types of schemas:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 External schema for user views </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/58267.xml">
Conceptual schema</link> integrates external schemata </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Internal schema that defines physical storage structures </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

At the center, the conceptual schema defines the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/22261.xml">
ontology</link> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/6978.xml">
concept</link>s as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/41841.xml">
user</link>s think of them and talk about them. The physical schema describes the internal formats of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/18985040.xml">
data</link> stored in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link>, and the external schema defines the view of the data presented to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/454746.xml">
application program</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> The framework attempted to permit multiple data models to be used for external schemata.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Modeling Guidelines </st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="A3_2_Synthesizing_an_Entity.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Synthesizing an Entity in Phase One – Entity Definition
</caption>
</image>

The modeling process can be devided into five stages of model developing.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Phase Zero - Project Initiation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

These objectives of the project initiation phase include:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Project definition — a general statement of what has to be done, why, and how it will get done.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Source material — a plan for the acquisition of source material, including indexing and filing.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Author conventions — a fundamental declaration of the conventions (optional methods) by which the author chooses to make and manage the model.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Phase One – Entity Definition</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The objective of this phase is to identify and define the entities that fall within the problem domain being modeled. The first step in this process is the identification of entities.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Phase Two – Relationship Definition</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The objective of Phase Two is to identify and define the basic relationships between entities. At this stage of modeling, some relationships may be non-specific and will require additional refinement in subsequent phases. The primary outputs from Phase Two are:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Relationship matrix</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Relationship definitions</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Entity-level diagrams</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="A3_4_Entity_Relationship_Matrix.jpg">
<caption>

Entity Relationship Matrix
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_5_Entity_Level_Diagram.jpg">
<caption>

Entity Level Diagram
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_6_Phase_Two_(Entity_Level)_Diagram_Example.jpg">
<caption>

Entity Level Diagram Example
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_7_Reference_Diagram_(FEO).jpg">
<caption>

Reference Diagram 
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Phase Three - Key Definitions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The objectives of Phase Three are to:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Refine the non-specific relationships from Phase Two.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Define key attributes for each entity.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Migrate primary keys to establish foreign keys.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Validate relationships and keys</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="A3_8_Example_Reference_Diagram.jpg">
<caption>

Example Reference Diagram
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_9_Non-Specific_Relationship_Refinement.jpg">
<caption>

Non-Specific Relationship Refinement
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_10_Scope_of_a_Function_View.jpg">
<caption>

Scope of a Function View
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_11_Attribute_Examples.jpg">
<caption>

Attribute Examples
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_16_No-Repeat_Rule_Refinement.jpg">
<caption>

No-Repeat Rule Refinement
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_17_Rule_Refinement.jpg">
<caption>

Rule Refinement.jpg
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_19_Path_Assertions.jpg">
<caption>

Path Assertions
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_21_Example_of_Phase_Three_Function_View_Diagram.jpg">
<caption>

Example of Phase Three Function View Diagram
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Phase Four - Attribute Definition</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

Phase Four is the final stage of model developing. The objectives of this plan are to:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Develop an attribute pool</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Establish attribute ownership</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Define nonkey attributes</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Validate and refine the data structure</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="A3_23_Phase_Four_-_Applying_the_No_Repeat_Rule.jpg">
<caption>

Applying the No Repeat Rule
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="A3_24_Example_of_Phase_Four_Function.jpg">
<caption>

Example of Phase Four Function
</caption>
</image>
</p>


</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 IDEF1X Meta Model </st>
<p>

<image width="280px" src="B_5_1_IDEF1X_Diagram.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Meta Model of IDEF1X.
</caption>
</image>
 
IDEF1X can be used to model IDEF1X itself. Such <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/1674626.xml">
meta model</link>s can be used for various purposes, such as repository design, tool design, or in order to specify the set of valid IDEF1X models. Depending on the purpose, somewhat different models result. There is no “one right model.” For example, a model for a tool that supports building models incrementally must allow incomplete or even inconsistent models. The meta model for formalization emphasizes alignment with the concepts of the formalization. Incomplete or inconsistent models are not provided for. There are two important limitations on meta models. First, they specify syntax, not semantics. Second, a meta model must be supplemented with constraints in natural or formal language. The formal theory of IDEF1X provides both the semantics and a means to precisely express the necessary constraints.</p>
<p>

A meta model for IDEF1X is given here. The name of the view is mm. The domain hierarchy and constraints are also given. The constraints are expressed as sentences in the formal theory of the meta model. The meta model informally defines the set of valid IDEF1X models in the usual way. The meta model also formally defines the set of valid IDEF1X models in the following way. The meta model, as an IDEF1X model, has a corresponding formal theory. The semantics of the theory are defined in the standard way. That is, an interpretaion of a theory consists of a domain of individuals and a set of assignments:
<indent level="1">

To each constant in the theory, an individual in the domain is assigned.
</indent>
:To each n-ary function symbol in the theory, an n-ary function over the domain is assigned.
<indent level="1">

To each n-ary predicate symbol in the theory, an n-ary relation over the domain is assigned.
</indent>
In the intended interpretation, the domain of individuals consists of views, such as production; entities, such as part and vendor; domains, such as qty_on_hand; connection relationships; category clusters; and so on. If every axiom in the theory is true in the interpretation, then the interpretation is called a model for the theory. Every model for the IDEF1X theory corresponding to the IDEF1X meta model and its constraints is a valid IDEF1X model.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/9502078.xml">
CA ERwin Data Modeler</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<requirement wordnetid="105892651" confidence="0.8">
<duty wordnetid="101129920" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_control wordnetid="101123598" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/7109929.xml">
Conceptual model (computer science)</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</social_control>
</event>
</duty>
</requirement>
</group_action>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/6999575.xml">
ER/Studio</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/2361538.xml">
IDEF0</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/19638350.xml">
IDEF5</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/1240376.xml">
ISO 10303</link></format>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/9485555.xml">
Logic Works</link></institution>
</company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/99342.xml">
Weak entity</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<image width="30px" src="NIST_logo.svg">
</image>
 <it>This article incorporates text from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link> publication of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/21888.xml">
National Institute of Standards and Technology</link>, a U.S. government agency.</it></p>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.itl.nist.gov/fipspubs/idef1x.doc">
FIPS Publication 184</weblink> released of IDEF1X by the Computer Systems Laboratory of the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST). 21 December 1993.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 itl.nist.gov (1993) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.itl.nist.gov/fipspubs/idef1x.doc">
<it>Integration Definition for Information Modeling (IDEFIX)''</it></weblink>. 21 Dec 1993.</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fas.org/irp/doddir/army/strap/strpsec2.htm">
STRAP SECTION 2 APPROACH</weblink>. Retrieved 30 September 2008.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Mary E.S. Loomis (1987). <it>The Database Book</it>. p. 26.</entry>
<entry id="5">
 John F. Sowa (2004). [ "The Challenge of Knowledge Soup"]. published in: <it>Research Trends in Science, Technology and Mathematics Education</it>. Edited by J. Ramadas &amp; S. Chunawala, Homi Bhabha Centre, Mumbai, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Gad Ariav &amp; James Clifford (1986). <it>New Directions for Database Systems: Revised Versions of the Papers</it>. New York University Graduate School of Business Administration. Center for Research on Information Systems, 1986.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Thomas A. Bruce (1992). <it>Designing Quality Databases With Idef1X Information Models</it>. Dorset House Publishing. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Y. Tina Lee &amp; Shigeki Umeda (2000). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mel.nist.gov/msidlibrary/doc/idefx.pdf">
"An IDEF1x Information Model for a Supply Chain Simulation"</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 U.S. Department of Interior (2005). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.doi.gov/ocio/architecture/drmsg/doi_drm_overview_5_2005.doc">
"Data Reference Model Overview"</weblink>. May 4, 2005</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.itl.nist.gov/fipspubs/idef1x.doc">
FIPS Publication 184</weblink> Announcing the IDEF1X Standard December 1993 by the Computer Systems Laboratory of the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.idef.com/idef1X.html">
Overview of IDEF1X</weblink> at www.idef.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.essentialstrategies.com/publications/modeling/idef1x.htm">
IDEF1X</weblink> Overview from Essential Strategies, Inc.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cio.gov.bc.ca/other/daf/IDEF1X_Cheat_Sheet.pdf">
IDEF1X "Cheat Sheet"</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
