<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:17:33[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Content filtering</title>
<id>3183663</id>
<revision>
<id>242010166</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T13:54:26Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>VashiDonsk</username>
<id>1252425</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Anti-spam</category>
<category>Spam filtering</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/7144.xml">
Content-control software</link></it>
</indent>
<b>Content filtering</b> is the technique whereby content is blocked or allowed based on analysis of its content, rather than its source or other criteria. It is most widely used on the internet to filter email and web access.
<sec>
<st>
 Content filtering of email </st>

<p>

Content filtering is the most commonly used group of methods to filter <practice wordnetid="100410247" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/28368.xml">
spam</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</practice>
. Content filters act either on the content, the information contained in the mail body, or on the mail headers (like "Subject:") to either classify, accept or reject a message.</p>
<p>

The most popular filter is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/3595957.xml">
Bayesian filter</link>, which is a statistical filter. </p>
<p>

Usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/268622.xml">
anti-virus</link> methods can be classified as content filters too, since they scan simplified versions of either the <link>
binary attachment</link>s of mail or the <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 contents. Content filters can also refer to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/1331235.xml">
parental controls</link> software that analyzes data and either restricts the data or changes the data as with chat filtering. Depending on where content or packets are filtered in the OSI or Internet model, content filtering will refer to technologies designed to ascertain the logic of data and that depends on the application, spam, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/18994196.xml">
viruses</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/6010.xml">
computer worm</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/39776.xml">
denial-of-service attack</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/30056.xml">
trojans</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/28951.xml">
spyware</link>, human understandable subject of data and much more because to an extent it depends on the application or user requirements, hate websites, swear words, chat application subject matter. </p>
<p>

It is important to note that the Internet does not have a clear security model standard designed to limit the extent of security incidents such as worms which could potentially overload the Internet causing a global denial of service. Developing intelligent and sophisticated content filtering technology with standards and cooperation among ISPs may be the solution.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Content filtering of web content </st>

<p>

Content filtering is commonly used by organisations such as offices and schools to prevent computer users from viewing inappropriate web sites or content. Filtering rules are typically set by a central IT department and may be implemented via software on individual computers or at a central point on the network such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/78768.xml">
proxy server</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/25748.xml">
internet router</link>. Depending on the sophistication of the system used, it may be possible for different computer users to have different levels of internet access.</p>
<p>

Content filtering software is sometimes also used on home computers in order to restrict access to inappropriate websites for children using the computer. Such software is typically described as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/1331235.xml">
parental control</link> software.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Filtering methods </st>

<p>

Common content filtering methods include: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/3595957.xml">
Bayesian</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Attachment - The blocking of certain types of file (e.g. executable programs)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mail header - Filtering based solely on the analysis of e-mail headers. Made less effective by the ease of message header forgery.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mailing List - Used to detect mailing list messages and file them in appropriate folders.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HTML anomalies </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Language </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Heuristic - Filtering based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link> scoring of the content based on multiple criteria.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Regular Expression - Filtering based on rules written as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/25717.xml">
regular expressions</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Phrases - Filtering based on detecting phrases in the content text.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Proximity - Filtering based on detecting words or phrases when used in proximity.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 URL - Filtering based on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link>. Suitable for blocking websites or sections of websites.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Content-encoding</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Char-set</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Most content filtering systems use a combination of techniques.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ecommsec.com/?action=fullnews&amp;id=7">
Setting Up ISP Grade Content Filtering</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://filteringfacts.org/">
Filtering Facts</weblink>.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
