<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:18:26[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<social_group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107950920">
<market  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101097292">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<gathering  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107975026">
<community  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108223802">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<web_site  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="106359193">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Experts-Exchange</title>
<id>3201061</id>
<revision>
<id>244481548</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T00:41:02Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Knowledge markets</category>
<category>Software developer communities</category>
<category>Community websites</category>
<category>Online social networking</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Experts_Exchange_logo.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Experts-Exchange logo
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Experts-Exchange (EE)</b>, founded in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/34636.xml">
1996</link>, is an online "ask an expert" site for computer related questions. The free access is limited (see below) while fee-based premium service is available without such limitations.</p>
<p>

In Experts-Exchange, users are awarded with points for answering questions asked by other users. This results in a competition for obtaining more points. Those who obtain 3,000 points each month are given access to all features of the web site, known as <it>premium services</it>. Premium services are also available by payment.</p>
<p>

Experts-Exchange went bankrupt in 2001. Austin Miller and Randy Redberg took ownership of Experts-Exchange afterwards and the company was made profitable again. Experts-Exchange has more than 2 million solutions now.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Experts-Exchange has mostly been among the top 1500 visited websites in the first 6 months of 2008, based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/264302.xml">
Alexa</link>'s rank.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> It's users are mainly young to middle-aged males.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
 Operating Mode </st>

<p>

The askers can post their questions in relevant "Zones" after they are registered at the site. The experts propose comments, and the asker is expected to select one or more comments that best solve the problem as the answer, and to grade the answer (from A for excellent answers to C for answers that helped a bit but didn't provide a complete solution) in order to award the most helpful experts. This is achieved by a patented system (U.S. Patent 6,064,978 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>) that encourages experts to accumulate award points by providing satisfactory answers, and questioners to continue pushing experts until an adequate solution is obtained.</p>
<p>

The maximum point value for a question is 500 points and the minimum is 20. Based on Experts-Exchange guidelines, 500 points should be assigned to questions of a high level of difficulty, for an urgent request, or where some other large time or cost savings benefit will be gained by the asker.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>
However, members with premium services subscription often assign the maximum point value to their simple or intermediate questions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

An expert ranking system is provided to certify the experts according to their expertise, contributions and activities. A high ranking in most topic areas is generally indicative of an expert who devotes a substantial amount of time and may have a high level of expertise. The list of top experts includes a number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/557084.xml">
Microsoft MVP</link>s as well.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> It is announced on Microsoft Exchange team's blog that Experts-Exchange is among the communities they actively look into  to find people who make good candidates for Exchange MVPs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>
<p>

Volunteered members with various administrative privileges maintain the site by resolving arguments, closing questions left open by the asker, and assisting members with their site-related questions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Membership</st>

<p>

One must be a member of Experts-Exchange to be able to ask questions. As of late 2007, it is also necessary to be a member to view the solutions. People who are not signed in are redirected to a page where they can sign up, when they try to visit any Experts-Exchange page beyond the first page. This is accomplished through setting cookies on their machines. However, there are workarounds available<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>, including simply scrolling to the bottom of the page where the answers are visible.</p>
<p>

There are two membership plans available: free membership, and premium services.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Free membership</st>

<p>

Users may sign up for a free membership account and receive a limited quantity of question points (125) that they can spend to get answers to their IT questions from other members (experts). They will be given addition 5 points each day, which they can accumulate and use for their next questions. Nonetheless, they cannot accumulate more than 500 question points.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

Free membership allows the member to search in Experts-Exchange questions using its built in search engine, but clicking on the search results redirects them to a page asking them to subscribe for premium services.</p>
<p>

Another limitation of the free membership is the use of ads and popups which the site employs resulting in slower loading pages and diminished usability.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Premium services</st>

<p>

There are premium services available by fee-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/259338.xml">
subscription</link>, as well as by accumulating sufficient points (10,000) and maintaining minimum points over time (3,000 per month).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> Members subscribed to premium services can benefit the full power of Experts-Exchange built in search engine. Also, Experts-Exchange pages load faster for these members because the advertisements are removed from the page.</p>
<p>

Users buying premium services can cancel their subscription upon their decision; this has to be done before the next billing date. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

Originally, the name and URL of the site was expertsexchange.com but this created confusion and ridicule as many users intrepreted it as Expert-Sex-Change as opposed to Experts-Exchange. Subsequently, the URL was changed to experts-exchange.com.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>
<p>

Experts-Exchange went bankrupt in 2001 after venture capitalists moved the company to San Mateo, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/5407.xml">
CA</link></country>
, and was brought back largely through the efforts of unpaid volunteers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> The period following the bankruptcy recovery was marked by a rapid growth and expansion of the knowledge base and saw technical advances.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>
<p>

Experts-Exchange was chosen as a runner-up for <it>Best web resource for developers</it> award by VSJ on 2006;<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/8933015.xml">
The Code Project</link></web_site>
</group>
</machine>
</community>
</device>
</gathering>
</instrumentality>
</social_group>
</artifact>
</computer>
 won this award and the other runner-up was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/63316.xml">
MSDN</link>.</p>
<p>

In the late months of 2006, Experts-Exchange allowed users to try out a new version of their website. In late January 2007, the legacy site was replaced. Many complaints and bugs were reported during this time, but since then most have been fixed. Experts Exchange offers a skin (Expert Skin) that paid members or qualified experts may use if they prefer the Legacy site over the new one. The benefits of the Expert skin will Include smaller sized, less graphics-intensive pages, and a more text-based experience, which can be useful to users with low bandwidth.</p>
<p>

The new site also brought about many new topic areas (now called 'zones') and the ability to cross-post. Cross-posting provides benefits for both those who ask and answer questions. Those who ask questions can place a link to it in up to 3 zones (instead of just one), which means more experts are likely to see the question and answer it. Experts who receive points on such a question will get the allotted amount of points in all 3 zones, making it easier for them to get certificates in other zones that are related. The expert's total points is only increased once for the question (even if the question appears in multiple zones).</p>
<p>

New rankings have also been added, as some experts have achieved the Genius ranking and had nothing else to aim for. The new rankings that come after 'Genius' are: 'Savant' (for 10 million points), 'Elite' (for 25 million points), 'Technocrat' (for 50 million points), and 'Legend' (for 100 million points). <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>
<p>

On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/21761.xml">
13 November</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>, the number of solutions on Experts-Exchange reached 2,000,000. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> Experts-Exchange ran a competition from almost a month before that date. The competition was announced on Experts-Exchange web site and its newsletter. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/102490.xml">
Dell</link> laptop and a t-shirt was given to the user who asked the 2,000,000th question, the expert who answered it, and the user who made the nearest guess for the time and date of the 2,000,000th solution.</p>
<p>

On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/15789.xml">
3 January</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>, it was announced that an Expert has reached 20,000,000 points in total and 18,000,000 points in one zone. Both of these values were the most in Experts-Exchange to date. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Reception </st>

<p>

Experts-Exchange has been praised as one of the best technical support sites by some of its reviewers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/1467304.xml">
PC Magazine</link></magazine>
 lists Experts-Exchange as one of the top 101 websites. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref></p>
<p>

Different views are expressed in reviews written by <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<shop wordnetid="104202417" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<mercantile_establishment wordnetid="103748162" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<bookshop wordnetid="102871525" confidence="0.8">
<place_of_business wordnetid="103953020" confidence="0.8">
<establishment wordnetid="103297735" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/90451.xml">
Amazon.com</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</establishment>
</place_of_business>
</bookshop>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</mercantile_establishment>
</structure>
</shop>
</computer>
 users about Experts-Exchange <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref>. While some users have found it easy to answer a couple of questions and get free premium access to the web site, others have found Experts-Exchange results in search engine searches annoying. Some search engine users have been frustrated that a large number of Experts Exchange results appear in response to technical queries, but the pages are apparently not available without payment;<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref> at the time, there was no way to view the solutions except by creating an account, or scroll down to the bottom of the page.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Controversy </st>

<p>

It has been frequently alleged on various web bulletin boards that Experts-Exchange engages regularly in questionable tactics to deceive potential customers. Previously, Experts-Exchange showed a different content for its pages when they were crawled by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/33120.xml">
spiders</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref> This was considered a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/418364.xml">
cloaking</link>, which is considered a violation of most search engines' terms of service.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref> </p>
<p>

In 2005, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/1877273.xml">
Greasmonkey</link> script was published on the internet which would hide results from Experts-Exchange website from Google search results, when installed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref> Comments on this script are controversial, especially because there are a few ways to get to Experts-Exchange's answers without subscribing to the web site.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/twoMillionSolutions.jsp">
Experts-Exchange passed 2 million solutions</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-22</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alexa.com/data/details/traffic_details/experts-exchange.com?site0=experts-exchange.com&amp;y=t&amp;z=0&amp;h=300&amp;w=470&amp;c=1&amp;u%5B%5D=experts-exchange.com&amp;x=2008-09-22T12%3A25%3A42.000Z&amp;check=www.alexa.com&amp;signature=NQA%2BSMjsNMu%2BnUwxIognoMSNhSU%3D&amp;range=6m&amp;size=Medium">
Alexa's graph for Experts-Exchange's rank in 2008</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-22</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.quantcast.com/experts-exchange.com">
Audience profile for Experts-Exchnage</weblink>".&#32;  Quantcast.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-22</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?patentnumber=6064978">
U.S. Patent 6,064,978</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pat2pdf.org/pat2pdf/foo.pl?number=6064978">
&nbsp;</weblink>. United States Patent (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/19659.xml">
16 May</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link>).</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/help.jsp#hi4">
Experts-Exchange's Help Page</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/Community_Support/Input/Q_22059528.html?qid=22059528#17936185">
Experts-Exchange's Topic</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Butler, Simon.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amset.co.uk/about-simon.asp">
Simon Butler's Personal Page</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/M_1024607.html">
FlyGuyBob's Member Profile</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="9">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/M_1087631.html">
Exchange_Admin's Member Profile</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="10">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/M_1354672.html">
Aneeshattingal's Member Profile</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="11">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ee-stuff.com/Newsletter/032404newsletter.htm">
Experts Exchange Community News</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Microsoft Exchange Team&#32;(2004-05-05).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://msexchangeteam.com/archive/2004/05/05/126630.aspx">
Where Microsoft Exchange Team looks for potential MVP candidates</weblink>".&#32;  Microsoft Exchange Team Blog.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="13">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.daniweb.com/forums/thread44437.html">
How to always view answers on Experts Exchange</weblink>".&#32;  Daniweb forums&#32;(2006-04-29).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="14">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.askstudent.com/hacking/how-to-obtain-free-answers-from-experts-exchangecom/">
How to obtain free answers from Experts-Exchange.com</weblink>".&#32;  AskStudent&#32;(2006-10-20).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="15">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/help.jsp#hi20">
Experts-Exchange's Help Page</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="17">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/help.jsp#hi106">
Experts Exchange point system, payment and service features</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-29</link>.</entry>
<entry id="16">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/help.jsp#hi7">
Experts-Exchange's Help Page</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="19">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/Community_Support/Input/Q_20462342.html#7754371">
Expert-Exchange's Topic</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange&#32;(2003-01-18).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="18">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://workingsolo.com.au/2008/whats-in-a-name/">
Domain name change</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-22</link>.</entry>
<entry id="21">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vsj.co.uk/xml/display.asp?id=580">
VSJ Reader Awards 2006</weblink>".&#32;  VSJ&#32;(2006-08-29).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="20">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/Community_Support/Input/Q_20543746.html#8203183">
2002 highlight reel</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange&#32;(2003-03-25).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="23">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/twoMillionSolutions.jsp">
Two million solutions on Experts-Exchange</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="22">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/ranksDefined.jsp">
Experts-Exchange ranks and their definitions</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="25">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ee-stuff.com/Newsletter/010308newsletter.htm">
Experts-Exchange Newsletter</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange&#32;(2008-01-03).</entry>
<entry id="24">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ee-stuff.com/Newsletter/102407newsletter.htm">
Experts-Exchange Newsletter</weblink>".&#32;  Experts-Exchange&#32;(2007-11-24).</entry>
<entry id="27">
Ragusa, Alphonse&#32;(2004-11-18).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,1895,1680755,00.asp">
Experts-Exchange as one of the top 101 web sites</weblink>".&#32;  <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/1467304.xml">
PC Magazine</link></magazine>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="26">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.techsupportalert.com/best_paid_tech_support_sites.htm">
Tech Support Alert</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="29">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.webuser.co.uk/sites/site_review.php?rev_id=337">
Experts-Exchange Review</weblink>".&#32;  webuser.co.uk&#32;(2003-06-30).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="28">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.techdose.com/viewtopic.php?aid=63">
Experts-Exchange - Knowledgebase for Nerds</weblink>"&#32;(2004-03-12).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-02-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="31">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.coldfusionjedi.com/index.cfm/2006/4/10/Bye-bye-ExpertsExchange">
Cold Fusion Jedi</weblink>"&#32;(2006-04-10).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-31</link>.</entry>
<entry id="30">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/review/product/B00006BLAS/ref=cm_cr_dp_all_helpful/105-1934369-9253243?%5Fencoding=UTF8&amp;coliid=&amp;showViewpoints=1&amp;colid=&amp;sortBy=bySubmissionDateDescending">
Experts-Exchange reviews on Amazon.com</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="34">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/support/webmasters/bin/answer.py?answer=35769">
Google Webmaster Guidelines</weblink>".&#32;  Google Webmaster Help Center&#32;(2008).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-06</link>.</entry>
<entry id="35">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://userscripts.org/scripts/show/1898">
Google experts-exchange.com remover</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-22</link>.</entry>
<entry id="32">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://angrykeyboarder.wordpress.com/2007/08/01/experts-exchange-should-be-removed-from-google-search-results/">
Angry Keyboarder</weblink>"&#32;(2007-08-01).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-31</link>.</entry>
<entry id="33">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://forums.searchenginewatch.com/showthread.php?t=11974">
Forum post on 2006, showing EE used a form of cloaking</weblink>"&#32;(2006-06-05).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-22</link>.</entry>
<entry id="36">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.clazh.com/how-to-access-experts-exchange-and-bypass-without-registering/">
How To Access Experts Exchange and Bypass Without Registering</weblink>"&#32;(2007-11-20).</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com">
Experts-Exchange website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.experts-exchange.com/registerFree2.jsp">
Experts-Exchange free registration</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Similar services</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.europeanexperts.org/">
European Experts Exchange</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bytes.com/">
Bytes (used to be TheScripts Developer Network)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.codeproject.com/">
The Code Project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mindbottling.com/">
Mindbottling.com</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://techrepublic.com.com/">
Tech Republic</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://knowledgebid.com/">
KnowledgeBid</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.codedigest.com/">
CodeDigest.Com - Free .Net articles, tutorials, codes, etc.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://itknowledgeexchange.techtarget.com/">
ITKnowledgeExchange</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stackoverflow.com/">
StackOverflow.com</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss2>
<st>
General Questions</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<market wordnetid="101097292" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/195649.xml">
Google Answers</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</market>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/3385969.xml">
Yahoo! Answers</link></web_site>
</entry>
</list>
</p>


</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</web_site>
</act>
</group>
</community>
</gathering>
</event>
</market>
</social_group>
</article>
