<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:12:07[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Subtraction without borrowing</title>
<id>3202799</id>
<revision>
<id>208605187</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-27T21:01:22Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Arithmetic</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from April 2008</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A commonly known <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/74141.xml">
subtraction</link> method is the <it>borrowing method</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.  To perform <b><it>a - b</it></b> using this method, <b><it>b</it></b>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/74141.xml">
subtrahend</link>, is written below <b><it>a</it></b>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/74141.xml">
minuend</link>, such that the digits of the two numbers are aligned in columns.  When a digit of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/74141.xml">
minuend</link> is smaller than the corresponding digit of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/74141.xml">
subtrahend</link> below it, the procedure calls for <b><it>borrowing</it></b> one power of <b>10</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> from the digit of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/74141.xml">
minuend</link> that is immediately to the left of the current digit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Then the value of the "lending" digit is reduced by <b>1</b>. (More formally this is the <it>decomposition algorithm</it> because the "borrowed" power of <b>10</b> does not have to be and is never returned.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>)  Anyone who subtracts using the borrowing method must do so from right to left, starting at the lowest-value digit and proceeding toward the highest-value digit.  It is also necessary to remember to reduce the value of each “lending” digit by <b>1</b> before subtracting the corresponding digit of the subtrahend from it. Because of these requirements, learning subtraction with borrowing is difficult for some students.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><p>

An alternative to the borrowing method is <b><it>subtraction without borrowing</it></b>.  There are several methods for subtraction without borrowing. However most of them employ other computational methods that are as complex as the methods they aim to replace or they introduce mathematical concepts for which the students who learn subtraction with borrowing are not ready. Among these are methods that use negative numbers and some variations of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/358754.xml">
method of complements</link>.</p>
<p>

<b>Note.</b> The subtraction methods mentioned here assume that the minuend is larger than the subtrahend. If the minuend is smaller than the subtrahend, the roles of the numbers are reversed and any subtraction method can be used followed by setting the result to be negative. If the two numbers are equal the result is zero and no method is needed.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Algorithm </st>
<p>

The basic algorithm is:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Change the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/74141.xml">
minuend</link>:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 Subtract <b>1</b> from the rightmost consecutive digit that is larger than the corresponding digit of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/74141.xml">
subtrahend</link>;</entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 Change each digit to the right of the digit you reduced by <b>1</b> (Step #1.1) to <b>9</b> -- this is your new minuend;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Add <b>1</b> to the number whose digits you changed to <b>9</b>'s -- this sum is the difference between the original minuend and the new one;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Carry out the subtraction using the new minuend;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Add the difference you got in Step #2 to the result of Step #3. This is the final answer.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Descriptive example </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(April 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


As demonstrated by the example below, subtraction without borrowing employs single-digit subtraction in each column of digits and then addition.</p>


<p>

<b>  65432</b>      (minuend)
<b>- 27894</b>      (subtrahend)</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Change the minuend to <b>59999</b>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The difference between the original minuend and this new one is <b>5433</b>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

It is necessary to remember this difference. 
This is easy because it equals to the minuend without its leftmost digit plus <b>1</b>:</p>

<p>

<b>  5432</b>
<b>+    1</b>
<b>  5433</b></p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Now perform the revised subtraction, using the new minuend</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>  59999</b>
<b>- 27894</b>
<b>  32105</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Now add the difference, which we noted above, to the result</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<b> 32105</b>
<b>+ 5433</b>
<b> 37538</b>
<b> =====</b></p>


<p>

This is the final answer <b>(65432 - 27894 = 37538)</b>.</p>




</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Example 2 - the Simplified Procedure </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(April 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


A small change in writing the numbers simplifies this procedure significantly, especially during the learning process. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

We start by writing the two numbers with a blank line between them:</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<b>  65432</b>      (minuend)

<b>- 23894</b>      (subtrahend)</p>

<p>

Since we notice that, in this case, each of the two most-significant digits of the minuend is larger than the corresponding digit of the subtrahend, we...</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Reduce by <b>1</b> the second most significant digit, not the first, and</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Change only  the last three digits of the minuend to <b>9</b>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Write the new minuend  -- <b>64999</b> -- on the blank line under the original minuend:</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<b>  65432</b>      (original minuend)
<b>  64999</b>      (new minuend)
<b>- 23894</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Note that the difference between the original minuend and the new one equals the number consisting of the digits that we changed to <b>9</b> plus <b>1</b>:</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>432 + 1 = 433</b></p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Now perform the revised subtraction (from the new minuend).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

We continue to write the original minuend for reference only, because it is important to remember the original task; we no longer use it.</p>

<p>

<b>  65432</b>      (original minuend)
<b>  64999</b>      (new minuend)
<b>- 23894</b>
<b>  41105</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Finally add the difference, which we noted above, to the result</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b> 41105</b>
<b>+  433</b>
<b> 41538</b>
<b> =====</b></p>


<p>

This is the final answer <b>(65432 - 23894 = 41538)</b>.</p>

<p>

After it is completed, the operation may appear on the worksheet like so:</p>
<p>

<b>  65432</b>      (original minuend)
<b>  64999</b>      (new minuend)
<b>- 23894</b>
<b>  41105</b>
<b>+  433</b>
<b> 41538</b>
<b> =====</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Note that the original minuend is not crossed. When kids are taught to cross text they often overdo it to a point the original text can no longer be read. It is important to know the original minuend and be able to reconstruct the original subtraction assignment.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

This is a simplified, informal algorithm. In some cases a different procedure is called for or simpler one can be used. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

This is a generalization of a common practice of many people, including early-grade students. For example, when facing a subtraction problem such as <b>1001 - 567</b>, teachers have reported that some third-grade students had solved it by doing <b>999 - 567 + 2</b>. Indeed, an ancient Hindu system of mathematics, known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/12939249.xml">
Vedic mathematics</link> includes this special case as one of its sixteen sutras (principles).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> </entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Footnotes and References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Only a brief, informal discussion is included here until a formal entry of <it>dynamic subtraction</it> is provided.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 This brief discussion of the <it>borrowing method</it> refers to the decimal number system and decimal place values. The basic procedures described here can be applied to other situations. Only the boundary values and the borrowed magnitudes depend on the number system and the place values. For example, while performing time subtraction, if borrowing is necessary for the <b>tens</b> digit of the seconds, the borrowed <b>minute</b> adds <b>60</b> seconds to the number of seconds specified by the current digit, not <b>10</b>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
 Also this discussion of the <it>borrowing method</it> does not address more complex situations such as when the “lending” digit is <b>0</b> (zero) and, therefore, nothing can be borrowed from it.</entry>
<entry id="4">
 Subtraction in the United States: An Historical Perspective, Susan Ross, Mary Pratt-Cotter, <it>The Mathematics Educator</it>, Vol. 8, No. 1 (original publication) and Vol. 10, No. 1 (reprint.)
http://math.coe.uga.edu/TME/Issues/v10n2/5ross.pdf</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mathventures.com/mathed/Arithmetic/SubtractionWithoutBorrowingLite.htm">
 Subtraction Without Borrowing</weblink> on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mathventures.com/">
MathVentures</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mathventures.com/mathed/Arithmetic/SubtractionWithoutBorrowingSimple.htm">
A descriptive example of the simplified procedure</weblink> (at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mathventures.com">
MathVentures</weblink>)</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vedicmaths.org/Introduction/Tutorial/Tutorial.asp#tutorial1">
Vedic Maths, Tutorial 1</weblink> on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vedicmaths.org">
VedicMaths.org</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
