<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:19:04[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Ballistic conduction</title>
<id>3345023</id>
<revision>
<id>234605118</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-27T17:21:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CharlesC</username>
<id>182379</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Nanoelectronics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Ballistic conduction</b> is the characteristic of a material, known as a <it>ballistic conductor</it>, which has <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/6015.xml">
crystal</link>line properties that allow <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/9476.xml">
electrons</link> to flow through the material without collisions. The material must be free of impurities that electrons could collide with. In ordinary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/198984.xml">
conductors</link>, flowing electrons continually collide with the atoms making up the material, slowing down the electrons and causing the material to heat, effectively creating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/61577.xml">
resistance</link>. Ballistic conduction differs from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/26884.xml">
superconductivity</link> due to the absence of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/51117.xml">
Meissner effect</link> in the material.<p>

Ballistic conduction occurs in some carbon <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/428386.xml">
nanotube</link>s.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Ballistic conduction on micro-scale</st>
<p>

Probably any conduction process over a short enough distance (~several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/21837.xml">
nanometer</link>s) could be considered as ballistic conduction,
because the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/22934.xml">
probability</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/164483.xml">
scattering</link> on an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/2061993.xml">
impurity</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/85754.xml">
phonon</link> is very low at such a short distance. </p>
<p>

Most common studies of ballistic conductivity has been conducted at this micro- or nano-scale, often at low temperature.
For example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/52206.xml">
nanowires</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/27775.xml">
STM</link> contacted molecules, metal particles or nano-scale <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/27709.xml">
semiconductor</link> structures are often very good approximations of ballistic conductors.</p>
<p>

"Ballisticity" of conduction is probabilistic.  There are no totally ballistic conductors or totally non-ballistic conductors.  Ballisticity is expressed as a probability that an electron will travel without scattering.</p>
<p>

In so-called ballistic conductors (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/911833.xml">
graphene</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/428386.xml">
nanotube</link>s, and some types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/642886.xml">
quantum well</link> systems), the probability of scattering is low enough to consider conduction as ballistic on an almost macroscopic scale.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Importance of ballistic conductivity</st>
<p>

Despite ballistic conductivity being connected with very low resistance of particular materials, the major importance is not energy efficient transport of power over long distance, but rather <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/21488.xml">
nanoscience</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/315578.xml">
information processing</link> electronics applications.</p>
<p>

Ballistic conduction enables use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanical</link> properties of electron <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/145343.xml">
wave function</link>s. Ballistic transport is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/231495.xml">
coherent</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/59874.xml">
wave mechanics</link> terms. Phenomena like <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<scientific_research wordnetid="100641820" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="100639556" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<research wordnetid="100636921" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/8667.xml">
double-split interference</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</research>
</act>
</investigation>
</experiment>
</event>
</scientific_research>
</work>
, spacial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/41660.xml">
resonance</link> (and other optical or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/20097.xml">
microwave</link>-like effects) could be exploited in electronic systems at nanoscale.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Optical analogies of ballistic conduction</st>
<p>
 
A comparison with light provides an analogy between ballistic and non-ballistic conduction.
Ballistic electrons behave like light in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/41863.xml">
waveguide</link> or a high-quality <link>
optical assembly</link>. Non-ballistic electrons behave like light diffused in milk or reflected off a white wall or a piece of paper.</p>
<p>

Electrons can be scattered several ways in a conductor.  Electrons have several properties: wavelength (~energy), direction, phase, and spin orientation. Different materials have different scattering probabilities which cause different incoherence rates (stochasticity). Some kinds of scattering can only cause a change in electron direction, others can cause energy loss.</p>
<p>

Consider a coherent source of electrons (like a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/17556.xml">
laser</link>) connected to a conductor. Over a limited distance, the electron wave function will remain coherent.  You still can deterministically predict its behavior (and use it for computation theoretically).  After some greater distance, scattering causes each electron to have a slightly different [phase] and/or direction.  But there is still almost no energy loss. Like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/261993.xml">
monochromatic</link> light passing through milk, electrons undergo <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/268923.xml">
elastic</link> interactions. Information about the state of the electrons at the input is then lost.  Transport becomes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistical</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/292222.xml">
stochastic</link>.  From the resistance point of view, stochastic (not oriented) movement of electrons is useless even if they carry the same energy - they move thermally. If the electrons undergo <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/268923.xml">
inelastic</link> interactions too, they lose energy and the result is a second mechanism of resistance. Electrons which undergo inelastic interaction are then similar to non-monochromatic light.         </p>
<p>

For correct usage of this analogy consideration of several facts is needed:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/23535.xml">
Photons</link> are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/18978718.xml">
bosons</link> and electrons are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/11529.xml">
fermions</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

There is <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/179060.xml">
coulombic repulsion</link></concept>
</idea>
 between electrons.</entry>
</list>

Thus this analogy is good only for single-electron conduction because electron processes are strongly and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/146103.xml">
nonlinear</link> dependent on other electrons.  
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

It is more likely that an electron would lose energy than a photon would, because of the electron's non-zero <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/162321.xml">
rest mass</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Electron interactions with the environment, each other, and other particles are generally stronger than interactions with and between photons.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

Electronic Transport in Mesoscopic Systems, Supriyo Datta, Contributor: Haroon Ahmad,Alec Broers, Michael Pepper, Published 1997 by Cambridge University Press, ISBN 0521599431</p>

</ss1>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
