<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:17:04[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network calculus</title>
<id>3346954</id>
<revision>
<id>188209910</id>
<timestamp>2008-01-31T19:27:44Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Nihonjoe</username>
<id>446342</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Network performance</category>
<category>Computer network analysis</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Network calculus</b> is a theoretical framework for analysing performance guarantees in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/4122592.xml">
computer network</link>s. As traffic flows through a network it is subject to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/206360.xml">
constraint</link>s imposed by the system components, for example:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/40996.xml">
link</link> capacity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 traffic shapers (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/1056496.xml">
leaky bucket</link>s)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/6008196.xml">
congestion control</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 background traffic</entry>
</list>
<p>

These constraints can be expressed and analysed with network calculus methods. Constraint curves can be <it>combined</it> using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../519/7519.xml">
convolution</link> under <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/867041.xml">
min-plus algebra</link>. Network calculus can also be used to express traffic arrival and departure functions as well as service curves.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Traffic envelopes</st>
<p>

Traffic flows in networks are described as cumulative functions. For example, <math>A(t)</math> 
is the number of bits in the interval <math>[0,t)</math>. <math>A(t)</math> is said to conform to an envelope respectively arrival curve <math>E(t)</math> if for all <math>t</math> it holds that</p>
<p>

<math>
E(t) \ge \sup_{\tau \ge 0} \{A(t+\tau) - A(\tau) \} = (A \oslash A)(t).
</math></p>
<p>

Thus, <math>E(t)</math> places an upper constraint on flow <math>A(t)</math>, i.e. an envelope <math>E(t)</math> specifies an upper bound on the number of bits of flow <math>A(t)</math> seen in any interval of length <math>t</math> starting at an arbitrary <math>\tau</math>. The above equation can be rephrased for all <math>t</math> as</p>
<p>

<math>
A(t) \le \inf_{0 \leq \tau \leq t} \{ A(\tau) + E(t-\tau) \} = (A \otimes E)(t).
</math></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Service curves</st>
<p>

In order to provide performance guarantees to traffic flows it may be necessary to implement reservations in the network. Service curves provide a means of expressing resource allocations. </p>
<p>

Let <math>A(t)</math> be a flow arriving at the ingress of a system, e.g. a link, a scheduler, a traffic shaper, or a whole network, and <math>D(t)</math> be the flow departing at the egress. The system is said to provide a service curve <math>S(t)</math>, if for all <math>t</math> it holds that</p>
<p>

<math>
D(t) \ge \inf_{0 \le \tau \le t} \{A(\tau) + S(t-\tau) \} = (A \otimes S)(t).
</math></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Min-plus algebra</st>
<p>

In filter theory respectively linear systems theory the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../519/7519.xml">
convolution</link> of two functions <math>f</math> and <math>g</math> is defined as</p>
<p>

<math>
(f \ast g) (t) := \sum_{\tau} f(\tau) \cdot g(t-\tau).
</math></p>
<p>

In <b>min-plus algebra</b> the <it>sum</it> is replaced by the minimum respectively <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/39382.xml">
infimum</link></it> operator and the <it>product</it> is replaced by the <it>sum</it>. So the min-plus convolution of two functions <math>f</math> and <math>g</math> becomes</p>
<p>

<math>
(f \otimes g) (t) := \inf_{0 \leq \tau \leq t}\left\{f(\tau) + g(t-\tau)\right\}
</math></p>
<p>

e.g. see the definition of service curves. Convolution and min-plus convolution share many algebraic properties. In particular both are commutative and associative.</p>
<p>

A so-called min-plus de-convolution operation is defined as</p>
<p>

<math>
(f \oslash g) (t) := \sup_{\tau \ge 0}\left\{f(t+\tau) - g(\tau)\right\}
</math></p>
<p>

e.g. as used in the definition of traffic envelopes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Concatenation</st>
<p>

Consider two systems with service curve <math>S_1(t)</math> and <math>S_2(t)</math> in series. Let <math>A(t)</math> be the arrival function at system 1 and <math>D(t)</math> the departure function of system 2. By iterative application of the definition of service curves we have </p>
<p>

<math>D(t) \geq (A \otimes S_1) \otimes S_2)(t)</math>.</p>
<p>

By associativity of the min-plus convolution it follows that </p>
<p>

<math>D(t) \geq (A \otimes (S_1 \otimes S_2))(t)</math></p>
<p>

i.e. the tandem of systems <math>S_1(t)</math> and <math>S_2(t)</math> is equivalent to a single, lumped system <math>S_{e2e}(t)</math> where</p>
<p>

<math>S_{e2e}(t) = (S_1 \otimes S_2)(t)</math>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Performance bounds</st>
<p>

The virtual backlog is defined as the vertical deviation of <math>A(t)</math> and <math>D(t)</math></p>
<p>

<math>
B(t) = A(t) - D(t), \forall t \ge 0.
</math> </p>
<p>

Using the concepts of traffic envelopes and service curves the maximum backlog is bounded by</p>
<p>

<math>
B_{\max} \le \sup_{\tau \ge 0} \{E(\tau) - S(\tau) \} = (E \oslash S)(0).
</math></p>
<p>

The delay <math>W(t)</math> is defined as the horizontal deviation of <math>A(t)</math> and <math>D(t)</math></p>
<p>

<math>
W(t) = \inf \{w : A(t) - D(t+w) \le 0\} , \forall t \ge 0.
</math></p>
<p>

Using the concepts of traffic envelopes and service curves the maximum delay is bounded by</p>
<p>

<math>
W_{\max} \le \inf \{w : \sup_{\tau \ge w} \{ E(\tau-w) - S(\tau) \} \le 0 \} = \inf \{w : (E \oslash S)(-w) \le 0 \}.
</math></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

Books that cover Network Calculus
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C.-S. Chang: <it>Performance Guarantees in Communications Networks</it>, Springer, 2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 J.-Y. Le Boudec and P. Thiran: <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lrcwww.epfl.ch/PS_files/NetCal.htm">
Network Calculus: A Theory of Deterministic Queuing Systems for the Internet</weblink></it>, Springer, LNCS, 2001.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A. Kumar, D. Manjunath, and J. Kuri: <it>Communication Networking: An Analytical Approach</it>, Elsevier, 2004.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Related books on max-plus algebra and convex optimization
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 R. T. Rockafellar: <it>Convex Analysis</it>, Princeton University Press, 1972.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 F. Baccelli, G. Cohen, G. J. Olsder, and J.-P. Quadrat: <it>Synchronization and Linearity: An Algebra for Discrete Event Systems</it>, Wiley, 1992.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Some related research papers
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 R. L. Cruz: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/18.61109">
A Calculus for Network Delay. Part I: Network Elements in Isolation</weblink>  and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/18.61110">
Part II: Network Analysis</weblink> , IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 37(1):114-141, Jan. 1991.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 O. Yaron and M. Sidi: <it>Performance and Stability of Communication Networks via Robust Exponential Bounds</it>, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, 1(3):372-385, Jun. 1993.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C.-S. Chang: <it>Stability, Queue Length and Delay of Deterministic and Stochastic Queueing Networks</it>, IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, 39(5):913-931, May 1994.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 D. E. Wrege, E. W. Knightly, H. Zhang, and J. Liebeherr: <it>Deterministic delay bounds for VBR video in packet-switching networks: Fundamental limits and practical tradeoffs</it>, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, 4(3):352-362, Jun. 1996.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 R. L. Cruz: <it>SCED+: Efficient Management of Quality of Service Guarantees</it>, IEEE INFOCOM, pp. 625-634, Mar. 1998.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 J.-Y. Le Boudec: <it>Application of Network Calculus to Guaranteed Service Networks</it>, IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 44(3):1087-1096, May 1998.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C.-S. Chang: <it>On Deterministic Traffic Regulation and Service Guarantees: A Systematic Approach by Filtering</it>, IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 44(3):1097-1110, May 1998.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 R. Agrawal, R. L. Cruz, C. Okino, and R. Rajan: <it>Performance Bounds for Flow Control Protocols</it>, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, 7(3):310-323, Jun. 1999.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 D. Starobinski and M. Sidi: <it>Stochastically Bounded Burstiness for Communication Networks</it>, IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 46(1):206-212, Jan. 2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A. Charny and J.-Y. Le Boudec: <it>Delay Bounds in a Network with Aggregate Scheduling</it>, QoFIS, pp. 1-13, Sep. 2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 R.-R. Boorstyn, A. Burchard, J. Liebeherr, and C. Oottamakorn: <it>Statistical Service Assurances for Traffic Scheduling Algorithms</it>, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications, 18(12):2651-2664, Dec. 2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 J.-Y. Le Boudec: <it>Some properties of variable length packet shapers</it>, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, 10(3):329-337, Jun. 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Q. Yin, Y. Jiang, S. Jiang, and P. Y. Kong: <it>Analysis of Generalized Stochastically Bounded Bursty Traffic for Communication Networks</it>, IEEE LCN, pp. 141-149, Nov. 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C.-S. Chang, R. L. Cruz, J.-Y. Le Boudec, and P. Thiran: <it>A Min, + System Theory for Constrained Traffic Regulation and Dynamic Service Guarantees</it>, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, 10(6):805-817, Dec. 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 D. Starobinski, M. Karpovsky, and L. Zakrevski: <it>Application of Network Calculus to General Topologies using Turn-Prohibition</it>, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, 11(3):411-421, Jun. 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C. Li, A. Burchard, and J. Liebeherr: <it>A Network Calculus with Effective Bandwidth</it>, University of Virginia, Technical Report CS-2003-20, Nov. 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 F. Ciucu, A. Burchard, and J. Liebeherr: <it>A Network Service Curve Approach for the Stochastic Analysis of Networks</it>, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, 52(6):2300–2312­, Jun. 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 M. Fidler and S. Recker: <it>Conjugate network calculus: A dual approach applying the Legendre transform</it>, Computer Networks, 50(8):1026-1039, Jun. 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 M. Fidler: <it>An End-to-End Probabilistic Network Calculus with Moment Generating Functions</it>, IEEE IWQoS, Jun. 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A. Burchard, J. Liebeherr, and  S. D. Patek: <it>A Min-Plus Calculus for End-to-end Statistical Service Guarantees</it>, IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 52(9):4105–4114­, Sep. 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Eitan Altman, Kostya Avrachenkov, and Chadi Barakat: <it>TCP network calculus: The case of large bandwidth-delay product</it>, In proceedings of IEEE INFOCOM, NY, June 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kym Watson, Juergen Jasperneite: <it>Determining End-to-End Delays using Network Calculus</it>, in 5th IFAC International Conference on Fieldbus Systems and their Applications (FeT´2003) S.: 255-260, Aveiro, Portugal, Jul 2003</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
