<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:17:38[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Computation tree</title>
<id>3365796</id>
<revision>
<id>77843946</id>
<timestamp>2006-09-26T03:56:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Pascal.Tesson</username>
<id>1283289</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computational complexity theory</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>computation tree</b> is a representation for the computation steps of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/21935.xml">
non-deterministic Turing machine</link> on a specified input. A computation <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/48560.xml">
tree</link> is an <link>
acyclic graph</link> of nodes and edges. Each node in the tree represents a single computational state, while each edge represents a transition to the next possible computation. The number of nodes of the tree is the size of the tree and the length of the path from the root to a given node is the depth of the node. The largest depth of an output node is the depth of the tree. The output nodes of the tree are called leaves. <p>

In a computation tree each output node is labeled Yes or No. If a tree, T, with an input space X, if <math> x \in X </math> and the path for x ends in node labeled yes, then the input x is accepted. Else it is rejected.</p>
<p>

The depth of the computation tree for a given input is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/4627844.xml">
computation time</link> for the Turing machine on that input.</p>
<p>

One of the primary methods of showing that a computational problem <it>L</it> is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/1176530.xml">
complete</link> for a given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/502426.xml">
complexity class</link> <it>C</it> is to show that the computation tree of any algorithm in <it>C</it> can be directly analyzed in terms of <it>L</it>.</p>

</bdy>
</article>
