<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:26:18[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<condition  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113920429">
<happening  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107283608">
<state  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100024720">
<adversity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114475661">
<catastrophe  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114476290">
<fortune  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114473222">
<fire  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107302836">
<failure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100066636">
<misfortune  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114475405">
<nonaccomplishment  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100066216">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<explosion  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107308563">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<discharge  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107307754">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<header>
<title>2005 Hertfordshire Oil Storage Terminal fire</title>
<id>3384168</id>
<revision>
<id>242736380</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T12:59:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>JonRB</username>
<id>1212401</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>2005 in England</category>
<category>Gas explosions</category>
<category>Fires in England</category>
<category>Engineering failures</category>
<category>Oil infrastructure of the United Kingdom</category>
<category>History of Hertfordshire</category>
<category>Explosions in the United Kingdom</category>
<category>Industrial disasters</category>
<category>2005 fires</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

|
|- 
| 
<image width="195px" src="Hertfordshire_outline_map_with_UK.png">
<caption>

2005 Hertfordshire Oil Storage Terminal fire (Hertfordshire)
</caption>
</image>
<image width="8x8px" src="Red_pog2.svg">
<caption>

2005 Hertfordshire Oil Storage Terminal fire
</caption>
</image>
Hemel Hempstead in Hertfordshire
<image width="200px" src="Hemel_Hempstead_fuel_explosion_map.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

In this satellite photo the pollution from the explosion and fires, appearing black, is spreading in two main streams from the explosion site at the apex of the inverted 'v'.   The orange dot is a marker, not the actual fire. 
</caption>
</image>

<image width="200px" src="buncefield2.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The fire seen from a vantage point between the Northgate and 3Com buildings.
</caption>
</image>

<p>

The <b>2005 Hertfordshire Oil Storage Terminal fire</b> was caused by a series of explosions early on the morning of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/8396.xml">
11 December</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>. The terminal, generally known as the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<terminal wordnetid="104412901" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<station wordnetid="104306080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/3384290.xml">
Buncefield Depot</link></station>
</facility>
</terminal>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
, is an oil storage facility located near the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<expressway wordnetid="103306610" confidence="0.8">
<highway wordnetid="103519981" confidence="0.8">
<way wordnetid="104564698" confidence="0.8">
<road wordnetid="104096066" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/181818.xml">
M1 motorway</link></road>
</way>
</highway>
</expressway>
</artifact>
 on the edge of <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/258642.xml">
Hemel Hempstead</link></site>
 in <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/13986.xml">
Hertfordshire</link></county>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/9316.xml">
England</link></country>
. News reports described the incident as the biggest of its kind in peacetime <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  The tank fires were extinguished by the afternoon of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8852.xml">
13 December</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>. However, one storage tank re-ignited in the evening, and the firefighters left it to burn, rather than attempting to re-extinguish it.</p>


<sec>
<st>
The incident</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Explosion and fire</st>
<p>

The first and largest explosion occurred at 06:01 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/32063.xml">
UTC</link> near container 912. From all accounts, it seems to have been an unconfined <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/32505.xml">
vapour</link> cloud explosion of unusually high strength. Because of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/52141.xml">
inversion layer</link>, the explosions were heard a hundred miles (160&nbsp;km) away; there were reports it was audible in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
 and the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/21148.xml">
Netherlands</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/1390040.xml">
British Geological Survey</link></company>
 monitored the event, which measured 2.4 on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/19467352.xml">
Richter scale</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> It was reported that people were woken in south London, and as far west as Wokingham, where in its southern suburb, Finchampstead, numerous people felt the shockwave after the initial explosion. Subsequent explosions occurred at 06:27 and 06:28. Witnesses observed flames hundreds of feet high from many miles away, with the smoke cloud visible from space, and as far north as Lincolnshire.</p>
<p>

Damage from the blasts, ranging from broken windows (including Holy Trinity, the local church and Leverstock Green School losing over 90 panes) and blown-in or warped front doors to an entire wall being removed from a warehouse, occurred more than half a mile (800&nbsp;m) away. Buildings in neighbouring <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/28523.xml">
St Albans</link></site>
 also suffered: for example, Townsend School had serious blast damage, and a window was blown out of <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<religious_residence wordnetid="104073948" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<residence wordnetid="104079244" confidence="0.8">
<dwelling wordnetid="103259505" confidence="0.8">
<church wordnetid="103028079" confidence="0.8">
<housing wordnetid="103546340" confidence="0.8">
<monastery wordnetid="103781244" confidence="0.8">
<place_of_worship wordnetid="103953416" confidence="0.8">
<cathedral wordnetid="102984061" confidence="0.8">
<house wordnetid="103544360" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/73070.xml">
St Albans Abbey</link></house>
</cathedral>
</place_of_worship>
</monastery>
</housing>
</church>
</dwelling>
</residence>
</artifact>
</building>
</religious_residence>
</structure>
 (both c. 5 miles (8 km) from the site).  Several nearby office blocks were hit so badly that almost every window, front and back, was blown in as the explosion ripped through them. Had this happened during the working day, these offices would have been full of people; possibly causing many deaths. Reports also indicated that cars in nearby streets caught fire. The roof of at least one house was blown off. Buildings in the vicinity were evacuated by police, not only because of the smoke and possibility of more explosions but because of the danger of structural damage making the buildings unstable.</p>
<p>

There were 43 reported injuries; two people were deemed to be seriously injured enough to be kept in hospital, one in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/349407.xml">
Watford</link></village>
 General Hospital, with breathing difficulties, and another in Hemel Hempstead Hospital; they were not in a life-threatening condition. Some early media reports spoke of eight fatalities, but these may have been persons missing. All members of staff from the terminal were accounted for.</p>
<p>

Hertfordshire police and fire services and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/98066.xml">
Member of Parliament</link> for the area, <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<soldier wordnetid="110622053" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<enlisted_person wordnetid="110058777" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/1867366.xml">
Mike Penning</link></enlisted_person>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</person>
</soldier>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
, said that there were seven fuel tanks on the site which, as of 14:00 on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/8633.xml">
12 December</link>, had not been affected; these tanks were at risk of exploding if the fire were to spread.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Tackling the blaze</st>
<p>

Around 150 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/146303.xml">
firefighter</link>s were called to the incident--they began to tackle the blaze at 08:20 on the morning of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/8633.xml">
12 December</link>, putting in containment measures before applying a large quantity of foam.  It was estimated that this would be the largest 'single-seat' fire in the world ever to be fought by a fire brigade, and foam supplies from sites all over the UK were drawn upon. Plans had been in place to start using foam at midnight on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/8396.xml">
11 December</link>, but were delayed by last-minute concerns over possible <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollution</link> of local rivers and underlying water sources from contaminated water used to fight the fires.  Six high volume pumps were used to extract 25,000 litres of water per minute (91 gallons per second) from a reservoir 2.4 kilometers (1.5 miles) from the fire, with six more high volume pumps deployed at various locations to serve as boosters.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> 32,000 litres per minute (117 gallons per second) of aerated foam were directed against the fire for just over four hours, after which the pumping rate was reduced.  Half the 20 individual fires were reported extinguished by midday. By 16:30 it was reported that a further two tank fires had been extinguished, but that one of the earlier extinguished tanks had ruptured and re-ignited, and was now threatening to cause the explosion of an adjacent tank.  This led to the M1 motorway being closed again, the public exclusion area being widened and firefighters being temporarily withdrawn until the risk from the threatened tank could be determined. </p>
<p>

Firefighting operations were resumed at about 20:00 and it was anticipated that all fires could be extinguished during the night.  Further damage occurred to one of the storage tanks in the early hours of the morning, causing firefighters to be withdrawn once more, but operations resumed at 08:30.  By midday on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8852.xml">
13 December</link>, all but three fires had been extinguished, although the largest tank was still burning.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/2604771.xml">
Bronze command</link> (that is operations on the ground) was visited by the Bishop of St Albans, the local Vicar and the industrial chaplain supporting the fire crews to see how they were coping.  The smoke plume had been considerably reduced and was more grey, indicating the amount of vapourised water now combining with the smoke.  Firefighters were confident that the remaining fires could be extinguished during the day.  It was reported at 16:45 that all tank fires were now extinguished, although some smaller fires remained.  75% of firefighters for Hertfordshire were involved in fighting the fire, together with support from 16 other brigades.  The entire gold command operation involving many agencies as well as all the emergency services was run from <police wordnetid="108209687" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/3390149.xml">
Hertfordshire Constabulary</link></police>
's headquarters in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/346496.xml">
Welwyn Garden City</link></site>
 some distance from the fire.</p>
<p>

A further fire broke out during the early morning of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/8851.xml">
14 December</link>. Firefighters were of the view that extinguishing it would leave the risk of petroleum vapour re-igniting or exploding, so it would be better to allow the fire, which was well contained, to burn itself out. </p>
<p>

Hertfordshire Fire Service's deputy chief Mark Yates stated that escaping petroleum vapour was the most likely cause of the original explosion and fire.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Smoke cloud</st>
<p>

<image width="200px" src="Buncefield-Smoke.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The smoke plume from <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<hamlet wordnetid="108226978" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/402837.xml">
Dunsmore</link></group>
</hamlet>
</community>
</gathering>
</social_group>
, <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/55688.xml">
Bucks</link></county>
 (about twenty miles (32 km) away).
</caption>
</image>

The black smoke cloud, which was clearly visible from satellite photographs, drifted at high altitude, around 9,000&nbsp;feet (2,700&nbsp;m), towards <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/43980.xml">
Reading</link></site>
 and <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/59908.xml">
Swindon</link></site>
, and could be seen across much of <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/52926.xml">
South East England</link></region>
. The small particles in the smoke, which contained <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/13257.xml">
hydrocarbon</link>s, can be an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/326481.xml">
irritant</link> but had low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/170567.xml">
toxicity</link> and were not expected to cause any long-term harm. The <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/319671.xml">
Met Office</link></agency>
 issued warnings that the smoke in the atmosphere could come down in rainfall during the night of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/8396.xml">
11 December</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

For the first two days of the fire, the high thermal energy made the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/3406041.xml">
plume</link> highly buoyant; this, together with settled weather conditions, allowed the plume to rise to a great height with little cross-mixing. When the fire was reduced in intensity it was reported to be possible that the plume would be less buoyant and that ground-level smoke concentrations could then rise significantly.</p>
<p>

By <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/8633.xml">
12 December</link>, it was reported that the smoke cloud had reached northern <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
; it was expected to arrive in northern <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 by the weekend.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

To investigate the smoke cloud the <it>Facility for Airborne Atmospheric Measurements</it>, a research aircraft operated jointly by <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<council wordnetid="108310949" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/816406.xml">
NERC</link></council>
</administrative_unit>
 and the Met Office, made two flights on the 12th and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8852.xml">
13 December</link>. In the first flight the edge of the plume was followed along the south coast of England. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/6136.xml">
Carbon monoxide</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/286685.xml">
nitrogen oxide</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/22718.xml">
ozone</link> concentrations were found to be low with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/286688.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Black+carbon%22])">
soot particles</link> being the major component in the cloud. The second flight went into the centre of the plume to obtain data to help forecasting and emergency teams.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Reactions and response</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Evacuations and closures</st>
<p>

Hundreds of homes in the Hemel Hempstead area were evacuated, with about 2000 people having to find alternative accommodation, and emergency services asked residents of the smoke-affected areas to close their windows and doors and stay inside. Hertfordshire Constabulary advised people who had houses with smashed windows to seek refuge with friends or family nearby if possible. Some people whose homes were damaged by the blast were placed in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/14276.xml">
hotel</link>s, while others stayed in a nearby <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/235723.xml">
shopping centre</link>. <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/804161.xml">
Total</link></company>
, the operator of the Buncefield depot, set up a helpline for people whose properties had been damaged by the explosion, and called in local authorities and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/88801.xml">
Salvation Army</link> to provide accommodation or other help.</p>
<p>

About 227 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/28022.xml">
school</link>s across Hertfordshire and Buckinghamshire as well as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/17727.xml">
libraries</link> and other public buildings were closed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/8633.xml">
December 12</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8852.xml">
December 13</link> for public safety.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> Police and local authorities advised residents to consult the  "Hertfordshire Direct" website<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> for up-to-date information. The <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/503360.xml">
University of Hertfordshire</link></university>
 campus located further afield in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/13985.xml">
Hatfield</link></site>
 remained open.  Meanwhile, 78 schools in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/55639.xml">
Luton</link></village>
 borough were closed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8852.xml">
13 December</link> and a limited number of schools in <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/69769.xml">
Bedfordshire</link></county>
.  These were closed on the advice of Hertfordshire's Health Protection Agency that all schools should be closed in a 10-mile (16&nbsp;km) radius of the incident site due to concerns of the smoke plume and children's health.  They reopened as normal on 14 December.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Transport disruption</st>
<p>

The incident occurred close to junction 8 of the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<expressway wordnetid="103306610" confidence="0.8">
<highway wordnetid="103519981" confidence="0.8">
<way wordnetid="104564698" confidence="0.8">
<road wordnetid="104096066" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/181818.xml">
M1 motorway</link></road>
</way>
</highway>
</expressway>
</artifact>
. The motorway was shut between junctions 12 and 6a (about eighteen miles (29 km)) shortly after the incident. Other roads in the vicinity, including the short <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<expressway wordnetid="103306610" confidence="0.8">
<highway wordnetid="103519981" confidence="0.8">
<way wordnetid="104564698" confidence="0.8">
<road wordnetid="104096066" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/643050.xml">
M10 motorway</link></road>
</way>
</highway>
</expressway>
</artifact>
, were also closed. </p>
<p>

Some local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/61260.xml">
petrol stations</link> reported long queues as people started <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/3235310.xml">
panic buying</link>.  A spokesman for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/304272.xml">
Department for Trade and Industry</link> gave assurances that no petrol shortage was likely to result from the incident.</p>
<p>

The oil terminal supplied 30% of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ter/Joseph_F$orce_C$rater.xml">
Heathrow Airport</link>'s fuel, and because of the fire, the airport had to start rationing fuel.  Some long-haul flights to the Far-East and Australia had to "pit-stop" at <link>
Stansted Airport</link> or other European airports to refuel, while short-haul operators were asked to fuel their planes for the round trip before flying to Heathrow.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Fuel shortages continued for months after the explosion.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Business disruption</st>
<p>

A number of companies was affected by an inability to reach premises used for distribution even where the premises themselves were largely unaffected by the blast.</p>
<p>

The worst hit of the buildings were the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/3417455.xml">
Northgate Information Solutions</link></institution>
</company>
 headquarters and the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/208013.xml">
Fujifilm</link></company>
 building, both of which were totally devastated. As of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8852.xml">
December 13</link> their buildings were completely unusable. The Fujifilm building was rendered unsafe, and demolition began soon afterwards.  By June 2006 it had been completely removed from the site.</p>
<p>

The Northgate and Fujifilm buildings were closest to the blast, although the surrounding Catherine House (to the north), Keystone Distribution building (to the west), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/35503.xml">
3Com Corporation</link> and RO buildings (to the south), were also extensively damaged.  As a result of the destruction of the equipment in the Northgate building several websites it hosts were inaccessible—including that of the <party wordnetid="108256968" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/19279158.xml">
Labour Party</link></party>
. <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/485606.xml">
Addenbrooke's Hospital</link></hospital>
 in Cambridge was also affected with the IT system dealing with admissions and discharges needing to be replaced for several days by a manual system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Local criticism</st>
<p>

Criticism was expressed by local citizens and the local MP that originally the depot had been constructed away from other buildings, but that <bubble wordnetid="109229709" confidence="0.8">
<ball wordnetid="113899404" confidence="0.8">
<globule wordnetid="109289709" confidence="0.8">
<sphere wordnetid="113899200" confidence="0.8">
<round_shape wordnetid="113865483" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/1465584.xml">
developmental pressures</link></shape>
</round_shape>
</sphere>
</globule>
</ball>
</bubble>
 had led to both houses and commercial premises being built near the depot.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Legal action</st>
<p>

A total of 2,700 claims have been filed by residents, businesses and insurers. 
A group of 146 claimants are hoping to bring a class action against Hertfordshire Oil Storage Ltd. On 17 March 2006 a High Court official, Senior Master Turner, adjourned a hearing on whether to permit the class action until October 2006.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Groundwater pollution</st>
<p>

In May 2006 <water_company wordnetid="108186546" confidence="0.8">
<utility wordnetid="108185758" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="108186047" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/8317485.xml">
Three Valleys Water</link></institution>
</service>
</company>
</utility>
</water_company>
 announced that it had detected the fire retardant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/824704.xml">
perfluorooctane sulfonate</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/824704.xml">
PFOS</link>), used in fire fighting foam, in a ground water bore hole close to the Buncefield site. It stated that no water from this well entered the public water supply and that a nearby well and pumping station had been closed since the fire as a precaution. The chemical is a known health risk and the UK government had been about to ban its use. However just before the announcement, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/3018846.xml">
Drinking Water Inspectorate</link> announced that it was increasing the safe level of the chemical in drinking water. Hemel Hempstead MP, <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<soldier wordnetid="110622053" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<enlisted_person wordnetid="110058777" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/1867366.xml">
Mike Penning</link></enlisted_person>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</person>
</soldier>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
 accused the government of changing the rules to suit the situation in which PFOS levels in drinking water in the area may rise in the future.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Inquiry</st>
<p>

A government inquiry held jointly by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/361308.xml">
Health and Safety Executive</link> (HSE) and the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/529059.xml">
Environment Agency</link></administration>
</group>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
</social_group>
</body>
 was started, but calls for a full public enquiry were declined.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> The Board included <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/415813.xml">
Lord Newton of Braintree</link>, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/12960657.xml">
Prof Dougal Drysdale</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, an authority on fire safety and Dr Peter Baxter, a medical expert. Environment Agency and HSE staff were also on the board. Its aim was to identify the immediate causes of the explosion, rather than consider who was to blame for any deficiencies, so as not to prejudice further legal proceedings. An initial progress report by the Major Incident Investigation Board on 21 February 2006 did not go into the causes of the explosion, but summed up the event and the immediate reaction from the emergency services.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> A second progress report, published 11 April 2006, looked at the environmental impact.</p>
<p>

A further announcement was made on 9 May 2006 about the sequence of events which caused the explosion.  Starting at 19:00 on the evening of 10 December Tank 912, towards the north west of the main depot, was filled with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/23639.xml">
unleaded petrol</link>. At midnight the terminal closed, and a check was made of the contents of tanks which found everything normal. From about 03:00 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/4023295.xml">
level gauge</link> for Tank 912 began indicating an unchanging level reading, despite filling continuing at 550 cubic metres per hour (19,500 cu ft per hour). Calculations show that the tank would have begun to overflow at about 05:20. 40 minutes later, an estimated 300 tonnes of petrol would have spilled down the side of the tank onto the ground inside <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../953/3755953.xml">
bund</link> wall A</it> - a semi-enclosed compound surrounding several tanks. There is evidence suggesting that a high level switch, which should have detected that the tank was full and shut off the supply, failed to operate.  CCTV footage shows a cloud of vapour 1 to 2 metres (3 to 7 feet) deep flowing away from the tank. By 06:01, when the first explosion occurred, the cloud had spread beyond the boundaries of the site.</p>
<p>

The extent of the damage meant it was not possible to determine the exact source of ignition, but possibilities include an emergency <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/82330.xml">
generator</link></invention>
 and the depot's fire pump system. The investigators did not believe that it was caused either by the driver of a fuel tanker, as had been speculated, or by anyone using a mobile phone. It was felt unlikely that the explosion had a widespread effect on air quality at ground level.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Responsibility and legal claims</st>
<p>

On 23 May 2008 a <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<assembly wordnetid="108163792" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<court wordnetid="108329453" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/572602.xml">
High Court</link></group>
</court>
</gathering>
</assembly>
</social_group>
 judge ruled that <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/804161.xml">
Total</link></company>
 UK was negligent over the cause of the explosion. Mr Justice David Steel issued a summary judgment after hearing that both Total and <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<terminal wordnetid="104412901" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<station wordnetid="104306080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/3384290.xml">
Hertfordshire Oil Storage Ltd</link></station>
</facility>
</terminal>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 (HOSL) had agreed that negligence was the cause. Total UK claimed that the duty supervisor at the time was responsible for the explosion, but refused to admit either civil or criminal liability for the incident.  Claimants, include insurance companies, small businesses and about 280 families whose properties were damaged or destroyed, are claiming up to £1 billion in damages.  Total UK intends to argue that it should not be liable for damages because it could not reasonably have foreseen that it would cause the destruction it did. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The terminal</st>
<p>

<image width="200px" src="Northgate_Arial_Photo.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Aerial photograph showing the Northgate building (centre) and the Fujifilm building (upper centre), both of which were so badly damaged that they have since been demolished and entirely removed.  Some of the oil tanks are visible at the right of the photograph.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<terminal wordnetid="104412901" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<station wordnetid="104306080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/3384290.xml">
Hertfordshire Oil Storage Terminal</link></station>
</facility>
</terminal>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
</it>
</indent>
The <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<terminal wordnetid="104412901" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<station wordnetid="104306080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/3384290.xml">
Hertfordshire Oil Storage Terminal</link></station>
</facility>
</terminal>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 (HOSL - Hertfordshire Oil Storage Ltd), generally known as the Buncefield complex, was the fifth largest oil-products storage depot in the UK, with a capacity of about 60 million <link>
Imperial gallon</link>s (273 million litres) of fuel, although it was not always filled. This was about 5% of UK oil storage capacity. It was a major hub on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/3385509.xml">
UK's oil pipeline network</link> (UKOP) with pipelines to <subdivision wordnetid="108674251" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/338683.xml">
Humberside</link></subdivision>
 and <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/151325.xml">
Merseyside</link></county>
 and is an important fuel source to the British aviation industry, providing aircraft fuel for local airports including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/101359.xml">
London Gatwick</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ter/Joseph_F$orce_C$rater.xml">
London Heathrow</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/206934.xml">
Luton</link> airports. About half of the complex is dedicated to the storage of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/642298.xml">
aviation fuel</link>. The remainder of the complex stores <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/23639.xml">
petrol</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/81761.xml">
diesel</link> fuel for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/61260.xml">
petrol station</link>s across much of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/52926.xml">
South-East</link> of England. The terminal is owned by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/804161.xml">
TOTAL UK Limited</link></company>
 (60%) and <oil_company wordnetid="108069241" confidence="0.8">
<name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/59224.xml">
Texaco</link></institution>
</language_unit>
</part>
</trade_name>
</company>
</name>
</oil_company>
 40%.</p>
<p>

The seat of the fire, and the worst damaged section, was "HOSL West", used by Total and Texaco to store a variety of fuels, and the neighbouring <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/3407129.xml">
British Pipeline Agency</link></institution>
</company>
 area.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Initial speculation on causes</st>
<p>

The police issued a statement saying that they were treating the incident as an accident as opposed to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/19522363.xml">
terrorist attack</link>. Rumours of a deliberate attack, in the form of an aeroplane deliberately crashed into the site, spread in the initial aftermath of the explosion because of the distinctive noise the event made. They may have been given some credence because of the proximity of Luton airport to the site of the incident, and the fact that numerous flight paths crisscross the area.</p>
<p>

Italian television stations early on the morning of the fire described the event as a possible terrorist attack and went to the extent of showing features on the <terrorist_attack wordnetid="101246697" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/2185939.xml">
July 2005 terrorist bombings</link></terrorist_attack>
. Speculation about the possible terrorist nature of the blasts was prompted by the fact that a videotape allegedly released by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/1921.xml">
al-Qaeda</link> four days previously had called for attacks on fuel depots and refineries containing oil "stolen" from Muslim countries.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> However, the cause of the blasts will likely not be known until a full investigation is completed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>
<p>

An oil industry specialist speculated on <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<announcement wordnetid="106746580" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106748466" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/1139893.xml">
BBC News</link></program>
</announcement>
</message>
</statement>
 that a vapour leak could have built up to explosive concentrations because of the ground frost in the area keeping vapour concentration at ground level. This would have resulted in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/31418.xml">
fuel-air explosion</link>. It is industry practice for detection systems to be in place to reveal leakages. In order for this scenario to be fulfilled, there must have been a leakage that was not picked up by the leak detection system.</p>
<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/4621.xml">
BBC News 24</link> interview with a petrol tanker driver, who was about to load his tanker at 06:00, reported a cloud of mist rolling in from the tank farm area behind the loading bay. All electric lights were turned off and they were ordered to leave the site on foot. As he was doing so, the blast blew him off his feet. In another interview, a security guard in a nearby office building reported an unusual smell of petrol inside his building before the explosion. Hertfordshire police reported speaking to a tanker driver concerned that switching the engine cut-off on his tanker might have triggered the explosion.</p>
<p>

Other safety experts spoke of a known "weekend effect" in industry, in which weekend maintenance creates an unsafe condition.</p>
<p>

A retired military explosives safety officer submitted a published paper on the explosion to the HSE inquiry.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>  The paper was intended to help those who lived close to petrol storage depots and who were worried about the risks they faced.  It contained different views from those of other experts whose opinions had been voiced publicly.  It was critical of the HSE's general safety culture.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
One year on</st>
<p>

An anniversary service was held in <link>
Holy Trinity Church Leverstock Green</link> on Sunday the 10th of December at which the Bishop of St Albans spoke, calling again for a full public inquiry, for assurances that the local hospital would maintain its accident and emergency department, and for the community to continue to build on good relationships formed because of the blast.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4752819.stm">
Buncefield tank 'was overflowing'</weblink>", BBC News.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-06-05</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/4521232.stm">
Can sound really travel 200 miles?</weblink>", BBC News.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-13</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/1390040.xml">
British Geological Survey</link></company>
.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.earthquakes.bgs.ac.uk/recent_events/20051211060131.2.html">
EXPL-HEMEL HEMPSTEAD</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-11</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
FRSonline.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.frsonline.fire.gov.uk/resilience/article/51/443">
High Volume Pumps at Buncefield</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-06-30</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4518500.stm">
Smoke cloud spreading over South</weblink>", BBC News.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-11</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zaman.com/?bl=hotnews&amp;alt=&amp;trh=20051212&amp;hn=27449">
Smoke of British Oil Depot Fire Reaches France</weblink>", Anadolu News Agency.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-12</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<council wordnetid="108310949" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/816406.xml">
Natural Environment Research Council</link></council>
</administrative_unit>
.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nerc.ac.uk/publications/latestpressrelease/2005-58oil.asp">
Oil depot explosion</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-12</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Natural Environment Research Council.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nerc.ac.uk/publications/latestpressrelease/2005_58oil.asp">
Oil depot explosion - update</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-14</link>.</entry>
<entry id="9">
<county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/13986.xml">
Hertfordshire County Council</link></county>
.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hertsdirect.org.uk">
Buncefield Depot Explosion – services affected</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-13</link>.</entry>
<entry id="10">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.luton.gov.uk/internet/references/news/news%20archive/2005%20news%20releases/december%202005/Schools%20in%20Luton%20to%20clos">
Luton schools re-open</weblink>".&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/9524004.xml">
Luton Borough Council</link>&#32;(<link>
2005-12-13</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-16</link>.</entry>
<entry id="11">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/4534014.stm">
Oil fire leads to plane pitstops</weblink>", BBC News.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/cambridgeshire/4521608.stm">
Oil blaze hits hospital systems</weblink>", BBC News.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-12</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/beds/bucks/herts/4816058.stm">
Buncefield victims in court move</weblink>", BBC News&#32;(<link>
2006-03-17</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hemelhempsteadtoday.co.uk/mk4custompages/CustomPage.aspx?pageID=58601">
Report on the Buncefield Investigation reports of May 06</weblink>".&#32;  Hemelhempstead Today&#32;(2007-05).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-16</link>.</entry>
<entry id="15">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prnewswire.co.uk/cgi/news/release?id=161759">
Buncefield Victims Criticise Cover Up</weblink>", PR Newswire&#32;(<link>
2006-01-12</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.edie.net/news/news_story.asp?id=11110&amp;channel=0">
Questions still unanswered in Buncefield probe</weblink>", Edie News Center&#32;(<link>
2006-02-22</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/beds/bucks/herts/4734838.stm">
Delayed Buncefield findings due</weblink>", BBC News&#32;(<link>
2006-02-21</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="19">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.forbes.com/business/energy/feeds/ap/2005/12/11/ap2383564.html">
UK Police Say Fuel Blasts an Accident</weblink>", Forbes.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2005-12-11</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
Alex Spence and Michael Herman&#32;(2008-05-23).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://business.timesonline.co.uk/tol/business/law/article3993400.ece">
Total negligent over blast at Buncefield</weblink>", <it><newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/39127.xml">
The Times</link></newspaper>
</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-12</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="21">
Robert Willcox.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.explosafety.homecall.co.uk/Vapour%20Explosions.pdf">
Vapour Explosions</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-06-20</link>.</entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/2005/dec/14/buncefieldfueldepotfire2005.guardianletters">
Letters: A black cloud over Buncefield | UK news | The Guardian</weblink></entry>
<entry id="22">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stalbans.anglican.org/news/2006/buncefield06.htm">
Hemel remembers Buncefield one year on</weblink>".&#32;  St Albans Diocese.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-16</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sceptre Fundraising Team&#32;(2006). The Buncefield Explosion.&#32;Sceptre Education. ISBN 0-9552759-0-3.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.buncefieldinvestigation.gov.uk/reports/initialreport.pdf">
Initial Report</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).&#32;  Buncefield Major Incident Investigation Board&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/15878.xml">
13 July</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="45px" src="Wikinews-logo.svg">

</image>

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/1173018.xml">
Wikinews</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</group>
</property>
</undertaking>
</community>
</gathering>
</event>
</possession>
</social_group>
</work>
 has related news:
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.buncefieldinvestigation.gov.uk/index.htm">
The Buncefield Investigation</weblink> Official government enquiry.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.herts.police.uk/about/buncefield_incident.htm">
Hertfordshire Constabulary</weblink> Aerial photographs of the fire in progress.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.total.gb.com/media/mediatool.cfm?page=home">
Buncefield Terminal Incident</weblink> Pages on the Total UK website.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4517962.stm">
BBC article Massive blaze rages at fuel depot</weblink>", BBC News&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/8633.xml">
12 December</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>).&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sky.com/skynews/article/0,,30000-1205711,00.html">
Fire Rages After Blasts At Oil Depot</weblink>", Sky News&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/8396.xml">
11 December</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>).&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hemelhempsteadtoday.co.uk/newsfront.aspx?sectionid=841&amp;moreover=news">
Hemel Today News</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rte.ie/news/2005/1211/hertfords.html">
Fire at Hertfordshire oil depot is contained</weblink>", RTÉ News&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/8396.xml">
11 December</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>).&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rte.ie/news/2005/1213/buncefield.html">
Buncefield oil depot fires extinguished</weblink>", RTÉ News&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8852.xml">
13 December</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>).&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.earthquakes.bgs.ac.uk/recent_events/world_special/alert_info.htm">
British Geological Survey seismic alert for this event</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/file_on_4/4709666.stm">
Buncefield parallels drawn abroad</weblink>", BBC News&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/10882.xml">
14 February</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>).&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://homepage.ntlworld.com/alan-turnbull/secret2.htm#buncefield">
New high resolution aerial photo (January 2006) of aftermath at Buncefield depot</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.multimap.com/map/photo.cgi?client=public&amp;x=508725&amp;y=208414&amp;scale=10000">
Aerial photo</weblink> of the Buncefield terminal. Other <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rhaworth.myby.co.uk/oscoor_a.htm?TL087084_region:GB_scale:25000">
map and aerial photo sources</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bbs.keyhole.com/ubb/showthreaded.php?Cat=0&amp;Board=currentEvents&amp;Number=229722&amp;fpart=&amp;PHPSESSID=">
Google Earth Placemark</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.merrymedia.co.uk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=814&amp;Itemid=62">
Media Coverage of Fire</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hemelhempsteadtoday.co.uk/mk4custompages/CustomPage.aspx?PageID=55070">
Local newspaper's reader photos</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jonrb.com/photo/Fujifilm/index.html">
Photographs of Fujifilm's offices by a freelancer working there at the time</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/48361.xml">
Coordinates</link>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stable.toolserver.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=2005_Hertfordshire_Oil_Storage_Terminal_fire&amp;params=51_45_49_N_0_25_26_W_">
51°45′49″N 0°25′26″W﻿ / ﻿51.76361, -0.42389</weblink></p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</psychological_feature>
</discharge>
</act>
</explosion>
</event>
</nonaccomplishment>
</misfortune>
</failure>
</fire>
</fortune>
</catastrophe>
</adversity>
</state>
</happening>
</condition>
</article>
