<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:23:33[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Triage tag</title>
<id>3393904</id>
<revision>
<id>212526193</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-15T03:45:55Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Triage</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(April 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<image location="right" width="150px" src="Deconference-2002-triage-tag.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Typical triage tag used for emergency mass casualty <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/1004399.xml">
decontamination</link>.
</caption>
</image>

<b>Triage Tags</b> is a tool first responders and medical personnel use during a mass casualty incident i.e., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/30919.xml">
triage</link>. With the aide of the triage tags, the first-arriving personnel are able to effectively and efficiently distribute the limited resources and provide the necessary immediate care for the victims until more help arrives. The concept behind triage tags was first introduced by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/1233162.xml">
Baron Dominique Jean Larrey</link></scientist>
, a French surgeon in <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<emperor wordnetid="110053004" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/69880.xml">
Napoleon’s</link></emperor>
</person>
 army.  Simple Triage and Rapid Treatment (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/3407633.xml">
START</link>) is a strategy that the first responders and medical personnel employ to evaluate the severity of injury of each victim as quickly as possible and tag the victims in about 30-60 seconds. The triage tags are placed near the head and are used to better separate the victims so that when more help arrives, the patients are easily recognizable for the extra help to ascertain the most dire cases.  
<sec>
<st>
Design</st>
<p>

A triage tag is two-sided, but the actual layout of the sections vary between states and between governmental agencies. It is common nowadays to use triage tags to allow first responders to have a better handle of the victims during a triage. There is not a universal agreement in the design of a triage tag, so each state has implemented their own version to meet their needs. The example Triage Tag shown to the right is the All Risk(R) Triage Tag manufactured by Disaster Management Systems (DMS) located in Pomona, California. This triage tag is manufactured using synthetic paper to enable decontamination. It is the standard tag of several states including Florida and California. A military version using the terms "EXPECTANT" instead of "MORGUE" and "MINIMAL" rather than "MINOR" is also available.</p>
<p>

The design of a triage tag could be as simple as the METTAG MT-137, which the military and many governmental agencies use.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Dynamic Triage Tag</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="SmartTag_TriageTag.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

SmartTag
</caption>
</image>

Another popular Triage Tag is the Smart Tag with its unique folded design means that effective triage is quick and simple, but most importantly it allows casualties to be re-triaged without having to replace the tag. It has been adopted as the standard triage tag for New York, Connecticut, Philadelphia, Boston and Nevada.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Standard Sections Of A Triage Tag</st>
<p>

The basic sections of a triage tag include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The four colors of triage and they come in the form of:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Black (Deceased) which entails no care needed</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Red (Immediate) which entails life threatening injuries</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Yellow (Delayed) which entails non-life threatening injuries</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Green: (Minor) which entails minor injuries</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A section informing medical personnel of the patient’s vital signs along with the treatment administered.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A section on the patient’s demographics i.e., gender, residential address, etc. and the patient’s medical history.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A section with a full pictorial view of the human body. The medical personnel indicates which parts of the body are injured.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Categories</st>
<p>

There are three basic categories of a triage tag (from top-to-bottom):
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 tear off sections to label the victim properly in terms of severity of injury and to inform other medical personnel, that may arrive later, of the victim’s status.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 main body for the first responders to fill out during their assessment of the patient. This portion will stay with the patient. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 peel off stickers to keep a record of what transportation or treatment was provided to the victim.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Benefits</st>
<p>

A benefit in using the triage tag, besides the fact of improving traffic flow and increasing distributed care among injured patients is during the collection of data. The fill-in slots on the triage tags do not need to be filled out all at once. Information can be obtained and added onto the triage tag throughout the triage. There are cases which a patient’s medical condition changes while still in triage, medical personnel would just tag the patient again with the updated information and label the tags sequentially. </p>
<p>

The other option is to use a tag which can be altered and where the priority can go up or down. This eliminates the need to re-tag the patient. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Examples of types</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The military uses the MT-137 design while Maryland and New Jersey use their customized version.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The(<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mettag.com">
METTAG Medical Emergency Triage Tags</weblink>) was developed in the early 1970s and is widely used among the U.S. military, federal, state, and local agencies, and others.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Another example of a triage tags is the dynamic folding tag Smart Tag from TSG Associates. This was adopted by the State of NY in 2004, the British Military in 2002, used by London Ambulance Service in the terrorist bombings of 2005 and used by the combined forces Afghanistan in 2006. An older style dynamic card is the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spservices.co.uk/product_info.php/products_id/550">
"Cruciform"</weblink>, used in parts of the UK including some of the North Sea oil industry and used by the Royal London Hospital during the London bombings in 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

New York, Philadelphia, Boston and Nevada have chosen the Smart Tag with its folded design means that effective triage is quick and simple.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The States of Connecticut and Massachusetts also mandated the Smart Tag for state wide use.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Maryland has a more detailed customized design of a triage tag</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

New Jersey also has a more detailed customized design</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/7061.xml">
Community Emergency Response Team</link></organization>
s carry color-coded <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/9972860.xml">
flagging tape</link> for triage use.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ris/5th_arrondissement_of_P$aris.xml">
Emergency Medical Technician</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/500273.xml">
First responders</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/384064.xml">
Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act</link> (HIPAA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/1027461.xml">
MSEHPA</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/1661968.xml">
Client confidentiality</link></entry>
</list>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>


</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.triagetags.com/c-6-all-risk-triage-tags.aspx</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.disastermanagementsystems.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.emedicine.com/emerg/topic670.htm</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tsgassociates.co.uk/English/Civilian/products/smart_tag.htm">
Smart Tag</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.state.nj.us/health/ems/documents/njdisastertag.pdf</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.miemss.umaryland.edu/MDTriage.pdf</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
