<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:37:56[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>WordNet</title>
<id>33955</id>
<revision>
<id>244070617</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T05:15:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Velho</username>
<id>158002</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Dictionaries</category>
<category>Computational linguistics</category>
<category>Knowledge representation</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>WordNet</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/3663597.xml">
semantic lexicon</link> for the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English language</link></language>
. It groups English words into sets of synonyms called <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/3553110.xml">
synsets</link></it>, provides short, general definitions, and records the various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantic</link> relations between these <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/67396.xml">
synonym</link> sets. The purpose is twofold: to produce a combination of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/7931.xml">
dictionary</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/30334.xml">
thesaurus</link> that is more intuitively usable, and to support automatic text analysis and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link> applications. The database and software tools have been released under a <link>
BSD style license</link> and can be downloaded and used freely. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> can also be browsed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/41440.xml">
online</link>.<p>

WordNet was created and is being maintained at the Cognitive Science Laboratory of <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/23922.xml">
Princeton University</link></university>
 under the direction of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
psychology</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/19360771.xml">
professor</link> <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/387853.xml">
George A. Miller</link></scientist>
</person>
. Development began in 1985. Over the years, the project received about $3 million of funding, mainly from government agencies interested in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/19980.xml">
machine translation</link>.  In recent years, Dr. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<compiler wordnetid="109946957" confidence="0.8">
<lexicographer wordnetid="110256080" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<linguist wordnetid="110264437" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/7970570.xml">
Christiane Fellbaum</link></linguist>
</writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</lexicographer>
</compiler>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 has overseen the development of WordNet.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Database contents </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/1292458.xml">
As of 2006</link>, the database contains about 150,000 words organized in over 115,000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/3553110.xml">
synsets</link> for a total of 207,000 word-sense pairs; in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/8013.xml">
compressed</link> form, it is about 12 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/19918.xml">
megabyte</link>s in size.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

WordNet distinguishes between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/37495.xml">
noun</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/37354.xml">
verb</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/37512.xml">
adjective</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/37513.xml">
adverb</link>s because they follow different grammatical rules. Every synset contains a group of synonymous words or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/435356.xml">
collocation</link>s (a <it>collocation</it> is a sequence of words that go together to form a specific meaning, such as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/383038.xml">
car pool</link>"); different senses of a word are in different synsets. The meaning of the synsets is further clarified  with short defining <it>glosses</it> (Definitions and/or example sentences). A typical example synset with gloss is:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 good, right, ripe -- (most suitable or right for a particular purpose; "a good time to plant tomatoes"; "the right time to act"; "the time is ripe for great sociological changes")
</indent>

Most synsets are connected to other synsets via a number of semantic relations. These relations vary based on the type of word, and include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/37495.xml">
Noun</link>s</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/155337.xml">
hypernym</link>s</it>: <it>Y</it> is a hypernym of <it>X</it> if every <it>X</it> is a (kind of) <it>Y</it> (<it>canine</it> is a hypernym of <it>dog</it>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/155337.xml">
hyponym</link>s</it>: <it>Y</it> is a hyponym of <it>X</it> if every <it>Y</it> is a (kind of) <it>X</it> (<it>dog</it> is a hyponym of <it>canine</it>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>coordinate terms</it>: <it>Y</it> is a coordinate term of <it>X</it> if <it>X</it> and <it>Y</it> share a hypernym (<it>wolf</it> is a coordinate term of <it>dog</it>, and <it>dog</it> is a coordinate term of <it>wolf</it>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/826496.xml">
holonym</link></it>: <it>Y</it> is a holonym of <it>X</it> if <it>X</it> is a part of <it>Y</it> (<it>building</it> is a holonym of <it>window</it>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/245986.xml">
meronym</link></it>: <it>Y</it> is a meronym of <it>X</it> if <it>Y</it> is a part of <it>X</it> (<it>window</it> is a meronym of <it>building</it>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/37354.xml">
Verb</link>s</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>hypernym</it>: the verb <it>Y</it> is a hypernym of the verb <it>X</it> if the activity <it>X</it> is a (kind of) <it>Y</it> (<it>travel</it> is an hypernym of <it>movement</it>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>troponym</it>: the verb <it>Y</it> is a troponym of the verb <it>X</it> if the activity <it>Y</it> is doing <it>X</it> in some manner (<it>to lisp</it> is a troponym of <it>to talk</it>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>entailment</it>: the verb <it>Y</it> is entailed by <it>X</it> if by doing <it>X</it> you must be doing <it>Y</it> (<it>to sleep</it> is entailed by <it>to snore</it>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>coordinate terms</it>: those verbs sharing a common hypernym (<it>to lisp</it> and <it>to yell</it>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/37512.xml">
Adjective</link>s</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>related nouns''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>similar to''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>participle of verb''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/37513.xml">
Adverb</link>s</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>root adjectives''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

While semantic relations apply to all members of a synset because they share a meaning but are all mutually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/67396.xml">
synonym</link>s, words can also be connected to other words through lexical relations, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/147930.xml">
antonym</link>s (opposites of each other) and derivationally related, as well.</p>
<p>

WordNet also provides the <it>polysemy count</it> of a word: the number of synsets that contain the word. If a word participates in several synsets (i.e. has several senses) then typically some senses are much more common than others. WordNet quantifies this by the <it>frequency score</it>: in which several sample texts have all words semantically tagged with the corresponding synset, and then a count provided indicating how often a word appears in a specific sense.</p>
<p>

The morphology functions of the software distributed with the database try to deduce the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/2639048.xml">
lemma</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/264211.xml">
root</link> form of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/1449866.xml">
word</link> from the user's input; only the root form is stored in the database unless it has irregular inflected forms.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Knowledge structure </st>
<p>

Both nouns and verbs are organized into hierarchies, defined by hypernym or <it>IS A</it> relationships. For instance, the first sense of the word <it>dog</it> would have the following hypernym hierarchy; the words at the same level are synonyms of each other: some sense of <it>dog</it> is synonymous with some other senses of <it>domestic dog</it> and <it>Canis familiaris</it>, and so on. Each set of synonyms (<it>synset</it>),  has a unique index and shares its properties, such as a gloss (or dictionary) definition.</p>
<p>

dog, domestic dog, Canis familiaris
=&amp;gt; canine, canid
=&amp;gt; carnivore
=&amp;gt; placental, placental mammal, eutherian, eutherian mammal
=&amp;gt; mammal
=&amp;gt; vertebrate, craniate
=&amp;gt; chordate
=&amp;gt; animal, animate being, beast, brute, creature, fauna
=&amp;gt; ...</p>
<p>

At the top level, these hierarchies are organized into <link>
base types</link>, 25 primitive groups for nouns, and 15 for verbs. These groups form <it>lexicographic files</it> at a maintenance level.  These primitive groups are connected to an abstract root node that has, for some time, been assumed by various applications that use WordNet.</p>
<p>

In the case of adjectives, the organization is different. Two opposite 'head' senses work as binary poles, while 'satellite' synonyms connect to each of the heads via synonymy relations. Thus, the hierarchies, and the concept involved with lexicographic files, do not apply here the same way they do for nouns and verbs.</p>
<p>

The network of nouns is far deeper than that of the other parts of speech.  Verbs have a far <it>bushier</it> structure, and adjectives are organized into many distinct clusters.  Adverbs are defined in terms of the adjectives they are derived from, and thus inherit their structure from that of the adjectives.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Psychological justification </st>

<p>

The goal of WordNet was to develop a system that would be consistent with the knowledge acquired over the years about how human beings process language.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/324918.xml">
Anomic aphasia</link>, for example, creates a condition that seems to selectively encumber individuals' ability to name objects; this makes the decision to partition the parts of speech into distinct hierarchies more of a principled decision than an arbitrary one.  </p>
<p>

In the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/155337.xml">
hyponym</link>y, psychological experiments revealed that individuals can access properties of nouns more quickly depending on when a characteristic becomes a defining property.  That is, individuals can quickly verify that <it>canaries can sing</it> because a canary is a songbird (only one level of hyponymy), but requires slightly more time to verify that <it>canaries can fly</it> (two levels of hyponymy) and even more time to verify <it>canaries have skin</it> (multiple levels of hyponymy).  This suggests that  we too store semantic information in a way that is much like WordNet, because we only retain the most specific information needed to differentiate one particular concept from similar concepts.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 WordNet as an ontology </st>

<p>

The hypernym/hyponym relationships among the noun synsets can be interpreted as specialization relations between conceptual categories. In other words, WordNet can be interpreted and used as a lexical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/49681.xml">
ontology</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link> sense. However, such an ontology should normally be corrected before being used since it contains hundreds of basic semantic inconsistencies such as (i) the existence of common specializations for exclusive categories and (ii) redundancies in the specialization hierarchy. Furthermore, transforming WordNet into a lexical ontology usable for knowledge representation should normally also involve (i)&nbsp;distinguishing the specialization relations into subtypeOf and instanceOf relations, and (ii)&nbsp;associating intuitive unique identifiers to each category. Although such corrections and transformations have been performed and documented as part of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.webkb.org/doc/wn/">
integration of WordNet&nbsp;1.7 into the cooperatively updatable knowledge base of WebKB-2</weblink>, most projects claiming to re-use WordNet for knowledge-based applications (typically, knowledge-oriented information retrieval) simply re-use it directly.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Limitations </st>

<p>

Unlike other dictionaries, WordNet does not include information about <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/888207.xml">
etymology</link>, pronunciation and the forms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/190196.xml">
irregular verb</link>s and contains only limited information about usage.</p>
<p>

The actual lexicographical and semantical information is maintained in <it>lexicographer files</it>, which are then processed by a tool called <it>grind</it> to produce the distributed database. Both grind and the lexicographer files are freely available in a separate distribution, but modifying and maintaining the database requires expertise.</p>
<p>

Though WordNet contains a sufficiently wide range of common words, it does not cover special domain vocabulary. Since it is primarily designed to act as an underlying database for different applications, those applications cannot be used in specific domains that are not covered by WordNet.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Applications in Information Systems </st>

<p>

WordNet has been used for a number of different purposes in information systems, including word sense disambiguation, information retrieval, automatic text classification, automatic text summarization, and even automatic crossword puzzle generation.</p>
<p>

A project at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/4157.xml">
Brown University</link></university>
 started by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/6351448.xml">
Jeff Stibel</link></scholar>
</head>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</administrator>
</leader>
</person>
</executive>
</physical_entity>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/6421364.xml">
James A. Anderson</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <link>
Steve Reiss</link> and others called <link>
Applied Cognition Lab</link> created a disambiguator using WordNet in 1998.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  The project later morphed into a company called <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/6087782.xml">
Simpli</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
, which is now owned by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/962708.xml">
ValueClick</link></institution>
</company>
. George Miller joined the Company as a member of the Advisory Board.  Simpli built an Internet search engine that utilized a knowledge base principally based on WordNet to disambiguate and expand keywords and synsets to help retrieve information online.  WordNet was expanded upon to add increased dimensionality, such as intentionality (used for x), people (<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/736.xml">
Albert Einstein</link></scientist>
</person>
) and colloquial terminology more relevant to Internet search (i.e., blogging, ecommerce).   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/1729542.xml">
Neural network</link> algorithms searched the expanded WordNet for related terms to disambiguate search keywords (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/16527.xml">
Java</link>, in the sense of coffee) and expand the search synset (Coffee, Drink, Joe) to improve search engine results.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>   Before the company was acquired, it performed searches across search engines such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo</link>!, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/429624.xml">
Ask.com</link></company>
 and others.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Another prominent example of the use of WordNet is to determine the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/1473135.xml">
similarity</link> between words. Various algorithms have been proposed, and these include considering the distance between the conceptual categories of words, as well as considering the hierarchical structure of the WordNet ontology. A number of these WordNet-based word similarity algorithms are implemented in a <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/23939.xml">
Perl</link></programming_language>
 package called <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.d.umn.edu/~tpederse/similarity.html">
WordNet::Similarity</weblink>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Interfaces </st>

<p>

Princeton maintains a list of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wordnet.princeton.edu/links">
related projects</weblink> that includes links to some of the widely used <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
application programming interface</link>s available for accessing WordNet using various programming languages and environments.</p>
<p>

Other interfaces include the following:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.defineitfast.com/find/">
WordNet on Ajax::DefineItFast.com</weblink> allows users to browse Wordnet 3.0 using an <word wordnetid="106286395" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<neologism wordnetid="106294441" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/1610950.xml">
ajax</link></language_unit>
</neologism>
</part>
</word>
 interface.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mfwallace.googlepages.com/jawbone.html">
Jawbone</weblink> project provides a <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
 API to the WordNet 2.1 and 3.0 data.  The source code is released under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/19193.xml">
MIT license</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/">
Natural Language Toolkit</weblink> provides a <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/23862.xml">
Python</link></programming_language>
 API to the WordNet 3.0.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.cpan.org/perldoc?Lingua::Wordnet">
Lingua::Wordnet</weblink> provides a <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/23939.xml">
Perl</link></programming_language>
 interface to WordNet.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.cpan.org/perldoc?WordNet::Similarity">
WordNet::Similarity</weblink> Perl module for computing measures of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/8285409.xml">
semantic relatedness</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cozyenglish.com/dictionary">
Dictionary::CozyEnglish</weblink> implemented a WordNet 3.0 interface that integrates with <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/605856.xml">
WordPress</link></software>
. Blog and website owners can embed this API via a set of HTML code.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.visualthesaurus.com/">
Visual Thesaurus</weblink> is a subscription-based commercial application that presents WordNet data through an innovative and user-friendly interface.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/448573.xml">
WordWeb</link></software>
 is an extended dictionary based on WordNet, also available commercially as <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wordweb.info/developer/SQL.html">
SQL tables</weblink> for use in other applications. Includes many additional terms, derived forms and pronunciations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ug.it.usyd.edu.au/~smer3502/assignment3/form.html">
Visual representation of WordNet</weblink> - interface which attempts to visualise the relations.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Related projects </st>

<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/53885.xml">
EuroWordNet</link> project has produced WordNets for several European languages and linked them together; these are not freely available however. The <link>
Global Wordnet</link> project attempts to coordinate the production and linking of "wordnets" for all languages. <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/48518.xml">
Oxford University Press</link></company>
, the publisher of the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<wordbook wordnetid="106418693" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<dictionary wordnetid="106418901" confidence="0.8">
<reference_book wordnetid="106417598" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/22641.xml">
Oxford English Dictionary</link></publication>
</reference_book>
</dictionary>
</book>
</wordbook>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
, has voiced plans to produce their own online competitor to WordNet.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/11725761.xml">
eXtended WordNet</link> is a project at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/537010.xml">
University of Texas at Dallas</link></university>
 which aims to improve WordNet by semantically parsing the glosses, thus making the information contained in these definitions available for automatic knowledge processing systems. It is also freely available under a license similar to WordNet's.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/649244.xml">
GCIDE</link> project produces a dictionary by combining a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link> <it><hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/158441.xml">
Webster's Dictionary</link></characteristic>
</hallmark>
</it> from 1913 with some WordNet definitions and material provided by volunteers.
It is released under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/18934404.xml">
copyleft</link> license <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GPL</link>.</p>
<p>

WordNet is also commonly re-used via mappings between the WordNet categories and the categories from other ontologies. Most often, only the top-level categories of WordNet are mapped. However, the authors of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/247601.xml">
SUMO</link> ontology have produced a mapping between all of the WordNet synsets, (including nouns, verbs, adjectives and adverbs), and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/247601.xml">
SUMO class</link>es.  The most recent addition of the mappings provides links to all of the more specific terms in the MId-Level Ontology (MILO), which extends SUMO. <link>
OpenCyc</link> has 12,000 terms linked to WordNet synonym sets.</p>
<p>

In most works that claim to have integrated WordNet into other ontologies, the content of WordNet has not simply been corrected when semantic problems have been encountered; instead, WordNet has been used as an inspiration source but heavily re-interpreted and updated whenever suitable. This was the case when, for example, the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/oltramari02restructuring.html">
top-level ontology of WordNet was re-structured</weblink> according to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/10608923.xml">
OntoClean</link> based approach or when WordNet was used as a primary source for constructing the lower classes of the SENSUS ontology.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/2112884.xml">
FrameNet</link> is a project similar to WordNet. It consists of a lexicon which is based on annotating over 100,000 sentences with their semantic properties. The unit in focus is the <it>lexical frame</it>, a type of state or event together with the properties associated with it.</p>
<p>

An independent project titled <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wordnet.cemetech.net">
wordNet</weblink> with an initial lowercase w is an ongoing project to links words and phrases via a custom <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/33120.xml">
Web crawler</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/14907562.xml">
Lexical markup framework</link> (LMF) is a work in progress within <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/11234940.xml">
ISO/TC37</link> in order to define a common standardized framework for the construction of lexicons, including WordNet.</p>
<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ceid.upatras.gr/Balkanet/">
BalkaNet</weblink> project has produced WordNets for six European languages (Bulgarian, Czech, Greek, Romanian, Turkish and Serbian). For this project, freely available XML-based WordNet editor was developed. This editor - <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nlp.fi.muni.cz/projekty/visdic/">
VisDic</weblink> - is not in active development anymore, but is still used for the creation of various WordNets. Its successor, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://deb.fi.muni.cz">
DEBVisDic</weblink>, is client-server application and is currently used for the editing of several WordNets (Dutch in Cornetto project, Polish, Hungarian, several African languages, Chinese).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wordnet.princeton.edu/man/wnstats.7WN">
WNSTATS(7WN) manual page</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
Collins A., Quillian M. R. 1972. "Experiments on Semantic Memory and Language Comprehension" in <it>Cognition in Learning and Memory</it>. Wiley, New York.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.forbes.com/1999/10/04/feat.html">
Forbes article</weblink>".&#32;  Forbes.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.infotoday.com/newsbreaks/nb1220-2.htm">
Info Today Publication</weblink>".&#32;  Info Today.</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0HDN/is_2000_May_25/ai_62332783">
providence Journal Article</weblink>".&#32;  Providence Journal.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
Semantic Web</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/30463.xml">
taxonomy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/3553110.xml">
Synonym Ring</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/6164652.xml">
ThoughtTreasure</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/294441.xml">
Is-a</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/155337.xml">
Hyponym</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Free Download single <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tomeraider.com/ebooks/reference/dictionaries_and_thesauri/english/wordnet_dictionary_ebook--BK634.php">
Wordnet Dictionary</weblink> file for your <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/37545.xml">
Palm OS</link></O>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/69170.xml">
Pocket PC</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/212084.xml">
Tomeraider</link> format.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wordnet.princeton.edu/">
The WordNet Home Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wordnet.princeton.edu/links">
Wordnet Related Projects</weblink> – comprehensive list of interfaces and extensions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.globalwordnet.org/">
Global Wordnet</weblink> + <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://deb.fi.muni.cz/clients-debgrid.php">
DEBGrid</weblink> (Global Wordnet web interface)</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
