<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:23:57[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<possession  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100032613">
<property  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113244109">
<header>
<title>Hell.com</title>
<id>3401521</id>
<revision>
<id>240196461</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-22T10:16:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lobosolo</username>
<id>74014</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Websites</category>
<category>Internet properties established in 1995</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Website</name>
<parameters>
<author>
<link>
Kenneth Aronson</link> (CEO/Founder)</author>
<name>
HELL.COM</name>
<owner>
<link>
BAT Flli LLC</link></owner>
<url>
http://www.hell.com/</url>
</parameters>
</template>




<p>

<b>Hell.com</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link> created on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/1154.xml">
August 2</link>,<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/34658.xml">
1995</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> that serves as "a launching pad for cool designers and leading net.artists."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> It has been known for being quite barren and simple; many media companies, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/30680.xml">
New York Times</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/31600.xml">
TIME</link>, and numerous others, have taken a liking to this site as well as curious visitors and hackers. Due to this, the site has been heavily speculated by some as the frontend for a secretive global group with an unknown purpose, although it could be likely to be no more than a collaboration for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/977463.xml">
net.art</link>. Despite the site's sparseness, it receives thousands of visitors daily.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Layout</st>
<p>

Currently, the main page seemingly comprises a white background with two sentences in the lower center that state "HELL.COM is a private parallel web." and "There is no access via web browser." When the mouse arrow is moved over the center of the page, the whole background turns black, prominently showing a white logo of a circle with a downwards facing arrow inside.</p>
<p>

The logo, when clicked on, takes you to another page that has an all-black background with a Google search box in the middle. Some time ago, the search box reacted when certain "keywords" were entered (e.g. redemption, hell, answer), which would take the visitor to other pages. This search box replaced all other content of most of Hell.com's known pages other than the e-mail login some time ago.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Original layout</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

EDIT* In 1994-1995 - Hell.com only displayed a warning that you were not invited and to go away.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

When the site was first introduced, the site hosted a variety of unique features; ones that gave the site a mysterious, yet intriguing, kind of feeling. In the original design, the index page featured a random aphorism in place of the logo. The aphorism took a visitor to a "links" page that consisted of three links:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"no access"Contains the Hell.com logo that links to:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Disclaimer pageThe writing states that "this is a parallel web. there is no public access. the waiting list is approximately 18-22 months." There are two further links; "apply"- which allows you to enter an email address to send you an email asking for a payment, and "don't"- which closes the window</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"redemption"Contains a red link called "soul redemption program". The link sends the visitor to:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Questions pageA <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/20947.xml">
Flash</link></software>
 page in which hundreds of questions fly towards the user through black space. Clicking one of them provides an "answer." A link to the left reading "Yes" passes onto the Payment page</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Payment pageThis is a set of a few pages whereby, after several warnings that the payment is real, one can fill out a form to donate for a range of amount options from $10 to $10000<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> and later changed to $20, $200 or $2000.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"search"Added on February <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/35187.xml">
8</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>, this link leads to the Search Page (see below)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20060204020810/www.hell.com/l0/xit.html">
Search page</weblink>Contains a seemingly normal Google search box; however, certain "keywords" typed in the box can take you to other pages. Known "keywords" are:</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

<it>redemption</it>Links to Questions Page</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

<it>hell</it>Links to Links Page</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

<it>answer</it>This link first led to a picture of a bald, naked woman falling through darkness. Soon after that, the link sends the user to a "sister site" called <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cygne-noir.com">
cygne-noir.com</weblink>. It is mostly in the same format of Hell.com and acts as a portfolio for <link>
Kenneth Aronson</link>. It used to contain a gallery of sensual female nudes, but now only contains a logo (not the same as Hell.com's logo) and the word "cygne-noir." Some say that this is proof that Aronson is the webmaster of Hell.com: the portfolio describes Aronson as "<it>A conceptual artist who uses photography as part of his process. His digital work has been featured at The Brooklyn Academy of Music, The Absolut LA international, Robert Berman Gallery, Montreal International Film Festival, as well as exhibitions in the UK, France, Italy, Spain, Korea, and Mexico.</it>" According to <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kennetharonson.com/cultural.html">
Aronson's personal site</weblink>, he is the "CEO/ Founder of this parallel network/ [Hell.com] which is considered the enigma of the web", further backing up the notion that Hell.com is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/977463.xml">
net.art</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
E-mail accounts</st>
<p>

A <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hell.com.cybrport.com/@/">
page</weblink> found on Hell.com contains a login screen used for e-mail accounts. Apparently, "@hell.com email accounts are 'given' to patrons who made a donation to the project."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> These "patrons" are people who are on the guestlist up to 2005.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> By paying twenty-five dollars, a person receives a one year e-mail address; those who pay $100 will become a patron for life.</p>
<p>

The e-mail account is "mailPLUS", a high level of service provided by everyone.net. The service consists of "pro SPAM filtering, increased storage space, direct POP3 access to the server, (and) customer support," as well as having a "@hell.com" in the e-mail address itself. It states that "these services are billed directly by them and have nothing to do with HELL.COM."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

By <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>, Hell.com stopped selling e-mail addresses due to "an enormous percentage of delinquent accounts."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Subscription</st>
<p>

It is possible to navigate to a page where you use your <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/17182301.xml">
credit card</link> to pay for a subscription to Hell.com, apparently opening up certain hidden areas and explaining more about what the site is. However you cannot know what you are buying, and it costs $50 initially, followed by an unlimited bill of $10 a month. Furthermore, it explicitly states that discovering what the site is about will take several years, and no answers will ever be given.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Purpose</st>
<p>

According to CEO/Founder Kenneth Aronson,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> Hell.com exists for the purpose of providing a forum for the creation of *ar , or alternative reality.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> He defines that "*ar is the creation of something new. Whereas a virtual reality is an attempt to simulate the real world in virtual space. ar* is something new created in virtual space that becomes a reality in the physical world." Its aims are documented and well known from the site final.org<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/30680.xml">
New York Times</link> article written in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/34647.xml">
1998</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>
<p>

On SweetCucumber.com, Hell.com was described as "a very private and somewhat mysterious place for Net-artists to hang out and create Web-art (or Net-art, as it was called in the late nineties), without being directly visible to the grand public."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

A past version of Hell.com states that: 
HELL.COM is a private non commercial project devoted to establishing an alternative reality. it has absolutely nothing to do with theology, religion, cults, adult content, entertainment, or art. </p>
<p>

HELL.COM is not associated with any business nor organization.
it is supported entirely by a few individuals, its patron members, guest contributions, and the sale of official product.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>


<p>

Hell.com draws its membership from the art, design, programming, and theoretical realms, but is open to those who are willing to explore new possibilities in communication. It also seeks strategic alliances with media labs, universities, individuals and organizations experimenting in media and human communication.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>
<p>

A "sister site" of Hell.com, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bat.hell.com/">
bat.hell.com</weblink> tells:</p>
<p>

HELL.COM is a private parallel network comprised of acknowledged visionaries with diverse skillsets working from 20 nations. Described as the 'bleeding edge of the web' by the <network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/19344654.xml">
BBC</link></network>
, the project has been pushing the boundaries of the internet to discover new levels of human communication.</p>
<p>

&ndash;  <cite >BAT.hell.com text, <it>HELL<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></it></cite></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Relations</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Net.art</st>
<p>

All that can be surmised as to the purpose of the site is that its members, at least partially, are creative designers, specialising in creating sites like Hell.com that are abstract, dark, intractable, but mysterious. They have run at least 2 projects ("surface" and "HL2") where members have anonymously collaborated to create "projects", end-results that are non-informative webpages like Hell.com for people's viewing pleasure (HL2 apparently takes 90 minutes to explore). On this level, Hell.com is an example of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/977463.xml">
net.art</link>. However these creative projects seem to be only one facet of the larger Hell.com group.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Bat. Hell.com</st>
<p>

BAT is described as the "creative thinktank" of Hell.com. It claims to excel in "simple effective solutions", "alternative perspectives" and "extreme ideas".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> As well, under the title "INVISIBLE", BAT states that it works "confidentially as a mercenary resource", apparently for "leading advertising, communications, and technology companies."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Final.org</st>
<p>

On <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kennetharonson.com/cultural.html">
Aronson's Portfolio's "cultural" page</weblink>, a link to the site has been made under the link to Hell.com, being labeled as "overview."</p>
<p>

In May 2006, the layout of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20060514084509/http://hell.com/">
Hell.com's index page</weblink> had similarities to <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://final.org/">
Final.org's</weblink>. They both take on the same structure of word layouts and both share a white background. Moreover, the logo-file of Hell.com is hosted at final.org, which can be seen if one uses the 'view source' option of one's browser.</p>
<p>

It is possible to navigate to further pages including a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/9878372.xml">
User Login</link>. One of these pages includes a FAQ for users, which answers one or two questions about the process of the site. Most notably, these two answers stand out:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In response to a question about spam emails that a user had received:"we share nothing with no one...ever"</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"where can i get more info about HELL.COM?""our goal is to provoke questions...not answer them"</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further known information</st>

<p>

Kenneth Aronson has a MySpace profile<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Events</st>
<p>

Hell.com has hosted four events in the past couple of years:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"s u r f a c e" Opened on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
January 1</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link> and closed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/15791.xml">
January 26</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link>, it was Hell.com's first event<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> and "is a self contained immersive experience of selected content from the projects parallel web." It was a presentation of "the collaborative work by 17 members of the HELL project."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> During the first 48 hours of its release, 0100101110101101.ORG downloaded the site's files and created a copy as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/156327.xml">
anticopyright</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.entropy8zuper.org/skinonskinonskin/againandagainandagain.html">
http://www.entropy8zuper.org/skinonskinonskin/againandagainandagain.html"skinonskinonskin"</weblink> Opened in September 1999, this event is a network installation by Auriea Harvey (Entropy8) and Michael Samyn (Zuper!)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref> The site has a pay-per-view entry, costing eight euros for five days on access and €100 for a lifetime access.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"chaos" Released in November 2000</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://final.org/10llO/">
http://final.org/10llO/"Gateway"</weblink> Opened in 2002, the gateway was an environmental chat project that stopped working in November 2006. The environmental chat was developed by various net artists; among them the artists behind <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.8081.com/">
http://www.8081.com/"8081.com"</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medialounge.org">
http://www.medialounge.org"medialounge.org"</weblink>. The chat itself involves a type of console by which you apparently link to the Hell.com parallel web. You are able to access a number of flash animations by typing certain words known as "keywords" on the grey bar located on the upper left corner of the screen. The animations differ depending on which keyword you type in (for example "seba", "luca" and "anto" which are the names of the artists of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.8081.com/">
http://www.8081.com/"8081.com"</weblink>).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.globalhalo.com/vi/">
did love her"</weblink> is the documented discovery and the reaction that the gateway caused on the guests that explored the environment.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Site alterations</st>
<p>

Every now and then the site's normal set of pages becomes inaccessible to be replaced with some different, usually one-paged frontend. For instance:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Around Christmas of 2005, the site became nothing but links to World Hunger Year and Debt AIDS Trade Africa, with a red-tinted image containing <tradition wordnetid="105809745" confidence="0.8">
<fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.8">
<imaginary_being wordnetid="109483738" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/8720252.xml">
Santa Claus</link></imaginary_being>
</fictional_character>
</tradition>
 and an <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<see wordnetid="108586825" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/5334607.xml">
Africa</link></location>
</seat>
</see>
</area>
</center>
</region>
n boy. There was also an image with the text "Nohell", a presumed reference to <link>
Noël</link> and Christmas. The site's title was "PLEASE", suggesting that the site owner wished one to donate to these organizations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Around March 2006, the frontpage aphorism ceased to be a link, meaning that the site again thus only had one page. Accompanying the aphorism was a Google search box which didn't respond to the standard "keywords" (see above, Site Map - Search page).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Around April 2006, the site underwent a massive change. The front page now presents one with a selection of links which take you to various similar-looking pages filled with adverts and news. It is possible to navigate to the chat zone (see above) directly from the site now. It is not known if these changes are permanent.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

As of June 2006, the + sign at the bottom of the index page takes one to http://final.org, from which can be accessed the chat zone. It is now known that at least some other participants in the chat zone are actual people.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

As of August 2006 accessing the front page produces a non-linked random aphorism.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
0100101110101101.org's version</st>
<p>

Sometime in 1997, the website <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://0100101110101101.org/">
0100101110101101.org</weblink> acquired the webpage code of Hell.com during the first 48 hours of one of its events and created a similar one as "<it>a digital monument to the principles upon which the Internet runs,</it>" and an anticopyright.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> "'The belief that information must be free,'" explained at the time (by) Renato, (a) 0100101110101101.ORG spokesman, 'is a tribute to the way in which a very good computer or a valid program works: binary numbers move in accordance with the most logic, direct and necessary way to do their complex function. What is a computer if not something that benefits by the free flow of information? Copyright is boring.'<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref></p>
<p>

About two hours later, after the acquired code was made into a separate site, an e-mail from Hell.com was sent to 0100101110101101.org in response as well as accusing them of stealing work of Hell.com's members: </p>
<p>

<table style="margin:auto; border-collapse:collapse; border-style:none; background-color:transparent; " class="cquote">
<row>
<col style="color:#B2B7F2;font-size:35px;font-family:'Times New Roman',serif;font-weight:bold;text-align:left;padding:10px 10px;" width="20" valign="top">
“</col>
<col style="padding:4px 10px;" valign="top">
 cute...
please immediately remove this material from your server<p>

you are in violation of international copyright laws which are clearly posted in the copyright information contained in our source code.</p>
<p>

also of note,</p>
<p>

it appears as though you have violated the copyrights of quite a few of our members individually:::::::::::::::</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.0100101110101101.ORG">
http://www.0100101110101101.ORG</weblink>on behalf of these individuals we request that you also remove 
these materials from your server as well<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref></p>
</col>
<col style="color:#B2B7F2;font-size:36px;font-family:'Times New Roman',serif;font-weight:bold;text-align:right;padding:10px 10px;" width="20" valign="bottom">
”</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

In reaction to the questions "So what was the idea behind taking this site?" and "To access a formerly closed system, that was open only to a self-proclaimed elite, and make it
accessible to everybody?" 0100101110101101.org answered that "the feeling that Hell.com was
exactly the opposite of what we think that the web could and should be, but
this is not really our own idea."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref></p>
<p>

In an interview, Aronson stated that "'Anyone can spin this any way they want, but in the final analysis, it is just simple theft. It's a publicity stunt to create awareness for a bunch of people who have no apparent talents.'"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref></p>
<p>

Despite the fact that "HELL.COM has ... threatened legal proceedings for copyright 
violations", the event is still readily available and 0100101110101101.org has not removed the pages from their site.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sale of Hell.com's domain name</st>
<p>

On April <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link> Aronson attempted to sell Hell.com in an auction with an eight million dollar reserve bid,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref> but decided against it.</p>
<p>

In an interview with Domenico Quarenta of the magazine <it>Cluster</it>, Aronson stated that having the most visible address is "negative for us, but has a large value... which could be exchanged for resources to help further the goals of the project." Then, to explain the first sale, he announced that he "held off announcing the sale ... During this time the dot com crash happened and what was worth 8(eight) million became saleable at only a couple of million... so i decided to wait until the market recovered."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref></p>
<p>

Then, on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/22434.xml">
October 27</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>, it was reported in the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/173070.xml">
Wall Street Journal</link></it> that the Hell.com domain name would be sold that day in a live auction by the domain company <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/592817.xml">
Moniker</link>. A one million dollar reserve bid was placed and Kenneth Aronson announced that the proceeds would be used to benefit the hell.com community. However, CNNMoney announced that Hell.com was not bought by any of the bidders even though Aronson said that, "'Branding experts said the name is recognized more than Coca-Cola.'"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rhizome.org/thread.rhiz?thread=621&amp;page=1#1638">
no-such--interview with Kenneth Aronson</weblink>".&#32;  Rhizome.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alexa.com/data/details/main?q=&amp;url=hell.com">
Hell.com</weblink>".&#32;  Alexa Internet, Inc..&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://0100101110101101.org/home/copies/story.html">
Copies story</weblink>".&#32;  0100101110101101.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-04</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alexa.com/data/details/traffic_details?q=&amp;url=hell.com">
Related Info for: hell.com/</weblink>".&#32;  Alexa Internet, Inc..&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-03</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20011214213652/http://hell.com/PAY/soul.html">
HELL.COM BUYBACK</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20041025083006/hell.com/PAY/soul.html">
HELL.COM BUYBACK</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/200406sex12000051/http://www.hell.com/3/vip/@/2.html#w2">
@HELL.COM/Internet Archive</weblink>".&#32;  HELL.COM.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-14</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hell.com.cybrport.com/@/faq.html">
FAQ- mailPLUS</weblink>".&#32;  HELL.COM/everyone.net.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-04</link>.</entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hell.com.cybrport.com/@/faq.html#how">
Hell Mail Faq</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kennetharonson.com/cultural">
kenneth aronson</weblink>".&#32;  Robert Berman, BERMAN/TURNER PROJECTS.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-03</link>.</entry>
<entry id="11">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://final.org/ar/ar.html">
alternative reality ( *ar )</weblink>".&#32;  FINAL.ORG.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-03</link>.</entry>
<entry id="12">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://final.org/ar/HELL.html#3">
reality</weblink>".&#32;  FINAL.ORG.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="13">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://final.org/ar/HELL.html">
phenomenon</weblink>".&#32;  FINAL.ORG.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-03</link>.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Mirapaul, Matthew&#32;(1998-04-23).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/library/tech/98/04/cyber/artsatlarge/23artsatlarge.html">
Artists Open Door to Private Underworld</weblink>", The New York Times.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sweetcucumber.com/?p=4">
Hell.com</weblink>".&#32;  SweetCucumber.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-18</link>.</entry>
<entry id="17">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://final.org/ar/nuwho.html#new">
resource</weblink>".&#32;  FINAL.ORG.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="16">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20040611142545/www.hell.com/3/vip/info.html">
1</weblink>".&#32;  HELL.COM.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-03</link>.</entry>
<entry id="19">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bat.hell.com/">
BAT</weblink>".&#32;  bat.hell.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-14</link>.</entry>
<entry id="18">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bat.hell.com/">
HELL.COM</weblink>".&#32;  bat.hell.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-14</link>.</entry>
<entry id="21">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.myspace.com/cygnenoir">
kenneth (Myspace profile)</weblink>".&#32;  Myspace.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-03</link>.</entry>
<entry id="20">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bat.hell.com/">
INVISIBLE</weblink>".&#32;  bat.hell.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-14</link>.</entry>
<entry id="23">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://final.org/ar/SURFACE.html">
s u r f a c e</weblink>".&#32;  FINAL.ORG.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="22">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.zuper.com/portfolio/zx7/">
Zuper! Portfolio</weblink>".&#32;  Zuper!.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="25">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.entropy8zuper.org/skinonskinonskin/postmasters/index.html">
skinonskinonskin at postmasters</weblink>".&#32;  Entropy8Zuper!.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-14</link>.</entry>
<entry id="24">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.entropy8zuper.org/skinonskinonskin/postmasters/pressrelease.html">
PRESS RELEASE:</weblink>".&#32;  Entropy8Zuper!.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-14</link>.</entry>
<entry id="27">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nmartproject.net/artists/?p=761">
Artists Network Database</weblink>".&#32;  8081.</entry>
<entry id="26">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.entropy8zuper.org/skinonskinonskin/entry.html">
e8z!</weblink>".&#32;  Entropy8Zuper!.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-14</link>.</entry>
<entry id="29">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eyebeam.org/reblog/archives/2006/12/copypaste_netart.html">
Copy-paste (net.)art</weblink>".&#32;  we-make-money-not-art.com/.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-04</link>.</entry>
<entry id="28">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://subsol.c3.hu/subsol_2/contributors/01orgtext.html">
ART.HACKTIVISM 0100101110101101.ORG</weblink>".&#32;  Luther Blissett.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="31">
Baumgärtel, Tilman&#32;(1999-09-12).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://translate.google.com/translate?u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.heise.de%2Ftp%2Fr4%2Fartikel%2F5%2F5572%2F1.html&amp;langpair=de%7Cen&amp;hl=en&amp;safe=off&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;prev=%2Flanguage_tools">
Keine Künstler, nur Betrachter (translated from German)</weblink>", Heise Zeitschriften Verlag.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-18</link>.&nbsp; </entry>
<entry id="30">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://0100101110101101.org/home/copies/hell_reaction.html">
Hell.com reaction</weblink>".&#32;  0100101110101101.org.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-04</link>.</entry>
<entry id="34">
Reuters&#32;(2006-10-28).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2006/10/28/1161749343255.html">
Hell doesn't sell</weblink>", The Sydney Morning Herald..&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="35">
Quaranta, Domenico.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.domenicoquaranta.net/04_hell.com_eng.html">
A SEASON IN HELL</weblink>", Cluster.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="32">
Mirapaul, Matthew&#32;(1999-07-08).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/library/tech/99/07/cyber/artsatlarge/08artsatlarge.html">
An Attack on the Commercialization of Web Art</weblink>", The New York Times.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-16</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="33">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://0100101110101101.org/home/copies/hell.com">
ANTI©1999 0100101110101101.ORG</weblink></entry>
<entry id="36">
Lamothe, Keisha&#32;(2006-10-27).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://money.cnn.com/2006/10/27/technology/hell.com_domain/index.htm?cnn=yes">
Web domain Hell.com hath no takers</weblink>", Cable News Network LP, LLLP..&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-16</link>.&nbsp; </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

Official:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hell.com">
HELL.COM</weblink> (may not work in Mozilla/non-Java browsers)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hell.com.cybrport.com/@/">
HELL.COM's e-mail login</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://final.org/">
FINAL.ORG</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bat.hell.com/">
BAT |out of hell</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kennetharonson.com">
kenneth aronson |public art</weblink> Kenneth Aronson's website</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cygne-noir.com/">
C Y G N E N O I R</weblink> Kenneth Aronson's portfolio</entry>
</list>

Events:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.entropy8zuper.org/skinonskinonskin/againandagainandagain.html">
skinnonskinonskin</weblink> Hell.com event during 1999 created by "entropy8" and "Zuper!"</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</property>
</possession>
</article>
