<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:25:53[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<body  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107965085">
<social_group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107950920">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<college  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108278169">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<header>
<title>Sussex Downs College</title>
<id>3450819</id>
<revision>
<id>243152357</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T11:11:44Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Signalhead</username>
<id>2989394</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Eastbourne</category>
<category>Sixth form colleges in the United Kingdom</category>
<category>Lewes</category>
<category>Further education colleges in Sussex</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox School</name>
<parameters>

<image width="150px" src="Sussex_Downs_College_Logo.jpg">
<caption>

Sussex Downs College Logo
</caption>
</image>
<city>
<site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/18729001.xml">
Eastbourne</link></site>
</city>
<principal>
John Blake</principal>
<lower_age>
16</lower_age>
<nickname>
SDC</nickname>
<postcode>
BN23 6DP</postcode>
<homepage>
http://www.sussexdowns.ac.uk</homepage>
<county>
<county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/67923.xml">
East Sussex</link></county>
</county>
<language>
English</language>
<motto>
Putting Students First</motto>
<budget>
£40m</budget>
<athletics>
Football, tennis, track &amp; field</athletics>
<school_colours>
Green, blue</school_colours>
<established>
November 2001</established>
<enrolment>
6220 full time; 14400 part time</enrolment>
<campus_type>
Urban</campus_type>
<gender>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../118/364118.xml">
Coeducational</link></gender>
<country>
GBR</country>
<streetaddress>
Headquarters: Cross Levels Way</streetaddress>
<campus>
Eastbourne, Lewes, Denton Island, Wealden Skills Centre, Hailsham</campus>
<ofsted>
133435</ofsted>
<staff>
1400</staff>
<name>
Sussex Downs College</name>
<revenue>
£38m+</revenue>
<imagesize>
200</imagesize>
</parameters>
</template>





<p>

<b>Sussex Downs College</b> (SDC) is a large <fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<phase wordnetid="115290337" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/234351.xml">
further education</link></phase>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
 (FE) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/5689.xml">
college</link> in the <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/52926.xml">
South East of England</link></region>
.  It has campuses in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/18729001.xml">
Eastbourne</link></site>
, <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/67930.xml">
Lewes</link></site>
, <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/152008.xml">
Newhaven</link></site>
 and <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/144791.xml">
Uckfield</link></site>
.  It was formed from the merger of three smaller colleges in the region - Lewes Sixth Form College, Park Sixth Form College and Eastbourne College of Arts and Technology (more recently known as Eastbourne Vocational College).</p>
<p>

Although there was primarily some speculation over a successful merger Sussex Downs College has since proved itself of exceptional standard, achieving CoVE status (Certificate of Vocational Excellence) an award that very few other colleges have managed to attain.</p>

<sec>
<st>
College Offer</st>
<p>

By offering provision for 16-19s, adults, international students and some courses in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/14423.xml">
Higher Education</link>, the college attracts people from all walks of life. Although functioning as one college the ethos of the individual campuses remains the same giving the students an individual choice as to how they learn, yet the security of a vastly equipped support network.</p>
<p>

Funded via the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/725949.xml">
Learning and Skills Council</link>, the college offers <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/162619.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22United_Kingdom%22])">
Apprenticeships</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/17684703.xml">
Train to Gain</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/11338390.xml">
Skills for life</link> and traditional college delivery alongside commercial courses such as minute taking, training in common software packages and full cost <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/231917.xml">
NVQs</link>.  The range of subjects offered by the college is highly diverse as it stretches from GCSEs and A levels in a majority of academic subjects, to vocational courses in areas such as hairdressing, motor vehicle and business administration.  Learners have several options with regards to attendance- full time, part time, day release (one day a week), evening classes and work-based delivery.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/301482.xml">
Office for Standards in Education</link> describes the college's programmes as follows:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 "The college has provision in all the areas of learning defined by the Learning and Skills Council (LSC). The most significant areas of learning in terms of student enrolments: are science and mathematics; business; information and communications technology (ICT); health and social care; visual and performing arts; humanities; English, languages and communication; and foundation programmes. Work-based learning has recently been introduced in a wide range of vocational areas, including business, construction, engineering, hairdressing and beauty therapy, and health and social care. The college is designated as a Centre of Vocational Excellence for the performing arts and entertainment industries. In 2000/01, the college had 3,080 full-time students aged 16 to 18, 809 full-time adult students and 12,782 part-time adult students. Some 82% of students classify themselves as white. The proportion of students from minority ethnic groups is small and reflects the composition of the local population. Female students made up 63% of the student population in 2000/01."
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
School ranking</st>
<p>

For the year 2004, Sussex Downs College received an A/AS-level performance ranking from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/301463.xml">
Department for Education and Skills</link> of 228.2, 
below the national average of 269.2.
This ranking should dramatically improve given the College's recent success of obtaining at an A level pass rate of 98.6% in its 2006
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/bsp/hi/education/04/school_tables/secondary_schools/html/845_8009.stm">
Ofsted Report</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>
<p>

The college has a wealth of modern, spacious buildings across the three campuses, however there remain a number of inadequate facilities, such as Park College in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/18729001.xml">
Eastbourne</link></site>
. Previous students have complained of substantial overcrowding in the corridors and social areas as well as cramped teaching spaces and not nearly enough ICT resources. The college is however in the process of upgrading and constructing new buildings. The college at lewes has many of the same problems and the numerous eatiries become crowded quickly at lunch time.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Tutors</st>
<p>

The tutors at sussex downs are nice and very helpful students get 1:1 support with them every quarter. This creates a good atmosphere amongst students in the fact you know if there is somebody to talk to if there is a need.</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sussexdowns.ac.uk">
Sussex Downs College Web Site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ofsted.gov.uk/reports/manreports/850.htm">
Evaluation by the Adult Learning Inspectorate, Office for Standards in Education</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</group>
</college>
</entity>
</social_group>
</body>
</article>
