<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:21:17[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<communicator  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109610660">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<writer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110794014">
<journalist  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110224578">
<header>
<title>Hamad Al-Jassir</title>
<id>3459807</id>
<revision>
<id>243220185</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T17:43:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Saudi Arabian journalists</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Hamad Al-Jasser</b> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/34649.xml">
1907</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/27947.xml">
september 14</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link>) was a prominent <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/349303.xml">
Saudi Arabia</link></country>
n journalist and historian.  He is particularly noted for founding Saudi Arabia's first central region magazine, the first comprehensive geographical locations reference in Saudi Arabia and the authorship of a comprehensive genealogical work popular in the country.
<sec>
<st>
Early life</st>
<p>

Hamad Al-Jasser was born in the small village of Al-Burood in 1907.  He grew up physically weak, not learning how to walk until the age of four.  His mother died when he was just seven years old.  He went to the village school, Al-Kuttab, and learned how to read and write.</p>
<p>

In 1920, his father sent him to live with a relative who was studying in the capital, <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/51554.xml">
Riyadh</link></city>
. There, in line with normal educational practice in the country at the time, he memorised the whole of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/36922.xml">
Quran</link>, and learned about the lives of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/178433.xml">
Sheikh</link>s.</p>
<p>

After the relative he was living with in Riyadh died, he returned to his hometown Al-Burood.  At this point his father had fallen ill, and so his grandfather put him in charge of educating the young people of Al-Burood.  However his older brother, Jasser Al-Jasser, was unhappy with his presence in Al-Burood and so took him back to Riyadh, to continue his education among other students and Sheikhs.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Career</st>
<p>

Al-Jasser became a teacher, and taught throughout Saudi Arabia.  He also served as a judge in Northern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/184235.xml">
Hejaz</link>.  He went on to establish the first magazine in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia: "Al-Yamama", in 1951.  He then wrote, edited, and was very much involved in the magazine, and journalism in general.</p>
<p>

He wrote many geographical/historical books, all specialized in the Arabian Peninsula.  One of his works, the famous   genealogical work جمهرة أنساب الأسر المتحضرة في نجد is popularly known as Kitab Al-Ansab, "The Book of Roots".  The book lists all Saudi families together with a brief history of the family. As a result, the book is very popular and found widely throughout Saudi Arabia.</p>
<p>

He also established a second magazine, "Al-Arab", and a Publishing house "Dar Al-Yamama for Research, publishing and Distribution", which he supervised.</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</journalist>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
</article>
