<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:52:11[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<process  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105701363">
<inquiry  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105797597">
<thinking  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105770926">
<problem_solving  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105796750">
<experiment  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105798043">
<trial  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105799212">
<higher_cognitive_process  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105770664">
<header>
<title>Graduate Record Examination</title>
<id>346643</id>
<revision>
<id>243845462</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T08:38:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Morven</username>
<id>19833</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Standardized tests in the United States</category>
<category>Educational assessment and evaluation</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Graduate Record Examination</b> or <b>GRE</b> is a commercially-run <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/225971.xml">
standardized test</link> that is an admissions requirement for many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/346628.xml">
graduate school</link>s principally in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, but also in other English speaking countries. Created and administered by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/347550.xml">
Educational Testing Service</link></company>
 (or ETS), the exam is primarily focused on testing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
abstract thinking</link> skills in the areas of math, vocabulary, and analytical writing.  The GRE is typically a computer-based exam that is administered by select qualified testing centers; however, paper-based exams are offered in areas of the world that lack the technological requirements. <p>

In the graduate school admissions process, the level of emphasis that is placed upon GRE scores varies widely between schools and even departments within schools. The importance of a GRE score can range from being an important selection factor to being a mere admission formality.</p>
<p>

Critics of the GRE have argued that the exam format is so rigid that it effectively tests only how well a student can conform to a standardized test taking procedure.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> ETS responded by announcing plans in 2006 to radically redesign the test structure starting in the fall of 2007; however, the company has since announced, "Plans for launching an entirely new test all at once were dropped, and ETS decided to introduce new question types and improvements gradually over time." The new questions have been gradually introduced since November of 2007.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Structure</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

</indent>

The exam consists of three graded sections, plus a required experimental section that is not included in the reported score. The three graded sections are analytical writing, <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
verbal</link></language>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/861437.xml">
quantitative</link>. The analytical writing section will always appear first, while the verbal, quantitative, and experimental sections may appear in any order on the test.  An additional non-scored and clearly-marked optional research section may also appear at end of the test. The entire test procedure takes about 3 hours.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Analytical writing section</st>
<p>

The analytical writing section consists of two different essays, an "issue task" and an "argument task".  
The writing section is graded on a scale of 0-6, in half-point increments. The essays are written on a computer using a word processing program specifically designed by ETS. The program allows only basic computer functions and does not contain a spell-checker or other advanced features. Each essay is scored by at least two readers on a six-point <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/206358.xml">
holistic</link> scale.  If the two scores are within one point, the average of the scores is taken.  If the two scores differ by more than a point, a third reader examines the response.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Issue task</st>
<p>

The test taker will be able to choose between two topics upon which to write an essay. The time allowed for this essay is 45 minutes.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Argument task</st>
<p>

The test taker will be given an "argument" and will be asked to write an essay that explains why one "side" of the argument is superior. Typically, the task requires that the taker identify and critique the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/53986.xml">
 logical fallacies</link> of the argument.  The time allotted for this essay is 30 minutes.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Verbal section</st>
<p>

One graded multiple-choice section is always a <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
verbal</link></language>
 section, consisting of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/103533.xml">
analogies</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/147930.xml">
antonyms</link>, sentence completions, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/1639193.xml">
reading comprehension</link> passages. Multiple-choice response sections are graded on a scale of 200-800, in 10 point increments. This section primarily tests vocabulary, and average scores in this section are substantially lower than those in the quantitative section.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> In a typical examination, this section may consist of 30 questions, and 30 minutes may be allotted to complete the section.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Quantitative section</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/861437.xml">
quantitative</link> section, the other multiple-choice section, consists of problem solving and quantitative comparison questions that test high-school level math. Multiple-choice response sections are graded on a scale of 200-800, in 10 point increments. In a typical examination, this section may consist of 28 questions, and test takers may be given 45 minutes to complete the section.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Experimental section</st>
<p>

The experimental section will be either a verbal, quantitative or the essay section which contains new questions that ETS is considering for future test editions. This section will not count toward the test-taker's score; however, the section will appear identical to either the "actual" verbal or quantitative section and will likewise be a multiple-choice test with the same number of questions and the same time allotment as the "real" verbal or quantitative section. The test taker will have no way of knowing  which section is experimental, so the test taker is forced to complete this section. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

If the experimental section appears as an analytical writing question (essay), if an "issue" type question is presented, a choice between two topics will not be given. This coupled with the fact that the true analytical writing section is the first test given can help the test-taker to deduce which is the experimental section and the taker can thus lower the importance of that section.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Research Section</st>
<p>

An additional research section may appear at the end of the test. Unlike the experimental section, this section will be clearly marked and will be completely optional. The test taker's participation or  refusal to participate will not affect the reported score in any way.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Scoring</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Computerized adaptive testing</st>
<p>

The common (Verbal and Quantitative) multiple-choice portions of the exam currently use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/1743830.xml">
computer-adaptive testing</link> (CAT) methods that automatically change the difficulty of questions as the test taker proceeds with the exam, depending on the number of correct or incorrect answers that are given. The test taker is not allowed to go back and change the answers to previous questions, and some type of answer must be given before the next question is presented. </p>
<p>

The first question that is given in a multiple-choice section is considered to be an "average level" question that half of the GRE test takers will answer correctly. If the question is answered correctly, then subsequent questions become more difficult. If the question is answered incorrectly, then subsequent questions become easier, until a question is answered correctly.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>  This approach to administration yields scores that are of similar accuracy while using approximately half as many items.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>  However, this effect is moderated with the GRE because it has a fixed length; true CATs are variable-length, where the test will stop itself once it has zeroed in on a candidate's ability level.</p>
<p>

The actual scoring of the test is done with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/420159.xml">
item response theory</link> (IRT).  While CAT is associated with IRT, IRT is actually used to score non-CAT exams.  The GRE subject tests, which are administered in the traditional paper-and-pencil format, use the same IRT scoring algorithm.  The difference that CAT provides is that items are dynamically selected so that the test taker only sees items of appropriate difficulty.  Besides the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/24982.xml">
psychometric</link> benefits, this has the added benefit of not wasting the examinee's time by administering items that are far too hard or easy.  This occurs in fixed-form testing.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Scaled score percentiles</st>
<p>

The percentiles of the current test are as follows:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>
<table class="prettytable">
<header>
Scaled score</header>
<header>
Verbal Reasoning %</header>
<header>
Quantitative Reasoning %</header>
<row>
<col>
800</col>
<col>
99</col>
<col>
94</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
780</col>
<col>
99</col>
<col>
90</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
760</col>
<col>
99</col>
<col>
86</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
740</col>
<col>
99</col>
<col>
82</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
720</col>
<col>
98</col>
<col>
77</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
700</col>
<col>
97</col>
<col>
72</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
680</col>
<col>
96</col>
<col>
68</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
660</col>
<col>
94</col>
<col>
63</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
640</col>
<col>
91</col>
<col>
58</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
620</col>
<col>
89</col>
<col>
53</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
600</col>
<col>
85</col>
<col>
49</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
580</col>
<col>
81</col>
<col>
44</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
560</col>
<col>
76</col>
<col>
40</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
540</col>
<col>
71</col>
<col>
35</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
520</col>
<col>
65</col>
<col>
31</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
500</col>
<col>
60</col>
<col>
28</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
480</col>
<col>
55</col>
<col>
24</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
460</col>
<col>
49</col>
<col>
21</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
440</col>
<col>
43</col>
<col>
18</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
420</col>
<col>
37</col>
<col>
15</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
400</col>
<col>
31</col>
<col>
13</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
380</col>
<col>
26</col>
<col>
11</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
360</col>
<col>
21</col>
<col>
9</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
340</col>
<col>
15</col>
<col>
7</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
320</col>
<col>
10</col>
<col>
5</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
300</col>
<col>
6</col>
<col>
4</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
280</col>
<col>
3</col>
<col>
3</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
260</col>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
2</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
240</col>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
1</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
220</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
1</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
200</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
0</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
mean</header>
<col>
465</col>
<col>
584</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<table class="prettytable">
<header>
Analytical Writing score</header>
<header>
Writing %</header>
<row>
<col>
6</col>
<col>
96</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
5.5</col>
<col>
88</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
5</col>
<col>
73</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
4.5</col>
<col>
54</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
4</col>
<col>
33</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
3.5</col>
<col>
18</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
3</col>
<col>
7</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
2.5</col>
<col>
2</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
2</col>
<col>
1</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
1.5</col>
<col>
0</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
0</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
0.5</col>
<col>
0</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
mean</header>
<col>
4.1</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

Comparisons for "Intended Graduate Major" are "limited to those who earned their college degrees up to two years prior to the test date." ETS provides no score data for "non-traditional" students who have been out of school more than two years, although their own report "RR-99-16" indicated that 22% of all test takers in 1996 were over the age of 30.</p>

</ss2>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Use in admissions</st>
<p>

Many graduate schools in <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English</link></language>
-speaking countries (especially in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
) require GRE test results as part of the admission  procedure. The GRE test is a standardized test intended to measure the abilities of all graduates in tasks of general academic nature, regardless of their fields of specialization. The GRE is supposed to measure the extent to which <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/217289.xml">
undergraduate</link> education has developed an individual's verbal and quantitative skills in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
abstract thinking</link>.</p>
<p>

Unlike other standardized admissions tests (such as the <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/144716.xml">
SAT</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
, <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="107197021" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/386327.xml">
LSAT</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</examination>
</process>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/241891.xml">
MCAT</link>), the use and weight of GRE scores vary considerably not only from school to school, but from department to department, and from program to program too.  Programs in liberal arts topics may only consider the applicant's verbal score to be of interest, while math and science programs may only consider quantitative ability; however, since most applicants to math, science, or engineering graduate programs all have high quantitative scores, the verbal score can become a deciding factor even in these programs.  Some schools use the GRE in admissions decisions, but not in funding decisions; others use the GRE for the selection of scholarship and fellowship candidates, but not for admissions.  In some cases, the GRE may be a general requirement for graduate admissions imposed by the university, while particular departments may not consider the scores at all.  Graduate schools will typically provide information about how the GRE is considered in admissions and funding decisions, and the average scores of previously admitted students. The best way to find out how a particular school or program evaluates a GRE score in the admissions process is to contact the person in charge of graduate admissions for the specific program in question (and not the graduate school in general). </p>
<p>

Programs that involve significant expository writing require the submission of a prepared writing sample that is considered more useful in determining writing ability than the analytical writing section; however, the writing scores of foreign students are sometimes given more scrutiny and are used as an indicator of overall comfort with and mastery of conversational English.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
GRE Subject Tests</st>
<p>

In addition to the General Test, there are also eight GRE Subject Tests testing knowledge in the specific areas of <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/5569863.xml">
Biochemistry, Cell and Molecular Biology</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
, <link>
Biology</link>, <link>
Chemistry</link>, <link>
Computer Science</link>, <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/5568297.xml">
Literature in English</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/3664705.xml">
Mathematics</link>, <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/12696.xml">
Physics</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
, and <link>
Psychology</link>. In the past, subject tests were also offered in the areas of Economics, Revised Education, Engineering, Geology, History, Music, Political Science, and Sociology. In April 1998, the Revised Education and Political Science exams were discontinued. In April 2000, the History and Sociology exams were discontinued, and the other four were discontinued in April 2001.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.physicsgre.com/engineering-gre.shtml">
http://www.physicsgre.com/engineering-gre.shtml</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Preparation</st>
<p>

A variety of resources are available for those wishing to prepare for the GRE.  Upon registration, ETS provides preparation software called PowerPrep, which contains two practice tests of retired questions, as well as further practice questions and review material. Since the software replicates both the test format and the questions used, it can be useful to predict the actual GRE scores. ETS does not license their past questions to any other company, making them the only source for official retired material. ETS used to publish the "BIG BOOK" which contained a number of actual GRE questions; however, this publishing was abandoned. Several companies provide courses, books and other unofficial preparation materials.</p>
<p>

ETS has claimed that content of the GRE is "un-coachable"; however, many test preparation companies like IMS Learning Resources, VISU etc 
claim that the test format is so rigid that familiarizing oneself with the test's organization, timing, specific foci, and the use of  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/2241374.xml">
process of elimination</link> is the best way to increase a GRE score.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Testing locations</st>

<p>

While the general and subject tests are held at many undergraduate institutions, the computer-based general test is only held at test centers with appropriate technological accommodations.  Students in major cities in the US, or those attending large US universities, will usually find a nearby test center, while those in more isolated areas may have to travel a few hours to an urban or university location. Many industrialized countries also have test centers, but at times test-takers must cross country borders (see GRE website for details).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>

<p>

Test takers complain about the strict test center rules. For instance, test takers may not use pens or bring their own scratch paper. Paper and pencils are provided at the testing center. Food and drink are prohibited in the test centers, as are chewing gum, jackets and hats.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Bias</st>

<p>

Critics have claimed that the computer-adaptive methodology may discourage some test takers, because the question difficulty changes with performance. For example, if the test-taker is presented with remarkably easy questions half way into the exam, they may infer that they are not performing well, which will influence their abilities as the exam continues, even though question difficulty is subjective. </p>
<p>

Critics have also stated that the computer-adaptive method of placing more weight on the first several questions is biased against test takers who typically perform poorly at the beginning of a test due to stress or confusion before becoming more comfortable as the exam continues.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>
<p>

The GRE has also been subjected to the same racial bias criticisms that have been lodged against other admissions tests. In 1998, the Journal of Blacks in Higher Education noted that the mean score for black test-takers in 1996 was 389 on the verbal section, 409 on the quantitative section, and 423 on the analytic, while white test-takers averaged 496, 538, and 564, respectively.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

There is also a bias towards those students who have the financial resources to take privately owned test taking classes. These classes do typically result in better scores; however, many such companies and tutors focus solely on how to use the test's format to one's advantage, and not how to actually learn the material on the exam. In the United States, the cost of the general test is $140 US as of July 1, 2008, although ETS will reduce the fee under certain circumstances.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Weak predictor of graduate school performance</st>
<p>

The GREs are criticized for not being a true measure of a whether a student will be successful in graduate school.  The ETS published a report ("What is the Value of the GRE?") that points out the GRE's shortcomings in attempting to predict a student's index of success at the graduate level. A PDF form of the report can be viewed  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/Media/Tests/GRE/pdf/grevalue.pdf">
here</weblink>. </p>
<p>

While the verbal section tests vocabulary and verbal reasoning, the vocabulary employed is not specifically relevant to any particular area of study, and (in the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/103533.xml">
analogies</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/147930.xml">
antonym</link>s) is presented without context.  The quantitative portion of the test covers topics that are far too elementary for any program in the fields of math or science, as well as being irrelevant for the study of most liberal arts topics.  The Analytic Writing section (derived from ETS' unpopular Writing Assessment Test) may be less useful in assessing writing ability than a prepared writing sample, or than  a 'Personal Statement' or '<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/2782656.xml">
Statement of purpose</link>' relevant to the appropriate field (which is also required for admissions by many programs).  </p>
<p>

Dr. Robert Sternberg of Tufts University found that the GRE general test was weakly predictive of success in graduate studies in psychology. The weak predictability may be related to the mathematics portion of the GRE general test because a good foundation of mathematics is important in understanding advanced statistics.  However, in some branches of psychology, the application of statistics is only a small part.</p>
<p>

The mathematical portion of the GRE general test is the only area of the GRE general test that may have predictive ability in the natural sciences.  The natural sciences require a strong foundation in mathematics for success in both core courses and in statistical analysis  related to research. However, it is not clear whether the GRE accurately assesses mathematical skills required for success in graduate school.</p>
<p>

Recent reports and questionnaires have shown that the GRE General Test is not as significant in determining graduate admissions as once believed and that some schools are moving away from placing an emphasis on high GRE scores.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Validity</st>
<p>

A meta-analysis of the GRE's validity in predicting graduate school success found a correlation of .3 to .4 between the GRE and both first year and overall graduate GPA.  The correlation between GRE score and graduate school completion rates ranged from .11 (for the now defunct analytical section) to .39 (for the GRE subject test).<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.uvic.ca/psyc/lindsay/teaching/499/readings/kuncel.pdf">
http://web.uvic.ca/psyc/lindsay/teaching/499/readings/kuncel.pdf</weblink> </p>
<p>

However, when the analysis is extended to review of the literature in the past, such a review appeared in a 1985 issue of the journal Research in Higher Education. Over eighty pages in length, it is one of the most exhaustive literature reviews on the question of test validity.
The author Leonard Baird focused on studies completed between 1966 and 1984, reported in any of nineteen highly-regarded scholarly journals. In study after study many of the reported correlation coefficients were zero or near zero, and some studies even showed significant negative coefficients. Most striking, many of these negative correlations appear in the studies concerning the relationship between test scores and the number of publications and citations for graduates of PhD programs. For instance:
"Clark and Centra studied two samples of doctoral recipients… The resulting sample consisted of 239 chemists, 142 historians, and 221 psychologists, all of whom had at least one GRE score. In chemistry, the correlation of number of articles and book chapters with GRE-verbal was -.02; with GRE-quantitative it was -.01; and with GRE-advanced it was .15… For all historians, these correlations were -.24, -.14, and .00. For all psychologists, the correlations were -.05, -.02, and .02.
Clark and Centra also examined the distribution of number of publications by GRE scores. The distributions were essentially flat, with no particular trend. In fact, the largest number of publications was reported by the lowest scoring groups in all three fields(emphasis added)." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

Currently the GRE Scores are valid for 5 years.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Plans for the revised GRE</st>

<p>

In 2006, ETS announced plans to enact significant changes in the format of the GRE. Planned changes for the revised GRE included a longer testing time, a departure from computer-adaptive testing, a new grading scale, and an enhanced focus on reasoning skills and critical thinking for both the quantitative and qualitative sections.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> </p>
<p>

On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/1777.xml">
April 2</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>, ETS announced the decision to cancel plans for revising the GRE.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> The announcement cited concerns over the ability to provide clear and equal access to the new test after the planned change as an explanation for the cancellation. They did state, however, that they do plan "to implement many of the planned test content improvements in the future", although exact details regarding those changes have not yet been announced.</p>
<p>

Changes to the GRE will begin to take effect on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/21460.xml">
November 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>, as ETS will start to include new types of questions in the exam. The changes mostly center on "fill in the blank" type answers for both the math and vocabulary sections that require the test-taker to fill in the blank directly, without being able to choose from a multiple choice list of answers. ETS currently plans to introduce two of these new types of questions in each qualitative or vocabulary section, while the majority of questions will presented in the regular format. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

On January 2008, the Reading Comprehension within the verbal sections has been reformatted, passages's "line numbers will be replaced with highlighting when necessary in order to focus the test taker on specific information in the passage" to "help students more easily find the pertinent information in reading passages."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
GRE prior to October 2002</st>
<p>

Prior to October 2002, the GRE had a separate Analytical Ability section which tested candidates on logical and analytical reasoning abilities. This section has now been replaced by the Analytical Writing portion.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.abroadeducation.com.np/test-preparation/gre/test-modules.html">
GRE Test Modules</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/841060.xml">
Princeton Review</link>, <it>Cracking the GRE, 2007 edition</it> p. 19 # ISBN 0375765514, ISBN-13 978-0375765513. 2006 </entry>
<entry id="2">
<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.c988ba0e5dd572bada20bc47c3921509/?vgnextoid=8fc9a1d64ffd3110VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=bf8146f1674f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD">
Gre General Test to Include New Questions</weblink>''</it></entry>
<entry id="3">
 <b><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.1488512ecfd5b8849a77b13bc3921509/?vgnextoid=0a51d2b54c0c5010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=6236e3b5f64f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD#Computer_Based_General_Test_Content_and_Structure">
GRE Test Content</weblink> </b></entry>
<entry id="4">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.1488512ecfd5b8849a77b13bc3921509/?vgnextoid=0a51d2b54c0c5010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=6236e3b5f64f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD#Computer_Based_General_Test_Content_and_Structure">
GRE Test Content</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="5">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.1488512ecfd5b8849a77b13bc3921509/?vgnextoid=0a51d2b54c0c5010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=6236e3b5f64f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD#Computer_Based_General_Test_Content_and_Structure">
GRE Test Content</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="6">
PowerScore GRE Preparation. Retrieved February 4, 2007, from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.powerscore.com/gre/scoringscale.htm">
PowerScore GRE Preparation</weblink>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.1488512ecfd5b8849a77b13bc3921509/?vgnextoid=0a51d2b54c0c5010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=6236e3b5f64f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD#Computer_Based_General_Test_Content_and_Structure">
GRE Test Content</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="8">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.1488512ecfd5b8849a77b13bc3921509/?vgnextoid=0a51d2b54c0c5010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=6236e3b5f64f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD#Computer_Based_General_Test_Content_and_Structure">
GRE Test Content</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="9">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.1488512ecfd5b8849a77b13bc3921509/?vgnextoid=0a51d2b54c0c5010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=6236e3b5f64f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD#Computer_Based_General_Test_Content_and_Structure">
GRE Test Content</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="10">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/841060.xml">
Princeton Review</link>, <it>Cracking the GRE, 2007 edition</it> p. 19 # ISBN 0375765514, ISBN-13 978-0375765513. 2006 </entry>
<entry id="11">
Weiss, D.J., &amp; Kingsbury, G.G.(1984). Application of computerized adaptive testing to educational problems. <it>Journal of Educational Measurement, 21</it>, 361-375. </entry>
<entry id="12">
GRE: Guide to the Use of Scores 2007-08. Retrieved October 25, 2007, from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/Media/Tests/GRE/pdf/994994.pdf">
Guide to the Use of Scores 2007-08</weblink>.</entry>
<entry id="13">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/841060.xml">
Princeton Review</link>, <it>Cracking the GRE, 2007 edition</it> p. 19 # ISBN 0375765514, ISBN-13 978-0375765513. 2006 </entry>
<entry id="14">
 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dailybruin.ucla.edu/archives/id/4597/">
Testing service cancels February GRE</weblink></it> </entry>
<entry id="15">
"Estimating the Effect a Ban on Racial Preferences Would Have on African- American Admissions to the Nation's Leading Graduate Schools." <it>The Journal of Blacks in Higher Education</it>, No. 19. (Spring, 1998), pp. 80-82.</entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.princetonreview.com/grad/testprep/testprep.asp?TPRPAGE=880&amp;TYPE=GRE">
Comparison Chart of GRE Changes</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
Leonard L. Baird, "Do Grades and Tests Predict Adult Accomplishment?" Research in Higher Education 23, no. 1, 1985, page 25.</entry>
<entry id="19">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.c988ba0e5dd572bada20bc47c3921509/?vgnextoid=8fc9a1d64ffd3110VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=bf8146f1674f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD">
GRE® General Test to Include New Question Types in November</weblink></entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.c988ba0e5dd572bada20bc47c3921509/?vgnextoid=e9e8b524b40b1110VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=dd2d253b164f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD">
Plans for the Revised GRE Cancelled</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/portal/site/ets/menuitem.c988ba0e5dd572bada20bc47c3921509/?vgnextoid=fbf8d69b413f6110VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD&amp;vgnextchannel=bf8146f1674f4010VgnVCM10000022f95190RCRD">
Revisions to the Computer-based GRE General Test in 2008</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../124/293124.xml">
List of admissions tests</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/346628.xml">
Graduate school</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/12696.xml">
GRE Physics Test</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/">
Educational Testing Service</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gla.ac.uk/departments/philosophy/Undergraduate%20Resources/Honours/Postgrad_Applications/PGAppsUS.htm#_GRE">
What is GRE? Glasgow University Help Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ftp.ets.org/pub/gre/01736_iclist.pdf">
Institution Code List</weblink> – List of institutions (with code numbers) that receive GRE scores</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/Media/Tests/GRE/pdf/gre%20practice%20general%20test.pdf">
GRE Practice test</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
</article>
