<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:51:13[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<market  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101097292">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Valuation (finance)</title>
<id>347107</id>
<revision>
<id>242858024</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T23:38:16Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>HoulihanLokey</username>
<id>4886074</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Financial economics</category>
<category>Financial markets</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/11162.xml">
finance</link>, <b>valuation</b> is the process of estimating the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/730256.xml">
market value</link> of a financial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/18934838.xml">
asset</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/101757.xml">
liability</link>.  Valuations can be done on assets (for example, investments in marketable securities such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/19372783.xml">
stock</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/9272073.xml">
option</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
business</link> enterprises, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/299146.xml">
intangible asset</link>s such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/23273.xml">
patent</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/18935023.xml">
trademark</link>s) or on liabilities (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/60737.xml">
Bond</link>s issued by a company). Valuations are required in many contexts including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/347107.xml">
investment analysis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/5187.xml">
capital</link> budgeting, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/20769.xml">
merger</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/20769.xml">
acquisition</link> transactions, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/93755.xml">
financial reporting</link>, taxable events to determine the proper <link>
tax liability</link>, and in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/113258.xml">
litigation</link>.
<sec>
<st>
Valuation overview</st>
<p>

Valuation of financial assets is done using one or more of these types of models: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/6552479.xml">
Relative value</link> models determine the value based on the market prices of similar assets.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link>
Absolute value model</link>s determine the value by estimating the expected future earnings from owning the asset discounted to their present value.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link>
Option pricing model</link>s are used for certain types of financial assets (e.g., <safety wordnetid="114538472" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<security wordnetid="114539268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/209278.xml">
warrant</link></security>
</state>
</condition>
</safety>
s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/207383.xml">
put option</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/204251.xml">
call option</link>s, employee <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/9272073.xml">
stock option</link>s, investments with <link>
embedded option</link>s such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/1318322.xml">
callable bond</link>) and are a complex present value model. The most common option pricing models are the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/113515.xml">
Black-Scholes</link>-<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/97367.xml">
Merton</link></scientist>
</person>
 models and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/3815666.xml">
lattice models</link>. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Common terms for the value of an asset or liability are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/1436263.xml">
fair market value</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/644005.xml">
fair value</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/320459.xml">
intrinsic value</link>. The meanings of these terms differ. The most common term is fair market value defined as the cash price an item would sell for between a willing buyer and willing seller assuming they both have knowledge of the relevant facts and they have no compulsion to buy or sell. Fair value is used in different contexts and has multiple meanings. Some people use the term to mean the same thing as fair market value. Fair value is also a term used in accounting and law. It is used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/1426478.xml">
generally accepted accounting principles</link> (GAAP) for financial reporting and in law in shareholder rights legal statutes. In these cases, fair value is defined in the accounting literature or the law, respectively. Fair value may be different from fair market value in the accounting and legal contexts. <b>Intrinsic value is an asset's true value regardless of the market price. When an analyst determines a stock's intrinsic value is greater than its market price, the analyst issues a "buy" recommendation and vice versa. The determination of intrinsic value may be subject to personal opinion and vary among individual analysts.</b>
For a comprehensive discussion on financial valuation see <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/6103095.xml">
Aswath Damodaran</link></writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
, <it>Investment Valuation</it>, (New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2002).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Business valuation</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
Business</link>es or fractional interests in businesses may be valued for various purposes such as mergers and acquisitions, sale of securities, and taxable events. An accurate valuation of privately owned companies largely depends on the reliability of the company's financial information. <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/262293.xml">
Public company</link></institution>
</kind>
</type>
</company>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 financial statements are audited by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/187472.xml">
Certified Public Accountant</link>s (US), <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/6233623.xml">
Chartered Certified Accountant</link></company>
s (<body wordnetid="105216365" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/1674332.xml">
ACCA</link></natural_object>
</body>
) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/1272582.xml">
Chartered Accountant</link>s (UK and Canada) and overseen by a government regulator. Private companies do not have government oversight and are generally not required to have their financial statements audited. Private company financial statements are commonly prepared to minimize taxes by lowering taxable income and the financial information may not be accurate. Public companies tend to want higher earnings to increase their share prices. Inaccurate financial information can lead to over- and undervaluation. In an acquisition, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/299610.xml">
due diligence</link> is commonly performed by the buyer to validate the representations made by the seller.</p>
<p>

Financial statements prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles (GAAP) usually express the values of the assets at their costs rather than their higher market values.  For example, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/100374.xml">
balance sheet</link> would reflect a piece of land at the purchase price rather than its appreciated value. Certain types of assets and liabilities such as securities held for sale will be reflected at their market values rather than their costs so that the company's financial information is more meaningful. This process is called "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/457618.xml">
mark-to-market</link>" but is subject to manager bias who may be compensated more with higher values. An extreme example of a company taking advantage of mark-to-market accounting to pump their own share price was <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/10166.xml">
Enron</link></company>
.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Main business valuation methods</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Discounted cash flows method</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link>
Valuation discounted cash flows</link></it>
</indent>
This method determines the value of a firm based on all of its expected future cash flows discounted to the present (i.e., the present value). The discount is based on an opportunity cost of capital, which is sometimes called a discount rate, and is expressed as a percentage.  The opportunity cost is estimated using a relation of risk and return.  The more risky the firm, the more return investors expect. Therefore, an investor's required rate of return for investing capital is higher when a firm has more risks.  Furthermore, firms that are more risky have a lower value than safer ones, all other things being equal.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Guideline companies method</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link>
Valuation using price multiples</link></it>
</indent>
This method determines the value of a firm by observing the prices of similar companies (guideline companies) that sold in the market. Those sales could be shares of stock or sales of entire firms.  The observed prices serve as valuation benchmarks. From the prices, one calculates price multiples such as the price-to-earnings or price-to-book value ratios.  Next, one or more price multiples are used to value the firm.  For example, the average price-to-earnings multiple of the guideline companies is applied to the subject firm's earnings to estimate its value.  </p>
<p>

Many price multiples can be calculated.  Most are based on a financial statement element such as a firm's earnings (price-to-earnings) or book value (price-to-book value) but multiples can be based on other factors such as price-per-subscriber.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Usage</st>
<p>

In finance, valuation analysis is required for many reasons including tax assessment, wills and estates, divorce settlements, business analysis, and basic bookkeeping and accounting. Since the value of things fluctuates over time, valuations are as of a specific date e.g., the end of the accounting quarter or year. They may alternatively be mark-to-market estimates of the current value of assets or liabilities as of this minute or this day for the purposes of managing portfolios and associated financial risk (for example, within large financial firms including investment banks and stockbrokers).</p>
<p>

Some balance sheet items are much easier to value than others. Publicly traded stocks and bonds have prices that are quoted frequently and readily available. Other assets are harder to value. For instance, private firms that have no frequently quoted price. Additionally, financial instruments that have prices that are partly dependent on theoretical models of one kind or another are difficult to value. For example, options are generally valued using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/113515.xml">
Black-Scholes</link> model while the liabilities of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/383367.xml">
life assurance</link> firms are valued using the theory of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/63218.xml">
present value</link>. Intangible business assets, like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/355296.xml">
goodwill</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/14724.xml">
intellectual property</link>, are open to a wide range of value interpretations. </p>
<p>

It is possible and conventional for financial professionals to make their own estimates of the valuations of assets or liabilities that they are interested in. Their calculations are of various kinds including analyses of companies that focus on price-to-book, price-to-earnings, price-to-cashflow and present value calculations, and analyses of bonds that focus on credit ratings, assessments of default risk, risk premia and levels of real interest rates. All of these approaches may be thought of as creating estimates of value that compete for credibility with the prevailing share or bond prices, where applicable, and may or may not result in buying or selling by market participants. Where the valuation is for the purpose of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/20769.xml">
merger or acquisition</link> the respective businesses make available further detailed financial information, usually on the completion of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/22052.xml">
Non-disclosure agreement</link>.</p>
<p>

It is very important to note that valuation is more an art than a science because it requires judgement:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

There are very different situations and purposes in which you value an asset (e.g. company in distress, tax purposes, mergers &amp; acquisitions, quarterly reporting). In turn this requires different methods or a different interpretation of the same method each time.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

All valuation models and methods have their limitations (e.g., mathematical, complexity, simplicity, comparability) and could be widely criticized. As a general rule the valuation models are most useful when you use the same valuation method as the "partner" you are interacting with. Mostly the method used is industry or purpose specific;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

The quality of some of the input data may vary widely </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

In all valuation models there are a great number of assumptions that need to be made and things might not turn out the way you expect. Your best way out of that is to be able to explain and stand for each assumption you make;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

When a valuation is prepared all assumptions should be clearly stated, especially the context. It is improper, for example, to value a going concern, based on an assumption that it is going out of business, since then only a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/291268.xml">
salvage value</link> remains.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Valuation of a distressed company</st>
<p>

Additional adjustments to a valuation approach, whether it is market-, income- or asset-based, may be necessary in some instances. These involve:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

excess or restricted cash</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

other non-operating assets and liabilities</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

lack of marketability discount</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

control premium or lack of control discount</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

above or below market leases</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

excess salaries in the case of private companies.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

There are other adjustments to the financial statements that have to be made when valuing a distressed company. Andrew Miller identifies typical adjustments used to recast the financial statements that include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

working capital adjustment</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

deferred capital expeditures</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

cost of goods sold adjustment</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

non-recurring professional fess and costs</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

certain non-operating income/expense items.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Valuation of intangible assets</st>
<p>

Valuation models can be used to value intangible assets such as patents, copyrights, software, trade secrets, and customer relationships.  Since few sales of benchmark intangible assets can ever be observed, one often values these sorts of assets using either a present value model or estimating the costs to recreate it.  Regardless of the method, the process is often time consuming and costly.</p>
<p>

Valuations of intangible assets are often necessary for financial reporting and intellectual property transactions.</p>
<p>

Stock markets give indirectly an estimate of a corporation's intangible asset value. It can be reckoned as the difference between its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/58829.xml">
market capitalisation</link> and its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/265292.xml">
book value</link> (by including only hard assets in it).</p>
<p>

There have been several new tools developed recently aiding in the valuation of intellectual property.  The 25% Rule, Monte Carlo Analysis, and Derivative Revenue Model (based on license revenue) are just a few of these tools.  Also, traditional methods such as Net Present Value, Internal Rate of Return, and Discounted Cash Flow can also be used.  However, these do not take into account the "book value", or "pre-revenue" asset value of non income producing intellectual property.  With the negotiability and transferability of intellectual property being liberalized by court decsions in the 1990's, several valuation specialists and merchant banking organizations have taken up valuation and market making in intellecutual property.  Essentially, treating intellectual propery instruments as another asset class for investor portfolios and treating them more like securities.  Several firms are prevalent in this field, Ocean Tomo of Chicago, Intellectual Ventures in Seattle, and Crais Management Group, LLC in New Orleans.  They have initiated auctions of intellectual property blocks.  This some have done as a percursor to their plans to create a "stock market" for intellectual property.  Patents and trademarks would be the dominant form of security traded on these exchanges.  To have an open market for intellectual property would create a more uniform and transparent form of IP valuation.  The "Bid" and "Ask" system, many believe, is the most efficient form of valuing an asset.  A "stock exchange" for intellectual property would change the face of intellectual property valuation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Valuation of mining projects</st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/20381.xml">
mining</link>, valuation is the process of determining the value or worth of a mining property.</p>
<p>

Mining valuations are sometimes required for IPO's, fairness opinions, litigation, mergers &amp; acquisitions and shareholder related matters.</p>
<p>

In valuation of a mining project or mining property, fair market value is the standard of value to be used. The CIMVal Standards are a recognised standard for valuation of mining projects and is also recognised by the Toronto Stock Exchange (Venture). The standards spearheaded by Spence &amp; Roscoe, stress the use of the cost approach, market approach and the income approach, depending on the stage of development of the mining property or project. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Asset pricing models</st>
<p>

<it>See also <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/734434.xml">
Modern portfolio theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
</it>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<market wordnetid="101097292" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/163062.xml">
Capital asset pricing model</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</theory>
</explanation>
</event>
</thinking>
</market>
</process>
 (CAPM)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/793367.xml">
Arbitrage pricing theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
 (APT)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/113515.xml">
Black-Scholes</link> (for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/9272073.xml">
options</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/6972600.xml">
Single-index model</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/11636212.xml">
Applied Information Economics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/12217885.xml">
Appraisal</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/1885799.xml">
Business valuation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/7676410.xml">
Business valuation standard</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/291268.xml">
Depreciation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<market wordnetid="101097292" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/6440284.xml">
Earnings response coefficient</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</theory>
</explanation>
</event>
</thinking>
</market>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <market wordnetid="101097292" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/164602.xml">
Efficient market hypothesis</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</market>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/63085.xml">
Equity investment</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/11941961.xml">
Intellectual property valuation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/1557851.xml">
Investment management</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/897547.xml">
Market-based valuation</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/63218.xml">
Present value</link></concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/239887.xml">
Pricing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/871336.xml">
Real estate appraisal</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/644426.xml">
Stock valuation</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Joseph Swanson and Peter Marshall, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/12566935.xml">
Houlihan Lokey</link> and Lyndon Norley, Kirkland &amp; Ellis International LLP (2008). A Practitioner's Guide to Corporate Restructuring, Andrew Miller’s Valuation of a Distressed Company page 24. ISBN: 9781905121311</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible expanded " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/614839.xml">
Corporate finance</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../118/163118.xml">
investment banking</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;  text-align:left;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/866603.xml">
Capital
structure</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;background:transparent;;;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/4213088.xml">
Senior secured debt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/6985176.xml">
Senior debt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/5285432.xml">
Second lien debt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/13306148.xml">
Subordinated debt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/1323679.xml">
Mezzanine debt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/342028.xml">
Convertible debt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/12248426.xml">
Exchangeable debt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/533478.xml">
Preferred equity</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/18960652.xml">
Shareholder loan</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/19372783.xml">
Common equity</link>&nbsp;·  <speech wordnetid="107109196" confidence="0.8">
<saying wordnetid="107151380" confidence="0.8">
<safety wordnetid="114538472" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<security wordnetid="114539268" confidence="0.8">
<motto wordnetid="107152259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/1915189.xml">
Pari passu</link></motto>
</security>
</state>
</auditory_communication>
</condition>
</safety>
</saying>
</speech>
</col>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 0px 0px 2px;" rowspan="5">
<image width="150px" src="">

</image>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;  text-align:left;;" class="navbox-group">
Transactions
(terms/conditions)</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;background:transparent;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;padding:0.15em 0; line-height:1.1em;  width:7.0em; background:#f7f7f7;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/19372783.xml">
Equity offerings</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;  width:auto;;background:#f7f7f7;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/63879.xml">
Initial public offering (IPO)</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/3795878.xml">
Secondary Market Offering (SEO)</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/6985012.xml">
Follow-on offering</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/1586842.xml">
Greenshoe</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/12676367.xml">
Reverse</link>)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/9856771.xml">
Book building</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;padding:0.15em 0; line-height:1.1em;  width:7.0em; background:#f7f7f7;;background:transparent;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/20769.xml">
Mergers andacquisitions</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;  width:auto;;background:transparent;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/56119.xml">
Takeover</link>&nbsp;·  <change_of_integrity wordnetid="100376063" confidence="0.8">
<amalgamation wordnetid="101238424" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<combination wordnetid="100378985" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<consolidation wordnetid="101237415" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/1672188.xml">
Reverse takeover</link></consolidation>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</combination>
</change>
</event>
</amalgamation>
</change_of_integrity>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/1300769.xml">
Tender offer</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/56117.xml">
Poison pill</link>&nbsp;·  <change_of_integrity wordnetid="100376063" confidence="0.8">
<amalgamation wordnetid="101238424" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<combination wordnetid="100378985" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<consolidation wordnetid="101237415" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/13330956.xml">
Freeze-out merger</link></consolidation>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</combination>
</change>
</event>
</amalgamation>
</change_of_integrity>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/14884926.xml">
Tag-along right</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/17289060.xml">
Drag-along right</link>&nbsp;·  <amalgamation wordnetid="101238424" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<security wordnetid="114539268" confidence="0.8">
<safety wordnetid="114538472" confidence="0.8">
<change_of_integrity wordnetid="100376063" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<combination wordnetid="100378985" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<consolidation wordnetid="101237415" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/12148336.xml">
Control premium</link></consolidation>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</combination>
</action>
</event>
</change_of_integrity>
</safety>
</security>
</state>
</change>
</condition>
</amalgamation>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/981983.xml">
Divestment</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/4470547.xml">
Demerger</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;padding:0.15em 0; line-height:1.1em;  width:7.0em; background:#f7f7f7;;" class="navbox-group">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/1376839.xml">
Leverage</link></concept>
</idea>
</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;  width:auto;;background:#f7f7f7;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/58834.xml">
Leveraged buyout</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/1420971.xml">
Leveraged recap</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/9621656.xml">
Financial sponsor</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/191280.xml">
Private equity</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/60737.xml">
Bond offering</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/49770.xml">
High-yield debt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/12069475.xml">
DIP financing</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;  text-align:left;;" class="navbox-group">
<market wordnetid="101097292" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/347107.xml">
Valuation</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</market>
</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;background:transparent;;;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/2844974.xml">
Financial modeling</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/426749.xml">
APV</link></concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/9023.xml">
DCF</link></concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/55345.xml">
Net present value (NPV)</link></concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/695167.xml">
Cost of capital</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/165266.xml">
Weighted average</link>)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/4732425.xml">
Comparable company analysis</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/964342.xml">
Enterprise value</link>&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/9688951.xml">
Tax shield</link></concept>
</idea>
&nbsp;·  <change_of_integrity wordnetid="100376063" confidence="0.8">
<amalgamation wordnetid="101238424" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<combination wordnetid="100378985" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<consolidation wordnetid="101237415" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/1377561.xml">
Minority interest</link></consolidation>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</combination>
</change>
</event>
</amalgamation>
</change_of_integrity>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/216476.xml">
EVA</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/1716701.xml">
MVA</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/6839462.xml">
List of investment banks</link>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/253845.xml">
List of finance topics</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</market>
</article>
