<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:22:54[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<university  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108286163">
<header>
<title>University of Hyderabad</title>
<id>3489887</id>
<revision>
<id>244687441</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-12T01:31:59Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DragonBot</username>
<id>5466012</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Central universities in India</category>
<category>Education in Hyderabad, India</category>
<category>Universities and colleges in Andhra Pradesh</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox University</name>
<parameters>

<image width="100px" src="Uhseal.png">
<caption>

Official Logo of the Hyderabad University
</caption>
</image>
<free_label>
Affiliations</free_label>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uohyd.ernet.in/">
www.uohyd.ernet.in</weblink></website>
<state>
<legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
Andhra Pradesh</link></legal_power>
</state>
<established>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/34654.xml">
1974</link></established>
<type>
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/1640986.xml">
Public</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</type>
<city>
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/37534.xml">
Hyderabad</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</village>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</city>
<country>
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
</country>
<chancellor>
Justice <link>
M N Venkata Chaliah</link></chancellor>
<vice_chancellor>
Professor Dr.<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/16586173.xml">
Seyed E Hasnain</link></vice_chancellor>
<name>
University of Hyderabad (Central university)</name>
<motto>
"Sa Vidhya Ya Vimukthaye" (In <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/27698.xml">
Sanskrit</link></language>
 for "Education results in liberation")</motto>
<postgrad_label>
post-graduate</postgrad_label>
<campus>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/764593.xml">
Urban</link></campus>
</parameters>
</template>


The <b>University of Hyderabad</b> is an institute of post-graduate teaching and research. The school was established by an act of the Parliament of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
 in 1974 as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/7125829.xml">
Central University</link>. Over the years, it has emerged as a top ranking institute of higher education and research in India. The university also offers courses under distance learning programs. The university is a member of the 'Association of Indian Universities' (AIU), the 'Association of Commonwealth Universities' (ACU) and 'International Council for Distance Education'. An Academic Staff College has been functioning on the university campus since 1988 under the UGC scheme for improving the standards of teaching in colleges and universities. The college organizes orientation and refresher courses for college and university teachers.
<sec>
<st>
 Location </st>

<p>

The university is located at GachiBowli, about 20 km from the city of <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/37534.xml">
Hyderabad</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</village>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 on the old Hyderabad-Bombay highway. Stretching over nearly 2,300&nbsp;acres (9.3&nbsp;km2) of land, the campus is the home of a variety of birds. The campus contains woods and lakes with descriptory names such as Buffalo Lake and Peacock Lake. Students find as if they are in the nature's bosom because of the lush green surroundings with beautiful rocks and lakes.The university also has a city campus, "The Golden Threshold", the residence of the late <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/133117.xml">
Sarojini Naidu</link></person>
. The Sarojini Naidu School was located at the Golden Threshold premises for nearly 15 years before it moved to the main campus in Gachibowli in 2003.  A Centre for Folk Culture Studies established with financial support from the Ford Foundation also functions from the Golden Threshold under the aegis of the SN SCHOOL  http://snschool.googlepages.com/</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Academics </st>

<p>

The university is divided into the following schools, each of which offer multiple post-graduate/research courses in their respective domains. </p>
<p>

<b>* School of Mathematics and Computer - This is further divided into two departments:</b></p>
<p>

<b># Department of Mathematics and Statistics</b> </p>
<p>

<b># Department of Computer and Information Sciences</b></p>
<p>

<b>* School of Physics</b></p>
<p>

<b>* School of Chemistry</b></p>
<p>

<b>* School of Life Sciences</b> </p>
<p>

<b>* School of Humanities</b> </p>
<p>

<b>* School of Social Sciences</b> </p>
<p>

<b>* School of Performing Arts, Fine Arts and Communications</b></p>
<p>

<b>* Sarojini Naidu School of Performing Arts, Fine Arts and Communications</b></p>
<p>

<b>* School of Management Studies</b> </p>
<p>

<b>* Study India Program</b></p>
<p>

The university offers courses like M.A, M.Sc, M.C.A, M.Tech in various disciplines. Recently, the University has decided to offer undergraduate courses as well. The [Indira Gandhi memorial Library] of the university was one of the first in the country to be completely computerised. The university offers various scholarships to top scoring students, talented students with no financial means, and physically handicapped students. The university offers facilities for campus placements. A large number of students from various courses are offered jobs through campus placements every year.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Department of mathematics and statistics</st>

<p>

The Department of   Mathematics and Statistics is a part of the School of Mathematics and Computer/Information sciences, which was established in February 1978 with Prof. M. Venkata Raman, formerly Head, Department of mathematics, Madurai University, as the first dean of the school. Currently there are 17 regular faculty members and 2 visiting faculty with research specialization cutting across the broad areas of Algebra, Analysis, Geometry, Number theory, Applied mathematics, Statistics and Operation Research.</p>
<p>

Department has a distinguished faculty  which has research collaborations with other prestigious institutes in India and abroad. These include research collaborations with other leading research institutes like TIFR, IMSc., ISI and IISc. </p>
<p>

The department has been able to receive recognition from various funding agencies. DST has selected this department under its FIST (Funds for Infrastructure in Science and Technology) (Level II) scheme. This grant is to support research in areas under Cryptology, Modelling &amp; Simulation and Dynamical Systems. The Department has also been chosen by the UGC for support under COSIST (Committee for Strengthening Infrastructure in Science &amp; Technology) programme. It is also a recipient of the Special Assistance Programme (SAP) of the UGC. The National Board of Higher Mathematics, (NBHM) has recognized our library as a regional library of the NBHM. And thus provides library grant each year for subscribing journals in Mathematics and Mathematical Statistics.</p>
<p>

The teaching here is oriented towards preparing the students to go for research in Mathematics/Statistics. Thus the students who join here get a strong background in mathematics at the M.Sc. level. Consequently students of this department consistently perform well in examinations or interviews for research fellowships in various prestigious institutes in India and abroad. Because of the through training that students receive here, they are also highly sought after in the job market even with their M.Sc. degree. Students find it a privilege to be here because of the academic environment and the facilities they have here.  </p>
<p>

The Ph.D.students of the department receives post doctoral fellowships in other reputed institutes in the country or abroad. Many of them have excelled in their careers in various organizations within the country and abroad. </p>
<p>

For more details, please visit the Department website http://mathstat.uohyd.ernet.in ( or http://172.16.16.9 from inside the University campus)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
School of Humanities</st>

<p>

School of Humanities is located near Peacock lake on campus. This school has six Departments and Two Centres. Mohan G. Ramanan, Department of English now working as a Dean of the School. Those includes</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Department of English</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Department of Philosophy</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Department of Hindi</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Department of Telugu</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Department of Urdu</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Department of Sanskrit Studies     </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Centre for Applied Linguistics and Translation Studies</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Centre for Comparative Literature </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 English Language Teaching cell </entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Department of English</st>
<p>

Ammulu university
The Department admits into its M.A. programme graduates from ANY basic discipline.  It aims at providing instruction and carrying out research in both traditional and current areas of English Studies.  In addition to core English Literature and American Literature components, it encourages work in New Literatures in English, Comparative Studies, Translation, Culture, Language Studies and Pedagogy<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>
<p>

The Department is supported by a UGC-DRS (SAP) programme which is now in its Third Phase.  The UGC has sanctioned the programme, “Assistance for Strengthening of Infrastructure for Humanities and Social Sciences (ASIHSS)” for five years, beginning April 1, 2006.     The Department has xerox machines, audio-visual equipment, and a substantial text-book library built up purely on the strength of donations from faculty, students and other well-wishers. Some P.Cs have been set aside for the use of Research  Scholars and the visually challenged. The Department’s  Multimedia Laboratory is used for the study of language, drama, media and contemporary images. </p>
<p>

Several donors have contributed financially to the Department, and scholarships and prizes like the Late Mrs. Rita Nair Award, the Dorothy Deering Prize, the Chanduri Family Scholarship/Library Fund and the Linda Dittmar Award are given  annually. Prof. Sachidananda Mohanty if presently working as the Head of the Department</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Department of Philosophy</st>

<p>

The Department is eminently known in the country for research in diverse fields of philosophy.  It has been recognised by the UGC as a Department of Special Assistance since 1987.  The thrust areas of research under this programme are (1) Philosophy of Language: Indian and Western: (2) Cognitive Science (including Logic and Philosophy of Mind).  The Department has also received grants under ASIHSS for a period of five years since April 2006 to March 2011.  The thrust areas under this scheme are (1) Philosophy of Science and (2) Moral and Political Philosophy – both from Indian and Western Perspectives.  In addition to these, the Department also carries on research in Philosophy of Wittgenstein, Contemporary Western Philosophy,  and systems of Indian Philosophy like Nyaya and Buddhism<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. The Department offers facilities of xerox and computers to all students, apart from the centralized facilities. A Raghu Rama Raju is presently working as Head of the Department for the Department of Philosophy<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Department of Hindi</st>

<p>

The Department of Hindi aims at providing teaching and research facilities in Hindi keeping in view the changing social norms, communication patterns, different social roles of language in our society and fast changing literary values in our time.  While drawing up the syllabus, sufficient care has been taken to cater to the above needs.  It has been kept flexible enough to incorporate various requirements of the students in the context of contemporary society.  Special attention is also given to the regional and comprehensive studies of language and literature<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. Presently, Shashi Mudiraj is working as the Head of the Department.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Department of Telugu</st>

<p>

The main   objective of the Department of Telugu is to prom­ote studies in Telugu Language and Literature. The Department undertakes  teaching and research in Telugu with emphasis on vari­ous aspects of historical and comparative studies in language and literature.  The syllabus for various courses is drawn keeping in view of the changing needs of the society in relation to language use, and the role of literature in the society.   An equal importance is also given for studies in Classical literature and Sanskrit, along with interdisciplinary approach<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>. B Ramabrahmam is presently working as Head of the Department. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Department of Urdu</st>

<p>

The Department of Urdu lays emphasis on the inter‑disciplinary job‑oriented education in Urdu.  It provides an atmosphere, which helps the student in developing his intel­ligence, organising ability and research aptitude. The Department also aims at developing the importance of national integration through its study and research programmes.  It also provides an atmosphere for the development of creative talents among stud­ents.  This Department is the only Department of Urdu in India having its own fully equipped Computer Lab with 12 PCs having Multimedia kits, CD read write drives, scanners and all the PCs are connected to internet<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>. Prof. Mohd. Baig Ehsas, is presently working as the Head of the Department of Urdu.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Department of Sanskrit Studies</st>

<p>

Sanskrit is a repository of unlimited invaluable knowledge of Ancient Indian Heritage.  There is an urgent need for knowledge mining from Ancient Sanskrit texts for bridge building between the past and the future through the present.  Keeping this in view, a unique research oriented Department of Sanskrit Studies was established in 2006 which will act as an interface between Sanskrit and the sub-fields of the Humanities, Social Sciences and the Sciences. Amba Kulkarniis presently working as Head of the Department.</p>
<p>

Major goals of the Department are :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To build bridges between the Ancient Indian knowledge systems and the current knowledge systems. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To explore Ancient Sciences and Technologies with a modern perspective to build alternate viable systems for the future.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To collect, preserve, and maintain the manuscripts dealing with Ancient Indian Sciences and Technology.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To train traditional scholars in order to undertake research in application oriented knowledge mining.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Centre for Applied Linguistics and Translation Studies</st>

<p>

The Centre for Applied Linguistics and Translation Studies (CALTS), created as a research centre in 1988, established a post-graduate teaching programme in 1990. CALTS specializes in language interface studies with a special emphasis on Language Technology (for which a Special Assistance Programme has been sanctioned by UGC from 2002 to 2007), translation studies, lexicography, language planning and language teaching. CALTS has three ongoing projects on language technology and machine translation funded by MCIT, Govt. of India and UPE.   Widely perceived as one of the advanced centres of teaching and research in linguistics and translation studies in the country, the Centre, jointly with IIT Kanpur, has also created a substantial computation facility for research and training in Natural Language Processing (NLP) and Machine Translation (MT).  CALTS has specialised faculty members in other areas too, which include formal syntax and semantics, historical linguistics, stylistics,  psycholinguistics  and sociolinguistics as well as specialists in different ancient and modern Indian and foreign languages, such as Sanskrit, Telugu, Tamil, Kannada, Malayalam, Marathi, Oriya, Bengali and Russian<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>. G. Uma Maheshwara Rao is presently working as Head of the Centre.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Centre for Comparative Literature</st>

<p>

The Centre for Comparative Literature functioning since 1988, aims at providing an interface between literatures and cultures with a contemporary charge. The Centre offers research programmes in M.Phil and Ph.D. The endeavour is to: encourage young learners to research expressive modes and archives of knowledge beyond those of their own culture; forge alliances with and develop sensitivity to differences in cultures and traditions; develop a critical awareness of socio-political and cultural discourses in terms of their impact on the literary and cultural studies<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. Tutun Mukherjee is presently working as the Head of the Department.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Department of political science </st>

<p>

Department of Political Science is one of the best departments in the country from both research and academic perspective. Presently there are 20 faculy working in the Department. The student, teacher ratio is 9:1 at the department of Political Science. Present Head of the Department is Prof. P Eashwaraiah.The Department of Political Science currently has Special Assistance Programme, supported by the U.G.C., in International Relations and Political Theory.  The Human Rights programme and the North East India programme are supported by the UPE project. The Department offers courses leading to M.A., M.Phil., and Ph.D. degrees. The Department has a faculty and student exchange programme with the Uppsala University, Sweden<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>. M.A, M.Phil, Ph.D programmes have been offering by the department of Political Science.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Center for the Study of Social Exclusion and Inclusive Policy</st>

<p>

Recent University Grants Commission initiation of establishing centers for the study of social exclusion in assorted universities bestow a new era to study all kinds of deprivations as one unit under social exclusion. The University of Hyderabad which is becoming world class university has been offered such one center by the UGC. Presently Director of the Center is Prof. N. Sudhakar Rao. This Center is offering M. Phil programme where seven students have joined thorugh the recent admission process<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>. From the present (2008-09) academic year the center started offering Ph. D programe with three candidates. Dr. Ramdas Rupavath, Prof. G. Sudarshanam, Sri. B. Chandrasekhar Rao, Dr. K Y Ratnam of  the Department of Political Science, Dr. Nagraj, Dr. Purender Prasad of the Department of Sociology, Sri. Laxminarayana of Department of Economics, Prof. K. P. Rao, Dr. M N Rajesh of Department of History have been appointed as temporary faculty of this new center of Social Exclusion and Inclusive Policy. </p>
<p>

This center's objectives and norms have been prepared by the UGC. Those are</p>
<p>

•Conceptualizing discrimination, exclusion and inclusion based on caste/ethnicity and religion</p>
<p>

•Developing understanding of the nature and dynamics of discrimination and exclusion</p>
<p>

•Contextualizing and problematizing discrimination, exclusion and inclusion</p>
<p>

•Developing an understanding of discrimination at an empirical level</p>
<p>

•Formulating policies for protecting the rights of these groups and eradicating the problem of exclusion and discrimination.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dcis.uohyd.ernet.in">
http://dcis.uohyd.ernet.in</weblink>Department of computer and information sciences (DCIS)</st>
<p>

DCIS is one of the major and active departments in University of Hyderabad. DCIS runs  many courses like M.tech. in Artificial Intelligence (intake 25), Computer Science(30) and Information Technology(25)(connected to IDRBT) and MCA. It consists of several labs including the Main Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Image Processing Lab, Natural and Speech Processing Lab, Enterprise application and Integration Lab, Networks and System Security Lab, Embedded System Design Lab, Software Engineering, and Web Services Lab, Project Lab consisting of thin SUN clients, Intelligent Information Retrieval Lab. These labs are well connected by an Intranet facility through Amber Cluster. Project Lab is equipied with <b>SUN machines</b> and artificial intelligence lab is equipied with high performance Muticore <b>XEON Systems</b> and  <b>IBM machines</b> with Linux operating system.</p>
<p>

The department and the members of the faculty are well known in their respective fields. <b>In fact University of Hyderabad is the only institution within the University system in India to be placed on the map of institutions known for research in Computer Science in the report published in IEEE Computer, June 1997.
</b>
All Faculties in the department has received such international and national awards including UNESCO Young Scientist Award, DST's BOYSCAST AWARD. and had served as members of Program Committees and Organising Committees of several national and international conferences. They have also served such organizations as AICTE in various capacities.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Student activities </st>
<p>

There are a total of 13 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/233996.xml">
hostel</link>s (8 for men and 5 for women) for students to stay in. There is a <b>shopping complex</b> available inside the campus for students to purchase necessary items. <b>A health care center</b> active in the campus for the needs of students, which works on the basis of 24/7.</p>
<p>

<b>DST</b> auditorium for seminar and showing documentary films shown by S.N. school. DST auditorium is on of the best auditoriums in Hyderabad having centralized A.C. . There is also an active students union which acts as a forum for students to raise their issues with the administration.</p>
<p>

Students with an interest in Electronics, Computer Science etc. can join the IEEE Student Branch UoH by joining IEEE (www.ieee.org) as student members.
Some information about their past activities can be seen here: http://www.members.tripod.com/ieeehcu/. 
More current activities can be seen here:http://dcis.uohyd.ernet.in/htmfiles/placement/images/Page%20_%2021.jpg.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Extracurricular activities </st>

<p>

A number of cultural activities are held throughout the year on the campus, some of which are held by the University Authorities, and the rest of which are held by the students themselves. <b>Sukoon</b> is an annual cultural festival where students from colleges all over Hyderabad are invited to participate. Annual sports competitions are held in various disciplines. Festivals like <vacation wordnetid="115137890" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/186177.xml">
Diwali</link></vacation>
 and Dussera are celebrated by various student groups.</p>
<p>

The university has 3 guest houses. Namely Visiting scholars, Lakeview guest house Jubilee which have excellent suits, double rooms, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/317328.xml">
dormitories</link>.</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/7125829.xml">
Central Universities of India</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 2px 0px 0px;" rowspan="1">
<image width="60px" src="Flag_of_India.svg" type="border">
<caption>

Flag of India
</caption>
</image>
</col>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/461463.xml">
Aligarh Muslim University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/11452445.xml">
Assam University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/12640625.xml">
Babasaheb Bhimrao Ambedkar University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/922696.xml">
Banaras Hindu University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/3489887.xml">
Hyderabad Central University</link>&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/8820754.xml">
Indira Gandhi National Open University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/1045779.xml">
Jamia Millia Islamia</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/1505056.xml">
Jawaharlal Nehru University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/14967227.xml">
Mahatma Gandhi Antarrashtriya Hindi Vishwavidyalaya</link></group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/1335875.xml">
Manipur University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/2966710.xml">
Maulana Azad National Urdu University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/7196223.xml">
Mizoram University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/8262011.xml">
Nagaland University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/793219.xml">
North Eastern Hill University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/8283182.xml">
Pondicherry University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/19680648.xml">
Sikkim University</link>&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/5115698.xml">
Tezpur University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/2881629.xml">
Tripura University</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/17485119.xml">
The English and Foreign Languages University</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/1595081.xml">
University of Allahabad</link>&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/1430270.xml">
University of Delhi</link></university>
&nbsp;· 
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/2189518.xml">
Visva-Bharati University</link></university>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/humanities/mission_english.html</entry>
<entry id="2">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/humanities/mission_philosophy.html</entry>
<entry id="3">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/humanities/Raghuramaraju_A.html</entry>
<entry id="4">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/humanities/mission_hindi.html</entry>
<entry id="5">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/humanities/mission_telugu.html</entry>
<entry id="6">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/humanities/mission_urdu.html</entry>
<entry id="7">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/humanities/faculty_translation_studies.html</entry>
<entry id="8">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/humanities/mission_comparative_literature.html</entry>
<entry id="9">
http://172.16.1.100/academic/school_study/social_sciences/mission_political_science.html</entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uohyd.ernet.in/pdf/results2007/w1mpei.pdf">
University Of Hyderabad</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uohyd.ernet.in/">
Official Site of the University</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hyderabaduniversity.org/">
A Cyber Joint for University Of Hyderabad Alumni</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uohyd.ernet.in/alumni/ALUMNI.htm">
Site For Alumni</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://202.41.85.161/">
School of Chemistry - A UGC Center for Advanced Studies</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.library.uohyd.ernet.in:8000/">
Indira Gandhi Memorial Library</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://202.41.85.84/">
Center for Modeling, Simulation and Design (CMSD)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://snschool.googlepages.com/">
snschool of performing arts,fine arts&amp;communication</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/29937621@N03/">
http://www.flickr.com/photos/29937621@N03/</weblink> hcu images</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/HCUmasscomm/">
Alumni of the Department of Communication, University of Hyderabad</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Universities in <legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
Andhra Pradesh</link></legal_power>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/2519092.xml">
Andhra University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/166052.xml">
Osmania University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/5299257.xml">
Kakatiya University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/582842.xml">
Acharya Nagarjuna University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/4636407.xml">
Sri Venkateswara University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/3489887.xml">
Hyderabad Central University</link>&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/13185232.xml">
Potti Sreeramulu Telugu University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/2966710.xml">
Maulana Azad National Urdu University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <link>
Adi Kavi Nannaya University</link>&nbsp;·  <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/13179137.xml">
B.R. Ambedkar Open University</link></group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/1873505.xml">
Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/4819895.xml">
Sri Krishnadevaraya University</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/3426802.xml">
NALSAR University of Law</link>&nbsp;·  <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/4227939.xml">
Acharya N. G. Ranga Agricultural University</link></group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
&nbsp;·  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/13184988.xml">
NTR University of Health Sciences</link></university>
&nbsp;·  <link>
Nalgonda University, Naldona</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
Telangana University, Nizamabad</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">

Universities and colleges in India by state or territory|Universities and colleges in India by state or territory</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</university>
</article>
