<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:23:00[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<social_group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107950920">
<society  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107966140">
<company  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108058098">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>Royal Liver Friendly Society</title>
<id>3492597</id>
<revision>
<id>243328836</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T01:49:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Friendly societies</category>
<category>Financial services companies of the United Kingdom</category>
<category>Companies based in Liverpool</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Royal Liver Assurance</b> is a multi-billion pound operation, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/403777.xml">
friendly society</link> with over 1.7 million members in the Ireland and the UK.<p>

<b>Liverpool Burial Society</b> was founded by a group of working men from Liverpool in the <link>
Lyver Inn</link> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/15888.xml">
24 July</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/34983.xml">
1850</link> to "provide for the decent interment of deceased members". By 1857 the Society had moved to its fourth head office and had expanded throughout the United Kingdom. By the end of the 1890’s a decision was taken to build what would become the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/730993.xml">
Royal Liver Building</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
; it opened on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/16091.xml">
19 July</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/34605.xml">
1911</link>.During the 20th century, Royal Liver Assurance expanded to cover the whole of the United Kingdom and the Republic of Ireland.Today, Royal Liver Assurance employs around 900 people, has approximately 3.4 million policies in force for 1.7 million members and manages more than £3.7 billion in funds. </p>
<p>

The Royal Liver Assurance has operated a delegation system since 1886; today, there are about 230 or so elected delegates.</p>
<p>

On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/1011.xml">
30 April</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>, <link>
Royal London Mutual Insurance</link> started talks over a possible merger with Royal Liver.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.royallondongroup.co.uk/media/article.asp?view=416">
http://www.royallondongroup.co.uk/media/article.asp?view=416</weblink></p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.royal-liver.com">
Royal Liver</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>




Who is Royal Liver Group?
The Royal Liver Group consists of 
1)	Royal Liver Assurance Limited an Incorporated Friendly Society, founded in Liverpool in 1850 for the mutual benefit and financial security of local families and RLA Ltd’s 3 subsidiary companies of 
2) Park Row Group plc – Financial advisors in the UK and 
3) Royal Liver Asset Managers in the UK 
and 4) Citadel Financial Advice Limited in Ireland. 
Although owned by Royal Liver, Park Row and Citadel are independent companies offering financial advice on a wide range of issues and financial services in the UK and Ireland respectively. 
The Royal Liver Group also includes 5) Progress which is a trading name for Royal Liver Assurance Limited in the UK and 6) Caledonian Life which is a trading name for Royal Liver Assurance Limited in Ireland. </p>
<p>

Royal Liver Assurance Limited is authorised and regulated by the Financial Services Authority and is a member of the Association of Mutual Insurers (AMI). 
Corporate social responsibility
The Royal Liver Poetry of Place competition sees schoolchildren write poems about their favourite Liverpool places, which are voted for by the public via the Royal Liver website.</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</group>
</company>
</society>
</social_group>
</article>
