<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:32:09[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<disease  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="114070360">
<header>
<title>Psychogenic amnesia</title>
<id>3510370</id>
<revision>
<id>236405568</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-05T07:49:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jack-A-Roe</username>
<id>5867479</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Diseases</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Disease</name>
<parameters>
<MedlinePlus>
003257</MedlinePlus>
<Name>
Psychogenic amnesia/functional amnesia/dissociative amnesia</Name>
<ICD10>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/3530350.xml">
F</link><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/classifications/apps/icd/icd10online/?gf40.htm+f440">
44.0</weblink></ICD10>
<ICD9>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.icd9data.com/getICD9Code.ashx?icd9300.1">
300.1</weblink></ICD9>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>Psychogenic amnesia</b>, also known as <b>functional</b> or <b>dissociative amnesia</b>, is a disorder characterized by abnormal memory functioning in the absence of structural brain damage or a known neurobiological cause; severe cases are very rare.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> It is defined by the presence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/1042651.xml">
retrograde amnesia</link> or the inability to retrieve stored memories and events leading up to the onset of amnesia and an absence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/530537.xml">
anterograde amnesia</link> or the inability to form new long term memories.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> In most cases, patients lose their autobiographical memory and personal identity even though they are able to learn new information and perform everyday functions normally. Other times, there may be a loss of basic semantic knowledge and procedural skills such as reading and writing.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

There are two types of psychogenic amnesia, global and situation-specific.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  Global amnesia, also known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/10898.xml">
fugue state</link>,  refers to a sudden loss of personal identity that lasts a few hours to days. This is preceded by severe stress and/or depressed mood. Fugue state is very rare, and usually resolves over time, often helped by therapy. Situation-specific amnesia is a type of dissociative amnesia occurs as a result of a severely stressful event, as in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/82974.xml">
post-traumatic stress disorder</link>.  Dissociative amnesia is due to psychological rather than physiological causes and can sometimes be helped by therapy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
 Memory and the brain </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/18844.xml">
Memory</link></it>
</indent>
There are three types of memory – sensory, short-term, and long-term memory. Sensory memory lasts up to hundreds of milliseconds and short-term memory lasts from seconds to minutes while anything else longer than short-term memory is considered to be a long-term memory.</p>
<p>

The information obtained from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/25096.xml">
peripheral nervous system</link> (PNS) is processed in four stages - encoding, consolidating, storage, and retrieval. During encoding, the limbic system is responsible for bottlenecking or filtering information obtained from the PNS. According to the type of information given, the duration of consolidating stage varies drastically. Majority of consolidated information gets stored in the cerebral cortical networks where the limbic system record episodic-autobiographical events. These stored episodic and semantic memories can be obtained by triggering the uncinate fascicle that interconnects the regions of the temporofrontal junction area.</p>
<p>

Emotion seems to play an important role in memory processing in structures like the cingulated gyrus, the septal nuclei, and the amygdala that is primarily involved in emotional memories.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> Functional imaging of normal patients reveal that right-hemisperic amygdala and ventral prefrontal regions are activated when they were retrieving autobiographical information and events. Additionally, the hippocampal region is known to be linked to recognizing faces.
Researchers have found that emotional memories can be suppressed in non-mentally ill individuals via the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/1967493.xml">
prefrontal cortex</link> in two stages - an initial suppression of the sensory aspects of the memory, followed by a a suppression of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/10406.xml">
emotion</link>al aspect.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>  It has also been proposed that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/530691.xml">
glucocorticoid</link>s can impair memory retrieval, though to date this has only been tested in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/26471.xml">
rat</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

Traumas can interfere with several memory functions. van der Kolk divided these functional disturbances into four sets, traumatic amnesia, global memory impairment, dissociative processes and traumatic memories' sensorimotor organization. Traumatic amnesia involves the loss of remembering traumatic experiences. The younger the subject and the longer the traumatic event is, the greater the chance of significant amnesia. Global memory impairment makes it difficult for these subjects to construct an accurate account of their present and past history. Dissociation refers to memories being stored as fragments and not as unitary wholes. Not being able to integrate traumatic memories seems to be the main element which leads to PTSD.  In the sensorimotor organization of traumatic memories, sensations are fragmented into different sensory components.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Psychogenic and organic amnesia </st>
<p>

Clinically, psychogenic amnesia is characterized by the loss of the ability to retrieve stored memory without having damages to the brain while organic amnesia is characterized by damages to the medial or anterior temporal and/or prefrontal regions caused by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/625404.xml">
stroke</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/1057414.xml">
traumatic brain injury</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/490305.xml">
ischemia</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/37636.xml">
encephalitis</link>.  Some characteristics that define organic amnesia is the maintenance of personal identity, basic semantic knowledge and procedural skills as well as neuroradiological images showing cerebral damage to the cortical and/or subcortical areas known to be associated with long-term memory while some characteristics that define psychogenic amnesia is the loss of personal identity, semantic knowledge, and procedural abilities at least in the early phase of amnesia as well as damage directly affecting cerebral areas critical for memory functioning that cannot be detected in clinical history or neuroradiological exams.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Imaging of psychogenic amnesia</st>
<p>
 
Psychogenic amnesia is defined by the lack of structural damage to the brain, but upon <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/234714.xml">
functional imaging</link>, an abnormal brain activity can be seen.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> Tests using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/226722.xml">
functional magnetic resonance imaging</link> suggest that patients with psychogenic amnesia are unable to retrieve emotional memories normally during the amnesic period, suggesting that changes in the limbic functions are related to the symptoms of psychogenic amnesia.  By performing a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/24032.xml">
positron emission tomography</link> activation study on psychogenic amnesic patients with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/485309.xml">
face recognition</link>, it was found that activation of the right anterior medial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/466322.xml">
temporal region</link> including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/146000.xml">
amygdala</link> was increased in the patient whereas bilateral <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml">
hippocampal</link> regions increased only in the control subjects, demonstrating again that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/200405.xml">
limbic</link> and limbic-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/6082.xml">
cortical</link> functions are related to the symptoms of psychogenic amnesia.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Risk factors </st>
<p>

Patients exposed to physically or emotionally traumatic events  and are at a higher risk for developing psychogenic amnesia because they seem to damage the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/21120.xml">
neuron</link>s in toto in the brain.  Examples of individuals at greater risk of psychogenic amnesia due to traumatic events include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/37338.xml">
soldier</link>s who have experienced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/43702.xml">
combat</link>, individuals <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/7397019.xml">
sexually</link> and <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/526609.xml">
physically abused</link></disease>
 during <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/167331.xml">
childhood</link> and individuals who have been experienced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/18978563.xml">
domestic violence</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/58921.xml">
natural disaster</link>s, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/30636.xml">
terrorist acts</link>; essentially any sufficiently severe psychological stress, internal conflicts, or intolerable life situation.  Child abuse, especially chronic child abuse starting at an early age has been related to the development of high levels of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/529089.xml">
dissociative</link> symptoms, including amnesia for abuse memories. The study strongly suggested that "independent corroboration of recovered memories of abuse is often present" and that the recovery of the abuse memories generally is not associated with psychotherapy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Theoretical explanations </st>
<p>

Psychogenic amnesia is far from being completely understood and while several explanations have been proposed, none of them have been verified as the mechanism that fits all types of psychogenic amnesia.  Different theories include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/23585.xml">
Freudian psychology</link> states that psychogenic amnesia is an act of self-preservation, an alternative to suicide.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/5961.xml">
Cognitive</link> point-of-view states that this disorder utilizes the body’s personal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantic</link> belief system to repress unwanted memories from entering the consciousness by altering <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/984726.xml">
neuropeptide</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/21865.xml">
neurotransmitter</link>s released during stressful events, affecting the formation and recall of memory.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Betrayal trauma theory suggests that psychogenic amnesia is an adaptive response to childhood abuse. When a parent or other powerful figure violates a fundamental ethic of human relationships, victims may need to remain unaware of the trauma not to reduce suffering but rather to promote survival. Amnesia enables the child to maintain an attachment with a figure vital to survival, development, and thriving. Analysis of evolutionary pressures, mental modules, social cognitions, and developmental needs suggests that the degree to which the most fundamental human ethics are violated can influence the nature, form, and processes of trauma and responses to trauma."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Normal autobiographical memory processing is blocked by imbalance or altered release of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/5235623.xml">
stress hormone</link>s such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/530691.xml">
glucocorticoid</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/530700.xml">
mineralocorticoid</link>s in the brain.  The regions of expanded <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/200405.xml">
limbic system</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/406608.xml">
right hemisphere</link> are more vulnerable to stress and trauma, affecting the body's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/511394.xml">
opioid</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/13311.xml">
hormone</link>s, and neurotransmitters such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/9903342.xml">
norepinephrine</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/28764.xml">
serotonin</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/984731.xml">
neuropeptide Y</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>  Increased levels of glucocorticoid and mineralocorticoid receptor density may affect the anterior temporal, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/3766002.xml">
orbitofrontal cortex</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml">
hippocampal</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/146000.xml">
amygdala</link>r regions. These morphological changes may be caused by loss of regulation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/159266.xml">
gene expression</link>s in those receptors along with inhibition of neurotrophic factors during chronic stress conditions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/146072.xml">
Stress</link> may directly affects the medial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/466322.xml">
temporal</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/761575.xml">
diencephalic</link> system, inhibiting the retrieval of autobiographical memories and producing a loss of personal identity.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/213328.xml">
Negative feedback</link> produced by this system may dampen the patient's emotions, giving a perplexed or 'flat' appearance.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Treatments </st>
<p>

Currently, various treatments are available for patients with psychogenic amnesia although no well-controlled studies on the effectiveness of different treatments exist.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/23585.xml">
Psychoanalysis</link> - uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/50400.xml">
dream analysis</link>, interpretation and other psychoanalytic methods to retrieve memories; may also involve placing patients in threatening situations where they are overwhelmed with intense emotion. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/180121.xml">
Medication</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/1837058.xml">
relaxation technique</link>s - in conjunction with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/4781.xml">
benzodiazepine</link>s and other hypnotic medications, the patient is urged to relax and attempt to recall memories.  With the help of psychotherapy and learning their autobiographies from family members, most patients recover their memories completely.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

It has been proposed that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/7338732.xml">
abreaction</link> could be used in conjunction with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/646748.xml">
midazolam</link> to recover memories.  This technique was used the <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
second World War</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
 but is currently much less popular.  The technique is thought to work either through depressing the function of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/58686.xml">
cerebral cortex</link> and therefore making the memory more tolerable when expressed, or through relieving the strength of an emotion attached to a memory which is so intense it suppresses memory function.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Some studies about psychogenic amnesia have concluded that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/24931.xml">
psychotherapy</link> is not connected to recovered memories of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/18721790.xml">
child sexual abuse</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>Data suggests that one’s amnesic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/509678.xml">
recovered memory</link> is spontaneous, and that this is triggered by abuse-related stimuli.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Popular culture</st>
<p>

Psychogenic amnesia is a common plot device in many films and books.  Notable examples include the character of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/902251.xml">
Jason Bourne</link>, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<singer wordnetid="110599806" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/144936.xml">
Jackie Chan</link></actor>
</singer>
</person>
 in <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/190053.xml">
Who Am I?</link></movie>
</it> and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../071/48071.xml">
Goldie Hawn</link></actor>
</person>
 in <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/2209172.xml">
Overboard</link></movie>
</it>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/354031.xml">
Depersonalization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/2413401.xml">
Dissociative disorders</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/10898.xml">
Fugue state</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Brandt J, Van Gorp WG&#32;(2006).&#32;"Functional ("psychogenic") amnesia". <it>Semin Neurol</it>&#32;<b>26</b>&#32;(3): 331–40. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1055%2Fs-2006-945519">
10.1055/s-2006-945519</weblink>. PMID 16791779.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Markowitsch HJ&#32;(2003).&#32;"Psychogenic amnesia". <it>Neuroimage</it>&#32;<b>20 Suppl 1</b>: S132–8. PMID 14597306.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Yasuno F, Nishikawa T, Nakagawa Y, et al&#32;(2000).&#32;"Functional anatomical study of psychogenic amnesia". <it>Psychiatry Res</it>&#32;<b>99</b>&#32;(1): 43–57. PMID 10891648.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Mackenzie Ross S&#32;(2000).&#32;"Profound retrograde amnesia following mild head injury: organic or functional?". <it>Cortex</it>&#32;<b>36</b>&#32;(4): 521–37. PMID 11059453.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Serra L, Fadda L, Buccione I, Caltagirone C, Carlesimo GA&#32;(2007).&#32;"Psychogenic and organic amnesia: a multidimensional assessment of clinical, neuroradiological, neuropsychological and psychopathological features". <it>Behav Neurol</it>&#32;<b>18</b>&#32;(1): 53–64. PMID 17297220.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kopelman MD&#32;(2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/125/10/2152">
Disorders of memory</weblink>". <it>Brain</it>&#32;<b>125</b>&#32;(Pt 10): 2152–90. PMID 12244076. Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-05</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
Myers, Catherine E.&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.memorylossonline.com/glossary/psychogenicamnesia.html">
Memory Loss &amp; The Brain</weblink>".&#32;  <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/80135.xml">
Rutgers University</link></university>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-12-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Yang JC, Jeong GW, Lee MS, et al&#32;(2005).&#32;"Functional MR imaging of psychogenic amnesia: a case report". <it>Korean J Radiol</it>&#32;<b>6</b>&#32;(3): 196–9. PMID 16145296.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Depue BE, Curran T, Banich MT&#32;(2007).&#32;"Prefrontal regions orchestrate suppression of emotional memories via a two-phase process". <it>Science</it>&#32;<b>317</b>&#32;(5835): 215–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126%2Fscience.1139560">
10.1126/science.1139560</weblink>. PMID 17626877.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Roozendaal B, de Quervain DJ, Schelling G, McGaugh JL&#32;(2004).&#32;"A systemically administered beta-adrenoceptor antagonist blocks corticosterone-induced impairment of contextual memory retrieval in rats". <it>Neurobiol Learn Mem</it>&#32;<b>81</b>&#32;(2): 150–4. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.nlm.2003.10.001">
10.1016/j.nlm.2003.10.001</weblink>. PMID 14990235.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">van der Kolk BA, Fisler R&#32;(1995).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.trauma-pages.com/a/vanderk2.php">
Dissociation and the fragmentary nature of traumatic memories: overview and exploratory study</weblink>". <it>J Trauma Stress</it>&#32;<b>8</b>&#32;(4): 505–25. PMID 8564271. Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-22</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
  <cite style="font-style:normal">Heilbronner, R; Martelli, MF, Nicholson, K, Zasler, ND&#32;(2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://villamartelli.com/CCPN2006Handout1.pdf">
Brain injury and functional disorders part IV</weblink>"&#32;(pdf). <it>Journal of Controversial Medical Claims</it>&#32;<b>9</b>&#32;(3): 1–7. Retrieved on <link>
2007-12-05</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Chu JA, Frey LM, Ganzel BL, Matthews JA&#32;(1999).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/content/full/156/5/749">
Memories of childhood abuse: dissociation, amnesia, and corroboration</weblink>". <it>Am J Psychiatry</it>&#32;<b>156</b>&#32;(5): 749–55. PMID 10327909.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Freyd, J.&#32;(1994).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.questia.com/read/95814385">
Betrayal Trauma: Traumatic Amnesia as an Adaptive Response to Childhood Abuse.</weblink>". <it>Ethics &amp; Behavior</it>&#32;<b>4</b>&#32;(4): 307–330. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1207%2Fs15327019eb0404_1">
10.1207/s15327019eb0404_1</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-13</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Reinhold, N; Kuehnel, S, Brand, M &amp; Markowitsch, HJ&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/ben/cmir/2006/00000002/00000001/art00004">
Functional neuroimaging in memory and memory disturbances</weblink>". <it>Current Medical Imaging Reviews</it>&#32;<b>2</b>&#32;(1): 35–57. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2174%2F157340506775541668">
10.2174/157340506775541668</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2007-12-05</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Albach, Francine; Peter Paul Moormann, Bob Bermond&#32;(Dec-1996).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1794/1774">
Memory recovery of childhood sexual abuse</weblink>". <it>Dissociation</it>&#32;<b>Vol. 9, No. 4, p. 261-273</b>. <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<identifier wordnetid="107270601" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/234930.xml">
ISSN</link></system_of_measurement>
</identifier>
</signal>
</standard>
</symbol>
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://worldcat.org/issn/0896-2863">
0896-2863</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-03</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Vattakatuchery, JJ; Chesterman, P&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informaworld.com/smpp/432725912-4932359/content~content=a759276300~db=all~order=page">
The use of abreaction to recover memories in psychogenic amnesia: A case report</weblink>". <it>Journal of Forensic Psychiatry and Psychology</it>&#32;<b>17</b>&#32;(4): 647–653. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080%2F14789940600965938">
10.1080/14789940600965938</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2007-12-05</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brown.edu/Departments/Taubman_Center/Recovmem/">
Recovered Memory Project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.leadershipcouncil.org/1/tm/prev.html">
Summary of Research Examining the Prevalence of Full or Partial  Dissociative Amnesia for Traumatic Events</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

[https://scholarsbank.uoregon.edu/dspace/handle/1794/1129  The official journal of the International Society for the Study of Dissociation (ISSD), published between 1988 and 1997]</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sidran.org/">
Sidran Institute - PTSD and Dissociation Resources for Survivors, Supporters and Professionals</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://boundless.uoregon.edu/digcol/diss/index.html">
Dissociation and Trauma Archives - Full text searchable articles and case studies published in the 1800s and early 1900s.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</disease>
</entity>
</article>
