<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:26:15[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Transistor models</title>
<id>3518436</id>
<revision>
<id>235711646</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-02T00:49:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Toffile</username>
<id>290968</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Transistor modeling</category>
<category>Electronic engineering</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/30011.xml">
Transistor</link>s are complicated devices. In order to ensure the reliable operation of circuits employing transistors, it is necessary to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
 scientifically model</link> the physical phenomena observed in their operation using <b>transistor models</b>. There exists a variety of different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
models</link> that range in complexity and in purpose. Transistor models divide into two major groups: models for device design and models for circuit design.
<sec>
<st>
Models for device design</st>
<p>

The modern transistor has an internal structure that exploits complex physical mechanisms. Device design requires a detailed understanding of how device manufacturing processes such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/15539.xml">
ion implantation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/2684031.xml">
impurity diffusion</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/8556260.xml">
oxide growth</link>, <link>
annealing</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/8726682.xml">
etching</link> affect device behavior. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/5275369.xml">
Process models</link>  simulate the manufacturing steps and provide a microscopic description of device "geometry" to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/5326978.xml">
device simulator</link>. By "geometry" is meant not only readily identified geometrical features such as whether the gate is planar or wrap-around, or whether the source and drain are raised or recessed (see Figure 1 for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/173874.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22The_floating-gate_transistor%22])">
memory device</link> with some unusual modeling challenges related to charging the floating gate by an avalanche process), but also details inside the structure, such as the doping profiles after completion of device processing.
<image width="150px" src="FAMOS_esq.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 1: Floating-gate avalanche injection memory device FAMOS
</caption>
</image>

With this information about what the device looks like, the device simulator models the physical processes taking place in the device to determine its electrical behavior in a variety of circumstances: DC current-voltage behavior, transient behavior (both large-signal and small-signal), dependence on device layout (long and narrow versus short and wide, or interdigitated versus rectangular, or isolated versus proximate to other devices). These simulations tell the device designer whether the device process will produce devices with the electrical behavior needed by the circuit designer, and is used to inform the process designer about any necessary process improvements. Once the process gets close to manufacture, the predicted device characteristics are compared with measurement on test devices to check that the process and device models are working adequately.</p>
<p>

Although long ago the device behavior modeled in this way was very simple - mainly drift plus diffusion in simple geometries - today many more processes must be modeled at a microscopic level; for example, leakage currents in junctions and oxides, complex transport of carriers including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/7586919.xml">
velocity saturation</link> and ballistic transport, quantum mechanical effects, use of multiple materials (for example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/662175.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22SiGe_Transistors%22])">
Si-SiGe</link> devices, and stacks of different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/2332464.xml">
dielectrics</link>) and even the statistical effects due to the probabilistic nature of ion placement and carrier transport inside the device. Several times a year the technology changes and simulations have to be repeated. The models may require change to reflect new physical effects, or to provide greater accuracy. The maintenance and improvement of these models is a business in itself.</p>
<p>

These models are very computer intensive, involving detailed spatial and temporal solutions of coupled partial differential equations on three-dimensional grids inside the device.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>
Such models are slow to run and provide detail not needed for circuit design. Therefore, faster transistor models oriented toward circuit parameters are used for circuit design.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Models for circuit design (<it>compact</it> models)</st>
<p>

Transistor models are used for almost all modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/216881.xml">
electronic design</link> work. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/1665281.xml">
Analog circuit</link> <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/10900720.xml">
simulators</link></format>
</information>
</message>
 such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/180251.xml">
SPICE</link> use models to predict the behavior of a design. Most design work is related to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/2951035.xml">
integrated circuit design</link>s which have a very large tooling cost, primarily for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/642903.xml">
photomask</link>s used to create the devices, and there is a large economic incentive to get the design working without any iterations. Complete and accurate models allow a large percentage of designs to work the first time.</p>
<p>

Modern circuits are usually very complex. The performance of such circuits is difficult to predict without accurate computer models, including but not limited to models of the devices used. The device models include effects of transistor layout: width, length, interdigitation, proximity to other devices; transient and DC <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/2572375.xml">
current-voltage characteristic</link>s; parasitic device capacitance, resistance, and inductance; time delays; and temperature effects; to name a few items. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Large-signal nonlinear models</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/146103.xml">
Nonlinear</link>, or large signal transistor models fall into three main types:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>
</p>
<ss2>
<st>
Physical models</st>
<p>
 
<indent level="1">

 These are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/5326978.xml">
models based upon  device physics</link>, based upon approximate modeling of physical phenomena within a transistor.  Parameters within these models are based upon physical properties such as oxide thicknesses, substrate doping concentrations, carrier mobility, etc. In the past these models were used extensively, but the complexity of modern devices makes them inadequate for quantitative design. Nonetheless, they find a place in hand analysis (that is, at the conceptual stage of circuit design), for example, for simplified estimates of signal-swing limitations.
</indent>

</p>
</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Empirical models</st>
<p>
 
<indent level="1">

 This type of model is entirely based upon <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/555425.xml">
curve fitting</link>, using whatever functions and parameter values most adequately fit measured data to enable simulation of transistor operation.  Unlike a physical model, the parameters in an empirical model need have no fundamental basis, and will depend on the fitting procedure used to find them. The fitting procedure is key to success of these models if they are to be used to extrapolate to designs lying outside the range of data to which the models were originally fitted. Such extrapolation is a hope of such models, but is not fully realized so far.
</indent>
====Tabular models==== 
<indent level="1">

 The third type of model is a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/356457.xml">
look-up table</link> containing a large number of values for common device parameters such as drain current and device parasitics.  These values are indexed in reference to their corresponding bias voltage combinations.  Thus, model accuracy is increased by inclusion of additional data points within the table.  The chief advantage of this type of model is decreased simulation time (see article <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/356457.xml">
look-up table</link> for discussion of the computational advantages of look-up tables). A limitation of these models is that they work best for designs that use devices within the table (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/14569.xml">
interpolation</link>) and are unreliable for devices outside the table (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/546415.xml">
extrapolation</link>).
</indent>

The use of nonlinear models, which describe the entire operating area of a transistor, is required for digital designs, for circuits that operate in a large-signal regime such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/3214.xml">
power amplifier</link>s and <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<electrical_device wordnetid="103269401" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<circuit wordnetid="103033362" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/9924.xml">
mixers</link></circuit>
</device>
</electrical_device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
, and for the large-signal simulation of any circuit, for example, for stability or distortion analysis.</p>
<p>

Nonlinear models are used with a computer simulation program, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/180251.xml">
SPICE</link>. The models in SPICE are a hybrid of physical and empirical models, and such models are incomplete unless they include specification of how parameter values are to be extracted, especially as "unrealistic" (that is, unphysical) values can be made to fit the measured data without such a prescription. An incorrect set of fitting parameters results in wild predictions for devices that were not part of the originally fitted data set.</p>
<p>

Large-signal computer models for devices continually evolve to keep up with changes in technology. To attempt standardization of model parameters used in different simulators, an industry working group was formed, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/14664694.xml">
Compact Model Council</link>, to choose, maintain and promote the use of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geia.org/index.asp?bid=1333">
standard models</weblink>. An elusive goal in such modeling is prediction of how circuits using the next generation of devices should work, to identify before the next step which direction the technology should take, and have models ready beforehand.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Small-signal linear models</st>
<p>
  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/1731760.xml">
Small-signal</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/722503.xml">
linear</link> models are used to evaluate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/1145733.xml">
stability</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/41968.xml">
gain</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/3966982.xml">
noise</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/3967.xml">
bandwidth</link>, both in the conceptual stages of circuit design (to decide between alternative design ideas before computer simulation is warranted) and using computers.  A small-signal model is generated by taking derivatives of the current-voltage curves about a bias point or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/7458892.xml">
Q-point</link>.  As long as the signal is small relative to the nonlinearity of the device, the derivatives do not vary significantly, and can be treated as standard linear circuit elements. 
A big advantage of small signal models is they can be solved directly, while large signal nonlinear models are generally solved iteratively, with possible <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<equation wordnetid="106669864" confidence="0.8">
<mathematical_statement wordnetid="106732169" confidence="0.8">
<link>
convergence or stability</link></mathematical_statement>
</equation>
</message>
</statement>
 issues.  By simplification to a linear model, the whole apparatus for solving linear equations becomes available, for example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/249617.xml">
simultaneous equations</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/8468.xml">
determinant</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/246323.xml">
matrix theory</link> (often studied as part of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/18422.xml">
linear algebra</link>), especially <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<theorem wordnetid="106752293" confidence="0.8">
<proposition wordnetid="106750804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/166008.xml">
Cramer's rule</link></proposition>
</theorem>
</message>
</statement>
. Another advantage is that a linear model is easier to think about, and helps to organize thought.</p>

<ss3>
<st>
Small-signal parameters</st>
<p>

A transistor’s parameters represent its electrical properties.  Engineers employ transistor parameters in production-line testing and in circuit design.  A group of a transistor’s parameters sufficient to predict circuit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/41968.xml">
gain</link>, input <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/41957.xml">
impedance</link>, and output <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/41957.xml">
impedance</link> are components in its small-signal model.  </p>
<p>

Parameters used in small-signal circuits (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/1301093.xml">
two ports</link>) adopt names related to the names of these circuits such as</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Transmission parameters</link> (T-parameters),</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Hybrid-parameters</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 (h-parameters),</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/10087500.xml">
Impedance parameters</link> (z-parameters),</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/10058495.xml">
Admittance parameters</link> (y-parameters), and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/1972332.xml">
Scattering parameters</link> (S-parameters).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

These parameters all can be evaluated using measured <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/1972332.xml">
scattering parameter</link> data.  Scattering parameters, or S parameters, can be measured for a transistor at a given bias point with a <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/1972332.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Measurement+of+S-parameters%22])">
vector network analyzer</link></network>
</group>
</system>
.</p>

</ss3>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Popular models</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Gummel–Poon model</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/49338.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Ebers=E2=80=93Moll_model%22])">
Ebers–Moll model</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-device.eecs.berkeley.edu/~bsim3">
BSIM3</weblink> (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/14661086.xml">
BSIM</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-device.eecs.berkeley.edu/~bsim3/bsim4.html">
BSIM4</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-device.eecs.berkeley.edu/~bsimsoi">
BSIMSOI</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/14860424.xml">
EKV MOSFET Model</link> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://legwww.epfl.ch/ekv/">
its web site at <link>
EPFL</link></weblink>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pspmodel.asu.edu/">
PSP</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iee.et.tu-dresden.de/iee/eb/hic_new/hic_start.html">
HICUM</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mextram.ewi.tudelft.nl/">
MEXTRAM</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/13618652.xml">
Hybrid-pi model</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link>
H-parameter model</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Carlo Jacoboni, Paolo Lugli&#32;(1989). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=3cWnyhKmACEC&amp;pg=PP1&amp;dq=isbn:3211821104&amp;sig=TCFY-o_l5gLj8OblcwGgQeB4Xts">
The Monte Carlo Method for Semiconductor Device Simulation</weblink>.&#32;Wien:&#32;Springer-Verlag. ISBN 3211821104.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Siegfried Selberherr&#32;(1984). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=EE4HlRZTYi4C&amp;pg=PA97&amp;dq=isbn:3211818006&amp;sig=19_iT2-C0gy8WdBIPcLc7gRAXw8#PPP1,M1">
Analysis and Simulation of Semiconductor Devices</weblink>.&#32;Wien:&#32;Springer-Verlag. ISBN 3211818006.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Tibor Grasser (Editor)&#32;(2003). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=HBkA3_pZMp4C&amp;dq=%22MOSFET++simulation%22&amp;as_brr=0">
Advanced Device Modeling and Simulation (Int. J. High Speed Electron. and Systems)</weblink>.&#32;World Scientific. ISBN 9812386076.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Kramer, Kevin M. and Hitchon, W. Nicholas G.&#32;(1997). Semiconductor devices: a simulation approach.&#32;Upper Saddle River, NJ:&#32;Prentice Hall PTR. ISBN 0-13-614330-X.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Dragica Vasileska, Stephen Goodnick&#32;(2006). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=DBPnzqy5Fd8C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=%22gate+tunneling%22&amp;as_brr=0#PPA83,M1">
Computational Electronics</weblink>.&#32;Morgan &amp; Claypool,&#32;p .83. ISBN 1598290568.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Carlos Galup-Montoro, Mǻrcio C Schneider&#32;(2007). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=yrrDcRm9bfUC&amp;pg=PA293&amp;dq=%22gate+tunneling%22&amp;as_brr=0&amp;sig=SJv5PSqaLbMdw10sEQPFd3ykN8E#PPA1,M1">
Mosfet Modeling for Circuit Analysis And Design</weblink>.&#32;World Scientific. ISBN 9812568107.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Narain Arora&#32;(2007). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=SkT2xOuvpuYC&amp;dq=%22table+lookup+model%22&amp;as_brr=0">
Mosfet Modeling for VLSI Simulation: Theory And Practice</weblink>.&#32;World Scientific,&#32;Chapter 1. ISBN 981256862X.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Yannis Tsividis&#32;(1999). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://worldcat.org/isbn/0070655235">
Operational Modeling of the MOS Transistor</weblink>, Second Edition,&#32;New York:&#32;McGraw-Hill. ISBN 0-07-065523-5.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Agilent EEsof EDA, IC-CAP Parameter Extraction and Device Modeling Software http://eesof.tm.agilent.com/products/iccap_main.html</it></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/49338.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Theory+and+modeling%22])">
Bipolar junction transistor#Theory and modeling</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/1972332.xml">
S-parameters</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/1731760.xml">
Small-signal model</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/180251.xml">
SPICE</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/1301093.xml">
Two-port network</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/976730.xml">
Safe operating area</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/216881.xml">
Electronic design automation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/10900720.xml">
Electronic circuit simulation</link></format>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/5326978.xml">
Semiconductor device modeling</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
