<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:52:55[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Limit state design</title>
<id>352354</id>
<revision>
<id>231660007</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-13T11:16:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>JAnDbot</username>
<id>1725149</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> Civil engineering</category>
<category>Structural engineering</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Limit state design</b> (LSD) refers to a design methodology used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/45829.xml">
structural engineering</link>.  The methodology is in fact a modernization and rationalization of engineering knowledge which was well established prior to the adoption of LSD.  Beyond the concept of a limit state, LSD simply entails the application of statistics to determine the level of safety required by or during the design process.
<sec>
<st>
Criteria</st>
<p>

Limit state <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/8560.xml">
design</link> requires the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/93545.xml">
structure</link> to satisfy two principal criteria: the <link>
ultimate limit</link> state (ULS) and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/13192028.xml">
serviceability limit</link> state (SLS). A limit state is a set of performance criteria  (e.g. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/22522.xml">
vibration</link> levels, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/1272169.xml">
deflection</link>, strength, stability, buckling, twisting, collapse) that must be met when the structure is subject to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/3633309.xml">
loads</link>. </p>
<p>

Any design process involves a number of assumptions.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/41323.xml">
load</link>s to which a structure will be subjected must be estimated, sizes of members to check must be chosen and design criteria must be selected.  All engineering design criteria have a common goal: that of ensuring a safe and   functional structure.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ultimate Limit State</st>
<p>

To satisfy the ultimate limit state, the structure must not collapse when subjected to the peak <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/3584524.xml">
design load</link> for which it was designed.  A structure is deemed to satisfy the ultimate limit state criteria if all factored <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/1255570.xml">
bending</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/437619.xml">
shear</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/228107.xml">
tensile</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/424487.xml">
compressive</link> stresses are below the factored resistance calculated for the section under consideration.  The limit state criteria can also be set in terms of stress rather than load. Thus the structural element being analysed (e.g. a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/630099.xml">
beam</link> or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/6920.xml">
column</link> or other load bearing element, such as walls) is shown to be safe when the factored loads are less than their factored resistance.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Serviceability Limit State</st>
<p>

To satisfy the serviceability limit state criteria, a structure must remain functional for its intended use subject to routine (read: everyday) loading, and as such the structure must not cause <link>
occupant discomfort</link> under routine conditions.  A structure is deemed to satisfy the serviceability limit state when the constituent elements do not deflect by more than certain limits laid down in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/537481.xml">
building code</link>s, the floors fall within predetermined <link>
vibration criteria</link>, in addition to other possible requirements as required by the applicable building code. Examples of further serviceability limit requirements may include crack widths in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/5371.xml">
concrete</link>, which typically must be kept below specified dimensions.  A structure where the serviceability requirements are not met, e.g. the beams deflect by more than the SLS limit, will not necessarily <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/352322.xml">
fail structurally</link>. The purpose of SLS requirements is to ensure that people in the structure are not unnerved by large deflections of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/82926.xml">
floor</link>, vibration caused by walking, sickened by excessive swaying of the building during high winds, or by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/3397.xml">
bridge</link> swaying from side to side and to keep beam deflections low enough to ensure that brittle finishes on the ceiling above do not crack, affecting the appearance and longevity of the structure. Many of these limits depend on the finish materials (sheetrock, acoustical tile) selected by the architect, as such, the limits in the building codes on deflections are generally descriptive and leave the choice to the engineer of record (this may not be as true outside the U.S.)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Factor Development</st>
<p>

The load and resistance factors are determined using statistics and a pre-selected probability of failure. Variability in the quality of construction, consistency of the construction material are accounted for in the factors.  A factor of unity (one) or less is applied to the resistances of the material, and a factor of unity or greater to the loads.  These factors can differ significantly for different materials or even between differing grades of the same material.  Wood and masonry typically have smaller factors than concrete, which in turn has smaller factors than steel. The factors applied to resistance also account for the degree of scientific confidence in the derivation of the values - i.e. smaller values are used when there isn't much research on the specific type of failure mode). Factors associated with loads are normally independent on the type of material involved, but can be influenced by the type of construction. </p>
<p>

In determining the specific magnitude of the factors, more deterministic loads (like dead loads, the weight of the structure and permanent attachments like walls, floor treatments, ceiling finishes) are given lower factors (for example 1.4) than highly variable loads like earthquake, wind, or live (occupancy) loads (1.6). Impact loads are typically given higher factors still (say 2.0) in order to account for both their unpredictable magnitudes and the dynamic nature of the loading vs. the static nature of most models. While arguably not philosophically superior to permissible or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/1877149.xml">
allowable stress design</link>, it does have the potential to produce a more consistently designed structure as each element is intended to have the same probability of failure. In practical terms this normally results in a more efficient structure, and as such, it can be argued that LSD is superior from a practical engineering viewpoint</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Example Treatment of LSD in Codes</st>
<p>

The following is the treatment of LSD found in the <written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106667317" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/1110664.xml">
National Building Code of Canada</link></code>
</written_communication>
:</p>
<p>

NBCC 1995 Format
φR &amp;gt; αDD + ψ γ {αLL + αQQ + αTT}</p>
<p>

where φ = Resistance Factor
ψ = Load Combination Factor
γ = Importance Factor      
αD = Dead Load Factor
αL = Live Load Factor
αQ = Earthquake Load Factor
αT = Thermal Effect (Temperature) Load Factor</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The State of the Art</st>
<p>

Limit state design has replaced the older concept of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/1877149.xml">
permissible stress design</link> in most forms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ar)/5762_(H$ebrew_year).xml">
civil engineering</link>. Notable exceptions are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/12306.xml">
geotechnical engineering</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/50571.xml">
transportation engineering</link>.  Even so, new codes are currently being developed for both geotechnical and transportation engineering which are LSD based. As a result, most modern buildings are designed in accordance with a code which is based on limit state theory.  For example, in the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
UK</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/27058.xml">
Steel</link> structures are designed in accordance with <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/2160932.xml">
BS 5950</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/54232.xml">
reinforced concrete</link> structures to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/1512566.xml">
BS 8110</link>, both of which are codes based on limit state theory. Australia, Canada, China, France, Indonesia, and New Zealand (among many others) utilise limit state theory in the development of their design codes. In the purest sense, it is now considered inappropriate to discuss <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/262553.xml">
safety factor</link>s when working with LSD, as there are concerns that this may lead to confusion.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
United States: Late Majority, or Laggard?</st>
<p>

The United States has been particularly slow to adopt Limit State(s) design (known as Load and Resistance Factor Design in the US), and as a result it is more thoroughly adopted outside the United States. Inside the U.S. there has been significant resistance to this technique, so much so that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/11007164.xml">
American Institute of Steel Construction</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/11007154.xml">
AISC</link>) is now issuing a combined manual of steel construction (the 2005 manual) that contains both methods of design side by side (ASD - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/1877149.xml">
Allowable Stress Design</link>, last updated in 1989), and <link>
LRFD</link> - load and resistance factor design).  In terms of the US steel code, research and progress has been reserved to LRFD code, with the exception of addenda regarding safety concerns. Even so, many American engineers continue to prefer the ASD code.  The difficulty may lie in the high regionalization of US Engineering practice, coupled with the high number of governing bodies, codes and states which each regulate the engineering profession individually.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<knowledge_domain wordnetid="105999266" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<discipline wordnetid="105996646" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/45829.xml">
Structural engineering</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</discipline>
</event>
</knowledge_domain>
</occupation>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/1877149.xml">
Allowable stress design</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/9499804.xml">
Probabilistic design</link></entry>
</list>


</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
