<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:52:17[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Little Entente</title>
<id>356001</id>
<revision>
<id>243600633</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T06:32:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Charles Matthews</username>
<id>12978</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Yugoslavia</category>
<category>Modern Europe</category>
<category>History of Romania</category>
<category>1920 in law</category>
<category>History of Czechoslovakia</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Little Entente</b> was an alliance formed in 1920 and 1921 by <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/5322.xml">
Czechoslovakia</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/25445.xml">
Romania</link></country>
 and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/232269.xml">
Yugoslavia</link></country>
 with the purpose of common defense against <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/13275.xml">
Hungarian</link></country>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/15226.xml">
irredentism</link> and the prevention of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/13824.xml">
Habsburg</link> restoration. <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
 supported the alliance by signing treaties with each member country. <p>

The Little Entente began to break down in 1936 and disbanded completely in 1938. France had seen the Little Entente as an opportunity, in the interests of French security, to revitalize the threat of a two-front war against Germany.  </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Origins </st>

<p>

The first attempts seeking a mutual defense of the successor states of the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
Austria-Hungary</link></country>
 took place at the <link>
Paris Peace Conference of 1919</link>. The most remarkable and ardent proponent of the certain alliance binding the successor states was <link>
Edvard Beneš</link> who served as Foreign Minister of <link>
Czechoslovakia</link> from 1918 to 1935. <link>
Beneš</link> played the crucial role in establishing the Little Entente to such extent, that he was regarded as its real founder (Zeman and Klimek 1997: 89) The Project of this alliance also clearly reflected his belief in necessity of democratic development for Czechoslovakia and other European states as well (Protheroe 2006: 102).</p>
<p>

The obvious aim of the alliance proposed by Beneš was to prevent the resurgence of Hungarian power and the restoration of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/1041515.xml">
Habsburg Monarchy</link>. The real purpose of the Little Entente followed much broader pattern. The alliance was designed to stop any encroachments on the independence of the member states committed by any European power. This meant that Beneš intended to gain the respect both from <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/13275.xml">
Hungary</link></country>
 and other powers such as <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
, and the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
. In addition, the Little Entente should strengthen the influence of its member states in international deliberations (Gordon and Gilbert 1994: 112).</p>
<p>

Another interpretation explaining the background of the forming of the Little Entente could be based on considerations concerning a new balance of power in Europe after <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/4764461.xml">
World War I</link></conflict>
. <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
 planned to contain a possible German aggression by forming an arrangement composed of German neighbours. Before World War I, Russia served as a suitable ally for the mentioned purpose. The end of World War I left France with the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/26779.xml">
Soviet Union</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 not willing to figure as French ally. Thus France sough for an alternative states neighbouring Germany and having close ties to France. As the Little Entente fulfilled these conditions, France strongly support its formation (Spielvogel 2005: 751).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Formation </st>

<p>

The first step towards founding a collective defense arrangement in the <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/5188.xml">
Central Europe</link></location>
</region>
 was a convention between <link>
Czechoslovakia</link> and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link>
Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</link></country>
 signed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/1417.xml">
August 14</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/34676.xml">
1920</link>. The treaty guaranteed the mutual assistance in the event of an unprovoked attack launched by Hungary against any stipulator. Subsequently, Beneš suggested a participation in the emerging alliance to <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/25445.xml">
Romania</link></country>
 on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/1490.xml">
August 17</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/34676.xml">
1920</link>, but his offer was rejected by irresolute Romanian government. Although the mentioned treaty was signed, it did not served as a regular allied convention.</p>
<p>

The true allied conventions were signed in order as follows:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The treaty between Czechoslovakia and Romania signed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/1827.xml">
April 23</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/34724.xml">
1921</link> in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/36877.xml">
Bucharest</link></village>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The treaty between the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link>
Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</link></country>
 and Romania signed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/15795.xml">
June 7</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/34724.xml">
1921</link> in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/55904.xml">
Belgrade</link></village>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The treaty between Czechoslovakia and the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes signed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/1711.xml">
August 31</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/34866.xml">
1922</link> in Belgrade.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The mentioned conventions encompassed almost identical terms as the treaty from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/1417.xml">
August 14</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/34676.xml">
1920</link>. Again, it was stated that in the event of an unprovoked attack employed by <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/13275.xml">
Hungary</link></country>
 against a certain stipulator other parties should provided mutual assistance. In addition, the treaties defined the mutual assistance via special military convention which was to be signed. Until the such convention comes into force, an interim measures was to be taken. The member states of the Little Entente also pledged themselves to cooperation in terms of foreign policy towards Hungary (Glasgow 1926: 103-104). </p>
<p>

During its formation, the Little Entente had to prove its determination of being a safeguard against any restoration sponsored by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/13824.xml">
Habsburgs</link>. Firstly, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/153477.xml">
Karl I of Austria</link> returned to Hungary from <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/26748.xml">
Switzerland</link></country>
 on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/20427.xml">
March 26</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/34724.xml">
1921</link>. He reclaimed the Hungarian throne, but this action earned neither the support of <link>
Miklós Horthy</link>, nor consent of the Little Entente. Thus <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/153477.xml">
Karl I of Austria</link> was forced to leave the country on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1175.xml">
April 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/34724.xml">
1921</link>. On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/22442.xml">
October 20</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/34724.xml">
1921</link>, he nevertheless returned to Hungary and renewed his claims. The situation was complicated by the fact that Karl I managed to gain the support from a certain part of the army (Dowling 2002: 43).</p>
<p>

The Little Entente reacted promptly under the guidance of <link>
Beneš</link>. Its member states began to mobilize its armies and the threat of direct involvement of the Little Entente was imminent. Moreover, other European powers expressed their refusal to restoration attempts of Karl I. Under these circumstances Hungarian government defeated Karl's followers and even they arrested Karl on <time_off wordnetid="115118453" confidence="0.8">
<fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<vacation wordnetid="115137890" confidence="0.8">
<leisure wordnetid="115137676" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/22345.xml">
October 24</link></leisure>
</vacation>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
</time_off>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/34724.xml">
1921</link>. Then the time of Hungarian reluctance to deprive Karl I of his titles and increasing danger of military incursion of the Little Entente into Hungary followed. Finally, Hungarian government passed the act abrogating the sovereign rights of Karl I on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/21760.xml">
November 10</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/34724.xml">
1921</link> (Protheroe 2006: 87).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Consolidation </st>

<p>

Although the thwarted restoration of Habsburgs posed an unambiguous success of the Little Entente, the events following this peak of the Entente's cooperation showed increasing tensions within the alliance. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/2526324.xml">
Genoa Conference</link> which was held from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/2564.xml">
April 10</link> to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/19632.xml">
May 19</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/34866.xml">
1922</link> highlighted the divergences of opinion among the member states of the Little Entente. The problem arose from the possible recognition of the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/26779.xml">
Soviet Union</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 by its European counterparts. As Czechoslovakia was mainly an industrial state, it was prone to normalize its relations with the Soviet Union and therefore to recognize the new formed state. On the other hand, the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link>
Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</link></country>
 together with Romania were agriculture-based countries not interested in economical cooperation with the Soviet Union. Neverthenless, all member states participating in the Little Entente congruously considered the Soviet Union as the threat (Fink et al 2002: 187-190).</p>
<p>

In the 1920s, France as the decisive supporter of the Little Entente pursued its policy towards tightening the alliance. Hence this power launched a series of friendship treaties aimed at forging the relations between France, Czechoslovakia, Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, and Romania. The mentioned treaties were signed as follows:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Treaty of Alliance and Friendship between France and Czechoslovakia, signed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/15845.xml">
January 25</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/34675.xml">
1924</link> in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/22989.xml">
Paris</link></site>
. The treaty was concluded for an unlimited time.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Treaty of Friendship between France and Romania, signed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/15805.xml">
June 10</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/34609.xml">
1926</link> in Paris. Originally, the treaty was concluded for 10 years, but it was extended for another 10 years on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/21759.xml">
November 8</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/34673.xml">
1936</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Treaty of Friendship between France and Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, signed on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/21460.xml">
November 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/34939.xml">
1927</link> in Paris. Originally, the treaty was concluded for five years, but it was extended on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/21760.xml">
November 10</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/34775.xml">
1932</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/8356.xml">
December 2</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/34684.xml">
1937</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

These treaties obliged the parties to consult their foreign policies, foremost the security matters of the involved states (Osmanczyk 2002: 632).</p>
<p>

The inevitable consequence of the successful performance of the Little Entente was its institutionalisation. Guided by this purpose, the Pact of Organisation, also called <it>The Little Entente System</it> or <it>The Reorganisation Pact</it>, was signed in <town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/12521.xml">
Geneva</link></town>
 on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/11362.xml">
February 16</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/34864.xml">
1933</link>, providing a legal framework for a permanent collaboration among the member states. According to that treaty, a Permanent Council together with a Permanent Secretary were to be established. The former body was designed for periodical meetings attended by the foreign ministers of the three countries, while the latter one was to provide a day-to-day routine operations of the Little Entente (Schlesinger 1998: 421). The meetings of the proposed Council were to be held in the capitals of the member states at least three times per year, thus enhancing a regular harmonization of foreign policies pursued by the given countries (Ragsdale 2004: 10). Moreover, by implementation of the Economic Council into the organisation structure of the Little Entente the member states declared their will to coordinate its economic interests too.</p>
<p>

The successful performance of the Little Entente resulted in its institutionalisation. Guided by this purpose, the Pact of Organisation, also called <it>The Little Entente System</it> or <it>The Reorganisation Pact</it>, was signed in Geneva on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/11362.xml">
February 16</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/34864.xml">
1933</link>. The treaty was delivered by Ministers of Foreign Affairs of the member states - Bogoljub D. Jevtic for <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/232269.xml">
Yugoslavia</link></country>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<curate wordnetid="109983572" confidence="0.8">
<clergyman wordnetid="109927451" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_leader wordnetid="109505153" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<official wordnetid="110372373" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<diplomat wordnetid="110013927" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/495558.xml">
Nicolae Titulescu</link></scholar>
</diplomat>
</causal_agent>
</official>
</alumnus>
</worker>
</spiritual_leader>
</leader>
</clergyman>
</curate>
</intellectual>
</person>
</skilled_worker>
</physical_entity>
 for Romania, and <link>
Edvard Beneš</link> for Czechoslovakia. The aim of the Pact of Organisation was to provide a legal framework for a permanent collaboration among the member states. This objective was to be reached by an establishing of new institutions operating on behalf of the member states within the Little Entente. The main instruments of collaboration were:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Permanent Council. This body was to consist of the ministers of foreign affairs of the three respective countries or of the special delegates appointed for that purpose. Decisions of the council were to be brought unanimously. The council was designed to meet at least three times per year. The mentioned meetings were to be held in each of the member states and in Geneva during the session of the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/17926.xml">
League of Nations</link></organization>
. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Secretariat of the Permanent Council. This body were to perform day-to-day routine operations of the Little Entente. In addition, a certain section of the secretariat was aimed to function permanently in the seat of the League of Nations.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Economic Council. By implementation of the council into the organisation structure of the Little Entente the member states declared their will to coordinate its economic interests too.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <alliance wordnetid="114418822" confidence="0.8">
<union wordnetid="114418395" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<coalition wordnetid="114418662" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/290941.xml">
Triple Entente</link></coalition>
</state>
</union>
</alliance>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dowling, Maria, 2002. <it>Czechoslovakia</it>. New York, NY: <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/48518.xml">
Oxford University Press</link></company>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fink, Carole, Axel Frohn, and Jürgen Heideking, 2002. <it>Genoa, Rapallo, and European Reconstruction in 1922</it>. Cambridge, UK: <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/73199.xml">
Cambridge University Press</link></company>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<immigrant wordnetid="110199489" confidence="0.8">
<migrant wordnetid="110314952" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<traveler wordnetid="109629752" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/14370815.xml">
Gilbert, Felix</link></associate>
</scholar>
</historian>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</traveler>
</intellectual>
</migrant>
</immigrant>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 and David Clay Large, 1991. <it>The End of European Era, 1890 to Present</it>. 4th edition worldwide. 1st edition in the Czech Republic. Prague: Mladá fronta.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Glasgow, George, 1926. <it>From Dawes to Locarno; Being a Critical Record of an Important Achievement in European Diplomacy, 1924-1925</it>. Ayer Publishing.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gordon, Craig A. and Felix Gilbert (eds), 1994. <it>The Diplomats, 1919-1939</it>. Princeton, NJ: <firm wordnetid="108059870" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<publisher wordnetid="108062623" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/1251967.xml">
Princeton University Press</link></publisher>
</business>
</enterprise>
</firm>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Nálevka, Vladimír, 2000. <it>The World Politics in the Twentieth Century (I.)</it> [Světová politika ve 20. století (I.)]. 1st edition. Prague: Aleš Skřivan.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Osmanczyk, Edmund Jan, 2002. <it>Encyclopedia of the United Nations and International Agreements</it>. New York, NY: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/803136.xml">
Routledge</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Pact of the Organization of the Little Entente</it>. In: <it>Recueil des traites</it> SDN, v. CXXXIX, p. 233. Available from http://www.mfa.gov.yu/History/poa_e.html</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Protheroe, Gerald J., 2006. <it>Searching for Security in a New Europe</it>. New York, NY: Routledge.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ragsdale, Hugh, 2004. <it>The Soviets, the Munich Crisis, and the Coming of World War II</it>. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Spielvogel, Jackson J., 2005. <it>Western Civilization: Volume II: Since 1500</it>. Thomson Wadsworth.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Zeman, Zbyněk and Antonín Klimek, 1997. <it>The Life of Edvard Benes 1884-1948: Czechoslovakia in Peace and War</it>. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
