<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:37:39[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Po Sum On</title>
<id>3602652</id>
<revision>
<id>243271816</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T21:33:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Traditional Chinese medicine</category>
<category>Ointments</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from December 2007</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Po_Sum_On&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Po+Sum+On%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<b>Po Sum On</b> (保心安, Bao Xin An) is a medicated oil from <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/13404.xml">
Hong Kong</link></country>
.</p>
<p>

The product was licensed since 1907 by the <b>Po Sum On Medicine Factory Limited</b> and sold in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5042862.xml">
Chinese</link> herbal stores world wide.The ointment and healing balm were invented by Kwok Cheu Nam and manufactured originally at the company's factory at 162 Tung Lo Wan Road, Causeway Bay, Hong Kong.</p>
<p>

<b>Active Ingredients:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../209/23209.xml">
Peppermint Oil</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../480/549480.xml">
Dragon's Blood</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Cinnamon Oil</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Camelia Oil</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<b>Po Sum On Oil Ingredients</b>
<b>Peppermint Oil</b>
Menthe haplocalyx. Peppermint oil is a volatile oil which is frozen from a solution distilled from fresh peppermint and water. According to ancient Chinese medicine books, peppermint oil's main effect is relieving headache caused by colds and flu's, primary infection of the upper respiratory canal, and sore throat, mouth ulcer, skin rash and lungs discomfort caused by fever or other epidemic diseases.</p>
<p>

<b>Chinese camellia Oil</b>
Camellia sinensis (tea oil). A volatile oil extracted by distilling dried camellia branches and leaves, it has a light colour and fragrance and a consistency like olive oil that gives this formulation its rich quality. According to ancient Chinese medicine books, Chinese camellia oil can eliminate chill and ease pain. It is a major ingredient for cold remedies and stomach tonic. </p>
<p>

<b>Dragon's Blood</b>
Daemonorops draco, also known as Resina Draconis (pinyin is xue jie). According to the import medicinal herbs standards set forth by China's Ministry of Health, Dragon's Blood can stop bleeding and eases bruises. Dispels blood stasis and alleviated pain; used for fractures, strains and contusions. </p>
<p>

<b>Liquorice</b>
Glycyrrhiza uralensis. (pinyin = gan cao).The dried root of liquorice, a legume. According to ancient Chinese medicine books, liquorice can eliminate heat, toxins and sputum, ease coughing, and sooth cramps and pains in the limbs.</p>
<p>

<b>Scute</b>
Radix Scutellaria baicalensis. (pinyin = huang qin). Clears heat, treats hot sores and swellings. 
<b>Use &amp; Safety</b>
The oil and balm have passed the safety tests of Zhongshan University and SGS of Hong Kong. It is verified that the products cause no skin irritation or allergic reaction, and are safe and suitable for long-term use. 
<b>NB</b> This product is suitable for external use only, for adults and children over two years old. Do not apply close to the eyes, or delicate or wounded skin. In case of accidental ingestion, seek medical attention immediately. In the event of skin allergic reaction, cease using. </p>
<p>

If the symptoms persist after several days, stop using it and consult a doctor. Do not cover the treatment area with bandage after application.
Used commonly for relief of muscular tension in neck, shoulders and upper back.</p>
<p>

<b>Typical application:</b>
apply to upper back, neck and back of head. This formula has a descending action, so caution is advised in those with low blood pressure. </p>
<p>

Although originally formulated for the upper back and neck, it is also very effective when massaged into other areas where there is pain. One source advises adding a teasponnful to a bowl of warm water to soak hands/feet affected by arthritis.</p>


<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.posumon.com.hk">
Po Sum On</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
