<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:37:55[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>STING</title>
<id>3606017</id>
<revision>
<id>215507690</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-28T14:40:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DOI bot</username>
<id>6652755</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Mathematical biology</category>
<category>Bioinformatics software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="STING.gif">
</image>

STING (<b>S</b>equence <b>T</b>o and with<b>IN</b> <b>G</b>raphics) is a free Web-based suite of programs for a comprehensive analysis of the relationship between protein sequence, structure, function, and stability.
STING is freely accessible at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS">
EMBRAPA Information Technology (CNPTIA)- Brazil</weblink> or at any of its mirrors sites <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ar.embnet.org/SMS">
La Plata University - Argentina</weblink>,
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gibk26.bse.kyutech.ac.jp/SMS">
Kyushu Institute of Technology - Japan</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://trantor.bioc.columbia.edu/SMS">
Columbia University - USA</weblink>.<p>

__TOC__</p>

<sec>
<st>
STING modules</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Sting Millennium</st>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STINGm/">
Sting Millennium</weblink> is a Web-based suite of programs that starts with the visualization of a molecular structure (using <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jmol.sourceforge.net">
JMOL</weblink> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/3939419.xml">
CHIME</link>)and leads the user through a series of operations resulting in an extensive structural analysis of the molecule:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

amino acid sequence and structure positions, with emphasis on bi-directional coupling of sequence and 3-D informationn</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

pattern search, neighbors identification</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

H-bonds, angles, and distances between atoms are easy to obtain thanks to the intuitive graphic and menu interface</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

sequence to structure relationships</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

analysis of structure's quality </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

nature and volume of atomic contacts of intra- and inter-chain type</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

analysis of amino acid relative conservation at specified position among homologous proteins</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Accessible Surface Area</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

relationship of relative conservation to the intra-chain contacts</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

functional parameters deciphered</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sting Report</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STINGm/SMSReport/">
Sting Report</weblink> is a service for extracting information about an individual amino acid of a protein.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> This information is presented as a series of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/12702.xml">
GIF</link> images and a table, integrated in a single printer-friendly <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 page, containing values of up to 125 structure/function descriptors/parameters. Sting Report allows the visualization of all the information about a specific residue, on platforms with the most elementary configurations (without Java, Chime, or other plug-ins).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Java Protein Dossier</st>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/JPD/">
Java Protein Dossier - JPD</weblink> is an interactive presentation of important physical-chemical characteristics of the macromolecular structure described in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> file.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> By using color code scales for each residue of the sequence, JPD shows corresponding: temperature factor, solvent accessibility of the single chain (and also in complex with the other present chains in given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> file), hydrophobicity, sequence conservation in a multiple alignment (relative entropy), double occupancies, reliability, pockets, rotamers, and histograms representing the atomic contacts. JPD also shows the identification of Interface Forming Residue (IFR) and their internal contacts. JPD offers information about electrostatic potential and curvature on protein surface. In addition, comparison of the Secondary Structure annotated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link>, by DSSP and by Stride is presented. The JPD_HELP below is presented in the separate organizational units, so that a user is capable to quickly understand what is available in STING_DB and how to access this information. JPD relays much on the image summaries, rather than using the words.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
PDB Metrics</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/pdb_metrics/">
PDB Metrics</weblink>is a powerful tool for the bioinformatics researcher to analyze the PDB's collection of protein structure descriptions from a variety of perspectives, and recover specific files using a repertoire of alternate criteria.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> PDB-Metrics employs a database system to maintain several measures extracted from files deposited in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link>, such as size, type, deposition date, number of chains, number of models (for proteins resolved using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/9820525.xml">
NMR</link>--Nuclear Magnetic Resonance), resolution (for non-NMR files), number of atoms, and the frequency of each kind of residue in the protein, among other characteristics. The PDB-Metrics database also includes keywords, taken from the headers of the PDB files, to support information search and recovery. This database is periodically updated (usually once a week). The time of the most recent update of the PDB-Metrics database appears in the top of the PDB-Metrics main page. This date and time refers to the moment PDB-Metrics started the updating process, using a local copy of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link>, which must have been synchronized with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> central repository some minutes earlier.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Graphical Contacts </st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/Grap_Contacts/">
Graphical Contacts</weblink>shows the atomic contacts between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acids</link> in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> entry received a special attention.  The complete profile of the interactions can be analyzed in the contacts window containing <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 table, which displays residue name and number, its pair in contact establishing, type of the contact, distance between contacting atoms, and accessibility and entropy of two contacting residues. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 IFR Graphical Contacts </st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/IFR_Grap_Contacts/">
IFR Graphical Contacts</weblink>The atomic contacts between amino acids belonging to facing chains in a given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> entry received a special attention.  The complete profile of the interactions across the interface can be analyzed in the contacts window containing <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 table, which displays residue chain name, residue name and number, its pair in contact establishing across the interface, type of the contact, distance between contacting atoms, and accessibility and entropy of two contacting residues. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Protein DNA Contacts</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/PDNAC/">
Protein DNA Contacts</weblink></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Java Table of Contacts</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/JTC/">
Java Table of Contacts</weblink></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Ramachandran Plot </st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STINGm/ramachandran/">
Ramachandran Plot</weblink>Intelligent graphical presentation of the <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/964378.xml">
Ramachandran Plot</link></method>
</know-how>
 using all advantages of Java programming language.  The use of the existing options allows an inter-connection of data in the dihedral angle plot with the 3-D structure of the molecule.  A selected number of amino acids can be highlighted for a better correlation between its position in the structure and the position of the Psi/Phi angles marked in the diagram.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
ConSSeq</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STINGm/consseq/">
ConSSeq</weblink>
This service presents PDB file sequence and consensus sequence (as found in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/4532439.xml">
HSSP</link>) colored by conservation, color coded graphic bars of relative entropy, information about residues present in other homologous sequences, with their respective frequency.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> For fast visualization, this program generates the sequence logo.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
XY Graphics Java Plot</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STINGm/XYGraphics/">
XY Graphics Java Plot</weblink> is the STING component which permits to a user to examine one of 150 different parameters in a simple yet intuitive plot showing the numerical values at the Y-axes and the sequence residue numbers at the X-axis.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Java Cα-Cα Distance Plot</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/distance/distCaCa/">
Java Cα-Cα Distance Plot</weblink>module displays the level curves of the distances between the alpha carbon of each residue and alpha carbon atoms of every other residue, within a single chain of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> file.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Java Cβ-Cβ Distance Plot</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/distance/distCbCb/">
Java Cβ-Cβ Distance Plot</weblink>module displays the level curves of the distances between the beta carbon of each residue and beta carbon atoms of every other residue, within a single chain of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> file.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Diamond Sting MSA</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/JMSA/">
Diamond Sting MSA</weblink></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Diamond Sting Phylogenetic Tree</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/JP_3/">
Diamond Sting Phylogenetic Tree</weblink></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Scorpion</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/SCORPION/">
Scorpion</weblink>is the Web-based tool for analysis of the amino acid frequencies within protein chain(s) (of given pdb file or group of pdb files) as well as for analysis of 3-D contacts between the C-alpha and/or Last Heavy Atoms (LHA) in the amino acid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/1152896.xml">
side chain</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Formiga</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/FORMIGA/">
Formiga</weblink>is a program for the calculation of the residue frequency and atomic contacts from inter-facial areas between two or more protein chains, for a given (list of) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> file(s).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sting Paint</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STINGm/STINGpaint/">
Sting Paint</weblink>is a visual aid to display multiple sequence alignments with the amino acids colored by physico-chemical properties. STING paint now supports the following sequence and Multiple-Sequence Alignment (MSA) formats: Coloring sequence of any <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> entry, Coloring any sequence in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/1009996.xml">
FASTA</link> format, Coloring MSA in CE and PRISM output format Coloring MSA in CLUSTAL-W, PSI-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/363695.xml">
BLAST</link>, and GCG output format.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
PDB Cartoon</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STINGm/pdbcartoon/">
PDB Cartoon</weblink>
produces the image of the amino acid sequence along with the secondary structure elements, rendered as cartoons .</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Protein Dossier</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STINGm/proteindossier2/">
Protein Dossier</weblink>provides a graphical report of several important structural characteristics of the PDB entry. It offers a plot from PDB cartoon annotated with color-coded scales representing for each amino acid the corresponding temperature factor, solvent accessibility of the chain in isolation and in complex with the other present chains in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> file, sequence conservation in a multiple alignment (relative sequence entropy), and histograms representing the atomic contacts (as in the Graphical contacts module), as well as IFR residue identification and IFR contacts. In addition, comparison of the Secondary Structure annotated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/18355070.xml">
PDB</link> and by DSSP is presented. Protein Dossier is an excellent tool to browse through valuable information about the protein chain. Collection of information is allowing the user to make very knowledgeable decisions about the possible role of a specific amino acid (or a number of them) in defining the function. It also helps in deciphering what effect the specific mutation will have on the structure and function of the protein.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Not Maintained Anymore</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Spider</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sms.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/SPIDER/">
Spider</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Ema</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sms.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/EMA/">
Ema</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hornet</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sms.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/HORNET/">
Hornet</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
PDB Search</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sms.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/cgi-bin/SMS/pdbsearch/index_pdb.pl">
PDB Search</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sting</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sms.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/STING-L/">
Sting</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Contacts</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sms.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/contacts/">
Contacts</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
IFR Contacts</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sms.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS/ifr_contacts/">
IFR Contacts</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Neshich G, Togawa R, Mancini A, Kuser P, Yamagishi M, Pappas G, Torres W, Fonseca e Campos T, Ferreira L, Luna F, Oliveira A, Miura R, Inoue M, Horita L, de Souza D, Dominiquini F, Alvaro A, Lima C, Ogawa F, Gomes G, Palandrani J, dos Santos G, de Freitas E, Mattiuz A, Costa I, de Almeida C, Souza S, Baudet C, Higa R&#32;(2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/picrender.fcgi?artid=168984&amp;blobtype=pdf">
STING Millennium: A web-based suite of programs for comprehensive and simultaneous analysis of protein structure and sequence</weblink>". <it>Nucleic Acids Res</it>&#32;<b>31</b>&#32;(13): 3386–92. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fnar%2Fgkg578">
10.1093/nar/gkg578</weblink>. PMID 12824333.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Neshich G, Mancini A, Yamagishi M, Kuser P, Fileto R, Pinto I, Palandrani J, Krauchenco J, Baudet C, Montagner A, Higa R&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/picrender.fcgi?artid=540065&amp;blobtype=pdf">
STING Report: convenient web-based application for graphic and tabular presentations of protein sequence, structure and function descriptors from the STING database</weblink>". <it>Nucleic Acids Res</it>&#32;<b>33</b>&#32;(Database issue): D269–74. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fnar%2Fgki111">
10.1093/nar/gki111</weblink>. PMID 15608194.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Neshich G, Rocchia W, Mancini A, Yamagishi M, Kuser P, Fileto R, Baudet C, Pinto I, Montagner A, Palandrani J, Krauchenco J, Torres R, Souza S, Togawa R, Higa R&#32;(2004).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/picrender.fcgi?artid=441618&amp;blobtype=pdf">
JavaProtein Dossier: a novel web-based data visualization tool for comprehensive analysis of protein structure</weblink>". <it>Nucleic Acids Res</it>&#32;<b>32</b>&#32;(Web Server issue): W595–601. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fnar%2Fgkh480">
10.1093/nar/gkh480</weblink>. PMID 15215458.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Fileto R, Kuser P, Yamagishi M, Ribeiro A, Quinalia T, Franco E, Mancini A, Higa R, Oliveira S, Santos E, Vieira F, Mazoni I, Cruz S, Neshich G&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.funpecrp.com.br/gmr/year2006/vol2-5/gmr0194_abstract.htm">
PDB-Metrics: a web tool for exploring the PDB contents</weblink>". <it>Genet Mol Res</it>&#32;<b>5</b>&#32;(2): 333–41. PMID 16819713.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Higa R, Montagner A, Togawa R, Kuser P, Yamagishi M, Mancini A, Pappas G, Miura R, Horita L, Neshich G&#32;(2004).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/20/12/1983">
ConSSeq: a web-based application for analysis of amino acid conservation based on HSSP database and within context of structure</weblink>". <it>Bioinformatics</it>&#32;<b>20</b>&#32;(12): 1983–5. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fbioinformatics%2Fbth185">
10.1093/bioinformatics/bth185</weblink>. PMID 15044236.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Higa R, Oliveira A, Horita L, Miura R, Inoue M, Kuser P, Mancini A, Yamagishi M, Togawa R, Neshich G&#32;(2004).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/20/12/1989">
Defining 3D residue environment in protein structures using SCORPION and FORMIGA</weblink>". <it>Bioinformatics</it>&#32;<b>20</b>&#32;(12): 1989–91. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fbioinformatics%2Fbth190">
10.1093/bioinformatics/bth190</weblink>. PMID 15044232.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Higa R. H. , Togawa R. C. , Montagner A. J. ,  Palandrani J. C. , Okimoto I. K. , Kuser P. R. , Yamagishi M. E. B. ,  Mancini A. L.,  Neshich G. (2004), <it>STING Millennium Suite: integrated software for extensive analyses of 3-D structures of proteins and their complexes</it>, <b>BMC Bioinformatics</b>, 5:107 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/content/pdf/1471-2105-5-107.pdf">
pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mancini A. L. , Higa R. H. , Oliveira A., Dominiquini F., Kuser P. R., Yamagishi M. E. B., Togawa R. C., Neshich G. (2004) <it>STING Contacts: a Web-based application for identification and analysis of amino acid contacts within protein structure and across protein interfaces</it>, <b>Bioinformatics</b>, 20, pp. 2145-2147 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/20/13/2145.pdf">
pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Neshich G., Borro L. C., Higa R. H., Kuser P. R., Yamagishi M.E. B., Franco E. H., Krauchenco J. N., Fileto R., Ribeiro A. A., Bezerra G. B. P., Velludo T. M., Jimenez T. S., Furukawa N., Teshima H., Kitajima K., Bava A., Sarai A., Togawa R. C., Mancini A. L. (2005), <it>The Diamond STING server</it>, <b>Nucleic Acids Research</b>, 33, Web Server issue, pp. W29-W35 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/33/suppl_2/W29">
pdf</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbi.cnptia.embrapa.br/SMS">
STAR STING</weblink> </entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/55170.xml">
Genomics</link>topics</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/323792.xml">
Genome project</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/2606560.xml">
Paleopolyploidy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../087/61087.xml">
Glycomics</link>&nbsp;·  <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/5219699.xml">
Human Genome Project</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/55172.xml">
Proteomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/1029211.xml">
Metabolomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/5168909.xml">
Chemogenomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/303101.xml">
Structural genomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/1889064.xml">
Pharmacogenetics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/1004486.xml">
Pharmacogenomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/1677333.xml">
Toxicogenomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/2571276.xml">
Computational genomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/575697.xml">
Cheminformatics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/467899.xml">
Systems biology</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Major subfields of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biology</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/674.xml">
Anatomy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/2787.xml">
Astrobiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/3954.xml">
Biochemistry</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/3878.xml">
Biostatistics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/4183.xml">
Botany</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/6339.xml">
Cell biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/56566.xml">
Chronobiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/8449.xml">
Developmental biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/9630.xml">
Ecology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/66997.xml">
Epidemiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/418101.xml">
Evolutionary biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/12266.xml">
Genetics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/55170.xml">
Genomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/411951.xml">
Human biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/14959.xml">
Immunology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/20021.xml">
Marine biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/19909.xml">
Microbiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/19200.xml">
Molecular biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/21245.xml">
Neuroscience</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
Nutrition</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/19179706.xml">
Origin of life</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/23084.xml">
Paleontology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/383854.xml">
Parasitology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/48791.xml">
Pathology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/23597.xml">
Physiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/467899.xml">
Systems biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/3036154.xml">
Taxonomy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/34413.xml">
Zoology</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
