<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:53:16[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<algorithm  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105847438">
<header>
<title>BLAST</title>
<id>363695</id>
<revision>
<id>243114548</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T05:58:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Thorwald</username>
<id>74279</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Bioinformatics software</category>
<category>Computational phylogenetics</category>
<category>Laboratory software</category>
<category>Bioinformatics algorithms</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Software</name>
<parameters>
<genre>
Bioinformatics tool</genre>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/blast/">
ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/blast/</weblink></website>
<developer>
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/14855138.xml">
Myers, E.</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/671703.xml">
Altschul S.F.</link></scientist>
, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/14860831.xml">
Gish W.</link></scientist>
, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/10454365.xml">
Miller E.W.</link></scientist>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/6700950.xml">
Lipman D.J.</link>, <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/149306.xml">
NCBI</link></association>
</institute>
</developer>
<name>
BLAST</name>
<latest_release_version>
2.2.18</latest_release_version>
<license>
Public Domain</license>
<operating_system>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
UNIX</link>, <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/19006979.xml">
Mac</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
MS-Windows</link></operating_system>
</parameters>
</template>


This article is about the bioinformatics software tool.&#32;&#32;For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/87562.xml">
Blast</link>.<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link>, <b>B</b>asic <b>L</b>ocal <b>A</b>lignment <b>S</b>earch <b>T</b>ool, or <b>BLAST</b>, is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> for comparing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/24511.xml">
primary</link> biological sequence information, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino-acid</link> sequences of different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link>s or the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/21505.xml">
nucleotide</link>s of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/331535.xml">
DNA sequence</link>s. A <it>BLAST search</it> enables a researcher to compare a query sequence with a library or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> of sequences, and identify library sequences that resemble the query sequence above a certain threshold. For example, following the discovery of a previously unknown gene in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/575890.xml">
mouse</link>, a scientist will typically perform a BLAST search of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/42888.xml">
human genome</link> to see if humans carry a similar gene; BLAST will identify sequences in the human genome that resemble the mouse gene based on similarity of sequence. The BLAST program was designed by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/14855138.xml">
Eugene Myers</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/671703.xml">
Stephen Altschul</link></scientist>
, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/14860831.xml">
Warren Gish</link></scientist>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/6700950.xml">
David J. Lipman</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/10454365.xml">
Webb Miller</link></scientist>
 at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/46174.xml">
NIH</link> and was published in J. Mol. Biol. in 1990.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Background</st>

<p>

BLAST is one of the most widely used bioinformatics programs<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, because it addresses a fundamental problem and the algorithm emphasizes speed over sensitivity. This emphasis on speed is vital to making the algorithm practical on the huge genome databases currently available, although subsequent algorithms can be even faster.</p>
<p>

Before fast algorithms such as BLAST and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/1009996.xml">
FASTA</link> were developed, doing database searches for the protein or nucleic sequences was very time consuming by using a full alignment program like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/125297.xml">
dynamic programming</link>. BLAST is about 50 times faster than the dynamic programming; however, it cannot guarantee the optimal alignments of the query and database sequences as in the dynamic programming, but just work to find the related sequences in a database search. BLAST is more time efficient than FASTA by searching only for the more significant patterns in the sequences, but with comparative sensitivity. This could be further realized by knowing the algorithm of BLAST introduced below.</p>
<p>

Examples of other questions that researchers use BLAST to answer are:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Which <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/9028799.xml">
bacteria</link>l <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/28023.xml">
species</link> have a protein that is related in lineage to a certain protein with known <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/24511.xml">
amino-acid sequence</link>?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Where does a certain sequence of DNA originate?</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 What other genes encode proteins that exhibit structures or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/443318.xml">
motifs</link> such as ones that have just been determined?</entry>
</list>

BLAST is also often used as part of other algorithms that require approximate sequence matching.</p>
<p>

The BLAST algorithm and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/5783.xml">
computer program</link> that implements it were developed by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/671703.xml">
Stephen Altschul</link></scientist>
, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/14860831.xml">
Warren Gish</link></scientist>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/6700950.xml">
David Lipman</link> at the U.S. <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/149306.xml">
National Center for Biotechnology Information</link></association>
</institute>
 (NCBI), <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/10454365.xml">
Webb Miller</link></scientist>
 at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/1209509.xml">
Pennsylvania State University</link></university>
, and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/1773498.xml">
Gene Myers</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/32015.xml">
University of Arizona</link></university>
. It is available on the web on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/">
the NCBI website</weblink>. Alternative implementations include <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blast.wustl.edu/">
WU-BLAST</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fsa-blast.org/">
FSA-BLAST</weblink>.</p>
<p>

The original paper by Altschul, <it>et al.</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> was the most highly cited paper published in the 1990s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Input/Output </st>
<p>

Input and output conform to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/468001.xml">
FASTA format</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Algorithm </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 BLAST </st>
<p>

To run, BLAST requires a query sequence to search for, and a sequence to search against (also called the target sequence) or a sequence database containing multiple such sequences. BLAST will find subsequences in the database which are similar to subsequences in the query. In typical usage, the query sequence is much smaller than the database, e.g., the query may be one thousand nucleotides while the database is several billion nucleotides.</p>
<p>

The main idea of BLAST is that there are often high-scoring segment pairs (HSP) contained in a statistically significant alignment. BLAST searches for high scoring <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/149289.xml">
sequence alignment</link>s between the query sequence and sequences in the database using a heuristic approach that approximates the <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/1606195.xml">
Smith-Waterman algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
. The exhaustive Smith-Waterman approach is too slow for searching large genomic databases such as <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/617565.xml">
GenBank</link></association>
</institute>
. Therefore, the BLAST algorithm uses a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link> approach that is less accurate than the Smith-Waterman but over 50 times faster. The speed and relatively good accuracy of BLAST are among the key technical innovation of the BLAST programs.</p>
<p>

Here the algorithm of BLASTP (a protein to protein search) is introduced to present the concept of BLAST.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Remove low-complexity region or sequence repeats in the query sequence.</b> Low-complexity region means a region of a sequence is composed of few kinds of elements. These regions might give high scores that confuse the program to find the actual significant sequences in the database, so they should be filtered out. The regions will be marked with an X (protein sequences) or N (nucleic acid sequences) and then be ignored by the BLAST program. To filter out the low-complexity regions, the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Education/BLASTinfo/Seg.html">
SEG</weblink> program is used for protein sequences and the program <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pub/agarwala/windowmasker/windowmasker_suppl.pdf">
DUST</weblink> is used for DNA sequences. On the other hand, the program <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bighost.area.ba.cnr.it/BIG/GCGManual/xnu.html">
XNU</weblink> is used to mask off the tandem repeats in protein sequences.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Make a k-letter word list of the query sequence.</b> Take k=3 for example, we list the words of length 3 in the query protein sequence (k is usually 11 for a DNA sequence) “sequentially”, until the last letter of the query sequence is included. The method can be illustrated in figure 1.<image width="150px" src="query_word.jpg" type="frame">
<caption>

Fig. 1 The method to establish the k-letter query word list.
</caption>
</image>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>List the possible matching words.</b> This step is one of the main differences between BLAST and FASTA. FASTA cares about all of the common words in the database and query sequences that are listed in step 2; however, BLAST cares about only the high-scoring words. The scores are created by comparing the word in the list in step 2 with all the 3-letter words. By using the scoring matrix (substitution matrix) to score the comparison of each residue pair, there are 20^3 possible match scores for a 3-letter word. For example, the score obtained by comparing PQG with PEG and PQA is 15 and 12, respectively. For DNA words, a match is scored as +5 and a mismatch as -4.  After that, a neighborhood word score threshold T is used to reduce the number of possible matching words. The words whose scores are greater than the threshold T will remain in the possible matching words list, while those with lower scores will be discarded. For example, PEG is kept, but PQA is abandoned when T is 13.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Organize the remaining high-scoring words into an efficient search tree.</b>This is for the purpose that the program can rapidly compare the high-scoring words to the database sequences.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Repeat step 1 to 4 for each 3-letter word in the query sequence.</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Scan the database sequences for exact match with the remaining high-scoring words.</b> The BLAST program scans the database sequences for the remaining high-scoring word, such as PEG, of each position. If an exact match is found, this match is used to seed a possible ungapped alignment between the query and database sequences.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Extend the exact matches to high-scoring segment pair (HSP).</b></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The original version of BLAST stretches a longer alignment between the query and the database sequence in left and right direction, from the position where exact match is scanned. The extension doesn’t stop until the accumulated total score of the HSP begins to decrease. A simplified example is presented in figure 2.<image width="150px" src="extension_process.jpg" type="frame">
<caption>

Fig. 2 The process to extension the exact match.
</caption>
</image>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 To save more time, a newer version of BLAST, called BLAST2 or gapped BLAST, has been developed. BLAST2 adopts a lower neighborhood word score threshold to maintain the same level of sensitivity for detecting sequence similarity. Therefore, the possible matching words list in step 3 becomes longer. Next, the exact matched regions, within distance A from each other on the same diagonal in figure 3, will be joined as a longer new region. Finally, the new regions are then extended as the same method in the original version of BLAST, and the HSPs’ (High-scoring segment pair) scores of the extended regions are then created by using a substitution matrix as before.<image width="150px" src="neighbor_HSP.jpg" type="frame">
<caption>

Fig. 3 The positions of the exact matches.
</caption>
</image>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>List all of the HSPs in the database whose score is high enough to be considered.</b> We list the HSPs whose scores are greater than the empirically determined cutoff score S. By examining the distribution of the alignment scores modeled by comparing random sequences, a cutoff score S can be determined such that its value is large enough to guarantee the significance of the remained HSPs.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Evaluate the significance of the HSP score.</b> BLAST next assesses the statistical significance of each HSP score by exploiting the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.itl.nist.gov/div898/handbook/eda/section3/eda366g.htm">
Gumbel extreme value distribution (EVD)</weblink>. (It is proved that the distribution of Smith-Waterman local alignment scores between two random sequences follows the Gumbel EVD, regardless of whether gaps are allowed in the alignment). In accordance with the Gumbel EVD, the probability p of observing a score S equal to or greater than x is given by the equation<math>p\left( S\ge x \right)=1-\exp \left( -e^{-\lambda \left( x-\mu  \right)} \right)</math>,where<math>\mu ={}^{\left[ \log \left( Km'n' \right) \right]}\!\!\diagup\!\!{}_{\lambda }\;</math>The statistical parameters <math>\lambda </math> and <math>\mathrm{K}</math> are estimated by fitting the distribution of the ungapped local alignment scores, of the query sequence and a lot of shuffled versions (Global or local shuffling) of a database sequence, to the Gumbel extreme value distribution. Note that <math>\lambda </math> and <math>\mathrm{K}</math> depend upon the substitution matrix, gap penalties, and sequence composition (the letter frequencies).The m’ and n’ is the effective length of the query and database sequence, respectively. The original sequence length is shortened to the effective length to compensate for the edge effect (an alignment start near the end of one of the query or database sequence is likely not to have enough sequence to build an optimal alignment). They can be calculated as<math>m'\approx m-{}^{\left( \ln Kmn \right)}\!\!\diagup\!\!{}_{H}\;</math><math>n'\approx n-{}^{\left( \ln Kmn \right)}\!\!\diagup\!\!{}_{H}\;</math>,where <math> \mathrm{H} </math> is the average expected score per aligned pair of residues in an alignment of two random sequences. Altschul and Gish gave the typical values, <math>\lambda = 0.318 </math>, <math> \mathrm{K} = 0.13 </math>, and <math> \mathrm{H} = 0.40 </math>, for ungapped local alignment using <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uky.edu/Classes/BIO/520/BIO520WWW/blosum62.htm">
BLOSUM62</weblink> as the substitution matrix. Using the typical values for assessing the significance is called the lookup table methods, and is not accurate. The expect score E of a database match is the number of times that an unrelated database sequence would obtain a score S higher than x by chance. The expectation E obtained in a search for a database of D sequences is given by<math>E\approx 1-e^{-p\left( s&amp;gt;x \right)D}</math>Furthermore, when <math>p&amp;lt;0.1</math>, E could be approximated by the Poisson distribution as<math>E\approx pD</math>Note that the E value accessing the significance of the HSP score here (for ungapped local alignment) is not identical to the one in the later step to evaluate the final gapped local alignment score, due to the variation of the statistical parameters.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Make two or more HSP regions into a longer alignment.</b> Sometimes, we find two or more HSP regions in one database sequence that can be made into a longer alignment. This provides additional evidence of the relation between the query and database sequence. There are two methods, the Poisson method and the sum-of scores method, to compare the significance of the newly combined HSP regions. Suppose that there are two combined HSP regions with the sets of score (65, 40) and (52, 45), respectively. The Poisson method gives more significance to the set with the lower score of each set is higher (45&amp;gt;40). However, the sum-of-scores method prefers the first set, because 65+40 (105) is greater than 52+45(97). The original BLAST uses the Poisson method; gapped BLAST and the WU-BLAST use the sum-of scores method.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Show the gapped Smith-Waterman local alignments of the query and each of the matched database sequences.</b></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The original BLAST only generates ungapped alignments including the initially found HSPs individually, even when there is more than one HSP found in one database sequence.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 BLAST2 versions produce a single alignment with gaps that can include all of the initially found HSP regions. Note that the computation of the score and its corresponding E score is involved with the adequate gap penalties.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Report the matches whose expect score is lower than a threshold parameter E.</b></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Parallel BLAST </st>
<p>

Parallel BLAST versions are implemented using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/221466.xml">
MPI</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/634671.xml">
Pthreads</link>, and have been ported to various platforms including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link>, <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
, <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/46145.xml">
Solaris</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
AIX</link>. Popular approaches to parallelize BLAST include query distribution, hash table segmentation, computation parallelization, and database segmentation (partition) .</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Program </st>
<p>

The BLAST program can either be downloaded and run as a command-line utility "blastall" or accessed for free over the web. The BLAST web server, hosted by the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/149306.xml">
NCBI</link></association>
</institute>
, allows anyone with a web browser to perform similarity searches against constantly updated databases of proteins and DNA that include most of the newly sequenced organisms. </p>
<p>

BLAST is actually a family of programs (all included in the blastall executable). These include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<b>Nucleotide-nucleotide BLAST (blastn)</b>: This program, given a DNA query, returns the most similar DNA sequences from the DNA database that the user specifies.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<b>Protein-protein BLAST (blastp)</b>: This program, given a protein query, returns the most similar protein sequences from the protein database that the user specifies.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<b>Position-Specific Iterative BLAST (PSI-BLAST)</b>: This program is used to find distant relatives of a protein. First, a list of all closely related proteins is created. These proteins are combined into a general "profile" sequence, which summarises significant features present in these sequences. A query against the protein database is then run using this profile, and a larger group of proteins is found. This larger group is used to construct another profile, and the process is repeated.  By including related proteins in the search, PSI-BLAST is much more sensitive in picking up distant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/149326.xml">
evolutionary relationship</link>s than a standard protein-protein BLAST.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<b>Nucleotide 6-frame translation-protein (blastx)</b>: This program compares the six-frame conceptual translation products of a nucleotide query sequence (both strands) against a protein sequence database.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<b>Nucleotide 6-frame translation-nucleotide 6-frame translation (tblastx)</b>: This program is the slowest of the BLAST family. It translates the query nucleotide sequence in all six possible frames and compares it against the six-frame translations of a nucleotide sequence database. The purpose of tblastx is to find very distant relationships between nucleotide sequences.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<b>Protein-nucleotide 6-frame translation (tblastn)</b>: This program compares a protein query against the all six <link>
frame translation</link>s of a nucleotide sequence database.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<b>Large numbers of query sequences (megablast)</b>: When comparing large numbers of input sequences via the command-line BLAST, "megablast" is much faster than running BLAST multiple times. It concatenates many input sequences together to form a large sequence before searching the BLAST database, then post-analyze the search results to glean individual alignments and statistical values.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Alternative versions</st>
<p>

An extremely fast but considerably less sensitive alternative to BLAST that compares nucleotide sequences to the genome is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/10512032.xml">
BLAT</link> (<b>B</b>last <b>L</b>ike <b>A</b>lignment <b>T</b>ool). A version designed for comparing multiple large genomes or chromosomes is <link>
BLASTZ</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Accelerated versions</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

There are two main <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/10969.xml">
field-programmable gate array</link> (FPGA) implementations of the BLAST algorithm. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.progeniq.com">
Progeniq</weblink> is up to 100x faster than a software implementation running on the same processor. TimeLogic <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.timelogic.com">
http://www.timelogic.com</weblink> offers a  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/592814.xml">
FPGA</link> BLAST package called <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.timelogic.com/decypher_blast.html">
Tera-BLAST</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Mitrion-C Open Bio Project is an ongoing effort to port blast to run on Mitrion FPGAs. It is available <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mitc-openbio.sourceforge.net/">
on SourceForge</weblink>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Casey, RM (2005). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.b-eye-network.com/view/1730">
BLAST Sequences Aid in Genomics and Proteomics</weblink>". <it>Business Intelligence Network</it>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Altschul SF, Gish W, Miller W, Myers EW, Lipman DJ&#32;(1990).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-math.mit.edu/~lippert/18.417/papers/altschuletal1990.pdf">
Basic local alignment search tool</weblink>". <it>J Mol Biol</it>&#32;<b>215</b>&#32;(3): 403–410. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006%2Fjmbi.1990.9999">
10.1006/jmbi.1990.9999</weblink>. PMID 2231712.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencewatch.com/july-aug2000/sw_july-aug2000_page3.htm">
Sense from Sequences: Stephen F. Altschul on Bettering BLAST</weblink>. ScienceWatch July/August 2000.</entry>
<entry id="4">
D.W. Mount (2004). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformaticsonline.org/">
Bioinformatics: Sequence and Genome Analysis.</weblink>". Cold Spring Harbor Press<it>.</it></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/1004679.xml">
Needleman-Wunsch algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/1606195.xml">
Smith-Waterman algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/149289.xml">
Sequence alignment</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/5806900.xml">
Sequence alignment software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/5278545.xml">
Sequerome</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/9162441.xml">
eTBLAST</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/">
NCBI-BLAST website</weblink></entry>
</list>

</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Variations of BLAST</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blast.wustl.edu/">
WU-BLAST</weblink> &mdash; the original gapping BLAST with statistics, developed and maintained by Warren Gish at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/58920.xml">
Washington University in St. Louis</link></university>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/blast">
EBI's BLAST Services</weblink> &mdash; <link>
EBI's</link> main blast services page.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fsa-blast.org/">
FSA-BLAST</weblink> &mdash; a new, faster but still accurate version of NCBI BLAST based on recently published algorithmic improvements</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://services.nbic.nl:4080/bb/cgi-bin/bb_login.cgi">
NBIC mpiBLAST</weblink> &mdash; at the Netherlands Bioinformatics Centre</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-users.cs.umn.edu/~rangwala/final_bglBLAST.pdf">
Parallel BLAST</weblink> &mdash; a dual scheduling BLAST tested on the Blue Gene/L</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mpiblast.org/">
mpiBLAST</weblink> &mdash; open-source parallel BLAST</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://developer.apple.com/darwin/projects/blast/">
A/G BLAST</weblink> &mdash; implementation for PowerPC G4/G5 processors and Mac OS X, from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/856.xml">
Apple Computer</link>'s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/993522.xml">
Advanced Computation Group</link> and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/362464.xml">
Genentech</link></company>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://3d-alignment.eu">
STRAP</weblink> &mdash; the protein workbench <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.charite.de/bioinf/strap/">
STRAP</weblink> contains a comfortable BLAST front-end with a cache for BLAST results</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Commercial versions</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dnasoftware.com/ThermoBLAST/tabid/110/Default.aspx">
ThermoBLAST by DNA Software Inc.</weblink> &mdash; scans entire genomes quickly and accurately combing the power of BLAST with the most advanced thermodynamics parameters</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformaticssolutions.com/products/ph/index.php">
PatternHunter</weblink> &mdash; an alternative software which provides similar functionality to BLAST while claiming increased speed and sensitivity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.korilog.com/products">
KoriBlast</weblink> &mdash; a reliable graphical environment dedicated to sequence data mining. KoriBlast combines Blast searches with advanced data management capabilities and a state-of-the-art graphical user interface.</entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Tutorials</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Education/BLASTinfo/tut1.html">
NCBI-BLAST Tutorial</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openwetware.org/wiki/BLAST">
BLAST HOWTO</weblink> &mdash; at the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openwetware.org/">
OpenWetWare wiki</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cshprotocols.org/cgi/content/full/2007/14/pdb.top17">
Using the Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Databases supported by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/2611971.xml">
Bioinformatic Harvester</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/363695.xml">
NCBI-BLAST</link> &nbsp;·  CDD &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/2039930.xml">
Ensembl</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/8758178.xml">
Flybase</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
Flymine</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/3808493.xml">
GFP-cDNA</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/393024.xml">
Genome browser</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
GeneCard</link> &nbsp;·  <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/1520204.xml">
Google Scholar</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 &nbsp;·  <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/8283008.xml">
GoPubMed</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/19609372.xml">
Harvester42</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/3948246.xml">
HomoloGene</link> &nbsp;·  <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/2871644.xml">
iHOP</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 &nbsp;·  <link>
IPI</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/670449.xml">
OMIM</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
MGI</link> &nbsp;·  <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/4945516.xml">
Mitocheck</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/4901423.xml">
PSORT</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
PolyMeta</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
RGD</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/1664428.xml">
UniProt</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
SOURCE</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/3954457.xml">
SOSUI</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
RZPD</link> &nbsp;·  <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/13907558.xml">
Sciencenet</link></software>
 &nbsp;·  <link>
STRING</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
SMART</link> &nbsp;·  <link>
TAIR</link> &nbsp;·  <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/9518432.xml">
WikiProfessional</link></software>
 &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/12879182.xml">
ZFIN</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>




</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</algorithm>
</entity>
</article>
