<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:39:41[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Intranet</title>
<id>37481</id>
<revision>
<id>243630134</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T11:17:41Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Epbr123</username>
<id>1395162</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Internet privacy</category>
<category>Computer network security</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

An <b>intranet</b> is a private computer network that uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/15323.xml">
Internet protocol</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/5652.xml">
network</link> connectivity to securely share any part of an organization's information or operational systems with its employees. Sometimes the term refers only to the organization's internal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link>, but often it is a more extensive part of the organization's computer infrastructure and private websites are an important component and focal point of internal communication and collaboration.<p>

An intranet is built from the same concepts and technologies used for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/667970.xml">
clients</link> and <generic wordnetid="107899976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/42116.xml">
servers</link></generic>
 running on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/15476.xml">
Internet Protocol Suite</link> (TCP/IP). Any of the well known Internet protocols may be found in an intranet, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/2701104.xml">
HTTP</link> (web services), <link>
SMTP</link> (e-mail), and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/53289.xml">
FTP</link> (file transfer). There is often an attempt to employ Internet technologies to provide modern interfaces to legacy information systems hosting corporate data.</p>
<p>

An <b>intranet</b> can be understood as a private version of the Internet, or as a private extension of the Internet confined to an organization. The term first appeared in print on April 19, 1995, in <it>Digital News &amp; Review</it> in an article authored by technical editor Stephen Lawton.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Intranet-Site content is almost always private and requires authorization for each web viewer, provided either through specific user authentication or by default, based on the location of the viewer's computer on the private network.</p>
<p>

Intranets differ from <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/131823.xml">
extranets</link></it> in that the former are generally restricted to employees of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link> while extranets may also be accessed by customers, suppliers, or other approved parties.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Extranets extend a private network onto the Internet with special provisions for access, authorization and authentication (see also <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/2166952.xml">
AAA protocol</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
).</p>
<p>

An organization's intranet does not necessarily have to provide access to the Internet. When such access is provided it is usually through a network <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/1338556.xml">
gateway</link> with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1362296.xml">
firewall</link>, shielding the intranet from unauthorized external access. The gateway often also implements user <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authentication</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> of messages, and often <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/147130.xml">
virtual private network</link> (VPN) connectivity for off-site employees to access company information, computing resources and internal communications.</p>
<p>

Increasingly, intranets are being used to deliver tools and applications, e.g., collaboration (to facilitate working in groups and teleconferencing) or sophisticated corporate directories, sales and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/6968.xml">
Customer relationship management</link> tools, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/24042.xml">
project management</link> etc., to advance productivity.</p>
<p>

Intranets are also being used as corporate culture-change platforms. For example, large numbers of employees discussing key issues in an intranet forum application could lead to new ideas in management, productivity, quality, and other corporate issues.</p>
<p>

In large intranets, website traffic is often similar to public website traffic and can be better understood by using web metrics software to track overall activity.  User surveys also improve intranet website effectiveness. </p>
<p>

Intranet user-experience, editorial, and technology teams work together to produce in-house sites. Most commonly, intranets are managed by the communications, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/1023078.xml">
HR</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/153852.xml">
CIO</link> departments of large organizations, or some combination of these.</p>
<p>

Because of the scope and variety of content and the number of system interfaces, intranets of many organizations are much more complex than their respective public websites. Intranets and their use are growing rapidly. According to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/14272052.xml">
Intranet design annual</link> 2007 from <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/1240594.xml">
Nielsen Norman Group</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, the number of pages on participants' intranets averaged 200,000 over the years 2001 to 2003 and has grown to an average of 6 million pages over 2005–2007.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Benefits of intranets</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Workforce productivity: Intranets can help users to locate and view information faster and use applications relevant to their roles and responsibilities. With the help of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/33173.xml">
web browser</link> interface, users can access data held in any database the organization wants to make available, anytime and - subject to security provisions - from anywhere within the company workstations, increasing employees' ability to perform their jobs faster, more accurately, and with confidence that they have the right information. It also helps to improve the services provided to the users.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Time: With intranets, organizations can make more information available to employees on a "pull" basis (i.e., employees can link to relevant information at a time which suits them) rather than being deluged indiscriminately by emails.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Communication: Intranets can serve as powerful tools for communication within an organization, vertically and horizontally.  From a communications standpoint, intranets are useful to communicate strategic initiatives that have a global reach throughout the organization.  The type of information that can easily be conveyed is the purpose of the initiative and what the initiative is aiming to achieve, who is driving the initiative, results achieved to date, and who to speak to for more information. By providing this information on the intranet, staff have the opportunity to keep up-to-date with the strategic focus of the organization. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Web publishing allows <b>cumbersome</b> corporate knowledge to be maintained and easily accessed throughout the company using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/287801.xml">
hypermedia</link> and Web technologies. Examples include: employee manuals, benefits documents, company policies, business standards, newsfeeds, and even training, can be accessed using common Internet standards (Acrobat files, Flash files, CGI applications). Because each business unit can update the online copy of a document, the most recent version is always available to employees using the intranet.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Business operations and management: Intranets are also being used as a platform for developing and deploying applications to support business operations and decisions across the internetworked enterprise.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Cost-effective: Users can view information and data via web-browser rather than maintaining physical documents such as procedure manuals, internal phone list and requisition forms.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Promote common corporate culture: Every user is viewing the same information within the Intranet.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Enhance Collaboration: With information easily accessible by all authorised users, teamwork is enabled.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Cross-platform Capability: Standards-compliant web browsers are available for Windows, Mac, and UNIX.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Planning and creating an intranet</st>
<p>

Most organizations devote considerable resources into the planning and implementation of their intranet as it is of strategic importance to the organization's success. Some of the planning would include topics such as:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The purpose and goals the intranet</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Persons or departments responsible for implementation and management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Implementation schedules and phase-out of existing systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Defining and implementing security of the intranet</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 How they'll ensure to keep it within legal boundaries and other constraints</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Level of interactivity (eg <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/32851.xml">
wiki</link>s, on-line forms) desired.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Is the input of new data and updating of existing data to be centrally controlled or devolved.</entry>
</list>

These are in addition to the hardware and software decisions (like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/75885.xml">
Content Management Systems</link>), participation issues (like good taste, harassment, confidentiality), and features to be supported <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>.</p>
<p>

The actual implementation would include steps such as
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 User involvement to identify users' information needs.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Setting up web server(s) with the appropriate hardware and software.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Setting up web server access using a TCP/IP network.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Installing required user applications on computers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Creation of document framework for the content to be hosted.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 User involvement in testing and promoting use of intranet.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<portal wordnetid="103985684" confidence="0.8">
<way wordnetid="104564698" confidence="0.8">
<access wordnetid="102671062" confidence="0.8">
<entrance wordnetid="103290771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/5016773.xml">
Enterprise portal</link></entrance>
</access>
</way>
</portal>
</artifact>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/131823.xml">
Extranet</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/2050786.xml">
Intraweb</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/17739.xml">
Local Area Network</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/38140.xml">
Wide Area Network</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/54293.xml">
Web portal</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/4038708.xml">
Servers</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Stephen Lawton's <it>Digital News &amp; Review</it> article "Intranets Fuel Growth of Internet Access Tools." <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.afab.com/DNR_intranets.htm">
http://www.afab.com/DNR_intranets.htm</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
Callaghan, J. (2002), "<b>Inside Intranets &amp; Extranets: Knowledge Management AND the Struggle for Power</b>", Palgrave Macmillan, ISBN 0-333-98743-8</entry>
<entry id="3">
Pernice Coyne, Kara; Schwartz, Mathew; Nielsen, Jakob (2007), "<b>Intranet Design Annual 2007</b>", <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/1240594.xml">
Nielsen Norman Group</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry id="4">
University of South Carolina <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.libsci.sc.edu/bob/class/clis724/SpecialLibrariesHandbook/Int&amp;SpecLib.html">
Making the most of inhouse communications</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bookrags.com/sciences/computerscience/intranet-csci-04.html">
Intranet: Table of Contents | Macmillan Computer Sciences: Internet and Beyond</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.steptwo.com.au/papers/kmc_continuousimprovement/index.html</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.useit.com/alertbox/intranet_design.html</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
