<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:41:40[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>DELTA (ELT)</title>
<id>3760381</id>
<revision>
<id>241098231</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-26T10:33:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>XLinkBot</username>
<id>6163802</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>English-language education</category>
<category>Professional certification</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Articles lacking reliable references from January 2008</category>
<category>All articles lacking sources</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  that appear in reliable, third-party publications.</b>
s and sources affiliated with the subject of the article are generally not sufficient for a Wikipedia article. Please include more appropriate  from , or discuss the issue on the talk page. <it>(January 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


</p>
<p>

<b>DELTA</b>, the <it>Diploma in English Language Teaching to Adults</it>, is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/6251.xml">
professional qualification</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/415406.xml">
English language teaching</link> awarded by <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/741571.xml">
Cambridge Assessment</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
, formerly UCLES, a part of the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/31796.xml">
University of Cambridge</link></university>
.  The Diploma (or Dip) is often seen as a follow-up to the certificate known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/952323.xml">
CELTA</link>, once the individual has done a couple of years of teaching and has decided on a more long-term and serious commitment to the teaching of English.  The Dip does not cover related non-teaching responsibilities (administration, training of teachers, and so on), but those who undertake these tasks often hold this qualification, or its equivalent.</p>
<p>

The diploma is awarded upon passing a course which includes supervised teaching practice, observation of other teachers, completion of a range of written assignments, completion of an extended assignment, and a written examination. The DELTA is available in many different countries throughout the world. The course can be taken part-time over a year or more, or full-time over a period of two to three months. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/8997.xml">
Distance learning</link> is also available.  It is widely recognized around the world, as is the CELTA. The DELTA is also integrated into some MA programs.  The DELTA and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/3760614.xml">
LTCL DipTESOL</link> are often seen as roughly equivalent qualifications.</p>
<p>

The DELTA was introduced in 1999. It replaced the DTEFLA, the Diploma in Teaching English as a Foreign Language to Adults, which was administered jointly by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/85748.xml">
RSA</link> and <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/741571.xml">
UCLES</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
. The two qualifications were equivalent in level but the DELTA was more narrowly focused on teaching English as a foreign language; that is, the old qualification focussed on teaching English to those who need it for exams, study, work or travel, whereas the new qualification includes the needs of immigrants settling in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/210706.xml">
anglophone</link> countries. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Accreditation in the United Kingdom </st>
<p>

The DELTA is accredited by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/292134.xml">
Qualifications and Curriculum Authority</link> as a Diploma in Teaching ESOL at NQF level 7 on the <qualification wordnetid="104717139" confidence="0.8">
<fitness wordnetid="104716864" confidence="0.8">
<suitability wordnetid="104715487" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/3233460.xml">
National Qualifications Framework</link></suitability>
</fitness>
</qualification>
 for <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/9316.xml">
England</link></country>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/69894.xml">
Wales</link> and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/21265.xml">
Northern Ireland</link></country>
.  Following government restructuring of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/234351.xml">
Further Education</link> (FE) the DELTA alone will be insufficient to teach ESOL/EFL in FE from 2010. An <link>
extension module</link> has been created to help teachers and lecturers currently in employment and who already hold the DELTA to upgrade their qualification to the required Level 4 certificate of subject specialism.  However, teachers and lecturers employed from September 2010 onwards will be required to have completed a specialised Post-Graduate Certificate in Education (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/1231385.xml">
PGCE</link>) at NQF Level 7, as well as the Level 4 certificate, regardless of DELTA certification. Compared to the DELTA, the PGCE has a higher standard of observed classroom practice, content regarding classroom management, student assessment and curriculum development and also confers professional teacher status (QTS/QTLS) which the DELTA does not.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/952323.xml">
CELTA</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/1059235.xml">
Teaching English as a Foreign Language</link> (TEFL) for a discussion of travel-teaching</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cambridgeesol.org/teaching/delta.htm">
DELTA</weblink> - Official DELTA site</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thedistancedelta.com">
Distance DELTA</weblink> - Information on distance learning for the DELTA</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
