<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:38:53[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>CertTESOL</title>
<id>3760578</id>
<revision>
<id>209043016</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-29T17:51:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DinoBot2</username>
<id>7128788</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>English-language education</category>
<category>Professional certification</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

The <b>Certificate in TESOL</b> (CertTESOL) is an accredited <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/6251.xml">
professional qualification</link> awarded in the teaching of English for Speakers of Other Languages (ESOL) by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/13608331.xml">
Trinity College London</link>.  It is a commonly taken teaching qualification in the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/415406.xml">
English language learning and teaching</link> (ELT). Many people take this qualification in order to travel and teach around the world (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/1059235.xml">
TEFL</link> for an extended discussion).</p>

<sec>
<st>
About the Qualification</st>
<p>

The CertTESOL is designed for those with little or no experience of teaching English. It provides the basic skills and knowledge needed to take up a first post as an ESOL teacher. The program also gives an introduction to theory and an insight into the challenges facing the learner and the role of the teacher. </p>
<p>

The qualification is awarded upon passing a course which includes supervised teaching practice and written assignments, and is accredited in the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/292134.xml">
Qualifications and Curriculum Authority</link> at Level 4 on the UK <qualification wordnetid="104717139" confidence="0.8">
<fitness wordnetid="104716864" confidence="0.8">
<suitability wordnetid="104715487" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/3233460.xml">
National Qualifications Framework</link></suitability>
</fitness>
</qualification>
. The CertTESOL is widely respected and recognised by language schools around the world.  </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Availability</st>
<p>

The CertTESOL is available in many different countries throughout the world, and some institutions offer a portion of the course in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/8997.xml">
distance learning</link>. The course can be taken part-time over several months to a year, or full-time in a four- or five-week period.</p>
<p>

Experienced teachers can further their career by taking a more advanced diploma, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/3760614.xml">
LTCL DipTESOL</link>. This is often seen as a follow-up to the CertTESOL. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Admission Requirements</st>
<p>

The CertTESOL is open to all those for whom English is a first, second or foreign language. Your own use of spoken and written English will need to be of an appropriate standard for you to be a role model of English for your learners and help them understand the nature of the language. The validation guidelines set out the requirements - these include a minimum age of 18 and evidence of qualifications achieved for entry to higher education in the UK (A levels) or equivalent.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Comparative Qualifications</st>
<p>

The CertTESOL and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/952323.xml">
CELTA</link> are viewed as equivalent qualifications, both being recognized and accepted by the <body wordnetid="105216365" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/429846.xml">
British Council</link></natural_object>
</body>
 as an initial TESOL qualification for teachers in its accredited teaching organisations in the UK and in its own teaching operations overseas. Both have at least one hundred hours of instruction and six hours of supervised teaching practice. </p>
<p>

Similarly, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/3760614.xml">
LTCL DipTESOL</link> is viewed as equivalent to the DELTA, both being accredited in the UK at Level 7 on the National Qualifications Framework, as are Masters degrees. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.trinitycollege.co.uk/site/?id=201">
CertTESOL</weblink> - 'Trinity College London ESOL' CertTESOL page</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.trinitycollege.co.uk/locator/course_flash.php">
Course providers</weblink> - Where to take the CertTESOL course?</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
