<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:54:59[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<information  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106634376">
<electronic_database  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106588511">
<lexical_database  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106638868">
<wordnet  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106639428">
<database  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106637824">
<header>
<title>Banyan VINES</title>
<id>378184</id>
<revision>
<id>236384265</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-05T04:27:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Steeev</username>
<id>31035</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Operating systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<b>Banyan VINES</b> (for <it>Virtual Integrated NEtwork Service</it>) was a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link> network <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> and the set of computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/630770.xml">
network protocol</link>s it used to talk to client machines on the network.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/879635.xml">
Banyan</link> company based the VINES operating system on <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
, and the network protocols on the archetypical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/44221.xml">
Xerox XNS</link> stack. VINES formed one of a group of XNS-based systems which also included <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/363188.xml">
Novell NetWare</link></O>
 and <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/99695.xml">
ARCNET</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
; like most of these earlier products it has since disappeared from the market, Banyan along with it.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/1913008.xml">
James Allchin</link>, who has since worked as Group Vice President for Platforms at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft Corporation</link> until his retirement at January 30, 2007, worked as the chief architect of Banyan VINES.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 VINES technology </st>
<p>

VINES ran on a low-level protocol known as <b>VIP</b>, the <it>VINES Internetwork Protocol</it>: essentially identical to the lower layers of XNS. Addresses consisted of a 32-bit address and a 16-bit subnet which mapped onto the 48-bit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/9499.xml">
Ethernet</link> address in order to route to machines. This meant that, like other XNS-based systems, VINES could only support a two-level internet.</p>
<p>

A set of routing algorithms, however, set VINES apart from other XNS systems at this level. The key differentiator, <b>ARP</b> (<it>Address Resolution Protocol</it>), allowed VINES clients to automatically set up their own network addresses. When a client first booted up it broadcast a request on the subnet asking for servers, which would respond with suggested addresses. The client would use the first to respond, although the servers could hand off "better" <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/25750.xml">
routing</link> instructions to the client if the network changed. The overall concept  very much resembled <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
AppleTalk</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
's AARP system, with the exception that VINES required at least one server, whereas AARP functioned completely "headlessly". Like AARP, VINES required an inherently "chatty" network, sending updates about the status of clients to other servers on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../067/15067.xml">
internetwork</link>.</p>
<p>

Rounding out its lower-level system, VINES used <b>RTP</b> (the <it>Routing Table Protocol</it>), a low-overhead message system for passing around information about changes to the routing, and ARP to determine the address of other nodes on the system. These closely resembled the similar systems used in other XNS-based protocols. VINES also included <b>ICP</b> (the <it>Internet Control Protocol</it>), which it used to pass error-messages and metrics.</p>
<p>

At the middle layer level, VINES used fairly standard software. The <b>unreliable datagram service</b> and <b>data-stream service</b> operated essentially identically to <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/31929.xml">
UDP</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/30538.xml">
TCP</link> on top of <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/15323.xml">
IP</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
. However VINES also added a <b>reliable message service</b> as well, a sort of hybrid of the two that offered guaranteed delivery of a single packet.</p>
<p>

At the topmost layer, VINES provided the standard file and print services, as well as the unique <b>StreetTalk</b>, likely the first truly practical globally-consistent <link>
name-service</link> for an entire internetwork. Using a globally distributed, partially replicated database, StreetTalk could meld multiple widely-separated networks into a single network that allowed seamless resource-sharing. It accomplished this through its rigidly hierarchical naming-scheme; entries in the directory always had the form  <it>item</it>@<it>group</it>@<it>organization</it>. This applied to user accounts as well as to resources like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/5272.xml">
printer</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/41151.xml">
file server</link>s. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
VINES client software</st>
<p>

VINES client-software ran on most PC-based operating systems, including <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/20027.xml">
MS-DOS</link></O>
 and earlier versions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link>. It was fairly light-weight on the client, and hence remained in use during the later half of the 1990s, when many machines not up to the task of running other networking stacks then in widespread use. This occurred on the server side as well, as VINES generally offered good performance even from mediocre hardware.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Initial market release </st>
<p>

With the low bandwidth requirements inherent in the efficient StreetTalk model, global companies and governments that grasped the inherent advantages of world-wide directory services seamlessly spanning multiple time zones caught on to the technological edge that VINES brought to the IT table. Gas and oil companies, power companies, public utilities, the US Government including the State Department, Treasury Department, and the US department of Defense implemented VINES in world-wide operations. The US State Department, for example, was an early adopter of the VINES technology. Able to take advantage of the then high-speed 56k modems for telephonic connectivity of the developed world to the limited telephone modem speeds of 300 baud over bad analog telephone systems in the <politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<grouping wordnetid="101012360" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<categorization wordnetid="101012712" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/30305.xml">
Third World</link></categorization>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</social_relation>
</event>
</grouping>
</politics>
, VINES was able to link embassies around the world.  VINES also came with built-in point-to-point and group chat capability that was useful for basic communication over secure lines.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Defense Department adoption </st>
<p>

By the late 1980s the US Marine Corps was in search of simple off-the-shelf worldwide network connectivity with rich built-in email, file, and print features. By 1988 the Marine Corps had standardized on VINES as both its garrison (base) and forward-deployed ground-based battlefield email-centric network operating system. Using both ground-based secure radio channels and satellite and military tactical phone switches the Marine Corps was ready for its first big test of VINES, the 1990-1991 Gulf War. Units were able to seamlessly coordinate ground, naval, and air strikes across military boundaries by using the chat function to pass target lists and adjust naval gun fire on the fly. Ground fire support coordination agencies used VINES up and down command channels from Battalion-to-Regiment through Division-to-Corps and Squadron-to-Group to Aircraft Wing-to-Corps, as well as in peer-to-peer unit communication.  </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 VINES competitors </st>
<p>

For fully one decade Banyan's OS competitors, Novell and Microsoft, dismissed the utility of directory services. Thus VINES virtually dominated what would come to be called the "directory services" space from 1985 to 1995. While seeming to ignore VINES, Novell and eventually Microsoft, companies with a flat server- or domain-based network model, came to realize the strategic value of the directory services model. With little warning Novell went from playing down the value of directory services to announcing its own flavor, <link>
Netware Directory Services</link>, or NDS (eventually Novell would change their term NDS to mean Novell Directory Services).</p>
<p>

Microsoft, originally a 100% desktop operating system company, which had gone through its own round of operating system development, first with IBM by initially partnering with them to develop an Intel-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/147773.xml">
disk operating system</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/148169.xml">
PCDOS</link> and its Microsoft twin, <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/20027.xml">
MS-DOS</link></O>
, and eventually by sharing true network operating system development with <link>
IBM LAN Manager</link> and its Microsoft twin, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/1123994.xml">
Microsoft LAN Manager</link>. had parted company with IBM and continued its development of LAN Manager into what would become known as <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/33438.xml">
Windows NT</link></family>
, essentially its OS 4.0. NT was an originally a flat server or domain-based operating system with none of the advantages of either VINES or NDS.</p>
<p>

For Windows NT 5.0 (released as <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/33941.xml">
Windows 2000</link></version>
), however, Microsoft included <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/2807.xml">
Active Directory</link></part>
</component>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</concept>
</idea>
</system>
, an LDAP directory service based on the directory from its Exchange mail server. Active Directory was as robust as and, in several key ways, superior to VINES. While VINES was limited to a three-part name, user.company.org, like Novell's NDS structure, Active Directory was not bound at all to such a limiting naming convention. And, unlike either NDS or VINES, Active Directory had developed an additional capability, both lacked, its "forest and trees" organizational model. The combination of a better architecture and a marketing company the size of Microsoft signaled doom for StreetTalk, VINES as an OS, and finally Banyan itself.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Decline </st>
<p>

By the late 1990s, VINES' once-touted StreetTalk Services' non-flat, non-domain model with its built in messaging, efficiency and onetime performance edge had lost ground to newer technology.</p>
<p>

Banyan, always a technology-driven company and not a sales-driven company was unable to market its product far beyond its initial base of multi-national and government entities.  Unable to quickly develop an OS to take advantage of newer hardware, and not realizing that it was the Streetalk directory services itself, rather than the shrink-wrapped OS, that was the prime value added, VINES sales rapidly dried up, both due to these problems as well as the rapid rise of <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/33438.xml">
Windows NT</link></family>
. Banyan increasingly turned to StreetTalk as a differentiator, eventually porting it to NT as a stand-alone product and offering it as an interface to <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/18508.xml">
LDAP</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 systems. </p>
<p>

Dropping their Banyan brand, for <b>ePresence</b> in 1999, as a general <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> services company. It sold its services division to <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/61274.xml">
Unisys</link></company>
 in late 2003 and liquidated its remaining holdings in its Switchboard.com subsidiary which had been based in the StreetTalk technology.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Continuing influence </st>
<p>

Former Banyan customers, employees and technicians still communicate with each other via Internet <link>
user groups</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/33645.xml">
blog</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/38892.xml">
chat room</link>s. As the earliest implementers of directory services, former Banyan people had a ten year jump on both Novell and Microsoft in understanding both the business advantages as well as the architecture and implementation aspects of directory services. Former Banyan consultants now work in many areas of IT and still form a cadre with unique experience and unrivaled skills in the directory services industry. Consulting companies that once specialized in VINES now specialize in Active Directory and Unix, Linux and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link> implementations support for directory services. </p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</article>
