<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:55:22[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Education in Japan</title>
<id>379031</id>
<revision>
<id>243398142</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T10:30:46Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Flewis</username>
<id>7826393</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Education in Japan</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In successive international tests of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link>, Japanese children consistently rank at or near the top (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/5211371.xml">
TIMSS</link>)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/876446.xml">
Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology</link> (MEXT) is responsible for educational administration. 
<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/3205166.xml">
History of education in Japan</link></it> 
</indent>
<image location="right" width="150px" src="Terakoya_for_girls.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>
</p>
<p>

Formal education in Japan began with the adoption of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/156154.xml">
Chinese culture</link> in the 6th century. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/3267529.xml">
Buddhist</link> and <political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../820/5820.xml">
Confucian</link></political_orientation>
 teachings as well as sciences, <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<art wordnetid="102743547" confidence="0.8">
<fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.8">
<imaginary_being wordnetid="109483738" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/1119765.xml">
calligraphy</link></imaginary_being>
</fictional_character>
</art>
</artifact>
</creation>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/8691.xml">
divination</link> and literature were taught at the courts of <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<capital wordnetid="108518505" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/9974600.xml">
Asuka</link></capital>
</location>
</seat>
</area>
</center>
</region>
, <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/6792846.xml">
Nara</link></site>
 and <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/37652.xml">
Heian</link></site>
. Scholar officials were chosen through an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/244479.xml">
Imperial examination</link> system. But contrary to China, the system never fully took hold and titles and posts at the court remained hereditary family possessions. The rise of the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/28288.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Etymology_of_samurai_and_related_words%22])">
bushi</link></it>, the military class, during the <fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<era wordnetid="115248564" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/201198.xml">
Kamakura period</link></era>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
 ended the influence of scholar officials, but Buddhist monasteries remained influential centers of learning. </p>
<p>

During the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/164945.xml">
Edo period</link> (1603-1867), the <link>
daimyō</link> vied for power in the largely pacified country. Since their influence could not be raised through war, they competed on the economic field. Their warrior-turned-bureaucrat Samurai elite had to be educated not only in military strategy and the martial arts, but also agriculture and accounting. Likewise, the wealthy merchant class needed education for their daily business, and their wealth allowed them to be patrons of arts and science. But temple schools (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/3609189.xml">
terakoya</link>) educated peasants too, and it is estimated that at the end of the Edo period 50% of the male and 20% of the female population possessed some degree of literacy. Even though contact with foreign countries was restricted, books from China and Europe were eagerly imported and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/1360770.xml">
Rangaku</link> ("Dutch studies") became a popular area of scholarly interest.</p>
<p>

After the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/21033.xml">
Meiji Restoration</link> of 1868, the methods and structures of Western learning were adopted as a means to make Japan a strong, modern nation. Students and even high-ranking government officials were sent abroad to study, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../944/1105944.xml">
Iwakura mission</link>. Foreign scholars, the so-called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/705256.xml">
o-yatoi gaikokujin</link>, were invited to teach at newly founded universities and military academies. Compulsory education was introduced, mainly after the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/4206694.xml">
Prussian model</link>. By 1890, only 20 years after the resumption of full international relations, Japan discontinued employment of the foreign consultants.  </p>
<p>

The rise of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/1952028.xml">
militarism</link> led to the use of the education system to prepare the nation for war. The military even sent its own instructors to schools. After the defeat in World War II, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/87995.xml">
allied occupation</link> government set an <school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/87996.xml">
education reform</link></institution>
</educational_institution>
</school>
 as one of its primary goals, to eradicate militarist teachings and "democratize" Japan. The education system was rebuilt after the American model.</p>
<p>

The end of the 1960s were a time of student protests around the world, and also in Japan. The main subject of protest was the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/2991107.xml">
Japan-U.S. security treaty</link>. A number of reforms were carried out in the post-war period until today. They aimed at easing the burden of entrance examinations, promoting internationalization and information technologies, diversifying education and supporting lifelong learning.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Structure</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Kindergarten and Nursery school</st>
<p>

Early <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/167331.xml">
childhood</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/9252.xml">
education</link> begins at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/249429.xml">
home</link>, and there are numerous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/3778.xml">
book</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/29831.xml">
television</link> shows aimed at helping <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/83430.xml">
mother</link>s of preschool children to educate their children and to "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/83441.xml">
parent</link>" more effectively. Much of the home training is devoted to teaching manners, proper <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/1967733.xml">
social behavior</link>, and structured <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/18006808.xml">
play</link>, although <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/239515.xml">
verbal</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/21690.xml">
number</link> skills are also popular themes. Parents are strongly committed to early education and frequently enroll their children in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/432881.xml">
preschool</link>s.</p>
<p>

Kindergartens (<it>yochien</it> 幼稚園), predominantly staffed by young female <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/320947.xml">
junior college</link> graduates, are supervised by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/876446.xml">
Ministry of Education</link>, but are not part of the official education system. The 58 percent of kindergartens that are private accounted for 77 percent of all children enrolled. In addition to kindergartens there exists a well-developed system of government-supervised day-care centers (<it>hoikuen</it> 保育園), supervised by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/1327943.xml">
Ministry of Labor</link>. Where as kindergartens follow educational aims, preschools are predominately concerned with providing care for infants and toddlers. Same as kindergartens there are public or privately run preschools. Together, these two kinds of institutions enroll well over 90 percent of all preschoolage children prior to their entrance into the formal system at first grade. The Ministry of Education's 1990 Course of Study for Preschools, which applies to both kinds of institutions, covers such areas as human relationships, environment, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/1449866.xml">
word</link>s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/17524.xml">
language</link>), and expression. Starting from March 2008 the new revision of curriculum guidelines for kindergartens as well as for preschools came into effect.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Elementary school</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Japanese_classroom.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A typical classroom in Japanese junior high school
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/2664260.xml">
Elementary schools in Japan</link></institution>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</it>
</indent>
More than 99% of children are enrolled in elementary school. All children enter <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/1066022.xml">
first grade</link> at age six, and starting school is considered a very important event in a child's life.</p>
<p>

Virtually all elementary education takes place in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/56083.xml">
public schools</link>; less than 1% of the schools are private. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/299959.xml">
Private schools</link> tended to be costly, although the rate of cost increases in tuition for these schools had slowed in the 1980s. Some private elementary schools are prestigious, and they serve as a first step to higher-level private schools with which they are affiliated, and thence to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/19725260.xml">
university</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Junior high school</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/378410.xml">
Secondary education in Japan</link></it>
</indent>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/234954.xml">
Lower secondary school</link> covers grades seven, eight, and nine, children between the ages of roughly 12 and 15, with increased focus on academic studies. Although it is still possible to leave the formal education system after completing lower secondary school and find employment, fewer than 4% did so by the late 1980s.</p>
<p>

Like elementary schools, most lower-secondary schools in the 1980s were public, but 5% were private. Private schools were costly, averaging 558,592 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/34392.xml">
yen</link> (US$3,989) per student in 1988, about four times more than the 130,828 yen (US$934) that the ministry estimated as the cost for students enrolled in public lower secondary schools. 
Teachers often majored in the subjects they taught, and more than 80 % graduated from a four-year college. Classes are large, with thirty-eight students per class on average, and each class is assigned a homeroom teacher who doubles as counselor. Unlike elementary students, lower-secondary school students have different teachers for different subjects. The teacher, however, rather than the students, moves to a new room for each fifty-minute period. </p>
<p>

Instruction in lower-secondary schools tends to rely on the lecture method. Teachers also use other media, such as television and radio, and there is some laboratory work. By 1989 about 45 % of all public lower secondary schools had computers, including schools that used them only for administrative purposes. Classroom organization is still based on small work groups, although no longer for reasons of discipline.</p>
<p>

All course contents are specified in the Course of Study for Lower-Secondary Schools. Some subjects, such as Japanese language and mathematics, are coordinated with the elementary curriculum. Others, such as foreign-language study, usually English, begin at this level. The curriculum covers Japanese language, social studies, mathematics, science, music, fine arts, health, and physical education. All students also are exposed to either industrial arts or homemaking. Moral education and special activities continue to receive attention.  Many students also participate in after-school sport clubs that occupy them until around 6pm most weekdays.</p>
<p>

A growing number of JHS students also attend Juku, private extracurricular study schools, in the evenings and weekends.  A focus by students upon these other studies and the increasingly structured demands upon students' time have been criticised by teachers and in the media for contributing to a decline in classroom standards and student performance in recent years.</p>
<p>

The ministry recognizes a need to improve the teaching of all foreign languages, especially English. To improve instruction in spoken English, the government invites many young native speakers of English to Japan to serve as assistants to school boards and prefectures under its <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/301313.xml">
Japan Exchange and Teaching Program</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
. By 1988 participants numbered over 1,000.  This program seems to be being phased out in many areas where the supply of foreign native speakers facilitates their employment through less expensive private agencies.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
High school</st>
<p>

Even though <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/42556.xml">
upper secondary school</link> is not compulsory in Japan, 99% of all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/234954.xml">
lower secondary school</link> graduates entered upper secondary schools as of  2005<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. Private upper-secondary schools account for about 55 % of all upper-secondary schools, and neither public nor private schools are free . The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/1104032.xml">
Ministry of education</link> estimated that annual family expenses for the education of a child in a public upper-secondary school were about 300,000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/34392.xml">
yen</link> (US$2,142) in both 1980s and that private upper-secondary schools were about twice as expensive. </p>
<p>

The most common type of upper-secondary schools has a fulltime, general program that offered academic courses for students preparing for higher education and also technical and vocational courses for students expecting to find employment after graduation. More than 70 % of upper-secondary school students were enrolled in the general academic program in the late 1980s. A small number of schools offer part-time or evening courses or correspondence education. </p>
<p>

The first-year programs for students in both academic and commercial courses are similar. They include basic academic courses, such as <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/15606.xml">
Japanese language</link></language>
, <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English</link></language>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/26700.xml">
science</link>. In upper-secondary school, differences in ability are first publicly acknowledged, and course content and course selection are far more individualized in the second year. However, there is a core of academic material throughout all programs. </p>
<p>

Vocational-technical programs includes several hundred specialized courses, such as information processing, navigation, fish farming, business English, and ceramics. Business and industrial courses are the most popular, accounting for 72 % of all students in full-time vocational programs in 1989. </p>
<p>

Most upper-secondary teachers are university graduates. Uppersecondary schools are organized into departments, and teachers specialize in their major fields although they teach a variety of courses within their disciplines. Teaching depends largely on the lecture system, with the main goal of covering the very demanding curriculum in the time allotted. Approach and subject coverage tends to be uniform, at least in the public schools. </p>
<p>

Training of disabled students, particularly at the uppersecondary level, emphasizes vocational education to enable students to be as independent as possible within society. Vocational training varies considerably depending on the student's disability, but the options are limited for some. It is clear that the government is aware of the necessity of broadening the range of possibilities for these students. Advancement to higher education is also a goal of the government, and it struggles to have institutions of higher learning accept more disabled students.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Universities and colleges</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/2664075.xml">
Higher education in Japan</link></it>
</indent>
As of  1991, more than 2.1 million students were enrolled in 507 universities. At the top of the higher education structure, these institutions provide four-year training leading to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/188874.xml">
bachelor's degree</link>, and some offer six-year programs leading to a professional degree. There are two types of public four-year colleges: the ninety-six <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/2664137.xml">
national universities</link></group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
 (including the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/7735478.xml">
Open University of Japan</link></university>
) and the thirty-nine local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/1640986.xml">
public universities</link>, founded by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/74478.xml">
prefectures</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/19038.xml">
municipalities</link>. The 372 remaining four-year colleges in 1991 were private. </p>
<p>

The overwhelming majority of college students attend full-time day programs. In 1990 the most popular courses, enrolling almost 40 percent of all undergraduate students, were in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/26781.xml">
social sciences</link>, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
business</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
law</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/2593.xml">
accounting</link>. Other popular subjects were <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/9251.xml">
engineering</link> (19 percent), the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/53132.xml">
humanities</link> (15 percent), and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/9252.xml">
education</link> (7 percent). </p>
<p>

The average costs (tuition, fees, and living expenses) for a year of higher education in 1986 were 1.4 million yen (US$10,000). To help defray expenses, students frequently work part-time or borrow money through the government-supported <link>
Japan Scholarship Association</link>. Assistance also is offered by local governments, nonprofit corporations, and other institutions. </p>
<p>

According to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/5902984.xml">
The Times Higher Education Supplement</link>, the two top-ranking universities in Japan are the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/166215.xml">
University of Tokyo</link></university>
 and <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/187911.xml">
Kyoto University</link></university>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/819526.xml">
Juku</link></institution>
</kind>
</type>
</company>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/15431345.xml">
Yutori education</link></group>
</collection>
</law>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/301313.xml">
JET Programme</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/2664075.xml">
Japanese University Entrance Examinations</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/56085.xml">
Japanese school uniform</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/883941.xml">
Eikaiwa</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/15781401.xml">
Curriculum guideline</link></group>
</collection>
</law>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.apa.org/monitor/mar05/scores.html">
PISA scores for 15 year olds in Japan, 2005: </weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
STATISTICAL ABSTRACT 2006 edition(http://www.mext.go.jp/english/statist/index.htm)</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alnaja7.org/success/Education/times_world_ranking_2005.pdf">
The Times Higher Education Supplement World University Rankings</weblink>"&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link>).&#32;  TSL Education Ltd.&#32;(<link>
2005-10-28</link>).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-03-27</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Christopher P. Hood, <it>Japanese Education Reform: Nakasone's Legacy</it>, 2001, London: Routledge, ISBN 0-415-23283-X.</entry>
</list>

</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

David G. Hebert (2005). Music Competition, Cooperation, and Community: An Ethnography of a Japanese School Band. Doctoral Dissertation, University of Washington. Ann Arbor: Proquest/UMI.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kathleen S. Uno (1999). Passages to Modernity: Motherhood, Childhood, and Social Reform in Early Twentieth Century Japan. Hawai: University of Hawai'i Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mext.go.jp/english/index.htm">
Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/9252.xml">
Education</link> in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/689.xml">
Asia</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/68253.xml">
Sovereign
states</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/4243411.xml">
Afghanistan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/3301306.xml">
Armenia</link>1&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/16569312.xml">
Azerbaijan</link>1&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/16569349.xml">
Bahrain</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/2226161.xml">
Bangladesh</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/16569371.xml">
Bhutan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Brunei</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/1880014.xml">
Burma</link></education>
2&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/8603747.xml">
Cambodia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/407843.xml">
People's Republic of China</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Cyprus</link>1&nbsp;· 
<link>
East Timor</link>3&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../069/3520069.xml">
Egypt</link>4&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/18102855.xml">
Georgia</link>1&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/293121.xml">
India</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/852337.xml">
Indonesia</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/1332627.xml">
Iran</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/2347359.xml">
Iraq</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/5276547.xml">
Israel</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/379031.xml">
Japan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/6657224.xml">
Jordan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/6386465.xml">
Kazakhstan</link>4&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/1522498.xml">
North Korea</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/1495964.xml">
South Korea</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/16569380.xml">
Kuwait</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/16568262.xml">
Kyrgyzstan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/16569410.xml">
Laos</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/5989047.xml">
Lebanon</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/461990.xml">
Malaysia</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/2845577.xml">
Maldives</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/16569434.xml">
Mongolia</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/3920181.xml">
Nepal</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/3523609.xml">
Oman</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/2469201.xml">
Pakistan</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/7025539.xml">
Philippines</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../203/2676203.xml">
Qatar</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/674913.xml">
Russia</link>4&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/4243407.xml">
Saudi Arabia</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/447779.xml">
Singapore</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/4560910.xml">
Sri Lanka</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/4243402.xml">
Syria</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/16568312.xml">
Tajikistan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/1133834.xml">
Republic of China</link>5&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/550135.xml">
Thailand</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/4243200.xml">
Turkey</link>4&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/16568327.xml">
Turkmenistan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/16568373.xml">
United Arab Emirates</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/16568388.xml">
Uzbekistan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/1003714.xml">
Vietnam</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/10838211.xml">
Yemen</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/214529.xml">
Dependencies</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
,
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/1636026.xml">
autonomies</link>,other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/6450815.xml">
territories</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<p>

<link>
Aceh</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Adjara</link>1&nbsp;· 
<it><link>
Abkhazia</link></it>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Akrotiri and Dhekelia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Altai</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
British Indian Ocean Territory</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Buryatia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Christmas Island</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Cocos (Keeling) Islands</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Guangxi</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../067/250067.xml">
Hong Kong</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Inner Mongolia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Iraqi Kurdistan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Jakarta</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Khakassia</link>&nbsp;· 
<education wordnetid="100883297" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/895089.xml">
Macau</link></education>
&nbsp;· 
<it><link>
Nagorno-Karabakh</link></it>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Nakhchivan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Ningxia</link>&nbsp;· 
<it><link>
Northern Cyprus</link></it>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/5811793.xml">
Palestine</link> (<link>
Gaza Strip</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
West Bank</link>)&nbsp;· 
<link>
Papua</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Sakha</link>&nbsp;· 
<it><link>
South Ossetia</link></it>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Tibet</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Tuva</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
West Papua</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Xinjiang</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Yogyakarta</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";padding:0.4em 0.2em 0.2em; line-height:1.4em; font-size:95%;" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<it>Italics</it> indicates an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/523670.xml">
unrecognised or partially recognised country</link>.&nbsp; 
1 Sometimes included in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link>, depending on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/13973661.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Europe+and+Asia%22])">
border definitions</link>.&nbsp; 2 Also known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/19457.xml">
Myanmar</link>.&nbsp; 3 Sometimes included in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/22621.xml">
Oceania</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, and also known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/19159399.xml">
Timor-Leste</link>.&nbsp; 4 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/1775678.xml">
Transcontinental country</link>.&nbsp; 5 Commonly known as <island wordnetid="109316454" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/30107.xml">
Taiwan</link></island>
.&nbsp;</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
