<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:49:27[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<social_event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107288639">
<contest  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107456188">
<game  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100456199">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<header>
<title>The Art of the Heist</title>
<id>3822571</id>
<revision>
<id>211746662</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-11T22:35:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Anticipation of a New Lover&amp;apos;s Arrival, The</username>
<id>6510232</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Alternate reality games</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>The Art of the Heist</b> (aka <b>Stolen A3</b> or <b>Art of the H3ist</b>) was an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/197730.xml">
Alternate Reality Game</link> created to promote the <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/620051.xml">
Audi A3</link></car>
.
<sec>
<st>
The Game</st>
<p>

As a game, it falls under the classification of Alternate Reality Game, or ARG.  
The game involved, loosely, three layers of interaction.  Character Development and Back Story,  File and password <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/5694.xml">
Cracking</link>, and Live Events (or, generally, the Retrievals).  Players who were involved in the live events received special pins, and complimentary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/19644137.xml">
cell phones</link> (which, as a side note, were the root of some difficulty in getting activated by those who won them).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The story</st>
<p>

The story revolved around Nisha Roberts and Ian Yarbrough, and their art retrieval business, Last Resort Retrieval. The majority of the plot involved the attempts of Nisha, Ian, the players, and Nisha's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/5363.xml">
video game</link> designer friend, Virgil in trying to stop the world's greatest <product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/425514.xml">
art heist</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
.  Ian and Nisha, specifically, were hot on the tracks of a very coordinated theft team, which was led by a person who was initially identified only as Arclight.  Arclight was organizing theft timetables, commissioning forged replicas, doing reconnaissance work, and hiring all manner of unruly assistants for the big heist.  Virgil seemed to be the main suspect throughout much of the game, due to his odd behaviour and lousy attitude.</p>
<p>

Early in the game, a security camera recording was discovered which showed a shadowy villain stashing pieces of information inside 6 different Audi A3 cars.  The cars, throughout the course of the game, were all tracked down, and infiltrated by the Retrievers, to get back the information hidden in them.  By piecing together the whole of all data found in all cars, the full scope of the Big Art Heist was revealed.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Major Characters</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Nisha</st>
<p>

Nisha Roberts is an <product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/425514.xml">
art</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
 recovery expert working under the company name of Last Resort Retrieval, together with her boyfriend Ian.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Ian</st>
<p>

Ian is a computer hacker, and boyfriend of the often tempestuous Nisha.  Their relationship is explored to the degree of him being jealous of her being the one in the spotlight.  At one point in the game, he decides to boldly take on a job which Nisha would otherwise tackle, and is roundly criticised for his poor planning.
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Virgil</st>
<p>

Virgil is a legendary game designer.  He and Nisha are old friends.  He was married, but his wife died some years ago, sending Virgil's life into turmoil.  He has become a recluse, and had only recently (as of the time of this ARG) come out into the public eye once again, building a game based directly on Nisha Roberts, called <it>The Nisha Chronicles: Volume 1</it>.  During the game, Virgil was often foreshadowed as being the villain, but in reality he was simply paranoid due to his line of work, and traumatized by the loss of his wife.
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Arclight</st>
<p>

Arclight was the criminal mastermind behind the art theft.
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The Retrievers</st>
<p>

Essential to the play of the game were a number of real-life players, who would be broadly dubbed "retrievers."  Retrievers would be called in, on various occasions, to different places around the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, where they would attempt to retrieve an <link>
SD Card</link> from inside an <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/620051.xml">
Audi A3</link></car>
.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Game Websites</st>
<p>

<it>All in-game websites are now defunct.</it>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Stolen A3 - http://www.stolena3.com </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Virgil: King of Code - http://www.virgilkingofcode.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Last Resort Retrieval - http://www.lastresortretrieval.com</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Other Sites</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mckinney-silver.com/A3_H3ist/">
Art of the Heist Presentation</weblink> - An excellent presentation by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mckinney-silver.com/">
Mckinney</weblink>, one of the creators of this Alternate Reality Game, about the Art of the Heist</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</article>
