<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:58:31[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="104377057">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<standard  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107260623">
<system_of_measurement  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113577171">
<header>
<title>Health Level 7</title>
<id>384081</id>
<revision>
<id>243778041</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T00:15:38Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>William Avery</username>
<id>1398</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>International standards</category>
<category>ANSI standards</category>
<category>Standards organizations</category>
<category>medical informatics</category>
<category>Multi-agent systems</category>
<category>Health Standards</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Health Level Seven</b> (<b>HL7</b>), is an all-volunteer, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
not-for-profit organization</link> involved in development of international <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/261925.xml">
healthcare</link> standards.  “HL7” is also used to refer to some of the specific standards created by the organization (i.e. HL7 v2.x, v3.0, HL7 <link>
RIM</link> etc.). <p>

HL7 and its members provide a framework (and related standards) for the exchange, integration, sharing and retrieval of electronic health information. The standards, which support clinical practice and the management, delivery, and evaluation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/261925.xml">
health service</link>s, are the most commonly used in the world. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Organization</st>
<p>

HL7 is an international community of healthcare subject matter experts and information scientists collaborating to create standards for the exchange, management and integration of electronic healthcare information. </p>
<p>

HL7 promotes the use of such standards within and among healthcare organizations to increase the effectiveness and efficiency of healthcare delivery for the benefit of all. </p>
<p>

The HL7 community is organized in the form of a global organization (Health Level Seven, Inc.) and country-specific affiliate organizations. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Health Level Seven, Inc. (<b>HL7, Inc. </b>) is headquartered in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../60s/2060s.xml">
Ann Arbor</link></village>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/18859.xml">
Michigan</link></country>
, U.S.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The organizational structure of HL7 Inc. is as follows:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The organization is managed by a Board of Directors, which comprises eight elected positions and three appointed positions. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Members of HL7 are known collectively as “The Working Group”.  The Working Group is responsible for defining the HL7 standard protocol and is composed of Standing Administrative Committees and Working Groups.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>Standing Administrative committees</it> focus on organizational or promotional activities, such as Education, Implementation, Marketing, Outreach Committee for Clinical Research, Publishing and Performance Improvement and Tooling. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<it>Working groups</it> are directly responsible for the content of the Standards, framing the actual language of the specifications.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Origin</st>
<p>

HL7 was founded in 1987 to produce a standard for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/1075997.xml">
hospital information system</link>s. HL7, Inc. is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/541680.xml">
standards organization</link> that is accredited by the <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/659.xml">
American National Standards Institute</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (ANSI); it became accredited in 1994.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

HL7 affiliate organizations, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
not-for-profit organization</link>s incorporated in local jurisdictions, exist in over 40 countries.  The first affiliate organization was created in Germany in 1993.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Originally HL7 is one of several American National Standards Institute (ANSI) -accredited Standards Developing Organizations (SDOs) operating in the healthcare arena. Most SDOs produce standards (sometimes called specifications or protocols) for a particular healthcare domain such as pharmacy, medical devices, imaging or insurance (claims processing) transactions. Health Level Seven’s domain is clinical and administrative data. </p>
<p>

Today, HL7 has been adopted by several national Standards Developing Organizations outside U.S. and hence not being accredited by ANSI. However, HL7 is now adopted by ISO as a centre of gravity in international standardization and accredited as a partnering organization for mutual issuing of standards. The first mutually published standard is ISO/HL7 21731:2006 Health informatics -- HL7 version 3 -- Reference information model -- Release 1.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
 The Name "Health Level-7" </st>

<p>

The name "Health Level-7" is a reference to the seventh "application" layer of the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/22747.xml">
ISO OSI Reference model</link></system_of_measurement>
</advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
. The name indicates that HL7 is focuces on application layer protocols for the health care domain, independent of lower layers. HL7 effectively considers all lower layers merely as tools. :)</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Collaboration</st>
<p>

HL7 collaborates with other standards development organizations and national and international sanctioning bodies (e.g. ANSI and <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/14934.xml">
ISO</link></organization>
), in both the healthcare and information infrastructure domains to promote the use of supportive and compatible standards. HL7 collaborates with healthcare information technology users to ensure that HL7 standards meet real-world requirements, and that appropriate standards development efforts are initiated by HL7 to meet emergent requirements.</p>
<p>

About 45% of the global membership (of either HL7 Inc. or an HL7 affiliate) is located in Europe, 35% in North America, 15% in Asia-Oceania and 5% elsewhere. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
HL7 Standards</st>
<p>

Hospitals and other healthcare provider organizations typically have many different computer systems used for everything from billing records to patient tracking.  All of these systems should communicate with each other (or "interface") when they receive new information but not all do so.  HL7 specifies a number of flexible standards, guidelines, and methodologies by which various healthcare systems can do this. Such guidelines or data standards are a set of rules that allow information to be shared and processed in a uniform and consistent manner.  These data standards are meant to allow healthcare organizations to easily share clinical information.  Theoretically, this ability to exchange information should help to minimize the tendency for medical care to be geographically isolated and highly variable.</p>
<p>

HL7 develops Conceptual Standards (i.e. HL7 <link>
RIM</link>), Document Standards (i.e. HL7 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/4684004.xml">
CDA</link></system_of_measurement>
</format>
</standard>
</information>
</message>
), Application Standards (i.e. HL7 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/1322806.xml">
CCOW</link>) and Messaging Standards (i.e. HL7 v2.x and v3.0).  Messaging standards are particularly important because they define how information is packaged and communicated from one party to another.  Such standards set the language, structure and data types required for seamless integration from one system to another <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chcf.org/documents/CCDPProjectOverview.pdf">
http://www.chcf.org/documents/CCDPProjectOverview.pdf</weblink>.  </p>
<p>

HL7 encompasses the complete life cycle of a standards specification including the development, adoption, market recognition, utilization, and adherence.  Access to the HL7 standards requires paid membership of HL7 Inc. or one of its affiliates.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
HL7 Version 2.x</st>
<p>

The HL7 version 2 standard has the aim to support hospital workflows. It was originally created in 1987.</p>
<p>

<b>V2.x Messaging</b></p>
<p>

HL7 version 2 defines a series of electronic messages to support administrative, logistical, financial as well as clinical processes. Since 1987 the standard has been updated regularly, resulting in versions 2.1, 2.2, 2.3, 2.3.1, 2.4, 2.5, 2.5.1 and 2.6. Collectively these versions are known as <b>version 2.x</b>. The v2.x standards are backwards compatible, i.e. a message based on version 2.3 will be understood by an application that supports version 2.6.</p>
<p>

HL7 v2.x mostly uses a proprietary (non-XML) encoding syntax based on delimiters. </p>
<p>

HL7 v2.x has allowed for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/41285.xml">
interoperability</link> between electronic Patient Administration Systems (PAS), Electronic Practice Management (EPM) systems, Laboratory Information Systems (LIS), Dietary, Pharmacy and Billing systems as well as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/930653.xml">
Electronic Medical Record</link> (EMR) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/1129641.xml">
Electronic Health Record</link> (EHR) systems.  Currently, HL7’s v2.x messaging standard is supported by every major medical information systems vendor in the United States <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aspe.hhs.gov/sp/nhii/standards.html">
http://aspe.hhs.gov/sp/nhii/standards.html</weblink>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
HL7 Version 3</st>
<p>

The HL7 version 3 standard has the aim to support any and all healthcare workflows. Development of version 3 started around 1995, resulting in an initial standard publication in 2005. The v3 standard, as opposed to version 2, is based on a formal methodology (the HDF) and object oriented principles.</p>
<p>

<b>RIM</b></p>
<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/library/data-model/RIM/modelpage_mem.htm">
Reference Information Model</weblink> (RIM) is the cornerstone of the HL7 Version 3 development process and an essential part of the HL7 V3 development methodology.  RIM expresses the data content needed in a specific clinical or administrative context and provides an explicit representation of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/18077.xml">
lexical</link> connections that exist between the information carried in the fields of HL7 messages.  The RIM is essential to increasing precision and reducing implementation costs.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/Library/data-model/">
Models are available.</weblink></p>
<p>

<b>HL7 Development Framework</b></p>
<p>

The HL7 Version 3 Development Framework (HDF) is a continuously evolving process that seeks to develop specifications that facilitate interoperability between healthcare systems.  The HL7 RIM, vocabulary specifications, and model-driven process of analysis and design combine to make HL7 Version 3 one methodology for development of consensus-based standards for healthcare information system <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/41285.xml">
interoperability</link>.  The HDF is the most current rendition of the HL7 V3 development methodology.</p>
<p>

The HDF documents the processes, tools, actors, rules, and artifacts relevant to development of all HL7 standard specifications, not just messaging. Eventually, the HDF will encompass all of the HL7 standard specifications, including any new standards resulting from analysis of electronic health record architectures and requirements.</p>
<p>

HL7 specifications draw upon codes and vocabularies from a variety of sources.  The V3 vocabulary work assures that the systems implementing HL7 specifications have an unambiguous understanding of the code sources and code value domains they are using. </p>
<p>

<b>V3 Messaging</b></p>
<p>

The HL7 version 3 messaging standard defines a series of electronic messages (called <it>interactions</it>) to support any and all healthcare workflows. HL7 v3 messages are based on an XML encoding syntax.</p>
<p>

<b>V3 Clinical Document Architecture</b></p>
<p>

The HL7 version 3 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/4684004.xml">
Clinical Document Architecture</link></system_of_measurement>
</format>
</standard>
</information>
</message>
 (CDA) is an XML-based markup standard intended to specify the encoding, structure and semantics of clinical documents for exchange.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

See <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/4684004.xml">
Clinical Document Architecture</link></system_of_measurement>
</format>
</standard>
</information>
</message>
 for details.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

HL7 standards are very complex and hence it should be carefully designed by programmer.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods applied by HL7</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Arden syntax </st>

<p>

The <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/2661240.xml">
Arden syntax</link></system_of_measurement>
</format>
</standard>
</information>
</message>
 is a language for encoding medical knowledge. HL7 adopted and oversees the standard beginning with Arden syntax 2.0. These <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/4438288.xml">
Medical Logic Modules</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/4438288.xml">
MLM</link>s) are used in the clinical setting as they can contain sufficient knowledge to make single medical decisions.  They can produce alerts, diagnoses, interpretations, and contain a quality assurance function and administrative support.  An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/4438288.xml">
MLM</link> must be run on a computer that meets the minimum system requirements and has the correct program installed.  Once this is provided, the MLM can give advice when and where it is needed.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
MLLP</st>
<p>

A large portion of HL7 messaging is transported by Minimal Lower Layer Protocol (MLLP). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/technet/prodtechnol/biztalk/2006/library/hl7/906524fa-5870-4336-bc9a-e90c4461f053.mspx?mfr=true">
http://www.microsoft.com/technet/prodtechnol/biztalk/2006/library/hl7/906524fa-5870-4336-bc9a-e90c4461f053.mspx?mfr=true</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/integration/b2b/pdf/11_B2B_Lesson_HL7_MLLP.pdf">
http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/integration/b2b/pdf/11_B2B_Lesson_HL7_MLLP.pdf</weblink></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
CCOW</st>
<p>

Specification of components for context management , See: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/1322806.xml">
CCOW</link></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Functional EHR and PHR specifications</st>
<p>

Functional specifications for an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/1129641.xml">
electronic health record</link></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Country specific aspects</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Finland</st>

<p>

<b>National IT services for healthcare</b></p>
<p>

The Social Insurance Institution of Finland is building a national ePrescribing and
patient record archival service based on HL7 CDA R2 and V3 messages. Phased
deployment is scheduled for 2008-2011. Version 2 messaging is widely deployed in most 
hospitals and healthcare centers. CDA R1 is used in sharing patient records on 
a regional level.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hl7.fi">
HL7 Finland national affiliate</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Germany</st>
<p>

The German chapter of HL7 was founded in 1993. This is an entity for benefit to the public and registered as an association as HL7 e. V. </p>
<p>

Due to federal structure of operational administration in German healthcare, the standardization aspect is much behind the possibilities of the public economy and due to competitive interests in industry of low normative impact to healthcare information systems development. Currently HL7 in Germany still operates as an informal cluster without direct affiliation to national standardization. </p>
<p>

The voluntary membership in HL7 relies on personal interest and engagement of clinical users and mainly on industrial interest: Clinical memberships are in minority. There is no membership of governmental administration and thus low contribution to ongoing discussion e.g. on patient data records (EPA = elektronische Patientenakte) balancing data availability vs. data security. Impact on productivity for clininal information systems (KIS = Krankenhaus-Informationssysteme) is of no importance yet, as the variability of KIS has not been challenged by HL7.</p>
<p>

Governmental funding for a broader adoption of HL7 does yet not exist in Germany, neither on federal level nor in most of the regional governments.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
the Netherlands</st>
<p>

<b>AORTA - National Healthcare ICT infrastructure</b></p>
<p>

AORTA is the Dutch national infrastructure for the exchange of data between healthcare providers. AORTA uses HL7 version 3 messages and documents as its core mechanism for information exchange. The initial specifications were created in 2003. 
The Dutch Ministry of Health is working on a virtual national Electronic Patient Records (EPR) which will enable healthcare providers to share patient data. This development takes place in close collaboration with NICTIZ, the National Information and Communication Technology Institute for Healthcare. NICTIZ coordinates its efforts with regard to the usage of HL7 version 3 with the volunteers of HL7 the Netherlands. </p>
<p>

Almost all hospitals use HL7 version 2 to support hospital-internal workflows. EDIfact is being used to support workflows involving general practitioners (GPs/PCPs). EDIfact will be slowly replaced by HL7 version 3. 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hl7.nl">
HL7 the Netherlands</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nictiz.nl">
NICTIZ</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ringholm.de/docs/00980_en.htm">
AORTA whitepaper</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

=</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
USA</st>
<p>

<b>HIPAA</b></p>
<p>

HL7’s initial involvement in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/384064.xml">
Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act</link> (HIPAA) legislation began in 1996 with the formation of the Attachments special interest group to standardize the supplemental information needed to support health care insurance, and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/9611.xml">
e-commerce</link> transactions. The initial deliverable of this group was six recommended Claims Attachments for the Notice of Proposed Rule Making (NPRM) process. Future attachment projects include, but are not limited to, Home Health, Skilled Nursing Facility, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/8052331.xml">
durable medical equipment</link> (DME), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/1471159.xml">
end stage renal disease</link> (ESRD), and Pre-Authorization and Referrals. The Attachment special interest group has the responsibility for the implementation of the Administrative Simplification provisions of HIPAA mandates, providing on-going support, and representing HL7 in the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aspe.hhs.gov/admnsimp/final/dsmo.htm">
HIPAA Designated Standards Maintenance Organization (DSMO)</weblink>efforts. Its purpose is to encourage the use of HL7 for uniform implementation of this supplemental information. This SIG coordinates industry input to produce and maintain guides for HL7 messages that can stand alone or be embedded within <link>
ASC X12N</link> transactions.</p>
<p>

<b>Hurricane Katrina</b></p>
<p>

The HL7 group joined forces with the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.himssehrva.org/ASP/index.asp">
Electronic Health Record Vendors Association (EHRVA)</weblink> to assist patients in the aftermath of <hurricane wordnetid="111467018" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/2569378.xml">
Hurricane Katrina</link></hurricane>
. Members of both organizations were actively working on activities with local, state wide and national agencies (including the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dhhs.gov">
DHHS</weblink> and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/">
CDC</weblink>) to provide solutions for those in the affected area.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/4684004.xml">
Clinical Document Architecture (CDA)</link></system_of_measurement>
</format>
</standard>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/3626922.xml">
CDISC</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
DICOM</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/1547057.xml">
eHealth</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/8336428.xml">
EHRcom</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/8098264.xml">
European Institute for Health Records</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
European Union</link></economy>
)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/351581.xml">
Health Informatics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/8336020.xml">
Health Informatics Service Architecture</link> (HISA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/13772997.xml">
Healthcare Services Specification Project</link></system_of_measurement>
</format>
</standard>
</information>
</message>
 (HSSP)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/8837975.xml">
ISO TC 215</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/1756617.xml">
IHE</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/3154110.xml">
LOINC</link></format>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/2241254.xml">
openEHR Foundation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/2556015.xml">
SNOMED</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/3161236.xml">
SNOMED CT</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/7730818.xml">
Public Health Information Network</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lists.hl7.org/read/attachment/117742/1/membership_worldwide.xls">
HL7 Membership Numbers</weblink> as sent to the HL7 affiliates on 2007-11-08.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.HL7.org/">
HL7.org Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.HL7.org/EHR">
HL7.org EHR Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HL7 is a member of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.global-e-health-standards.org/">
Joint Initiative on SDO Global Health Informatics Standardization</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.HL7.org.au/HL7-Tools.htm">
HL7 Tools Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahml.org.au/">
Australian Healthcare Messaging Laboratory (AHML) - Online HL7 Message Testing and Certification</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aurora.regenstrief.org/javasig">
Comprehensive Implementation of HL7 v3 Specifications in Java</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fortherecordmag.com/archives/ftr_01082007p22.shtml">
HL7 101: A Beginner’s Guide</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hl7-experts.info/">
International HL7 Experts Consortium</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hl7connection.com/">
HL7 Connection – Blog; News, Tips, and Tools</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acadam.de/HL7Analyzer.zip">
free HL7 Analyzing Tool</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.duke.edu/~jgm/files/nist.2006.ppt">
NIST HL7 Conformance Testing Framework</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Critical reviews</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ontology.buffalo.edu/hl7/doublestandards.pdf">
HL7 RIM: An Incoherent Standard</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aurora.regenstrief.org/~schadow/Schadow-MIE06-r3.pdf">
The HL7 RIM Under Scrutiny - rebuttal</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hl7-watch.blogspot.com/">
HL7 Watch – Blog; critical review of HL7</weblink>. See also the posted comments for rebuttals to some of the critical theses advanced.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Open source tools</st>
<p>

There are a number of  OSS based tools that can foster worldwide adoption of the HL7 standards
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aurora.regenstrief.org/javasig">
The HL7 Java Special Interest Group's implementation of HL7 v3</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eclipse.org/ohf">
The Eclipse OHF project - v2 and v3 implementations (IDE type tools and run-time libraries)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mirthproject.org/">
The Mirth Project, a java based OSS HL7 interface engine</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hl7api.sourceforge.net/">
HAPI, An open-source, object-oriented HL7 2.x parser for Java</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hl7toolkit.sourceforge.net/">
The Perl HL7 Toolkit, an Open-Source HL7 Perl module</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pear.php.net/package/Net_HL7">
Pear (PHP) HL7 messaging API module</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aurora.regenstrief.org/xhl7">
The eXcessively Simple HL7 v2 Processing Platform using XML and XSLT</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rubyforge.org/projects/ruby-hl7">
The Ruby HL7 Library</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://xmlbeans.googlepages.com/">
HL7 Java binding</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nule.org/wp/?page_id=55">
nule.org HL7 Utilities</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</organization>
</system>
</article>
