<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:50:39[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<university  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108286163">
<header>
<title>Piedmont Technical College</title>
<id>3851106</id>
<revision>
<id>234901162</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-29T01:22:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Nightstallion</username>
<id>149211</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Universities and colleges in South Carolina</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox University</name>
<parameters>

<image width="150px" src="PiedmontSeal.gif">
<caption>

Piedmont Technical College
</caption>
</image>
<president>
Dr. Rayburn Brooks</president>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/">
www.ptc.edu</weblink></website>
<address>
P.O. Box 1467Greenwood, SC 29648</address>
<name>
Piedmont Technical College</name>
<state>
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/27956.xml">
SC</link></country>
</district>
</group>
</colony>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</social_group>
</body>
</region>
</state>
<established>
1966</established>
<motto>
<it>Porta ad successum</it>Gateway to success</motto>
<type>
Public, 2 Year</type>
<telephone>
(800)868-5528</telephone>
<country>
USA</country>
<city>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/134512.xml">
Greenwood</link></village>
</city>
</parameters>
</template>


<image location="right" width="250px" src="Piedmont_Technical_College.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Piedmont Technical College
</caption>
</image>

<b>Piedmont Technical College</b> is a comprehensive two-year <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/5696.xml">
community college</link> that serves seven counties in the Lakelands region of South Carolina. The college's primary site is the Lex Walters Campus in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/134512.xml">
Greenwood, South Carolina</link></village>
. Six additional County Centers also serve students in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/91910.xml">
Abbeville County</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/91891.xml">
Edgefield County</link>, <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/91879.xml">
Laurens County</link></county>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/91866.xml">
McCormick County</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/91865.xml">
Newberry County</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/91860.xml">
Saluda County</link>. Piedmont Technical College serves the largest geographic area of any institution in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/4455155.xml">
South Carolina Technical College System</link></group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
. The college was founded in 1966. Dr. Lex Walters led the college from 1969 to 2008. On Dr. Walters' retirement, Dr. Rayburn Brooks was named college president, and he assumed leadership of the college in March 2008.<p>

Piedmont Technical College offers academic degrees, diplomas, and certificates that are tied to the employment needs of the local community and area employers. The college's Continuing Education Division promotes local economic development with non-credit courses and training programs that serve individuals, businesses, and organizations. Piedmont Technical College has also received regional and state recognition for its distance learning programs.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Locations</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/locations/greenwood.htm">
<b>Lex Walters Campus</b> (Greenwood, SC)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/Abbeville">
<b>Abbeville County Center</b> (Abbeville, SC)</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/Edgefield">
<b>Edgefield County Center</b> (Edgefield, SC)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/Laurens">
<b>Laurens County Higher Education Center</b> (Clinton, SC)</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/McCormick">
<b>McCormick County Center</b> (McCormick, SC)</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/Newberry">
<b>Newberry County Center</b> (Newberry, SC)</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/Saluda">
<b>Saluda County Center</b> (Saluda, SC)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Academic Programs</st>

<p>

<b>ARTS &amp; SCIENCE:</b>
Associate of Arts; Associate of Science; and General Studies Certificate.</p>

<p>

<b>AGRICULTURE:</b>
Associate in Agriculture (Major in Horticulture)and Horticulture Landscape Management Certificate.</p>

<p>

<b>BUSINESS &amp; INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY:</b> Associate in Business (Majors in General Business, concentrations in Accounting, Management, Office Management and Business Transfer); 
Associate in Business (Major in Funeral Service);
Associate in Business (Major in Office Systems Technology; concentrations in Accounting, Legal, Medical, Spanish and Medical Coding); Associate in Computer Technology (Major in Computer Technology; concentrations in Programming, Networking and Internet); Automated Office Diploma; Accounting Certificate; Advertising Design Certificate; Cisco Computer Networking Certificate; Desktop Publishing Certificate; Entrepreneurship Certificate; Funeral Service Education Certificate; Illustration Certificate; Internet Certificate; Interior Design Certificate; PC Technician Certificate; Microcomputer Software Specialist Certificate; Office Technician Certificate; Photography Certificate; Professional Clay Certificate; and Word Processing Certificate.</p>

<p>

<b>ENGINEERING TECHNOLOGY:</b> Associate in Engineering Technology (Major in Electronic Engineering Technology); Associate in Engineering Technology (Major in Engineering Graphics Technology); Associate in Engineering Technology (Major in General Engineering Technology); Associate in Engineering Technology (Major in Mechanical Engineering Technology); and Computer Aided Drafting and Design Certificate.</p>

<p>

<b>OCCUPATIONAL TECHNOLOGY:</b> Associate Degree in Occupational Technology (Major in General Technology) and Associate Degree in Occupational Technology (Major in Vocational Technical Education).</p>

<p>

<b>INDUSTRIAL TECHNOLOGY:</b> Associate in Industrial Technology (Major in Automotive Technology); Associate in Industrial Technology (Major in Building Construction Technology); Associate in Industrial Technology (Major in Heating, Ventilation &amp; Air Conditioning Technology); Associate in Industrial Technology (Major in Industrial Electronics Technology); Associate in Industrial Technology (Major in Machine Tool Technology); Gunsmithing Certificate; Machine Tool Diploma; Welding Diploma; Carpentry Certificate; Computerized Numerical Control Certificate; Construction Management Certificate; Electrical Maintenance Technician Certificate; Heating Fundamentals Certificate; Industrial Maintenance Mechanics Certificate; Journeyman Welding Certificate; Machine Tool Operator Certificate; and Refrigeration Applications Certificate.</p>

<p>

<b>PUBLIC SERVICE:</b> Associate Degree in Public Service (Major in Criminal Justice); Associate Degree in Public Service (Major in Early Care and Education); Associate Degree in Public Service (Major in Human Services, concentration in Instructional Assistant); Basic Officer Training Certificate; Early Childhood Development Certificate; and Infant Toddler Certificate.</p>

<p>

<b>HEALTH SCIENCES</b>
Associate in Health Science (Major in Nursing); Associate in Health Science (Major in Radiologic Technology); Associate in Health Science (Major in Respiratory Care); Medical Assisting Diploma; Pharmacy Technician Diploma; Practical Nursing Diploma; Surgical Technology Diploma; Basic Emergency Medical Technician Certificate; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/1560270.xml">
Dental Hygiene</link> Certificate; General Health Science Certificate; Health Information Management Certificate; Massage Therapy Certificate; Medical Coding &amp; Billing Certificate; Medical Laboratory Technology Certificate; Occupational Therapy Assistant Certificate; Patient Care Technician Certificate; Phlebotomy Technician Certificate; Physical Therapy Assistant Certificate; Veterinary Technology Certificate.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu">
Piedmont Technical College</weblink> official website</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scteched.tec.sc.us">
South Carolina Technical College System</weblink> official website</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/coned">
Piedmont Technical College Continuing Education Division</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/dl">
Piedmont Technical College Distance Learning</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.edu/pottery">
Piedmont Technical College Center for Creative Economies (Pottery Center)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</university>
</article>
