<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:56:10[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>ID-based cryptography</title>
<id>385892</id>
<revision>
<id>235484182</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-01T00:26:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>MattTait</username>
<id>7757025</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cryptography</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>ID-based cryptography</b> (or <b>Identity-Based Encryption (IBE)</b> or <b>identity-based cryptography</b>) is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
public-key cryptography</link> in which the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
public key</link> of a user is some unique information about the identity of the user (e.g. a user's email address).  The first identity-based cryptosystem was a signature scheme developed by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/57314.xml">
Adi Shamir</link></scientist>
</person>
 in 1984<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, which allowed users to verify digital signatures using only public information such as the user's identifier.  Modern schemes include <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/7278723.xml">
Boneh</link></scientist>
/<link>
Franklin</link>'s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/16241421.xml">
pairing-based encryption scheme</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/16254122.xml">
Cocks's encryption scheme</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/200091.xml">
quadratic residue</link>s. 
<sec>
<st>
Usage</st>
<p>

Identity-based systems allow any party to generate a public key from a known identity value such as an ASCII string.  A trusted third party, called the <link>
Private Key Generator</link> (PKG), generates the corresponding private keys.  To operate, the PKG first publishes a master public key, and retains the corresponding <b>master private key</b> (referred to as <it>master key</it>).  Given the master public key, any party can compute a public key corresponding to the identity <it>ID</it> by combining the master public key with the identity value.  To obtain a corresponding private key, the party authorized to use the identity <it>ID</it> contacts the PKG, which uses the master private key to generate the private key for identity <it>ID</it>.</p>
<p>

As a result, parties may encrypt messages (or verify signatures) with no prior distribution of keys between individual participants.  This is extremely useful in cases where pre-distribution of authenticated keys is inconvenient or infeasible due to technical restraints.  However, to decrypt or sign messages, the authorized user must obtain the appropriate private key from the PKG.  A caveat of this approach is that the PKG must be highly trusted, as it is capable of generating any user's private key and may therefore decrypt (or sign) messages without authorization.  Because any user's private key can be generated through the use of the third party's secret, this system has inherent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/17114.xml">
key escrow</link>. A number of variant systems have been proposed which remove the escrow including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/391352.xml">
certificate-based encryption</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/391350.xml">
secure key issuing cryptography</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/391354.xml">
certificateless cryptography</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Protocol Framework</st>
<p>

<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/7278723.xml">
Dan Boneh</link></scientist>
 and <link>
Matthew K. Franklin</link> defined a set of four algorithms that form a complete IBE system:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Setup</b>: This algorithm is run by the PKG one time for creating the whole IBE environment. The master key is kept secret and used to derive users' private keys, while the system parameters are made public. It accepts a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/2290431.xml">
security parameter</link> <math>\textstyle k</math> (i.e. binary length of key material) and outputs:</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 A set <math>\textstyle \mathcal{P}</math> of system parameters, including the <link>
message space</link> and <link>
ciphertext space</link> <math>\textstyle \mathcal{M}</math> and <math>\textstyle \mathcal{C}</math>, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 a master key <math>\textstyle K_m</math>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Extract</b>: This algorithm is run by the PKG when a user requests his private key. Note that the verification of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authenticity</link> of the requestor and the secure transport of <math>\textstyle d</math> are problems with which IBE protocols do not try to deal. It takes as input <math>\textstyle \mathcal{P}</math>, <math>\textstyle K_m</math> and an identifier <math>\textstyle ID \in \left\{0,1\right\}^*</math> and returns the private key <math>\textstyle d</math> for user <math>\textstyle ID</math>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Encrypt</b>: Takes <math>\textstyle \mathcal{P}</math>, a message <math>\textstyle m \in \mathcal{M}</math> and <math>\textstyle ID \in \left\{0,1\right\}^*</math> and outputs the encryption <math>\textstyle c \in \mathcal{C}</math>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Decrypt</b>: Accepts <math>\textstyle d</math>, <math>\textstyle \mathcal{P}</math> and <math>\textstyle c \in \mathcal{C}</math> and returns <math>\textstyle m \in \mathcal{M}</math>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Correctness constraint</st>
<p>

In order for the whole system to work, one has to postulate that:</p>
<p>

<math> \forall m \in \mathcal{M}, ID \in \left\{0,1\right\}^*: Decrypt\left(Extract\left(\mathcal{P}, K_m, ID\right), \mathcal{P}, Encrypt\left(\mathcal{P}, m, ID \right) \right) = m </math></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Encryption schemes</st>
<p>

The most efficient identity-based encryption schemes are currently based on <link>
bilinear pairings</link> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/10225.xml">
elliptic curves</link>, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/1131644.xml">
Weil</link> or <link>
Tate</link> pairings.  The first of these schemes was developed by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/7278723.xml">
Dan Boneh</link></scientist>
 and <link>
Matthew K. Franklin</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>), and performs <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/1051442.xml">
probabilistic encryption</link> of arbitrary ciphertexts using an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/59458.xml">
Elgamal</link>-like approach.  Though the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/16241421.xml">
Boneh-Franklin scheme</link> is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/1182348.xml">
provably secure</link>, the security proof rests on relatively new assumptions about the hardness of problems in certain elliptic curve groups.  </p>
<p>

Another approach to identity-based encryption was proposed by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<cryptanalyst wordnetid="109981540" confidence="0.8">
<companion wordnetid="109945905" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<friend wordnetid="110112591" confidence="0.8">
<decoder wordnetid="109995398" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/578040.xml">
Clifford Cocks</link></decoder>
</friend>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</companion>
</cryptanalyst>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/16254122.xml">
Cocks IBE scheme</link> is based on well-studied assumptions (the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/1183041.xml">
quadratic residuosity assumption</link>) but encrypts messages one bit at a time with a high degree of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/2467473.xml">
ciphertext expansion</link>.  Thus it is highly inefficient and impractical for sending all but the shortest messages, such as a session key for use with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/53042.xml">
symmetric cipher</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Advantages </st>
<p>

One of the major advantages of any identity-based encryption scheme is that if there are only a finite number of users, after all users have been issued with keys the third party's secret can be destroyed. This can take place because this system assumes that, once issued, keys are always valid (as this basic system lacks a method of <link>
key revocation</link>).  The majority of derivatives of this system which have key revocation lose this advantage.</p>
<p>

Moreover, as public keys are derived from identifiers, IBE eliminates the need for a public key distribution infrastructure. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authenticity</link> of the public keys is guaranteed implicitly as long as the transport of the private keys to the corresponding user is kept secure (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Computer_security%22])">
Authenticity</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/40995.xml">
Integrity</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/353859.xml">
Confidentiality</link>).</p>
<p>

Apart from these aspects, IBE offers interesting features emanating from the possibility to encode additional information into the identifier. For instance, a sender might specify an expiration date for a message. He appends this timestamp to the actual recipient's identity (possibly using some binary format like X.509).  When the receiver contacts the PKG to retrieve the private key for this public key, the PKG can evaluate the identifier and decline the extraction if the expiration data has passed. Generally, embedding data in the ID corresponds to opening an additional channel between sender and PKG with authenticity guaranteed through the dependency of the private key on the identifier.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Problems with IB-cryptography </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Because the PKG generates private keys for users, it may decrypt and/or sign any message without authorisation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Because of the centralist approach for the PKG, IB-cryptography may be unsuitable for super-networks (such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The issue of implicit key escrow does not exist with the current <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/194112.xml">
PKI</link> system wherein private keys are usually generated on the user's computer.  A number of variant systems have been proposed which remove the escrow including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/391352.xml">
certificate-based encryption</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/458253.xml">
secret sharing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/391350.xml">
secure key issuing cryptography</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/391354.xml">
certificateless cryptography</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A secure channel between a user and the PKG is required for transmitting the private key on joining the system. Here, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/187813.xml">
SSL</link>-like connection could be a feasible  solution for large-scale system. This in turn requires the distribution of the PKG's authentic root public key which is an old and still not completely resolved issue with public key cryptography.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/590214.xml">
Trend Micro</link></company>
, owners of Identum's ID-based cryptography technology</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Adi Shamir, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iseca.org/modules/mydownloads/visit.php?cid=56&amp;lid=33">
Identity-Based Cryptosystems and Signature Schemes</weblink>. <it>Advances in Cryptology: Proceedings of CRYPTO 84, Lecture Notes in Computer Science</it>, 7:47--53, 1984</entry>
<entry id="2">
Dan Boneh, Matthew K. Franklin, Identity-Based Encryption from the Weil Pairing <it>Advances in Cryptology - Proceedings of CRYPTO 2001</it> (2001)</entry>
<entry id="3">
Clifford Cocks, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cesg.gov.uk/site/ast/idpkc/media/ciren.pdf">
An Identity Based Encryption Scheme Based on Quadratic Residues</weblink>, <it>Proceedings of the 8th IMA International Conference on Cryptography and Coding</it>, 2001</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.crypto.rub.de/its_seminar_ws0708.html">
Seminar 'Cryptography and Security in Banking'/'Alternative Cryptology', Ruhr University Bochum</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5091.txt">
RFC 5091 - the IETF RFC defining two common IBE algorithms</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hpl.hp.com/techreports/2003/HPL-2003-21.pdf">
HP Role-Based Encryption</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://planeta.terra.com.br/informatica/paulobarreto/pblounge.html">
The Pairing-Based Crypto Lounge</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://vsn.voltage.com">
The Voltage Security Network - IBE encryption web service</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://vsn.visus-it.com">
VSN Fully Managed Email Encryption Service - UK based IBE encryption web service</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ferris.com/2006/05/30/the-total-cost-of-ownership-for-voltage-identity-based-encryption-solutions/">
Analyst report on the cost of IBE versus PKI</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
