<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:51:12[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<computer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103082979">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<device  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103183080">
<machine  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103699975">
<web_site  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106359193">
<header>
<title>Computer game tracking websites</title>
<id>3865233</id>
<revision>
<id>237041956</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-08T10:57:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Christian Nurtsch</username>
<id>3814406</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Video game websites</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Computer-game-tracking websites</b> are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link>s that maintain performance statistics for players of certain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/5363.xml">
video game</link>s, allowing players to evaluate their competitive performance and ranking and allowing players to seek out others of comparable ability.
<sec>
<st>
 Examples </st>


<ss1>
<st>
GamerDNA</st>
<p>

The <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/12075550.xml">
GamerDNA</link></company>
 service allows gamers to track their game history across multiple platforms by aggregating history from Xbox Live, Xfire, Steam and other networks.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Battlefield Series</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/840342.xml">
Battlefield (video game series)</link></it>
</indent>

All games in the Battlefield Series have no official statistics and rankings colated by EA/DICE; however, there are third-party websites which have similar functionality, such as BF Tracks and BF2S</p>
<p>

BF Tracks provides nearly real-time and historical gameplay statistics for all public <it>Battlefield 1942</it> and <it>Battlefield Vietnam</it> servers (including servers running modifications). All such servers are continuously monitored and statistics from games played on each server are recorded in a database. Each player seen playing online is individually recognized within the database and players are ranked according to their "skill" based on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/164040.xml">
formula</link> that incorporates various parameters of the player's performance during gameplay. The  BF Tracks website provides a searchable interface to the database where players can view their statistics and see how they compare to every other player in the database. This is all performed automatically without the player needing to register themselves with the service.</p>
<p>

Battlefield 2 has several sites that offers a similar service to BF Tracks such as BF2S, but statistics are collected from the game itself which collect data from specific servers known as ranked servers, and most sites do not independently rank players based on their portfolio. However, these sites can, and most do, display and track more variables and statistics than BF Tracks could.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
GameTrack</st>
<p>

Another major tracking website is GameTrack. This site differs from BF Tracks in that it collects server/player data more often, resulting in true realtime tracking. In addition, it separates players into Rookie, Seasoned, and Veteran ranking classes depending on how much time they have in-game and how many maps they have played. GameTrack's ranking formula gives each game played a ranking, heavily depending on flags taken, kill:death ratio, and kill rate. GameTrack only retains game data from the last thirty days, older games are dropped and removed from stats. Players are tracked via their CD-Hashes, as opposed to just names.</p>
<p>

Getting a high percentage of your team's flag points is one of the main ways to get a good ranking on GameTrack, as it is weighted more than the other components. This ensures that team players get better rankings and veteran players are ranked against their peers.  Kill:death ratio will usually yield a high ranking when it is three and higher, and kill rate is considered good when it is around 1&ndash;1.5, although much higher numbers are possible.  The ranking system will give high rankings for low amounts in each category if a player's team did relatively badly and will also give lower rankings if the player's team did relatively well.</p>
<p>

As of January 2008 Gametrack has decided to cease collecting game statistics due to high bandwidth and a low budget. Instead the administrators opted to run the forums in the opinion that it is more used than the main site itself. However as stated in numerous gaming communities the administrators made this option based on a poll submitted on their forums, therefore biasing the whole question of site or forum as the forum goers would choose to keep it rather than have the site maintained instead. Many users of gametrack that prefer their own message boards are not aware of the poll that ran on the gametrack forum.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources</st>

<p>

The web site for gametrack is no longer fuctional
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</article>
