<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:56:18[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>MediaWiki:Blockedtext</title>
<id>388955</id>
<revision>
<id>233024513</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-20T01:41:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Xaosflux</username>
<id>502540</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

__NOEDITSECTION____NOTOC__<p>

[https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/w/index.php?title=Special:UserLogin Secure login]
<b>You are currently unable to edit pages on Wikipedia.</b>
<b><it>You can still read pages</it></b><it>, but cannot edit, change, or create them.</it></p>


<p>

Editing from $7 (your account, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/14921.xml">
IP address</link>, or IP address range) has been disabled by $1 for the following reason(s):
$2
This block has been set to expire: <b>$6</b>.</p>
<p>

Even if blocked, you will <it>usually</it> still be able to edit your  and contact other editors and administrators by email.</p>
<p>

<b>Note:</b> If you have JavaScript enabled, please use the [show] links across from each header to show more information.</p>




<p>

Other useful links:
&nbsp;&middot;
&nbsp;&middot;
Appealing blocks:  and </p>

<p>

<table style="margin:auto; width:100%; background:transparent;" class="collapsible collapsed">
<header style="text-align:left;">
What does this mean?</header>
<row>
<col>
 As on many websites, Wikipedia administrators occasionally  accounts and IP ranges that are deemed responsible for or related to problematic activity. You <b>may</b> be an innocent victim of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/136560.xml">
collateral damage</link>, whereby a block of some other activity has accidentally caused your account to be inaccessible. <b>Alternatively</b>,  your account or IP may have been identified by an administrator as responsible for or related to misuse, or some other breach of policy. <p>

If your account has been blocked by mistake, it will be reactivated very quickly, as soon as you let an administrator know of the problem. Otherwise, there is a rapid appeal process which obtains quick review by <it>other independent administrators</it>, and brief discussion of the matter. The box above gives the information you will need in either case, as provided by the blocking administrator.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 What is a block? </st>
<p>

A  is a measure used to protect Wikipedia from possible improper use, or modification in breach of . Once blocks are over, they become history unless problems recur. Blocks can apply to a user account, an IP, or a range of IPs.  identify unblocked usage which apparently should be blocked; this can be quickly rectified if incorrect.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Most common causes </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Your IP matches that used by another blocked account. Ask for further information and/or request unblocking.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Your account or a connected IP has been used in a problematic way, or your  was unsuitable and you need to choose another. The reason should be in the box above.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 You have just clicked a 'red link' - an article that does not yet exist - but you do not have access to  when no article exists already. Ask someone else to create the page for you, or  yourself to do so.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 You are using <it><work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<pedal wordnetid="103903424" confidence="0.8">
<accelerator wordnetid="102670683" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<implement wordnetid="103563967" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<bar wordnetid="102788689" confidence="0.8">
<lever wordnetid="103659292" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/1842570.xml">
Google Web Accelerator</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</lever>
</bar>
</act>
</implement>
</service>
</event>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</accelerator>
</pedal>
</work>
</it> or some other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/1752264.xml">
web accelerator</link>, or an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/769273.xml">
open proxy</link>, or other similar software to access this site, which can interfere with some aspects of Wikipedia's vandalism-management process. Some schools, colleges, workplaces and ISPs can also cause this problem. Disable these and try again, or see below.</entry>
</list>
</p>
</ss1>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<table style="margin:auto; width:100%; background:transparent;" class="collapsible collapsed">
<header style="text-align:left;">
What do I do now?</header>
<row>
<col feature="===" directly="===Alternatively," Appealing="==The" section="==">
<it>your reason here</it>&#125;}to the <b>bottom</b> of  (which you can edit while blocked, unless it is protected) to request unblocking. You will need to state a reason for this, and the block is then free to be discussed. Our  may help you in composing a persuasive unblock request.<p>

You may use the the freenode IRC network to discuss your block with administrators available at the time. If you have an IRC client, the unblock channel can be found at [irc://irc.freenode.net/wikipedia-en-unblock #wikipedia-en-unblock]. If you don't have an IRC client but still wish to use the channel, you can use <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://toolserver.org/~east718/?u">
this link</weblink> to the Wikimedia toolserver to use a web based client.</p>
<p>

If you cannot contact $1 or cannot resolve the matter privately, then independent unblock review as described above will be your best solution. More details and other options can be found at .</p>
<p>

<b>Please note:</b> While this block may be upsetting or unexpected, abuse of appeal processes, repeatedly using the unblock template when denied, , or , will often lead to  of that page preventing further use of the <it>unblock</it> template.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
IP blocked?</st>
<p>

If you are not blocked directly, your IP address ($3) or range has been "hard blocked" due to abuse either by the previous person who was <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/8622.xml">
allocated</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/53036.xml">
sharing</link> your IP address.</p>
<p>

Please copy-paste the following text to the <b>bottom</b> of .</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

{&#123;unblock-ip|1=$3|2=&amp;lt;nowiki&amp;gt;$2&amp;lt;/nowiki&amp;gt;|3=$1&#125;}
</indent>

<b>Do not do this if you were blocked directly or are not logged in</b>; instead, see the "Appealing" section above (under the "What do I do now?" header).</p>
<p>

If this problem affects you repeatedly, we encourage you to contact your <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/100245.xml">
Internet service provider</link> or IT department and ask them to contact <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="113790712" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/18618509.xml">
Wikimedia's</link></institution>
</group>
</foundation>
</community>
</gathering>
</company>
</social_group>
  about enabling <text wordnetid="106387980" confidence="0.8">
<line wordnetid="107012534" confidence="0.8">
<heading wordnetid="106343971" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/5933039.xml">
X-Forwarded-For</link></heading>
</line>
</text>
 HTTP headers on their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/78768.xml">
proxy server</link>s. This will reduce collateral damage from future autoblocks.</p>
</ss2>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<table style="margin:auto; width:100%; background:transparent;" class="collapsible collapsed">
<header style="text-align:left;">
Additional information</header>
<row>
<col>
<ss1>
<st>
Unregistered?</st>
<p>

<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/323710.xml">
MediaWiki</link></software>
, the software that Wikipedia runs on, identifies users without an account through their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/14921.xml">
IP address</link>. However, some IPs are shared by many people and as a result, unregistered users are sometimes blocked for the misbehavior of another editor. Since  have no way to accurately tell the claims of an innocent user from those of an anonymous vandal, you are strongly encouraged to <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special:UserLogin&amp;type=signup">
create an account</weblink>. See  for a full list of benefits that come with registration.</p>
<p>

Some blocks will still allow logged in users to continue editing. If you are currently blocked from creating an account, try the following:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Try again after the block on your IP address expires.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Create an account from a different computer.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ask a trusted friend on a different network to create an account for you. Be sure to change the password after logging in.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Use <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="113790712" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/18618509.xml">
Wikimedia's</link></institution>
</group>
</foundation>
</community>
</gathering>
</company>
</social_group>
 [https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/w/index.php?title=Special:UserLogin&amp;type=signup secure server]; this may bypass your network's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/78768.xml">
proxy server</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Emailing us</st>

<p>

Due to the high volume of email we receive, you are more likely to get a quick response if you try requesting an unblock via  first.</p>

<p>

Before you email us, please make sure your situation has not already been addressed by the above sections. Your  may also contain further details related to your block or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/14921.xml">
IP address</link><table style="margin:auto; width:100%; background:transparent;">
<row>
<col valign="top">
<b>To request unblocking:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IP address: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_talk:$3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Blocking admin: $4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Block reason: $2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Block originally applied to: $7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Your account name (if you have one): </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An explanation of why your block is unfair:</entry>
</list>
</col>
<col valign="top"><p>

<b>To request an account:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IP address: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_talk:$3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Blocking admin: $4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Block reason: $2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Block originally applied to: $7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Preferred account name:</entry>
</list>

<b>Note:</b> your preferred username must not be listed as already taken , and must comply with our .</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>

Even though emails sent to unblock-en-l mailing list are viewable only by  and trusted volunteers, under <b>no circumstances</b> should you email us your account's password or reveal it to anyone else even if asked to. When requesting an account, a temporary password will be generated and emailed to you. Please change the password on your new account as soon as possible.</p>
<p>

This list exists for the purpose of reviewing blocks only — any request to make edits to articles on your behalf will be disregarded. Correspondence containing ,  or  is likely to be ignored and may result in the lengthening of pre-existing blocks.</p>
<p>

<b>IMPORTANT:</b> Please do not email us without providing the information requested above.  We will always require that information to help you. [mailto:unblock-en-l@lists.wikimedia.org Click here to contact unblock-en-l].</p>
</ss1>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</bdy>
</article>
