<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:59:31[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<solvent  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="115047313">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<pollutant  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="114857278">
<header>
<title>Methyl tert-butyl ether</title>
<id>391568</id>
<revision>
<id>243680972</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T16:21:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Fuhghettaboutit</username>
<id>665998</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Hazardous air pollutants</category>
<category>Oxygenates</category>
<category>Pollutants</category>
<category>Ether solvents</category>
<category>Petroleum</category>
<category>Soil contamination</category>
<category>Ethers</category>
<category>Water pollution</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="float: right; clear: right; margin: 0 0 1em 1em; border-collapse: collapse;" width="250px" class="toccolours" border="1">
<header colspan="2" style="width: 30%; background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;">
Methyl <it>tert</it>-butyl ether</header>
<row>
<col>
 <image location="center" width="120px" src="MTBE-2D-skeletal.png">
<caption>

MTBE
</caption>
</image>
</col>
<col>
 <image location="center" width="120px" src="MTBE-3D-sticks.png">
<caption>

MTBE
</caption>
</image>
</col>
</row>

<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/3141503.xml">
IUPAC name</link></col>
<col>
2-Methoxy-2-methylpropane</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Other names</col>
<col>
Methyl <it>tertiary</it>-butyl etherMethyl <it>tert</it>-butyl etherMethyl <it>t</it>-butyl etherMTBE<it>tert</it>-Butyl methyl ethertBME</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
style="background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;" colspan="2"</header>
<header>
style="background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;" colspan="2"</header>
<header>
style="background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;" colspan="2"</header>
<col colspan="2" style="width: 30%; background: #F8EABA; text-align: center;">
 Except where noted otherwise, data are given for materials in their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/240224.xml">
standard state(at 25&nbsp;°C, 100&nbsp;kPa)</link></col>
</row>
</table>
<p>

<b>Methyl <it>tert</it></b><b>-butyl ether</b>, also known as <b>methyl tertiary butyl ether</b> and <b>MTBE</b>, is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/9722260.xml">
chemical</link> compound with molecular formula C5H12O.  MTBE is a volatile, flammable and colorless liquid that is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/13036672.xml">
immiscible</link>, yet reasonably soluble in water. MTBE has a minty odour vaguely reminiscent of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/765457.xml">
diethyl ether</link>, leading to unpleasant taste and odour in water. MTBE is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/23639.xml">
gasoline</link> additive, used as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/2195504.xml">
oxygenate</link> and to raise the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/147242.xml">
octane number</link>, although its use has declined in the United States in response to environmental and health concerns.  It has been found to easily <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollute</link> large quantities of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/262927.xml">
groundwater</link> when gasoline with MTBE is spilled or leaked at gas stations. MTBE is also used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/22208.xml">
organic chemistry</link> as a relatively inexpensive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/37431.xml">
solvent</link> with properties comparable to diethyl ether but with a higher <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/4115.xml">
boiling point</link> and lower <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/59497.xml">
solubility</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/17118471.xml">
water</link>. It is also used medically to dissolve <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/287531.xml">
gallstones</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Production</st>
<p>

MTBE is manufactured via the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/6271.xml">
chemical reaction</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/19712.xml">
methanol</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/1596651.xml">
isobutylene</link>. Methanol is derived from natural gas, and isobutylene is made from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/23195.xml">
crude oil</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/22131.xml">
natural gas</link>, thus MTBE, as used in motor gasoline, is a fossil fuel. In the United States, it was produced in very large quantities (more than 200,000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/594043.xml">
barrel</link>s per day in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link>) during its use as a fuel additive. Due to widespread releases of MTBE-containing gasoline from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/1744318.xml">
Underground Storage Tank</link>s all over the US, various jurisdictions banned the use of MTBE and production was reduced. MTBE contamination in drinking water <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/47481.xml">
aquifers</link> is a serious concern in many states (the most famous cases are <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/140899.xml">
Lake Tahoe</link></location>
</area>
</landmark>
</point>
</position>
</region>
</region>
 and Santa Monica).  By late 2006, most American gasoline retailers had ceased using MTBE as an oxygenate, and accordingly, US production had declined. Similarly, lack of growth or even decline of MTBE production has been seen in Western Europe. This is not due to environmental concerns; on the contrary, it is because the alternative ethanol-derived ether <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/1549946.xml">
ETBE</link> has been given more favorable tax treatment. Nevertheless, in other parts of the world, which account for about a half of 2004 production, the use of MTBE will continue and even grow.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Physical properties</st>
<p>

MTBE forms <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/56778.xml">
azeotrope</link>s with water (52.6 °C) and methanol (51.3 °C).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Uses</st>
<p>

MTBE is almost exclusively used as a fuel component in motor <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/23639.xml">
gasoline</link>. It is one of a group of chemicals commonly known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/2195504.xml">
oxygenate</link>s because they raise the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/22303.xml">
oxygen</link> content of gasoline. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
As anti-knocking agent</st>
<p>

In the US it has been used in gasoline at low levels since 1979  to replace <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/116035.xml">
tetra-ethyl lead</link> to increase its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/145997.xml">
octane</link> rating and help prevent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/228468.xml">
engine knocking</link>. Oxygen helps gasoline burn more completely, <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/627819.xml">
reducing tailpipe emissions</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 from pre-1984 motor vehicles. In more modern vehicles, the emissions reduction is negligible. In one respect, the oxygen dilutes or displaces gasoline components such as aromatics (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/18582186.xml">
benzene</link>) and sulfur. In another, oxygen optimizes the oxidation during combustion. Most refiners have chosen to use MTBE over other oxygenates primarily for its blending characteristics and for economic reasons. It is produced from natural gas, which is less expensive than oil.</p>
<p>

Since <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/34669.xml">
1992</link>, MTBE has been used at higher concentrations in some gasoline to fulfill the oxygenate requirements set by the <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
United States Congress</link></legislature>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/697291.xml">
Clean Air Act</link> amendments; however, since 1999, in California and other locations MTBE has begun to be phased out because of groundwater contamination (California Air Resources Board, 2004).  Due to its higher solubility in water MTBE moves more quickly than other fuel components (California Air Resources Board, 2004).  The Energy Policy Act of 2005 reduces the federal requirement for oxygen content in reformulated gasoline<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.</p>
<p>

In 1995  high levels of MTBE were unexpectedly discovered in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/15105978.xml">
water well</link>s of <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/28208.xml">
Santa Monica, California</link></village>
, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/191640.xml">
U.S. Geological Survey</link> reported detections.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  Subsequent U.S. findings indicate tens of thousands of contaminated sites in water wells distributed across the country. As per toxicity alone, MTBE is not classified as a hazard for the environment.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/391568.xml">
maximum contaminant level of MTBE</link> in drinking water has not yet been established by the EPA.  The leakage problem is partially attributed to the lack of effective regulations for underground storage tanks, but spillage from overfilling remains an important upset scenario.  As an ingredient in unleaded gasoline, MTBE is the most soluble part.  When dissolved in groundwater, MTBE will lead the contaminant plume with the remaining components such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/18582186.xml">
benzene</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/30699.xml">
toluene</link>, etc. to follow.  Thus the discovery of MTBE in public groundwater wells indicates that the contaminant source was a gasoline release.  Its criticism and subsequent decreased usage, some claim, is more a product of its easy detectability (taste) in extremely low concentrations (ppb) than its toxicity, as benzene is much more toxic but remains a fuel additive.  The MTBE concentrations used in the EU (usually 1.0–1.6%) and allowed (maximum 5%) in Europe are lower than in California.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

<ss2>
<st>
Alternatives</st>
<p>

Other compounds are available as oxygenate additives for gasoline, for example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/3398741.xml">
ethanol</link> and related ethers, e.g. <link>
tert-amyl methyl ether</link> (TAME). Reasons for using MTBE include economic considerations, as some of the production is obtained by adding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/19712.xml">
methanol</link> to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/1596651.xml">
isobutylene</link> produced as a by-product of other processes. However, most MTBE facilities have to manufacture the methanol and isobutylene required to produce MTBE.</p>
<p>

Ethanol has been advertised as a safe alternative by the agricultural interest groups in the USA and Europe. Its lack of toxicity is not different from MTBE, but as a polar solvent, it drives off nonpolar hydrocarbons from the gasoline, a problem that MTBE does not cause. Volatile hydrocarbons in gasoline vapors are known carcinogens and produce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/215047.xml">
photochemical smog</link>.</p>
<p>

Advocates of both sides of the debate in the United States sometimes claim that gasoline manufacturers have been forced to add MTBE to gasoline by law. It might be more correct to say they have been induced to do so, although any <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/2195504.xml">
oxygenate</link> would fulfill the law.</p>
<p>

In 2003, California was the first state to start replacing the MTBE with ethanol. Several other states started switching soon afterward. </p>
<p>

Higher quality gasoline is also an alternative, i.e. so that additives such as MTBE are unnecessary. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/1972482.xml">
Iso-octane</link> itself is used. MTBE plants can be retrofitted to produce iso-octane from isobutylene.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  Iso-octane is the ideal gasoline, being the standard reference for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/147242.xml">
octane rating</link>.</p>
<p>

In the long run, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/81761.xml">
diesel</link> fuel is also an alternative, although it requires a major switchover to diesel-run cars. There are several varieties of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/188551.xml">
biodiesel</link>; both oxygen-containing esters and oxygen-free alkyl biodiesels are available.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
As a solvent</st>
<p>

As a solvent, MTBE possesses one distinct advantage over most ethers- it has a much lower tendency to form explosive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/2296644.xml">
organic peroxide</link>s.  Opened bottles of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/765457.xml">
diethyl ether</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/240988.xml">
THF</link> can build up dangerous levels of these peroxides in months, whereas samples of MTBE are usually safe for years (but they should still be tested periodically). For this reason (as well as its higher boiling point), it is used as a solvent extensively in industry, where safety concerns and regulations make working with diethyl ether, THF, or other ethers much more difficult and expensive. However, despite the popularity of MTBE in industrial settings, it is rarely used as a solvent in academia. Research volumes are much smaller, leading to lower risks from other ethers, and in addition the use of MTBE as a solvent is very rare in literature synthetic procedures.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
As a chemical reagent</st>
<p>

Being an ether, MTBE is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/519765.xml">
Lewis base</link>.  However, unlike other ethers such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/765457.xml">
diethyl ether</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/240988.xml">
THF</link>, it does not coordinate well enough with magnesium to be used for making <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/454896.xml">
Grignard reagent</link>s. The <it>tert</it>-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/889926.xml">
butyl</link> group is easily cleaved off under strongly acidic conditions (forming a moderately stable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/241767.xml">
carbocation</link>), particularly if heated (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/1596651.xml">
isobutylene</link> is lost), something which can limit the use of MTBE as a solvent.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Persistence and pervasiveness in the environment</st>
<p>

The main environmental risk of MTBE is that it gives water an unpleasant taste at even very low concentrations, and thus can easily render large quantities of groundwater non-potable. MTBE is often introduced into water-supply aquifers by leaking <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/1744318.xml">
underground storage tank</link>s (USTs) at gasoline stations. Although USTs are much better constructed now than in the 1980s, accidental releases still take place because of the very large number of USTs. The high solubility and persistence of MTBE cause it to travel faster and farther than many other components of gasoline when released into an aquifer. It is also released when gasoline containing MTBE is spilled onto the ground. Because it is water soluble, it easily moves through soil, polluting both surface and groundwater.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

MTBE has widespread occurrences in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/47481.xml">
aquifer</link>s of <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/21139.xml">
North America</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, where the majority of groundwater chemistry data has been acquired. As one regional example, the <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/19283806.xml">
San Francisco Bay Area</link></location>
</area>
</region>
 Regional Water Quality Control Board has indicated MTBE is one of the groundwater pollutants of most widespread concern in this metropolitan region.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

MTBE is biodegradable to CO2 and water under aerobic conditions with the correct bacteria. However, the natural occurrence of these bacteria with the ability to break ether bonds is not high, and it appears that most strains of MTBE-oxidizing bacteria are slow-growing bacteria with low biomass production per unit MTBE oxidized. In the proper type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/616670.xml">
bioreactor</link>, such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/2467556.xml">
fluidized bed</link> bioreactor, MTBE can be rapidly and economically removed from water to undetectable levels.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health risks</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/1463550.xml">
IARC</link>, a cancer research agency of the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/33583.xml">
World Health Organization</link></organization>
, maintains MTBE is not classifiable as a human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/6445.xml">
carcinogen</link>. MTBE can be tasted in water at concentrations of 5 – 15 µg/l<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>.</p>
<p>

MTBE is not classified as a human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/6445.xml">
carcinogen</link> at low exposure levels by the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> However, exposure to large doses of MTBE carries significant non-cancer-related health risks. The effects of the prolonged presence of this alcohol derivative are not fully understood.</p>
<p>

As of 2007, researchers have limited data about the health effects of ingestion of MTBE. The <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
Environmental Protection Agency</link></agency>
 (EPA) has concluded that available data are not adequate to quantify health risks of MTBE at low exposure levels in drinking water, but that the data support the conclusion that MTBE is a potential human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/6445.xml">
carcinogen</link> at high doses.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Legislation and litigation</st>

<ss1>
<st>
United States</st>
<p>

MTBE is difficult to clean up due to its high solubility in water. Estimates of the cost of removing MTBE from groundwater and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/4229946.xml">
soil contamination</link> range from $1<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> to $30<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/1136363.xml">
billion</link>, including removing the compound from aquifers and municipal water supplies and replacing leaky underground oil tanks. There is some controversy centered around the question of who will pay the costs of this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/406260.xml">
remediation</link>. In one case, the cost to oil companies to clean up the MTBE in wells belonging to Santa Monica is estimated to exceed $200 million.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>  However, if one used the presently available <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/2467556.xml">
fluidized bed</link> bioreactor technology to remove the MTBE in this Santa Monica case, the cost would be a small fraction of the suggested $200 million.  It would be hard to justify the litigation cost, in this case, if it cost only a few million to clean it up.  </p>
<p>

Recent state laws have been passed to ban MTBE in certain areas. <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/5407.xml">
California</link></country>
 and <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/8210131.xml">
New York</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, which together accounted for 40% of U.S. MTBE consumption, banned the chemical starting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
January 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link>, and as of September 2005, twenty-five states had signed legislation banning MTBE. (A table of state by state information, as of 2002, is available at the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/62866.xml">
United States Department of Energy</link></agency>
 website.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

In 2000, the U.S. <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
EPA</link></agency>
 drafted plans to phase out the use of MTBE nationwide over four years.
As of fall 2006, hundreds of lawsuits are still pending regarding MTBE contamination of public and private drinking water supplies. </p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/2170017.xml">
Energy Policy Act of 2005</link>, passed in the House on April 21, 2005, did not include a provision for shielding MTBE manufacturers from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/312266.xml">
water contamination</link> lawsuits. This provision was first proposed in 2003 and had been thought by some to be a priority of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<officeholder wordnetid="110371450" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/216169.xml">
Tom DeLay</link></officeholder>
</person>
 and Rep. <congressman wordnetid="109955781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/938613.xml">
Joe Barton</link></congressman>
, chairman of the Energy and Commerce Committee.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> This bill did include a provision that gives MTBE makers, including some major <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/994887.xml">
oil companies</link>, $2 billion in transition assistance as MTBE is phased out over the next nine years.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> Due to opposition in the Senate,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> the conference report dropped all MTBE provisions. The final bill was passed by both houses and signed into law by President Bush.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> The lack of MTBE liability protection is resulting in a switchover to the use of ethanol as a gasoline additive, which is in limited supply as of April 2006. Some traders and consumer advocates are blaming this for an increase in gasoline prices.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> </p>
<p>

Certain patents important in the manufacture of MTBE are not held by American companies; for example, United States patent 5536886, <it>Process for preparing alkyl ethers</it>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> is owned by the Finnish company <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/2592783.xml">
Neste</link>. The same corporation also went on to patent the replacement of the MTBE process, an octane production process trademarked NExOCTANE.</p>
<p>

The United States Environmental Protection Agency (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
EPA</link>) currently lists methyl tertiary butyl ether (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/391568.xml">
MTBE</link>) as a candidate for a maximum contaminant level (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/5099796.xml">
MCL</link>) in drinking water<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref>. MCLs are determined by the EPA using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/170567.xml">
toxicity</link> data.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Michael Malveda, Hossein Janshekar, Masahiro Yoneyama. Gasoline Octane Improvers/Oxygenates. SRI Consulting. http://www.sriconsulting.com/CEH/Public/Reports/543.7500/</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/otaq/rfg_regs.htm#usage">
http://www.epa.gov/otaq/rfg regs.htm#usage</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/pubs/fs/fs11495">
U.S. Geological Survay detections</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<control wordnetid="105196375" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="105196582" confidence="0.8">
<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/9974.xml">
European Commission</link></power>
</authority>
</control>
. MTBE and the Requirements for Underground Storage Tank Construction and Operation in Member States.</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nesteengineering.com/default.asp?path=111,360,362,477">
http://www.nesteengineering.com/default.asp?path=111,360,362,477</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.halliburton.com/kbr/hydroChem/petroChem/nexoctane.jsp">
http://www.halliburton.com/kbr/hydroChem/petroChem/nexoctane.jsp</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sierraclub.org/policy/conservation/mtbe.asp">
Sierra Club on Gasoline Additive: MTBE</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.swrcb.ca.gov/rwqcb2/download/WMI%202004%20Executive%20Summary.pdf">
San Francisco Bay Area Regional Water Quality Control Board Integrated Basin Management Plan (2004)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Fischer A, Oehm C, Selle M, Werner P.&#32;(2005).&#32;"Biotic and abiotic transformations of methyl tertiary butyl ether (MTBE)". <it>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</it>&#32;<b>12</b>&#32;(6): 381–6.. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1065%2Fespr2005.08.277">
10.1065/espr2005.08.277</weblink>. PMID 16305145.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://monographs.iarc.fr/ENG/Monographs/vol73/volume73.pdf">
http://monographs.iarc.fr/ENG/Monographs/vol73/volume73.pdf</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/mtbe/faq.htm#concerns">
http://www.epa.gov/mtbe/faq.htm#concerns</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigma.org/wr/reports/05/050523.html">
SIGMA - Weekly Report</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mtbe-eresource.com/liu.cfm">
Long Island Utility Fighting to Defeat MTBE Safe Harbor - Napoli Bern - Attorneys</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ens-newswire.com/ens/feb2005/2005-02-17-09.asp#anchor2">
AmeriScan: February 17, 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eia.doe.gov/oiaf/servicerpt/mtbeban/table1.html">
Website U.S. Department of Energy</weblink></entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/7574562/+MTBE&amp;hl=en">
http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/7574562/+MTBE&amp;hl=en</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnn.com/2005/POLITICS/04/21/energy.bill.mtbe.ap/">
http://www.cnn.com/2005/POLITICS/04/21/energy.bill.mtbe.ap/</weblink></entry>
<entry id="19">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/z?d109:h.r.00006:">
http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/z?d109:h.r.00006:</weblink></entry>
<entry id="18">
Charles Babington, House Again Passes GOP Energy Measures, Washington Post, June 16, 2004, at A4 (House passes Energy Bill, but Senate opponents of MTBE provision in House Bill have the votes to prevent its enactment).</entry>
<entry id="21">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.freepatentsonline.com/5536886.html">
http://www.freepatentsonline.com/5536886.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://money.cnn.com/2006/04/18/news/economy/gas">
prices ethanol/index.htm?cnn=yes http://money.cnn.com/2006/04/18/news/economy/gas prices ethanol/index.htm?cnn=yes</weblink></entry>
<entry id="22">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/safewater/ccl/ccl2.html#chemical">
CCL 2 List</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/1549946.xml">
ETBE</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 [http://www.mtbe.us</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.efoa.org">
EFOA</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iarc.fr/">
Agency on Cancer Research, (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/87041.xml">
IACR</link>) a division of the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/33583.xml">
World Health Organization</link></organization>
</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/mtbe/">
MTBE webpage from the EPA</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.inchem.org/documents/iarc/vol73/73-13.html">
Summary of health effects data</weblink> from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/87041.xml">
IACR</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://firstgovsearch.gov/search?v%3aproject=firstgov&amp;v%3afile=viv_606%4018%3a2jU0T7&amp;v%3astate=root%7croot&amp;opener=full-window&amp;url=http%3a%2f%2fwww.eia.doe.gov%2fpub%2foil_gas%2fpetroleum%2ffeature_articles%2f2006%2fmtbe2006%2fmtbe2006.pdf&amp;rid=Ndoc1&amp;v%3aframe=redirect&amp;rsource=firstgov-msn&amp;v%3astate=%28root%29%7croot&amp;rrank=1&amp;">
Eliminating MTBE in Gasoline in 2006 (pdf)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mtbelitigationinfo.com/">
An online resource about MTBE litigation and the surrounding issues</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ewg.org/reports/withknowledge/">
MTBE: What The Oil Companies Knew And When They Knew It (from the Environmental Working Group)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</pollutant>
</entity>
</solvent>
</article>
