<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:43:53[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Building Information Modeling</title>
<id>3978080</id>
<revision>
<id>241195639</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-26T20:03:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Eddy.krygiel</username>
<id>7947584</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Construction</category>
<category>Data modeling</category>
<category>Building engineering</category>
<category>Computer-aided design</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Building Information Modeling (BIM)</b> is the process of generating and managing building data during its life cycle<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. Typically it uses three-dimensional, real-time, dynamic building modeling software to increase productivity in building design and construction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The process produces the Building Information Model (also abbreviated BIM), which encompasses building geometry, spatial relationships, geographic information, and quantities and properties of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/45995.xml">
building</link> components. 
<sec>
<st>
Origin of BIM</st>

<p>

There are two theories on the origin of the term building information modeling. The first one is that the term was coined by Autodesk <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> to describe "<process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<consequence wordnetid="111410625" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/10175073.xml">
3D</link></consequence>
</phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/22757.xml">
object-oriented</link>, <link>
AEC</link>-specific <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/37315.xml">
CAD</link>". The second theory claims that Professor Charles M. Eastman at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/9916781.xml">
Georgia Institute of Technology</link></ranking>
</university>
 coined the term <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. This theory is based on a view that the term <b>Building Information Model</b> is basically the same as <b>Building Product Model</b>, which Professor Eastman has used extensively in his book <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> and papers since the late 1970s. ('Product model' means 'data model' or 'information model' in engineering.) Nevertheless, it is agreed upon that the term was popularized by Jerry Laiserin <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> as a common name for a digital representation of the building process to facilitate exchange and interoperability of information in digital format. According to him<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> and others<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>, the first implementation of BIM was under the Virtual Building concept by Graphisoft's ArchiCAD, in its debut in 1987.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Definition</st>

<p>

Building information modeling covers geometry, spatial relationships, geographic information, quantities and properties of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/45995.xml">
building</link> components (for example manufacturers' details). BIM can be used to demonstrate the entire building life cycle including the processes of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/239038.xml">
construction</link> and facility operation. Quantities and shared properties of materials can easily be extracted. Scopes of work can be isolated and defined. Systems, assemblies, and sequences are able to be shown in a relative scale with the entire facility or group of facilities.</p>
<p>

BIM is able to achieve such improvements by modeling representations of the actual parts and pieces being used to build a building.  This is a substantial shift from the traditional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/37315.xml">
computer aided drafting</link> method of drawing with vector file based lines that combine to represent objects.</p>
<p>

The interoperability requirements of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/9521786.xml">
construction documents</link> include the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/10129174.xml">
drawings</link>, procurement details, environmental conditions, submittal processes and other specifications for building quality.  It is anticipated by proponents that BIM can be utilized to bridge the information loss associated with handing a project from design team, to construction team and to building owner/operator, by allowing each group to add to and reference back to all information they acquire during their period of contribution the BIM model.  For example, a building owner may find evidence of a leak in his building.  Rather than exploring the physical building, he may turn to his BIM and see that a water <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/32754.xml">
valve</link> is located in the suspect location.  He could also have in the model the specific valve size, manufacturer, part number, and any other information ever researched<b> in the past, pending adequate computing power.</b></p>
<p>

There have been attempts at creating a BIM for older, pre-existing facilities. They generally reference key metrics such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/17790686.xml">
Facility Condition Index</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/308598.xml">
FCI</link>. The validity of these models will need to be monitored over time, because trying to model a building constructed in, say 1927, requires numerous assumptions about design standards, building codes, construction methods, materials, etc., and therefore is far more complex than building a BIM at time of initial design.</p>
<p>

The <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/500492.xml">
American Institute of Architects</link></organization>
 has further defined BIM as "a model-based technology linked with a database of project information"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Building_Information_Modeling#endnote_definition">
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Building_Information_Modeling#endnote_definition</weblink>, and this reflects the general reliance on database technology as the foundation. In the future, structured text documents such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/14171448.xml">
specifications</link> may be able to be searched and linked to regional, national, and international standards.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Anticipated future potential</st>
<p>

BIM is currently employed by professionals on all building types from the simplest warehouse to many of the most complex new buildings, BIM design method is currently young in its development.  </p>
<p>

BIM provides the potential for a virtual information model to be handed from Design Team (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/1170.xml">
architects</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/60891.xml">
surveyors</link>, <link>
consulting engineers</link>, and others) to Contractor and Subcontractors and then to the Owner, each adding their own additional discipline-specific knowledge and tracking of changes to the single model.  The result is anticipated to greatly reduce the information loss that occurs when a new team takes "ownership" of the project as well as in delivering extensive information to owners of complex structures far beyond that which they are currently accustomed to having.</p>
<p>

BIM can greatly decrease errors made by design team members and the construction team (Contractors and Subcontractors) by allowing the use of conflict detection where the computer actually informs team members about parts of the building in conflict or clashing, and through detailed computer visualization of each part in relation to the total building.  As computers and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> become more capable of handling more building information, this will become even more pronounced than it is in current design and construction projects.  This error reduction is a great part of cost savings realized by all members of a project. Reduction in time required to complete construction directly contributes to the cost savings numbers as well. It's important to realize that this decrease can only be accomplished if the models are sufficiently developed in the Design Development phase.</p>
<p>

BIM is a process which goes far beyond switching to a new software. It requires changes to the definition of traditional architectural phases and more data sharing than most architects and engineers are used to. </p>
<p>

<link>
gbXML</link> is an emerging schema, a subset of the Building Information Modeling efforts, focused on green building design and operation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
BIM in the USA</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Contractors</st>

<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/7512060.xml">
Associated General Contractors</link> and contracting firms also have developed a variety of working definition of BIM which describe it generally as "an object-oriented building development tool that utilizes 5-D modeling concepts, information technology and software interoperability to design, construct and operate a building project, as well as communicate its details.</p>
<p>

Although the concept of BIM and relevant processes are being explored by contractors, architects and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/179684.xml">
developers</link> alike, the term itself is under debate<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>, and it is yet to be seen whether it will win over alternatives, which include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Virtual Building Environment</link> (VBE)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/3978080.xml">
Virtual Building</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
BuildingSMART</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Integrated Practice</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/14576735.xml">
Virtual Design and Construction</link> (VDC)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

BIM is often associated with IFCs (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/1149133.xml">
Industry Foundation Classes</link>) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/7604268.xml">
aecXML</link>, which are data structures for representing information used in BIM. IFCs were developed by the <link>
International Alliance for Interoperability</link>. There are other data structures which are proprietary, and many have been developed by CAD firms that are now incorporating BIM into their software. One of the earliest examples of a nationally approved BIM standard is the AISC (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/11007164.xml">
American Institute of Steel Construction</link>)-approved CIS/2 standard, a non proprietary standard with its roots in the UK.</p>
<p>

Proponents claim that BIM offers: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Improved visualization</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Improved productivity due to easy retrieval of information </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Increased coordination of construction documents</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Embedding and linking of vital information such as vendors for specific materials, location of details and quantities required for estimation and tendering </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Increased speed of delivery </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Reduced costs</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In August 2004 the US National Institute of Standards and Technology (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/21888.xml">
NIST</link>) issued a report entitled "Cost Analysis of Inadequate Interoperability in the U.S. Capital Facilities Industry" (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bfrl.nist.gov/oae/publications/gcrs/04867.pdf">
NIST GCR 04-867 (PDF)</weblink>, which came to the conclusion that, as a conservative estimate, $15.8 billion is lost annually by the U.S. capital facilities industry resulting from inadequate interoperability due to "the highly fragmented nature of the industry, the industry’s continued paperbased business practices, a lack of standardization, and inconsistent technology adoption among stakeholders".</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/903378.xml">
Architecture</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19278728.xml">
Architectural engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/2026112.xml">
Construction management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/6659320.xml">
Design computing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/14576735.xml">
Virtual Design and Construction</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Lee, G., Sacks, R., and Eastman, C. M. (2006). Specifying parametric building object behavior (BOB) for a building information modeling system. Automation in Construction, 15(6), 758-776.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Holness, Gordon V.R. "Building Information Modeling Gaining Momentum." ASHRAE Journal. Pp 28-40. June 2008.</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://industries.bnet.com/whitepaper.aspx?%26compid=3995%26docid=103305">
Archived version of Autodesk's white paper on Building Information Modeling</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
Yessios, C.I. Are We Forgetting Design? AECbytes Viewpoint #10  2004, http://www.aecbytes.com/viewpoint/2004/issue_10.html</entry>
<entry id="5">
Eastman, C.M., Building Product Models: Computer Environments Supporting Design and Construction. 1999, Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.laiserin.com/features/issue15/feature01.php">
Laiserin's explanation of why 'BIM' should be an industry standard-term</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.laiserin.com/features/issue19/feature01.php">
Graphisoft on BIM</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.laiserin.com/features/bim/newforma_bim.pdf">
Building Information Modeling Two Years Later –Huge Potential, Some Success and Several Limitations</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aecbytes.com/newsletter/2004/issue_5.html">
Discussion</weblink> of the BIM <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/1052571.xml">
acronym</link></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bim.arch.gatech.edu/?id=402">
What is BIM?</weblink> - by Professor Charles M. Eastman, Director of AEC Integration Lab at Georgia Tech.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aecbytes.com/viewpoint/2008/issue_35.html">
Managing BIM Technology in the Building Industry</weblink> - AECbytes Viewpoint #35: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/11158.xml">
February 12</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aecbytes.com">
AECbytes</weblink> - Analysis, Research and Reviews of AEC Technology</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.facilityinformationcouncil.org/bim/index.php">
Developing the US National BIM Standard</weblink> - BuildingSMART (NIBS)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cic.nist.gov/vrml/cis2.html">
CIS/2</weblink> - CIS/2 is the file exchange format that facilitates BIM for structural steel</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gsa.gov/bim">
GSA National BIM Program</weblink> - National 3D-4D BIM Program by the U.S. GSA (<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/424408.xml">
General Services Administration</link></agency>
)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.featurefactory.com/page.asp?pageid=122">
http://www.featurefactory.com/page.asp?pageid=122</weblink> - A description of BIM or Parametric Solid Modeling on the website of Feature Factory Design Build, an architectural fabricator.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.reedconstructiondata.com/articles/read/parametric-revit-objects-part-i-fundamentals/">
Overview of Parametric Objects</weblink> - An overview of parametric objects for BIM by Dennis Neeley, AIA</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vibesbv.com/">
http://www.vibesbv.com/</weblink> - VIBES - Virtual Building Engineers, specialized in BIM</entry>
</list>

American Society of Professional Estimators - www.aspenational.org</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/3978080.xml">
Building Information Modeling</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Full Building Information Modeling Packages</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/4410993.xml">
Graphisoft ArchiCAD</link></software>
&nbsp;&#124; <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link>
Bentley Architecture</link></company>
&nbsp;&#124; <link>
 Tekla Structures</link>&nbsp;&#124; <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/10324555.xml">
Graphisoft Constructor</link></software>
&nbsp;&#124; <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/7399459.xml">
Autodesk Revit</link></software>
&nbsp;&#124; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/10324666.xml">
Nemetschek N.A. VectorWorks Architect</link>&nbsp;&#124; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/19453261.xml">
GRAITEC Advance</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Building Information Modeling Compatible Packages</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/6665926.xml">
Data Design System</link>&nbsp;&#124; <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/8665933.xml">
NavisWorks JetStream</link></software>
&nbsp;&#124; <link>
 CodeBook by Project Blueprint</link>&nbsp;&#124; <link>
RoomData by Project Blueprint</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Building Information Modeling Related Topics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/1149133.xml">
Industry Foundation Classes</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
