<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:55:22[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Computational phylogenetics</title>
<id>3986130</id>
<revision>
<id>240956468</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-25T18:29:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>JohnnyHom</username>
<id>7939593</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computational phylogenetics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Computational phylogenetics</b> is the application of computational <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s, methods and programs to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/23962.xml">
phylogenetic</link> analyses. The goal is to assemble a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/149326.xml">
phylogenetic tree</link> representing a hypothesis about the evolutionary ancestry of a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/4250553.xml">
gene</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/28023.xml">
species</link>, or other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/199556.xml">
taxa</link>. For example, these techniques have been used to explore the family tree of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/2542626.xml">
hominid</link> species<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> and the relationships between specific genes shared by  many types of organisms.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Traditional phylogenetics relies on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/1099348.xml">
morphological</link> data obtained by measuring and quantifying the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/24543.xml">
phenotypic</link> properties of representative organisms, while the more recent field of molecular phylogenetics uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/21505.xml">
nucleotide</link> sequences encoding genes or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link> sequences encoding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link>s as the basis for classification. Many forms of molecular phylogenetics are closely related to and make extensive use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/149289.xml">
sequence alignment</link> in constructing and refining phylogenetic trees, which are used to classify the evolutionary relationships between homologous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/4250553.xml">
gene</link>s represented in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/12388.xml">
genome</link>s of divergent species. The phylogenetic trees constructed by computational methods are unlikely to perfectly reproduce the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/149326.xml">
evolutionary tree</link> that represents the historical relationships between the species being analyzed. The historical species tree may also differ from the historical tree of an individual homologous gene shared by those species.<p>

Producing a phylogenetic tree requires a measure of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/142431.xml">
homology</link> among the characteristics shared by the taxa being compared. In morphological studies, this requires explicit decisions about which physical characteristics to measure and how to use them to encode distinct states corresponding to the input taxa. In molecular studies, a primary problem is in producing a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/4066308.xml">
multiple sequence alignment</link> (MSA) between the genes or amino acid sequences of interest. Progressive sequence alignment methods produce a phylogenetic tree by necessity because they incorporate new sequences into the calculated alignment in order of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/2722642.xml">
genetic distance</link>. Although a phylogenetic tree can always be constructed from an MSA, phylogenetics methods such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/1130020.xml">
maximum parsimony</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/140806.xml">
maximum likelihood</link> do not require the production of an initial or concurrent MSA.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Types of phylogenetic trees</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/149326.xml">
Phylogenetic tree</link>s generated by computational phylogenetics can be either <it>rooted</it> or <it>unrooted</it> depending on the input data and the algorithm used. A rooted tree is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/19721986.xml">
directed graph</link> that explicitly identifies a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/1034339.xml">
most recent common ancestor</link> (MRCA), usually an imputed sequence that is not represented in the input. Genetic distance measures can be used to plot a tree with the input sequences as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/18228.xml">
leaf node</link>s and their distances from the root proportional to their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/2722642.xml">
genetic distance</link> from the hypothesized MRCA. Identification of a root usually requires the inclusion in the input data of at least one "outgroup" known to be only distantly related to the sequences of interest.</p>
<p>

By contrast, unrooted trees plot the distances and relationships between input sequences without making assumptions regarding their descent. An unrooted tree can always be produced from a rooted tree, but a root cannot usually be placed on an unrooted tree without additional data on divergence rates, such as the assumption of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/250001.xml">
molecular clock</link> hypothesis.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

The set of all possible phylogenetic trees for a given group of input sequences can be conceptualized as a discretely defined multidimensional "tree space" through which search paths can be traced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/52033.xml">
optimization</link> algorithms. Although counting the total number of trees for a nontrivial number of input sequences can be complicated by variations in the definition of a tree topology, it is always true that there are more rooted than unrooted trees for a given number of inputs and choice of parameters.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Coding characters and defining homology</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Morphological analysis</st>
<p>

The basic problem in morphological phylogenetics is the assembly of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19008728.xml">
matrix</link> representing a mapping from each of the taxa being compared to representative measurements for each of the phenotypic characteristics being used as a classifier. The types of phenotypic data used to construct this matrix depend on the taxa being compared; for individual species, they may involve measurements of average body size, lengths or sizes of particular bones or other physical features, or even behavioral manifestations. Of course, since not every possible phenotypic characteristic could be measured and encoded for analysis, the selection of which features to measure is a major inherent obstacle to the method. The decision of which traits to use as a basis for the matrix necessarily represents a hypothesis about which traits of a species or higher taxon are evolutionarily relevant.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Morphological studies can be confounded by examples of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/82804.xml">
convergent evolution</link> of phenotypes.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> A major challenge in constructing useful classes is the high likelihood of inter-taxon overlap in the distribution of the phenotype's variation. The inclusion of extinct taxa in morphological analysis is often difficult due to absence of or incomplete <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/10958.xml">
fossil</link> records, but has been shown to have a significant effect on the trees produced; in one study only the inclusion of extinct species of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/229914.xml">
ape</link>s produced a morphologically derived tree that was consistent with that produced from molecular data.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Some phenotypic classifications, particularly those used when analyzing very diverse groups of taxa, are discrete and unambiguous; classifying organisms as possessing or lacking a tail, for example, is straightforward in the majority of cases, as is counting features such as eyes or vertebrae. However, the most appropriate representation of continuously varying phenotypic measurements is a controversial problem without a general solution. A common method is simply to sort the measurements of interest into two or more classes, rendering continuous observed variation as discretely classifiable (e.g., all examples with humerus bones longer than a given cutoff are scored as members of one state, and all members whose humerus bones are shorter than the cutoff are scored as members of a second state). This results in an easily manipulated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/8495.xml">
data set</link> but has been criticized for poor reporting of the basis for the class definitions and for sacrificing information compared to methods that use a continuous weighted distribution of measurements.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> </p>
<p>

Because morphological data is extremely labor-intensive to collect, whether from literature sources or from field observations, reuse of previously compiled data matrices is not uncommon, although this may propagate flaws in the original matrix into multiple derivative analyses.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Molecular analysis</st>
<p>

The problem of character coding is very different in molecular analyses, as the characters in biological sequence data are immediate and discretely defined - distinct <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/21505.xml">
nucleotide</link>s in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
DNA</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/25758.xml">
RNA</link> sequences and distinct <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link>s in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link> sequences. However, defining homology can be challenging due to the inherent difficulties of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/4066308.xml">
multiple sequence alignment</link>. For a given gapped MSA, several rooted phylogenetic trees can be constructed that vary in their interpretations of which changes are "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/19702.xml">
mutation</link>s" versus ancestral characters, and which events are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/1795277.xml">
insertion mutations</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/245186.xml">
deletion mutations</link>. For example, given only a pairwise alignment with a gap region, it is impossible to determine whether one sequence bears an insertion mutation or the other carries a deletion. The problem is magnified in MSAs with unaligned and nonoverlapping gaps. In practice, sizable regions of a calculated alignment may be discounted in phylogenetic tree construction to avoid integrating noisy data into the tree calculation.</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Distance-matrix methods</st>
<p>

Distance-matrix methods of phylogenetic analysis explicitly rely on a measure of "genetic distance" between the sequences being classified, and therefore they require an MSA as an input. Distance is often defined as the fraction of mismatches at aligned positions, with gaps either ignored or counted as mismatches.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Distance methods attempt to construct an all-to-all matrix from the sequence query set describing the distance between each sequence pair. From this is constructed a phylogenetic tree that places closely related sequences under the same <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/30806.xml">
interior node</link> and whose branch lengths closely reproduce the observed distances between sequences. Distance-matrix methods may produce either rooted or unrooted trees, depending on the algorithm used to calculate them. They are frequently used as the basis for progressive and iterative types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/4066308.xml">
multiple sequence alignment</link>s. The main disadvantage of distance-matrix methods is their inability to efficiently use information about local high-variation regions that appear across multiple subtrees.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Neighbor-joining</st>
<p>

Neighbor-joining methods apply general <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/669675.xml">
data clustering</link> techniques to sequence analysis using genetic distance as a clustering metric. The simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/351798.xml">
neighbor-joining</link> method produces unrooted trees, but it does not assume a constant rate of evolution (i.e., a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/250001.xml">
molecular clock</link>) across lineages. Its relative, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/355968.xml">
UPGMA</link> (Unweighted Pair Group Method with Arithmetic mean) produces rooted trees and requires a constant-rate assumption - that is, it assumes an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/333996.xml">
ultrametric</link> tree in which the distances from the root to every branch tip are equal. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fitch-Margoliash method</st>
<p>

The Fitch-Margoliash method uses a weighted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/82359.xml">
least squares</link> method for clustering based on genetic distance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> Closely related sequences are given more weight in the tree construction process to correct for the increased inaccuracy in measuring distances between distantly related sequences. The distances used as input to the algorithm must be normalized to prevent large artifacts in computing relationships between closely related and distantly related groups. The distances calculated by this method must be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/91591.xml">
linear</link>; the linearity criterion for distances requires that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/9653.xml">
expected value</link>s of the branch lengths for two individual branches must equal the expected value of the sum of the two branch distances - a property that applies to biological sequences only when they have been corrected for the possibility of <link>
back mutation</link>s at individual sites. This correction is done through the use of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/363225.xml">
substitution matrix</link> such as that derived from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/1937800.xml">
Jukes-Cantor model</link> of DNA evolution. The distance correction is only necessary in practice when the evolution rates differ among branches.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

The least-squares criterion applied to these distances is more accurate but less efficient than the neighbor-joining methods. An additional improvement that corrects for correlations between distances that arise from many closely related sequences in the data set can also be applied at increased computational cost. Finding the optimal least-squares tree with any correction factor is <class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/39466.xml">
NP-complete</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> so <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link> search methods like those used in maximum-parsimony analysis are applied to the search through tree space.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Using outgroups</st>
<p>

Independent information about the relationship between sequences or groups can be used to help reduce the tree search space and root unrooted trees. Standard usage of distance-matrix methods involves the inclusion of at least one <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/948183.xml">
outgroup</link> sequence known to be only distantly related to the sequences of interest in the query set.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> This usage can be seen as a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/1640288.xml">
experimental control</link>. If the outgroup has been appropriately chosen, it will have a much greater <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/2722642.xml">
genetic distance</link> and thus a longer branch length than any other sequence, and it will appear near the root of a rooted tree. Choosing an appropriate outgroup requires the selection of a sequence that is moderately related to the sequences of interest; too close a relationship defeats the purpose of the outgroup and too distant adds <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/236932.xml">
noise</link> to the analysis.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Care should also be taken to avoid situations in which the species from which the sequences were taken are distantly related, but the gene encoded by the sequences is highly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/1333227.xml">
conserved</link> across lineages. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/205624.xml">
Horizontal gene transfer</link>, especially between otherwise divergent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/9028799.xml">
bacteria</link>, can also confound outgroup usage.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Maximum parsimony</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/1130020.xml">
Maximum parsimony</link> (MP) is a method of identifying the potential phylogenetic tree that requires the smallest total number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/9236.xml">
evolution</link>ary events to explain the observed sequence data. Some ways of scoring trees also include a "cost" associated with particular types of evolutionary events and attempt to locate the tree with the smallest total cost. This is a useful approach in cases where not every possible type of event is equally likely - for example, when particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/21505.xml">
nucleotide</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link>s are known to be more mutable than others.</p>
<p>

The most naive way of identifying the most parsimonious tree is simple enumeration - considering each possible tree in succession and searching for the tree with the smallest score. However, this is only possible for a relatively small number of sequences or species because the problem of identifying the most parsimonious tree is known to be <class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/54681.xml">
NP-hard</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
;<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> consequently a number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link> search methods for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/52033.xml">
optimization</link> have been developed to locate a highly parsimonious tree, if not the most optimal in the set. Most such methods involve a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/201489.xml">
steepest descent</link>-style minimization mechanism operating on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/7625755.xml">
tree rearrangement</link> criterion.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Branch and bound</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/456580.xml">
branch and bound</link> algorithm is a general method used to increase the efficiency of searches for near-optimal solutions of <class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/54681.xml">
NP-hard</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
 problems first applied to phylogenetics in the early 1980s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Branch and bound is particularly well suited to phylogenetic tree construction because it inherently requires dividing a problem into a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/41821.xml">
tree structure</link> as it subdivides the problem space into smaller regions. As its name implies, it requires as input both a branching rule (in the case of phylogenetics, the addition of the next species or sequence to the tree) and a bound (a rule that excludes certain regions of the search space from consideration, thereby assuming that the optimal solution cannot occupy that region). Identifying a good bound is the most challenging aspect of the algorithm's application to phylogenetics. A simple way of defining the bound is a maximum number of assumed evolutionary changes allowed per tree. A set of criteria known as Zharkikh's rules<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> severely limit the search space by defining characteristics shared by all candidate "most parsimonious" trees. The two most basic rules require the elimination of all but one redundant sequence (for cases where multiple observations have produced identical data) and the elimination of character sites at which two or more states do not occur in at least two species. Under ideal conditions these rules and their associated algorithm would completely define a tree.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sankoff-Morel-Cedergren algorithm</st>
<p>

The Sankoff-Morel-Cedergren algorithm was among the first published methods to simultaneously produce an MSA and a phylogenetic tree for nucleotide sequences.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> The method uses a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/1130020.xml">
maximum parsimony</link> calculation in conjunction with a scoring function that penalizes gaps and mismatches, thereby favoring the tree that introduces a minimal number of such events. The imputed sequences at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/30806.xml">
interior node</link>s of the tree are scored and summed over all the nodes in each possible tree. The lowest-scoring tree sum provides both an optimal tree and an optimal MSA given the scoring function. Because the method is highly computationally intensive, an approximate method in which initial guesses for the interior alignments are refined one node at a time. Both the full and the approximate version are in practice calculated by dynamic programming.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
MALIGN and POY</st>
<p>

More recent phylogenetic tree/MSA methods use heuristics to isolate high-scoring, but not necessarily optimal, trees. The MALIGN method uses a maximum-parsimony technique to compute a multiple alignment by maximizing a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/5376.xml">
cladogram</link> score, and its companion POY uses an iterative method that couples the optimization of the phylogenetic tree with improvements in the corresponding MSA.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> However, the use of these methods in constructing evolutionary hypotheses has been criticized as biased due to the deliberate construction of trees reflecting minimal evolutionary events.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> Both programs are available from the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/scicomp/projects.html">
American Museum of Natural History</weblink>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Maximum likelihood</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/140806.xml">
maximum likelihood</link> method uses standard statistical techniques for inferring <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/23543.xml">
probability distribution</link>s to assign probabilities to particular possible phylogenetic trees. The method requires a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/1937800.xml">
substitution model</link> to assess the probability of particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/19702.xml">
mutation</link>s; roughly, a tree that requires more mutations at interior nodes to explain the observed phylogeny will be assessed as having a lower probability. This is broadly similar to the maximum-parsimony method, but maximum likelihood allows additional statistical flexibility by permitting varying rates of evolution across both lineages and sites. In fact, the method requires that evolution at different sites and along different lineages must be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/27593.xml">
statistically independent</link>. Maximum likelihood is thus well suited to the analysis of distantly related sequences, but because it formally requires search of all possible combinations of tree topology and branch length, it is computationally expensive to perform on more than a few sequences.</p>
<p>

The "pruning" algorithm, a variant of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/125297.xml">
dynamic programming</link>, is often used to reduce the search space by efficiently calculating the likelihood of subtrees.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> The method calculates the likelihood for each site in a "linear" manner, starting at a node whose only descendants are leaves (that is, the tips of the tree) and working backwards toward the "bottom" node in nested sets. However, the trees produced by the method are only rooted if the substitution model is irreversible, which is not generally true of biological systems. The search for the maximum-likelihood tree also includes a branch length optimization component that is difficult to improve upon algorithmically; general <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/563854.xml">
global optimization</link> tools such as the <link>
Newton-Raphson</link> method are often used. Searching tree topologies defined by likelihood has not been shown to be NP-complete,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> but remains extremely challenging because branch-and-bound search is not yet effective for trees represented in this way.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Bayesian inference</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/49571.xml">
Bayesian inference</link> can be used to produce phylogenetic trees in a manner closely related to the maximum likelihood methods. Bayesian methods assume a prior <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/23543.xml">
probability distribution</link> of the possible trees, which may simply be the probability of any one tree among all the possible trees that could be generated from the data, or may be a more sophisticated estimate derived from the assumption that divergence events such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/29000.xml">
speciation</link> occur as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/47895.xml">
stochastic process</link>es. The choice of prior distribution is a point of contention among users of Bayesian-inference phylogenetics methods.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

Implementations of Bayesian methods generally use <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/236801.xml">
Markov chain Monte Carlo</link></method>
</know-how>
 sampling algorithms, although the choice of move set varies; selections used in Bayesian phylogenetics include circularly permuting  leaf nodes of a proposed tree at each step<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> and swapping descendant subtrees of a random <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/30806.xml">
internal node</link> between two related trees.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> The use of Bayesian methods in phylogenetics has been controversial, largely due to incomplete specification of the choice of move set, acceptance criterion, and prior distribution in published work.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Model selection</st>
<p>

Molecular phylogenetics methods rely on a defined <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/1937800.xml">
substitution model</link> that encodes a hypothesis about the relative rates of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/19702.xml">
mutation</link> at various sites along the gene or amino acid sequences being studied. At their simplest, substitution models aim to correct for differences in the rates of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../484/2652484.xml">
transitions</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/1053544.xml">
transversion</link>s in nucleotide sequences. The use of substitution models is necessitated by the fact that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/2722642.xml">
genetic distance</link> between two sequences increases linearly only for a short time after the two sequences diverge from each other (alternatively, the distance is linear only shortly before <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/3441831.xml">
coalescence</link>). The longer the amount of time after divergence, the more likely it becomes that two mutations occur at the same nucleotide site. Simple genetic distance calculations will thus undercount the number of mutation events that have occurred in evolutionary history. The extent of this undercount increases with increasing time since divergence, which can lead to the phenomenon of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/2388260.xml">
long branch attraction</link>, or the misassignment of two distantly related but <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/82804.xml">
convergently evolving</link> sequences as closely related.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> The maximum parsimony method is particularly susceptible to this problem due to its explicit search for a tree representing a minimum number of distinct evolutionary events.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Types of models</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/1937800.xml">
Substitution model</link></it>
</indent>

All substitution models assign a set of weights to each possible change of state represented in the sequence. The most common model types are implicitly reversible because they assign the same weight to, for example, a G&amp;gt;C nucleotide mutation as to a C&amp;gt;G mutation. The simplest possible model, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/1937800.xml">
Jukes-Cantor model</link>, assigns an equal probability to every possible change of state for a given nucleotide base. The rate of change between any two distinct nucleotides will be one-third of the overall substitution rate.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> More advanced models distinguish between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../484/2652484.xml">
transitions</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/1053544.xml">
transversion</link>s. The most general possible time-reversible model, called the GTR model, has contains six mutation rate parameters. An even more generalized model known as the general 12-parameter model breaks time-reversibility, at the cost of much additional complexity in calculating genetic distances that are consistent among multiple lineages.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> One possible variation on this theme adjusts the rates so that overall GC content - an important measure of DNA double helix stability - varies over time.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> </p>
<p>

Models may also allow for the variation of rates with positions in the input sequence. The most obvious example of such variation follows from the arrangement of nucleotides in protein-coding genes into three-base <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/12385.xml">
codon</link>s. If the location of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/1174560.xml">
open reading frame</link> (ORF) is known, rates of mutation can be adjusted for position of a given site within a codon, since it is known that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/581246.xml">
wobble base pair</link>ing can allow for higher mutation rates in the third nucleotide of a given codon without affecting the codon's meaning in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/12385.xml">
genetic code</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> A less hypothesis-driven example that does not rely on ORF identification simply assigns to each site a rate randomly drawn from a predetermined distribution, often the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/207079.xml">
gamma distribution</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/102476.xml">
log-normal distribution</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Finally, a more conservative estimate of rate variations known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../519/8981519.xml">
covarion</link> method allows <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/2724.xml">
autocorrelated</link> variations in rates, so that the mutation rate of a given site is correlated across sites and lineages.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Choosing the best model</st>
<p>

The selection of an appropriate model is critical for the production of good phylogenetic analyses, both because underparameterized or overly restrictive models may produce aberrant behavior when their underlying assumptions are violated, and because overly complex or overparameterized models are computationally expensive and the parameters may be overfit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> The most common method of model selection is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/45035.xml">
likelihood ratio test</link> (LRT), which produces a likelihood estimate that can be interpreted as a measure of "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/2474821.xml">
goodness of fit</link>" between the model and the input data.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> However, care must be taken in using these results, since a more complex model with more parameters will always have a higher likelihood than a simplified version of the same model, which can lead to the naive selection of models that are overly complex.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  For this reason model selection computer programs will choose the simplest model that is not significantly worse than more complex substitution models. A significant disadvantage of the LRT is the necessity of making a series of pairwise comparisons between models; it has been shown that the order in which the models are compared has a major effect on the one that is eventually selected.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>
<p>

An alternative model selection method is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/690512.xml">
Akaike information criterion</link> (AIC), formally an estimate of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/467527.xml">
Kullback-Leibler divergence</link> between the true model and the model being tested. It can be interpreted as a likelihood estimate with a correction factor to penalize overparameterized models.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> The AIC is calculated on an individual model rather than a pair, so it is independent of the order in which models are assessed. A related alternative, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/2473272.xml">
Bayesian information criterion</link> (BIC), has a similar basic interpretation but penalizes complex models more heavily.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/6022892.xml">
List of phylogenetics software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/5376.xml">
Cladistics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/4500351.xml">
PHYLIP</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/9738540.xml">
Phylogenetic comparative methods</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/149326.xml">
Phylogenetic tree</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/23962.xml">
Phylogenetics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/27813.xml">
Systematics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/3819211.xml">
Joe Felsenstein</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://evolution.genetics.washington.edu/phylip.html">
PHYLIP</weblink>, a freely distributed phylogenetic analysis package</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://paup.csit.fsu.edu/">
PAUP</weblink>, a similar analysis package available for purchase</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mrbayes.csit.fsu.edu/index.php">
MrBayes</weblink>, a program for the Bayesian estimation of phylogeny (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mrbayes.csit.fsu.edu/wiki/index.php/Main_Page">
software wiki</weblink>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.treefinder.de/">
Treefinder</weblink>, a graphical analysis environment for molecular phylogenetics</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://darwin.uvigo.es/software/modeltest.html">
Modeltest</weblink>, a program for selecting appropriate substitution models for nucleotide sequences</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.phylo.org/">
CIPRES: Cyberinfrastructure for Phylogenetic Research</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.trex.uqam.ca">
Phylogenetic inferring on the T-REX server</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://evolution.genetics.washington.edu/phylip/software.html">
List of phylogeny programs</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rustyspigot.com/Computer_Science/Bioinformatics.html#phylogeny">
Phylogeny Algorithms Pseudocode</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Strait DS, Grine FE. (2004). Inferring hominoid and early hominid phylogeny using craniodental characters: the role of fossil taxa. <it>J Hum Evol</it> 47(6):399-452.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Hodge T, Cope MJ. (2000). A myosin family tree. <it>J Cell Sci</it> 113: 3353-3354.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Mount DM. (2004). <it>Bioinformatics: Sequence and Genome Analysis</it> 2nd ed. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press: Cold Spring Harbor, NY.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Felsenstein J. (2004). <it>Inferring Phylogenies</it> Sinauer Associates: Sunderland, MA.</entry>
<entry id="5">
 Swiderski DL, Zelditch ML, Fink WL. (1998). Why morphometrics is not special: coding quantitative data for phylogenetic analysis. 47(3):508-19. </entry>
<entry id="6">
Gaubert P, Wozencraft WC, Cordeiro-Estrela P, Veron G. (2005). Mosaics of convergences and noise in morphological phylogenies: what's in a viverrid-like carnivoran? <it>Syst Biol</it> 54(6):865-94.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Wiens JJ. (2001). Character analysis in morphological phylogenetics: problems and solutions. <it>Syst Biol</it> 50(5):689-99. </entry>
<entry id="8">
Jenner RA. (2001). Bilaterian phylogeny and uncritical recycling of morphological data sets. <it>Syst Biol</it> 50(5): 730-743.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Fitch WM, Margoliash E. (1967). Construction of phylogenetic trees. <it>Science</it> 155: 279-84.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Day, WHE. (1986). Computational complexity of inferring phylogenies from dissimilarity matrices. <it>Bulletin of Mathematical Biology</it> 49:461-7.</entry>
<entry id="11">
Hendy MD, Penny D. (1982). Branch and bound algorithms to determine minimal evolutionary trees. <it>Math Biosci</it> 60: 133-42.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Ratner VA, Zharkikh AA, Kolchanov N, Rodin S, Solovyov S, Antonov AS. (1995). <it>Molecular Evolution</it> Biomathematics Series Vol 24. Springer-Verlag: New York, NY.</entry>
<entry id="13">
Sankoff D, Morel C, Cedergren RJ. (1973). Evolution of 5S RNA and the non-randomness of base replacement. <it>Nature New Biology</it> 245:232-4.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Wheeler WC, Gladstein DG. (1994). MALIGN: a multiple nucleic acid sequence alignment program. <it>J Heredity</it> 85: 417-18.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Simmons MP. (2004). Independence of alignment and tree search. <it>Mol Phylogenet Evol</it> 31(3):874-9.</entry>
<entry id="17">
Yang Z, Rannala B. (1997). bayesian phylogenetic inference using DNA sequences: a Merkov chain Monte Carlo method. <it>Mol Biol Evol</it> 46:409-18.</entry>
<entry id="16">
Mau B, Newton MA. (1997). Phylogenetic inference for binary data on dendrograms using Markov chain Monte Carlo. <it>J Comp Graph Stat</it> 6:122-31.</entry>
<entry id="19">
Galtier N, Guoy M. (1998.) Inferring pattern and process: maximum-likelihood implementation of a nonhomogeneous model of DNA sequence evolution for phylogenetic analysis. <it>Mol. Biol. Evol.</it> 15:871–79.</entry>
<entry id="18">
Sullivan J, Joyce P. (2005). Model selection in phylogenetics. Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics. 36: 445-466.</entry>
<entry id="21">
Pol D. (2004.) Empirical problems of the hierarchical likelihood ratio test for model selection. <it>Syst Biol</it> 53:949–62.</entry>
<entry id="20">
Fitch WM, Markowitz E. (1970). An improved method for determining codon variability in a gene and its application to the rate of fixation of mutations in evolution. <it>Biochemical Genetics</it> 4:579-593.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Topics in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/23962.xml">
phylogenetics</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Relevant fields</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/3986130.xml">
Computational phylogenetics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/149544.xml">
Molecular phylogeny</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/5376.xml">
Cladistics</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Basic concepts</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../006/1006006.xml">
Synapomorphy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/149326.xml">
Phylogenetic tree</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/3657198.xml">
Phylogenetic network</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/2388260.xml">
Long branch attraction</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Inference methods</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/1130020.xml">
Maximum parsimony</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/140806.xml">
Maximum likelihood</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/351798.xml">
Neighbor-joining</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/355968.xml">
UPGMA</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/7022979.xml">
Bayesian inference</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/9950498.xml">
Least squares</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Current topics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/436324.xml">
PhyloCode</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/2613851.xml">
DNA barcoding</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/635016.xml">
List of evolutionary biology topics</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Basic topics in 
evolutionary biology</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<expostulation wordnetid="107246742" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/2339577.xml">
Evidence of common descent</link></expostulation>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Processes of evolution</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/942048.xml">
Adaptation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/20650.xml">
Macroevolution</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/19544.xml">
Microevolution</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/29000.xml">
Speciation</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/219268.xml">
Population genetic</link>mechanisms</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/21147.xml">
Natural selection</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/72016.xml">
Genetic drift</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/327061.xml">
Gene flow</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/19702.xml">
Mutation</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/57414.xml">
Evolutionary developmental
biology</link>(Evo-devo) concepts</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/3040270.xml">
Phenotypic plasticity</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/3557327.xml">
Canalisation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/4122426.xml">
Modularity</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
The evolution of...</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/7025924.xml">
DNA</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/661661.xml">
Sex</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/5914541.xml">
Aging</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/2452832.xml">
Intelligence</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/13314227.xml">
The Ear</link>&nbsp;· <expostulation wordnetid="107246742" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/5645086.xml">
The Eye</link></expostulation>
&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/10589364.xml">
Flight</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/11008314.xml">
Plants</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/16866635.xml">
Fungi</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/12305127.xml">
Life</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/10326.xml">
Humans</link>&nbsp;· <link>
Dolphins and whales</link>&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/4577602.xml">
Birds</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Modes of speciation</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/839842.xml">
Anagenesis</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/1392377.xml">
Catagenesis</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/584238.xml">
Cladogenesis</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
History</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/788565.xml">
History of evolutionary thought</link>&nbsp;·  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/8145410.xml">
Charles&nbsp;Darwin</link></scientist>
</person>
&nbsp;·  <it><book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/29932.xml">
On the Origin of Species</link></book>
</it>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/97536.xml">
Modern&nbsp;evolutionary&nbsp;synthesis</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/1662015.xml">
Gene-centered view of evolution</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/18393.xml">
Life</link>(classification trees)</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other subfields</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/480107.xml">
Ecological genetics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/176052.xml">
Molecular evolution</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/23962.xml">
Phylogenetics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/27813.xml">
Systematics</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/635016.xml">
List of evolutionary biology topics</link>
&nbsp;·  <record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<chronology wordnetid="106503224" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<timeline wordnetid="106504965" confidence="0.8">
<written_record wordnetid="106502378" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/10029.xml">
Timeline of evolution</link></written_record>
</timeline>
</evidence>
</indication>
</chronology>
</record>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
