<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:48:42[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Teacher education</title>
<id>4003872</id>
<revision>
<id>244637811</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T20:35:34Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Retired username</username>
<id>319357</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Teacher training</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Teacher education</b> refers to the policies and procedures designed to equip <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/205075.xml">
teacher</link>s with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/243391.xml">
knowledge</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/352801.xml">
attitude</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/4805.xml">
behaviour</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/355343.xml">
skill</link>s they require to perform their tasks effectively in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/28022.xml">
school</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/1214654.xml">
classroom</link>.<p>

Teacher education is often divided into: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>initial teacher training / education</it> (a pre-service course before entering the classroom as a fully responsible teacher);</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>induction</it> (the process of providing training and support during the first few years of teaching or the first year in a particular school); </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>teacher development</it> or <it>continuing professional development (CPD)</it> (an in-service process for practicing teachers). </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The process of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/227112.xml">
mentoring</link></it> is also relevant.</p>
<p>

There is a longstanding and ongoing debate about the most appropriate term to describe these activities. The term 'teacher training' (which may give the impression that the activity involves training staff to undertake relatively routine tasks) seems to be losing ground to 'teacher education' (with its connotation of preparing staff for a professional role as a reflective practitioner)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Initial Teacher Education </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Organization </st>

<p>

Initial teacher education may be organized according to two basic models. </p>
<p>

In the 'consecutive' model, a teacher first obtains a qualification (often a first university degree), and then studies for a further period to gain an additional qualification in teaching; (in some systems this takes the form of a post-graduate degree, possibly even a Masters). </p>
<p>

The alternative is where a student simultaneously studies both an academic subject and the ways of teaching that subject, leading to a qualification as a teacher of that subject. </p>
<p>

Other pathways are also available. In some countries, it is possible for a person to receive training as a teacher under the responsibility of an accredited experienced practitioner in a school.</p>
<p>

Teacher Education in many countries takes place in institutions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/14423.xml">
Higher Education</link>.  An example of a traditional, comprehensive teacher education unit in the United States would be the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/19729622.xml">
Bradley University Department of Teacher Education</link> located in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<county_seat wordnetid="108547143" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/111774.xml">
Peoria, Illinois</link></urban_area>
</district>
</county_seat>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</seat>
</village>
</area>
</center>
</city>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Curricula </st>
<p>

The question of what knowledge, attitudes, behaviours and skills teachers should possess is the subject of much debate in many cultures. This is understandable, as teachers are entrusted with the transmission to children of society's beliefs, attitudes and deontology, as well as of information, advice and wisdom.</p>
<p>

Generally, Teacher Education curricula can be broken down into these blocks:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

foundational knowledge and skills--usually this area is about education-related aspects of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/24983.xml">
philosophy of education</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/2061136.xml">
history of education</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/10332.xml">
educational psychology</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/5704308.xml">
sociology of education</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

content-area and methods knowledge--often also including ways of teaching and assessing a specific subject, in which case this area may overlap with the first ("foundational") area. There is increasing debate about this aspect; because it is no longer possible to know in advance what kinds of knowledge and skill pupils will need when they enter adult life, it becomes harder to know what kinds of knowledge and skill teachers should have. Increasingly, emphasis is placed upon 'transversal' or 'horizontal' skills (such as 'learning to learn' or 'social competences', which cut across traditional subject boundaries, and therefore call into question traditional ways of designing the Teacher Education curriculum (and traditional ways of working in the classroom).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

practice at classroom teaching or at some other form of educational practice--usually supervised and supported in some way, though not always.  Practice can take the form of field observations, student teaching, or internship (See Supervised Field Experiences below.)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Supervised Field Experiences </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

field observations--include observation and limited participation within a classroom under the supervision of the classroom teacher</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

student teaching--includes a number of weeks teaching in an assigned classroom under the supervision of the classroom teacher and a supervisor (e.g. from the university)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

internship--teaching candidate is supervised within his or her own classroom</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

These three areas reflect the organization of most teacher education programs in North America (though not necessarily elsewhere in the world)--courses, modules, and other activities are often organized to belong to one of the three major areas of teacher education. The organization makes the programs more rational or logical in structure. The conventional organization has sometimes also been criticized, however, as artificial and unrepresentative of how teachers actually experience their work. Problems of practice frequently (perhaps usually) concern foundational issues, curriculum, and practical knowledge simultaneously, and separating them during teacher education may therefore not be helpful.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Quality Assurance </st>
<p>

Feedback on the performance of teachers is integral to many state and private education procedures, but takes many different forms. The 'no fault' approach is believed by some to be satisfactory, as weaknesses are carefully identified, assessed and then addressed through the provision of in service training.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/10313475.xml">
School of Education</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/419686.xml">
Pedagogy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/467367.xml">
Normal school</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gec.aed.org/publications_GEC.htm">
Research on Teacher Education in the Developing World</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.teacherswithoutborders.org">
Teacher leadership in developing countries</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.coe.uga.edu/tep/current.html">
Teaching Educational Psychology</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.umanitoba.ca/publications/cjeap">
Canadian Journal of Educational Administration and Policy</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://itec.macam.ac.il/portal/">
MOFET ITEC - International Portal of Teacher Education</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
see for example Cecil H Allen, In-Service Training of Teachers in  REVIEW OF EDUCATIONAL RESEARCH.1940; 10: 210-215 </entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
