<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:58:08[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<company  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108058098">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>AARP</title>
<id>402072</id>
<revision>
<id>244372835</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T14:09:02Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Thecurran</username>
<id>251903</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Magazine companies of the United States</category>
<category>Orphan initialisms</category>
<category>Lobbying organizations</category>
<category>Seniors&apos; organizations</category>
<category>Non-profit organizations based in the United States</category>
<category>Health care reform</category>
<category>Organizations established in 1958</category>
<category>Political advocacy groups in the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="AARP.png" type="frame">
<caption>

Current logo for AARP, in use since January 2007
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>For the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
AppleTalk</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 protocol developed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/856.xml">
Apple Computer</link>, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
AppleTalk address resolution protocol</link> (AARP).</it>
</indent>

<b>AARP</b>, formerly the <b>American Association of Retired Persons</b>, is a United States-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/46539.xml">
non-governmental organization</link> (a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/961742.xml">
special interest group</link>).  According to its mission statement,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> it is "a nonprofit, nonpartisan membership organization for people age 50 and over ... dedicated to enhancing quality of life for all as we age," which "provides a wide range of unique benefits, special products, and services for our members."  AARP operates as a <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
non-profit</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 advocate for its members and is one of the most powerful <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/48934.xml">
lobbying</link> groups in the United States,, but also sells insurance, investment funds and other financial products.  AARP claims over 38 million members,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> making it one of the largest membership organizations for people age 50 and over in the United States.  Membership is expected to grow significantly as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/8210419.xml">
baby boom</link>ers age.
</p>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Dr. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<disputant wordnetid="109615465" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<reformer wordnetid="110515194" confidence="0.8">
<militant wordnetid="110315837" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/1640138.xml">
Ethel Percy Andrus</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</causal_agent>
</militant>
</reformer>
</person>
</disputant>
</physical_entity>
 founded AARP in 1958. AARP evolved from the National Retired Teachers Association (NRTA), which Andrus had established in 1947 to promote her philosophy of productive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/16413778.xml">
aging</link>, and in response to the need of retired teachers for health insurance. After ten years, Andrus opened the organization to all Americans over 50, creating AARP. Today, NRTA is a division within AARP.</p>
<p>

According to critics, until the 1980s AARP was controlled by businessman Leonard Davis, who promoted its image as a non-profit advocate of retirees in order to sell insurance to members.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> In the 1990s, the <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/19592407.xml">
United States Senate</link></legislature>
 investigated AARP's non-profit status, with Republican Senator <senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/840213.xml">
Alan Simpson</link></senator>
, then chairman of the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/750795.xml">
Finance Committee's</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/11904797.xml">
Subcommittee on Social Security and Family Policy</link>, questioning the organization's tax exempt status in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/8107490.xml">
congressional hearing</link>s. These investigations did not reveal sufficient evidence to change the organization's status.</p>
<p>

The organization was originally named <it>American Association of Retired Persons</it>, but to reflect that its focus had become broader than American retirees, in 1999 it officially changed its name to just "AARP" (pronounced one letter at a time, "A-A-R-P").<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  AARP no longer requires that members be retired.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Activities</st>
<p>

AARP is widely known for addressing issues affecting older Americans through a multitude of initiatives, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/48934.xml">
lobbying</link> efforts at the state and national governmental level, an activity permitted by its <link>
501(c)(4)</link> status. The organization claims that it is non-partisan and does not support, oppose or give money to any candidates or political parties. AARP's total revenue for 2006 was approximately $1 billion and it spent $23 million on lobbying. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

AARP Services, Inc., founded in 1999, is a wholly owned subsidiary of AARP. AARP Services manages the wide range of products and services that are offered as benefits to AARP’s 38+ million members. The offers span health products, travel and leisure products, and life event services. Specific products include Medicare supplemental insurance; member discounts on rental cars, cruises, vacation packages and lodging; special offers on technology and gifts; pharmacy services; legal services; and long-term care insurance. AARP Services founded AARP Financial Incorporated, a subsidiary that manages AARP-endorsed financial products including AARP Funds. AARP Services develops new products, manages and markets products and services, creates and maintains partnership and sponsorship relationships, and develops and manages AARP’s Web site, AARP.org.</p>
<p>

AARP Services founded AARP Financial Incorporated, a subsidiary that manages AARP-endorsed financial products including AARP Funds.</p>
<p>

The AARP Foundation is AARP’s affiliated charity. Foundation programs provide security, protection and empowerment for older persons in need. Low-income older workers receive the job training and placement they need to re-join the workforce. Free tax preparation is provided for low- and moderate-income individuals, with special attention to those 60 and older. The Foundation’s litigation staff protects the legal rights of older Americans in critical health, long-term care, consumer and employment situations. Additional programs provide information, education and services to ensure that people over 50 lead lives of independence, dignity and purpose. Foundation programs are funded by grants, tax-deductible contributions and AARP. </p>
<p>

The organization also publishes <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/13854872.xml">
AARP The Magazine</link></publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</press>
</creation>
</print_media>
</magazine>
</product>
</work>
</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> (known until 2002 as <it>Modern Maturity</it>), a magazine focusing on aging issues.  Established in 1958, the magazine, distributed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/5295342.xml">
bi-monthly</link>, is sent to every AARP member, giving the free magazine a circulation AARP claims to be the "world's largest". AARP also publishes the AARP Bulletin, Segunda Juventud, Live &amp; Learn, and has a books division. </p>
<p>

The organization also produces radio and television programs. Prime Time Radio, hosted by veteran broadcaster Mike Cuthbert, is a one-hour weekly interview program that focuses on the wide-ranging interests and concerns of Americans 40 and older. The program is heard on radio stations across the country as well as on the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://radioprimetime.org">
Prime Time Radio</weblink> web site. Prime Time Focus, hosted by Alyne Ellis, is a 90-second daily feature with a five-minute weekend edition heard on more than 500 stations. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health care</st>
<p>

AARP's public stances influenced the <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
United States Congress</link></legislature>
' passage of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/378922.xml">
Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act</link>, which authorized the creation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/2870773.xml">
Medicare Part D</link>, in 2003, and also influenced the Congress' resistance to changes to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/48728.xml">
Social Security</link> in 2005. AARP also plans to address health care issues in their campaign targeting the 2008 elections with Divided We Fail.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Divided We Fail</st>
<p>
 
In early 2007 AARP launched "Divided We Fail",  designed to address health care and long-term financial security. The initiative was launched with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/7005392.xml">
Business Roundtable</link> and the <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/483275.xml">
Service Employees International Union</link></union>
, and encompasses advertising in national outlets and in the primary states, online activities, and traditional grassroots work, in order to engage the public, business and elected officials in the debate, and to encourage public leaders to offer solutions, according to the AARP.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Nancy LeaMond, executive officer for social impact, said, "We want to really get to these candidates and ask for action, answers and accountability on these questions."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

In November 2007, the <group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/2350093.xml">
National Federation of Independent Business</link></group>
 (NFIB) joined the Divided We Fail leadership. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

The initiative uses an "elephonkey" mixed animal as its symbol, with the head and forelegs of the <party wordnetid="108256968" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/32070.xml">
Republican</link></party>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/9279.xml">
elephant</link> and the ears, hindquarters, and tail of the kicking <party wordnetid="108256968" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/5043544.xml">
Democratic</link></party>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/55526.xml">
donkey</link>. "Champ" quickly became a recognizable symbol of the DWF initiative, fostered in part by television commercials that ran across the country. In addition, Divided We Fail Florida incorporated the initiative's mascot into an interactive educational vehicle, dubbed the "Champmobile," which traveled across the state and throughout the United States encouraging voters to "Let your voice be heard!"</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Future Champions</st>
<p>

In February 2007, AARP announced the launch of a new advertising campaign designed to address issues that will impact future generations and showcase the AARP brand. The campaign, called “Future Champions,” features children talking about the state of healthcare and financial security. The multigenerational focus is designed to reinforce the AARP's Divided We Fail coalition.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Health insurance</st>
<p>

Approximately seven million people have AARP branded health insurance, including drug coverage and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/3183394.xml">
medigap</link>, as of April 2007 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> and AARP earns more income from selling insurance to members than it does from membership dues. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> In 2008, AARP plans to begin offering several new health insurance products: An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/59097.xml">
HMO</link> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/58353.xml">
Medicare</link> recipients, in partnership with <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/1845551.xml">
UnitedHealth Group</link></company>
; and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/1184035.xml">
PPO</link> and "a high-deductible insurance policy that could be used with a health savings account" to people aged 50-64, in partnership with <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/78343.xml">
Aetna</link></company>
. AARP will likely become the largest source of health insurance for Medicare recipients, and AARP estimates the new products will increase its health insurance customers to 14 million by 2014.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> AARP is not an insurer and does not pay insurance claims. Instead, AARP allows its name to be used by insurance companies in the sale of insurance products, for which it is paid a commission like an insurance agent.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>
<p>

In an editorial column in the <it>Los Angeles Times</it>, critic Dale Van Atta says AARP 
does unauthorized lobbying for its membership, and lobbies against the best interests of its membership.
Van Atta says that by lobbying for the above-mentioned Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act, AARP leaders betrayed the membership.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>
<p>

According to an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/18622529.xml">
Annenberg Public Policy Center</link> report,
critics have said AARP had a conflict of interest in supporting the Act, because AARP “derives income from the sale of health and life insurance policies,” by licensing its brand to insurance dealers such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/2252525.xml">
New York Life</link></company>
,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> and would benefit financially from passage of the legislation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

<newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/945157.xml">
BusinessWeek</link></newspaper>
 magazine says that in the past questions have arisen about whether AARP's commercial interests may conflict with those of its membership, 
and characterizes many of the funds and insurance policies that AARP markets as providing considerably less benefit than seniors could get on their own.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/16413778.xml">
Aging</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<asset wordnetid="105154517" confidence="0.8">
<forte wordnetid="105159225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/1581682.xml">
Elderly care</link></forte>
</asset>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/436825.xml">
Geriatrics</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarp.org/about_aarp/aarp_overview/a2002-12-18-aarpmission.html">
AARP Mission Statement</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarp.org/research/press-center/presscurrentnews/rx_bargaining_power.html">
AARP puts full force of nearly 38 million members behind Congress’ efforts to give Medicare Rx bargaining power</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4D6133EF933A15753C1A960958260&amp;sec=&amp;pagewanted=print">
Krugman, Paul. "Demographics and Destiny", New York Times, 20 October 1996</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarp.org/about_aarp/aarp_overview/a2003-01-13-aarphistory.html">
AARP History</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/04/23/AR2007042301760.html">
On Issues From Medicare to Medication, AARP's Money Will Be There</weblink> Washington Post, 24 April 2007</entry>
<entry id="6">
http://www.aarpmagazine.org AARP The Magazine</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarp.org/research/press-center/presscurrentnews/groups_set_to_influence_political_debate.html">
AARP, Business Roundtable and SEIU Partner to Spur Action on Health Care, Long-term Financial Security</weblink>. January 16, 2007</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://newsmax.com/archives/ic/2007/3/22/73057.shtml?s=ic">
AARP Mobilizing to Hound 2008 Candidates</weblink>. March 22, 2007</entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nfib.com/object/IO_35243.html">
NFIB Joins AARP, Business Roundtable and SEIU in Divided We Fail</weblink> November 1, 2007</entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/health/17insure.html">
AARP Says It Will Become Major Medicare Insurer While Remaining a Consumer Lobby</weblink> New York Times, 17 April 2007</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/nation/la-na-aarp4mar04,1,7317388.story">
Los Angeles Times</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/health/17insure.html">
AARP Says It Will Become Major Medicare Insurer While Remaining a Consumer Lobby</weblink> New York Times, 17 April 2007</entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarp.org/research/press-center/presscurrentnews/aarp_announces_new_healthcare_relationship.html">
AARP Press Release</weblink> accessed 17 April 2007</entry>
<entry id="14">
Van Atta, Dale&#32;(<link>
24 Nov</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.commondreams.org/scriptfiles/views03/1124-07.htm">
This Isn't the Old AARP</weblink>", Los Angeles Times.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.newyorklife.com/cda/0,3254,13730,00.html">
AARP Life Insurance Program</weblink>, retrieved October 31, 2006</entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/05_11/b3924050_mz011.htm">
By Raising Its Voice, AARP Raises Questions</weblink> BusinessWeek, 14 March, 2005, accessed 7 January, 2008</entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.annenbergpublicpolicycenter.org/issueads05/2003-2004/Org%20Bios/aarp.htm">
Annenberg Public Policy Center report on AARP</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dale Van Atta, <it>Trust Betrayed: Inside the AARP</it> (Regnery Publishing,1998).   ISBN 0-89526-485-4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Charles R. Morris, <it>The AARP: America's Most Powerful Lobby and the Clash of Generations</it> (Crown, 1996).  ISBN 0-8129-2753-2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Peter G. Peterson, <it>Will America Grow Up Before It Grows Old? How the Coming Social Security Crisis Threatens You, Your Family, and Your Country</it> (Random House, 1996).  ISBN 0-679-45256-7</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarp.org">
Official website of the AARP</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarp.org/about_aarp/aarp_overview/">
AARP official history, financial reports, and mission statement</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarpmagazine.org">
Official website of <it>AARP The Magazine''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarp.org/bulletin">
Official website of <it>AARP Bulletin''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aarpsegundajuventud.org">
Official website of <it>AARP Segunda Juventud</it>, AARP's bilingual publication</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dividedwefail.org/">
Official website of Divided We Fail</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prospect.org/web/page.ww?section=root&amp;name=ViewPrint&amp;articleId=7702">
Detailed history of recent AARP lobbying</weblink> from the liberal publication <it><link>
The American Prospect</link></it>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.60plus.org/about-aarp.asp">
A critical history of AARP</weblink> by the competing organization, <it>60 Plus Association''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4D6133EF933A15753C1A960958260&amp;sec=&amp;pagewanted=print">
Demographics and Destiny, by Paul Krugman, <it>New York Times''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Schurenberg, Eric&#59;&#32;Lani Luciano&#32;(<link>
1988-10-01</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://money.cnn.com/magazines/moneymag/moneymag_archive/1988/10/01/84702/index.htm">
The Empire Called AARP</weblink>", <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/1190375.xml">
Money Magazine</link></it>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/6696324.xml">
Time Inc.</link></company>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-12</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</group>
</company>
</entity>
</organization>
</article>
