<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:58:09[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<theorist  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110706812">
<intellectual  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109621545">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<header>
<title>Ray Solomonoff</title>
<id>402673</id>
<revision>
<id>244048055</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T02:15:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Vivohobson</username>
<id>7949717</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>1926 births</category>
<category>History of artificial intelligence</category>
<category>Information theorists</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Ray Solomonoff</b> (born 1926, Cleveland, Ohio, son of Russian
immigrants) invented <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scholarpedia.org/article/Algorithmic_probability">
Algorithmic Probability</weblink> in 1960.  He first described his results at a Conference at Cal Tech, 
1960,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> and
in a report, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://world.std.com/~rjs/z138.pdf">
"A Preliminary Report on a General Theory of Inductive Inference,"</weblink> in Feb., 1960.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> He clarified these ideas more fully in his 1964 publications, "A Formal
Theory of Inductive Inference," <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://world.std.com/~rjs/1964pt1.pdf">
Part I</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://world.std.com/~rjs/1964pt2.pdf">
Part II."</weblink><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> <p>

Although he is best known for Algorithmic Probability and his General Theory of Inductive Inference, he made other important discoveries in related fields.
He wrote three <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://world.std.com/~rjs/50.pdf">
papers</weblink>, two with Rapoport, in 1950-52, that are regarded as the earliest statistical analysis of networks. He was one of the 10 attendees at the 1956 <link>
 Dartmouth Summer Research Conference on Artificial Intelligence</link>, a seminal event for artificial intelligence as a field.  There he wrote <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://world.std.com/~rjs/indinf56.pdf">
"An Inductive Inference Machine"</weblink>, publishing a version in 1957<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>.  This was the first paper to be written on Machine Learning.  He also invented probabilistic languages in the late 1950s.</p>
<p>

His most important breakthrough, however, was the invention of Algorithmic Probability.
Prior to the 1960s, the usual method of calculating
probability was based on frequency:  taking the ratio of favorable
results to the total number of trials.  In his 1960 publication,
and, more completely, in his 1964 publications,  Solomonoff seriously revised
this definition of probability.  He called this new form of
probability "Algorithmic Probability."</p>
<p>

What was later called Kolmogorov Complexity was a side product of his General
Theory. He described this idea in 1960: "Consider a very long sequence of symbols
...We shall consider such a sequence of symbols to be 'simple' and
have a high a priori probability, if there exists a very brief
description of this sequence - using, of course, some sort of
stipulated description method.  More exactly, if we use only the
symbols 0 and 1 to express our description, we will assign the
probability 2-<it>N</it> to a sequence of symbols if its
shortest possible binary description contains  <it>N</it>
digits."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Five years later, in 1965, the Russian mathematician Kolmogorov
independently presented a similar idea. When he became aware of Solomonoff's work, he acknowledged Solomonoff's priority, and for several years, Solomonoff's work was better known in the Soviet Union than in the Western World. 
The general consensus in the scientific community, however, was to associate this type
of complexity with Kolmogorov, who was more concerned with randomness
of a sequence. Algorithmic Probability became associated with Solomonoff,
who was focussed on prediction - the extrapolation of a sequence.</p>
<p>

Later in the same 1960 publication Solomonoff describes his improvement
on the single-shortest-code theory. This is Algorithmic
Probability.  He states: "It would seem that if there are several
different methods of describing a
sequence, each of these methods should be given <it>some</it> weight in
determining the probability of that sequence."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> He then shows how this idea can be used to generate 
the universal a priori probability distribution.</p>
<p>

In the early 60s, he continued to write and enlarge his
theory, publishing a number of reports leading up to his 
publications in 1964.  Although his work at first was not widely known, over the
years many people have come to recognize the importance and
priority of his discoveries. </p>
<p>

In 1968 he found a proof for the
efficacy of Algorithmic Probability<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>, but mainly because of lack
of general interest at that time, did not publish it until 10
years later. He showed that
Algorithmic Probability was "complete"; that if there was any
describable regularity in a body of data, that Algorithmic
Probability would eventually discover that regularity, needing a
relatively small sample of that data.  Algorithmic Probability is
the only probability system know to be "complete" in this way.In
1986 he described how Algorithmic Probability could be used in
applications to A.I. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

In 1970 he formed his own one man company, Oxbridge Research, and
has continued his research there except for short periods at other
institutions such as MIT, University of Saarland in Germany and IDSIA in Switzerland.  In 2003 he was 
the first recipient of the The Computer Learning Research
Center's Kolmogorov award and gave the inaugural 
Kolmogorov lecture at Royal Holloway, University of London. Solomonoff is
currently  visiting Professor at the CRLC.  </p>
<p>

In 2006 he spoke at <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<meeting wordnetid="108307589" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<conference wordnetid="108308497" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/5992535.xml">
AI@50</link></conference>
</group>
</gathering>
</meeting>
</social_group>
, "Dartmouth Artificial Intelligence Conference: 
the Next Fifty Years"  commemorating the fiftieth anniversary
of the original Dartmouth summer study group.  Solomonoff was one of five original participants to attend.  </p>
<p>

Most recently, in Feb. 2008, he
gave the keynote address at the Conference, "Current Trends in the
Theory and Application of Computer Science" held at Notre Dame
University in Lebanon.  He followed this with a short series of
lectures, and began research on new applications of Algorithmic Probability.</p>
<p>

A description of Solomonoff's life and work prior to 1997 is in his paper "The Discovery of Algorithmic Probability", Journal of Computer and System Sciences, Vol 55, No. 1, pp 73-88, August 1997. This paper, as well as most of the others mentioned here, are available on his website at his <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://world.std.com/~rjs/pubs.html">
publications page</weblink>. </p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Paper from conference on "Cerebral Systems and Computers",
California Institute of Technology, Feb 8-11, 1960, cited in "A
Formal Theory of Inductive Inference, Part 1, 1964, p. 1</entry>
<entry id="2">
"A Preliminary
Report on a General Theory of Inductive Inference," Report V-131,
Zator Co., Cambridge, Ma. Feb 4, 1960.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"A Formal
Theory of Inductive Inference, Part I" <it>Information and Control</it>,
Vol 7, No. 1 pp 1-22, March 1964, and
"A Formal Theory of Inductive Inference, Part II" <it>Information and Control</it>,
Vol 7, No. 2 pp 224-254, June 1964.</entry>
<entry id="4">
An Inductive Inference Machine," IRE Convention Record, Section on Information Theory, Part 2, pp. 56-62</entry>
<entry id="5">
"A Preliminary Report on a General Theory of Inductive
Inference,", 1960 p. 1</entry>
<entry id="6">
"A
Preliminary Report on a General Theory of Inductive
Inference,",1960, p.
17</entry>
<entry id="7">
"Complexity-based Induction
Systems, Comparisons and convergence Theorems" <it>IEEE Trans. on
Information Theory</it> IT-24, No. 4 (July,1978).</entry>
<entry id="8">
"The Application of Algorithmic Probability to Problems in
Artificial Intelligence", in Kanal and Lemmer (Eds.), <it>Uncertainty
in Artificial Intelligence,</it>, Elsevier Science Publishers B.V., pp
473-491, 1986.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1635.xml">
Kolmogorov complexity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/405562.xml">
Inductive inference</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ming Li and Paul Vitanyi, <it>An Introduction to Kolmogorov Complexity and It's Applications.</it>  Springer-Verlag, N.Y., 1997, includes historical notes on Solomonoff as well as a description and analysis of his work.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://world.std.com/~rjs/index.html">
Ray Solomonoff's Homepage</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 For a detailed description of Algorithmic Probability, see <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scholarpedia.org/article/Algorithmic_probability">
"Algorithmic Probability"</weblink> by Hutter,  Legg and Vitanyi in the scholarpedia.</entry>
</list>
</p>






</sec>
</bdy>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
