<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:52:12[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Hulda Regehr Clark</title>
<id>4034249</id>
<revision>
<id>244651328</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T21:48:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Husky44</username>
<id>8057862</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>University of Minnesota alumni</category>
<category>People in alternative medicine</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Year of birth missing (living people)</category>
<category>University of Saskatchewan alumni</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image upright="upright" location="right" width="150px" src="Drclark.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Hulda Regehr Clark
</caption>
</image>

<b>Hulda Regehr Clark</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/17951240.xml">
naturopath</link>, author, and controversial practitioner of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/1845.xml">
alternative medicine</link>.
<sec>
<st>
 Background </st>

<p>

Clark began her studies in biology at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/267686.xml">
University of Saskatchewan</link></university>
, <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
, where she was awarded the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/156992.xml">
Bachelor of Arts</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/493992.xml">
Magna Cum Laude</link>, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/4126896.xml">
Master of Arts</link>, with a High Honors major in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biology</link>. After two years of study at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/7954643.xml">
McGill University</link></university>
, she attended the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/416813.xml">
University of Minnesota</link></university>
, studying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/54000.xml">
biophysics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/6227883.xml">
cell physiology</link>. She received her <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
doctorate degree</link> in 1958 from the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/416813.xml">
University of Minnesota</link></university>
. Her own biographical sketch states that her degree was in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/23597.xml">
physiology</link>, but  the Graduate School's Register of Ph.D. Degrees conferred by the University of Minnesota  July 1956-June 1966 states that she received a Ph.D. in 1958 with a major in zoology and a minor in botany, with a thesis entitled "A study of the ion balance of crayfish muscle; evidence for two compartments of cellular potassium."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

In 1979 Clark left government-funded research and began private consulting and her own research. Presently, she operates the Century Nutrition health clinic in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/101739.xml">
Tijuana</link></village>
, <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/3966054.xml">
Mexico</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, where her focus is primarily on late stage <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer</link> patients. She has published several books on human health, including <it>The Cure of All Cancers</it>, <it>The Cure for HIV/AIDS</it> and <it>The Cure For All Diseases</it>. According to court records, Clark's books have generated over $7 million in sales, although Clark disputes this figure.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  </p>
<p>

She has a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/68819.xml">
naturopathy</link> degree from the <institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/9448282.xml">
Clayton College of Natural Health</link></institution>
,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> a school <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/653019.xml">
that lacks accreditation</link> from any accreditation agency recognized by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/70919.xml">
U.S. Department of Education</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Clark's claims </st>

<p>

Clark claims that disease essentially has two causes: parasites, bacteria and viruses; and pollutants which damage the immune system. She claims that parasites, bacteria and viruses can be eliminated by using herbal treatments and by using electrical treatments, which purportedly electrocute foreign organisms. In conjunction with eliminating pollutants from the diet and from the environment, such treatments can, she asserts, cure diseases. </p>
<p>

In her book "The Cure For All Cancers" Clark postulates that all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer</link>s are caused by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/24151.xml">
flatworm</link> <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/1043908.xml">
Fasciolopsis buski</link></it>. However, this worm does not live in the USA and Europe. <it>F. buski</it> exists mainly in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
, parts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5042862.xml">
China</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/202354.xml">
Vietnam</link></country>
 and other east-Asian countries, and there only in rural areas where people are eating unboiled food from water plants, or where pigs live close to humans. She also claims that HIV is a worm virus and that that worm is responsible for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/5069516.xml">
AIDS</link>: <it>"I find it </it>(F. buski)<it> in every case of HIV, Alzheimer's disease. Without this parasite you can't get HIV."</it> According to Clark <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/8389.xml">
depression</link> is caused by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../203/1079203.xml">
hookworm</link>s.</p>
<p>

She claims that all diseases can be cured using her methods, including pains in various parts of the body, digestion problems, all cancers, HIV/AIDS, warts, and diabetes.</p>
<p>

She claims that scientific medical treatments for diseases such as cancers and HIV/AIDS often only focus on treating the symptoms of these diseases, while her treatments are able to cure the disease itself.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> David Amrein's website contains a disclaimer stating that Clark's treatments are "not prescribed as treatment for medical or psychological conditions" and that "...the treatments outlined herein are not intended to be a replacement or substitute for other forms of conventional medical treatment."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Nonetheless, Clark has advocated for the use of her methods as a substitute for standard medical care:
Does this mean you can cancel your date for surgery, radiation or chemotherapy? YES! After curing your cancer with this recipe it cannot come back... Remember that oncologists are kind, sensitive, compassionate people. They want the best for you. They have no way of knowing about the true cause and cure of cancer since it has not been published for them.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>


<p>

Regarding the effectiveness of her treatment, Clark has written, "The method is 100% effective in stopping cancer regardless of the type of cancer or how terminal it may be. It follows that this method must work for you, too, if you are able to carry out the instructions."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Major methods and topics </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Diet Cleanup</b>:  She talks extensively about how contaminated she believes our <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/10646.xml">
food</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/17181894.xml">
supplements</link> are, with such things as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/47671.xml">
heavy metals</link>, manufacturing by-products and residue, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/51469.xml">
mold</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Homeography</b>: Clark calls this a "new science ... which is the electronic analog of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/14229.xml">
homeopathy</link>." She claims that an electronic signature of a substance can be transferred into bottles make a "bottle copy" of the original substance. The process can then be continued <it>ad infinitum</it> without any need to buy more of the original substance.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/2629174.xml">
Liver flush</link></b>:  She advocates the use of a 'liver flush', which is claimed to remove <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/287531.xml">
gallstones</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/43937.xml">
parasites</link> from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/17384301.xml">
liver</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/197021.xml">
bile duct</link>s.  This involves a partial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/1899768.xml">
fast</link> for a day, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/246267.xml">
epsom salt</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/168526.xml">
laxatives</link>, and a mixture of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/67401.xml">
grapefruit</link> juice.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/43937.xml">
Parasites</link></b>:  Clark insists that most people have parasites inside them, and that these parasites cause a host of problems.  She describes herbal and electronic methods to remove them. These methods include known herbal anti-parasitics as well as electronic treatment of her own device (Zapper, see below).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Syncrometer</b>:  A device invented by Clark, which she claims can detect contaminants in substances up to one part per trillion. The Syncrometer is a so-called bioresonance (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../906/292906.xml">
bio feedback</link>) unit.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Zapper</b>:  An electronic device which pulses low voltage DC current through the body at specific frequencies.  Clark claims this device can kill <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/19167679.xml">
virus</link>es, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/9028799.xml">
bacteria</link>, and parasites. In at least one reported case, a patient with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/233429.xml">
cardiac pacemaker</link> suffered serious <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/5562.xml">
arrhythmia</link>s as a result of interference from the "Zapper".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Federal Trade Commission and FDA action </st>
<p>

The <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/182215.xml">
Federal Trade Commission</link></agency>
 brought a complaint against the Dr. Clark Research Foundation over claims made in support of the Syncrometer, the Super-Zapper Deluxe, and "Dr. Clark's New 21 Day Program for Advanced Cancers".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> In November 2004, a stipulated judgement was reached in which purchasers of these devices were to be offered a full refund, and the Dr. Clark Research Foundation was barred from making a number of claims about the efficacy of the devices in question.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> The Director of Enforcement at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/11632.xml">
Food and Drug Administration</link> has stated that Clark's devices appear to be "fraudulent".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Legal issues </st>
<p>

In 1993, while Clark lived and practiced in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/14853.xml">
Indiana</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, a former patient complained to the Indiana <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/54376.xml">
attorney general</link>. An investigator for the Indiana Department of Health and a deputy attorney general visited her office  as part of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/83310.xml">
sting operation</link>. Clark proceeded to test the investigator and "told him he had the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/14170.xml">
HIV</link> virus [''sic''], but said that he did not have <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer</link>." She told the investigator that she could cure his HIV in 3 minutes, but that he would "get it back" unless he committed to returning for six more appointments. She then ordered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/336557.xml">
blood test</link>s from a laboratory. Upon learning of the undercover investigators' status, Clark stated that everything she had told them had been a "mistake". Two days later she had vacated the premises.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

In September 1999, Clark was located and arrested in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/28504.xml">
San Diego</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/5407.xml">
California</link></country>
, based on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/209287.xml">
fugitive warrant</link> from Indiana. According to Clark, this was the first time she learned about the charge. Her lawyer protested the long delay before her arrest, but a prosecutor implied that she fled Indiana "when she learned that she was being investigated by the state," and that the local police department had limited resources to devote to finding her.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> She was returned to Indiana to stand trial, where she was charged with practicing medicine without a license. The charge was later dismissed for failure to provide her with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/217229.xml">
speedy trial</link>. The judge's verdict did not address the merits of the charges but only the issue of whether the delay had compromised Clark's ability to mount a defense and her right to a speedy trial.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

In February 2001, Mexican authorities inspected Clark's Century Nutrition clinic and ordered it shut down, as the clinic had never registered and was operating without a license. In June 2001, the Mexican authorities announced that the clinic would be permitted to reopen, but was prohibited from offering "alternative" treatments. The clinic was also fined 160,000 pesos (about $18,000), and Clark was barred from working in Mexico, even as a consultant; however, the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/1026281.xml">
San Diego Union-Tribune</link></it> reported in 2003 that there was evidence that Clark continued to work at the clinic.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Evaluation of claims and criticism </st>
<p>

Hulda Clark has been criticized because her claims lack scientific validity and consist of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/481925.xml">
anecdotal evidence</link>. Joseph Pizzorno, a prominent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/17951240.xml">
naturopathic physician</link>, evaluated Clark's claims and found that her books mixed patients with conventionally diagnosed cancer with those whose cancer diagnosis was based solely on her use of the "Syncrometer". The patients with medically diagnosed cancer did not respond to Clark's treatment, while those she had diagnosed using the "Syncrometer" were "cured". Pizzorno concluded that Clark's treatments were ineffective and that treatments based on Clark's recommendations "pose a substantive public health danger".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>
<p>

The Swiss Study Group for Complementary and Alternative Methods in Cancer (SCAC) issued a strong warning to cancer patients considering Clark's methods:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

<table style="margin:auto; border-collapse:collapse; border-style:none; background-color:transparent; " class="cquote">
<row>
<col style="color:#B2B7F2;font-size:35px;font-family:'Times New Roman',serif;font-weight:bold;text-align:left;padding:10px 10px;" width="20" valign="top">
“</col>
<col style="padding:4px 10px;" valign="top">
There is no scientific basis for Hulda Clark's hypotheses and recommendations, including her suggested treatments.  The parasite Fasciolopsis buskii does in fact exist, but only in Asian countries, so that an infection in our country is ruled out. Consequently, this parasite does not enter into consideration as a cause of the numerous cases of cancer in the Western countries; at most, it might be one of several causes of liver cancer (and only for this type of cancer) in the Asian countries.  As a whole, Clark's thesis cannot be comprehended, nor is it proven.  In individual cases, her advice can be very extensive and costly. Hence if patients do not apply her method consistently and their disease continues to progress, they run the risk of attempting to blame themselves for this, rather than Clark's treatment which is ineffective, as viewed at present.</col>
<col style="color:#B2B7F2;font-size:36px;font-family:'Times New Roman',serif;font-weight:bold;text-align:right;padding:10px 10px;" width="20" valign="bottom">
”</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

Prominent alternative medicine proponent <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<health_professional wordnetid="110165109" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<medical_practitioner wordnetid="110305802" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<advocate wordnetid="109774783" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/1178580.xml">
Andrew Weil</link></research_worker>
</scholar>
</writer>
</advocate>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</medical_practitioner>
</communicator>
</doctor>
</professional>
</health_professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 has written, "No studies have backed up [Clark's] bizarre claims, and it’s unclear whether the cancer patients she’s supposedly cured ever had cancer to begin with."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>
<p>

In 2002, the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/1026281.xml">
San Diego Union-Tribune</link></it> reported that Clark and her son Geoff operated a restaurant and leased housing for patients at Clark's Tijuana clinic. The article described a couple whose daughter, suffering from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/423910.xml">
spinal muscular atrophy</link>, was treated for 10 months by Clark at a cost of approximately $30,000 without improvement. Despite the cost and lack of improvement, the couple stated that Clark insisted she was close to curing the child, and that stopping treatment might endanger her.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The patient's mother commented, "People don’t understand why we stayed so long, but Hulda Clark did a very good job of preying on us," and Clark, while stating she could not respond to the parents' allegations on grounds of patient confidentiality, denied their statements in general.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Works </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Cure for All Cancers (1993)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Cure For HIV / AIDS (1993)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Cure for All Diseases (1995)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Cure For All Advanced Cancers (1999)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Syncrometer Science Laboratory Manual (2000)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Prevention of all Cancers (2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Cure and Prevention of All Cancers (2007)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Library, University of Minnesota</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/reports/tjclinics/20020224-9999-operator.html">
"The 95 percent promise? Complaints trail entrepreneur, who claims remarkable cure rate"</weblink>, by Penni Crabtree and Sandra Dibble. Published in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/1026281.xml">
San Diego Union-Tribune</link> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/11007.xml">
February 24</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/35502.xml">
2002</link>. Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/18935042.xml">
March 7</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.drclark.net/en/hulda_clark/about_drclark.php">
Hulda Clark biographical sketch.</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20070211/NEWS/702110399/1007/DATELINE09&amp;cachetime=3&amp;template=dateline">
"State’s diploma mills draw academic ire"</weblink>, by Adam Jones, <it>Tuscaloosa News</it>. Published <link>
11 Feb</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>. Accessed <link>
14 Feb</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
The Cure For All Diseases</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.drclark.net/en/hulda_clark/drclark_disclaimer.php">
Disclaimer</weblink> from David Amrein's website, drclark.net. Accessed 15 Feb 2007.</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.drclark.net/en/disclaimer.php">
A second disclaimer</weblink> from Amrein's website, drclark.net. Accessed 15 Feb 2007.</entry>
<entry id="8">
As quoted in a page capture from www.drclark.net in a <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ftc.gov/os/caselist/0223051/030127comp0223051.htm">
Federal Trade Commission complaint against David Amrein's Dr. Clark Research Association</weblink>. Accessed 27 Dec 2006.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Clark HR. The Cure for All Cancers. San Diego, CA: ProMotion Publishing, 1993, p. 120.</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Furrer M, Naegeli B, Bertel O&#32;(2004).&#32;"Hazards of an alternative medicine device in a patient with a pacemaker". <it>N Engl J Med</it>&#32;<b>350</b>&#32;(16): 1688–90. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1056%2FNEJM200404153501623">
10.1056/NEJM200404153501623</weblink>. PMID 15084709.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/business/20030129-9999_1b29quack.html">
"FTC sues over health claims"</weblink>, by Penni Crabtree. Published in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/1026281.xml">
San Diego Union-Tribune</link> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/15814.xml">
January 29</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>. Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/18935042.xml">
March 7</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>.</entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casewatch.org/ftc/enforcements/amrein/consent.shtml">
STIPULATED FINAL JUDGMENT AND ORDER FOR PERMANENT INJUNCTION AND OTHER EQUITABLE RELIEF</weblink>, Civ. No. l:03CV0054. Decision of the United States District Court for the Northern Division of Ohio, Eastern Division, dated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/21452.xml">
November 18</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link>. Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/18935042.xml">
March 7</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>.</entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.quackwatch.org/01QuackeryRelatedTopics/Cancer/clarkaff/huffman.html">
State of Indiana vs. Hulda Clark: Probable Cause Affidavit, Filed August 16, 1993</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
Hinnefeld, Steve, <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.healthwatcher.net/Quackerywatch/Hulda_Clark/ht000419dismissal.html">
Clark won't face charges</weblink></it> in the Herald-Times of April 19, 2000.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Hinnefeld, Steve, <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.healthwatcher.net/Quackerywatch/Hulda_Clark/ht000405trial.html">
Woman who claims healing knowledge faces charges</weblink></it>, Herald Times, April 5, 2000, Accessed 7-11-2007</entry>
<entry id="17">
<it>A cure for AIDS</it>, Avert.org, retrieved November 7, 2007. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.avert.org/cure-for-aids.htm">
available online</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.quackwatch.org/01QuackeryRelatedTopics/Cancer/clarkaff/pizzorno.html">
Western Herb and Dietary Products: Evaluation by Dr. Joseph E. Pizzorno, N.D.</weblink> May 8, 2001. Accessed 15 Feb 2007.</entry>
<entry id="19">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.swisscancer.ch/dt_fr/content/orange/pdf/skak/01_clark_e.pdf">
Swiss Study Group for Complementary and  Alternative Methods in Cancer (SCAC)</weblink> warns cancer patients against reliance on Clark's methods.</entry>
<entry id="18">
<it>Feds prescribe a lawsuit for cancercure.com</it>, Puget Sound Business Journal, June 15, 2001. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bizjournals.com/seattle/stories/2001/06/18/tidbits.html">
available online</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.drweilselfhealing.com/print_friendly.asp?iDocumentID=183&amp;iBDC=2196">
Exploring Alternative Cancer Treatments</weblink>, from Dr. Andrew Weil's Self Healing. Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/19351.xml">
May 4</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Advocacy </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.HuldaClark.net/">
Hulda Clark's official web site</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Legal </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ftc.gov/opa/2003/01/drclark.htm">
Federal Trade Commission Action Against Dr. Clark Research Association</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.quackwatch.org/01QuackeryRelatedTopics/Cancer/clarkaff/huffman.html">
State of Indiana vs. Hulda Clark, Probable Cause Affadavit</weblink>. Filed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/1448.xml">
August 16</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/34598.xml">
1993</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Assessments of claims </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.swisscancer.ch/dt_fr/content/orange/pdf/skak/01_clark_e.pdf">
Swiss Study Group for Complementary and Alternative Methods in Cancer (SCAC): Hulda Clark</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cancerguide.org/hulda_clark.html">
CancerGuide: Hulda Clark's "Cure for All Cancers"</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.quackwatch.org/01QuackeryRelatedTopics/Cancer/clark.html">
The Bizarre Claims of Hulda Clark</weblink> - Page on Hulda Clark from <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/879168.xml">
Quackwatch</link></organization>
, which has been involved in litigation with Clark.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Newspaper coverage </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/reports/tjclinics/20020224-9999-operator.html">
"The 95 percent promise? Complaints trail entrepreneur, who claims remarkable cure rate"</weblink>. Published in the <it>San Diego Union-Tribune</it>,  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/11007.xml">
February 24</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/35502.xml">
2002</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/business/20030129-9999_1b29quack.html">
"FTC Sues over Health Claims"</weblink>, published in the <it>San Diego Union-Tribune</it>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/15814.xml">
January 29</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
