<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:58:37[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104377057">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<header>
<title>Web Feature Service</title>
<id>405742</id>
<revision>
<id>220103254</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-18T08:32:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>BOTijo</username>
<id>3729068</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Geographic information systems</category>
<category>Open Geospatial Consortium</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/1043855.xml">
Open Geospatial Consortium</link> <b>Web Feature Service</b> Interface Standard (<b>WFS</b>) provides an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/620746.xml">
interface</link> allowing requests for  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/18963910.xml">
geographical</link> features across the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
web</link></invention>
 using platform-independent calls.  One can think of geographical features as the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/27661.xml">
source code</link>" behind a map, whereas the <link>
 WMS</link> interface or online mapping portals like <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/1494648.xml">
Google Maps</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 return only an image, which end-users cannot edit or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Spatial+analysis+with+GIS+%22])">
 spatially analyze</link>.  The <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
XML</link></format>
-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/203653.xml">
GML</link> furnishes the default payload-encoding for transporting the geographic features, but other formats like <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/2770513.xml">
shapefiles</link></format>
 can also serve for transport. In early 2006, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/1043855.xml">
OGC</link> members approved the OpenGIS GML Simple Features Profile <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=15201">
http://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=15201</weblink>. This profile is designed to both increase interoperability between WFS servers and to improve the ease of implementation of the WFS standard. <p>

The OGC membership defined and maintains the WFS specification.  There are numerous commercial and open source implementations of the WFS interface standard, including an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link> reference implementation, called <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/1303216.xml">
GeoServer</link></software>
. A comprehensive list of WFS implementations can be found at the OGC Implementing Products page <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/resource/products/implementing">
http://www.opengeospatial.org/resource/products/implementing</weblink>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Overview </st>
<p>

The WFS specification defines interfaces for describing data manipulation operations of geographic features. Data manipulation operations include the ability to:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Get or Query features based on spatial and non-spatial constraints</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Create a new feature instance</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Delete a feature instance</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Update a feature instance</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The basic Web Feature Service allows querying and retrieval of features.  A transactional Web Feature Service (WFS-T) allows creation, deletion, and updating of features.</p>
<p>

A WFS describes discovery, query, or data transformation operations. The client generates the request and posts it to a web feature server using HTTP. The web feature server then executes the request. The WFS specification uses HTTP as the distributed computing platform, although this is not a hard requirement. </p>
<p>

There are two encodings defined for WFS operations:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/34138.xml">
XML</link></format>
 (amenable to HTTP POST/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/29215.xml">
SOAP</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Keyword-Value pairs (amenable to HTTP GET/<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/26346.xml">
Remote procedure call</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In the taxonomy of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/93483.xml">
Web Services</link>, WFS is best categorized as a non-RESTful RPC type service.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Communication models</st>
<p>

The WFS Web Feature Services or Web Feature Server specification supports two communication models:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Stateless Request Reply</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pub/Sub</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

A messaging system in which clients address messages to a specific node in a content hierarchy, called a topic. Publishers and subscribers are generally anonymous and can dynamically publish or subscribe to the content hierarchy. The system takes care of distributing the messages arriving from a node's multiple publishers to its multiple subscribers. Messages are generally not persistent and will only be received by subscribers who are listening at the time the message is sent. A special case known as a “durable subscription” allows subscribers to receive messages sent while the subscribers are not active. (Source: http://java.sun.com/j2ee/1.4/docs/glossary.html)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The Web Notification Service (WNS) is one of the implementation specifications for the Pub/Sub model. Regardless of the model, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link> format is used and specified in the WFS specification. At this time there are no open-standard implementations of WNSs. Vendors plan to release implementations once the standard has been ratified. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Data </st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/203653.xml">
Geography Markup Language (GML)</link> passes data back and forth between a Web Feature Server and a client. GML normally communicates geospatial data, but also supports other types of data.</p>
<p>

<b>GML</b></p>
<p>

GML is an XML dialect which can be used to model geographic features.  The 1.0.0 version of the WFS specification requires the use of GML version 2.1.2, while the 1.1.0 version of the WFS specification requires the use of GML version 3.1.1.  For both versions of the WFS specification, an arbitrary number of other encodings can also be defined, in addition to the required GML 2.1.2 or 3.1.1 format (for 1.0.0 and 1.1.1 respectively).</p>
<p>

GML 2.1.2 contains encoding support for basic geometric 'primitives':  points, lines, polygons, etc.</p>
<p>

GML 3.1.1 contains encoding support for more advanced geometric representations:  curves, surfaces, multi-dimensions (time, elevation, multi-band imagery).  In addition, GML 3.1.1 includes encoding support for topologically integrated datasets.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Public Interfaces</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Static Interfaces </st>
<p>

The static interface model for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/18257846.xml">
OGC</link> Web Service model appears in the figure below.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Wfs_ogc.gif">
<caption>

 Wfs_ogc.gif
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The Transaction and LockFeature operations are also optional.</p>
<p>

When writing a WFS , you must implement the following operations:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

GetCapabilities - this queries the WFS service to determine available options.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

DescribeFeatureType - this retrieves the XML schema to allow the WFS client to parse the resultsets.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

GetFeature - this performs the actual query - parameters such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/12087300.xml">
bounding box</link> and any other filters should be passed in, as appropriate, and the WFS service then returns a GML resultset containing full geometry and feature attributes.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Dynamic interfaces</st>
<p>

The dynamic request/reply interface model for the OGC Web Service model appears in the figure below.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Wfs_ogc2.gif">
<caption>

 Wfs_ogc2.gif
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Dynamic interface updates </st>
<p>

The client gets updates by one of two mechanisms:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Notification: Recommended but not mandatory. Depends on the availability of a WMS implementation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Polling: Use this method if a WMS implementation is not available.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>WFS dynamic interface web notification model</b></p>
<p>

This model uses the OGC Web Notification Service to send update notifications to registered clients. The Notification interface appears in the figure below.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Wfs_ogc3.gif">
<caption>

 Wfs_ogc3.gif
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>WFS dynamic interface web notification polling model</b></p>
<p>

The polling model interface appears in the figure below.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Wfs_ogc4.gif">
<caption>

 Wfs_ogc4.gif
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/wfs">
<it>OpenGIS Web Feature Service (WFS) Implementation Specification''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=8340">
<it>Filter Encoding Specification''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://geoserver.org">
<it>GeoServer Open Source Reference Implementation''</it></weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=18776">
<it>WNS: Draft OpenGIS Web Notification Service Implementation Specification''</it></weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</article>
