<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:40:54[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Allan variance</title>
<id>40708</id>
<revision>
<id>240226787</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-22T13:51:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ryulong</username>
<id>889851</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Measurement</category>
<category>Statistical deviation and dispersion</category>
<category>Clocks</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Allan variance</b>, named after <link>
David W. Allan</link>, is a measurement of stability in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/6449.xml">
clock</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/22522.xml">
oscillator</link>s.  It is also known as the <b>two-sample variance</b>.
It is defined as one half of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/30012.xml">
time</link> average of the squares of the differences between successive readings of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/41187.xml">
frequency deviation</link> sampled over the sampling period.
The Allan variance depends on the time period used between samples: therefore it is a function of the sample period, as well as the distribution being measured, and is displayed as a graph rather than a single number.
A low Allan variance is a characteristic of a clock with good stability over the measured period.<p>

The Allan variance is given by</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\sigma_y^2(\tau) = \frac{1}{2} \langle(y_{n+1} - y_n)^2\rangle,</math>
</indent>

where <it>yn</it> is the normalized frequency departure, averaged over sample period <it>n</it>, and <math>\tau</math> is the time per sample period. The samples are taken with no dead-time between them.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>y_n = \left\langle{\delta\nu \over \nu}\right\rangle_n,</math>
</indent>

where <it>ν</it> is the frequency, <it>δν</it> is the frequency error, and the average is taken over sampling period <it>n</it>.
For a clock, the time error, <it>xn</it>, at sampling period <it>n</it>, is the sum of the preceding frequency errors, given by</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>x_n = x_0 + \tau\sum_{i=0}^{n-1} y_i.</math>
</indent>

This can be reversed to compute frequency error from time error measurements</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>y_n = \frac{1}{\tau}(x_{n+1} - x_n),</math>
</indent>

which leads to the equation for Allan variance in terms of time errors:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\sigma_y^2(\tau) = \frac{1}{2\tau^2} \langle(x_{n+2} - 2 x_{n+1} + x_n)^2\rangle.</math>
</indent>

Just as with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/27590.xml">
standard deviation</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/32344.xml">
variance</link>, the Allan deviation is defined as the square root of the Allan variance.</p>
<p>

Allan variance is used as a measure of frequency stability in a variety of exotic precision oscillators, such as frequency-stabilized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/17556.xml">
laser</link>s over a period of a second or more.  Short term stability (under a second) is typically expressed as phase noise.  The Allan variance is also used to characterize the bias stability of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/44125.xml">
gyroscopes</link>, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/1958422.xml">
fiber optic gyroscope</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/19638.xml">
MEMS</link> gyroscopes.  There are also a number of variants, notably the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/18692467.xml">
modified Allan variance</link>, the <link>
total variance</link>, the <link>
moving Allan Variance</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18693501.xml">
Hadamard variance</link>, the modified Hadamard Variance, the Picinbono Variance, the Sigma-Z Variance, and others. All these variances and their variants can be categorized into the same form of stability variances, mainly, as mean-square averages of the output of a finite-difference filter acting, not on the phase or frequency samples, but on their cummulative sums.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Development </st>

<p>

The current review process by the IEEE for standard definitions of physical quantities for fundamental frequency and time metrology (Std 1139) has been going on for a long time. This standard covers the fundamental metrology for describing random instabilities of importance to frequency and time metrology. The primary mathematical method of analysis in Std 1139 is the two-sample variance also called the Allan variance. By “two-sample” variance the IEEE really means variance based on Finite Difference (FD), a method used in numerical solutions of differential equations. The need for FD methodology in precision oscillators stems from the facts that: a) the standard sample variance and its square root (standard deviation) commonly used and often associated with normal distributions diverges numerically for typical types of random noise affecting precision oscillators; and b) the instantaneous Frequency (limit of F as sample-interval goes to zero) is a physical impossibility to measure. These typical random noise types are obviously not normally distributed and generally follow an approximated Power Law type of distribution.</p>
<p>

However, modern statistics have given analyst in the trade the tools to develop alternate analytical techniques based solely in statistical theory, mainly, distribution theory (generalized functions). With the advent of regression distributions and stochastic analysis, analysts now have the potential to derive second-moments (variance) from corresponding moment-generating functions then use the consequent confidence interval to provide complete solutions to instability risks. This is a developmental quantum-leap in analysis from ad-hoc applications of multidisciplinary branches of mathematics to the application of pure statistics for the analysis of non-deterministic (random) instabilities.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/32344.xml">
Variance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/1802050.xml">
Variogram</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/65637.xml">
Metrology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/159886.xml">
Network time protocol</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/2142269.xml">
Precision Time Protocol</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/28738.xml">
Synchronization</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

1. "Uncertainty of Stability Variances Based on Finite Differences", C.A.Greenhall JPL-Caltech, W.J.Riley Symmetricon, Inc. 11-19-2003.</p>
<p>

2. "IEEE Standard Definitions of Physical Quantities for Fundamental Frequency and Time Metrology - Random Instabilities", IEEE STD 1139.</p>
<p>

3. Stochastic Calculus and Theory of Distributions, "Lecture Notes on Complex Analysis", Dr Ivan F Wilde, published by Imperial College Press.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.allanstime.com/AllanVariance/">
David W. Allan's Allan Variance Overview</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.allanstime.com">
David W. Allan's official web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wriley.com/">
Home page of Stable32</weblink>, a very popular clock stability analysis program, which includes many useful papers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.leapsecond.com/museum/manyadev.gif">
Allan deviation plots for a variety of high-quality oscillators.</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
