<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:00:11[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Walkthrough</title>
<id>413775</id>
<revision>
<id>243175327</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T13:27:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Architectural communication</category>
<category>Video game culture</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>walkthrough</b> is a term describing the consideration of a process at an abstract level. <p>

The term is often employed in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> industry (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/4931559.xml">
software walkthrough</link>) to describe the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/467886.xml">
process of inspecting</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/27661.xml">
source code</link> by following paths through the algorithms or code as determined by input conditions and choices made along the way. The purpose of such <it>code walkthroughs</it> is generally to provide assurance of the fitness for purpose of the algorithm or code; and occasionally to assess the competence or output of an individual or team. </p>
<p>

The term is employed in the theatrical and entertainment industry to describe a rehearsal where the major issues of choreography and interaction are practiced and resolved, prior to more formal "dress rehearsals".</p>
<p>

The term is often used in the world of learning where a tutor/trainer will walk through the process for the first time. It is regarded as a literal walk through of the learning at the groups pace ensuring that everyone takes in the new knowledge and skills.</p>
<p>

Something akin to walkthroughs are used in very many forms of human endeavour since the process is a thought experiment that seeks to determine the likely outcome(s) of an affair based on starting conditions and the effects of decisions taken.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Various usages</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Video games</st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/5363.xml">
video games</link>, a <b>walkthrough</b> is a document which attempts to teach a player how to beat or solve a particular game. Many people consider walkthroughs to be a form of cheating, but no game is suited to be a fair challenge to everyone. Walkthroughs are often made by amateurs after they have completed the game and date from the earliest <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/14789.xml">
text adventure</link>s and the simplest <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/14750902.xml">
graphic adventure</link> and puzzle-adventure games.  Now they are most common for complex games, such as <genre wordnetid="105845332" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/356777.xml">
role playing game</link></kind>
</psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</genre>
s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/53680.xml">
strategy game</link>s; less involved games usually have a <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<encyclopedia wordnetid="106427387" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<reference_book wordnetid="106417598" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/10916.xml">
FAQ</link></publication>
</reference_book>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</encyclopedia>
</product>
</work>
 instead.  </p>
<p>

A classic variation on the straightforward walkthrough is "progressive hints."  This type of walkthrough provides a series of hints, increasingly explicit, to try to guide the player to a solution without making it too obvious right away.  The player usually has control over how many of the progressively explicit hints will be revealed.  A notable implementation of progressive hints is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/7152284.xml">
Universal Hint System</link>, which defines formats for hint files so that client software can allow the player to control which hints are revealed.  A non-software implementation is the "red filter obfuscator", as described in US Patent 6833829, where the hints are printed under an obfuscating mess of red squiggles.  Placing a red <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/275636.xml">
color gel</link> over the printout reveals the text.</p>
<p>

Walkthroughs are typically organized according to the levels or stages of the game, they frequently contain the author's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/1884.xml">
ASCII art</link> of the game title or logo at the beginning, and are usually available for free on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>, as opposed to the more involved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/1068218.xml">
strategy guide</link>s, which are professionally printed with many graphics.  On the internet, one should also search for "solutions" as a synonym for the more puzzle-type games.  <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/8498138.xml">
GameFAQs</link></web_site>
 is one of the most popular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link>s for walkthroughs.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Auditing</st>

<p>

In an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/224700.xml">
audit</link>, a walkthrough is the act of reviewing a process or activity in scope. The purpose is to confirm if a documented process in use and is accurately reflecting current workflow. The walkthrough may also be used to test the accuracy of current or previously used control activities.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Architecture</st>

<p>

An architectural walkthrough utilises computer software to provide a virtual tour of a building or structure prior to its real life construction. The walkthrough is sometimes referred to as a flythrough; whilst the walkthrough is an important communication tool to demonstrate how the building will be seen by pedestrian users of a building, the software does not confine the viewer to this view point and permits the possibility of seeing the building from all angles. The first commercially viable walkthroughs became available during the 1980s when computing advances made affordable software available and the processing power of personal computers took such graphics out of the realms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/37153.xml">
super computer</link>s</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Video Walkthroughs</st>
<p>

The user shows how to beat the game using videos. These kind of walkthroughs are common at sites like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/3524766.xml">
Youtube</link> and are made with the help of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/18943937.xml">
emulators</link>, video recorders, etc. Some video walkthroughs have a name, Which is Let's Play. They can mainly be found at Youtube. There are lots of games that have been/are being Let's Played. Some of the games include Earthbound, Super Mario World 2 - Wario World 1, various SMW hacks, Yoshi Island, Cave Story, and others.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Theatre</st>

<p>

The term is employed in the theatrical and entertainment industry to describe a rehearsal where the major issues of choreography and interaction are practiced and resolved, prior to more formal "dress rehearsals". Performers will walk through their entrances and exits  on stage (rather than in character or in performance mode) and clarify any issues they might have (e.g. unknown cues to be resolved, places to stand or sit).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wikibooks-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wikibooks
</caption>
</image>

Wikibooks'  has more about this subject:
</p>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/1356771.xml">
List of gaming topics</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://faqs.ign.com">
IGN FAQs</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gamefaqs.com">
GameFAQs</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/EddiesGames">
Eddie's Channel with Video Games Video Walkthroughs!</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eddiesgames.com/">
Eddie's Personal Site. Full lists of video games video walkthroughs!</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
