<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:52:17[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Topsite (www)</title>
<id>4143099</id>
<revision>
<id>209200161</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-30T10:24:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Chris19910</username>
<id>6770994</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Websites</category>
<category>Website stubs</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<sec>
<st>
Topsites</st>
<p>

<b>Topsites</b> are sites with a ranked listing of different websites, generally related by an overall subject.  In many cases a topsite is a directory of related web sites which ranks the listed sites by popularity.  Topsite rankings are user generated, usually through voting by visitors (clicks in to the topsite) from member sites or by counting pageviews.  Most topsites have an anti-cheat protection system and some display traffic statistics, user ratings, and reviews.</p>
<p>

Topsites often list a top 50 or top 100 most popular sites with a similar topic.  They can be a significant source of free targeted traffic for member sites if that topsite becomes popular.  After 
several early <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link>s failed, some people thought topsites might replace them.</p>
<p>

Site ranking method is decided by the topsite owner, with votes compiled in a variety of ways. Many topsites have a limit of 1 vote per person within 24 hours.  A vote is usually cast by a click of a button graphic or logo. Rankings can be determined by several methods, including: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Unique incoming votes from users on participating member sites, to the topsite itself.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Outgoing votes from a topsite's visitors, to websites who are participating as a member.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The number of times a logo, button or banner gets downloaded from the topsite web server.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 A combination of above statistics.  Votes are often reset to zero each day, week or month.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Besides free incoming traffic, approved members of a topsite can usually display a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/34044.xml">
web banner</link> ad and site description. Many topsites allow a random choice of participating sites to be featured at the top of each page with a description and banner ad.  The 88x31 button has become the standard vote button size in topsite culture.  The advantage here is the topsite will show the member's larger standard-size banner (468x60) in return for the member displaying their smaller vote button.  This allows members to join several topsites without cluttering their page with large banner ads, while maximizing their exposure on each topsite.</p>
<p>

Topsites vary widely in both subject matter and quality. Some topsites are run on auto-pilot, with any site allowed to join automatically (which will lead to spam problems). Others have a strict requirement as to which websites are allowed to join. Often, only websites sharing the same topical theme or geographical area of the topsite itself are invited to join. Unless well maintained by the list owner, topsites quickly suffer from link rot and, as a result, become unreliable for typical visitors.  Seeing many broken images can be an indicator of low quality.</p>
<p>

Recently, numerous chat websites in Europe have been trying to join multiple topsites as a way to quickly get more incoming links and boost their site popularity for search engine rankings.  Ignoring a topsite's theme or requirements to sign up unrelated websites is considered spam.</p>
<p>

Topsites should be considered a valuable resource in niche web marketing, typically they have all the benefits of a directory but have the advantage of a dynamic, user powered ranking system which encourages a steady flow of traffic to related sites.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/3050839.xml">
Topsite Templating System</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
 TTS</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/793436.xml">
Topsite (warez)</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Controversies </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dynamoo.com/diary/topsites_topsitez_us.htm">
Biggest spammers Topsites.us exposed</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
