<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:03:05[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Knowledge integration</title>
<id>4144848</id>
<revision>
<id>243570297</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T02:06:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>タチコマ robot</username>
<id>421426</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Learning</category>
<category>Machine learning</category>
<category>Knowledge representation</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Knowledge integration</b> is the process of synthesizing multiple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/16920.xml">
knowledge model</link>s (or representations) into a common model (representation).<p>

Compared to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/2714749.xml">
information integration</link>, which involves merging information having different schemas and representation models, knowledge integration focuses more on synthesizing the understanding of a given subject from different perspectives.</p>
<p>

For example, multiple interpretations are possible of a set of student grades, typically each from a certain perspective. An overall, integrated view and understanding of this information can be achieved if these interpretations can be put under a common model, say, a student performance index.</p>
<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wise.berkeley.edu">
Web-based Inquiry Science Environment (WISE)</weblink>, from the University of California at Berkeley has been developed along the lines of knowledge integration theory.</p>

<p>

<b>Knowledge integration</b> has also been studied as the process of incorporating new information into a body of existing knowledge.  This process involves determining how the new information and the existing knowledge interact, how existing knowledge should be modified to accommodate the new information, and how the new information should be modified in light of the existing knowledge.</p>
<p>

A learning agent that actively investigates the consequences of new information can detect and exploit a variety of learning opportunities; e.g., to resolve knowledge conflicts and to fill knowledge gaps.  By exploiting these learning opportunities the learning agent is able to learn beyond the explicit content of the new information.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link> program KI, developed by Murray and Porter at the University of Texas at Austin, was created to study the use of automated and semi-automated knowledge integration to assist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/1904337.xml">
knowledge engineers</link> constructing a large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/239497.xml">
knowledge base</link>.</p>
<p>

The University of Waterloo operates a Bachelor of Knowledge Integration undergraduate degree program. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Linn, M. C. (2006) The Knowledge Integration Perspective on Learning and Instruction. R. Sawyer (Ed.). In <it>The Cambridge Handbook of the Learning Sciences.</it> Cambridge, MA. Cambridge University Press</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Murray, K. S. (1996) KI: A tool for Knowledge Integration. Proceedings of the Thirteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Murray, K. S. (1995) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ai.sri.com/pubs/files/1636.pdf">
Learning as Knowledge Integration</weblink>, Technical Report TR-95-41, The University of Texas at Austin</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Murray, K. S. (1990) Improving Explanatory Competence, Proceedings of the Twelfth Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Murray, K. S., Porter, B. W. (1990) Developing a Tool for Knowledge Integration: Initial Results. International Journal for Man-Machine Studies, volume 33</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Murray, K. S., Porter, B. W. (1989) Controlling Search for the Consequences of New Information during Knowledge Integration. Proceedings of the Sixth International Machine Learning Conference</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
