<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:03:16[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Demispan</title>
<id>4148967</id>
<revision>
<id>230745392</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-09T03:49:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dwaipayanc</username>
<id>200216</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Human anatomy</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Demispan</b> is the distance, in a human subject, from a point on the midline at their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/3080436.xml">
suprasternal notch</link> to the web between their middle and ring fingers along either horizontally outstretched arm and with their wrist in neutral rotation and zero extension or flexion.<p>

Measurement of the demispan is an alternative to patient standing height when measuring patient skeletal frame size for the purposes of nutritional or other growth assessment. It can be undertaken while the patient remains seated and thus is especially useful if they are unable to stand. It is also a more accurate measure of skeletal frame size in the elderly where standing height may be shortened by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/508173.xml">
kyphosis</link> and/or vertebral collapse.</p>
<p>

Demispan should be measured with a stainless steel (non-stretchable) tape.</p>
<p>

An estimate of patient height can be computed from their demispan measurement: </p>
<p>

Female height in cm = (1.35 x demispan in cm) + 60.1</p>
<p>

Male height in cm = (1.40 x demispan in cm) + 57.8</p>
<p>

This in turn allows computation of an estimated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/4788.xml">
Body Mass Index</link> (BMI) using the normal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>. Alternatively, instead of a BMI, a Demiquet Index can be computed directly from the demispan:</p>
<p>

Demiquet = weight (in kg) divided by the square of the demispan (in cm)</p>
<p>

The demiquet index is a more reliable measure of nutritional status than a BMI estimation in the elderly, for the reasons given above.</p>

<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/1480170.xml">
Ape index</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

This article or section does not cite its <b>.</b> You can  Wikipedia by introducing appropriate citations.</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
