<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:41:21[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<information  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106634376">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<property  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104916342">
<manner  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104928903">
<format  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106636806">
<header>
<title>Pulse-code modulation</title>
<id>41604</id>
<revision>
<id>243056313</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-04T23:14:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Radagast83</username>
<id>668752</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Digital audio recording</category>
<category>Audio codecs</category>
<category>Multiplexing</category>
<category>Radio modulation modes</category>
<category>Computer file formats</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

"PCM" redirects here. For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/23262.xml">
PCM (disambiguation)</link>.<p>

<b>Pulse-code <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/20637.xml">
modulation</link></b> (<b>PCM</b>) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/8276.xml">
digital</link> representation of an analog <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/41703.xml">
signal</link> where the magnitude of the signal is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/201605.xml">
sampled</link> regularly at uniform intervals, then <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/317018.xml">
quantized</link> to a series of symbols in a numeric (usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/238686.xml">
binary</link>) code. PCM has been used in digital <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/30003.xml">
telephone</link> systems and 1980s-era <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/320138.xml">
electronic musical keyboards</link>. It is also the standard form for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/53712.xml">
digital audio</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link>s and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/6429.xml">
compact disc</link> <medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/41920.xml">
"red book"</link></medium>
 format. It is also standard in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/8733.xml">
digital video</link>, for example, using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/15210.xml">
ITU-R</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/198207.xml">
BT.601</link>. However, straight PCM is not typically used for video in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/27767.xml">
standard definition</link> consumer applications such as <medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/11014498.xml">
DVD</link></medium>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/348300.xml">
DVR</link> because the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/272290.xml">
bit rate</link> required is far too high. 
</p>
<sec>
<st>
 Modulation </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Pcm.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Sampling and quantization of a signal (red) for 4-bit PCM
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

In the diagram, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/324749.xml">
sine wave</link> (red curve) is sampled and quantized for <b>PCM</b>. The sine wave is sampled at regular intervals, shown as ticks on the x-axis. For each sample, one of the available values (ticks on the y-axis) is chosen by some algorithm (in this case, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/54267.xml">
floor function</link> is used). This produces a fully discrete representation of the input signal (shaded area) that can be easily encoded as digital data for storage or manipulation. For the sine wave example at right, we can verify that the quantized values at the sampling moments are 7, 9, 11, 12, 13, 14, 14, 15, 15, 15, 14, etc. Encoding these values as <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/238686.xml">
binary numbers</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 would result in the following set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/21150.xml">
nibble</link>s: 0111, 1001, 1011, 1100, 1101, 1110, 1110, 1111, 1111, 1111, 1110, etc. These digital values could then be further processed or analyzed by a purpose-specific <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../TN$$/HT$C$_T$yT$N$.xml">
digital signal processor</link> or general purpose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/5218.xml">
CPU</link>. Several Pulse Code Modulation streams could also be <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/41389.xml">
multiplexed</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 into a larger aggregate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/47868.xml">
data stream</link>, generally for transmission of multiple streams over a single physical link. This technique is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/41796.xml">
time-division multiplexing</link>, or TDM, and is widely used, notably in the modern public telephone system.</p>
<p>

There are many ways to implement a real device that performs this task. In real systems, such a device is commonly implemented on a single <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/15150.xml">
integrated circuit</link> that lacks only the clock necessary for sampling, and is generally referred to as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/40367.xml">
ADC</link> (Analog-to-Digital converter). These devices will produce on their output a binary representation of the input whenever they are triggered by a clock signal, which would then be read by a processor of some sort.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Demodulation </st>

<p>

To produce output from the sampled data, the procedure of modulation is applied in reverse. After each sampling period has passed, the next value is read and the output of the system is shifted instantaneously (in an idealized system) to the new value. As a result of these instantaneous transitions, the discrete signal will have a significant amount of inherent high frequency energy, mostly harmonics of the sampling frequency (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/314652.xml">
square wave</link>). To smooth out the signal and remove these undesirable harmonics, the signal would be passed through analog filters that suppress artifacts outside the expected frequency range (<it>i.e.,</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/164685.xml">
greater than</link> <math>\frac{1}{2} f_s </math>, the maximum resolvable frequency). Some systems use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/41033.xml">
digital filter</link>ing to remove the lowest and largest harmonics.  In some systems, no explicit filtering is done at all; as it's impossible for any system to reproduce a signal with infinite bandwidth, inherent losses in the system compensate for the artifacts — or the system simply does not require much precision. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/37864.xml">
sampling theorem</link> suggests that practical PCM devices, provided a sampling frequency that is sufficiently greater than that of the input signal, can operate without introducing significant distortions within their designed frequency bands.</p>
<p>

The electronics involved in producing an accurate analog signal from the discrete data are similar to those used for generating the digital signal. These devices are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/92943.xml">
DACs</link> (digital-to-analog converters), and operate similarly to ADCs. They produce on their output a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/32549.xml">
voltage</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/6207.xml">
current</link> (depending on type) that represents the value presented on their inputs. This output would then generally be filtered and amplified for use.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Limitations </st>

<p>

There are two sources of impairment implicit in any PCM system:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Choosing a discrete value near the analog signal for each sample (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/2390668.xml">
quantization error</link>)</entry>
</list>

The quantization error swings between <math>-\frac{q}{2}</math> to <math>\frac{q}{2}</math>. In the ideal case (with a fully linear ADC) it is equally distributed over this interval thus with <math>\rho(x) = \frac{1}{q}</math> follows <math> \text{mean} = \int_{-q/2}^{q/2} x\rho(x)\, dx </math> equals zero while the <math> \text{variance} = \int_{-q/2}^{q/2} (x-\text{mean})^2 \rho(x)\, dx </math> equals to <math>\frac{q^2}{12}.</math>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Between samples no measurement of the signal is made; due to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/37864.xml">
sampling theorem</link> this results in any frequency above or equal to <math>\frac{1}{2} f_s </math> (<it>fs</it> being the sampling frequency) being distorted or lost completely (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/151474.xml">
aliasing</link> error).  This is also called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/164685.xml">
Nyquist frequency</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

As samples are dependent on <it>time</it>, an accurate clock is required for accurate reproduction. If either the encoding or decoding clock is not stable, its frequency drift will directly affect the output quality of the device. A slight difference between the encoding and decoding clock frequencies is not generally a major concern; a small constant error is not noticeable. Clock error does become a major issue if the clock is not stable, however. A drifting clock, even with a relatively small error, will cause very obvious distortions in audio and video signals, for example.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Digitization as part of the PCM process </st>

<p>

In conventional PCM, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/993.xml">
analog signal</link> may be processed (e.g. by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/262733.xml">
amplitude compression</link>) before being digitized. Once the signal is digitized, the PCM signal is usually subjected to further processing (e.g. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/8276.xml">
digital</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/8013.xml">
data compression</link>).</p>
<p>

Some forms of PCM combine signal processing with coding. Older versions of these systems applied the processing in the analog domain as part of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/40367.xml">
A/D</link> process, newer implementations do so in the digital domain. These simple techniques have been largely rendered obsolete by modern transform-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/18950025.xml">
audio compression</link> techniques.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Differential</b> (or <b>Delta</b>) <b>pulse-code modulation</b> (<b>DPCM</b>) encodes the PCM values as differences between the current and the predicted value. An algorithm predicts the next sample based on the previous samples, and the encoder stores only the difference between this prediction and the actual value. If the prediction is reasonable, fewer bits can be used to represent the same information. For audio, this type of encoding reduces the number of bits required per sample by about 25% compared to PCM.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Adaptive DPCM</b> (ADPCM) is a variant of DPCM that varies the size of the quantization step, to allow further reduction of the required bandwidth for a given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/41706.xml">
signal-to-noise ratio</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/41015.xml">
Delta modulation</link>, another variant, uses one bit per sample.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In telephony, a standard audio signal for a single phone call is encoded as 8000 analog samples per second, of 8 bits each, giving a 64 kbit/s digital signal known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/41037.xml">
DS0</link>.  The default <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/41702.xml">
signal compression</link> encoding on a DS0 is either <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/41382.xml">
&amp;mu;-law (mu-law)</link> PCM (North America and Japan) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/40707.xml">
a-law</link> PCM (Europe and most of the rest of the world).  These are logarithmic compression systems where a 12 or 13 bit linear PCM sample number is mapped into an 8 bit value.  This system is described by international standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/104113.xml">
G.711</link>.  An alternative proposal for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/11376.xml">
floating point</link> representation, with 5 bit mantissa and 3 bit radix, was abandoned.</p>
<p>

Where circuit costs are high and loss of voice quality is acceptable, it sometimes makes sense to compress the voice signal even further.  An ADPCM algorithm is used to map a series of 8 bit µ-law (or a-law) PCM samples into a series of 4 bit ADPCM samples.  In this way, the capacity of the line is doubled.  The technique is detailed in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/1079634.xml">
G.726</link> standard.</p>
<p>

Later it was found that even further compression was possible and additional standards were published. Some of these international standards describe systems and ideas which are covered by privately owned patents and thus use of these standards requires payments to the patent holders.</p>
<p>

Some ADPCM techniques are used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
Voice over IP</link> communications.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Encoding for transmission </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/41317.xml">
Line code</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
</it>
</indent>

Pulse-code modulation can be either <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/334418.xml">
return-to-zero</link> (RZ) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/41425.xml">
non-return-to-zero</link> (NRZ). For a NRZ system to be synchronized using in-band information, there must not be long sequences of identical symbols, such as ones or zeroes. For binary PCM systems, the density of 1-symbols is called <it>ones-density</it>.</p>
<p>

Ones-density is often controlled using precoding techniques such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/449077.xml">
Run Length Limited</link> encoding, where the PCM code is expanded into a slightly longer code with a guaranteed bound on ones-density before modulation into the channel. In other cases, extra <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/1437110.xml">
framing</link> bits are added into the stream which guarantee at least occasional symbol transitions.</p>
<p>

Another technique used to control ones-density is the use of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/41680.xml">
scrambler</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/23000.xml">
polynomial</link> on the raw data which will tend to turn the raw data stream into a stream that looks <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/23210.xml">
pseudo-random</link>, but where the raw stream can be recovered exactly by reversing the effect of the polynomial. In this case, long runs of zeroes or ones are still possible on the output, but are considered unlikely enough to be within normal engineering tolerance.</p>
<p>

In other cases, the long term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/47713.xml">
DC</link> value of the modulated signal is important, as building up a DC offset will tend to bias detector circuits out of their operating range. In this case special measures are taken to keep a count of the cumulative DC offset, and to modify the codes if necessary to make the DC offset always tend back to zero.</p>
<p>

Many of these codes are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/1431410.xml">
bipolar code</link>s, where the pulses can be positive, negative or absent. In the typical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/1431410.xml">
alternate mark inversion</link> code, non-zero pulses alternate between being positive and negative. These rules may be violated to generate special symbols used for framing or other special purposes.</p>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/41779.xml">
T-carrier</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History</st>
<p>

In the history of electrical communications, the earliest reason for sampling a signal was to interlace samples from different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/30010.xml">
telegraphy</link> sources, and convey them over a single telegraph cable. Telegraph <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/41796.xml">
time-division multiplexing</link> (TDM) was conveyed as early as 1853, by the American inventor M.B. Farmer. The electrical engineer W.M. Miner, in 1903, used an electro-mechanical commutator for time-division multiplex of multiple telegraph signals, and also applied this technology to telephony. He obtained intelligible speech from channels sampled at a rate above 3500–4300 Hz: below this was unsatisfactory.  This was TDM, but <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/51630.xml">
pulse-amplitude modulation</link> (PAM) rather than PCM.</p>
<p>

Paul M. Rainey of Western Electric in 1926 patented a facsimile machine using an optical mechanical analog to digital converter.  The machine did not go into production.  British engineer <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<commanding_officer wordnetid="109941964" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/14669400.xml">
Alec Reeves</link></military_officer>
</commanding_officer>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</engineer>
</worker>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
, unaware of previous work, conceived the use of PCM for voice communication in 1937 while working for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/66044.xml">
International Telephone and Telegraph</link> in France.  He described the theory and advantages, but no practical use resulted.  Reeves filed for a French patent in 1938, and his U.S. patent was granted in 1943.</p>
<p>

The first transmission of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/2917649.xml">
speech</link> by digital techniques was the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/740918.xml">
SIGSALY</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/32678.xml">
vocoder</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> equipment used for high-level Allied communications during <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
World War II</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
 from 1943. In 1943, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/3712.xml">
Bell Labs</link> researchers who designed the SIGSALY system, became aware of the use of PCM binary coding as already proposed by Alec Reeves. In 1949 for the Canadian Navy's <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/2583375.xml">
DATAR</link></computer>
 system, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/1974230.xml">
Ferranti</link></institution>
</company>
 Canada built a working PCM radio system that was able to transmit digitized radar data over long distances<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>
<p>

PCM in the 1950s used a cathode-ray coding tube with a grid having encoding perforations.  As in an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/15361791.xml">
oscilloscope</link>, the beam was swept horizontally at the sample rate while the vertical deflection was controlled by the input analog signal, causing the beam to pass through higher or lower portions of the perforated grid.  The grid interrupted the beam, producing current variations in binary code.  Rather than natural binary, the grid was perforated to produce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/50564.xml">
Gray code</link> lest a sweep along a transition zone produce glitches.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Nomenclature </st>

<p>

The word <it>pulse</it> in the term <it>Pulse-Code Modulation</it> refers to the "pulses" to be found in the transmission line. This perhaps is a natural consequence of this technique having evolved alongside two analog methods, <link>
pulse width modulation</link> and <link>
pulse position modulation</link>, in which the information to be encoded is in fact represented by discrete signal pulses of varying width or position, respectively. In this respect, PCM bears little resemblance to these other forms of signal encoding, except that all can be used in time division multiplexing, and the binary numbers of the PCM codes are represented as electrical pulses.  The device that performs the coding and decoding function in a telephone circuit is called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/6660.xml">
codec</link>.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/41116.xml">
Equivalent pulse code modulation noise</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/104113.xml">
G.711</link> – ITU-T standard for audio companding. It is primarily used in telephony.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/1499949.xml">
Linear Pulse Code Modulation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Nyquist–Shannon sampling theorem</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/81242.xml">
Pulse-width modulation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/317018.xml">
Quantization (signal processing)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/201605.xml">
Sampling (signal processing)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <magnitude_relation wordnetid="113815152" confidence="0.8">
<ratio wordnetid="113819207" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/3321592.xml">
SQNR</link></ratio>
</magnitude_relation>
 – One method of measuring quantization error.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Porter, Arthur. So Many Hills to Climb (2004) Beckham Publications Group</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal"><physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<inventor wordnetid="110214637" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/8320798.xml">
Franklin S. Cooper</link></creator>
</inventor>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
; Ignatius Mattingly&#32;(1969).&#32;"Computer-controlled PCM system for investigation of dichotic speech perception". <it>Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</it>&#32;<b>46</b>: 115. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1121%2F1.1972688">
10.1121/1.1972688</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Ken C. Pohlmann&#32;(1985). Principles of Digital Audio, 2nd ed.,&#32;Carmel, Indiana:&#32;Sams/Prentice-Hall Computer Publishing. ISBN 0-672-22634-0.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal"><physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<linguist wordnetid="110264437" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/8226222.xml">
D. H. Whalen</link></linguist>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, E. R. Wiley, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<linguist wordnetid="110264437" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/7202211.xml">
Philip E. Rubin</link></linguist>
</psychologist>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<inventor wordnetid="110214637" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/8320798.xml">
Franklin S. Cooper</link></creator>
</inventor>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
&#32;(1990).&#32;"The <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/6202324.xml">
Haskins Laboratories</link></association>
</institute>
 pulse code modulation (PCM) system". <it>Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, and Computers</it>&#32;<b>22</b>: 550–559.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Bill Waggener&#32;(1995). Pulse Code Modulation Techniques, 1st ed.,&#32;New York, NY:&#32;Van Nostrand Reinhold. ISBN 0-442-01436-8.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sajad Ahmad&#32;(1999). Pulse Code Modulation Systems Design, 1st ed.,&#32;Boston, MA:&#32;Artech House. ISBN 0-89006-776-7.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ralph-miller.org/">
Ralph Miller</weblink> and Bob Badgley invented multi-level PCM independently in their work at Bell Labs on <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/740918.xml">
SIGSALY</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?patentnumber=3912868">
U.S. Patent 3,912,868</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pat2pdf.org/pat2pdf/foo.pl?number=3912868">
&nbsp;</weblink>: N-ary Pulse Code Modulation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 According to the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<depository wordnetid="103177349" confidence="0.8">
<museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/69488.xml">
National Inventors Hall of Fame</link></museum>
</depository>
</facility>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
,  B.M Oliver and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/5693.xml">
Claude Shannon</link></scientist>
 are the inventors of PCM as described in 'Communication System Employing Pulse Code Modulation,' <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?patentnumber=2801281">
U.S. Patent 2,801,281</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pat2pdf.org/pat2pdf/foo.pl?number=2801281">
&nbsp;</weblink> filed in 1946 and 1952, granted in 1956.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/fdd/fdd000016.shtml">
Information about PCM</weblink>: A description of PCM with links to information about subtypes of this format (for example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/1499949.xml">
Linear Pulse Code Modulation</link>), and references to their specifications.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</format>
</manner>
</property>
</entity>
</information>
</message>
</article>
