<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 20:57:43[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Human-based computation</title>
<id>4253446</id>
<revision>
<id>244601914</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T17:26:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dogbreathcanada</username>
<id>540256</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Human-based computation</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link>, <b>human-based computation</b> is a technique when a computational process performs its function via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/235890.xml">
outsourcing</link> certain steps to humans (Kosorukoff, 2001). This approach leverages differences in abilities and alternative costs between humans and computer agents to achieve symbiotic human-computer interaction.<p>

In traditional computation, a human employs a computer to solve a problem: a human provides a formalized problem description to a computer, and receives a solution to interpret. In human-based computation, the roles are often reversed: the computer asks a person or a large number of people to solve a problem, then collects, interprets, and integrates their solutions.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Early work</st>

<p>

Human-based computation research has its origins in the early work on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/901162.xml">
interactive evolutionary computation</link>. The idea behind interactive evolutionary algorithms is due to <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/25867.xml">
Richard Dawkins</link></scientist>
</person>
. In the Biomorphs software accompanying his book <it><book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/66991.xml">
The Blind Watchmaker</link></book>
</it> (Dawkins, 1986) the preference of a human experimenter is used to guide the evolution of two-dimensional sets of line segments. In essence, this program asks a human to be the fitness function of an evolutionary algorithm, so that the algorithm can use human visual perception and aesthetic judgment to do something that a normal evolutionary algorithm cannot do. However, it is difficult to  get enough evaluations from a single human if we want to evolve more complex shapes. Victor Johnston and Karl Sims extended this concept by harnessing power of many people for fitness evaluation (Caldwell and Johnston, 1991; Sims, 1991). As a result, their programs could evolve beautiful faces and pieces of art appealing to public. These programs effectively reversed the common interaction between computers and humans. In these programs, the computer is no longer an agent of its user, but instead, a coordinator aggregating efforts of many human evaluators. These and other similar research efforts became the topic of research in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/901162.xml">
interactive evolutionary computation</link> or aestetic selection, however the scope of this research was limited to outsourcing evaluation and, as a result, it was not fully exploring the full potential of the outsourcing.</p>
<p>

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/901149.xml">
Human-based genetic algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 (HBGA) encourages human participation in multiple different roles. Humans are not limited to the role of evaluator, but can choose to perform a more diverse set of functions. In particular, they can contribute their innovative solutions into the evolutionary process, make incremental changes to existing  solutions, and perform intelligent recombination. In short, HBGA outsources to humans all operations of a typical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
genetic algorithm</link>. As a result of this outsourcing, HBGA can process the representations for which there is no computational innovation operators available, for example, natural languages. Thus, HBGA obviated the need for a fixed representational scheme that was a limiting factor of both standard and interactive EC. These algorithms can be also be viewed as novel forms of social organization coordinated by a computer program (Kosorukoff and Goldberg, 2002).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Classes of human-based computation</st>

<p>

Human-based computation methods combine computers and humans in different roles. Kosorukoff (2000) proposed a way to describe division of labor in computation, that groups human-based methods into three classes. The following table uses the evolutionary computation model to describe four classes of computation, three of which rely on humans in some role. For each class, a representative example is shown. The classification is in terms of the roles (innovation or selection) performed in each case by humans and computational processes. This table is a slice of three-dimensional table. The third dimension defines if the organizational function is performed by humans or a computer. Here it is assumed to be performed by a computer.</p>


<p>

<table cellpadding="0" border="1" cellspacing="0" bgcolor="white">
<row>
<col>
<table width="640" cellpadding="5" border="0" cellspacing="1" bgcolor="lightblue">
<row>
<header colspan="4">
Division of labor in computation</header>
</row>
<row bgcolor="#E0E0FF">
<header bgcolor="white">
Selection agentInnovation agent</header>
<header>
Computer</header>
<header>
Human</header>
</row>
<row>
<header bgcolor="#FFE0E0">
Computer</header>
<header>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
Genetic Algorithm</link></header>
<header>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/901162.xml">
Interactive genetic algorithm</link></header>
</row>
<row>
<header bgcolor="#FFE0E0">
Human</header>
<header>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/1743830.xml">
Computerized Tests</link></header>
<header>
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/901149.xml">
Human-based genetic algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</header>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<p>

Classes of human-based computation from this table can be referred by two-letter abbreviations: HC, CH, HH. Here the first letter identifies the type of agents performing innovation, the second letter specifies the type of selection agents. In some implementations (wiki is the most common example), human-based selection functionality might be limited, it can be shown with small h.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods of human-based computation</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (HC) <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/2540811.xml">
Darwin</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
 (Vyssotsky, Morris, McIlroy, 1961) and <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/274362.xml">
Core War</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
 (Jones, Dewdney 1984) These are games where several programs written by people compete in a tournament (computational simulation) in which fittest programs will survive. Authors of the programs copy, modify, and recombine successful strategies to improve their chances of winning.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (CH) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/901162.xml">
Interactive EC</link> (Caldwell and Johnston, 1991; Sims, 1991) IEC enables the user to create an abstract drawing only by selecting his/her favorite images, so human only performs fitness computation and software performs innovative role. [Unemi 1998] Simulated breeding style introduces no explicit fitness, just selection, which is easier for humans.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (HH2) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/32851.xml">
Wiki</link> (Cunningham, 1995) enabled editing the web content by multiple users, i.e. supported two types of human-based innovation (contributing new page and its incremental edits). However, the selection mechanism was absent until 2002, when wiki has been augmented with a revision history allowing for reversing of unhelpful changes. This provided means for selection among several versions of the same page and turned wiki into a tool supporting collaborative content evolution (would be classified as human-based evolution strategy in EC terms).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (HH3) <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/901149.xml">
Human-based genetic algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 (Kosorukoff, 1998) uses both human-based selection and three types of human-based innovation (contributing new content, mutation, and recombination). Thus, all operators of a typical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
genetic algorithm</link> are outsourced to humans (hence the origin of <b>human-based</b>). Examples include the <market wordnetid="101097292" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../812/8926812.xml">
3form Free Knowledge Exchange</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</market>
 (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://3form.com">
website</weblink>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/15228284.xml">
Knowledge iN</link>, and <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/3385969.xml">
Yahoo! Answers</link></web_site>
, all of which implement some form of collaborative problem-solving.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (HH1) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/6843345.xml">
Social search</link> applications accept contributions from users and attempt to use human evaluation to select the fittest contributions that get to the top of the list. These use one type of human-based innovation. Early work was done in the context of HBGA. <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/11041618.xml">
Digg</link></web_site>
 and <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/3829005.xml">
Reddit</link></web_site>
 are recently popular examples.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (HC) Computerized tests. A computer generates a problem and presents it to evaluate a user. For example <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/230834.xml">
CAPTCHA</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/723435.xml">
reverse Turing test</link>, tells human users from computer programs by presenting a problem that is supposedly easy for a human and difficult for a computer (Suggested by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/10151043.xml">
Moni Naor</link></scientist>
, 1996). Unfortunately, the results obtained from humans are usually discarded. This makes it an example of wasting human computation.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (HC) Interactive online <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/12279.xml">
guessing game</link>s: These are programs that extract knowledge from people in an entertaining way (Burgener, 1999; von Ahn 2003).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Incentives to participation</st>

<p>

In different human-based computation projects people are motivated by one or more of the following.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Receiving a fair share of the result</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Direct monetary compensation (e.g. in Amazon's Mechanical turk, ChaCha Search guide)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Desire to diversify their activity (e.g. "people aren't asked in their daily lives to be creative" <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Esthetic satisfaction</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Curiosity, desire to test if it works</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Volunteerism, desire to support a cause of the project</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reciprocity, exchange, mutual help</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Competitive spirit of a game</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Desire to communicate and share knowledge</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Desire to share a user innovation to see if someone else can improve on it</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Desire to game the system and influence the final result</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Many projects had explored various combinations of these incentives. See more information about motivation of participants in these projects in Kosorukoff (2000) and 
von Hippel (2005).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Human-based computation as a form of social organization</st>

<p>

Viewed as a form of social organization, human-based computation often surprisingly turns out to be more robust and productive than traditional organizations (Kosorukoff and Goldberg, 2002). The latter depend on obligations to maintain their more or less fixed structure, be functional and stable. Each of them is similar to a carefully designed mechanism with humans as its parts. However, this limits the freedom of their human employees and subjects them to various kinds of stresses. Most people, unlike mechanical parts, find it difficult to adapt to some fixed roles that best fit the organization. Evolutionary human-computation projects offer a natural solution to this problem. They adapt organizational structure to human spontaneity, accommodate human mistakes and creativity, and utilize both in a constructive way. This leaves their participants free from obligations without endangering the functionality of the whole, making people happier. There are still some challenging research problems that need to be solved before we can realize the full potential of this idea.</p>
<p>

The algorithmic outsourcing techniques used in human-based computation are much more scalable than the manual or automated techniques used to manage outsourcing traditionally. It is this scalability that allows to easily distribute the effort among thousands of participants. It was suggested recently that this mass outsourcing is sufficiently different from traditional small-scale outsourcing to merit a new name <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/5292585.xml">
crowdsourcing</link> (Howe, 2006).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/2155752.xml">
Citizen science</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/646904.xml">
Collaborative intelligence</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/4985613.xml">
Collaborative Innovation Networks</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/3130340.xml">
Collaborative human interpreter</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <word wordnetid="106286395" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<neologism wordnetid="106294441" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/5292585.xml">
Crowdsourcing</link></language_unit>
</neologism>
</part>
</word>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/18689983.xml">
Game with a purpose</link> (or GWAP)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/12212921.xml">
Galaxy Zoo</link></web_site>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/3833695.xml">
Human computer</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</group>
</collection>
</class>
</event>
</occupation>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/14473878.xml">
Human Computer Information Retrieval</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<argument wordnetid="106648724" confidence="0.8">
<scientific_research wordnetid="100641820" confidence="0.8">
<subject wordnetid="106599788" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<research wordnetid="100636921" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="100639556" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/247365.xml">
Simulated reality</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</experiment>
</event>
</message>
</research>
</indication>
</evidence>
</subject>
</scientific_research>
</argument>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/222034.xml">
Social software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/1416993.xml">
Social computing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/1201650.xml">
Social organization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/47284.xml">
Symbiotic intelligence</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Dawkins, R. (1986), The Blind Watchmaker, Longman, 1986; Penguin Books 1988.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Caldwell, C. and Johnston V. S. (1991), Tracking a Criminal Suspect through "Face-Space" with a Genetic Algorithm, in Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on Genetic Algorithm, Morgan Kaufmann Publisher, pp.416-421, July 1991. (US Patent 5,375,195 filed 1992.06.29)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Sims, K. (1991) Artificial Evolution for Computer Graphics, Computer Graphics, 25(4) (SIGGRAPH'91), 319-328 (US Patent 6,088,510 filed 1992.07.02)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Herdy, M. (1996) Evolution strategies with subjective selection. In Parallel Problem Solving from Nature, PPSN IV, Volume 1141 of LNCS (pp. 22-31)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Moni Naor (1996) Verification of a human in the loop, or Identification via the Turing Test, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/~naor/PAPERS/human_abs.html">
online</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Unemi, T. (1998) A Design of multi-field user interface for simulated breeding, Proceedings of the Third Asian Fuzzy and Intelligent System Symposium, 489-494</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Kosorukoff (1998) Alex Kosorukoff, Free Knowledge Exchange, human-based genetic algorithm on the web <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/19991122225801/http://formula.virtualave.net/">
archive</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://3form.com/formula/about-us.html">
description</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Lillibridge et al (1998) Method for selectively restricting access to computer systems, US Patent <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?patentnumber=6195698">
U.S. Patent 6,195,698</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pat2pdf.org/pat2pdf/foo.pl?number=6195698">
&nbsp;</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Burgener (1999) Twenty questions: the neural-net on the Internet <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20000229091147/http://www.20q.net/index.html">
archive</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://20q.net">
website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Kosorukoff, A. (2000) Social classification structures. Optimal decision making in an organization, Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference, GECCO-2000, Late breaking papers, 175--178 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.3form.com/alex/pub/classtre.pdf">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Kosorukoff, A. (2000) Human-based genetic algorithm <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geocities.com/alex+kosorukoff/hbga/hbga.html">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/33161.xml">
Cunningham, Ward</link></programmer>
</person>
 and Leuf, Bo (2001): The Wiki Way. Quick Collaboration on the Web. Addison-Wesley, ISBN 0-201-71499-X.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Hideyuki Takagi (2001), Interactive Evolutionary Computation: Fusion of the Capabilities of EC Optimization and Human Evaluation, Proceedings of the IEEE, vol.89, no. 9, pp. 1275-1296</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Kosorukoff, A (2001), Human-based Genetic Algorithm. IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, SMC-2001, 3464-3469</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Kosorukoff, A. &amp; Goldberg, D. E. (2001) Genetic algorithms for social innovation and creativity (Illigal report No 2001005). Urbana, IL: University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.3form.com/alex/pub/2001005.pdf">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Kosorukoff, A, Goldberg D. E. (2002), Genetic algorithm as a form of organization, Proceedings of Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference, GECCO-2002, pp 965-972 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.3form.com/alex/pub/gecco-2002-18.pdf">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Fogarty, T.C., (2003), Automatic concept evolution, Proceedings of The Second IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Informatics. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 von Ahn, L et al (2003) CAPTCHA: Using Hard AI Problems for Security In Eurocrypt 2003</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 von Ahn, L (2003) Method for labeling images through a computer game <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://appft1.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsearch-adv.html&amp;r=1&amp;p=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;d=PG01&amp;S1=%28%22von+Ahn%22.IN.%29&amp;OS=IN/%22von+Ahn%22&amp;RS=IN/%22von+Ahn%22">
US Patent Application 10/875913</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 von Ahn, L, Dabbish, L (2004) Labeling Images with a Computer Game In ACM CHI 2004 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~biglou/ESP.pdf">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Fogarty, T.C. and Hammond, M.O. (2005) Co-operative OuLiPian Generative Literature using Human Based Evolutionary Computing, GECCO 2005, Washington DC.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 von Hippel, E. (2005)  Democratizing Innovation, MIT Press <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.mit.edu/evhippel/www/democ1.htm">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gentry, C et al (2005) Secure Distributed Human Computation In Ninth International Conference on Financial Cryptography and Data Security FC'2005 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fc05.ifca.ai/p26.pdf">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 von Ahn, L et al (2006) Verbosity: A Game for Collecting Common-Sense Facts, ACM CHI Notes 2006 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~biglou/Verbosity.pdf">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 von Ahn, L at al (2006) Improving Accessibility of the Web with a Computer Game, ACM CHI Notes 2006 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~biglou/Phetch.pdf">
online</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Sunstein, C. (2006) Infotopia: How Many Minds Produce Knowledge, Oxford University Press, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Law/TechnologyandTelecomsLaw/?view=usa&amp;ci=9780195189285">
website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Tapscott, D., Williams, A. D. (2007) Wikinomics, Portfolio Hardcover <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wikinomics.com">
website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Footnotes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wired.com/techbiz/media/news/2007/07/crowd_captain">
(Q&amp;A) Your Assignment: Art</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-8246463980976635143">
Human computation</weblink>, a talk by Luis von Ahn</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://utyp.net/">
Utyp</weblink>, Open Source Human Computation based Search Engine for images and pictures utilizing a <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nthinking.net/miss/www.html">
Flash game</weblink></entry>
</list>

</p>

<p>

<link>
 out side computer contacet</link>. when thay thow the scintest a way yhat put out Charnobyl
He tock the technology's with him...  That the thechnology's that put out Charnobyl plus the  patent's and or coy right's to the Anti-carsanomia's. The Ukrine minastery was quick at the hip
but lost every thing. In cluding the technology that were used to save humen life..</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
