<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:01:05[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Algorithmically random sequence</title>
<id>4257548</id>
<revision>
<id>225378788</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-13T10:57:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lambiam</username>
<id>745100</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Randomness</category>
<category>Theoretical computer science</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

Intuitively, an <b>algorithmically random sequence</b> (or <b>random sequence</b>) is an infinite <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/27838.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Infinite+sequences+in+theoretical+computer+science%22])">
sequence</link> of 
binary digits that appears random to any algorithm.  The definition applies equally well to sequences on any finite set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/73443.xml">
characters</link>.
Random sequences are key objects of study in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/2829647.xml">
algorithmic information theory</link>.<p>

As different types of algorithm are sometimes considered, ranging from algorithms with specific bounds on their running time to algorithms which may ask questions of an oracle, there are different notions of randomness. The most common of these is known as <b>Martin-Löf randomness</b> (or <b>1-randomness</b>), but stronger and weaker forms of randomness also exist. The term "random" used to refer to a sequence without clarification is usually taken to mean "Martin-Löf random".</p>
<p>

Because infinite sequences of binary digits can be identified with real numbers in the unit interval, random binary sequences are often called <b>random real numbers</b>. Additionally infinite binary sequences correspond to characteristic functions of sets of natural numbers; therefore those sequences might be seen as sets of natural numbers.</p>
<p>

The class of all Martin-Löf random (binary) sequences is denoted by RAND.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

The first suitable definition of a random sequence was given by <link>
Per Martin-Löf</link> in 1966. Earlier researchers such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/821517.xml">
Richard von Mises</link> had attempted to formalize the notion of a test for randomness in order to define a random sequence as one that passed all tests for randomness; however, the precise notion of a randomness test was left vague. Martin-Löf's key insight was to use the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/30402.xml">
theory of computation</link> to formally define the notion of a test for randomness. This contrasts with the idea of randomness in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/22934.xml">
probability</link>; in that theory, no particular element of a sample space can be said to be random.</p>
<p>

Martin-Löf randomness has since been shown to admit many equivalent characterizations -- in terms of compression, randomness tests, and gambling -- that bear little outward resemblance to the original definition, but each of which satisfy our intuitive notion of properties that random sequences ought to have: random sequences should be incompressible, they should pass statistical tests for randomness, and it should be difficult to make money betting on them. The existence of these multiple definitions of Martin-Löf randomness, and the stability of these definitions under different models of computation, give evidence that Martin-Löf randomness is a fundamental property of mathematics and not an accident of Martin-Löf's particular model.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Three equivalent definitions </st>

<p>

Martin-Löf's original definition of a random sequence was in terms of constructive null covers; he defined a sequence to be random if it is not contained in any such cover.  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/402708.xml">
Leonid Levin</link></person>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/9439931.xml">
Claus-Peter Schnorr</link> proved a characterization in terms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1635.xml">
Kolmogorov complexity</link>:  a sequence is random if there is a uniform bound on the compressibility of its initial segments.   Schnorr gave a third equivalent definition in terms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/274536.xml">
martingales</link> (a type of betting strategy).  Li and Vitanyi's book <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://homepages.cwi.nl/~paulv/kolmogorov.html">
An Introduction to Kolmogorov Complexity and Its Applications</weblink> is an excellent introduction to these ideas.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Kolmogorov complexity</b> (Schnorr 1973, Levin 1973): <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1635.xml">
Kolmogorov complexity</link> can be thought of as a lower bound on the algorithmic compressibility of a finite sequence (of characters or binary digits). It assigns to each such sequence <it>w</it> a natural number <it>K(w)</it> that, intuitively, measures that minimum length of a computer program (written in some fixed programming language) that takes no input and will output <it>w</it> when run. More formally, <it>K(w)</it> is the length of the shortest input string such that some fixed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/71435.xml">
universal Turing machine</link> U with prefix free domain outputs <it>w</it>. In the informal version, the string is thought of as a program in some fixed language, and the universal Turing machine is an interpreter for that language. The prefix-free domain restriction is important; it means that the universal machine can tell when inputs finish. The definition of <it>K</it> depends on the universal machine used, but the difference between complexities relative to different universal machines is bounded by a constant, and so the resulting definition of randomness does not depend on the choice of machine. Given a natural number <it>c</it> and a sequence <it>w</it>, we say that <it>w</it> is <b><it>c</it></b><b>-incompressible</b> if <math>K(w) \geq |w| - c </math>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

<it>An infinite sequence </it>S<it> is Martin-Löf random if and only if there is a constant </it>c<it> such that all of </it>S<b>s finite <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/4556900.xml">
prefixes</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 are <it>c</it></b><b>-incompressible.''</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Constructive null covers</b> (Martin-Löf 1966): This is Martin-Löf's original definition. For a finite binary string <it>w</it> we let <it>Cw</it> denote the <b>cylinder generated by</b> <it>w</it>. This is the set of all infinite sequences beginning with <it>w</it>,  which is a basic open set in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/352376.xml">
Cantor space</link>.  The <b>product <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/19873.xml">
measure</link></b>  μ(<it>Cw</it>) of the cylinder generated by <it>w</it> is defined to be  2-|<it>w</it>|.  Every open subset of Cantor space is the union of a countable sequence of disjoint basic open sets, and the measure of an open set is exactly the sum of the measures of any such sequence.  An <it>effective open set</it> is an open set that is the union of the sequence of basic open sets determined by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/332090.xml">
recursively enumerable</link> sequence of binary strings.  A <it>constructive null cover</it> or <it>effective measure 0 set</it> is a recursively enumerable sequence <math>U_i</math> of effective open sets (that is, a sequence of indices for open sets) such that <math>U_{i+1} \subseteq U_i</math> and <math>\mu U_i \leq 2^{-i}</math> for each natural number <it>i</it>.  Every effective null cover determines a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../076/252076.xml">
<math>G_\delta</math></link> set of measure 0.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

<it>A sequence is defined to be Martin-Löf random if it is not contained in any <math>G_\delta</math> set determined by an effective null cover.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Constructive martingales</b> (Schnorr 1971): A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/274536.xml">
martingale</link> is a function <math>d:\{0,1\}^*\to[0,\infty)</math> such that, for all finite strings <it>w</it>, <math>d(w) = (d(w0) + d(w1))/2</math> - this is called the "fairness condition"; a martingale is viewed as a betting strategy, and the above condition requires that the better plays against fair odds. (This is Ville's original definition of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/4320222.xml">
martingale</link>, later extended by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/1547599.xml">
Joseph Leo Doob</link></scientist>
</person>
.) A constructive martingale <it>d</it> is a martingale that is <b>constructive</b> (also known as <b>weakly computable</b>, <b>lower semi-computable</b>, <b>subcomputable</b>): there exists a computable function <math>\widehat{d}:\{0,1\}^*\times\N\to{\mathbb{Q}}</math> such that, for all finite binary strings <it>w</it> and positive integers <it>t</it>,</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <math>\widehat{d}(w,t) \leq \widehat{d}(w,t+1) &amp;lt; d(w),</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <math>\lim_{t\to\infty} \widehat{d}(w,t) = d(w).</math> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

A martingale <it>d</it> is said to <b>succeed</b> on a sequence <it>S</it> if <math>\limsup_{n\to\infty} d(S \upharpoonright n) = \infty,</math> where <math>S \upharpoonright n</math> is the first <it>n</it> bits of <it>S</it>. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

<it>A sequence is Martin-Löf random if and only if no constructive martingale succeeds on it.''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

(Note that the definition of martingale used here differs slightly from the one used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/23542.xml">
probability theory</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> That definition of martingale has a similar fairness condition, which also states that the expected value after some observation is the same as the value before the observation, given the prior history of observations. The difference is that in probability theory, the prior history of observations just refers to the capital history, whereas here the history refers to the exact sequence of 0s and 1s in the string.)
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Interpretations of the definitions </st>

<p>

The Kolmogorov complexity characterization conveys the intuition that a random sequence is incompressible: no prefix can be produced by a program much shorter than the prefix.</p>
<p>

The null cover characterization conveys the intuition that a random real number should not have any property that is “uncommon”.  Each measure 0 set can be thought of as an uncommon property.  It is not possible for a sequence to lie in no measure 0 sets, because each one-point set has measure 0.  Martin-Löf's idea was to limit the definition to measure 0 sets that are effectively describable; the definition of an effective null cover determines a countable collection of effectively describable measure 0 sets and defines a sequence to be random if it does not lie in any of these particular measure 0 sets.   Since the union of a countable collection of measure 0 sets has measure 0, this definition immediately leads to the theorem that there is a measure 1 set of random sequences.</p>
<p>

The martingale characterization conveys the intuition that no effective procedure should be able to make money betting against a random sequence.   A martingale <it>d</it> is a betting strategy. <it>d</it> reads a finite string <it>w</it> and bets money on the next bit. It bets some fraction of its money that the next bit will be 0, and then remainder of its money that the next bit will be 1. <it>d</it> doubles the money it placed on the bit that actually occurred, and it loses the rest. <it>d</it>(<it>w</it>) is the amount of money it has after seeing the string <it>w</it>. Since the bet placed after seeing the string <it>w</it> can be calculated from the values <it>d</it>(<it>w</it>), <it>d</it>(<it>w</it>0), and <it>d</it>(<it>w</it>1), calculating the amount of money it has is equivalent to calculating the bet. The martingale characterization says that no betting strategy implementable by any computer (even in the weak sense of constructive strategies, which are not necessarily <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/3244084.xml">
computable</link>) can make money betting on a random sequence.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Properties of Martin-Löf random sequences</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is a constructive null cover of RANDc (where RANDc denotes the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/54347.xml">
complement</link></concept>
</idea>
 of RAND). This means that all effective tests for randomness (that is,  constructive null covers) are, in a sense, subsumed by this <it>universal</it> test for randomness, since any sequence that passes this single test for randomness will pass all tests for randomness. (Martin-Löf 1966)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is a <it>universal</it> constructive martingale <b>d</b>. This martingale is universal in the sense that, given any constructive martingale <it>d</it>, there is some constant <it>λ</it>&amp;gt;0 so that for any string <it>σ</it>, <math>\mathbf{d}(\sigma)\geq \lambda d(\sigma)</math>; hence if <it>d</it> succeeds on a sequence, then <b>d</b> succeeds on that sequence as well. Thus, <b>d</b> succeeds on every sequence in RANDc (but, since <b>d</b> is constructive, it succeeds on no sequence in RAND). (Schnorr 1971)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The class RAND is a <math>\Sigma^0_2</math> subset of Cantor space, where <math>\Sigma^0_2</math> refers to the second level of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/186475.xml">
arithmetical hierarchy</link>. This is because a sequence <it>S</it> is in RAND if and only if there is some open set in the universal effective null cover that does not contain <it>S</it>; this property can be seen to be definable by a <math>\Sigma^0_2</math> formula.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is a random sequence which is <math>\Delta^0_2</math>, that is, computable relative to an oracle for the Halting problem. (Schnorr 1971)  Chaitin's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../205/6205.xml">
Ω</link> is an example of such a sequence.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 No random sequence is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../800/54800.xml">
decidable</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/332090.xml">
computably enumerable</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/332090.xml">
co-computably-enumerable</link>. Since these correspond to the <math>\Delta_1^0</math>, <math>\Sigma_1^0</math>, and <math>\Pi_1^0</math> levels of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/186475.xml">
arithmetical hierarchy</link>, this means that <math>\Delta_2^0</math> is the lowest level in the arithmetical hierarchy where random sequences can be found.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 RANDc is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/19873.xml">
measure</link> 0 subset of the set of all infinite sequences. This is implied by the existence of a universal null cover. It is also implied by the fact that each constructive null cover covers a measure 0 set, there are only <link>
countably many</link> null covers, and a countable union of measure 0 sets has measure 0. This implies that RAND is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/19873.xml">
measure</link> 1 subset of the set of all infinite sequences.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Every random sequence is <null_set wordnetid="108001344" confidence="0.8">
<set wordnetid="107999699" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/204277.xml">
normal</link></set>
</null_set>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Every sequence is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/1188375.xml">
Turing reducible</link> to some random sequence. (Kučera 1985/1989, <link>
Gács</link> 1986).  Thus there are random sequences of arbitrarily high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/764405.xml">
Turing degree</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Relative randomness </st>
<p>

As each of the equivalent definitions of a Martin-Löf random sequence is based on what is computable by some Turing machine, one can naturally ask what is computable by a Turing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/22431.xml">
oracle machine</link>. For a fixed oracle <it>A</it>, a sequence <it>B</it> which is not only random but in fact satisfies the equivalent definitions for computability relative to <it>A</it> (e.g., no martingale which is constructive relative to the oracle <it>A</it> succeeds on <it>B</it>) is said to be random relative to <it>B</it>. Two sequences, while themselves random, may contain very similar information, and therefore neither will be random relative to the other. Any time there is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/1188375.xml">
Turing reduction</link> from one sequence to another, the second sequence cannot be random relative to the first, just as computable sequences are themselves nonrandom; in particular, this means that Chaitin's Ω is not random relative to the halting problem.</p>
<p>

An important result relating to relative randomness is van Lambolgen's theorem, which states that if <it>C</it> is the sequence composed from <it>A</it> and <it>B</it> by interleaving the first bit of <it>A</it>, the first bit of <it>B</it>, the second bit of <it>A</it>, the second bit of <it>B</it>, and so on, then <it>C</it> is algorithmically random if and only if <it>A</it> is algorithmically random, and <it>B</it> is algorithmically random relative to <it>A</it>. A very closely related consequence is that if both <it>A</it> and <it>B</it> are both random themselves, then <it>A</it> is random relative to <it>B</it> if and only if <it>B</it> is random relative to <it>A</it>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Stronger than Martin-Löf randomness </st>
<p>

Relative randomness gives us the first notion which is stronger than Martin-Löf randomness, which is randomness relative to some fixed oracle <it>A</it>. For any oracle, this is at least as strong, and for most oracles, it is strictly stronger, since there will be Martin-Löf random sequences which are not random relative to the oracle <it>A</it>. Important oracles often considered are the halting problem, <math>\emptyset '</math>, and the <it>n</it>th jump oracle, <math>\emptyset^{(n)}</math>, as these oracles are able to answer specific questions which naturally arise. A sequence which is random relative to the oracle <math>\emptyset^{(n-1)}</math> is called <it>n</it>-random; a sequence is 1-random, therefore, if and only if it is Martin-Löf random. A sequence which is <it>n</it>-random for every <it>n</it> is called arithmetically random. The <it>n</it>-random sequences sometimes arise when considering particularly complicated properties. One expects that a random sequence should not have properties which are very rare - specifically, if the properties are only possessed by a measure 0 collection of sequences - but this may not be true for Martin-Löf random sequences if the property is sufficiently complicated, as any statistic test which checks for the property may be too complicated to be a Martin-Löf test. However, for any such property that one is likely to consider, any sequence which is <it>n</it>-random for sufficiently large <it>n</it> will not have the unusual property. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Weaker than Martin-Löf randomness </st>
<p>

Additionally, there are several notions of randomness which are weaker than Martin-Löf randomness. Some of these are weak 1-randomness, Schnorr randomness, computable randomness, partial computable randomness. Additionally, Kolmogorov-Loveland randomness is known to be no stronger than Martin-Löf randomness, but it is not known whether it is actually weaker. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">John M. Hitchcock and Jack H. Lutz&#32;(2006).&#32;"Why computational complexity requires stricter martingales". <it>Theory of Computing Systems</it>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal">Rod Downey, Denis R. Hirschfeldt, Andre Nies, Sebastiaan A. Terwijn&#32;(2006).&#32;"Calibrating Randomness". <it>The Bulletin of Symbolic Logic</it>&#32;<b>12</b>&#32;(3/4): 411–491. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2178%2Fbsl%2F1154698741">
10.2178/bsl/1154698741</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal"><link>
Gács, P.</link>&#32;(1986).&#32;"Every sequence is reducible to a random one". <it>Information and Control</it>&#32;<b>70</b>&#32;(2/3): 186–192. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0019-9958%2886%2980004-3">
10.1016/S0019-9958(86)80004-3</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kučera, A.&#32;(1985). "Measure, &amp;Pi;10-classes and complete extensions of PA".&#32;<it>Recursion Theory Week</it>: 245–259, Lecture Notes in Mathematics 1141, Springer-Verlag.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kučera, A.&#32;(1989). "On the use of diagonally nonrecursive functions".&#32;<it>Studies in Logic and the Foundations of Mathematics</it>&#32;<b>129</b>: 219–239, North-Holland.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal"><person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/402708.xml">
Levin, L.</link></person>
&#32;(1973).&#32;"On the notion of a random sequence". <it>Soviet Mathematics Doklady</it>&#32;<b>14</b>: 1413–1416.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Li, M.; Vitanyi, P. M. B.&#32;(1997). An Introduction to Kolmogorov Complexity and its Applications, Second Edition,&#32;Berlin:&#32;Springer-Verlag.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal">Martin-Löf, P.&#32;(1966).&#32;"The definition of random sequences". <it>Information and Control</it>&#32;<b>9</b>: 602–619. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0019-9958%2866%2980018-9">
10.1016/S0019-9958(66)80018-9</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal"><scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/9439931.xml">
Schnorr, C. P.</link></scientist>
&#32;(1971).&#32;"A unified approach to the definition of a random sequence". <it>Mathematical Systems Theory</it>&#32;<b>5</b>&#32;(3): 246–258. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2FBF01694181">
10.1007/BF01694181</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal"><scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/9439931.xml">
Schnorr, C. P.</link></scientist>
&#32;(1973).&#32;"Process complexity and effective random tests". <it>Journal of Computer and System Sciences</it>&#32;<b>7</b>: 376–388. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0022-0000%2873%2980030-3">
10.1016/S0022-0000(73)80030-3</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Ville, J.&#32;(1939). Etude critique de la notion de collectif.&#32;Paris:&#32;Gauthier-Villars.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
