<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:02:10[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Structure of the Comecon</title>
<id>426755</id>
<revision>
<id>219474738</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-15T12:06:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Teutonic Tamer</username>
<id>5827990</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Comecon</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also the main article <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/384307.xml">
Comecon</link>.</it>
</indent>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/384307.xml">
Comecon</link>, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/325329.xml">
Cold War</link> <politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/97477.xml">
Eastern Bloc</link></social_relation>
</politics>
 equivalent to the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/9578.xml">
European Economic Community</link></organization>
, had an elaborate <b>organisational structure</b>, as laid out below.
<sec>
<st>
 The Conference </st>
<p>

Although not formally part of the organization's hierarchy, the <b>Conference of First Secretaries of Communist and Workers' Parties and of the Heads of Government of the Comecon Member Countries</b> was Comecon's most important organ. These party and government leaders gathered for conference meetings regularly to discuss topics of mutual interest. Because of the rank of conference participants, decisions made here have considerable influence on the actions taken by Comecon and its organs. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Comecon organs and institutions </st>
<p>

The official hierarchy of Comecon consisted of the <b>Session of the Council for Mutual Economic Assistance, the Executive Committee of the Council, the Secretariat of the Council, four council committees, twenty-four standing commissions, six interstate conferences, two scientific institutes, and several associated organizations</b>: </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Comecon session </st>
<p>

The Session, officially the highest Comecon organ, examined fundamental problems of socialist economic integration and directed the activities of the Secretariat and other subordinate organizations.</p>
<p>

Delegations from each Comecon member country attended these meetings. Prime ministers usually headed the delegations, which met during the second quarter of each year in a member country's capital (the location of the meeting was determined by a system of rotation based on the <W wordnetid="106833544" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/5639.xml">
Cyrillic alphabet</link></W>
). All interested parties had to consider recommendations handed down by the Session. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/30432.xml">
treaty</link> or other kind of legal agreement implemented adopted recommendations. Comecon itself might adopt decisions only on organizational and procedural matters pertaining to itself and its organs.</p>
<p>

Each country appointed one permanent representative to maintain relations between members and Comecon between annual meetings. An extraordinary Session, such as the one in December 1985, might be held with the consent of at least one-third of the members. Such meetings usually take place in Moscow. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Executive Committee </st>
<p>

The highest executive organ in Comecon, the Executive Committee, was entrusted with elaborating policy recommendations and supervising their implementation between sessions. In addition, it supervised work on plan coordination and scientific-technical cooperation. Composed of one representative from each member country, usually a deputy chairman of the Council of Ministers, the Executive Committee met quarterly, usually in <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/19004.xml">
Moscow</link></city>
. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/34748.xml">
1971</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/34654.xml">
1974</link>, the Executive Committee acquired economic departments that ranked above the standing commissions. These economic departments considerably strengthened the authority and importance of the Executive Committee. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Council committees </st>
<p>

There were four council committees: Council Committee for Cooperation in Planning, Council Committee for Scientific and Technical Cooperation, Council Committee for Cooperation in Material and Technical Supply, and Council Committee for Cooperation in Machine Building. Their mission was "to ensure the comprehensive examination and a multilateral settlement of the major problems of cooperation among member countries in the economy, science, and technology." All committees were headquartered in Moscow and usually met there. These committees advised the standing commissions, the Secretariat, the interstate conferences, and the scientific institutes in their areas of specialization. Their jurisdiction was generally wider than that of the standing commissions because they had the right to make policy recommendations to other Comecon organizations. </p>
<p>

The Council Committee for Cooperation in Planning was the most important of the four. It coordinated the national economic plans of Comecon members. As such, it ranked in importance only after the Session and the Executive Committee. Made up of the chairmen of Comecon members' national central planning offices, the Council Committee for Cooperation in Planning drew up draft agreements for joint projects, adopted a resolution approving these projects, and recommended approval to the concerned parties. If its decisions were not subject to approval by national governments and parties, this committee would be considered Comecon's supranational planning body. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Secretariat </st>
<p>

The international Secretariat, Comecon's only permanent body, was Comecon's primary economic research and administrative organ. The secretary, who has been a Soviet official since Comecon creation, was the official Comecon representative to Comecon member states and to other states and international organizations. Subordinate to the secretary were his deputy and the various departments of the Secretariat, which generally corresponded to the standing commissions. The Secretariat's responsibilities included preparation and organization of Comecon sessions and other meetings conducted under the auspices of Comecon; compilation of digests on Comecon activities; conduct of economic and other research for Comecon members; and preparation of recommendations on various issues concerning Comecon operations. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Standing commissions </st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/34672.xml">
1956</link> eight standing commissions were set up to help Comecon make recommendations pertaining to specific economic sectors. The commissions have been rearranged and renamed a number of times since the establishment of the first eight. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/34761.xml">
1986</link> there were twenty-four standing commissions . Each commission was headquartered in the capital of a member country and headed by one of that country's leading authorities in the field addressed by the commission. The Secretariat supervised the actual operations of the commissions. The standing commissions had authority only to make recommendations, which had then to be approved by the Executive Committee, presented to the Session, and ratified by the interested member countries. Commissions usually met twice a year in Moscow. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Interstate conferences </st>
<p>

The six interstate conferences (on water management, internal trade, legal matters, inventions and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/23273.xml">
patents</link>, pricing, and labor affairs) served as forums for discussing shared issues and experiences. They were purely consultative and generally acted in an advisory capacity to the Executive Committee or its specialized committees. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Scientific institutes </st>
<p>

The scientific institutes on standardization and on economic problems of the world socialist system concerned themselves with theoretical problems of international cooperation. Both were headquartered in Moscow and were staffed by experts from various member countries. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Affiliated agencies </st>
<p>

Several affiliated agencies, having a variety of relationships with Comecon, existed outside the official Comecon hierarchy. They served to develop "direct links between appropriate bodies and organizations of Comecon member countries."</p>
<p>

These affiliated agencies were divided into two categories: intergovernmental economic organizations (which worked on a higher level in the member countries and generally dealt with a wider range of managerial and coordinative activities) and international economic organizations (which worked closer to the operational level of research, production, or trade).</p>
<p>

A few examples of the former are the <link>
International Bank for Economic Cooperation</link> (managed the transferable ruble system), the <link>
International Investment Bank</link> (in charge of financing joint projects), and <link>
Intermetal</link> (encouraged cooperation in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/8483830.xml">
ferrous metallurgy</link>).</p>
<p>

International economic organizations generally took the form of either joint enterprises, international economic associations or unions, or international economic partnerships. The latter included <link>
Interatominstrument</link> (nuclear machinery producers), <link>
Intertekstilmash</link> (textile machinery producers), and Haldex (a Hungarian-Polish joint enterprise for reprocessing coal slag).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Source</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

This article incorporates <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/18935551.xml">
public domain</link> text written by the Federal Research Program of the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 <library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/18944081.xml">
Library of Congress</link></library>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
