<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:02:09[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</title>
<id>429680</id>
<revision>
<id>243406667</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T11:37:33Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Flewis</username>
<id>7826393</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Health and medicine related organisations in the United Kingdom</category>
<category>National Health Service</category>
<category>NHS Special Health Authorities</category>
<category>Healthcare quality</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

"NICE" redirects here. For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/429686.xml">
NICE (disambiguation)</link>.
The <b>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</b> or <b>NICE</b>  is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/3389360.xml">
Special Health Authority</link> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/16462572.xml">
National Health Service</link> in  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/275187.xml">
England and Wales</link>. It was set up as the "National Institute for Clinical Excellence" in 1999, and on 1 April 2005 joined with the Health Development Agency to become the new "National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence" (still abbreviated as NICE).<p>

NICE publishes clinical appraisals of whether particular treatments should be considered worthwhile by the NHS. These appraisals are based primarily on cost-effectiveness.</p>
<p>

NICE was established in an attempt to defuse the so-called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/1443347.xml">
postcode lottery</link> system of healthcare in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/275187.xml">
England and Wales</link>, where treatments that were available depended upon the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/783106.xml">
NHS Trust</link> area in which the patient happened to live. However its role in rationing treatment has led to NICE becoming a controversial body, which has gained a high profile internationally as a potential role model for the explicit prioritization of health services.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
 Technology appraisals</st>

<p>

Since January 2005 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/16462572.xml">
NHS</link> in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/9316.xml">
England</link></country>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/69894.xml">
Wales</link> has been legally obliged to provide funding for medicines and treatments recommended by NICE's technology appraisal board. This is at least in part as a result of well-publicised "postcode lottery" scandals in which certain treatments are funded in one part of the UK but not in another. </p>
<p>

If a technology is to be appraised by NICE then it must be referred to them by the <office wordnetid="103841666" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/356531.xml">
Secretary of State for Health</link></office>
. Once this has been done NICE works with the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<priesthood wordnetid="108113443" confidence="0.8">
<occupational_group wordnetid="108403631" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<profession wordnetid="108112096" confidence="0.8">
<ministry wordnetid="108113797" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/373579.xml">
Department of Health</link></group>
</ministry>
</profession>
</department>
</occupational_group>
</priesthood>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</social_group>
</body>
 to draw up the scope of the appraisal. </p>
<p>

NICE then invite "consultee" and "commentator" organisations to take part in the appraisal. A consultee organisation would include patient groups, organisations representing health care professionals and the manufacturers of the product undergoing appraisal. Consultees submit evidence during the appraisal and comment on the appraisal documents. Commentator organisations include the manufacturers of products to which the product undergoing appraisal is being compared. They comment on the documents that have been submitted and drawn up but do not actually submit information themselves. </p>
<p>

An independent academic centre then draws together and analyses all of the published information on the technology under appraisal and prepares an assessment report. This can be commented on by the Consultees and Commentators. Comments are then taken into account and changes made to the assessment report to produce an evaluation report. An independent Appraisal Committee then looks at the evaluation report, hears spoken testimony from clinical experts, patient groups and carers. They take their testimony into account and draw up a document known as the <it>appraisal consultation document</it>. This is sent to all consultees and commentators who are then able to make further comments. Once these comments have been taken into account the final document is drawn up called the <it>final appraisal determination</it>. This is submitted to NICE for approval.</p>
<p>

The process aims to be fully independent of government and lobbying power, basing decisions fully on clinical and cost-effectiveness. There have been concerns that lobbying by pharmaceutical companies to mobilise media attention and influence public opinion are attempts to influence the decision making process. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/5063352.stm">
http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/5063352.stm</weblink> A fast-track assessment system has been introduced to reach decisions where there is most pressure for a conclusion.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Clinical guidelines </st>

<p>

NICE carries out assessments of the most appropriate treatment regimes for different diseases. This must take into account both desired medical outcomes (i.e. the best possible result for the patient) and also economic arguments regarding differing treatments. </p>
<p>

NICE have set up several National Collaborating Centres who draw up the boundaries of the guideline, i.e. what it will cover. The National Collaborating Centre then appoints a Guideline Development Group whose job it is to work on the development of the clinical guideline. This group will consist of medical professionals, representatives of patient and carer groups and technical experts. They work together to asses the evidence for the guideline topic (e.g. clinical trials of competing products) before preparing a draft guideline. </p>
<p>

There are then two consultation periods in which stakeholder organisations are able to comment on the draft guideline. After the second consultation period an independent Guideline Review Panel reviews the guideline and stakeholder comments and ensures that these comments have been taken into account. </p>
<p>

The Guideline Development Group then finalises the recommendations and the National Collaboration Centre produces the final guideline. This is submitted to NICE who then formally approve the guideline and issues this guidance to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/16462572.xml">
NHS</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Cost effectiveness</st>

<p>

NICE attempts to rationalise for the NHS the trade off between spending money on different forms of treatment and when and when not to treat. It attempts to weigh up factors such as how much benefit the treatment gives, how long the benefit of the treatment will last for, and how much it costs.  Once it has done this it will make recommendations about which treatments can be given and in which circumstances in order to maximise the delivery of care within the available budget.</p>
<p>

<b>Health Benefits</b> or <it>Quality adjusted life years</it></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

NICE utilziles the concept of <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/1393169.xml">
quality-adjusted life years</link></b> or QALY to measure the benefits of a treatment quality and the quantity of life delivered by a given treatment regime. One interpretation of QALY would be how much lifespan a person would be prepared to give up to deliver one year of perfect health from the current state of ill health. By comparing QALY values before and after treatment one could calculate the benefit delivered by a given treatment to a given person. 
</indent>

<b>Cost/benefit ratio</b> or <it>cost per quality adjusted life-years gained</it></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

The cost of a treatment may be relatively easy to calculate but because people may be at different ages when they receive treatment, the gain may be different according to age. A heart operation on a small child may deliver many more years of quality of life than the same operation on a 76 year old man. By taking the cost of treatment and dividing it by the years gained an overall cost benefit ratio can be determined as the <b>cost per quality adjusted life-year gained</b> or CQG.
</indent>

<b>Basis of recommendations</b> - <it>the shadow price</it></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

Theoretically it might be possible to draw up a table of all possible treatments sorted by increasing <b>cost per quality adjusted life-year gained</b>. Those treatments with lowest cost per quality adjusted life-year gained would appear at the top of the table and deliver the most benefit per value spent and would be easiest to justify funding for. Those where the delivered benefit is low and the cost is high would appear at the bottom of the list. Decision makers would, theoretically, work down the table, adopting services that are the most cost effective. The point at which the NHS budget is exhausted would reveal the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/1913196.xml">
shadow price</link>, the threshold lying between the CQG gained of the last service that is funded and that of the next most cost effective service which is not funded.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

In practice this exercise is not done, but an assumed shadow price has been used by NICE for many years in its assesments to determine which treatments the NHS should and should not fund. It is set at £30,000 (about $US 60,000) per quality of life adjusted year gained.
</indent>

Source for this section: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nice2007.co.uk/ApplebyDevlin.pdf">
Searching for local NHS cost effectiveness thresholds: A feasibility study</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Criticism</st>

<p>

The work that NICE is involved in attracts the attention of many groups, including doctors, the pharmaceutical industry, and patients. NICE is often associated with controversy, because the need to make decisions at a national level can conflict with what is (or is believed to be) in the best interests of an individual patient. Decisions not to fund expensive treatments or those with no proven benefits are necessary to ensure that public funds are used wisely. From an individual's perspective it can sometimes seem that NICE is denying access to a potentially life-saving treatment but the denial is only effective as far as the use of public resources are concerned. Treatment may be available if the patient can find the resources to pay for treatment in the private sector and a doctor willing to administer it.</p>
<p>

NICE has been criticised for its over-reliance on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/10013.xml">
evidence-based medicine</link>, which it is argued privileges certain kinds of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/10390.xml">
econometric</link>ally derived types of studies over others. NICE has also been criticised for being too slow to reach decisions, especially when compared to the equivalent body for <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/26994.xml">
Scotland</link></country>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/15283949.xml">
Scottish Medicines Consortium</link>. On one occasion, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/391928.xml">
Royal National Institute for the Blind</link> accused NICE of incompetence over it not making a decision about a drug already approved for use in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/26994.xml">
Scotland</link></country>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Some of the more controversial NICE decisions have concerned beta-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/15120.xml">
interferon</link> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/50603.xml">
multiple sclerosis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/561843.xml">
imatinib</link> (Glivec) for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/18539.xml">
leukaemia</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/614750.xml">
trastuzumab</link> (Herceptin) for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/70547.xml">
breast cancer</link>.  All these are drugs with a high cost per treatment which NICE regards as too expensive relative to the improvements in health they bring. In effect NICE is saying that the money could and should be better used to treat other patients and deliver even greater benefits to the community overall.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/5680493.xml">
List of pharmacy organizations in the United Kingdom</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/15283949.xml">
Scottish Medicines Consortium</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springer.com/public+health/book/978-0-387-71995-5">
http://www.springer.com/public+health/book/978-0-387-71995-5</weblink> Schlander, M: Health Technology Assessments by the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence. New York, NY: Springer, 2007]</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rnib.org.uk/xpedio/groups/public/documents/publicwebsite/public_pr080807.hcsp">
RNIB accuses NICE of incompetence</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nice.org.uk/">
Official website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.evidence-based-medicine.co.uk/ebmfiles/WhatisNICE.pdf">
What is NICE? (Hayward Medical Communications)</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scottishmedicines.org.uk/smc/CCC_FirstPage.jsp">
Scottish Medicines Consortium Home Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nice2007.co.uk/AndreaSutcliffe.pdf">
NICE 2007 conference presentation on interest in NICE from the USA</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
