<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:03:33[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Black fax</title>
<id>433024</id>
<revision>
<id>242320339</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T19:50:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Preslethe</username>
<id>249117</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Fax</category>
<category>Practical jokes</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

The term <b>black fax</b> refers to a prank <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/10826.xml">
fax</link> transmission, consisting of one or more pages entirely filled with a uniform black tone and often made into a loop the sending machine will transmit endlessly.  The sender's intention is typically to consume as much of the recipient's fax ink, toner or thermal paper as possible, thus denying its owner its use (this is similar to computer-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/39776.xml">
denial of service</link> attacks).  A bonus for the malicious sender is that, in cases where the receiving fax machine prints the fax using water-based ink onto conventional paper, the saturated paper may disintegrate inside the fax machine's mechanism, thus entirely blocking it. Black faxes can be particularly effective as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/14744.xml">
CCITT</link> fax algorithm compresses the solid black image very well, so a very short fax call can produce many pages.  </p>
<p>

Black faxes have been used to harass large institutions or government departments, to retaliate against the senders of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/712475.xml">
junk fax</link>es, or merely as simple pranks.</p>
<p>

The basic principle of a black fax can be extended to form a <it>fax attack.</it> In this case, a single sheet is fed halfway through the sender's fax machine and taped end to end, forming an endless loop that cycles through the machine. Not only can solid black be used, but also images which will repeat endlessly on the receiver's machine until their toner runs out.</p>
<p>

The introduction of computer-based facsimile systems (combined with integrated document imaging solutions) at major corporations now means that black faxes are unlikely to cause problems for larger corporations.  Alternatively, the ability for computer modems to send faxes offers new avenues for abuse.  A program could be used to generate hundreds of pages of perfectly compressed, pure black and send them very quickly to the target fax machine.</p>
<p>

Black faxes are similar (in both intention and implementation) to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/82192.xml">
lace card</link>s.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wordspy.com/words/blackfax.asp">
Black Fax</weblink> at <link>
WordSpy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2002/jul/18/hacking.security">
Extreme Response not a solution</weblink> -<newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/19344515.xml">
The Guardian</link></newspaper>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;source=web&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=11&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.usdoj.gov%2Fusao%2Fnj%2Fpress%2Ffiles%2Fpdffiles%2Fshacind2.pdf&amp;ei=NTjQSMqSNJr8gAKRveiAAQ&amp;usg=AFQjCNGr7-kI0yeLxBadAD-7QHKi5rogwA&amp;sig2=8Qzzip0zIeoxQbXVZVFu8A">
Description of Black Faxing in court documents</weblink> -- usdoj.gov</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
