<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:00:53[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Information Integration Theory</title>
<id>4331787</id>
<revision>
<id>207902826</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-24T17:16:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Waacstats</username>
<id>1951353</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Social psychology</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from October 2006</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
<category>Cognition</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Information_Integration_Theory&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Information+Integration+Theory%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(October 2006)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

 
<image location="right" width="400px" src="information-integration.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Schematic Diagram of Information Integration Theory
</caption>
</image>

<b>Information Integration Theory</b> was proposed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15648844.xml">
Norman H. Anderson</link> to describe and model how a person integrates information from a number of sources in to make an overall judgment. The theory proposes three functions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  </p>
<p>

The <it>valuation function</it> V(S) is an empirically derived mapping of stimuli to an interval scale. It is unique up to an interval transformation (y = ax + b).</p>
<p>

The <it>integration function</it> r = I{s1,s2, .. ,sn}  is an algebraic function combining the subjective values of the information. "Cognitive Algebra" refers to the class of functions that are used to model the integration process.  They may be adding, averaging, weighted averaging, multiplying, etc.</p>
<p>

The <it>response production function</it> R = M(r) is the process by which the internal impression is translated into an overt response.</p>
<p>

Information Integration Theory differs from others theories in that it is not erected on a consistency principle such as balance or congruity but rather relies on algebraic models.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Integration Models </st>
<p>

There are three main types of algebraic models used in Information Integration Theory. Adding, Averaging, and Multiplying.</p>
<p>

<b>Adding Models</b>
R = Reaction/Overt Behavior
F/G = Contributing Factors</p>
<p>

R1 = F1 + G1 (Condition 1)
R2 = F2 + G2 (Condition 2)</p>
<p>

Typically an experiment is designed so that: 
R1 = R2, and
F1 &amp;gt; F2, so that
G1  G2</p>
<p>

There are two special cases known as discounting and augmentation. </p>
<p>

Discounting: The value of any factor is reduced if other factors that produce the same effect are added.
Example: F2 is not present or has a value of zero. If F1 is positive, then G1 must be less than G2.</p>
<p>

Augmentation: An inverse version of the typical model.
Example: If F1 is negative, then G1 must be greater than G2</p>
<p>

Two advantages of adding models; (1) Participants are not required to have an exact intuitive calculation, (2) The adding model itself need not be completely valid. Certain kinds of interaction among the factors would not affect the qualitative conclusions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
1</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Anderson, N. H. Application of an Additive Model to Impression Formation. <it>Science</it>, 1962, 138, 817-818</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Anderson, N. H. On the Quantification of Miller's Conflict Theory. <it>Psychological Review</it>, 1962, 69, 400-414</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Anderson, N. H. A Simple Model for Information Integration. In R.P. Abelson, E. Aronson, W.J. McGuire, T.M. Newcomb, M.J. Rosenberg, &amp; P.H. Tannenbaum (Eds.), <it>Theories of Cognitive Consistency: A Sourcebook.</it> Chicago: Rand McNally, 1968</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Anderson, N. H. Functional Measurement and Psychophysical Judgment. <it>Psychological Review</it>, 1970, 77, 153- 170.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Anderson, N. H. Integration Theory and Attitude Change. <it>Psychological Review</it>, 1971, 78, 171-206.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Anderson, N. H. (1981).  <it>Foundation of information integration theory</it>. New York: Academic Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Norman, K. L. (1973). <it>A method of maximum likelihood estimation for information integration models</it>. (CHIP No. 35). La Jolla, California: University of California, San Diego, Center for Human Information Processing.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Norman, K. L. (1976). A solution for weights and scale values in functional measurement. <it>Psychological Review, 83</it>, 80-84.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lap.umd.edu/simile/">
Stimulus Integration Models Iterated for Likelihood Estimates</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
