<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:06:50[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Open Communication</title>
<id>4334230</id>
<revision>
<id>191326967</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-14T02:03:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Open access</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

 <p>

<b>Open Communication</b>, or <it>Open Access to Communication</it> resources, means that anyone, on equal conditions with a transparent relation between cost and pricing, can get access to and share communication resources on one level to provide value added services on another level in a layered communication system architecture. Simply put, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/1778853.xml">
Open Access</link> plans are to deregulate oligarchy of telecom operators in a bid to give consumers more choices for equipment, services and service vendors or carriers. It will also provide some breathing room for the controversial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/1398166.xml">
Net Neutrality</link> that has been the central issue between <b>mobile carriers</b>, like AT&amp;T, Verizon and Sprint Nextel, and <b>web media moguls</b>, like eBay, Amazon.com and Google.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Socioeconomic Impact </st>

<p>

The concept of Open Access to Communication Resources is central in the ongoing transformation of the communication market from a "vertically integrated" market with a few operators owning and operating everything between the physical medium and the end-user, to an "open horizontal market" with an abundance of actors operating on different levels and providing value added services on top of each other.</p>
<p>

Open Access is also a broad approach to policy and regulatory issues that starts from the question: what do we want to bring about outside of purely industry sector concerns? It places an emphasis on: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

empowering citizens</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

encouraging local innovation, economic growth and investment</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

getting the best from public and private sector contributions. </entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

It is not simply about making micro-adjustments to the technical rules of the policy and regulatory framework but seeking to produce fundamental changes in the outcomes that can be delivered through it. Since the advent of <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
 (WWW) in the early 1990s, the greatest advantage the web culture has brought about through dot.com boom-and-bust cycles is decentralization that has created more user-centric society, embracing diversity, practicality, voluntarism and egalitarianism in every field across the planet.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controversy</st>

<p>

The FCC is scheduled to hold auctions on this 700 MHz frequency spectrum and seems to move toward auction rule change in favor of a partial Open Access plan that will require the highest bidder to use a third of the airwaves to build a network that is available to all wireless devices and services. It is most likely the FCC will decide for the partial Open Access.</p>
<p>

Google indicated its participation in the forthcoming auction in efforts to achieve full open access plans, also known as "wholesale measures", which are neither fully accepted by FCC nor by mobile carriers, like AT&amp;T and Verizon. However, AT&amp;T and Verizon opted for the partial Open Access, while Sprint Next is bent on building WiMAX networks across the continental USA. WiMAX stresses the interoperability in terms of equipment and applications.</p>
<p>

By and large, mobile technology takes center stage in communications and is unpredictable about its future course for now, and makes "what had been unthinkable a few years before" happen. Its cladogenetic evolution is proceeding at a dizzying pace, and this is why mobile content providers are concerned that 'network gatekeepers' like mobile carriers might end up stifling innovation and freer content distribution. Mobile search, mobile marketing, and mobile advertising are the fast-growing segments of the telecommunications industry and, as one industry executive said, 'blurring borderline between telecom and media industries' is getting more conspicuous.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Layers in Data Communication System Architecture</st>

<p>

The interesting layers in a data communication system architecture for terrestrial Optical Fibre Communication include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Physical passive infrastructure: right of way, ducts, fibre cables, fibre core terminated in an optical distribution frame with patch panels.  Actors on this level includes real estate owners, both public and private, other infrastructure actors, such as power utility companies, railway companies, pipeline companies (water, gas, oil, etc). Several fibre owners lease dark fibre to operators or end-users. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Optical transmission including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/80464.xml">
wavelength division multiplexing</link> (WDM) providing several communication channels in the same fibre core. Fibre owners sometimes provide wavelengths rather than dark fibre, sometimes both.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Link level: includes a variety of link level services for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/17739.xml">
Local Area Network</link> LAN, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/43326.xml">
Metropolitan Area Network</link> MAN and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/38140.xml">
Wide Area Network</link> WAN implemented by switches, etc. Operators on this level include "service operator-neutral" network operators.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Network level (IP), including unicast, multicast, anycast. Operators on this level include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/100245.xml">
Internet Service Providers</link> (ISPs)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

End-to-end transport level, including connection-oriented <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/30538.xml">
Transfer Control Protocol</link> (TCP) and datagram (UDP). Commercial services on this level are rare.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Services including session, presentation and application functionality, such as email (SMTP, POP, IMAP), web services (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/2701104.xml">
HTTP</link>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/53289.xml">
File Transfer Protocol</link> (FTP), terminal access (<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/31062.xml">
TELNET</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
), etc. Typical commercial actors on this level include Internet Cafes.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/12902100.xml">
700 Mhz wireless spectrum auction</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/9700175.xml">
Unbundled Access</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Report by Spintrack Consulting (funded by Infodev) on Open Access Models <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.infodev.org/files/2569_file_OPEN_ACCESS_REPORT.pdf">
Open Access Models: Options for Improving Backbone Access in Developing Countries -with a Focus on Sub-Saharan Africa</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 OECD's Competition Law and Policy Committee recommends structural separation for increased competition in public utilities <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/24/49/25315195.pdf">
Recommendation of the Council concerning Structural Separation in Regulated Industries</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/07/24/AR2007072400889.html?hpid=sec-tech">
FCC Majority Backs Open-Access Plan for Airwaves</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.com.com/2008-1039_3-6199374.html?part=rss&amp;tag=2038-12_3-0&amp;subj=news">
Google's battle for wireless spectrum</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/washington/AP-Airwaves-Auction.html?ex=1343534400&amp;en=0493e75f765f31df&amp;ei=5088&amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss">
FCC approves rules for airwaves sale</weblink></entry>
</list>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
