<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:01:27[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<representation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105926676">
<image  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105928118">
<header>
<title>Recovery disc</title>
<id>4341379</id>
<revision>
<id>231283040</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-11T18:52:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>ViperSnake151</username>
<id>403055</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>System software</category>
<category>Disk images</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>recovery disc</b> is a general term for media containing a backup of the original factory condition or favored condition of a computer as configured by an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/69922.xml">
original equipment manufacturer</link> or an end-user. OEM supplied recovery media is commonly shipped with most modern computers to allow the user to reformat the hard drive and reinstall the operating system and pre-loaded software as it was when it was shipped.
<sec>
<st>
OEM system recovery</st>
<p>

Most OEM recovery systems for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> based operating systems involve booting from a separate <recording wordnetid="104063868" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<sound_recording wordnetid="104262678" confidence="0.8">
<memory_device wordnetid="103744840" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<phonograph_record wordnetid="103924069" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/18959902.xml">
CD-ROM</link></medium>
</phonograph_record>
</device>
</memory_device>
</sound_recording>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</recording>
, <medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/11014498.xml">
DVD</link></medium>
, or hard drive partition, which in turn launches the recovery environment. After accepting the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/40412.xml">
license agreements</link> for the software and operating system, the recovery program will usually reformat the hard drive and then begin copying operating system and software files (although some recovery systems, such as the ones utilized by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/13973.xml">
Hewlett-Packard</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/570838.xml">
Gateway</link> do offer a "non-destructive recovery" option which backs up data before reinstalling the OS<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. After the recovery process is completed, first run configuration such as the Windows <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/5682393.xml">
Out-Of-Box Experience</link> wizard is run (along with any other additional setup the computer may perform), as it was on the initial startup of the computer. Most recovery systems use specialized software, though <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/59703.xml">
Toshiba</link></company>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/102490.xml">
Dell</link> licensed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/640080.xml">
Norton Ghost</link> technology for their recovery systems at one point.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> As of <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
, Dell now uses a <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/3632045.xml">
Windows Imaging Format</link></format>
 based image on a partition along with a tool launched from the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<window wordnetid="104587648" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<supporting_structure wordnetid="104361095" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<framework wordnetid="103391770" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/4167705.xml">
Windows Recovery Environment</link></framework>
</part>
</supporting_structure>
</component>
</window>
</artifact>
</concept>
</idea>
</structure>
's command prompt.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Some smaller OEM's instead ship sometimes customized Windows installation Disks with the computer in lieu of a dedicated recovery system (sometimes accompanied by "driver discs", or slipstreamed into the installation media), and sometimes alongside one.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Recovery partitions</st>
<p>

In recent years, bundled recovery CD-ROMs have become less common, as some OEM's are now utilizing hard drive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/191212.xml">
partitions</link> to store the recovery data. Accessing hard drive based system recovery is usually performed by pressing a specific key combination during or after the computer's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/1699425.xml">
POST</link>. Partition based recovery systems are usually faster than their disc based counterparts since the data is directly on the hard drive and no disc swapping is needed. They can also be cheaper for the OEM because they do not need to ship recovery CDs with the computer, adding the price of creating them to the cost of the computer.</p>
<p>

However, if the hard drive fails, is fully reformatted, or is replaced, the recovery partition will be lost. An application used to burn bootable recovery CDs or DVDs is sometimes offered in order to allow a backup of the recovery data.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> For computers with Recovery Partitions, these recovery CDs can also sometimes be ordered directly from the OEM. If they are used to recover the system, the recovery partition can sometimes be recreated with the recovery CD as well.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Disk Image Recovery</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <representation wordnetid="105926676" confidence="0.8">
<image wordnetid="105928118" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/634143.xml">
Disk cloning</link></image>
</representation>
</it>
</indent>
The advantages of OEM recovery media can be had, without some of their disadvantages, by using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/82921.xml">
disk imaging</link> software such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/6331985.xml">
Mondo Rescue</link></software>
, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/4429879.xml">
Acronis True Image</link></software>
, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/640080.xml">
Norton Ghost</link> to create a bootable recovery CD containing an image of the machine in the desired initial state. For example, a user can install their operating system, install all device drivers for their hardware, install other desired software, and configure other personal settings. Some smaller OEM's even use bootable CDs generated by this software as the actual recovery CD or DVD itself.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>
<p>

Due to the recovery discs containing all the applications and drivers for a computer, many manufacturers are omitting copies of product CDs in favor of the single recovery system to prevent unauthorized distribution of preloaded software, as the recovery media is usually locked to the computer it came with. This complicates clean installation with a fresh copy of the operating system, as to perform such actions and get a setup close to the recovery disc's result, they would need to purchase new licenses for any software which came bundled with their system, just so that they could obtain an installation disc for that software, and would also have to download the drivers for their computer's components manually.</p>
<p>

In addition, if the hardware configuration of the system changes, drivers and support for the additional hardware changes will not be on the recovery image, requiring users to reinstall their drivers.</p>
<p>

Some OEM's however do ship copies of the version of Windows shipped on the computer, along with driver and application discs, sometimes alongside dedicated recovery Disks.</p>
<p>

As mentioned earlier, if the system has a recovery partition, and the hard drive fails, is replaced, or if the recovery partition is deleted, the recovery data will be lost unless the user has a recovery CD or DVD set.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/55389.xml">
Master boot record</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://h10025.www1.hp.com/ewfrf/wc/document?cc=us&amp;docname=bph07145">
HP and Compaq Desktop PCs -  Performing an HP System Recovery in Windows XP</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-16</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.goodells.net/dellrestore/image.htm">
Inside the Dell PC Restore Partition</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-16</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.goodells.net/dellrestore/vista.htm">
Inside the Dell PC Restore Partition</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-16</link>.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://support.toshiba.ca/support/techsupport/tsbs/all/-TSB001019.htm">
How to Create/Use a Toshiba Recovery CD/DVD-ROM</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-16</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</image>
</representation>
</article>
