<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:41:45[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Spamdexing</title>
<id>43651</id>
<revision>
<id>243664508</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-07T14:58:31Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>FrankRizzo2006</username>
<id>4364763</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Black hat seo</category>
<category>Search engine optimization</category>
<category>Spamming</category>
<category>World Wide Web</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For spam on Wikipedia, see  and 
<b>Spamdexing</b> involves a number of methods, such as repeating unrelated phrases, to manipulate the relevancy or prominence of resources indexed by a <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
, in a manner inconsistent with the purpose of the indexing system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>
Some consider it to be a part of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/187946.xml">
search engine optimization</link>, though there are many search engine optimization methods that improve the quality and appearance of the content of web sites and serve content useful to many users.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Search engines use a variety of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s to determine relevancy ranking. Some of these include determining whether the search term appears in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/20556.xml">
META</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/6118940.xml">
keyword</link>s tag, others whether the search term appears in the <link>
body text</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link> of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/34063.xml">
web page</link>. Many search engines check for instances of spamdexing and will remove suspect pages from their indexes. Also, people working for a search-engine organization can quickly block the results-listing from entire websites that use spamdexing, perhaps alerted by user complaints of false matches. The rise of spamdexing in the mid-1990s made the leading search engines of the time less useful.  <p>

The success of <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 at both producing better search results and combating keyword spamming, through its reputation-based <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/23724.xml">
PageRank</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 link analysis system, helped it become the dominant search site late in the 1990s. Although it has not been rendered useless by spamdexing, Google has not been immune to more sophisticated methods. <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/286747.xml">
Google bomb</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
ing is another form of search engine result manipulation, which involves placing hyperlinks that directly affect the rank of other sites.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Google first algorithmically combated Google bombing on January 25, 2007.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

The earliest known reference<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> to the term <it>spamdexing</it> is by Eric Convey in his article "Porn sneaks way back on Web," <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/4171.xml">
The Boston Herald</link>, May 22, 1996, where he said:</p>
<p>

The problem arises when site operators load their Web pages with hundreds of extraneous terms so search engines will list them among legitimate addresses.</p>
<p>

The process is called "spamdexing," a combination of spamming — the Internet term for sending users unsolicited information — and "indexing." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Common spamdexing techniques can be classified into two broad classes: <it>content spam</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> (or <it>term spam</it>) and <it>link spam</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Content spam</st>
<p>

These techniques involve altering the logical view that a search engine has over the page's contents. They all aim at variants of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/1256134.xml">
vector space model</link> for information retrieval on text collections.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/1789102.xml">
Keyword stuffing</link> : This involves the calculated placement of keywords within a page to raise the keyword count, variety, and density of the page. This is useful to make a page appear to be relevant for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/33120.xml">
web crawler</link> in a way that makes it more likely to be found. Example: A promoter of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/47185.xml">
Ponzi scheme</link> wants to attract web surfers to a site where he advertises his scam. He places hidden text appropriate for a fan page of a popular music group on his page, hoping that the page will be listed as a fan site and receive many visits from music lovers. Older versions of indexing programs simply counted how often a keyword appeared, and used that to determine relevance levels. Most modern search engines have the ability to analyze a page for keyword stuffing and determine whether the frequency is consistent with other sites created specifically to attract search engine traffic.  Also, large webpages are truncated, so that massive dictionary lists cannot be indexed on a single webpage.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/1102959.xml">
Hidden or invisible</link> unrelated text : Disguising keywords and phrases by making them the same color as the background, using a tiny font size, or hiding them within <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 code such as "no frame" sections, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/2549393.xml">
ALT attributes</link>, zero-width/height DIVs, and "no script" sections. However, hidden text is not always spamdexing: it can also be used to enhance <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/302109.xml">
accessibility</link>.  People screening websites for a search-engine company might temporarily or permanently block an entire website for having invisible text on some webpages.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/20556.xml">
Meta tag</link> stuffing : Repeating keywords in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/20556.xml">
Meta tag</link>s, and using meta keywords that are unrelated to the site's content. This tactic has been ineffective since 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 "Gateway" or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/594839.xml">
doorway page</link>s : Creating low-quality web pages that contain very little content but are instead stuffed with very similar keywords and phrases. They are designed to rank highly within the search results, but serve no purpose to visitors looking for information. A doorway page will generally have "click here to enter" on the page.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/3152572.xml">
Scraper site</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
s : Scraper sites, also known as <it>Made for AdSense</it> sites, are created using various programs designed to 'scrape' search-engine results pages or other sources of content and create 'content' for a website.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  The specific presentation of content on these sites is unique, but is merely an amalgamation of content taken from other sources, often without permission. These types of websites are generally full of advertising (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1027207.xml">
pay-per-click</link> ads<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>), or redirect the user to other sites.  Some scraper sites have even outranked an original website for its own information and organization name. </entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Link spam</st>
<p>

Davison defines link spam (which he calls "nepotistic links") as "... links between pages that are present for reasons
other than merit." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Link spam takes advantage of link-based ranking algorithms, such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
's <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/23724.xml">
PageRank</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 algorithm, which gives a higher ranking to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link> the more other highly ranked websites link to it. These techniques also aim at influencing other link-based ranking techniques such as the <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/1851223.xml">
HITS algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/270213.xml">
Link farm</link>s : Involves creating tightly-knit communities of pages referencing each other, also known humorously as <it>mutual admiration societies</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Hidden links : Putting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/49547.xml">
link</link>s where visitors will not see them in order to increase <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/210641.xml">
link popularity</link>.  Highlighted link text can help rank a webpage higher for matching that phrase.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/8728576.xml">
Sybil attack</link>" : This is the forging of multiple identities for malicious intent, named after the famous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/39653.xml">
multiple personality disorder</link> patient "Sybil" (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/4003535.xml">
Shirley Ardell Mason</link></creator>
</scholar>
</artist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
). A spammer may create multiple web sites at different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/39878.xml">
domain name</link>s that all link to each other, such as fake blogs known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/2501302.xml">
spam blog</link>s.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/2501302.xml">
Spam blog</link>s : Spam blogs, also known as <it>splogs</it>, are fake blogs created solely for spamming. They are similar in nature to link farms.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Spam Canoe : This refers to the process in which a “boat” full of spam is sent out towards the intended target. When this canoe reaches “land” or the intended website or net address it will unload and overwhelm its target. This can often overload different web browsers and slow down computers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/3648363.xml">
Page hijacking</link> : This is achieved by creating a rogue copy of a popular website which shows contents similar to the original to a web crawler but redirects web surfers to unrelated or malicious websites.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Buying expired domains : Some link spammers monitor DNS records for domains that will expire soon, then buy them when they expire and replace the pages with links to their pages. <it>See</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/4512227.xml">
Domaining</link>. However Google resets the link data on expired domains.</entry>
</list>

Some of these techniques may be applied for creating a <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/286747.xml">
Google bomb</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
, this is, to cooperate with other users to boost the ranking of a particular page for a particular query.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/19124983.xml">
Cookie stuffing</link> : This involves placing an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/703758.xml">
affiliate</link> tracking cookie on a website visitor's computer without their knowledge, which will then generate revenue for the person doing the cookie stuffing.  This not only generates fraudulent affiliate sales, but also has the potential to overwrite other affiliates' cookies, essentially stealing their legitimately earned commissions.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Subscript text=== Using world-writable pages ===</p>
<p>

Web sites that can be edited by users, such as Wikis, blogs that allow comments to be posted, etc. can be used to insert links to spam sites if the appropriate anti-spam measures are not taken.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/528830.xml">
Spam in blogs</link> : This is the placing or solicitation of links randomly on other sites, placing a desired keyword into the hyperlinked text of the inbound link. Guest books, forums, blogs, and any site that accepts visitors' comments are particular targets and are often victims of drive-by spamming where automated software creates nonsense posts with links that are usually irrelevant and unwanted.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 Comment spam : Comment spam is a form of link spam that has arisen in web pages that allow dynamic user editing such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/32851.xml">
wikis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/33645.xml">
blogs</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/990224.xml">
guestbooks</link>.  It can be problematic because <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/430106.xml">
agents</link> can be written that automatically randomly select a user edited web page, such as a Wikipedia article, and add spamming links.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <b>Wiki spam</b> : Using the open editability of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/32851.xml">
wiki</link> systems to place links from the wiki site to the spam site. The subject of the spam site is often unrelated to the wiki page where the link is added. In early 2005, <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/5043734.xml">
Wikipedia</link></web_site>
 implemented a default '<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/3766084.xml">
nofollow</link>' value for the 'rel' HTML attribute. Links with this attribute are ignored by Google's <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/23724.xml">
PageRank</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 algorithm. Forum and Wiki admins can use these to discourage Wiki spam.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/1376814.xml">
Referrer log spamming</link> : When someone accesses a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/34063.xml">
web page</link>, i.e. the referee, by following a link from another web page, i.e. the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/5258885.xml">
referrer</link>, the referee is given the address of the referrer by the person's internet browser. Some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
website</link>s have a referrer log which shows which pages link to that site. By having a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/1569607.xml">
robot</link> randomly access many sites enough times, with a message or specific address given as the referrer, that message or internet address then appears in the referrer log of those sites that have referrer logs.  Since some <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
s base the importance of sites by the number of different sites linking to them, referrer-log spam may be used to increase the search engine rankings of the spammer's sites, by getting the referrer logs of many sites to link to them.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Other types of spamdexing</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/371038.xml">
Mirror websites</link> : Hosting of multiple websites all with conceptually similar content but using different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link>s.  Some search engines give a higher rank to results where the keyword searched for appears in the URL.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/636686.xml">
URL redirection</link> : Taking the user to another page without his or her intervention, e.g. using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/1753130.xml">
META refresh</link> tags, <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
, <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/9845.xml">
JavaScript</link></programming_language>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/351543.xml">
Server side redirect</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/418364.xml">
Cloaking</link> : Cloaking refers to any of several means to serve a page to the search-engine <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/33120.xml">
spider</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 that is different from that seen by human users. It can be an attempt to mislead search engines regarding the content on a particular web site. Cloaking, however, can also be used to ethically increase accessibility of a site to users with disabilities or provide human users with content that search engines aren't able to process or parse. It is also used to deliver content based on a user's location; Google itself uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/11170029.xml">
IP delivery</link>, a form of cloaking, to deliver results. Another form of cloaking is <it>code swapping</it>, i.e., optimizing a page for top ranking and then swapping another page in its place once a top ranking is achieved.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/11486091.xml">
Adversarial information retrieval</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/286747.xml">
Google bomb</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/270213.xml">
Link farm</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/2193171.xml">
TrustRank</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/3648363.xml">
302 Google Jacking</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/7602386.xml">
Index (search engine)</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 — overview of search engine indexing technology</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
  "Word Spy - spamdexing" (definition), March 2003, webpage:
  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wordspy.com/words/spamdexing.asp">
WordSpy-spamdexing</weblink>.
</entry>
<entry id="2">
Gyöngyi 2005</entry>
<entry id="3">
Ntoulas</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.firstmonday.org/issues/issue10_10/tatum/index.html">
Deconstructing Google bombs</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.com/2007/01/quick-word-about-googlebombs.html">
A quick word about Googlebombs</weblink>, January 2007</entry>
<entry id="6">
   "Scraper sites, spam and Google" (tactics/motives),
   Googlerankings.com diagnostics, 2007, webpage:
   <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://diagnostics.googlerankings.com/scraper-sites.html">
GR-SS</weblink>.
</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite id="CITEREFDavison2000" style="font-style:normal"><link>
Davison, Brian</link>&#32;(2000),&#32;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cse.lehigh.edu/~brian/pubs/2000/aaaiws/aaai2000ws.pdf">
"Recognizing Nepotistic Links on the Web"</weblink>,&#32;<it>AAAI-2000 workshop on Artificial Intelligence for Web Search</it>, Boston: AAAI Press, pp. 23–28</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www2.sims.berkeley.edu/courses/is141/f05/lectures/se-course-intro.pdf">
http://www2.sims.berkeley.edu/courses/is141/f05/lectures/se-course-intro.pdf</weblink><message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link></format>
</language>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;(1.55&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/60727.xml">
MiB</link>)</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal"><link>
Mishne, Gilad</link>;&#32;David Carmel and Ronny Lempel&#32;(2005 accessdate=2007-10-24). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://airweb.cse.lehigh.edu/2005/mishne.pdf">
Blocking Blog Spam with Language Model Disagreement</weblink>".&#32;<it>Proceedings of the First International Workshop on Adversarial Information Retrieval on the Web</it>. Retrieved on <link>
2007-10-24</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<ss1>
<st>
To report spamdexed pages</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Found on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/contact/spamreport.html">
Google search engine</weblink> results</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Found on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://help.yahoo.com/l/us/yahoo/search/spam_abuse.html">
Yahoo! search engine</weblink> results</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Search engine help pages for webmasters</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Google's <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/support/webmasters/bin/answer.py?answer=35769">
Webmaster Guidelines page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Yahoo!'s <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://help.yahoo.com/help/us/ysearch/indexing/index.html">
Search Engine Indexing page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

heloow Webmaster Tools]</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other tools and information for webmasters</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://airweb.cse.lehigh.edu/">
AIRWeb series of workshops on Adversarial Information Retrieval on the Web</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tool.motoricerca.info/spam-detector/">
Online tool that detects spam techniques on web pages</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gearhack.com/Articles/FightSpam/">
A list of open proxy and bot IP's.</weblink> Ban IP's on this list to prevent comment spam. Updated weekly.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gearhack.com/Forums/DisplayComments.php?file=Computer/Network/Internet/Protecting_Your_Wiki_From_Spam.html">
Protecting Your Wiki From Spam</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Spam Detecting <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://e-book-archive.blogspot.com/">
Book</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<practice wordnetid="100410247" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/28368.xml">
Spamming</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</practice>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link>
History</link>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/5200065.xml">
Network Abuse Clearinghouse</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/630770.xml">
Protocol</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
s</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;font-weight:normal;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/459847.xml">
E-mail</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.5em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/527353.xml">
Address munging</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/10748488.xml">
Bulk email software</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/4884478.xml">
Directory Harvest Attack</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/153977.xml">
DNSBL</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/1466663.xml">
Spambot</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/13497047.xml">
Pink contract</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;font-weight:normal;;" class="navbox-group">
Other</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.5em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/179958.xml">
Autodialer</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/2067563.xml">
Flyposting</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/712475.xml">
Junk fax</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/394592.xml">
Messaging</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/394616.xml">
Mobile phone</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/394596.xml">
Newsgroup</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/162180.xml">
Telemarketing</link>&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/1017252.xml">
VoIP</link></concept>
</idea>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/313737.xml">
Anti-spam</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/1626908.xml">
Disposable e-mail address</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/1497388.xml">
E-mail authentication</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/2064989.xml">
SORBS</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/1905427.xml">
SpamCop</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/1267954.xml">
Spamhaus</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/5718790.xml">
List poisoning</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/515929.xml">
Bayesian spam filtering</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/15252288.xml">
Policy block list</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/43651.xml">
Spamdexing</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/1789102.xml">
Keyword stuffing</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/286747.xml">
Google bomb</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·   <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/3152572.xml">
Scraper site</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/270213.xml">
Link farm</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/714684.xml">
Webring</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/418364.xml">
Cloaking</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/594839.xml">
Doorway page</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/636686.xml">
URL redirection</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/2501302.xml">
Spam blog</link>s&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/2791084.xml">
Sping</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/4803822.xml">
Forum spam</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/528830.xml">
Blog spam</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/4927965.xml">
Social networking spam</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/1376814.xml">
Referer spam</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/805626.xml">
Internet fraud</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/46526.xml">
Advance fee fraud</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/1093010.xml">
Lottery scam</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/17362858.xml">
Make Money Fast</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/12512849.xml">
Microcap stock fraud</link>&nbsp;·  <accomplishment wordnetid="100035189" confidence="0.8">
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<transgression wordnetid="100745005" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<crime wordnetid="100766234" confidence="0.8">
<wrongdoing wordnetid="100732746" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<feat wordnetid="100036762" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/428364.xml">
Phishing</link></activity>
</feat>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</wrongdoing>
</crime>
</event>
</transgression>
</occupation>
</accomplishment>
&nbsp;·  <accomplishment wordnetid="100035189" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<feat wordnetid="100036762" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/6002126.xml">
Vishing</link></feat>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</event>
</concept>
</idea>
</accomplishment>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
