<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:03:26[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<substance  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100020090">
<diet  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107561112">
<food  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021265">
<fare  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107560652">
<header>
<title>Zone diet</title>
<id>437978</id>
<revision>
<id>244430203</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T19:34:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Synthebot</username>
<id>3658625</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Diets</category>
<category>Low-carb diets</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Zone diet</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/8460.xml">
diet</link> popularized in books by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/306081.xml">
biochemist</link> <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<dietician wordnetid="110012484" confidence="0.8">
<specialist wordnetid="110631941" confidence="0.8">
<biochemist wordnetid="109854915" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<chemist wordnetid="109913824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/3821175.xml">
Barry Sears</link></chemist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biochemist>
</specialist>
</dietician>
</person>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
. It advocates consuming calories from carbohydrates, protein and fat in a ratio of 40%/30%/30%. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<sec>
<st>
 Theory </st>
<p>

The diet centers on a "40:30:30" ratio of calories obtained daily from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/5932.xml">
carbohydrate</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
fat</link>s, respectively.  The ideal formula has been under debate, although studies over the past several years (including a non-scientific study by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/1574304.xml">
PBS</link> documentary show <it><diversion wordnetid="100426928" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<show wordnetid="100520257" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<entertainment wordnetid="100429048" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/342761.xml">
Scientific American Frontiers</link></activity>
</entertainment>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</show>
</event>
</diversion>
</it>) have shown that it can produce weight loss at reasonable rates. The <it>Scientific American Frontiers</it> study compared the effectiveness of several popular 'diet' regimes including the Zone; somewhat to the surprise of the show's staff, the participants on the Zone experienced the greatest fat loss while simultaneously gaining muscle mass. Participants also reported the Zone as the easiest regime to adjust to, i.e. having the fewest adverse affects such as fatigue or hunger.  Most people who report fatigue find that the fatigue diminishes by day 2 or 3.</p>
<p>

"The Zone" is Sears' term for proper <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/13311.xml">
hormone</link> balance. When <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/14895.xml">
insulin</link> levels are neither too high nor too low, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../953/249953.xml">
glucagon</link> levels are not too high, then specific anti-inflammatory chemicals (types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/631312.xml">
eicosanoids</link>) are released, which have similar effects to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/1525.xml">
aspirin</link>, but without downsides such as gastric bleeding. Sears claims that a 30:40 ratio of protein to carbohydrates triggers this effect, and this is called 'The Zone.' Sears claims that these natural anti-inflammatories are heart and health friendly.</p>
<p>

Additionally, the human body in caloric balance is more efficient and does not have to store excess calories as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
fat</link>. The human body cannot store fat and burn fat at the same time, and Sears believes it takes time (significant time if insulin levels were high because of unbalanced eating) to switch from the former to the latter.  Using stored fat for energy causes weight loss.</p>
<p>

Another key feature of the Zone diet, introduced in his later books, is an intake of a particular ratio of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/22594.xml">
Omega-3</link> to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/681218.xml">
Omega-6</link> fatty acids. Dr. Sears is believed to have popularized the taking of pharmaceutical-grade Omega 3 fish oils.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Hormonal paradoxes</st>
<p>

Sears emphasizes a hormonal paradox contrary to the "low-fat" rationale, namely that low-fat diets increase the production of the hormone insulin, causing the body to store more fat. The example proposed by him is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/5307.xml">
cattle</link> ranching practice of fattening livestock efficiently by feeding them lots of low-fat grain. He and others also point out the supposed irony that human diets in the West for the last twenty years have been full of low-fat carbohydrates, yet people are considered more obese now.</p>
<p>

Additionally, Sears suggests fat consumption as <it>essential</it> for "burning" fat. </p>
<p>

His rationale is: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/1051404.xml">
Monounsaturated fat</link>s in a meal contribute to a feeling of fullness and decrease the rate at which carbohydrates are absorbed into the bloodstream.  Slower carbohydrate absorption means lower insulin levels which means less stored fat and a faster transition to fat burning.  If the body needs energy and can't burn fat because of high insulin levels, a person feels tired as their brain starves and metabolism slows to compensate.  This occurs because the brain runs on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/12950.xml">
glucose</link> and high insulin levels deplete blood glucose levels. Such a condition, rebound <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/13315.xml">
hypoglycemia</link>, causes sweet cravings (which just starts the high-insulin cycle all over again).</p>
<p>

Sears describes a Zone meal as follows: "Eat as much protein as the palm of your hand, as much nonstarchy raw vegetables as you can stand for the vitamins, enough carbohydrates to maintain mental clarity because the brain runs on glucose, and enough monounsaturated oils to keep feelings of hunger away."</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Comparison to low-carb diets</st>
<p>

The Zone is considered a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/459560.xml">
low-carb diet</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> It is not as restrictive in total carbohydrate intake as some of the other low-carbohydrate diets (e.g. the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/84121.xml">
Atkins diet</link></commodity>
</merchandise>
</artifact>
) that became extremely popular throughout the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 in 2003 and 2004. Sears claims these other diets miss the point. According to him, they ignore the importance of hormonal balance, as well as the influence of dietary balance on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/165423.xml">
digestion</link> and hormone production.  </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Specific cases</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Italy</st>
<p>

The introduction of the Zone in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/14532.xml">
Italy</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 began in 1997 by a physician, Aronne Romano M.D. who applied this nutritional style to patients and athletes. Since the 2nd edition of the book "Come Raggiungere la Zona" (The Zone), in 1999, the Chef Memo Romano and his brother Aronne modified the original recipes and menu to suit the local food and habits.  </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Famous obesity case</st>
<p>

Possibly the most famous case of someone using the diet effectively has been <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/9459826.xml">
Manuel Uribe</link>. After weighing in at around 560 kg (1234 lbs or over 88 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/679929.xml">
stone</link>) but within 2 years had lost about 184 kg. (Now he weighs 376 kg).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
After decades of failed weight-loss methods, including a botched liposuction that nearly killed him, devotion to the Zone Diet has been the only weight-loss program to have such a positive impact on the man, whose weight once topped 1,200 lbs. Dr. Barry Sears, along with two of Mexico's most prestigious physicians , Dr. Silvia Orozco Avina and Dr. Gustavo Orozco Avina, are at the helm of the interdisciplinary team of doctors, nutritionists and exercise physiologists who continue to work diligently to help Manuel reach his goal. </p>
<p>

Manuel's current diet consists of about 2,000 calories per day broken up into six meals. His specially-designed menu includes a wide variety of meals including egg-white omelets, fresh salads, chicken fajitas and fish filet in a bed of spring greens. In fact, Manuel's biggest problem is not lack of appetite control, but eating all the food he is supposed to eat. </p>
<p>

Despite his weight, Dr. Sears considers Manuel one of the healthiest men in Mexico. He is not at risk for diabetes, and his blood pressure and triglyceride levels are normal. In addition, his resting heart rate averages 62 beats per minute, a level usually found in trained athletes. Even though Manuel is confined to his bed, his medical team designed a tailored exercise regimen that includes sit-ups, pull-ups and hand-biking to help build muscle mass and accelerate fat loss.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Famous followers</st>
<p>

Several Hollywood stars, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/39942.xml">
Jennifer Aniston</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/204352.xml">
Renee Zellweger</link>, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/265422.xml">
Cindy Crawford</link></model>
</person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/278119.xml">
Charlie Sheen</link></actor>
</person>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/43356.xml">
Tiger Woods</link>, and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/31460.xml">
Tom Cruise</link></actor>
</person>
 are believed to have followed the Zone diet.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/581673.xml">
American Heart Association</link> does not recommend the Zone Diet due to high protein, lack of essential nutrients, and little information on long-term effects.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> However, Sears believes the characterization of the Zone diet as 'high-protein' is inaccurate. In his book, he advocates a formula based on lean body mass and activity level to determine the appropriate daily intake of protein. For example, a female of average height and average build who has a moderately active lifestyle is encouraged to eat around 60g of protein daily.</p>
<p>

Most <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/32591.xml">
vegetarian</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/32587.xml">
vegan</link> diets, according to Sears, are highly dissimilar from The Zone because they generally utilize very little protein relative to carbohydrate consumption. This, says Sears, prohibits the body from operating truly efficiently.  As critical as Sears is of vegetarian and vegan diets, individuals who promote a vegetarian diet are also very critical of aspects of the Zone and similar diets.  In 2000 Dr. Sears published the Soy Zone where he outlined a zone diet based around soy protein, making it more vegetarian-friendly.</p>
<p>

Other nutritional experts, including some of Sears' former colleagues, are critical of his conclusions from the scientific evidence, contending that he has distorted or exaggerated the meaning of much of the basic research. They point out that no direct studies to verify his conclusions have been performed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Official Zone books</st>
<p>

<b>(Partial list)</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sears, Barry&#32;(1995). The Zone: A Dietary Road Map.&#32;HarperCollins Publishers. ISBN 0060987065.</cite>&nbsp; Sears's initial book on the Zone diet.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sears, Barry&#32;(1997). Mastering the Zone.&#32;HarperCollins Publishers. ISBN 006101124X.</cite>&nbsp; Sears urges substitution of raw vegetables for pastas, breads and refined sugars. More diagrams and flowcharts than in <it>The Zone</it>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sears, Barry&#32;(1999). The Anti-Aging Zone.&#32;Regan Books. ISBN 0060392436.</cite>&nbsp; Information on meditation, relaxation and exercise in addition to diet.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sears, Barry;&#32;Kotz, Deborah&#32;(2000). A Week in the Zone: A Quick Course in the Healthiest Diet for You.&#32;Regan Books. ISBN 0060741902.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sears, Barry&#32;(2000). The Soy Zone.&#32;Regan Books. ISBN 0060393106.</cite>&nbsp; Discusses Sears preference for soy protein as part of his balanced eating program. "The longest-living people in the world" living in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/22477.xml">
Okinawa</link>, Japan consume much greater amounts of soy protein and eat smaller meals than most other people.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sears, Barry&#32;(2002). The Omega Rx Zone: The Miracle of the New High-Dose Fish Oil.&#32;Regan Books. ISBN 0060393130.</cite>&nbsp; Discusses "high-dose fish oil;" a newly-introduced invented pharmaceutical-grade fish oil that Sears touts as a medical miracle that will put the eicasonids in balance and reduce inflammation. Extra virgin olive oil is also promoted for its phytochemicals.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Sears, Barry&#32;(2005). The Anti-Inflammation Zone: Reversing the Silent Epidemic That's Destroying Our Health.&#32;Regan Books. ISBN 0060834145.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/639924.xml">
Diet (nutrition)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/84252.xml">
List of diets</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/19498762.xml">
Low-carb tortilla</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<diet wordnetid="107561112" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<fare wordnetid="107560652" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/8095528.xml">
Medical research related to low-carbohydrate diets</link></fare>
</food>
</diet>
</substance>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,257620,00.html">
FOXNews.com - Mexico's 'Half-Ton Man' Sheds Nearly 400 Poundsgenerated title --&amp;gt;</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/Anti-Inflammation-Zone-Reversing-Epidemic-Destroying/dp/0060595469">
Amazon.com: The Anti-Inflammation Zone: Reversing the Silent Epidemic That's Destroying Our Health: Books: Barry Sears</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.annecollins.com/zone-diet.htm">
Anne Collins - Short Review of Barry Sears Zone High Protein Low Carb Weight Loss Diet Program</weblink> Retrieved on October 25, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.manueluribe.com/manuel/">
Manuel Uribe</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-15</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.americanheart.org/presenter.jhtml?identifier=11234">
High-Protein Diets</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.webmd.com/diet/zone-what-it-is">
The Zone Diet</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ZoneDiet.com">
Official Website of the Zone Diet</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.drsears.com">
Dr. Barry Sears' Official Website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.anti-aging-guide.org/history-of-zone-diet.html">
History of The Zone Diet</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.433zonediet.com/">
Zone Diet Guide</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.the-zone-diet-recipes.com/">
Collection of Zone Diet Recipes</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.enterthezonediet.com/">
The definitive guide to The Zone Diet</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</fare>
</food>
</diet>
</substance>
</article>
