<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:14:23[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Pairwise comparison</title>
<id>4395832</id>
<revision>
<id>236652214</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-06T13:38:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Patrick</username>
<id>4388</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Psychometrics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Pairwise comparison</b> generally refers to any process of comparing entities in pairs to judge which of each pair is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/170162.xml">
preferred</link>, or has a greater amount of some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/861437.xml">
quantitative</link> property. The method of pairwise comparison is used in the scientific study of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/170162.xml">
preference</link>s, attitudes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/32561.xml">
voting systems</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/1745670.xml">
social choice</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/51256.xml">
public choice</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/938833.xml">
multiagent AI system</link>s.  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
psychology</link> literature, it is often referred to as <b>paired comparison</b>.<p>

Prominent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/24982.xml">
psychometrician</link> <link>
L. L. Thurstone</link> first introduced a scientific approach to using pairwise comparisons for measurement in 1927, which he referred to as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/2251120.xml">
Law of comparative judgment</link>. Thurstone linked this approach to psychophysical theory developed by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/748976.xml">
Ernst Heinrich Weber</link></scientist>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/203499.xml">
Gustav Fechner</link>.  Thurstone demonstrated that the method can be used to order items along a dimension such as preference or importance using an interval-type scale. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>
<p>

If a <link>
decision agent</link>, such as an individual or organization or even an agent within a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/938833.xml">
multiagent AI system</link>, must express a preference between two <link>
mutually distinct</link> alternatives to meet some objective, this preference can be expressed as a pairwise comparison.  If the two alternatives are x and y, the following are the possible pairwise comparisons:</p>
<p>

The agent prefers x over y: "x&amp;gt;y" or "xPy" </p>
<p>

The agent prefers y over x: "y&amp;gt;x" or "yPx"</p>
<p>

The agent is indifferent between both alternatives: "x=y" or "xIy"</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Probabilistic models for pairwise comparison</st>
<p>

In terms of modern psychometric theory, Thurstone's approach, called the law of comparative judgment, is more aptly regarded as a measurement model. The Bradley-Terry-Luce (BTL) model (Bradley &amp; Terry, 1952; Luce, 1959) is often applied to pairwise comparison data to scale preferences. The BTL model is identical to Thurstone's model if the simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/84563.xml">
logistic function</link> is used. Thurstone used the normal distribution in applications of the model. The simple logistic function varies by less than 0.01 from the cumulative normal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/350878.xml">
ogive</link> across the range, given an arbitrary scale factor.</p>
<p>

In the BTL model, the probability that object <it>j</it> is judged to have more of an attribute than object <it>i</it> is:</p>
<p>

<math>
\Pr \{X_{ji}=1\} =\frac{e^{{\delta_j} - {\delta_i}}}{1 + e^{{\delta_j} - {\delta_i}}},
</math></p>
<p>

where <math>\delta_i</math> is the scale location of object <it>i</it>. For example, the scale location might represent the perceived quality of a product, or the perceived weight of an object.</p>
<p>

The BTL is very closely related to the <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/2161615.xml">
Rasch model</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 for measurement. </p>
<p>

Thurstone used the method of pairwise comparisons as an approach to measuring perceived intensity of physical stimuli, attitudes, preferences, choices, and values. He also studied implications of the theory he developed for opinion polls and political voting (Thurstone, 1959).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Transitivity of pairwise comparisons</st>
<p>

For a given decision agent, if the information, objective, and alternatives used by the agent remain constant, then it is generally assumed that pairwise comparisons over those alternatives by the decision agent are transitive.  Most agree upon what transitivity is, though there is debate about the transitivity of indifference. The rules of transitivity are as follows for a given decision agent.</p>
<p>

If xPy and yPz, then xPz</p>
<p>

If xPy and yIz, then xPz</p>
<p>

If xIy and yPz, then xPz</p>
<p>

If xIy and yIz, then xIz</p>
<p>

This corresponds to (xPy or xIy) being a <link>
total preorder</link>, P being the corresponding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/828131.xml">
strict weak order</link>, and I being the corresponding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/9259.xml">
equivalence relation</link>.</p>
<p>

Probabilistic models require transitivity only within the bounds of errors of estimates of scale locations of entities. Thus, decisions need not be deterministically transitive in order to apply probabilistic models. However, transitivity will generally hold for a large number of comparisons if models such as the BTL can be effectively applied.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Argument for intransitivity of indifference</st>
<p>

Some contend that indifference is not transitive.  Consider the following example.  Suppose you like apples and you prefer apples that are larger.  Now suppose there exists an apple A, an apple B, and an apple C which have identical intrinsic characteristics except for the following. Suppose B is larger than A, but it is not discernible without an extremely sensitive scale.  Further suppose C is larger than B, but this also is not discernible without an extremely sensitive scale.  However, the difference in sizes between apples A and C is large enough that you can discern that C is larger than A without a sensitive scale. In psychophysical terms, the size difference between A and C is above the just noticeable difference ('jnd') while the size differences between A and B and B and C are below the jnd.</p>
<p>

You are confronted with the three apples in pairs without the benefit of a sensitive scale.  Therefore, when presented A and B alone, you are indifferent between apple A and apple B; and you are indifferent between apple B and apple C when presented B and C alone.  However, when the pair A and C are shown, you prefer C over A.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Preference orders</st>
<p>

If pairwise comparisons are in fact transitive in respect to the four mentioned rules, then pairwise comparisons for a list of alternatives (A1, A2, A3,...,An-1, and An) can take the form:</p>
<p>

A1(&amp;gt;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/105979.xml">
XOR</link>=)A2(&amp;gt;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/105979.xml">
XOR</link>=)A3(&amp;gt;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/105979.xml">
XOR</link>=)...(&amp;gt;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/105979.xml">
XOR</link>=)An-1(&amp;gt;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/105979.xml">
XOR</link>=)An</p>
<p>

For example, if there are three alternatives <math>a</math>, <math>b</math>, and <math>c</math> then the possible preference orders are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>a&amp;gt;b&amp;gt;c</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>a&amp;gt;c&amp;gt;b</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>b&amp;gt;a&amp;gt;c</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>b&amp;gt;c&amp;gt;a</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>c&amp;gt;a&amp;gt;b</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>c&amp;gt;b&amp;gt;a</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>a&amp;gt;b=c</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>b=c&amp;gt;a</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>b&amp;gt;a=c</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>a=c&amp;gt;b</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>c&amp;gt;a=b</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>a=b&amp;gt;c</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<math>a=b=c</math></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

If the number of alternatives is n, and indifference is not allowed, then the number of possible preference orders for any given n-value is n!.  If indifference is allowed, then the number of possible preference orders is the <series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="107938773" confidence="0.8">
<sequence wordnetid="108459252" confidence="0.8">
<ordering wordnetid="108456993" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link>
number of total preorders</link></group>
</ordering>
</sequence>
</arrangement>
</series>
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Strict_weak_ordering#The_number_of_total_preorders. It can be expressed as a function of n:</p>
<p>

<math>\sum_{k=1}^n k!*S_2(n,k)</math>, where S2(n, k) is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/2229292.xml">
Stirling number of the second kind</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bradley, R.A. and Terry, M.E. (1952). Rank analysis of incomplete block designs, I. the method of paired comparisons. <it>Biometrika</it>, 39, 324-345.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

David, H.A. (1988). The Method of Paired Comparisons. New York: Oxford University Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Luce, R.D. (1959). <it>Individual Choice Behaviours</it>: A Theoretical Analysis. New York: J. Wiley.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Thurstone, L.L. (1927).  A law of comparative judgement. <it>Psychological Review</it>, 34, 278-286.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Thurstone, L.L. (1929).  <it>The Measurement of Psychological Value</it>.  In T.V. Smith and W.K. Wright (Eds.), Essays in Philosophy by Seventeen Doctors of Philosophy of the 	University of Chicago.  Chicago: Open Court.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Thurstone, L.L. (1959).  <it>The Measurement of Values</it>.  Chicago: The University of Chicago Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources</st>

<p>

http://www.research.att.com/~njas/sequences/A000142</p>
<p>

http://www.research.att.com/~njas/sequences/A000670 </p>
<p>

Y. Chevaleyre, P.E. Dunne, U. Endriss, J. Lang, M. Lemaître, N. Maudet, J. Padget, S. Phelps, J.A. Rodríguez-Aguilar, and P. Sousa. Issues in Multiagent Resource Allocation. Informatica , 30:3-31, 2006. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/2251120.xml">
Law of comparative judgment</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/584962.xml">
Scaling</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
