<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:04:48[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Sequence motif</title>
<id>443294</id>
<revision>
<id>243833938</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T06:41:07Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Michael Hardy</username>
<id>4626</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing context</category>
<category>Wikipedia introduction cleanup</category>
<category>Bioinformatics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The introduction to this article provides <b>insufficient context</b> for those unfamiliar with the subject.
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Sequence_motif&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink> with a .</col>
</row>
</table>


In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/12266.xml">
genetics</link>, a <b>sequence motif</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/21505.xml">
nucleotide</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino-acid</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/27838.xml">
sequence</link> pattern that is widespread and has, or is conjectured to have, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biological</link> significance. For proteins, a sequence motif is distinguished from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/443318.xml">
structural motif</link>, a motif formed by the three dimensional arrangement of amino acids, which may not be adjacent.<p>

An example is the <link>
<it>N</it>-glycosylation</link> site motif:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <it>Asn, followed by anything but Pro, followed by either Ser or Thr, followed by anything but Pro</it>
</indent>

where the three-letter abbreviations are the conventional designations for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link>s (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/12385.xml">
genetic code</link>).</p>

<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>

<p>

When a sequence motif appears in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/10238.xml">
exon</link> of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/4250553.xml">
gene</link>, it may <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/12385.xml">
encode</link> the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/443318.xml">
structural motif</link>" of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link>; that is a stereotypical element of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
overall structure</link> of the protein. Nevertheless, motifs need not be associated with a distinctive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/28691.xml">
secondary structure</link>. "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/44284.xml">
Noncoding</link>" sequences are not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/262401.xml">
translated</link> into proteins, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/21496.xml">
nucleic acid</link>s with such motifs need not deviate from the typical shape (e.g. the "B-form" <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
DNA</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
double helix</link>).</p>
<p>

Outside of gene exons, there exist <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/240060.xml">
regulatory sequence</link> motifs</b> and motifs within the "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/44297.xml">
junk</link>," such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/577446.xml">
satellite DNA</link>. Some of these are believed to affect the shape of nucleic acids (see for example <link>
RNA self-splicing</link>), but this is only sometimes the case. For example, many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/966654.xml">
DNA binding protein</link>s that have affinities for specific motifs only bind DNA in its double-helical form. They are able to recognize motifs through contact with the double helix's major or minor groove. </p>
<p>

Short coding motifs, which appear to lack secondary structure, include those that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/423424.xml">
label</link> proteins for delivery to particular parts of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/4230.xml">
cell</link>, or mark them for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/58894.xml">
phosphorylation</link>.</p>
<p>

Within a  sequence or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> of sequences, researchers search and find motifs using computer-based techniques of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/235550.xml">
sequence analysis</link>, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/363695.xml">
BLAST</link>. Such techniques belong to the discipline of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link>.</p>
<p>

See also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/767937.xml">
consensus sequence</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Motif bioinformatics</st>

<p>

Consider the <it>N</it>-glycosylation site motif mentioned above:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <it>Asn, followed by anything but Pro, followed by either Ser or Thr, followed by anything but Pro</it>
</indent>

This pattern may be written as <b>N{P}[ST]{P}</b> where N = Asn, P = Pro, S = Ser, T = Thr; {X} means any amino acid except X; and [XY] means either X or Y.</p>
<p>

The notation [XY] does not give any indication of the probability of X or Y occurring in the pattern. Sometimes patterns are defined in terms of a probabilistic model such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/98770.xml">
hidden Markov model</link>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Motifs and consensus sequences</st>

<p>

The notation [XYZ] means X or Y or Z, but does not indicate the likelihood of any particular match.  For this reason, two or more patterns are often associated with a single motif: the defining pattern, and various typical patterns.</p>
<p>

For example, the defining sequence for the IQ motif may be taken to be:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 [FILV]Qxxx[RK]Gxxx[RK]xx[FILVWY]
</indent>

where x signifies any amino acid, and the square brackets indicate an alternative (see below for further details about notation).</p>
<p>

Usually, however, the first letter is I, and both [RK] choices resolve to R. Since the last choice is so wide, the pattern IQxxxRGxxxR is sometimes equated with the IQ motif itself, but a more accurate description would be a <it>consensus sequence for the IQ motif</it>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
De novo computational discovery of motifs</st>

<p>

There are software programs which, given multiple input sequences, attempt to identify one or more candidate motifs. One example is <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://meme.sdsc.edu/meme/">
MEME</weblink>, which generates statistical information for each candidate. 
Other algorithms include: CisModule, AlignAce, PhyloGibbs, Weeder.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Discovery through evolutionary conservation</st>

<p>

Motifs have been discovered by studying similar genes in different species. For example, by aligning the amino acid sequences specified by the GCM (<it>glial cells missing</it>) gene in man, mouse and <it>D. melanogaster</it>, Akiyama and others discovered a pattern which they called the GCM motif. It spans about 150 amino acid residues, and begins as follows:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 WDIND*.*P..*...D.F.*W***.**.IYS**...A.*H*S*WAMRNTNNHN
</indent>

Here each . signifies a single amino acid or a gap, and each * indicates one member of a closely-related family of amino acids.</p>
<p>

The authors were able to show that the motif has DNA binding activity.  A motif discovery algorithm that considers phylogenetic conservation is <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imsc.res.in/~rsidd/phylogibbs/">
PhyloGibbs</weblink>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Pattern description notations</st>

<p>

Several notations for describing motifs are in use but most of them are variants of standard notations for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/25717.xml">
regular expression</link>s and use these conventions:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 there is an alphabet of single characters, each denoting a specific amino acid or a set of amino acids;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a string of characters drawn from the alphabet denotes a sequence of the corresponding amino acids;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 any string of characters drawn from the alphabet enclosed in square brackets matches any one of the corresponding amino acids; e.g. [abc] matches any of the amino acids represented by a or b or c.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The fundamental idea behind all these notations is the matching principle, which assigns a meaning to a sequence of elements of the pattern notation:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <it>a sequence of elements of the pattern notation matches a sequence of amino acids if and only if the latter sequence can be partitioned into subsequences in such a way that each pattern element matches the corresponding subsequence in turn.</it>
</indent>

Thus the pattern [AB] [CDE] F matches the six amino acid sequences corresponding to ACF, ADF, AEF, BCF, BDF, and BEF.</p>
<p>

Different pattern description notations have other ways of forming pattern elements. One of these notations is the PROSITE notation, described in the following subsection.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
PROSITE pattern notation</st>

<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/4656324.xml">
PROSITE</link> notation uses the <link>
IUPAC</link> one-letter codes and conforms to the above description with the exception that a concatenation symbol, '-', is used between pattern elements, but it is often dropped between letters of the pattern alphabet.</p>
<p>

PROSITE allows the following pattern elements in addition to those described previously:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The lower case letter 'x' can be used as a pattern element to denote any amino acid.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A string of characters drawn from the alphabet and enclosed in braces (curly brackets) denotes any amino acid except for those in the string. For example, {ST} denotes any amino acid other than S or T.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If a pattern is restricted to the N-terminal of a sequence, the pattern is prefixed with <it>.</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If a pattern is restricted to the C-terminal of a sequence, the pattern is suffixed with '&amp;gt;'.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The character '&amp;gt;' can also occur inside a terminating square bracket pattern, so that S[T&amp;gt;] matches both "ST" and "S&amp;gt;".</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If e is a pattern element, and m and n are two decimal integers with m = n, then:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 e(m) is equivalent to the repetition of e exactly m times;</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 e(m,n) is equivalent to the repetition of e exactly k times for any integer k satisfying: m = k = n.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Some examples:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 x(3) is equivalent to x-x-x.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 x(2,4) matches any sequence that matches x-x or x-x-x or x-x-x-x.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The signature of the C2H2-type <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/234129.xml">
zinc finger</link></it> domain is:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 C-x(2,4)-C-x(3)-[LIVMFYWC]-x(8)-H-x(3,5)-H</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Matrices</st>
<p>

A matrix of numbers containing scores for each residue or nucleotide at each position of a fixed-length motif.  There are two types of weight matrices.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A position frequency matrix (PFM) records the position-dependent frequency of each residue or nucleotide.  PFMs can be experimentally determined from SELEX experiments or computationally discovered by tools such as MEME using hidden Markov models.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/3624902.xml">
position weight matrix</link> (PWM) contains log odds weights for computing a match score.  A cutoff is needed to specify whether an input sequence matches the motif or not. PWMs are calculated from PFMs.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

An example of a PFM from the TRANSFAC database for the transcription factor AP-1:</p>
<p>

<table style="text-align:center" class="wikitable" border="5">
<header>
Pos</header>
<header>
A</header>
<header>
C</header>
<header>
G</header>
<header>
T</header>
<header>
IUPAC</header>
<row>
<col>
01</col>
<col>
6</col>
<col>
2</col>
<col>
8</col>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
R</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
02</col>
<col>
3</col>
<col>
5</col>
<col>
9</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
S</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
03</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
17</col>
<col>
T</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
04</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
17</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
G</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
05</col>
<col>
17</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
A</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
06</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
16</col>
<col>
0</col>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
C</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
07</col>
<col>
3</col>
<col>
2</col>
<col>
3</col>
<col>
9</col>
<col>
T</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
08</col>
<col>
4</col>
<col>
7</col>
<col>
2</col>
<col>
4</col>
<col>
N</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
09</col>
<col>
9</col>
<col>
6</col>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
M</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
10</col>
<col>
4</col>
<col>
3</col>
<col>
7</col>
<col>
3</col>
<col>
N</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
11</col>
<col>
6</col>
<col>
3</col>
<col>
1</col>
<col>
7</col>
<col>
W</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

The first column specifies the position, the second column contains the number of occurrences of A at that position, the third column contains the number of occurrences of C at that position, the fourth column contains the number of occurrences of G at that position, the fifth column contains the number of occurrences of T at that position,  and the last column contains IUPAC notation for that position.
Note that each the sums of occurrences for A, C, G, and T for each row should be equal because the PFM is derived from aggregating several consensus sequences.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Another scheme</st>

<p>

This example comes from the paper by Matsuda and colleagues cited below.</p>
<p>

The <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
E. coli</link></it> lactose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/176670.xml">
operon</link> repressor LacI (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/102505.xml">
PDB</link> id 1lccA) and <it>E. coli</it> catabolite gene activator (PDB id 3gapA) both have a <it>helix-turn-helix</it> motif, but their amino acid sequences do not show much similarity, as shown in the table below.</p>
<p>

Matsuda and colleagues devised a code called the <it>3D chain code</it> for representing a protein structure as a string of letters.  This encoding scheme reveals the similarity between the proteins much more clearly than the amino acid sequence:</p>
<p>

<table cellpadding="5">
<row>

<header>
3D chain code</header>
<header>
Amino acid sequence</header>
</row>
<row>
<header>
1lccA</header>
<col>
TWWWWWWWKCLKWWWWWWG</col>
<col>
LYDVAEYAGVSYQTVSRVV</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
3gapA</header>
<col>
KWWWWWWGKCFKWWWWWWW</col>
<col>
RQEIGQIVGCSRETVGRIL</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/443318.xml">
structural motif</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Siddharthan R, van Nimwegen E, Siggia ED&#32;(2004).&#32;"PhyloGibbs: A Gibbs sampler incorporating phylogenetic information". <it>in Eskin E, Workman C (eds), RECOMB 2004 Satellite Workshop on Regulatory Genomics, LNBI 3318, 30­41 (Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2005)</it>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Siddharthan R, Siggia ED, van Nimwegen E&#32;(2005).&#32;"PhyloGibbs: A Gibbs sampling motif finder that incorporates phylogeny". <it>PLoS Comput Biol</it>&#32;<b>1</b>&#32;(7): e67. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pcbi.0010067">
10.1371/journal.pcbi.0010067</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>

</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Akiyama Y, <it>et al.</it> (1996). "The gcm-motif: a novel DNA-binding motif conserved in Drosophila and mammals". <it>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</it> <b>93</b> 14912-14916.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Matsuda H, Taniguchi F, Hashimoto A (1997). "An approach to detection of protein structural motifs using an encoding scheme of backbone conformations. <it>Proc. of 2nd Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</it> pp. 280-291.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Stormo GD (2000). "DNA binding sites: representation and discovery". <it>Bioinformatics</it> <b>16</b> 16-23.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Balla S, Thapar V, Verma S, Luong T, Faghri T, Huang CH, Rajasekaran S, del Campo JJ, Shinn JH, Mohler WA, Maciejewski MW, Gryk MR, Piccirillo B, Schiller SR, Schiller MR. (2006) "Minimotif Miner: a tool for investigating protein function" Nature Methods" Mar;3(3):175-7.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Schiller MR (2007) "Minimotif Miner: A Computational Tool to Investigate Protein Function, Disease, and Genetic Diversity" Current Protocols in Protein Science UNIT 2.12    </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kadaveru K, Vyas J, Schiller MR. (2008) "Viral infection and human disease – insights from minimotifs" Frontiers in Bioscience (in press)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Motif-finding methods</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://us.expasy.org/prosite">
PROSITE Database of protein families and domains</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://202.54.26.221/quadfinder">
Database and Analysis Suite for Quadruplex forming motifs in Nucleotide Sequences</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nun.isis.unc.edu/gcgmanual/meme.html">
MEME Documentation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gene-regulation.com/pub/databases.html">
TRANSFAC: A public database for transcription factor motifs</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dna.stanford.edu/emotif">
eMotif homepage (from Stanford University)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioprospector.stanford.edu">
Bioprospector homepage (from Stanford University)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.caltech.edu/cis-analysis.txt">
List of and comments on other programs useful for discovering cis-regulatory element motifs</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stud.uni-potsdam.de/~haussler/master">
Another more extensive, but less commented list of programs</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">
NCBI Home Page</weblink> NIH's National Library of Medicine NCBI (National Center for Biotechnology Information) link to a tremendous number of resources including sequence analysis and motif discovery.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stud.uni-potsdam.de/~haussler/wiki/index.php/Main_Page">
Transcriptional Regulation Wiki</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wikiomics.org/wiki/Sequence_motifs">
Wikiomic Sequence motifs page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.uga.edu/~che/BEST/">
BEST</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Motif-finding Web applications</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soe.ucsc.edu/~kent/improbizer/improbizer.html">
Improbizer</weblink> searches for motifs in DNA or RNA sequences that occur with improbable frequency</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cbcsrv.watson.ibm.com/Tspd.html">
TEIRESIS</weblink> search for short sequence motifs in Proteins</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/PLACE/signalscan.html">
PLACE</weblink> A Database of Plant Cis-acting Regulatory DNA Elements</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://genie.dartmouth.edu/scope/">
SCOPE</weblink> an ensemble of programs aimed at identifying novel cis-regulatory elements from groups of upstream sequences</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/~ppn3/gimsan/">
GIMSAN</weblink> motif-finder with biologically realistic and reliable statistical significance analysis </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://defiant.i2r.a-star.edu.sg/~ewijaya/MotifVoter2/">
MotifVoter</weblink> variance based ensemble method for discovery of binding sites</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fraenkel.mit.edu/webmotifs/form.html">
WebMotifs</weblink> use different programs to search for DNA-sequence motifs, and to easily combine and evaluate the results</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mnm.engr.uconn.edu/">
Minimotif Miner</weblink> public interface to the minimotif miner database which correlates short sequence amino acids to their biological function</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://meme.sdsc.edu/meme/">
MEME/MAST</weblink> discover motifs (highly conserved regions) in groups of related DNA or protein sequences</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blocks.fhcrc.org/blocks/blockmkr/make_blocks.html">
BLOCK-maker</weblink> finds conserved blocks in a group of two or more unaligned protein sequences</entry>
</list>
</p>



</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
