<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:12:01[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>DSSP (imaging)</title>
<id>4448948</id>
<revision>
<id>239868007</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-20T21:51:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jeff3000</username>
<id>170884</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Digital signal processing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>DSSP</b> stands for <it>digital shape sampling</it> and <it>processing</it>. It is an alternative and often preferred way of describing "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/18935488.xml">
reverse engineering</link>" <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> and hardware. The term originated in a 2005 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/4095240.xml">
Society of Manufacturing Engineers</link></company>
' "Blue Book"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> on the topic, which referenced numerous suppliers of both scanning hardware and processing software.<p>

DSSP employs various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/3054853.xml">
3D</link> scanning methods, including laser scanners, to acquire thousands to millions of points on the surface of a form and then software from a variety of suppliers to convert the resulting "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/155339.xml">
point cloud</link>" into forms useful for inspection, computer-aided design, visualization and other applications. It may also employ volumetric methods of scanning, such as digital <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/385523.xml">
tomography</link>.</p>
<p>

Some common applications include CAI (computer-aided inspection), creation of 3D <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/37315.xml">
CAD</link> models from scanned data, medical applications, 3D imaging for <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<meme wordnetid="105985126" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<acculturation wordnetid="105984936" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/1555022.xml">
Web 2.0</link></acculturation>
</activity>
</meme>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 applications, and the restoration of culturally significant artifacts; as well as conventional reverse engineering for creating replacement parts.</p>
<p>

The term 'reverse engineering' itself has acquired some notoriety when the technology has been used to copy others' designs. </p>
<p>

The term 'laser scanning' has also been used somewhat interchangeably for DSSP. However, there are two problems with the term as a broad description of the field. First, it is only one of many alternative scanning technologies. Second, it misses the essential role of processing software in converting point cloud data into useful forms.</p>
<p>

In some ways, DSSP is a 3D analog to DSP (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../TN$$/HT$C$_T$yT$N$.xml">
digital signal processing</link>) in that the software attempts to extract a clear and accurate 3D image from point data that may include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/41415.xml">
noise</link>. The notion of 'shape sampling' embedded in the term also acknowledges that, as in many measurement processes, the accuracy of the 3D data will depend upon the number and accuracy of points sampled.</p>
<p>

The speed and accuracy of both scanners to acquire data and software <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s to extract useful <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/18985040.xml">
data</link> has dramatically increased in recent years. As some the limitations of the technology are eliminated and costs reduced, more uses are appearing.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Peter Marks, Capturing a Competitive Edge Through Digital Shape Sampling &amp; Processing (DSSP), SME Blue Book Series, 2005, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irgplotters.com/media/DSSP.pdf">
PDF</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
