<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:07:00[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<party  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108256968">
<header>
<title>Marze Por Gohar</title>
<id>4455785</id>
<revision>
<id>226580480</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-19T05:09:02Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing copy edit from October 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing copy edit</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Political parties in Iran</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="30px" src="Acap.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  for  grammar, style, cohesion, tone or spelling.</b>
You can assist by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Marze_Por_Gohar&amp;action=edit">
editing it</weblink> now. A how-to is available.<it>&nbsp;(October 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

The <b>Marze Por Gohar Party</b>  (<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/11600.xml">
Persian</link></language>
:حزب مرزپرگهر ) is an <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/14653.xml">
Iran</link></country>
ian  nationalist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/23996.xml">
political party</link>. Their motto is "<it>Iranians for a secular republic</it>". The party was founded on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/15874.xml">
July 8</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/34647.xml">
1998</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/57654.xml">
Tehran, Iran</link>. It was established by a group of secular nationalist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/45353.xml">
writers</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/50100.xml">
journalists</link>. During the student demonstrations of July 1999, Marze Por Gohar Party, was highly active. </p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Marzeporgohar.gif" type="thumb">
<caption>

The official arm of the Marze Por Gohar Party
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> was one of the most <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org/index.php?l=1&amp;cat=20&amp;scat=&amp;artid=91">
active groups present at the pro-Democracy uprising</weblink> of the University students in July 1999. On the fifth day of the uprising, on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/15878.xml">
July 13</link>, MPG leaders and members were arrested and sent to the notorious <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<prison wordnetid="104005630" confidence="0.8">
<establishment wordnetid="103297735" confidence="0.8">
<correctional_institution wordnetid="103111690" confidence="0.8">
<penal_institution wordnetid="103907654" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="103574555" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/2033406.xml">
Towhid</link></institution>
</penal_institution>
</correctional_institution>
</establishment>
</prison>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
, one of Islamic Republic’s secret prisons. Due to constant threats of the Islamic elements, some members of this organization were forced to secretly flee the country. Since then, the party has been forced to conduct its affairs outside of Iran.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Outlook for Marze Por Gohar Party </st>
<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party's</weblink> main motto is that the current regime cannot be reformed. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe that politics and religion cannot be bedfellows. The separation of religion from the government is a basis of their ideal form of government. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe in a democratic republic. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe in a system where principals are embodied within the law and individual freedoms and individual and minority rights remain protected within democratic majority rule. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> want to spread Iranian national heritage and Iranian culture. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> want to create a society where all individuals regardless of ethnicity, religious background and gender can enjoy equality under the law. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe in a parliamentary system where all democratic parties can function. </p>
<p>

However <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe any political party with a program for destroying the democratic system, and basic human rights principals, must be excluded from participating in all levels of governmental elections, even though the freedom of speech will be protected. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe in minimizing the role of the government, except in military, foreign policy, security and strategic economic and welfare matters. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe in the participation of the people not only in representative affairs of the government but also in their own professional and social interests in the form of unlimited organizational matters within the society. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> foreign policy must be based on complete sovereignty and total respect of other nations who respect our national borders and accept our self-determination. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe in friendly and constructive relations with all nations and governments who can benefit Iranian national interest, and in particular we favor regional economic, political, strategic and cultural alliances with countries that share  ancient Iranian and Persian history, culture and values. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe in a strong Iran, capable of safeguarding our territorial integrity, strategic security and economic lifelines. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe that the private sector, in all viable industries and services, including tourism, light and heavy industry, information, modern and high technologies and countless other fields should become the backbone of the country's source of income while income from major natural resources such as oil should fund education, infra-structure projects, health, housing, and welfare as well as finance promising private sector endeavors. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> believe the future Iran should be open to all foreign investments capable of benefiting Iran and Iranian citizens and in particular the most advanced international technologies, services and expertise should be encouraged to participate. Iran should encourage the widest possible acquisition of science and technology from all over the world. </p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink> also favor Iranian participation in all profitable international investments which will not be contrary to the national and strategic interests.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org">
Marze Por Gohar Party</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marzeporgohar.org/old/main/ro/humanrights.php">
Roozbeh Farahanipour's report on Towhid Prison</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</party>
</article>
