<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:05:44[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<action  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100037396">
<interaction  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100039021">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<header>
<title>Competitive exclusion principle</title>
<id>451120</id>
<revision>
<id>244337669</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T09:24:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>タチコマ robot</username>
<id>421426</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles with unsourced statements</category>
<category>Articles with unsourced statements since August 2007</category>
<category>Biological interactions</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is missing  or needs .</b>
Using helps guard against copyright violations and factual inaccuracies. <it>(August 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

 
In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/1464824.xml">
community ecology</link>, the <b>competitive exclusion principle</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, sometimes referred to as <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/1290178.xml">
Gause's</link> Law of competitive exclusion</b> or just <b>Gause's Law</b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, is a theory which states that two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/28023.xml">
species</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/4715998.xml">
competing</link> for the same resources cannot stably coexist, if the ecological factors are constant. Either of the two competitors will always take over the other which leads to either the extinction of one of the competitors or its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/9236.xml">
evolution</link>ary or behavioural shift towards a different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/67244.xml">
ecological niche</link>.  
<sec>
<st>
Experimental basis</st>
<p>

Russian ecologist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/1290178.xml">
Georgii Frantsevich Gause</link>, formulated the law of competitive exclusion based on laboratory competition experiments using two species of <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/191149.xml">
Paramecium</link></it>, the <it>Paramecium aurelia</it> and <it>Paramecium caudatum</it>. Following a lag phase, the <it>Paramecium aurelia</it> was  consistently able to drive the other to extinction. The conditions were to add fresh water everyday and input a constant flow of food.
On the other hand, Gause was able to let the <it>Paramecium caudatum</it> survive by driving differently the environmental parameters (food, water): that explains why the Gause law is valid only if the ecological factors are constant.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Prediction</st>
<p>

Competitive exclusion is predicted by a number of mathematical and theoretical models, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/462534.xml">
Lotka-Volterra model</link>s of competition. However, for reasons that are poorly understood, competitive exclusion is rarely observed in natural <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9632.xml">
ecosystem</link>s, and many biological communities appear to violate Gause's Law. The best known example is the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/11396416.xml">
paradox of the plankton</link></it> (or short <it>diversity paradox</it>): All <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/25011.xml">
plankton</link> species live on a very limited number of resources, primarily <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/27743.xml">
solar energy</link> and minerals that are dissolved in the water. According to the competitive exclusion principle, only a small number of plankton species should be able to coexist on these resources. Nevertheless, large numbers of plankton species coexist within small regions of open sea.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Paradoxical traits</st>
<p>

A partial solution to the paradox lies in raising the dimensionality of the system. Spatial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/542490.xml">
heterogeneity</link>, multiple <link>
resource competition</link>, <link>
competition-colonization trade-off</link>s, and lag prevent exclusion (ignoring stochastic extinction over longer time-frames). However, such systems tend to be analytically intractable. In addition, many can theoretically support an unlimited number of species. A new paradox is created: Most well-known models that allow for stable coexistence allow for unlimited number of species to coexist, yet in nature, any community contains just a handful of species.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Re-definition</st>
<p>

Recent studies that address some of the assumptions made for the models predicting competitive exclusion have shown that these assumptions need to be reconsidered. For example, a slight modification of the assumption of how growth and body size are related leads to a different conclusion, namely that for a given ecosystem a certain range of species may coexist while others become outcompeted<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/2025411.xml">
Hardin, G.</link></scientist>
 (1960).  The Competitive Exclusion Principle.  <it>Science</it> <b>131</b>, 1292-1297.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/1290178.xml">
Gause, G. F.</link> (1934). <it>The struggle for existence</it>. Baltimore, MD: Williams &amp; Wilkins.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Rastetter, E. B. &amp; Ågren, G. I. (2002).  Changes in individual allometry can lead to coexistence without niche separation. <it>Ecosystems</it> <b>5</b>, 789-801.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Jason D. Moll and Joel S. Brown (2008): Competition and Coexistence with Multiple Life-History Stages. <it>Am Nat</it>, <b>171(6)</b>, 839-843.</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Vaurie, Charles (1950): Notes from the Walter Koelz Collections, Number 6. Notes on some Asiatic nuthatches and creepers. <it>American Museum Novitates</it> <b>1472</b>: 1-39. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://digitallibrary.amnh.org/dspace/bitstream/2246/4241/1/N1472.pdf">
PDF fulltext</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</interaction>
</action>
</event>
</article>
