<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:15:18[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>MacvsWindows</title>
<id>4529555</id>
<revision>
<id>218479997</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-10T20:55:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rockero</username>
<id>328895</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Operating system advocacy</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Xvsxp_logo.jpg">
<caption>

XvsXP Logo
</caption>
</image>

<b>Mac vs Windows</b> (formerly XvsXP) is an online <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> comparison site run by James Scariati and Michael Moriarty.
<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>

<p>

The site compares competing operating systems <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/33879.xml">
Windows XP SP2</link></version>
 and <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/641975.xml">
Mac OS X v10.4</link></version>
 through over 100 different topics.  The site explicitly includes only the "out-of-the-box" experience of each OS, as well as any freely released updates from the manufacturer. A unique feature of the site over many other OS comparison sites is that it features a forum to encourage readers to voice any concerns or comments about the site, as well as any suggestions for additions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<p>

The site was originally launched in March 2003 by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://danpouliot.com">
Dan Pouliot</weblink>, with the scope of the site explicit also to the concerns of the "creative professional". The site was originally intended to advocate OS X by virtue of a fair comparison to Windows XP.  Pouliot acknowledged that such a fair comparison was difficult, and he relied on debates within the site's own online forum to refine and expand the site. A PDF version of the site was available, and Pouliot reports it was downloaded 250,000 times between the launch of the site and the time the PDF was removed in January 2005.</p>
<p>

The site was almost closed down in January 2005, including a brief period when XvsXP was converted to a <link>
pay site</link>. Pouliot at that time decided he needed to move on, so a change of ownership was negotiated.</p>
<p>

In November <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>, the site officially changed hands to the current owners, James Scariati and Michael Moriarty, and a rewrite of the site began, with a renewed objective of an unbiased comparison. The point of view was changed away from first person. Content considered to be editorial in nature was removed. (One example that was removed can be seen in the Internet Archive Wayback Machine: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20040415221224/www.xvsxp.com/dialogs/">
http://web.archive.org/web/20040415221224/www.xvsxp.com/dialogs/</weblink> where Pouliot discussed one particular XP dialog box at length.)</p>
<p>

The site officially relaunched in March <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>, sporting a refreshed look and updated sections, as well as a format that was reportedly designed for ease of updating due to the upcoming releases of both operating systems, <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
 and <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/2001664.xml">
Mac OS X v10.5</link></version>
.</p>
<p>

On June 20th, 2007, XvsXP.com owners announced they were moving to a new website, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.macvswindows.com">
Mac vs. Windows</weblink>. One of the main new features introduced with their new website was the transition to a wiki model.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticism</st>
<p>

Some feel that XvsXP falls short of a complete comparison since it does not take into account other factors such as software availability, total cost of ownership, hardware interoperability and so forth. The owners contend that such topics fall outside of the site's scope as an operating system comparison and fall into a broader platform comparison. Both owners have stated that even the current comparison is a large amount of work, so a truly objective comparison of all aspects of each platform would require a team of full-time employees. In addition, the current "1 to 10" scoring system has been viewed as being too definitive for a subjective review.  This is also compounded in the "Final Score" page where there is no option to weigh the scores based on the user's concerns.  (e.g. security is given as much weight as icons).</p>
<p>

Further criticism of XvsXP can be lodged for the continued delays in providing coverage of the Windows side of the comparison.  As of June 10, 2007, the site still fails to show data on Windows Vista, over seven months after Vista’s Release to Manufacturing (RTM) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/features/2006/nov06/11-08VistaRTM.mspx">
http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/features/2006/nov06/11-08VistaRTM.mspx</weblink> .  This even though one of the XvsXP admins acknowledged (over four months ago <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xvsxp.com/">
http://www.xvsxp.com/</weblink> ) that Vista was released (their initial acknowledgement [February 8, 2007] of Vista came three months after it went RTM).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/22528.xml">
Operating system advocacy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/981531.xml">
Comparison of operating systems</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.XvsXP.com">
XvsXP Main Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.apple.com/applescript/news/ and http://www.apple.com/applescript/resources/ - XvsXP featured on Apple.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.g4tv.com/screensavers/episodes/3495/Chewbacca_Speaks_the_EFF_Google_Darktips.html - XvsXP featured on <network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/248316.xml">
TechTV</link></network>
 show <series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/209162.xml">
The Screen Savers</link></series>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://news.yahoo.com/s/nf/20060817/bs_nf/45454 - XvsXP featured on Yahoo News. (Link dead as of 00:45, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/15790.xml">
15 January</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link> (UTC))</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
