<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:20:50[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Bitext word alignment</title>
<id>4558674</id>
<revision>
<id>242611943</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T23:01:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles to be merged since October 2008</category>
<category>Machine translation</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Merge-arrow.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrow
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  into . ()</col>
</row>
</table>


This article is about aligning natural language words.&#32;&#32;For aligning groups of bytes, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/2247927.xml">
data structure alignment</link>.&#32;&#32;
<b>Bitext word alignment</b> or simply <b>word alignment</b> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/21652.xml">
natural language processing</link> task of identifying translation relationships among the words (or more rarely multiword units) in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/354374.xml">
bitext</link>, resulting in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/244431.xml">
bipartite graph</link> between the two sides of the bitext, with an arc between two words if and only if they are translations of one another.  Word alignment is typically done after <link>
sentence alignment</link> has already identified pairs of sentences that are translations of one another.</p>
<p>

Bitext word alignment is an important supporting task for most methods of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/4558491.xml">
statistical machine translation</link>;  the parameters of statistical machine translation models are typically estimated by observing word-aligned bitexts, and conversely automatic word alignment is typically done by choosing that alignment which best fits a statistical machine translation model.  Circular application of these two ideas results in an instance of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/470752.xml">
expectation-maximization algorithm</link>.</p>
<p>

This approach to training is an instance of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/233497.xml">
unsupervised learning</link>, in that the system is not given examples of the kind of output desired, but is trying to find values for the unobserved model and alignments which best explain the observed bitext.  Recent work has begun to explore supervised methods which rely on presenting the system with a (usually small) number of manually aligned sentences.  In addition to the benefit of the additional information provided by supervision, these models are typically also able to more easily take advantage of combining many features of the data, such as context, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/26860.xml">
syntactic structure</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/45059.xml">
part-of-speech</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/3107844.xml">
translation lexicon</link> information, which are difficult to integrate into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/1222578.xml">
generative statistical model</link>s traditionally used.</p>
<p>

Besides the training of machine translation systems, other applications of word alignment include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/3107844.xml">
translation lexicon</link> induction, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/3063695.xml">
word sense</link> discovery, and the cross-lingual projection of linguistic information.</p>

</bdy>
</article>
