<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:17:39[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108058098">
<header>
<title>ACL (software)</title>
<id>4589196</id>
<revision>
<id>232766913</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-18T21:11:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Balloonman</username>
<id>1182988</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Computer Assisted Auditing Techniques</category>
<category>Computer companies</category>
<category>Accounting software</category>
<category>Information technology audit</category>
<category>Data analysis software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Company</name>
<parameters>
<company_type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/1499655.xml">
Private</link></company_type>
<location_city>
Vancouver, British Columbia</location_city>
<location_country>
Canada</location_country>
<homepage>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ACL.com/">
www.acl.com</weblink></homepage>
<company_name>
Audit Command Language</company_name>
<company_logo>
<image width="150px" src="ACL_LOGO.gif">
<caption>

ACL logo
</caption>
</image>
</company_logo>
<Slogan__Data_you_can_trust._Results_you_can_see.__key_people>
, President and CEO Heather McKay, Vice President, Human ResourcesTony Murphy, Vice President, Worldwide SalesTerry Noreault, Vice President, DevelopmentBlair Simonite, Vice President, Finance and OperationsJohn Verver, Vice President, Alliances &amp; Product Strategy</Slogan__Data_you_can_trust._Results_you_can_see.__key_people>
<foundation>
1987</foundation>
<industry>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
Computer software</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/542306.xml">
Consulting</link><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/1986673.xml">
CAATTS</link></industry>
<products>
Audit Command Language (Network and desktop versions), Continuous Controls Monitoring, Direct Link, ACL Server Editions</products>
</parameters>
</template>


<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is written like .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=ACL_%28software%29&amp;action=edit">
rewrite this article</weblink> from a . For <b>blatant</b> advertising that would require a fundamental rewrite to become encyclopedic, use  to mark for .&nbsp;<it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

According to the Internal Auditor magazine, <b>Audit Command Language</b> ACL is "the most widely used data extraction and analysis product" and "the most widely used product for fraud detection and prevention" used in audit profession.  Traditionally auditors have manually sampled and reviewed documents supporting various transactions. The sampled items represented "a small portion of the total transactions and required auditors to statistically project the results to the overall universe. That process is largely obsolete in today's highly automated environment."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  By sampling 100% of the data, ACL can be used to find irregularities or patterns in transactions that could indicate control weaknesses or fraud.</p>
<p>

The "Financial Express" declared, "One major development in audit is the availability of General Audit Software such as Audit Command Language (ACL). ACL is a powerful auditing software that can be used for developing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/1986673.xml">
Computer Assisted Audit Tools</link> or CAATS."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  ACL's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
GUI</link> is "user friendly and does not require knowledge of a programming language."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  While ACL can be readily used with minimal instruction, a study sponsored by ISACA noted that <link>
Interactive Data Extraction and Analysis</link> (IDEA) , ACL's main competitor, may be easier to learn and use.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
 ACL Services Ltd. - the Company </st>

<p>

The company's clients include 82 percent of the Fortune 100 companies, 54% of the Global 500, the Big Four public accounting firms in 110 countries and hundreds of national, state, and local governments.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/4703507.xml">
Institute of Internal Auditors</link> selected ACL Services as one of only seven to participate in its IIA Partnership Program.  This partnership program requires is a commitment to "share tools, techniques, concepts, and philosophies with" IIA members.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  On May 9, 2007, Deloitte &amp; Touche, one of the Big Four accounting firms, and ACL announced an alliance where D &amp; T will become ACL Services' distribution network for ACL's Continuous Controls Monitoring (CCM.)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>  ACL's CCM solutions are designed to be compliant with the Treadway Commission of the Committee of Sponsoring Organizations (COSO).  This is considered the standard bearer for supporting SOX 404 compliance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 ACL - the Product </st>

<p>

ACL technology comprises <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/2720954.xml">
data analytics</link> software which provides assurance to organizations on its transactional data accuracy, completeness, and integrity. The technology gives organizations a single point of view into enterprise data. Prior to the late 1990's the use of personal computers for data analytics was impractical.  PC's did not have sufficient memory to perform tests of large data sets.  With the increase in size of computer storage, this limitation is no longer a factor.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  </p>
<p>

There are three fundamental ACL windows with ACL: view, navigator, and command log.  The view window consists of the data's fields and records.  The view can be edited, sorted, and modified to perform various test.  The navigator mirrors the functionality of Windows Explorer in that it uses a tree-structure to present tables, scripts, and other ACL objects. The command log is one of the major selling points of ACL.  The log preserves the steps and results of an ACL project/script.  The log thus becomes a permanent record that can be included in one's work paper demonstrating the steps used to reach various conclusions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> </p>
<p>

When the Salt Lake City audit department was "rocked by a seemingly endless string of scandals," the county auditors relied upon ACL to test every record in their review. Interim Auditor Sean Thomas concluded that by using ACL, the county auditor's office was able to streamline the audit process while making it more comprehensive.  "We are pleased to report," he wrote, "that the software does provide the user benefits outlined above, and it is very thorough and incredibly fast in providing answers to well-structured inquiries."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

The United States Air Force uses ACL to perform near real time audits.  The Catholic Healthcare Audit Network (CHAN) concluded that with the use of ACL "computer assisted audit technology will undoubtedly continue to play an integral role in CHAN's efforts to help clients manage business risk and comply with the government's increased scrutiny of healthcare billings."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>  The Investor's Group, a Canadian financial planning service, concluded that traditional audit techniques were "a waste of resources and time" after discovering "ACL's processing and analysis capabilities."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
ACL Certified Data Analyst (ACDA)</st>

<p>

ACL offers a certification as an ACL Certified Data Analyst.  This certification indicates that the user has met a certain level of skill expertise with ACL and data analytical concepts.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acl.com/">
ACL Home Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acl.com/pdfs/IIA_Survey_Summary.pdf">
 Institute of Internal Auditors Survey (pdf)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.TexasACL.com">
TexasACL User Group</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Speer, James. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://global.factiva.com/ha/default.aspx">
Notes from the: Auditor General of the Air Force</weblink> 1 January 2003. Air Force Comptroller. Vol 37. Issue 1. ISSN 0002-2365</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://global.factiva.com/ha/default.aspx">
Financial Express - Prevention Of Computer Frauds In Banking.</weblink> 1 June 2003.Financial Express</entry>
<entry id="3">
Warner, Paul. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://global.factiva.com/ha/default.aspx">
ACL for Windows</weblink>. 1 Nov 1998. CPA Journal. Volume 68. Issue 11. ISSN 0732-8435</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.isaca.org/Template.cfm?Section=Home&amp;CONTENTID=22828&amp;TEMPLATE=/ContentManagement/ContentDisplay.cfm">
Utilization of Generalized Audit Software in an Information Systems Auditing Course</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.deloitte.com/dtt/section_node/0,1042,sid%253D62488,00.html">
ACL Software and Support Services</weblink> Deloitte &amp; Touche Website.</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theiia.org//theiia/about-the-institute/advertising-sponsorships/partnership-program/?search=acl">
IIA Partnership Program</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acl.com/news/pr.aspx?Article=70&amp;bhcp=1">
ACL Announces Alliance Agreement with Deloitte &amp; Touche at the Gartner Compliance &amp; Risk Management Summit</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.s-ox.com/News/detail.cfm?articleID=877">
"Telus Chooses ACL for Continuous Controls Monitoring and Compliance"</weblink> June 15, 2006.  Sarbanes-Oxley Compliance Journal.  Accessed 6/29/07</entry>
<entry id="9">
Edwards, Alan.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://global.factiva.com/ha/default.aspx">
"Audit System Passes Test"</weblink>. 25 August 2004. Deseret Morning News.</entry>
<entry id="10">
 Burr, Thomas. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://global.factiva.com/ha/default.aspx">
"County Auditors get boost from software"</weblink> 10 August 2004. Salt Lake Tribune.</entry>
<entry id="11">
Rice, Tammy.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://global.factiva.com/ha/default.aspx">
"Automating health-care audits."</weblink> 1 June 2001.  Internal Auditor. Vol 58. Issue 3.  ISSN 0020-5745.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Kirk, Brad. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://global.factiva.com/ha/default.aspx">
"Delivering speed, accuracy, compliance"</weblink>. 1 Feb 2000.  Internal Auditor. Volume 57. Issue 1. ISSN 0020-5745</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</company>
</article>
