<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:12:41[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Genevestigator</title>
<id>4613989</id>
<revision>
<id>220070630</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-18T03:48:43Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Janstu</username>
<id>1044509</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Genetics</category>
<category>Bioinformatics software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Genevestigator</b> is a web-based application developed for biologists to rapidly find out in which tissues, at which stages of development, and to what stimuli, drug treatments, diseases, or genetic modifications genes of given organisms are activated. Results are processed from a large database of manually curated and quality-controlled Affymetrix microarrays hybridized with RNA samples extracted from a large variety of tissues and conditions. Currently, data is available for human,, mouse, rat, arabidopsis, and barley.<p>

Genevestigator was started in January 2004 by scientists from ETH Zurich. The analysis tool can be accessed at the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.genevestigator.ethz.ch">
Genevestigator</weblink> website.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Keywords</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/12069437.xml">
microarray databases</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

meta-analysis</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/662399.xml">
Affymetrix</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/467899.xml">
systems biology</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Tool for biologists</st>
<p>

Genevestigator is currently serving a community of 10'000 registered users (mostly biologists) from the animal and plant research fields. Its tools have been used in 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

molecular biology</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

toxicogenomics</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

biomarker discovery</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

biotechnology</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

pathway analysis</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

As of September 2007, its original articles have been cited more than 400 times (ISI Thomson) by researchers using the tools.</p>
<p>

Four tool sets, each containing several tools, are available:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Meta-Profile Analysis</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Biomarker Search</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Clustering Analysis</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Pathway Projector</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Underlying most of the tools is the concept of "meta-profiles". Meta-profiles are representative vectors of expression for a given type of condition. For example, for a gene of interest, its anatomy meta-profile is the vector of expression values across all anatomy categories that are available in the database for this gene and organism. In simple terms, it shows how strongly a gene is expressed in different anatomy parts.</p>
<p>

The concept of meta-profiles has been used in Genevestigator to characterize expression across anatomy, development, stimuli (drug treatments, diseases, stimuli) and mutations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Grennan AK (2006) Genevestigator. Facilitating web-based gene-expression analysis. Plant Physiology 141(4):1164-6</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Laule O, Hirsch-Hoffmann M, Hruz T, Gruissem W, and P Zimmermann (2006) Web-based analysis of the mouse transcriptome using Genevestigator. BMC Bioinformatics 7:311</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Zimmermann P, Hennig L and W Gruissem (2005) Gene expression analysis and network discovery using Genevestigator. Trends in Plant Science 9 10 , 407-409</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Zimmermann P, Hirsch-Hoffmann M, Hennig L and W Gruissem (2004) GENEVESTIGATOR: Arabidopsis Microarray Database and Analysis Toolbox. Plant Physiology 136 1 , 2621-2632</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Zimmermann P, Schildknecht B, Garcia-Hernandez M, Gruissem W, Craigon D, Mukherjee G, May S, Parkinson H, Rhee S, Wagner U and L Hennig (2006) MIAME/Plant - adding value to plant microarray experiments. Plant Methods  2 , 1</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.genevestigator.ethz.ch">
Genevestigator website</weblink>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
