<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:07:29[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network Service Providers in Nepal</title>
<id>465553</id>
<revision>
<id>215997850</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-30T16:51:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from May 2008</category>
<category>Communications in Nepal</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Network_Service_Providers_in_Nepal&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Network+Service+Providers+in+Nepal%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(May 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



<p>

There are few <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/803577.xml">
Network Service Provider</link>s (NSPs) in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/171166.xml">
Nepal</link></country>
</b>. </p>
<p>

1. <b>Mercantile Communications</b> http://www.mos.com.np</p>
<p>

This was the first ISP in Nepal and started its service in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/34658.xml">
1995</link>. It is providing the customers with wireless and dialup sevices.</p>
<p>

2. <b>Websurfer Nepal (Internet Service Provider in Nepal)</b>
http://www.websurfer.com.np</p>
<p>

Websurfer Nepal Internet Service provider (ISP) was founded in 2002 and the company has annually quadrupled its business since inception. It was co-founded by a young computer literate person who had as his aim in 1992 to venture into the Internet Market in Nepal. In his travels in the UK he formed a joint venture with the a successful businessman from United Kingdom who as a graduate in Computer Sciences at Imperial College London first made his fortune in Internet Businesses at an early age of the Internet. Founder Mr. K.T. Vimalanathan was successful in floating an Internet Company in FTSE100 on U.K Stock Exchange, and was a big contributory factor in the company's success. </p>
<p>

Websufer Nepal has formed a technology research and development department where the  engineers search the world for cutting edge technology and products to provide the stable and affordable services and products to the whole of Nepal. </p>
<p>

After careful research, development and implementation on a wireless internet service. Websurfer Nepal also provides Fibre Optic Cable Internet Service around Kathmandu, Patan, Bhaktapur, Lalitpur and some other districts of Nepal. The company also provides VSAT Networks, Dialup Internet, Cable Internet, Wireless Hotspots, Wireless Internet, Web Hosting and Cable TV.</p>
<p>

Web: http://www.websurfer.com.np </p>
<p>

3. <b>Worldlink Communications</b> http://www.wlink.com.np</p>
<p>

WorldLink is a pioneer IT Services Provider in Nepal with extensive expertise in Data Communication, Internet connectivity, VSAT Networking, Wireless Networking, Software Development, ICT Consulting, and Bandwidth Provisioning. In terms of subscriber numbers, WorldLink ranks as the largest ISP in the country in both retail and corporate clients. It was established in 1995.</p>
<p>

Web: http://www.wlink.com.np</p>
<p>

4. <b>Infocom Pvt Ltd</b></p>
<p>

Infocom is mainly focusing on dialup internet services. It also provides <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/157465.xml">
web hosting</link>, software development and VSAT services.</p>

</bdy>
</article>
