<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:20:32[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Bandwidth management</title>
<id>4672881</id>
<revision>
<id>240184893</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-22T08:39:11Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Hankwang</username>
<id>25806</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Network performance</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/5652.xml">
computer networking</link>, <b>bandwidth management</b> is the process of measuring and controlling the communications (traffic, packets) on a network link, to avoid filling the link to capacity or overfilling the link, which would result in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/430522.xml">
network congestion</link> and poor performance.
<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>

<p>

Almost everyone who has an Internet connection has at some time downloaded a large file, or run a peer-to-peer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/18949797.xml">
file sharing</link> program, and noticed that Web pages start to load very slowly, or fail to load. </p>
<p>

The reason is, of course, that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/231204.xml">
channel capacity</link> (or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/15612827.xml">
bandwidth</link>) of their Internet connection is limited, like the size of a highway, and when one tries to send too much information down it, more than its capacity, a virtual traffic jam results. This is also known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/430522.xml">
network congestion</link>. </p>
<p>

This analogy is important to understand the terms used: channel capacity is the width of the road, and traffic is the amount of data trying to use it. Controlling or managing traffic reduces capacity use, and is often described as bandwidth management, also known as bandwidth control, traffic control, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/6008196.xml">
congestion control</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/242669.xml">
traffic shaping</link> or traffic management.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Finding the culprit </st>

<p>

The user of a single computer on a dedicated connection will probably know what application has caused a problem or, barring <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/28951.xml">
spyware</link> that hides itself deep within a system, figure it out pretty quickly. This task is much harder for a network administrator who often does not know what applications others are running or how the applications use the network.</p>
<p>

More sophisticated Bandwidth Management techniques use a macro approach that manages traffic "per-user" rather than "per-application". This frees the network provider from having to constantly identify what clients/customers are doing, and avoids some of the legal concerns and public outcry about providers dictating what customers can do. This approach acknowledges that on ISP-type networks, "fairness" is a per client issue. By managing per-client, no single user can use more bandwidth than their allocation, no matter what application they may be running or how many users are on their endpoint.</p>
<p>

Typically a single user will not need bandwidth management. The real problem is when multiple users and applications are downloading simultaneously. Because TCP windows are large, these applications all throw a large amount of data into the same queue at your upstream provider. While the traffic arrives at this queue randomly; it is processed sequentially, resulting in choppy download speeds. The more applications that are downloading simultaneously, the larger the backlog. When the backlog grows too high, packets must be dropped to avoid having TCP retransmissions overflow the queue and wasting bandwidth with duplicate traffic. Avoiding dropped packets is the most critical function of bandwidth management. You can reduce this backlog using window shaping technology, which reduces the amount of traffic that each flow can transmit, thus reducing the queue depths and the necessity to drop packets.</p>
<p>

Troubleshooting network performance is a critical task for network administrators. An individual downloading large files on a dedicated network connection can happily consume as much bandwidth as the network is capable. On a shared network, if one user monopolizes the network, others will complain about any number of things related to the network responding slowly or timing out completely.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Fixing the problem </st>
<p>

To keep your Internet connection working fast and smoothly, you must control your use of bandwidth, to stay below the maximum capacity of the network link. To control something, you must be able to measure it. </p>
<p>

These tasks are usually viewed separately: much software exists for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/4674326.xml">
network traffic measurement</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/4673694.xml">
network traffic control</link>, but these are normally not integrated. And indeed it may not be necessary to integrate them. Once the cause of the heavy traffic is identified, it is usually simpler, and may be more effective, to shut it down or reschedule it than to try to manage its bandwidth use.</p>
<p>

Many aspects of the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/15476.xml">
Internet protocol suite</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 prevent communications links from reaching their maximum capacity in practice. Therefore, it is necessary to keep the link utilisation below the maximum theoretical capacity of the
link, in order to ensure fast responsiveness and eliminate bottleneck queues at the link endpoints, which increase latency. This is called <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/235023.xml">
congestion avoidance</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
.</p>
<p>

Some issues which limit the performance of a given link are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/30538.xml">
TCP</link> determines the capacity of a connection by flooding it until packets start being dropped (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/1977666.xml">
Slow-start</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Queueing in routers results in higher <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/19572286.xml">
latency</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/41296.xml">
jitter</link> as the network approaches (and occasionally exceeds) capacity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
TCP global synchronisation</link> when the network reaches capacity results in waste of bandwidth</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Burstiness</link> of web traffic requires spare bandwidth to rapidly accommodate the bursty traffic</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lack of widespread support for <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/235023.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22IP+ECN%22])">
explicit congestion notification</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/25315.xml">
Quality of Service</link> management on the Internet</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/100245.xml">
Internet Service Provider</link>s typically retain control over queue management and quality of service at their end of the link</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Window Shaping</link> allows higher end products to reduce traffic flows, which reduce queue depth and allow more users to share more bandwidth fairly</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

An alternative approach to improved performance is to reduce the amount of traffic generated whilst <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/33173.xml">
browsing</link>. This can be achieved by removing photographic and other bandwidth intensive content from webpages and render the page as text-only. This can be particularly beneficial on low bandwidth connections, for instance in the developing world. Disabling <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/15215.xml">
Internet Explorer</link></software>
 options such as <it>show pictures</it> allow  pages to be downloaded and viewed minus the pictures. The website <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/16847389.xml">
Loband</link> can be used to deliver a simplified page, with colours removed and images replaced by links.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Tools and techniques </st>

<p>

Software for measuring network traffic can be divided into two broad classes: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
packet sniffer</link>s, which look at individual packets, and management applications which give a broader overview of network traffic.</p>
<p>

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<analyzer wordnetid="102708711" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
Packet sniffer</link></instrument>
</analyzer>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
s are very useful for network experts tracking down tricky problems. But the volume of information they generate is enormous. A fast broadband connection can transmit thousands or millions of packets per second, and inspecting each one in detail is unlikely to help you make your network faster. In addition, understanding the output of these analysers requires a detailed understanding of network protocols such as <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/15476.xml">
TCP/IP</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/2701104.xml">
HTTP</link>. For most network administrators, the broad overview is likely to be more useful, at least as a starting point for tracking down rogue users of their networks.</p>
<p>

Many companies sell expensive solutions to help manage a network, which may or may not include managing the bandwidth of an upstream connection. There are also a few lower cost options. Some are researched and described on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/4674326.xml">
network traffic measurement</link> page.</p>
<p>

Typically, lower end bandwidth management devices will delay packets using queues that release packets at intervals that can be defined by user policies. This works well on small to medium networks where traffic flows do not have to be reduced to achieve good results. One major problem with delay techniques is when traffic is delayed multiple times by multiple devices in a stream. This can cause retransmissions to occur because a particular packet is delayed for too long, which can significantly slow a connection.</p>
<p>

Some higher end bandwidth management  devices use TCP window shaping to reduce the overall flows in your network. By "fooling" the upstream server sending the traffic with a smaller window request, the server will send less data. This has a "pacing" effect on the traffic, and reduces the amount of traffic in your upstream queues without requiring a separate device to manage it. Since the queues are less clogged, traffic flows with less jitter at a naturally lower speed without having to use delay techniques. Window shaping can increase the capacity of your network by 20-40 times (a window of 64K will allow 42 full packets to be sent by downloading servers; this can be adaptively reduced to 1 with window shaping). </p>
<p>

Of course TCP window shaping only is effective on TCP traffic, so most high-end devices use some combination of delay queues and TCP window shaping.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/4673093.xml">
INASP</link> runs bandwidth management training workshops and produces reports</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Authorization part of the <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/2166952.xml">
AAA protocol</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
 makes reference to traffic management and bandwidth control</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bandwidth management using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/4888473.xml">
NetFlow</link> and IPFIX data</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/235023.xml">
Network congestion avoidance</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 lists some techniques for prevention and management of congestion on routers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/242669.xml">
Traffic shaping</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/986684.xml">
Rate limiting</link> are bandwidth management (traffic control) techniques</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bandwidth management is a subset of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/41410.xml">
Network management</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/41501.xml">
Performance management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/4674326.xml">
Network traffic measurement</link> is a subset of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/1663751.xml">
Network monitoring</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/1653981.xml">
Bandwidth throttling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/1805538.xml">
Bandwidth cap</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bgci.org/worldwide/view_loband/">
BGCI view loband</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.loband.org/loband/main">
loband website</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "Deploying IP and MPLS QoS for Multiservice Networks: Theory and Practice" by John Evans, Clarence Filsfils (Morgan Kaufmann, 2007, ISBN 0-12-370549-5)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pcquest.com/content/depth/102110503.asp">
PC Quest How-To on bandwidth management with Linux</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bwmo.net/">
"How To Accelerate Your Internet", a free PDF book released under a Creative Commons licence</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
