<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:18:32[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>SAP Implementation</title>
<id>4683670</id>
<revision>
<id>242482074</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T12:31:16Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Kmorozov</username>
<id>238736</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Software development process</category>
<category>SAP (company)</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>SAP Implementation</b> is the whole of processes that defines a complete <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/27565.xml">
method</link> to implement <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/276773.xml">
SAP</link></company>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> in an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link>. The SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link> method described in this entry is a generic method and not a specific <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link> method as such. It is based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/805228.xml">
best practice</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/304471.xml">
case studies</link> from various literature sources and presents a collection of processes and products that make up a complete implementation method to allow any organization to plan and execute the implementation of SAP (<link>
ERP</link>) software.
<sec>
<st>
 Introduction </st>

<p>

The implementation of <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/276773.xml">
SAP</link></company>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link>, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/208783.xml">
SAP R/3</link> is almost always a massive operation that brings a lot of changes in the organization. The whole process can take up to several years. Virtually every person in the organization is involved, whether they are part of the SAP technical support organization (TSO) or the actual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/3783979.xml">
end-users</link> of the SAP software. The resulting changes that the implementation of SAP generates are intended to reach high level goals, such as improved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/5177.xml">
communication</link> and increased return on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/18985062.xml">
information</link> (as people will work with the same information). It is therefore very important that the implementation process is planned and executed with the usage of a solid method. There are various SAP implementation methods, such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/18622259.xml">
IBM</link></company>
’s Ascendant.  An example of how one company, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/231364.xml">
Robert Bosch GmbH</link></company>
, implemented SAP R/3 over 10 years is available <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.idea-group.com/books/details.asp?id=5560">
http://www.idea-group.com/books/details.asp?id=5560</weblink>.  This study shows that designing IT architecture is very critical in SAP implementation practices.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="SAP_Implementation_process-data_diagram.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 1: SAP Implementation process-data diagram
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The SAP implementation process is made up out of four main phases, i.e. the project preparation where a vision of the future-state of the SAP solution is being created, a sizing and blueprinting phase where the solution stack is created and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/156423.xml">
training</link> is being performed, a functional development phase and finally a final preparation phase, when the last <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/29090.xml">
tests</link> are being performed before the actual go live. For each phase, the vital activities are addressed and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/10933184.xml">
deliverable</link>s/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/240410.xml">
product</link>s are explained.</p>
<p>

The process-data diagram that is depicted at the right, gives an overview of all of these activities/processes and deliverables. The four gray boxes depict the four main <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link> phases, which each contain several processes that are in this case all sequential. The boxes at the right show all the deliverables/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/6978.xml">
concept</link>s that result from the processes. Boxes without a shadow have no further sub-concepts. Boxes with a black shadow depict complex closed concepts, so concepts that have sub-concepts, which however will not be described in any more detail. Boxes with a white shadow (a box behind it) depict open closed concepts, where the sub-concepts are expanded in greater detail. The lines with diamonds show a has-a relationship between concepts.</p>
<p>

Many of implementations are also done with ASAP(Accelerated SAP) methodolgy evolved from best practises in SAP.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Table of concepts</st>

<p>

The data table below provides a summary of all the concepts addressed in the process-data diagram.</p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<header>
Concept</header>
<header>
Definition</header>
<row>
<col>
CHANGE MANAGEMENT</col>
<col>
<list>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

Activities involved in (1) defining and installing new values, attitudes, norms, and behaviors within an organization that support new ways of doing work and overcome resistance to change; (2) building consensus among customers and stakeholders on specific changes designed to better meet their needs; and (3) planning, testing, and implementing all aspects of the transition from one organizational structure or business process to another. (www.gao.gov)</entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
CHANGE MANAGEMENT DOCUMENTATION.</col>
<col>
All documentation that is required and being delivered whilst performing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/14599027.xml">
change management</link>, e.g. the functional test cases and all the other documents a new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/127759.xml">
end-user</link>of SAP requires and the various tools and approaches used to manage change by the TSO. (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
COST OF OWNERSHIP ANALYSIS</col>
<col>
 Determination of where and when the costs are inquired within the context of the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/2119352.xml">
solution stack</link> and ongoing operations. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/651604.xml">
analysis</link>addresses all internal and external costs, both one-time as well as recurring (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
CUTOVER</col>
<col>
 The process of transitioning from one <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>to a new one (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
CUTOVER PLAN</col>
<col>
 All documentation related to planning, preparing and executing cutover, describing how to lock down the system from a technical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/14599027.xml">
change management</link>perspective, preparing the TSO for its new role and rolling out the SAP graphical user interface to all future end users. (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
DATA CENTER</col>
<col>
 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/579730.xml">
data center</link> is a facility used for housing a large amount of electronic equipment, typically <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link>s and communications equipment. (www.wikipedia.org)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
DATA CENTER REQUIREMENT</col>
<col>
 A requirement for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/276769.xml">
SAP</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/579730.xml">
data center</link>, i.e. a physical requirement like power requirements, a rack requirement, a network infrastructure requirement or a requirement to the network server. (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
DISASTER RECOVERY (DR) REQUIREMENT</col>
<col>
 Requirement that focuses on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/8008410.xml">
downtime</link>that lasts many hours to days or even weeks (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
FUNCTIONAL TEST CASE</col>
<col>
A set of conditions or variables under which a tester will determine if a certain business process works (www.wikipedia.org)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
HIGH AVAILABILITY (HA) REQUIREMENT</col>
<col>
Requirements that describes the amount of time that the system needs to be available to satisfy the needs of the users. (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
INSTALLATION DOCUMENTATION</col>
<col>
 All documentation related to the <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/634625.xml">
installation</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 of an end-to-end <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/276769.xml">
SAP</link>solution (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
OPERATIONS MANUAL</col>
<col>
The collection of current state system documentation, day-to-day and other regularly scheduled operations tasks, various installation and operations checklists and how-to process documents. (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
SAP</col>
<col>
 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/276773.xml">
SAP AG</link></company>
is the name of the biggest European software company. The head office is in Walldorf, Germany. SAP was founded in 1972 as Systemanalyse und Programmentwicklung ("Systems Analysis and Product") by five former IBM employees in Mannheim, Germany. (www.wikipedia.org)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
SAP IMPLEMENTATION PROJECT PLAN</col>
<col>
 A comprehensive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/166554.xml">
project plan</link> that contains all products that are delivered whilst performing an SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link>project (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
SOLUTION STACK</col>
<col>
Set of software subsystems or components needed to deliver a fully functional solution, e.g. a product or service. (www.wikipedia.org)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
SOLUTION STACK PARTNERS LIST</col>
<col>
 A list of all vendors that deliver the products that make up the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/2119352.xml">
solution stack</link>(Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
SOLUTION VISION</col>
<col>
A vision of the future-state of the SAP solution (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
STRESS TEST PLAN</col>
<col>
 A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/1584125.xml">
test plan</link>that is focused at determining the stability of a given system or entity. It involves testing beyond normal operational capacity, often to a breaking point, in order to observe the results. (www.wikipedia.org</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
TEST PLAN</col>
<col>
A detail of how the test will proceed, who will do the testing, what will be tested, in how much time the test will take place, and to what quality level the test will be performed. (IEEE 829)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
TRAINING</col>
<col>
 The acquisition of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/243391.xml">
knowledge</link>, skills, and attitudes as a result of the teaching of vocational or practical skills and knowledge that relates to specific useful skills (www.wikipedia.org)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
TRAINING PLAN</col>
<col>
 Consisting of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/156423.xml">
training</link>units, a training plan is the result of hierarchical decompositions of a training goal, tailored according to the learning preferences and prior knowledge of the trainee. A plan is the means by which the trainee satisfies the goal. (www.ece.eps.hw.ac.uk/)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
TSO</col>
<col>
Technical Support Organization. The people that are committed to implementation and management of SAP. (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
TSO CHART</col>
<col>
A chart that depicts the structure of the TSO. (Anderson, 2003)</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Activity table</st>

<p>

The following table provides a summary of all of the activities that form the SAP implementation process. These activities will be described with more detail and elaborated with examples in the rest of this entry.</p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<header>
Activity</header>
<header>
Sub-Activity</header>
<header>
Description</header>
<row>
<col rowspan="2">
Project preparation</col>
<col>
Craft solution vision</col>
<col>
Refine and communicate a SOLUTION VISION of the future-state of the SAP solution, to sketch a design that meets both business and financial requirements. The focus should be on the company’s core business and how the SAP solution will better enable that core business to be successful.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Design and initially staff the SAP TSO</col>
<col>
 Design and staff the key positions of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/276769.xml">
SAP</link>Technical Support Organization (TSO), the organization that is charged with addressing, designing, implementing and supporting the SAP solution.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col rowspan="8">
Sizing and blueprinting</col>
<col>
 Perform <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/508666.xml">
cost of ownership</link>analysis</col>
<col>
 Perform a COST OF OWNERSHIP ANALYSIS to determine how to get the best business solution for the least money i.e. to determine where and when the costs are incurred within the context of the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/2119352.xml">
solution stack</link>.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 Identify <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/3824661.xml">
high availability</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/640655.xml">
disaster recovery</link>requirements</col>
<col>
 Determine all HIGH AVAILABILITY and DISASTER RECOVERY REQUIREMENTS, to plan what to do with later <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/8008410.xml">
downtime</link>of the SAP system</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 Engage SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/2119352.xml">
solution stack</link>vendors</col>
<col>
 Select the best SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/13615.xml">
hardware</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link>technology partners for all layers and components of the SAP SOLUTION STACK, based on a side-by-side sizing comparison</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Staff TSO</col>
<col>
 Staff the bulk of the TSO, i.e. fill the positions that directly support the near-term objectives of the implementation, which are to develop and begin <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/634625.xml">
installation</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/276769.xml">
SAP</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/579730.xml">
data center</link>.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 Execute <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/156423.xml">
training</link></col>
<col>
 Train the various members of the SAP TSO, like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/579730.xml">
data center</link> specialists, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/3824661.xml">
high availability</link> specialist and network specialists and train the end-users to give all the required <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/276769.xml">
SAP</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/243391.xml">
knowledge</link>and skills</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Setup SAP DATA CENTER</col>
<col>
Build a new SAP DATA CENTER facility or transform the current data center into a foundation capable of supporting the SAP SOLUTION STACK</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Perform installations</col>
<col>
 Install the (My)SAP components and technological foundations like a web application <generic wordnetid="107899976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/42116.xml">
server</link></generic>
or enterprise portal.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Round out support for SAP</col>
<col>
Identify and staff the remaining TSO roles, e.g. roles that relate to help desk work and other such support providing work.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col rowspan="3">
SAP functional development</col>
<col>
 Address <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/14599027.xml">
Change Management</link></col>
<col>
 Develop a planned approach to the changes in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link>. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../094/14850094.xml">
objective</link> is to maximize the collective efforts of all people involved in the change and minimize the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/25617.xml">
risk</link> of failure of implementing the changes related to the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link>.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Address SAP systems and operations management</col>
<col>
 Create a foundation for the SAP systems <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/19881.xml">
management</link>and SAP computer operations, by creating a SAP OPERATIONS MANUAL and by evaluating SAP management applications.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Perform functional, integration and regression tests</col>
<col>
Test the SAP business processes, by executing functional tests to ensure that business processes work, integration tests to ensure that the organization’s business processes work together with other business processes and regression tests to prove that a specific set of data and processes yield consistent and repeatable results.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col rowspan="2">
Final Preparation</col>
<col>
Perform systems and stress tests</col>
<col>
Plan, script, execute and monitor SAP STRESS TESTS, to see if the expectations of the end users, defined in service level agreements, will be met.</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Prepare for cutover</col>
<col>
Plan, prepare and execute the CUTOVER, by creating a CUTOVER PLAN that describes all cutover tasks that have to be performed before the actual go-live</col>
</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2">
Go Live</col>
<col>
Turn on the SAP system for the end-users</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Implementation processes</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Project preparation</st>

<p>

The project preparation phase, depicted below, focuses at two main activities, i.e. to make a setup for the TSO and to define a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../729/28729.xml">
solution</link> vision. These activities allow an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link> to put in on the right track towards <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link>.</p>
<p>

<image location="none" width="313px" src="SAP_Implementation_project_preparation.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 2: Project preparation phase
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>Design and initially staff the SAP TSO</b>
<image location="right" width="200px" src="SAP_Implementation_TSO_chart.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 3: TSO chart example
</caption>
</image>

The first major step of the project preparation phase is to design and initially staff an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/276769.xml">
SAP</link> technical support organization (TSO), which is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link> that is charged with addressing, designing, implementing and supporting the SAP solution. This can be programmers, project management, database administrators, test teams, etc. At this point, the focus should be at staffing the key positions of the TSO, e.g. the high-level project team and SAP professionals like the senior <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/254789.xml">
database administrator</link> and the solution architect. Next to that, this is the time to make decisions about choosing for internal staff members or external consultants.</p>
<p>

The image at the right shows a typical TSO chart.</p>
<p>

<b>Craft solution vision</b></p>
<p>

The second project preparation job is to define a so-called solution vision, i.e. a vision of the future-state of the SAP solution, where it is important to address both business and financial requirements (budgets). The main focus within the vision should be on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/4918223.xml">
company</link>’s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/2886264.xml">
core business</link> and how the SAP solution will better enable that core business to be successful. Next to that, the shortcomings of the current systems should be described and short but clear requirements should be provided regarding availability (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/279585.xml">
uptime</link>), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/41684.xml">
security</link>, manageability and scalability of the SAP system.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sizing and blueprinting</st>

<p>

The next phase is often referred to as the sizing and blueprinting phase and forms the main chunk of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link> process. The phase is illustrated below.
<image location="none" width="313px" src="SAP_Implementation_sizing_and_blueprinting.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 4: Sizing and blueprinting phase
</caption>
</image>

<b>Perform cost of ownership analysis</b>
<image location="right" width="200px" src="SAP_Implementation_solution_stack_delta_analysis.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 5: Solution stack delta analysis
</caption>
</image>

This phase starts with performing a total <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/508666.xml">
cost of ownership</link> analysis (TCO analysis) to determine how to get the best business solution at the lowest costs. This means to compare SAP solution stack options and alternatives and then determine what costs each part of the stack will bring and when these costs will be incurred. Parts of the stack are for example the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/13615.xml">
hardware</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link>, which form the acquisition costs. Next to that, there should be taken a look at recurring costs like maintenance costs and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/8008410.xml">
downtime</link> costs. Instead of performing a complete TCO analysis for various solution stack alternatives that would like to compare, it can be wise just to do a so-called delta analysis, where only the differences between solutions (stacks) are identified and analyzed. The image at the right depicts the essence of a delta analysis.</p>
<p>

<b>Identify high availability and disaster recovery requirements</b></p>
<p>

The next step is identifying the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/3824661.xml">
high availability</link> requirements and the more serious <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/640655.xml">
disaster recovery</link> requirements. This is to plan what to do with later <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/8008410.xml">
downtime</link> of the SAP system, caused by e.g. hardware failures, application failures or power outages. It should be noted that it is very important to calculate the cost of downtime, so that an organization has a good idea of its actual availability requirements.</p>
<p>

<b>Engage SAP solution stack vendors</b>
<image location="right" width="100px" src="SAP_Implementation_simplified_sap_solution_stack.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 6: Simplified SAP solution stack
</caption>
</image>

A true sizing process is to engage the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/2119352.xml">
solution stack</link> vendors, which is the next step. This means selecting the best SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/13615.xml">
hardware</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> technology partners for all layers and components of the solution stack, based on a side-by-side sizing comparison. The most important factors that are of influence here are the estimated numbers of (concurrent) users and batch sizes. A wise thing to do is to involve SAP AG itself to let them create a sizing proposal stating the advised solution stack, before moving to SAP’s technology partners/SAP vendors, like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/13973.xml">
HP</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/26980.xml">
Sun Microsystems</link></institution>
</company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/18622259.xml">
IBM</link></company>
. A simplified solution stack is depicted at the right, showing the many layers for which software and hardware has to be acquired. Note the overlap with the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/22747.xml">
OSI model</link></system_of_measurement>
</advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
.</p>
<p>

<b>Staff TSO</b></p>
<p>

The TSO is the most important resource for an organization that is implementing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/276769.xml">
SAP</link>, so staffing the TSO is a vital job which can consume a lot of time. In a previous phase, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link> should already have staffed the most vital positions. At this point the organization should staff the bulk of the TSO, i.e. fill the positions that directly support the near-term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../094/14850094.xml">
objective</link>s of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link>, which are to develop and begin the installation/implementation of the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/579730.xml">
data center</link>. Examples are: data center experts, network <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/174521.xml">
infrastructure</link> experts, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/41684.xml">
security</link> specialists and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/254789.xml">
database administration</link> experts.</p>
<p>

There are many ways to find the right people within or outside the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link> for all of the TSO positions and it depends on the organization how much time it wants to spend on staffing.</p>
<p>

<b>Training</b></p>
<p>

One of the most vital stages of the implementation process is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/156423.xml">
training</link>. Very few people within an organization are SAP experts or even have worked with SAP software. It is therefore very important to train the end users but especially the SAP TSO: the people who design and implement the solution. Many people within the TSO need all kinds of training. Some examples of these positions:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SAP Network Specialists</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
Database</link> Administrators</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/41684.xml">
Security</link> specialists</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/164430.xml">
Documentation</link> specialists</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Et cetera</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

All of these people need to acquire the required SAP knowledge and skills or even SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/3692331.xml">
certification</link>s through training. Moreover, people need to learn to do business in a totally new way. To define how much SAP training every person needs, a company can make use of a skillset <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19008728.xml">
matrix</link>. With this matrix, a manager can identify who possesses what knowledge, to manage and plan training, by defining the height of expertise with a number between e.g. 1 and 4 for each skill for each employee.</p>
<p>

<b>Setup SAP data center</b></p>
<p>

The next step is to set up the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/579730.xml">
data center</link>. This means either building a new data center facility or transforming the current data center into a foundation capable of supporting the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/2119352.xml">
solution stack</link>, i.e. all of the technology layers and components (SAP software products) in a productive SAP installation. The most important factor when designing the data center is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/40760.xml">
availability</link>. The high availability and disaster recovery requirements which should have been defined earlier, give a good idea of the required data center requirements to host the SAP software. Data center requirements can be a:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Physical requirement like power requirements</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Rack requirement</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Network infrastructure requirement or </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Requirement to the network server.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Perform installations</b></p>
<p>

The following step is to <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/634625.xml">
install</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 the required SAP software parts which are called components and technological foundations like a web application server or <link>
enterprise portals</link>, to a state ready for business process configuration. The most vital sub steps are to prepare your OS, prepare the database server and then start installing SAP software. Here it is very important to use installation guides, which are published for each SAP component or technology solution by SAP AG. Examples of SAP components are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

R/3 Enterprise — Transaction Processing</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

mySAP BI — Business Information Warehouse</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

mySAP CRM — <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/6968.xml">
Customer Relationship Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

mySAP KW — Knowledge Warehouse</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

mySAP PLM — <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/597229.xml">
Product Lifecycle Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

mySAP SCM — <link>
Supply Chain Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

mySAP SEM — Strategic Enterprise Management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

mySAP SRM — Supplier Relationship Management</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Round out support for SAP</b></p>
<p>

Before moving into the functional development phase, the organization should identify and staff the remaining TSO roles, e.g. roles that relate to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/13544.xml">
helpdesk</link> work and other such support providing work.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Functional development</st>

<p>

The next phase is the functional development phase, where it is all about <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/14599027.xml">
change management</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/29090.xml">
testing</link>. This phase is depicted below.</p>
<p>

<image location="none" width="313px" src="SAP_Implementation_functional_development.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 7: Functional development phase
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>Address change management</b></p>
<p>

The next challenge for an organization is all about <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/14599027.xml">
change management</link> / change control, which means to develop a planned approach to the changes the organization faces. The objective here is to maximize the collective efforts of all people involved in the change and to minimize the risk of failure of implementing the changes related to the SAP implementation.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/407704.xml">
implementation</link> of SAP software will most surely come with many changes and an organization can expect many natural reactions, i.e. denial, to these changes. To fight this, it is most important to create a solid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1070207.xml">
project team</link> dedicated to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/14599027.xml">
change management</link> and to communicate the solution vision and goals of this team. This team should be prepared to handle the many change issues that come from various sources like:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/127759.xml">
End-user</link> requests</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/1578179.xml">
Operations</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/579730.xml">
Data center</link> team</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

DBA group</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/2726769.xml">
Systems management</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>SAP systems and operations management</b></p>
<p>

Next thing is to create a foundation for the SAP systems management and SAP computer operations, by creating a SAP operations manual and by evaluating SAP management applications. The manual is a collection of current state system documentation, day-to-day and other regularly scheduled operations tasks, various installation and operations checklists and how-to process documents.</p>
<p>

<b>Functional, integration and regression testing</b></p>
<p>

Testing is very important before going live with any system. Before going live with a SAP system, it is vital to do many different kinds of testing, since there is often a large, complex infrastructure of hardware and software involved. Both requirements as well as quality parameters are to be tested. Important types of testing are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Functional testing: to test using functional use cases, i.e. a set of conditions or variables under which a tester will determine if a certain business process works</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/355711.xml">
Integration testing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/38411.xml">
Regression testing</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

All tests should be preceded by creating solid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/1584125.xml">
test plan</link>s.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Final preparation</st>

<p>

The last phase before going live can be referred to as the final preparation phase and is depicted below.</p>
<p>

<image location="none" width="313px" src="SAP_Implementation_final_preparation.png" type="thumbnail">
<caption>

Figure 8: Final preparation phase
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>Systems and stress testing</b></p>
<p>

Another vital preparation activity before going live with SAP is systems and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/214554.xml">
stress testing</link>.
This means planning, scripting, executing and monitoring system and stress tests, to see if the expectations of the end users, defined in service level agreements, will be met. This can be done with SAP’s standard application <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/4498.xml">
benchmarks</link>, to benchmark the organization’s configurations against configurations that have been tested by SAP’s hardware technology partners. Again, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/1584125.xml">
test plan</link> should be created at first.</p>
<p>

<b>Prepare for cutover</b></p>
<p>

The final phase before going live with SAP is often referred to as the cutover phase, which is the process of transitioning from one system to a new one. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link> needs to plan, prepare and execute the cutover, by creating a cutover plan that describes all cutover tasks that have to be performed before the actual go-live. Examples of cutover tasks are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Review and update all systems-related operations procedures like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/533867.xml">
backup</link> policies and system monitoring</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Assign ownership of SAP’s functional processes to individuals</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Let <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/276773.xml">
SAP AG</link></company>
 do a GoingLive check, to get their blessing to go live with the system</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lock down the system, i.e. do not make any more changes to the SAP system</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Go Live</st>

<p>

All of the previously described phases all lead towards this final moment: the go-live. Go-live means to turn on the SAP system for the end-users and to obtain feedback on the solution and to monitor the solution. It is also the moment where product software adoption comes into play. More information on this topic:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Critical success factors</st>

<p>

In order to successfully implement SAP in an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/105070.xml">
organization</link>, there are several things that are of great importance. First it is very important to get the support from all the people that are involved in implementing SAP, but also the people that will actually use the SAP <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link>. Second it is essential to create a solution vision at the beginning of the implementation track, so that everybody within the organization knows why SAP is being implemented. Third and last it is very important to test the SAP hardware and software rigorously and to ensure that the end-users are ready to use SAP before going live, because there are many known projects that failed because of a lack of support and SAP knowledge.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/4703877.xml">
Product Software Adoption</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Anderson, G.W. (2003). SAP Planning: Best Practices in Implementation. Sams Publishing</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Francalanci, C. (2001). Predicting the implementation effort of ERP projects: empirical evidence on SAP/R3. Journal of information technology, Vol. 16, Issue 1, pp33–48.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hirt, S. G., Swanson, E. B. (1999). Adopting SAP at Siemens Power Corporation. Journal of Information Technology, Vol. 14, Issue 3, pp243–251.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Krumbholz, M., Maiden, N. (2001). The implementation of enterprise resource planning packages in different organisational and national cultures. Information systems, Vol. 26, Issue 3, pp185–204.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sankar, C.S., and Rau, K-H., (2006). Implementation Strategies for SAP R/3 in a Multinational Organization, Cybertech Publishing, Hershey, PA, 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Xue, Y., Liang, H., Boulton, W.R., Snyder, C.A. (2005) ERP implementation failures in China: Case studies with implications for ERP vendors. International journal of production economics, Vol. 97, Issue 3, pp279–295.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Yusuf, Y., Gunasekaran, A., Abthorpe, M.S. (2004). Enterprise information systems project implementation: A case study of ERP in Rolls-Royce. International journal of production economics, Vol. 87, Issue: 3, pp251–266.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
