<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:18:32[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Region of interest</title>
<id>4683778</id>
<revision>
<id>166905045</id>
<timestamp>2007-10-25T03:17:33Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bobblehead</username>
<id>1475555</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Medical imaging</category>
<category>Radiology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>Region of Interest</b>, often abbreviated <b>ROI</b>, is a selected subset of samples within a dataset identified for a particular purpose.<p>

For example:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 on a waveform (1D dataset), a time or frequency interval</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 on an image (2D dataset), the boundaries of an object</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 in a volume (3D dataset), the contours or surfaces outlining an object</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 in a time-volume (4D dataset), the outline of an object at or during a particular time interval</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The concept of an ROI is commonly used in medical imaging. For example, the boundaries of a tumor may be defined on an image or in a volume, for the purpose of measuring its size. The endocardial border may be defined on an image, perhaps during different phases of the cardiac cycle, say end-systole and end-diastole, for the purpose of assessing cardiac function.</p>
<p>

There are three fundamentally different means of encoding an ROI:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 burned in to the dataset, with a value that may or may not be outside the normal range of normally occurring values</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 as separate purely graphic information, such as with vector or bitmap (rasterized) drawing elements, perhaps with some accompanying plain (unstructured) text annotation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 as separate structured semantic information (such as coded value types) with a set of spatial and/or temporal coordinates</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Medical imaging standards such as DICOM provide general and application-specific mechanisms to support various use-cases.</p>
<p>

For <link>
DICOM</link> images (two or more dimensions):</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 burned in graphics and text may occur within the normal pixel value range (e.g., as the maximum white value) (deprecated)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 bitmap (rasterized) <b>overlay</b> graphics and text may be present in unused high bits of the pixel data or in a separate attribute (deprecated)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 vector graphics may be encoded in separate image attributes as <b>curves</b> (deprecated)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 unstructured vector graphics and text as well as bitmap (rasterized) overlay graphics may be encoded in a separate object as a <b>presentation state</b> that references the image object to which it is to be applied</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 structured data may be encoded in a separate object as a <b>structured report</b> in the form of a tree of name-value pairs of coded or text concepts possibly associated with derived quantitative information can reference spatial and/or temporal coordinates that in turn reference the image objects to which they apply</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 reference locations may be encoded as <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/894734.xml">
fiducial</link>s</b> in the form of spatial coordinates with an associated coded purpose, either as pixel coordinates by reference to specific images, or as coordinates in a named 3D cartesian space</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 pixels (possibly non-contiguous) may be classified into <b>segments</b> encoded in a <b>segmentation</b> object as either binary or probabilistic values in a raster (which is not required to have the same spatial sampling or extent as the images from which the segmentation was derived)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

For <link>
DICOM</link> radiotherapy:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 contours of objects may be defined as <b>structure sets</b>, either as pixel coordinates by reference to specific images, or as coordinates in a named 3D cartesian space</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

For <link>
DICOM</link> time-based waveforms:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 burned in values may occur with the waveform (deprecated)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 annotations may be encoded in a separate attribute can select multiple time points or a range of time points, either by sample number or specified time</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 structured data may be encoded in a separate object as a <b>structured report</b> in the form of a tree of name-value pairs of coded or text concepts possibly associated with derived quantitative information can reference temporal coordinates that in turn reference the waveform objects to which they apply</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/384081.xml">
HL7</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/55691.xml">
CDA</link> (<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/4684004.xml">
Clinical Document Architecture</link></system_of_measurement>
</format>
</standard>
</information>
</message>
) also has a subset of mechanisms similar to (and intended to be compatible with) DICOM for referencing image-related spatial coordinates as observations; it allows for a circle, ellipse, polyline or point to be defined as integer pixel-relative coordinates referencing an external multi-media image object, which may be of a consumer rather than medical image format (e.g., a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/12702.xml">
GIF</link>, <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/24306.xml">
PNG</link></format>
 or <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/16009.xml">
JPEG</link></format>
).</p>
<p>

As far as non-medical standards are concerned, in addition to the purely graphic markup languages (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/24080.xml">
PostScript</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link>) and vector graphic (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/27751.xml">
SVG</link>) and 3D (such as <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/101679.xml">
VRML</link></format>
) drawing file formats that are widely available, and which carry no specific ROI semantics, some standards such as <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/63285.xml">
JPEG 2000</link></format>
 specifically provide mechanisms to label and/or compress to a different degree of fidelity, what they refer to as regions of interest.</p>

</bdy>
</article>
