<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:15:28[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108058098">
<header>
<title>Narus</title>
<id>4692170</id>
<revision>
<id>243445699</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T15:16:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Frap</username>
<id>612852</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Telecommunications companies of the United States</category>
<category>Privacy of telecommunications</category>
<category>Deep packet inspection</category>
<category>Companies established in 1997</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Company</name>
<parameters>
<company_name>
Narus</company_name>
<company_type>
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/1499655.xml">
Private</link></institution>
</kind>
</type>
</company>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</company_type>
<foundation>
1997</foundation>
<industry>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/30322.xml">
Telecommunication</link></industry>
<location_country>
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
</location_country>
<location_city>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/108161.xml">
Mountain View, California</link></village>
</location_city>
<products>
Monitoring/surveillance systems</products>
<homepage>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.narus.com/">
www.narus.com</weblink></homepage>
<key_people>
Founder, Ori Cohen</key_people>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>Narus</b> is a private company founded in 1997 by <link>
Ori Cohen</link>, who had been in charge of technology development for <link>
VDONet</link>, an early <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/28682.xml">
media streaming</link> pioneer.  </p>
<p>

It is notable for being the creator of <b>NarusInsight</b>, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/37153.xml">
supercomputer</link> system which is used by the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/21939.xml">
NSA</link></agency>
 and other bodies to perform <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/331195.xml">
mass surveillance</link> and monitoring of citizens' and corporations' Internet communications in real-time, and whose installation in <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/17555269.xml">
AT&amp;T</link></company>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/49728.xml">
San Francisco</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/48402.xml">
Internet backbone</link> gave rise to a 2006 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/7200.xml">
class action lawsuit</link> by the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/18949836.xml">
Electronic Frontier Foundation</link></company>
 against AT&amp;T. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eff.org/cases/att">
EFF vs AT&amp;T</weblink></p>

<sec>
<st>
Management and investors</st>
<p>

According to Narus's own website <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://narus.com/about/board.html">
listing of the Board of Directors</weblink>, Dr. Cohen is no longer the Chairman of the Board.</p>
<p>

Prior to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/177704.xml">
9/11</link> Narus worked on building <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../453/14925453.xml">
carrier-grade</link> tools to analyze IP network traffic for billing purposes, to prevent what they term "revenue leakage". Post-9/11 they have continued down that path while adding more semantic monitoring abilities for surveillance purposes. In 2004, Narus <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20050206184639/narus.com/press/2004/0929.html">
engaged</weblink> the former Deputy Director of the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/21939.xml">
National Security Agency</link></agency>
, <link>
William Crowell</link> as a director. From the Press Release announcing this:
<indent level="1">

"Crowell is an independent security consultant and holds several board positions with a variety of technology and technology-based security companies. Since 9/11, Crowell has served on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/8957.xml">
Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency</link> (DARPA) Task Force on Terrorism and Deterrence, the National Research Council Committee on Science and Technology for Countering Terrorism and the Markle Foundation Task Force on National Security in the Information Age."
</indent>

Narus has <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/257210.xml">
 venture funding</link> from companies including JP Morgan Partners, <firm wordnetid="108059870" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/5100026.xml">
Mayfield</link></institution>
</business>
</enterprise>
</company>
</firm>
, NeoCarta, Presidio Venture Partners, Walden International, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/14617.xml">
Intel</link>, NTT Software and Sumisho Electronics.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
NarusInsight</st>
<p>

The capabilities of the NarusInsight system are alarming to many privacy advocates. Narus lists several partners who provide various technologies similar to the features of insight. It is unclear if any of these partners are responsible for some of the features. Several of the partners are funded by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/955206.xml">
In-Q-Tel</link></company>
.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
System specification</st>
<p>

From <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://narus.com/products/index.html">
the Key Features list of NarusInsight</weblink>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Universal data collection from links, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/25748.xml">
router</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/660075.xml">
soft switches</link>, <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/113021.xml">
IDS</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/269059.xml">
IPS</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link>s, etc. provides network view across IP networks.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Normalization, Correlation, Aggregation and Analysis provide a model of user, element, protocol, application and network behaviors, in real-time.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/3824661.xml">
Seven 9s</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/3824661.xml">
reliability</link> from data collection to data processing and analysis.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/43734.xml">
Packet</link> processing performance that supports network speeds of up to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/1861262.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22OC-192%22])">
OC-192</link> at <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/146145.xml">
layer 4</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/1861262.xml">
OC-48</link> at <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/172179.xml">
layer 7</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
, enabling carriers to monitor traffic at either the edge of the network or at the core.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Scalability to support large, complex IP networks.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

NarusInsight's functionality can be configured to feed a particular activity or IP service such as security, lawful intercept or even <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/424589.xml">
Skype</link></software>
 detection and blocking.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
System capabilities</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Packet-mode data intercepts for Service Providers and Carriers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wireline to wireless and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/63973.xml">
Wi-Fi</link> or dialup to broadband.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Instant Compliance" with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/530413.xml">
CALEA</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/18934452.xml">
ETSI</link> for simple, fast and hands-free compliance.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Carrier-grade speeds, performance and scalability.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Supports all of your services, out-of-the-box.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Securely manages resources while simplifying audits and reporting.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Network and vendor agnostic.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Enables additional application for revenue generation or revenue protection.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This data flows right into <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://narus.com/products/intercept.html">
NarusInsight Intercept Suite</weblink>, which enables packet-level, flow-level, and application-level usage information is captured and analyzed as well as raw user session packets for forensic analysis, surveillance or in satisfying regulatory compliance for lawful intercept.</p>
<p>

The Lawful Intercept module offers carriers and service providers compliance with regulatory requirements regarding lawful intercept. The Lawful Intercept module provides an end-to-end solution consisting of Administration, Access and Delivery functions. The Lawful Intercept module is compliant with CALEA and ETSI standards. It can be seamlessly integrated with third party products for testing/validation or as a complete law enforcement solution.</p>
<p>

The Directed Analysis module seamlessly integrates with NarusInsight Secure Suite or other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/39776.xml">
DDoS</link>, intrusion or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/1199510.xml">
anomaly detection systems</link>, securely providing analysts with real-time, surgical targeting of suspect information (from flow to application to full packets). The Directed Analysis module provides industry standard formats and offers tools for archival and integration with third party investigative tools.</p>
<p>

These capabilities include playback of streaming media (i.e. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
VoIP</link>), rendering of web pages, examination of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
e-mail</link> and the ability to analyze the payload/attachments of e-mail or file transfer protocols. Narus partner products offer the ability to quickly analyze information collected by the Directed Analysis or Lawful Intercept modules. When Narus partners' powerful analytic tools are combined with the surgical targeting and real-time collection capabilities of Directed Analysis and Lawful Intercept modules, analysts or law enforcement agents are provided capabilities that have been unavailable thus far.</p>
<p>

According to a company press release, the latest version of NarusInsight Intercept Suite (NIS) is "the industry's only network traffic intelligence system that supports real-time precision targeting, capturing and reconstruction of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/75887.xml">
webmail</link> traffic... including Google Gmail, MSN Hotmail, Yahoo! Mail, and Gawab Mail (English and Arabic versions)." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Usage</st>
<p>

It is useful to examine the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/22747.xml">
OSI model</link></system_of_measurement>
</advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 of seven layers which underpins all communication on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>. NarusInsight focuses on two layers: number four, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/146145.xml">
transport layer</link>, built on standards like TCP and UDP, the physical building blocks of Internet data traffic, and number seven, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/172179.xml">
application layer</link>, built on standards like <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/13443.xml">
HTTP</link></system_of_measurement>
</format>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</information>
</message>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/53289.xml">
FTP</link>, which are dependent on the application using them, i.e. Internet Explorer, Kazaa, Skype, etc. NarusInsight monitors 10 billion bits per second at level four and 2.5 billion bits per second at level seven. For reference, a 256K <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/41038.xml">
DSL</link> line equals 0.25 million bits per second (<link>
Mbit/s</link>), and a 56 kbit/s telephone modem around 0.05 Mbit/s. So a single NarusInsight machine can monitor traffic equal to the maximum capacity of around 39,000 DSL lines or 195,000 telephone modems. But, in practical terms, since individual internet connections are not continually filled to capacity, the 10 Gbit/s capacity of one Narus installation enables it to monitor the combined traffic of several million broadband users.</p>
<p>

It can also perform semantic analysis of the same traffic as it is happening, in other words analyze the content, meaning, structure and significance of this entire traffic, as it is happening.</p>
<p>

The exact use of this data is not fully documented. A starting point is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/3630688.xml">
Internet Protocol Detail Record</link>, used to record information about usage activity within the telecom infrastructure (such as a call completion). NDM-U stands for "Network Data Management - Usage". It refers to a functional operation within the Telecom Management Forum's Telecom Operations Map. The NDM function collects data from devices and services in a service providers network. Usage refers to the type of data which is the focus of this document. These standards were built into Narus' systems.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

"IPDR.org has been in existence since 1999 and more than a dozen vendors have actual IPDR implementations "etched in code". Their systems are actually able to talk to each other and interoperate. Version 2.5 and up of the NDM-U represents a stable basis for development. IPDR.org's Interoperability Pavilion is a working demonstration of multiple companies exchanging service usage data in that format."
</indent>
Service usage data. That would be data on the actual usage of the Internet. And what kind of data would this be? Way back in 1999, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.earthweb.com/xSP/article.php/45291">
this article</weblink> stated:
<indent level="1">

"In an effort to provide more complex network <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/480015.xml">
traffic analysis</link>, Narus is introducing its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/29109.xml">
semantic network</link> traffic service. The company cites research which predicts the fast-growing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/100245.xml">
ISP</link> sector will become stagnant without the ability to offer differentiated services. In order to gain significant revenues from these services, a technology was necessary to allow usage based pricing.
</indent>
:"We realized that, at the heart of the data that is needed to accurately measure usage and enable 'pay-as-you-go' business models for Internet service providers, is what we call the 'semantics' of network traffic," said Ori Cohen, Narus' founder and chief executive officer.
<indent level="1">

"In short, by seeing the 'semantics' of network traffic, service providers can see 'inside' the data, providing much more detailed insight about the use of the Internet and the perceived value of specific applications than existing technologies allow."
</indent>
:"Semantic Traffic Analysis uses network technology to consistently capture and analyze all IP data streams on heavily trafficked networks remotely and non-invasively. In addition, the semantics of the data stream are determined also, as well as the protocol used and the application taking place. A variety of other data is available as well."
In this context, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantics</link> is not just the data, but rather the meaning of the data. It looks at the data in a more comprehensive way than looking for keywords. Each NarusInsight machine does this at 2500 million bits per second, in real-time.</p>
<p>

From <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://narus.com/solutions/intercept.html">
Narus' Lawful Intercept and Regulatory Compliance page</weblink>:
<indent level="1">

"Explosive Internet growth in recent years has transformed worldwide communications, yielding tremendous efficiencies and benefits, as well as many risks."
</indent>
:"For example, terrorist attacks around the globe have been carefully orchestrated through Internet-based forms of communications such as e-mail, messaging, hidden Web pages and now VoIP, forcing governmental organizations and law enforcement agencies to re-evaluate how they are providing public security as it becomes so much easier and faster to communicate electronically."
<indent level="1">

"Recent mandates and the resulting standards referenced under CALEA in the United States and ETSI in Western Europe aim to preserve the right of law enforcement agencies to conduct authorized electronic surveillance in an effort to protect the public and its right to privacy. However, these mandates create IT headaches for carriers as they struggle to meet the requirements."
</indent>
:"With a suite of products targeted at meeting <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/1833462.xml">
lawful intercept</link></power>
</concept>
</idea>
 requirements, Narus simplifies lawful intercept tasks helping carriers and agencies meet requirements without experiencing any degradation in service quality."</p>



</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS140435+10-Dec-2007+BW20071210?sp=true">
Narus Expands Traffic Intelligence Solution to Webmail Targeting</weblink>", Reuters&#32;(2007-12-10).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-02-13</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/4731056.xml">
Hepting vs. AT&amp;T</link>, the 2006 lawsuit in which the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/18949836.xml">
Electronic Frontier Foundation</link></company>
 alleges <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/17555269.xml">
AT&amp;T</link></company>
 allowed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/21939.xml">
NSA</link> to tap the entirety of its clients' Internet and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
Voice over IP</link> communications using Narus equipment.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/6126365.xml">
Room 641A</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</disagreement>
</dispute>
</event>
</location>
</controversy>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/29122.xml">
SIGINT</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.narus.com/">
Official website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dailykos.com/storyonly/2006/4/8/14724/28476">
DailyKos.com: Source story for implications of the company's product</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wired.com/news/technology/0,70914-0.html">
Wired News article</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wired.com/news/technology/0,70908-0.html">
Wired News article</weblink> (AT&amp;T whistleblower Mark Klein discusses Narus STA 6400)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blog.wired.com/27BStroke6/att_klein_wired.pdf">
Documents, including pictures, wiring diagrams, and equipment lists and installation dates, from Mark Klein</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/homefront/view/">
Frontline Flash Video "Spying on the Home Front"</weblink>` TV documentary originally aired on PBS 15 May 2007 with a section entitled "The NSA's Eavesdropping at AT&amp;T" with the story of Mark Klein exposing NSA wiretapping with a secure room and Narus STA 6400 at an AT&amp;T facility in San Francisco, CA]</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</company>
</article>
