<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:26:37[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<facility  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103315023">
<station  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104306080">
<header>
<title>Serdang Power Station</title>
<id>4715980</id>
<revision>
<id>229687025</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-04T01:44:55Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Natural gas-fired power stations in Malaysia</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from August 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is written like .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Serdang_Power_Station&amp;action=edit">
rewrite this article</weblink> from a . For <b>blatant</b> advertising that would require a fundamental rewrite to become encyclopedic, use  to mark for .&nbsp;<it>(August 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>Putrajaya Power Station</b> is a main power station in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/1019119.xml">
Klang Valley</link>. Located in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/925666.xml">
Serdang</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/236714.xml">
Selangor</link> near <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/59569.xml">
Putrajaya</link></village>
. </p>
<p>

Putrajaya Power Station (hereinafter referred to as PJPS) or previously known as Serdang Power Station is one of seven thermal power stations owned by Tenaga Nasional Berhad (hereinafter referred as TNB). Under the management of the Generation Division, a TNB’s generation wing, its core business is generating electricity by operating and maintaining the power plants. </p>
<p>

Its name has been officially changed to Putrajaya Power Station on 15th February 2006. </p>
<p>

PJPS, built in 1993 with a total generating capacity of 625 MW was part of  TNB’s plan to increase power generation capacity to meet the nation’s rising electricity demand in the early 1990s. </p>
<p>

The gas turbine plant in PJPS consists of two units of 110MW General Electric Frame 9E model and three units of Siemens 135MW V94.2 Ratio model (Figure P.1).
PJPS is a peaking power plant serving Klang Valley load centre. Its operating regime is of two shift cycle, operating between 12 to 16 hours daily. The importance of the GT is to meet the load demand during peak hours and stabilize the grid line voltage. The machine can be put on commercial loading within 30 minutes upon request and this ability makes PJPS crucial in the eyes of NLDC. </p>
<p>

PJPS is strategically located in Putrajaya, a new administrative centre of Malaysia. For this reason, the station has been identified as a lead station for restoration of Putrajaya Island in the event of interruption of electricity.  This role, “Keeping The Lights On for Putrajaya” is a new challenge for PJPS.</p>
<p>

Although this operating regime is not the most optimum way in terms of efficiencies and could lead to faster aging due to the start stop operation, it is vital to ensure the national grid stability throughout the system. </p>
<p>

Since its first operation in 1994, PJPS manages to play its role in supporting TNB to maintain its stature as the major electricity power generator and play the leading role in powering the nation.</p>
<p>

<b>Organizational Excellence</b></p>
<p>

PJPS is maintaining its vision to be a "WORLD CLASS POWER STATION". In keeping up to this struggle, PJPS is committed to strive on and implement all the quality related systems to contribute towards achieving the vision. </p>
<p>

Adding to the long list of certification such as the MS-ISO 9002 Quality Assurance System, Environmental Management System EMS 14001, Occupational Health and Safety Assessment Series OHSAS 18001 Certification and the upgrading of the Quality Management System to ISO 9001-2000 in the year 2003, is the 5S Practice certification on 1st June 2005. The station has successfully converted its EMS14001:1996 to EMS14001:2004 version. </p>
<p>

In 2003, PJPS created history by being the first business unit in TNB to be awarded the coveted Anugerah Kualiti Presiden (AKP). AKP, which uses a set of audit criteria modeled to the Prime Minister Award and Malcolm Baldrige National Quality Award (USA) is the highest recognition scheme in TNB awarded to a business unit that demonstrates the excellence in management of quality and its services.</p>
<p>

For the year 2004, PJPS maintained the recognition as the highest scorer in the AKP audit.  This has prompted PJPS to strive even more towards recapturing the AKP award. </p>
<p>

With strong determination and passion towards Total Quality Management, PJPS has increased its effort and the strategy paid off as PJPS was selected as the winner of AKP in 2005 for the second time in three years.</p>
<p>

PJPS is confident that, with the continuous commitment of its management and employees, the station will maintain the highest level of excellence in quality and management, thus realizing its vision to be a world-class power station in 2010.</p>
<p>

Organizational Culture
The original shared values of PJPS have guided the company successfully over many years. It was set by PJPS management and executives back in 1996. Those are:</p>
<p>

•	Integrity and Accountability
•	Honesty
•	Mutual Trust And Respect
•	Sense of Belonging and Ownership
•	Openness</p>
<p>

65% of the employees population are diploma holders or higher. This unique environment is part of PJPS’s strength. It contributes to our excellence culture, small but highly educated community. </p>
<p>

PJPS empower its employees by giving them opportunity to lead through special activities. It is a common practice that every employee should be involved in at least one quality related activity as in Putrajaya Quality Committee. </p>
<p>

PJPS promote the excellence culture by encouraging open communication between teams, team participation in setting goals and empowering teams to manage and improve their processes. </p>
<p>

The team culture is emphasized by using the terms ‘Team Members’ instead of ‘employees’ and ‘Geese Masters’ instead of leaders.</p>

</bdy>
</station>
</facility>
</artifact>
</article>
