<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:27:11[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Bapco Bahrain</title>
<id>4733482</id>
<revision>
<id>218593499</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-11T09:59:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Oil and gas companies of Bahrain</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="BapcoTanks.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Bapco Oil Reservoirs in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/4006219.xml">
Sitra</link>
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Bahrain Petroleum Company</b> (Bapco), wholly owned by the Government of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/18933277.xml">
Bahrain</link></country>
, is engaged in the oil industry including exploration and prospecting for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
oil</link>, drilling, production, refining, distribution of petroleum products and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/22131.xml">
natural gas</link>, sales and exports of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/23195.xml">
crude oil</link> and refined products.
The company owns a 250,000 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/640764.xml">
barrel</link>-a-day refinery, storage facilities for more than 14&nbsp;million barrels (2,200,000&nbsp;m3), a marketing terminal, and a marine terminal for its petroleum products.</p>
<p>

BAPCO's prime customers for crude oil and refined products are based in the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/19323.xml">
Middle East</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/11672.xml">
Far East</link>, <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/28741.xml">
Southeast Asia</link></location>
</region>
 and<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<see wordnetid="108586825" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/5334607.xml">
Africa</link></location>
</seat>
</see>
</area>
</center>
</region>
, and 95% of refined products are exported.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Exploration and Development</st>
<p>

BAPCO carries out extensive studies on a continuous basis to explore - with the use of advanced techniques and methods - new oil and gas reserves and obtain more accurate data on the existing reserves.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Drilling and Production</st>
<p>

To maintain production from Bahrain Field at the optimum levels, advanced drilling techniques are applied to new wells, as well as working over the existing wells. As a result of increased demand by the growing industrial base in Bahrain, BAPCO has expanded its gas facilities and increased its natural gas production capacity.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Refining</st>
<p>

The Bahrain Refinery - one of the largest in the Middle East and the oldest in the GCC - refines over 250,000&nbsp;barrels (40,000&nbsp;m3) of crude every day. About one-sixth of this crude originates from Bahrain Field; the remainder is pumped from <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/349303.xml">
Saudi Arabia</link></country>
 in a pipeline extending 27 kilometres over land and a further 27 kilometres under the sea before reaching the north-west of Bahrain.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Storage</st>
<p>

There are more than 170 storage tanks at different sites with a total capacity of over 14&nbsp;million barrels (2,200,000&nbsp;m3).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Products</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/361384.xml">
Liquefied Petroleum Gas</link> (LPG), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/184342.xml">
Naphtha</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/23639.xml">
Gasoline</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/16992.xml">
Kerosene</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/642298.xml">
Aviation turbine fuel</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/81761.xml">
Diesel oil</link>, <link>
Heavy lube distillate</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/392547.xml">
Fuel oil</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/657.xml">
Asphalt</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Marketing</st>
<p>

BAPCO exports crude oil to world markets and sells petroleum products locally and internationally. It also supplies and sells <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/642298.xml">
aviation fuel</link> at the <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/464443.xml">
Bahrain International Airport</link></airport>
 through its affiliate, The Bahrain Aviation Fuelling Company (BAFCO), in which the company is a 60% <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/146081.xml">
shareholder</link>. BAFCO was established in 1985 and its current Mobile Controller is <b><it>Abdulla Buhamood</it></b>.</p>
<p>

The company also provides the full requirements of natural gas to the power generating plants and other industries in the country.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Training and Development</st>
<p>

BAPCO is pressing ahead with its ambitious human resource management programme to ensure that the skills of its workforce match the technological and business demands of the new millennium. In addition, its scholarship and sponsorship programmes support more than 150 students in higher education in Bahrain and abroad.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Environment, Health and Safety</st>
<p>

Protection of the environment continues to be a major focus of the company's policy. In line with best practice, BAPCO has created an EHS policy that integrates the functions of occupational health, industrial safety and environment. A founder member of the <link>
Gulf Area Oil Companies Mutual Aid Organisation</link> (GAOCMAO), the company remains at the forefront of technical expertise in oil spill response. A clearly set out policy, a range of protective clothing and equipment, full training and strict monitoring form BAPCO's ongoing commitment to the prevention and control of accidents and emergencies.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.bapco.com.bh/</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
