<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:41:48[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Fishing reel</title>
<id>47338</id>
<revision>
<id>242428223</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T05:14:10Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Geronimo20</username>
<id>332930</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Fishing equipment</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="text-align: center;" class="infobox">
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/36581.xml">
fishing</link></header>
<row>
<col>
 <image location="center" width="90px" src="Fishing_reel.jpg">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/47337.xml">
fishing rod</link></header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/10964957.xml">
rod taper</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/7498299.xml">
bamboo fly rod</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/7040631.xml">
fly rod building</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/47338.xml">
fishing reel</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/12764618.xml">
bite indicator</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
----</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/6209845.xml">
tackle</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/705225.xml">
recreational</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
----</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/18425054.xml">
I N D E X</link></header>
</row>

</table>

<image location="left" width="200px" src="Fishing_reel.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A spinning reel
</caption>
</image>

A <b>fishing reel</b> is a device used for the deployment and retrieval of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/47339.xml">
fishing line</link> using a spool mounted on an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/160573.xml">
axle</link>.  Fishing reels are traditionally used in the recreational sport of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/223418.xml">
angling</link>.  They are most often used in conjunction with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/47337.xml">
fishing rod</link>, though some specialized reels are mounted directly to boat gunwales or transoms. The earliest known illustration of a fishing reel is from Chinese paintings and records beginning about 1195 A.D. Fishing reels first appeared in England around 1650 A.D., and by the 1760s, London tackle shops were advertising multiplying or gear-retrieved reels.  <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/115033.xml">
Paris, Kentucky</link></village>
 native George Snyder is generally given credit for inventing the first fishing reel in America around 1820, a bait casting design that quickly became popular with American anglers.  
<sec>
<st>
Types of fishing reels</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Centrepin Reel</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Angler_on_a_Wintry_Lake,_by_Ma_Yuan,_1195.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

"Angler on a Wintry Lake," painted in 1195 by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<painter wordnetid="110391653" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/8374705.xml">
Ma Yuan</link></creator>
</artist>
</painter>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, featuring the oldest known depiction of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/47338.xml">
fishing reel</link>
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Mainly used for fly fishing.The fly reel or fly casting reel has traditionally been rather simple in terms of mechanical construction, little has changed from the design patented by Charles F. Orvis in 1874.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  However, in recent years improvements have been made with the development of better reels and drags for fighting larger fish.  A fly reel is normally operated by stripping line off the reel with one hand, while casting the rod with the other hand.  Early fly reels often had no drag at all, but merely a click/pawl mechanism intended to keep the reel from overrunning when line was pulled from the spool.  To slow a fish, the angler simply applied hand pressure to the rim of the revolving spool (known as "palming the rim"). Later, these click/pawl mechanisms were modified to provide a limited adjustable drag. Although adequate for smaller fish, these did not possess a wide adjustment range or the power to slow larger fish.</p>
<p>

Modern fly reels typically have more sophisticated disc-type drag systems made of composite materials that feature increased adjustment range, consistency, and resistance to high temperatures from drag friction.  Most of these fly reels also feature large-arbor spools designed to reduce line memory, maintain consistent drag and assist the quick retrieval of slack line in the event a hooked fish makes a sudden run towards the angler. </p>
<p>

At one time, multiplier fly reels were widely available. These reels had a geared line retrieve of 2:1 or 3:1 that allowed faster retrieval of the fly line.  However, their additional weight, complexity and expense did not justify the advantage of faster line retrieval in the eyes of many anglers.  As a result, today they are rarely used.  </p>
<p>

Automatic fly reels use a coiled spring mechanism that pulls the line into the reel with the flick of a lever.  Automatic reels tend to be heavy for their size, and have limited line capacity. Automatic fly reels peaked in popularity during the 1960s, and since that time they have been outsold many times over by manual fly reels.           </p>
<p>

Saltwater fly reels are designed specifically for use in an ocean environment.  Saltwater fly reels are normally much larger in diameter than most freshwater fly reels in order to provide a large line and backing capacity designed for the long runs of powerful ocean <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/1545806.xml">
game fish</link>.  To prevent corrosion, saltwater fly reels often use aerospace <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/904.xml">
aluminum</link> frames and spools, electroplated and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/27059.xml">
stainless steel</link> components, with sealed and waterproof bearing and drive mechanisms.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Fly Reel Operation</entry>
</list>

Fly reels are normally manual, single-action designs. A rotating a handle on the side of the reel rotates the spool which retrieves the line, usually at a 1:1 ratio (i.e., one complete revolution of the handle equals one revolution of the spool).</p>
<p>

The centrepin reel is also used for coarse fishing, where one can use it to trot on a fast flowing river.  Normally, the float would be pulled under because of the fast current, but the centrepin reel automatically releases line, thus making the float not go under.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Bait casting reel</st>
<p>

Bait casting reels are reels in which line is stored on a bearing supported revolving spool.  The bait casting reel is mounted above the rod, hence its other name, the <it>overhead reel</it>.  The bait casting reel dates from at least the mid-1600s, but came into wide use by amateur anglers during the 1870s.  Early bait casting reels were often constructed with brass or iron gears, with casings and spools made of brass, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/315487.xml">
German silver</link>, or hard rubber.  Early reels were often operated by inverting the reel and using back winding to retrieve line. For this reason, the reel crank handle was positioned on the right side of the reel.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  As a result, the right-hand crank position for bait casting reels has become customary over the years, though models with left-hand retrieve are now gaining in popularity.  Many of today's bait casting reels are constructed using aluminum, stainless steel, and/or synthetic composite materials.  They typically include a level-wind mechanism to prevent the line from being trapped under itself on the spool during rewind and interfering with subsequent casts.  Many are also fitted with anti-reverse handles and drags designed to slow runs by large and powerful game fish.  Because the momentum of the forward cast must rotate the spool as well as propel the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/764520.xml">
fishing lure</link>, bait casting designs normally require heavier lures for proper operation than with other types of reels.  The gear ratio in bait casting reels was initially about 3/1, later standardized at 4/1 in most reels, but recent developments have seen many bait casting reels with gear ratios as high as 5.5/1 or even higher.  Higher gear ratios allow much faster retrieval of line, but sacrifice a small amount of power in exchange.</p>
<p>

Spool tension on most modern bait casting reels can be adjusted with adjustable spool tension, a centrifugal brake, or a magnetic "cast control."  This reduces spool overrun during a cast and the resultant line snare, known as backlash.  Each time a lure of a different weight is attached, the cast control must be adjusted.  The bait casting reel design will operate well with a wide variety of fishing lines, ranging from braided multifilament and heat-fused "superlines" to copolymer, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/78517.xml">
fluorocarbon</link>, and nylon monofilaments (<it>see</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/47339.xml">
Fishing line</link>).  Most bait casting reels can also easily be palmed or thumbed to increase the drag, set the hook, or to accurately halt the lure at a given point in the cast. </p>
<p>

A variation of the bait casting reel is the big game reel. These are very large and robust fishing reels, designed and built for heavy saltwater species such as tuna, marlin, sailfish and sharks.  Big game reels are not designed for casting, but used for trolling or fishing set baits and lures on the open ocean. </p>
<p>

Bait casting reels are sometimes referred to as <it>conventional reels</it> in the U.S. They are known as <it>multiplier reels</it> in Europe, on account of their geared line retrieve (one turn of the handle resulting in multiple turns of the spool).</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Bait Casting Reel Operation</entry>
</list>

A bait casting reel and rod is cast by moving the rod backward, then snapping it forward.  During the forward cast, the weight of the lure pulls the line off the reel.  The thumb is used to halt the lure at the desired location and to prevent spool overrun. Though modern centrifigal braking systems help to control backlash, using a bait casting reel still requires practice, and a certain amount of finesse on the part of the fisherman for best results.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="270px" src="Fishing_reel.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Parts of a spinning reel: <b>1</b>: Pick up or bail <b>2</b>: Reel seat <b>3</b>: Reel foot <b>4</b>: Handle <b>5</b>: Support arm <b>6</b>: Anti-reverse lever <b>7</b>: Skirted spool <b>8</b>: Fishing line <b>9</b>: Drag adjustment knob
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Spinning (fixed spool) reel</st>
<p>

Reels utilizing a fixed spool were in use in North America as early as the 1870s.  They were originally developed to allow the use of artificial flies, or other lures for trout or salmon, that were too light in weight to be easily cast by bait casting reels.  Fixed spooled reels are normally mounted below the rod.  Spinning reels also solved the problem of backlash, as they did not have a rotating spool to overrun and foul the line. The earliest fixed-spool reels turned the spool 90 degrees in the body of the reel for retrieval, and then reversed it back into casting position.  In casting position, line was drawn off in coils from the end of the fixed, non-rotating spool.  </p>
<p>

In 1948, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/268126.xml">
Mitchell</link> Reel Company of <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<commune wordnetid="108541609" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/3116044.xml">
Cluses</link></district>
</commune>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, France introduced the Mitchell 300, the first modern commercially successful spinning reel, with a design that oriented the face of the spool forward in a permanently fixed position below the fishing rod.  A mechanical line pickup was used to retrieve the cast line (eventually developed into a wire bail design), and an anti-reverse lever prevented the crank handle from rotating while a fish was pulling line from the spool.  Because the line did not have to pull against a rotating spool, much lighter lures could be cast than with a bait casting reel.  Conversely, halting the cast and stopping the lure at the desired position requires practice in learning to feather the line with the forefinger as it uncoils from the spool.  Most spinning reels operate best with fairly limp, flexible fishing lines.</p>
<p>

Though spinning reels do not suffer from backlash, the line can be trapped underneath itself on the spool or even detach from the reel in loose loops of line.  Various oscillating spool mechanisms have been introduced over the years in an effort to solve this problem.  Spinning reels also tend to have more issues with twisting of the fishing line.  Line twist in spinning reels can occur from the spin of an attached lure, the action of the wire bail against the line when engaged by the crank handle, or even retrieval of line that is under load (spinning reel users normally pump the rod up and down, then retrieve the slack line to avoid line twist and stress on internal components).  Most anglers who use a spinning reel also manually reposition the bail after each cast in order to minimize line twist.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Fixed Spool Reel Operation</entry>
</list>

Fixed spool reels are cast by opening the bail, grasping the line with the forefinger, and then using a backward snap of the rod followed by a forward cast while releasing the line with the forefinger at the same time.  On the retrieve, the large rotating wire cage or bail (either manually or trigger-operated) serves as the line pickup, restoring the line to its original position on the spool.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Spin cast reel</st>
<p>

The first commercial spin cast reels were introduced by the Denison-Johnson Reel Company and the Zero Hour Bomb Company (ZEBCO) in 1949.  The spin cast reel is an attempt to solve the problem of backlash found in bait cast designs, while reducing line twist and snare complaints sometimes encountered with traditional spinning reel designs. Just as with the spinning reel, the line is thrown from a fixed spool and can therefore be used with relatively light lures and baits.  However, the spin cast reel eliminates the large wire bail and line roller of the spinning reel in favor of one or two simple pickup pins and a metal cup to wind the line on the spool.  Traditionally mounted above the rod, the spin cast reel is also fitted with an external nose cone that encloses and protects the fixed spool.</p>
<p>

With a fixed spool, spin cast reels can cast lighter lures than bait cast reels, although friction of the nose cone against the unspooling line slightly reduces casting distance compared to spinning reels.  Spin cast reels also generally have narrow spools with less line capacity than either bait casting or spinning reels of equivalent size. However, this tends to reduce line snare issues.   Like other types of reels, spin cast reels are frequently fitted with both anti-reverse crank levers and friction drags, and some also have level-wind (oscillating spool) mechanisms.  Most spin cast reels operate best with limp monofilament lines, though at least one spin cast reel manufacturer installs a thermally fused "superline" into one of its models as standard equipment. During the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/19283873.xml">
1950</link>'s and into the mid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/34664.xml">
1960</link>'s, they were widely used and very popular, though the spinning reel has since eclipsed them in popularity in North America.  They remain a favorite fishing tool for beginners.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Spin Cast Reel Operation</entry>
</list>

Pressing a button on the rear of the reel disengages the line pickup, and the button is then released during the forward cast to allow the line to fly off the spool. The button is pressed again to stop the lure at the position desired.  Upon cranking the handle, the pickup pin immediately re-engages the line and spools it onto the reel.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Underspin reel</st>
<p>

Underspin or Triggerspin reels are spin cast reels in which the reel is mounted underneath a standard spinning rod.  With the reel's weight suspended beneath the rod, underspin reels are generally more comfortable to cast and hold for long periods, and the ability to use all standard spinning rods greatly increases its versatility compared to traditional spin cast reels. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Underspin Reel Operation</entry>
</list>

A lever or trigger is grasped or rotated (usually by the forefinger) and this action suspends the line in place.  During the forward cast, the lever/trigger is released, and the line flies off the fixed spool.  When necessary, the lever can be activated once again to stop the lure at a given point in the cast.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Reel Mechanisms</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Direct-drive reel</entry>
</list>

Direct-drive reels have the spool and handle directly coupled. When the handle moves forwards, the spool moves forwards, and vice-versa. With a fast-running fish, this may have consequences for the angler's knuckles. Traditional fly reels are direct-drive. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Anti-reverse reel</entry>
</list>

In anti-reverse reels, a mechanism allows line to pay out while the handle remains stationary. Depending on the drag setting, line may also pay out, as with a running fish, while the angler reels in. Bait casting reels and many modern saltwater fly reels are examples of this design.
The mechanism works either with a 'dog' or 'pawl' design that engages into a cog wheel attached to the handle shaft. The latest design is Instant Anti-Reverse, or IAR. This system incorporates a one-way clutch bearing on the handle shaft to restrict handle movement to forward motion only.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Drag Mechanisms</st>

<p>

Drag is a mechanical means of applying variable pressure to the turning spool in order to act as a friction brake against it.  It can be as simple as a flat spring pressing against the edge of the spool, or as sophisticated as a complicated arrangement of leather and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/15028152.xml">
Teflon</link> discs.  Properly set drag allows larger and more powerful fish to be safely brought to boat and landed, as the drag will "slip" below the breaking point of the line, but in combination with the angle of the rod, it puts relentless pressure on the fish, quickly tiring it.  As a rough general rule, drag is nominally set at about one-half of the line's breaking strength.  It can be adjusted up or down as needed by the fisherman while playing a fish, though it takes practice to do this without adding too much drag which frequently results in a broken line and a lost fish.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Manufacturers</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../963/4514963.xml">
Abu Garcia</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/4027818.xml">
Okuma</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <manufacturer wordnetid="108060446" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/242648.xml">
Shimano</link></institution>
</business>
</enterprise>
</company>
</manufacturer>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/18064202.xml">
Shakespeare Fishing Tackle</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/11082843.xml">
Daiwa Seiko Corporation</link></company>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/223418.xml">
Angling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/99030.xml">
Bass fishing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/47339.xml">
Fishing line</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/47337.xml">
Fishing rod</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/218754.xml">
Fly Fishing</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Henshall, J.A., <it>Book of the Black Bass</it>, (1881)</entry>
<entry id="2">
Henshall, J.A., <it>Book of the Black Bass</it>, (1881)</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Henshall, J.A., <it>Book of the Black Bass</it> Cincinnati: J.A. Henshall (1881)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Turner, Graham, <it>Fishing Tackle: A Collector's Guide</it>, Ward Lock Ltd. (1991)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.orcaonline.org/reel_history.htm">
O.R.C.A. Online, <it>Reel History''</it></weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.powerandmotoryacht.com/sportfishing/history-of-fishing-reels/">
Quantum Leap</weblink> – the development of fishing reels.</entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/307491.xml">
Fisheries</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/36581.xml">
fishing</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/307491.xml">
Fisheries</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/1171019.xml">
Fisheries science</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/494704.xml">
Management</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/6145678.xml">
Quota</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/17169979.xml">
Wild</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/581326.xml">
Habitats</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/153520.xml">
Farmed</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/1634.xml">
Aquaculture</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/2579103.xml">
Fish types</link></col>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 0px 0px 2px;" rowspan="13">
<image width="160px" src="Trawer_Hauling_Nets.jpg">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/36581.xml">
Fishing</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/16015052.xml">
Fishing history</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/10079376.xml">
Fishing vessel</link>s&nbsp;·  <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/11017175.xml">
Environment</link></issue>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/491120.xml">
Industry</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/1028691.xml">
Commercial fishing</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/11967708.xml">
Processing</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/16673298.xml">
Products</link>&nbsp;·  <group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<selling wordnetid="101113068" confidence="0.8">
<transaction wordnetid="101106808" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<commerce wordnetid="101090446" confidence="0.8">
<sale wordnetid="101114824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/16684864.xml">
Marketing</link></sale>
</commerce>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</transaction>
</selling>
</group_action>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/7332666.xml">
Markets</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/705225.xml">
Recreational</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/223418.xml">
Angling</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/525221.xml">
Game fishing</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/218754.xml">
Fly fishing</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/13089116.xml">
Techniques</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/16804599.xml">
Gathering</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/306254.xml">
Spearfishing</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/1282465.xml">
Line fishing</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/1137395.xml">
Netting</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/335840.xml">
Trawling</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/4321490.xml">
Trapping</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/1790672.xml">
Other</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/6209845.xml">
Tackle</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/989954.xml">
Hook</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/47339.xml">
Line</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/2212621.xml">
Sinker</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/47337.xml">
Rod</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/18388052.xml">
Bait</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/764520.xml">
Lures</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/9470597.xml">
Artificial flies</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/12764618.xml">
Bite alarm</link>s</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Locations</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/16701166.xml">
Fishing by country</link>&nbsp;·  <diversion wordnetid="100426928" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<sport wordnetid="100523513" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/11289055.xml">
Localities</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</sport>
</event>
</diversion>
&nbsp;·  <stream wordnetid="109448361" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<body_of_water wordnetid="109225146" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<river wordnetid="109411430" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/6869616.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Fishing+community%22])">
Communities</link></river>
</group>
</community>
</gathering>
</body_of_water>
</social_group>
</stream>
&nbsp;·  <slope wordnetid="109437454" confidence="0.8">
<geological_formation wordnetid="109287968" confidence="0.8">
<bank wordnetid="109213565" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/2193792.xml">
Fishing banks</link></bank>
</geological_formation>
</slope>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/18429296.xml">
List of topics by subject</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
