<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:27:28[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<procedure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101023820">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Tip of the tongue</title>
<id>4743980</id>
<revision>
<id>239628014</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-19T19:07:33Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>NerdyNSK</username>
<id>2487856</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Figures of speech</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
<category>Memory processes</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>tip of the tongue</b> (<b>TOT</b> or <b>Tot</b>) phenomenon is an instance of knowing something that cannot immediately be recalled.  TOT is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/297724.xml">
experience</link> with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/18844.xml">
memory</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/236809.xml">
recollection</link> involving difficulty retrieving a well-known <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/1449866.xml">
word</link> or familiar <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/164226.xml">
name</link>.  When experiencing TOT, people feel that the blocked word is on the verge of being recovered. Despite failure in finding the word, people have the feeling that the blocked word is figuratively "on the tip of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/55999.xml">
tongue</link>."  Inaccessibility and the sense of imminence are two key features of an operational definition of TOTs (A.S. Brown, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/34703.xml">
1991</link>).
<sec>
<st>
History of Tip of the Tongue</st>
<p>

The experience of TOT appeared in non-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/351220.xml">
academic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/18963870.xml">
literature</link> as early as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/34715.xml">
1885</link>.  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<dramatist wordnetid="110030277" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
Anton Chekhov</link></doctor>
</dramatist>
</writer>
</person>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/28296.xml">
short story</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ibiblio.org/eldritch/ac/horsey.htm">
"A Horsey Name"</weblink> is about the main character's tip-of-the-tongue experience involving a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/72243.xml">
surname</link>.  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/34707.xml">
1890</link>, pioneering <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/72132.xml">
psychologist</link> <philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/90682.xml">
William James</link></philosopher>
 discussed the phenomenon in his text <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/James/Principles/">
<it>The Principles of Psychology''</it></weblink>. James described the TOT state as "a gap that is intensely active".</p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/34691.xml">
1966</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18426501.xml">
Harvard</link> psychologists Roger Brown and David McNeill reported the first <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/307139.xml">
empirical</link> investigation of the tip-of-the-tongue state.  They recounted, "[t]he signs of it were unmistakable" and "he [a research participant] would appear to be in mild torment, something like on the brink of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/232411.xml">
sneeze</link>, and if he found the word his relief was considerable."  They also found that TOT is a fairly universal phenomenon, TOTs occur about once a week and increase as you age, and they're often caused by proper names.  Further, people experiencing TOT are often able to access the first letter of the "target word" fairly accurately and they also bring up words related to the "target word."  Finally, R. Brown and McNeill have some good news: target words are retrieved during the experience of a TOT phenomenon about half of the time (A.S. Brown, 1991).</p>
<p>

Although it is not explicitly called by this name it is interesting to note that TOT is briefly considered by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/308.xml">
Aristotle</link></philosopher>
</person>
 in "On Memory and Reminiscence", in his discussion on recollection. (453a, 28)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Recent TOT literature</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Universality</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/106238.xml">
Cognitive</link> psychologist Bennett Schwartz examined fifty-one <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/17524.xml">
language</link>s and found that forty-five of them include expressions using the word <it>tongue</it> to describe the TOT state.  Some languages use multiple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/20518.xml">
metaphors</link>.  In <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/16756.xml">
Korean</link></language>
, the metaphor "going round and round at the end of the tongue" is used, as well as "caught in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/90655.xml">
throat</link>." <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/10597.xml">
French</link></language>
 speakers use the "tongue" metaphor. In some languages, tongue is often replaced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/2136925.xml">
lip</link>, "I got it (the word) right on my lips", the concept remaining identical, and having an obvious relation to the tongue. The results of the language survey suggest that the use of the "tongue" metaphor is not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/47563.xml">
idiom</link>atic to <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English</link></language>
 but instead a commonality of the TOT phenomenon.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/25524.xml">
Research</link> involving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/5128279.xml">
diaries</link> kept of TOT experiences show that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/5689.xml">
college</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/155526.xml">
student</link>s have approximately one or two TOTs per <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/33538.xml">
week</link>, while <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/229060.xml">
elderly</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/167334.xml">
adult</link>s have about two to four TOTs per week (Schacter, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>).  TOTs occur most frequently for names of people, but for common words as well.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Etiology and the TOT in different psychology subdisciplines</st>

<ss3>
<st>
A.S. Brown (1991) and Tulving's (1989) critique of the doctrine of concordance</st>
<p>

A second major landmark study of TOTs was a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/538779.xml">
review</link> paper by A.S. Brown (1991), who detailed the pertinent research that had been done on TOTs for the 25-year period since R. Brown and McNeill (1966).  In most sections of his review, A.S. Brown raised theoretical questions about TOTs that warrant further study, but most remain untested today.  Instead of duplicating this coverage, Schwartz (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link>) explored the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/10055.xml">
etiology</link> of the phenomenon.  Schwartz considers TOTs in light of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/1623866.xml">
Tulving</link>’s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/34847.xml">
1989</link>) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/453596.xml">
critique</link> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/18935258.xml">
doctrine</link> of concordance and how it applies to the etiology of TOTs.  The doctrine of concordance states that cognitive processes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/4805.xml">
behavior</link>, and phenomenological experience are highly correlated.  In Tulving’s view, cognitive processes should not be confused with the study of phenomenological experiences.  For example, the cognitive process of “retrieval” is not the same thing as or comparable to the experience of “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/236809.xml">
recollection</link>.”</p>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Psycholinguistics, memory perspectives, and metacognition</st>
<p>

The TOT has been studied using three different subdisciplines as approaches:  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/160538.xml">
psycholinguistics</link>, memory perspectives, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/1480420.xml">
metacognition</link>.  The first two are consistent with concordance and argue for <it>direct access</it> (a view that TOTs and word retrieval are caused by the same retrieval processes), while the metacognitive approach challenges concordance.  </p>
<p>

Most research to date concerning TOTs has come from the psycholinguistic perspective.  This perspective focuses on TOTs as a temporary breakdown in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/18077.xml">
lexical</link> retrieval.  This approach has linked TOTs to other errors in spoken language, such as slips of the tongue and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/28543.xml">
spoonerism</link>s.  Researchers from the memory perspective have viewed TOTs as a marker of retrieval processes gone awry.  Metacognitive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
model</link>s focus on the role that monitoring and controlling processes play in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/106238.xml">
cognition</link>.  This approach views TOTs as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/317465.xml">
inference</link>s based on non-target <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/18985062.xml">
information</link> that is accessible to rememberers.</p>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Three hypotheses of direct-access</st>
<p>

The direct-access views of the psycholinguistic and memory perspectives fall into three basic hypotheses.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The first is the blocking <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/14281.xml">
hypothesis</link> which states that TOTs occur because the rememberers recognize blocking words as incorrect but cannot retrieve the correct but inhibited target.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The second is the incomplete activation hypothesis which views that TOTs are caused by the sensitivity to the existence of an unrecalled target in memory, accompanied by the failure to retrieve the target into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/5664.xml">
conscious</link> memory.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The third hypothesis is the transmission deficit model which states that TOTs are brought about when the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantic</link> representation of the word is activated, but there is a failure to prime the complete <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/23247.xml">
phonological</link> representation of the target word.</entry>
</list>

The psycholinguistic approach views TOTs as a "window" on word retrieval (Schwartz, 1999).  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link>, Deborah Burke and Lori James reported on their research employing a repetition <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/473325.xml">
priming</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/175308.xml">
paradigm</link> that utilized prime words that shared phonological components with potential TOT target words.  They concluded that their results "support the transmission deficit model that the weak connections among phonological representations that cause TOTs are strengthened by production of phonologically related words" (Burke &amp; James, 2000, p. 1378).</p>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
Support for direct-access</st>
<p>

Providing support for the direct-access views are research subjects recognition of TOT targets and their ability to give partial information of TOT targets.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/1208543.xml">
Recognition</link> of the correct target following a TOT experience is much greater than recognition of the correct target when subjects are not experiencing a TOT.  And research subjects can usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/236809.xml">
recall</link> phonological information related to the TOT targets, such as the first <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/3675310.xml">
letter</link> of the word, the number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/44911.xml">
syllable</link>s, and the syllabic stress.</p>

</ss3>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
TOT and Neurobiology</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Neural basis of TOT</st>

<p>

<table style="margin:0 0 5px 5px; float:right; width: 270px;" class="toccolours">
<row>
<col style="text-align: center; background:dimgray; color:#ffffff;">
<b> Human Cerebrum </b></col>
</row>
<row style="text-align: center;">
<header style="background:white">
 <image width="250px" src="Lobes_of_the_brain_NL.svg">
</image>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/469220.xml">
Frontal lobe</link>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/466322.xml">
Temporal lobe</link>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/465886.xml">
Parietal lobe</link>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/472212.xml">
Occipital lobe</link></header>
</row>
<row>
<header style="text-align: left; line-height: 1;">
 Lobes of the human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/487841.xml">
cerebrum</link>.  The temporal lobe (green) and frontal lobe (blue)are thought to play an important role in speech</header>
</row>
</table>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/419589.xml">
anterior cingulate</link> and right middle <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/469220.xml">
frontal cortices</link> are two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../944/21944.xml">
neural</link> areas implicated in the TOT phenomenon.  One study showed that, relative to successful retrieval or unsuccessful retrieval not accompanied by a TOT, retrieval failures accompanied by TOTs elicited a selective response in anterior cingulate-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/1967493.xml">
prefrontal cortices</link>.  The study also found that while attempting to retrieve information, subjects rely heavily on visual spatial clues in correctly retrieving the information.  For example, some subjects in the study that were trying to recall a name described looking at the person's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/53234.xml">
face</link> in attempting to retrieve the name.  Also, when trying to recall the name of an author, the subjects described attempting to read the name of the author from an imagined book.  The authors of the study suggest that "the extent that the subjects in our <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/226722.xml">
fMRI</link> study used a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/305136.xml">
visual</link> imagery strategy when in a TOT condition, the activation observed in right inferior PFC could constitute the neural correlates of these efforts to resolve these retrieval failures" (Maril et al., 2001, p. 657).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Three stage neural network model</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Ambox_?.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>All or part of this article may be .</b>
Please help . Suggestions may be on the . <it>(May 2007)</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>

<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Neural_network.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Simplified view of an artificial neural network
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

One <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/30746.xml">
theory</link> of why the tip of the tongue phenomenon occurs comes from Petro Gopych (2001), a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/19360771.xml">
professor</link> at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/719914.xml">
Kharkiv National University</link>. Gopych’s model proposes three stages in word recall process.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<it>Word <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/349771.xml">
node</link> selection''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

This first stage involves actually selecting which word we are trying to recall. When specifying the word, we identify the learned <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
artificial neural network</link> (ANN) which contains information about the target word, and then activate that part.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<it>Word retrieval''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

According to Gopych, free recall exhibits <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/242260.xml">
positive</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/242258.xml">
negative</link> outputs <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
random</link>ly in the learned ANN. When trying to recall a specific word, otherwise known as cued recall, the retrieval process depicts a “spike” of these outputs with a fixed part of the true information (specific word). The result of attempts to retrieve the word from the learned ANN is an output of positive and negative units.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<it>Comparison of patterns''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The pattern of outputs determined by the retrieval attempts is compared to a reference pattern from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/8661267.xml">
metamemory</link>. If the sample pattern matches the reference pattern, the searching stops because the word that was searched for is recalled. If there is no match, the retrieval process (stage 2) starts over again and a pattern of outputs enters the ANN. This continues until the reference pattern is detected or the process is stopped independently. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Gopych believes that the problem in recalling a specified word comes from a damaged ANN. He suggests that the stored semantic information is damaged or incompletely selected. The severity of the damage determines the power of the TOT.</p>
<p>

Gopych’s three stage <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/1729542.xml">
neural network</link> theory can be used to explain many aspects of TOT including semantic priming, immediate, delay, or eventually full TOT resolution, age dependence in TOTs, recollection of the first letter of the target word, and many more. Using the number of attempts of memory retrieval, the duration of time intervals between successive sets of spikes, and the duration of single <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/21120.xml">
neuron</link> spikes, the retrieval <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/2259059.xml">
chronometry</link> can be determined. Gopych’s theory also supports Tulving’s challenge to the doctrine of concordance.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 TOT across the lifespan</st>
<p>

TOT research in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/128987.xml">
children</link> has mainly focused on when they begin to experience TOTs and what the experience is like for them (Brown, 1991).  Wellman (1977) found evidence that children between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/217280.xml">
kindergarten</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../006/1066006.xml">
third grade</link> (ages 4-7) did experience TOTs, though very rarely.  They were able to recall pieces of the target word, words that sound like it or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/26226.xml">
rhyme</link>d with it, and long words that included it.  Further, they would tell researchers that they knew the word, but were having trouble remembering it.  Like adults, they also became uncomfortable and frustrated by the experience.  Finally, his findings suggest that TOTs occur more often in third graders (ages 6-7) than they do in kindergarteners and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/1066022.xml">
first grade</link>rs.</p>
<p>

More research has been done with TOTs in older adults.  In terms of subjective estimates, research has found that older adults report experiencing TOTs about as often as younger adults (Brown, 1991).  However, studies by Burke et al. (1991) and Cohen and Faulkner (1986) with more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/4410781.xml">
objective</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/19022.xml">
measurement</link>s received different results.  Their participants kept diaries for four weeks, recording their TOT experiences, and young adults were found to experience significantly fewer TOTs than older adults.  Other TOT literature has found that older adults remember less information about the target word and bring up fewer related words during the TOT experience and are less active in resolving the TOT experience (Brown, 1991).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>



<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brown, A.S. (1991). A review of the tip-of-the-tongue experience. <it>Psychological Bulletin, 109</it>(2), 204-223.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brown, R., &amp; McNeill, D. (1966). The "tip-of-the-tongue" phenomenon. <it>Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior, 5</it>, 325-337.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Burke, D., MacKay, D.G., Worthley, J.S., &amp; Wade,E. (1991).  On the tip of the tongue: What causes word finding failures in young and older adults?  <it>Journal of Memory and Language,</it> 30, 237-246.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Burke, D.M., &amp; James, L.E. (2000). Phonological priming effects on word retrieval and tip-of-the-tongue experiences in young and older adults. <it>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory and Cognition, 26</it>, 1378-1391.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cohen, G. &amp; Faulkner, D. (1986).  Memory for proper names: Age differences in retrieval.  <it>British Journal of Developmental Psychology,</it> 4, 187-197.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gopych, P.M. (2001). <it>Quantitative Neural Network Model of the Tip-of-the-Tongue Phenomenon Based on Synthesized Memory-Psycholinguistic-Metacognitive Approach</it>. Kharkiv National University, <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/2788558.xml">
Kharkiv</link></city>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/31750.xml">
Ukraine</link></country>
. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Maril, A., Wagner, A. D., &amp; Schacter, D. L. (2001). On the tip of the tongue: An event-related fMRI study of semantic retrieval failure and cognitive conflict. <it>Neuron, 31</it>, 653-660.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Schacter, D.L. (2001). <it>The seven sins of memory: How the mind forgets and remembers</it>. New York: Houghton Mifflin.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Schwartz, B.L. (1999). Sparkling at the end of the tongue: The etiology of the tip-of-the-tongue phenomenology. <it>Psychonomic Bulletin &amp; Review, 6</it>(3), 379-393.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Wellman, H. M. (1977). Tip of the tongue and feeling of knowing experiences: A developmental study of memory monitoring.  <it>Child Development, 48</it>, 13-21.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/106238.xml">
Cognition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/1480420.xml">
Metacognition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/317501.xml">
Introspection</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/5757907.xml">
Lethologica</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/1853648.xml">
Mental block</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/529089.xml">
Dissociation</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/03/10/AR2008031001612.html">
<it>It's on the Tip of Your Tongue''</it></weblink>, an article published by <it>The Washington Post</it> on 11 March 2008.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ageworks.com/course_demo/520/module3/images/tongue.gif">
"Tip of the Tongue"</weblink> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/7165.xml">
cartoon</link>, by Dave Coverly</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a961213.html">
"What's the Word for When You Can't Think of the Word?"</weblink> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/1418306.xml">
The Straight Dope</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cogprints.org/382/00/TOThtml.html">
<it>Tip-of-the-Tongue Phenomena: An Introductory Phenomenological Analysis''</it></weblink> from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/905735.xml">
Cogprints</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wjh.harvard.edu/~caram/PDFs/1997_Caramazza_Miozzo.pdf">
<it>The Relation Between Syntactic and Phonological Knowledge in Lexical Access: Evidence From the 'Tip-of-the-Tongue' Phenomenon''</it></weblink> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link> file, requires <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/203896.xml">
Adobe Acrobat Reader</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/psocpubs/mrc/2001/00000029/00000001/art00012">
<it>The Relation of Tip-of-the-Tongue States and Retrieval Time''</it></weblink> -- an investigation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/10406.xml">
emotion</link>al TOTs versus nonemotional TOTs (full text in PDF)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.CL/0107012.3">
<it>Three-Stage Quantitative Neural Network Model of the Tip-of-the-Tongue Phenomenon''</it></weblink> (full text PDF in <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/25431.xml">
Russian</link></language>
, with an English <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/556400.xml">
abstract</link>)</entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</article>
