<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:08:36[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<know-how  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105616786">
<method  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105660268">
<header>
<title>Structural alignment</title>
<id>474908</id>
<revision>
<id>243116694</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T06:15:05Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Thorwald</username>
<id>74279</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Protein methods</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="Alignment_of_thioredoxins.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Structural alignment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/1170407.xml">
thioredoxin</link>s from humans and the fly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/173204.xml">
Drosophila melanogaster</link>. The proteins are shown as ribbons, with the human protein in red, and the fly protein in yellow. Generated from PDB <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/explore.do?structureId=3TRX">
3TRX</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/explore.do?structureId=1XWC">
1XWC</weblink>.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Structural alignment</b> is a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/149289.xml">
sequence alignment</link> based on comparison of shape. These alignments attempt to establish equivalences between two or more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/23001.xml">
polymer</link> structures based on their shape and three-dimensional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
conformation</link>. This process is usually applied to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
tertiary structure</link>s but can also be used for large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/25758.xml">
RNA</link> molecules. In contrast to simple structural superposition, where at least some equivalent residues of the two structures are known, structural alignment requires no <it>a priori</it> knowledge of equivalent positions. Structural alignment is a valuable tool for the comparison of proteins with low sequence similarity, where evolutionary relationships between proteins cannot be easily detected by standard sequence alignment techniques. Structural alignment can therefore be used to imply <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/9236.xml">
evolution</link>ary relationships between proteins that share very little common sequence. However, caution should be used in using the results as evidence for shared evolutionary ancestry because of the possible confounding effects of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/82804.xml">
convergent evolution</link> by which multiple unrelated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link> sequences converge on a common <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
tertiary structure</link>. </p>
<p>

Structural alignments can compare two sequences or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/4066308.xml">
multiple sequences</link>. Because these alignments rely on information about all the query sequences' three-dimensional conformations, the method can only be used on sequences where these structures are known. These are usually found by <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/34151.xml">
X-ray crystallography</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/1908527.xml">
NMR spectroscopy</link>. It is possible to perform a structural alignment on structures produced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/306769.xml">
structure prediction</link> methods. Indeed, evaluating such predictions often requires a structural alignment between the model and the true known structure to assess the model's quality. Structural alignments are especially useful in analyzing data from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/303101.xml">
structural genomics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/55172.xml">
proteomics</link> efforts, and they can be used as comparison points to evaluate alignments produced by purely sequence-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link> methods.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

The outputs of a structural alignment are a superposition of the atomic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/81931.xml">
coordinate sets</link> and a minimal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/66819.xml">
root mean square</link> distance (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/4177506.xml">
RMSD</link>) between the structures. The RMSD of two aligned structures indicates their divergence from one another. Structural alignment can be complicated by the existence of multiple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/10130725.xml">
protein domain</link>s within one or more of the input structures, because changes in relative orientation of the domains between two structures to be aligned can artificially inflate the RMSD.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Data produced by structural alignment </st>
<p>

The minimum information produced from a successful structural alignment is a set of superposed three-dimensional coordinates for each input structure. (Note that one input element may be fixed as a reference and therefore its superposed coordinates do not change.) The fitted structures can be used to calculate mutual RMSD values, as well as other more sophisticated measures of structural similarity such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/7214369.xml">
global distance test</link> (GDT<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, the metric used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/461517.xml">
CASP</link>). The structural alignment also implies a corresponding one-dimensional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/149289.xml">
sequence alignment</link> from which a sequence identity, or the percentage of residues that are identical between the input structures, can be calculated as a measure of how closely the two sequences are related.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Types of comparisons</st>
<p>

Because protein structures are composed of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link>s whose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/1152896.xml">
side chain</link>s are linked by a common protein backbone, a number of different possible subsets of the atoms that make up a protein macromolecule can be used in producing a structural alignment and calculating the corresponding RMSD values. When aligning structures with very different sequences, the side chain atoms generally are not taken into account because their identities differ between many aligned residues. For this reason it is common for structural alignment methods to use by default only the backbone atoms included in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/24446.xml">
peptide bond</link>. For simplicity and efficiency, often only the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/2475322.xml">
alpha carbon</link> positions are considered, since the peptide bond has a minimally variant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/12984700.xml">
planar</link> conformation. Only when the structures to be aligned are highly similar or even identical is it meaningful to align side-chain atom positions, in which case the RMSD reflects not only the conformation of the protein backbone but also the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/1527574.xml">
rotamer</link>ic states of the side chains. Other comparison criteria that reduce noise and bolster positive matches include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/28691.xml">
secondary structure</link> assignment, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/6893752.xml">
native contact</link> maps or residue interaction patterns, measures of side chain packing, and measures of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/13609.xml">
hydrogen bond</link> retention.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Structural superposition</st>
<p>

The most basic possible comparison between protein structures makes no attempt to align the input structures and requires a precalculated alignment as input to determine which of the residues in the sequence are intended to be considered in the RMSD calculation. Structural superposition is commonly used to compare multiple conformations of the same protein (in which case no alignment is necessary, since the sequences are the same) and to evaluate the quality of alignments produced using only sequence information between two or more sequences whose structures are known.  This method traditionally uses a simple least-squares fitting algorithm, in which the optimal rotations and translations are found by minimizing the sum of the squared distances among all structures in the superposition.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> More recently, maximum likelihood and Bayesian methods have greatly increased the accuracy of the estimated rotations, translations, and covariance matrices for the superposition <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>. </p>
<p>

Algorithms based on multidimensional rotations and modified <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/51440.xml">
quaternion</link>s have been developed to identify topological relationships between protein structures without the need for a predetermined alignment. Such algorithms have successfully identified canonical folds such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/6207833.xml">
four-helix bundle</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wishart.biology.ualberta.ca/SuperPose/">
SuperPose</weblink> method is sufficiently extensible to correct for relative domain rotations and other structural pitfalls.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Algorithmic complexity </st>
<p>

Both the optimal "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/3135539.xml">
threading</link>" of a protein sequence onto a known structure<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> and the production of an optimal multiple sequence alignment<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> have been shown to be <class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/39466.xml">
NP-complete</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
. However, this does not imply that the structural alignment problem is NP-complete. On the basis of the argument that a true optimal solution is not biologically meaningful due to the experimental error inherent in protein structure determination, an approximate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/44576.xml">
polynomial-time</link> algorithm for structural alignment that produces a family of "optimal" solutions within an approximation parameter for a given scoring function has been developed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> However, at <math>O(n^{10}/\epsilon^6)</math> for a globular protein of <it>n</it> residues, the algorithm is still too computationally expensive for practical use. As a consequence, practical algorithms that converge to the global solutions of the alignment, given a scoring function, do not exist. Most algorithms are, therefore, heuristic, but algorithms that guarantee the convergence to at least local maximizers of the scoring functions, and are practical, have been developed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Representation of structures </st>
<p>

Protein structures have to be represented in some coordinate-independent space to make them comparable. This is typically achieved by constructing a sequence-to-sequence matrix or series of matrices that encompass comparative metrics: rather than absolute distances relative to a fixed coordinate space. An intuitive representation is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/831350.xml">
distance matrix</link>, which is a two-dimensional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19008728.xml">
matrix</link> containing all pairwise distances between some subset of the atoms in each structure (such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/2475322.xml">
alpha carbons</link>). The matrix increases in dimensionality as the number of structures to be simultaneously aligned increases. Reducing the protein to a coarse metric such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/28691.xml">
secondary structure</link> elements (SSEs) or structural fragments can also produce sensible alignments, despite the loss of information from discarding distances, as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/236932.xml">
noise</link> is also discarded.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> Choosing a representation to facilitate computation is critical to developing an efficient alignment mechanism.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods</st>
<p>

Structural alignment techniques have been used in comparing individual structures or sets of structures as well as in the production of "all-to-all" comparison databases that measure the divergence between every pair of structures present in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/102505.xml">
Protein Data Bank</link> (PDB). Such databases are used to classify proteins by their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
fold</link>.
<image width="150px" src="Ssap-vectors.png" type="frame">
<caption>

Illustration of the atom-to-atom vectors calculated in SSAP. From these vectors would be constructed a series of vector differences, e.g., between (FA) in Protein 1 and (SI) in Protein 2. The two sequences are plotted on the two dimensions of a matrix to form a difference matrix between the two proteins. Dynamic programming is applied to all possible difference matrices to construct a series of optimal local alignment paths that are then summed to form the summary matrix, on which a second round of dynamic programming is performed.
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
DALI</st>
<p>

A common and popular structural alignment method is the DALI, or distance alignment matrix method, which breaks the input structures into hexapeptide fragments and calculates a distance matrix by evaluating the contact patterns between successive fragments.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/28691.xml">
Secondary structure</link> features that involve residues that are contiguous in sequence appear on the matrix's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/194990.xml">
main diagonal</link>; other diagonals in the matrix reflect spatial contacts between residues that are not near each other in the sequence. When these diagonals are parallel to the main diagonal, the features they represent are parallel; when they are perpendicular, their features are antiparallel. This representation is memory-intensive because the features in the square matrix are symmetrical (and thus redundant) about the main diagonal. </p>
<p>

When two proteins' distance matrices share the same or similar features in approximately the same positions, they can be said to have similar folds with similar-length loops connecting their secondary structure elements. DALI's actual alignment process requires a similarity search after the two proteins' distance matrices are built; this is normally conducted via a series of overlapping submatrices of size 6x6. Submatrix matches are then reassembled into a final alignment via a standard score-maximization algorithm - the original version of DALI used a <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/56098.xml">
Monte Carlo</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 simulation to maximize a structural similarity score that is a function of the distances between putative corresponding atoms. In particular, more distant atoms within corresponding features are exponentially downweighted to reduce the effects of noise introduced by loop mobility, helix torsions, and other minor structural variations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> Because DALI relies on an all-to-all distance matrix, it can account for the possibility that structurally aligned features might appear in different orders within the two sequences being compared.</p>
<p>

The DALI method has also been used to construct a database known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/2249250.xml">
FSSP</link> (Fold classification based on Structure-Structure alignment of Proteins, or Families of Structurally Similar Proteins) in which all known protein structures are aligned with each other to determine their structural neighbors and fold classification. There is an <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/2056296.xml">
EBI</link></association>
</institute>
-maintained <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/dali/">
searchable database</weblink> based on DALI as well as a <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ekhidna.biocenter.helsinki.fi/dali_lite/downloads/download.html">
downloadable program</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ekhidna.biocenter.helsinki.fi/dali/start">
web search</weblink> based on a standalone version known as DaliLite.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
SSAP</st>
<p>

The SSAP (Sequential Structure Alignment Program) method uses double <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/125297.xml">
dynamic programming</link> to produce a structural alignment based on atom-to-atom <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/32533.xml">
vectors</link> in structure space. Instead of the alpha carbons typically used in structural alignment, SSAP constructs its vectors from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/2475322.xml">
beta carbon</link>s  for all residues except glycine, a method which thus takes into account the rotameric state of each residue as well as its location along the backbone. SSAP works by first constructing a series of inter-residue distance vectors between each residue and its nearest non-contiguous neighbors on each protein. A series of matrices are then constructed containing the vector differences between neighbors for each pair of residues for which vectors were constructed. Dynamic programming applied to each resulting matrix determines a series of optimal local alignments which are then summed into a "summary" matrix to which dynamic programming is applied again to determine the overall structural alignment.</p>
<p>

SSAP originally produced only pairwise alignments but has since been extended to multiple alignments as well.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> It has been applied in an all-to-all fashion to produce a hierarchical fold classification scheme known as CATH (Class, Architecture, Topology, Homology),<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> which has been used to construct the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cathdb.info/latest/index.html">
CATH Protein Structure Classification</weblink> database.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Combinatorial extension</st>
<p>

The combinatorial extension (CE) method is similar to DALI in that it too breaks each structure in the query set into a series of fragments that it then attempts to reassemble into a complete alignment. A series of pairwise combinations of fragments called aligned fragment pairs, or AFPs, are used to define a similarity matrix through which an optimal path is generated to identify the final alignment. Only AFPs that meet given criteria for local similarity are included in the matrix as a means of reducing the necessary search space and thereby increasing efficiency.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> A number of similarity metrics are possible; the original definition of the CE method included only structural superpositions and inter-residue distances but has since been expanded to include local environmental properties such as secondary structure, solvent exposure, hydrogen-bonding patterns, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../046/338046.xml">
dihedral angle</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> </p>
<p>

An alignment path is calculated as the optimal path through the similarity matrix by linearly progressing through the sequences and extending the alignment with the next possible high-scoring AFP pair. The initial AFP pair that nucleates the alignment can occur at any point in the sequence matrix. Extensions then proceed with the next AFP that meets given distance criteria restricting the alignment to low gap sizes. The size of each AFP and the maximum gap size are required input parameters but are usually set to empirically determined values of 8 and 30 respectively.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> Like DALI and SSAP, CE has been used to construct an all-to-all fold classification <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cl.sdsc.edu/">
database</weblink> from the known protein structures in the PDB.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
MAMMOTH</st>
<p>

<b>MA</b>tching <b>M</b>olecular <b>M</b>odels <b>O</b>btained from <b>T</b>heory.  <b>MAMMOTH</b>-based structure alignment methods decomposes the protein structure into short peptides (heptapeptides) which are compared with the heptapeptides of another protein.  Similarity score between two heptapeptides is calculated using a unit-vector RMS (URMS) method. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>  These scores are stored in a similarity matrix, and with a hybrid (local-global) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/125297.xml">
dynamic programming</link> the optimal residue alignment is calculated.  Protein similarity scores calculated with MAMMOTH is derived from the likelihood of obtaining a given structural alignment by chance. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>  This method has been optimized for speed and accuracy, and is suited for large-scale structural genomics studies.  MAMMOTH is used by <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/3255539.xml">
Rosetta@home</link></software>
.</p>
<p>

<b>MAMMOTH-mult</b> is an extension of the MAMMOTH algorithm to be used to align related family of protein structures.  This algorithm is very fast and produces consistent and high quality structural alignments.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> Multiple structural alignments calculated with MAMMOTH-mult produces structurally-implied sequence alignments that can be further used for multiple-template homology modeling, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link>
HMM</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
-based protein structure prediction, and profile-type PSI-BLAST searches.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
RAPIDO</st>
<p>

<b>R</b>apid <b>A</b>lignment of <b>P</b>roteins <b>I</b>n terms of <b>DO</b>mains. <b>RAPIDO</b> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> is a web server for the 3D alignment of crystal structures of different protein molecules, in the presence of conformational changes. Similar to what CE does as a first step, RAPIDO identifies fragments that are structurally similar in the two proteins using an approach based on difference distance matrices. The Matching Fragment Pairs (MFPs) are then represented as nodes in a graph which are chained together to form an alignment by means of an algorithm for the identification of the longest path on a DAG (Directed Acyclic Graph). The final step of refinement is performed to improve the quality of the alignment. After aligning the two structures the server applies a genetic algorithm for the identification of conformationally invariant regions <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref>. These regions correspond to groups of atoms whose interatomic distances are constant (within a defined tolerance).  In doing so RAPIDO takes into account the variation in the reliability of atomic coordinates by employing weighting-functions based on the refined B-values. The regions identified as conformationally invariant by RAPIDO represent reliable sets of atoms for the superposition of the two structures that can be used for a detailed analysis of changes in the conformation. In addition to the functionalities provided by existing tools, RAPIDO can identify structurally equivalent regions even when these consist of fragments that are distant in terms of sequence and separated by other movable domains.
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Recent developments</st>
<p>

Improvements in structural alignment methods constitute an active area of research, and new or modified methods are often proposed that are claimed to offer advantages over the older and more widely distributed techniques. A recent example, TM-align, uses a novel method for weighting its distance matrix, to which standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/125297.xml">
dynamic programming</link> is then applied.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> The weighting is proposed to accelerate the convergence of dynamic programming and correct for effects arising from alignment lengths. In a benchmarking study, TM-align has been reported to improve in both speed and accuracy over DALI and CE.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref></p>
<p>

Beneath common sequential structure alignment tools, also non-sequential approaches have been developed in the recent time. Some examples are GANGSTA+ <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref> and TopoFit <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref>. The three dimensional alignment results (sequential and non-sequential) of an all-against-all protein database calculation is available for browsing at http://gangsta.chemie.fu-berlin.de.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 RNA structural alignment </st>
<p>

Structural alignment techniques have traditionally been applied exclusively to proteins, as the primary biological <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/106231.xml">
macromolecule</link>s that assume characteristic three-dimensional structures. However, large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/25758.xml">
RNA</link> molecules also form characteristic tertiary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/5054730.xml">
structures,</link> which are mediated primarily by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/13609.xml">
hydrogen bond</link>s formed between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/4292.xml">
base pair</link>s as well as <link>
base stacking</link>. Functionally similar <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/196493.xml">
noncoding RNA</link> molecules can be especially difficult to extract from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/55170.xml">
genomics</link> data because structure is more strongly conserved than sequence in RNA as well as in proteins,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> and the more limited alphabet of RNA decreases the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/542447.xml">
information content</link> of any given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/21505.xml">
nucleotide</link> at any given position.  </p>
<p>

A recent method for pairwise structural alignment of RNA sequences with low sequence identity has been published and implemented in the program <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://foldalign.kvl.dk/">
FOLDALIGN</weblink>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> However, this method is not truly analogous to protein structural alignment techniques because it computationally predicts the structures of the RNA input sequences rather than requiring experimentally determined structures as input. Although computational prediction of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/52085.xml">
protein folding</link> process has not been particularly successful to date, RNA structures without <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/2163614.xml">
pseudoknot</link>s can often be sensibly predicted using <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/39221.xml">
free energy</link></concept>
</idea>
-based scoring methods that account for base pairing and stacking.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Software </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/5876172.xml">
Structural alignment software</link></it>
</indent>
Choosing a software tool for structural alignment can be a challenge due to the large variety of available packages that differ significantly in methodology and reliability. Due to its integration with other <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/2056296.xml">
European Bioinformatics Institute</link></association>
</institute>
 web-based tools, the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/dali/">
EBI DALI</weblink> DaliLite webserver has an advantage in the production of single structural alignments for researchers interested in using the alignments to guide experimental work (rather than studying alignment methods themselves). Another useful EBI method is the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/msd-srv/ssm/ssmstart.html">
Secondary Structure Matcher</weblink>, which relies on the presence of at least two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/28691.xml">
secondary structure</link> elements. A more complete list of currently available and freely distributed structural alignment software can be found in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/5876172.xml">
structural alignment software</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/4066308.xml">
Multiple sequence alignment</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/5806900.xml">
Sequence alignment software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/149289.xml">
Sequence alignment</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/746131.xml">
Structural Classification of Proteins</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Zhang Y, Skolnick J. (2005). The protein structure prediction problem could be solved using the current PDB library. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 102(4):1029-34.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Zemla A. (2003). LGA - A Method for Finding 3-D Similarities in Protein Structures. <it>Nucleic Acids Research</it>, 31(13):3370-3374.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Godzik A. (1996). The structural alignment of proteins: is there a unique answer? <it>Protein Sci</it> 5:1325-8.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Martin ACR. http://www.bioinf.org.uk/software/profit/doc/ The software package <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bioinf.org.uk/software/profit/">
ProFit</weblink> (implements McLachlan, AD (1982). Rapid Comparison of Protein Structures. <it>Acta Cryst</it> A38, 871-873.)</entry>
<entry id="5">
Theobald DL, Wuttke DS (2006). Empirical Bayes hierarchical models for regularizing maximum likelihood estimation in the matrix Gaussian Procrustes problem. <it>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</it> 103(49):18521-18527. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/cgi/content/full/103/49/18521">
Open Access</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="6">
Theobald DL, Wuttke DS (2006). THESEUS: Maximum likelihood superpositioning and analysis of macromolecular structures. <it>Bioinformatics</it> 22(17):2171-2172. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/btl332?ijkey=BrYm4QyQZzMzu8s&amp;keytype=ref">
Open Access</weblink> http://www.theseus3d.org/ </entry>
<entry id="7">
Diederichs K. (1995). Structural superposition of proteins with unknown alignment and detection of topological similarity using a six-dimensional search algorithm. <it>Proteins</it> 23(2):187-95.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Maiti R, Van Domselaar GH, Zhang H, Wishart DS. (2004). SuperPose: a simple server for sophisticated structural superposition. <it>Nucleic Acids Res</it> 32(Web Server issue):W590-4.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Lathrop RH. (1994). The protein threading problem with sequence amino acid interaction preferences is NP-complete. <it>Protein Eng</it> 7(9):1059-68.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Wang L, Jiang T. (1994) On the complexity of multiple sequence alignment. <it>J Comput Biol</it> 1:337-348.</entry>
<entry id="11">
Kolodny R, Linial N. (2004). Approximate protein structural alignment in polynomial time <it>PNAS</it> 101(33): 12201-12206.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Martinez L, Andreani, R, Martinez, JM. (2007). Convergent algorithms for protein structural alignment <it>BMC Bioinformatics</it> 8:306.</entry>
<entry id="13">
Mount DM. (2004). <it>Bioinformatics: Sequence and Genome Analysis</it> 2nd ed. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press: Cold Spring Harbor, NY.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Holm L, Sander C (1996). Mapping the protein universe. <it>Science</it> 273: 595-603.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Taylor WR, Flores TP, Orengo CA. (1994). Multiple protein structure alignment. <it>Protein Sci</it> 3(10):1858-70.</entry>
<entry id="17">
Shindyalov IN, Bourne PE (1998) Protein structure alignment by incremental combinatorial extension (CE) of the optimal path. <it>Protein Eng</it> 11(9) 739-747.</entry>
<entry id="16">
Orengo CA, Michie AD, Jones S, Jones DT, Swindells MB, Thornton JM. (1997) CATH: A hierarchical classification of protein domain structures. <it>Structure</it> 5(8): 1093-1108.</entry>
<entry id="19">
 Ortiz, A. R., C. E. Strauss, and O. Olmea (2002, November). Mammoth (matching molecular models obtained from theory): An automated method for model comparison. Protein Sci  11 (11), 2606-2621.</entry>
<entry id="18">
 Kedem, K., Chew, L., and Elber, R. 1999. Unit-vector RMS (URMS) as a tool to analyze molecular dynamics trajectories. Proteins 37: 554–564 </entry>
<entry id="21">
Mosca, Schneider TR. (2008) RAPIDO: a web server for the alignment of protein structures in the presence of conformational changes, Nucleic Acids Research, doi: 10.1093/nar/gkn197 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/gkn197?ijkey=xfzxsZlvgO3xFZz&amp;keytype=ref">
Open Access</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://webapps.embl-hamburg.de/rapido">
RAPIDO server</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
 Lupyan, D., A. Leo-Macias, and A. R. Ortiz (2005, August). A new progressive-iterative algorithm for multiple structure alignment. Bioinformatics  21 (15), 3255-3263.</entry>
<entry id="23">
Zhang Y, Skolnick J. (2005) TM-align: A protein structure alignment algorithm based on TM-score. <it>Nucleic Acids Research</it> 33: 2302-2309.</entry>
<entry id="22">
Schneider. (2002) A genetic algorithm for the identification of conformationally invariant regions in protein molecules. Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr vol. 58 (Pt 2) pp. 195-208</entry>
<entry id="25">
Guerler A, Knapp E.W. (2008) Novel protein folds and their nonsequential structural analogs. <it>Protein Science</it> 17.</entry>
<entry id="24">
 Zhang Y, Skolnick J. (2004) Scoring function for automated assessment of protein structure template quality. <it>Proteins</it> 57: 702-710.</entry>
<entry id="27">
Torarinsson E, Sawera M, Havgaard JH, Fredholm M, Gorodkin J. (2006). Torarinsson E, Sawera M, Havgaard JH, Fredholm M, Gorodkin J. <it>Genome Res</it> 16(7):885-9.</entry>
<entry id="26">
Valentin A. Ilyin, Alexej Abyzov, and Chesley M.Leslin, Structural alignment of proteins by a novel TOPOFIT method, as a superimposition of common volumes at a topomax point. (preprint) Protein Science (2004), 13:1865-1874</entry>
<entry id="29">
Mathews DH, Turner DH. (2006). Prediction of RNA secondary structure by free energy minimization. <it>Curr Opin Struct Biol</it> 16(3):270-8.</entry>
<entry id="28">
Havgaard JH, Lyngso RB, Stormo GD, Gorodkin J. (2005). Pairwise local structural alignment of RNA sequences with sequence similarity less than 40%. <it>Bioinformatics</it> 21(9):1815-24.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bourne PE, Shindyalov IN. (2003): <it>Structure Comparison and Alignment</it>. In: Bourne, P.E., Weissig, H. (Eds): <it>Structural Bioinformatics</it>. Hoboken NJ: Wiley-Liss. ISBN 0-471-20200-2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Yuan X, Bystroff C.(2004) "Non-sequential Structure-based Alignments Reveal Topology-independent Core Packing Arrangements in Proteins", Bioinformatics. Nov 5, 2004</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Jung J, Lee B. (2000). Protein structure alignment using environmental profiles. <it>Protein Eng</it> 13:535-543.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ye Y, Godzik A. (2005). Multiple flexible structure alignment using partial order graphs <it>Bioinformatics</it> 21(10): 2362-2369 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/21/10/2362">
Abstract</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sippl M, Wiederstein M (2008). A note on difficult structure alignment problems. <it>Bioinformatics</it> 24(3): 426-427 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/24/3/426?ijkey=oWkOpf10zxhKaF2&amp;keytype=ref">
Full Text</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#e7dcc3" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
Proteins</link>: key <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/2634439.xml">
methods</link>of study</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/59861.xml">
Experiment</link>al</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/542744.xml">
Protein purification</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/143533.xml">
Green fluorescent protein</link> - <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/174030.xml">
Western blot</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 - <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/507330.xml">
Protein immunostaining</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/1076110.xml">
Protein sequencing</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <chemical_analysis wordnetid="100646833" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/12582.xml">
Gel electrophoresis</link></chemical_analysis>
/<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/589968.xml">
Protein electrophoresis</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</method>
</experiment>
</know-how>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
</technique>
 - <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<assay wordnetid="105738625" confidence="0.8">
<classification wordnetid="105732756" confidence="0.8">
<basic_cognitive_process wordnetid="105701944" confidence="0.8">
<appraisal wordnetid="105733583" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/1799688.xml">
Protein immunoprecipitation</link></appraisal>
</basic_cognitive_process>
</classification>
</assay>
</process>
 - <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/1983032.xml">
Peptide mass fingerprinting</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/306769.xml">
Protein structure prediction</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/2606518.xml">
Protein-protein docking</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/474908.xml">
Protein structural alignment</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/7786535.xml">
Protein ontology</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/4350008.xml">
Protein-protein interaction prediction</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: AntiqueWhite;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/496309.xml">
Assay</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/2634856.xml">
Enzyme assay</link></method>
</know-how>
 - <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/1098915.xml">
Protein assay</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</method>
</experiment>
</know-how>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/3599041.xml">
Secretion assay</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>




</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</method>
</know-how>
</article>
