<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:18:01[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Response amplitude operator</title>
<id>4767944</id>
<revision>
<id>243875000</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-08T12:34:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Crowsnest</username>
<id>6054452</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Naval architecture</category>
<category>Ship construction</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/187377.xml">
ship design</link> and design of other floating structures, a <b>response amplitude operator</b> (<b>RAO</b>) is an engineering statistic, or set of such statistics, that are used to determine the likely behaviour of a ship when operating at sea. Known by the acronym of <it>RAO</it>, response amplitude operators are usually obtained from models of proposed ship designs tested in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/614515.xml">
model basin</link>, or from running specialized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/305924.xml">
CFD</link> computer programs, often both. RAOs are usually calculated for all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/5456327.xml">
ship motions</link> and for all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/1557418.xml">
wave headings</link>.
<sec>
<st>
 Usage </st>
<p>

RAOs are effectively <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/31146.xml">
transfer function</link>s used to determine the effect that a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/1212631.xml">
sea state</link> will have upon the motion of a ship through the water, and therefore, for example, whether or not (in the case of cargo vessels) the addition of cargo to the vessel will require measures to be taken to improve <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/1561307.xml">
stability</link> and prevent the cargo from shifting within the vessel. Generation of extensive RAOs at the design phase allows shipbuilders to determine the modifications to a design that may be required for safety reasons (i.e., to make the design robust and resistant to capsizing or sinking in highly adverse sea conditions) or to improve performance (e.g., improve top speed, fuel consumption, stability in rough seas). RAOs are computed in tandem with the generation of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/11034.xml">
hydrodynamic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link>, which is a model of the effects of water pressure upon the ship's hull under a wide variety of flow conditions. Together, the RAOs and hydrodynamic database provide (inasmuch as this is possible within modelling and engineering constraints) certain assurances about the behaviour of a proposed ship design. They also allow the designer to dimension the ship or structure so it will hold up to the most extreme sea states it will likely be subjected to (based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/1212631.xml">
sea state</link> statistics).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 RAOs in ship design </st>
<p>

Different modelling and design criteria will affect the nature of the 'ideal' RAO curves (as plotted graphically) being sought for a particular ship: for example, an ocean cruise liner will have a considerable emphasis placed upon minimizing accelerations to ensure the comfort of the passengers, while the stability concerns for a naval warship will be concentrated upon making the ship an effective weapons platform.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Methods for calculating </st>
<p>

When calculating the response of ships in regular waves it is often possible to neglect the effects of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18963754.xml">
viscosity</link> in certain modes of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/5456327.xml">
motion</link>. Fairly accurate results can then be found by using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/1431342.xml">
potential theory</link>. The calculations are often divided into two sub-problems:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Finding the forces on the ship when it is restrained from motion and subjected to regular waves. The forces acting on the body are:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 The <link>
Froude–Krylov force</link>, which is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/23619.xml">
pressure</link> in the undisturbed waves integrated over the wetted surface of the ship.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/8603.xml">
Diffraction</link> forces, which are pressures that occur due to the disturbances in the water because of the ship being present.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Finding the forces on the ship when it is forced to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/22522.xml">
oscillate</link> in still water conditions. The forces are divided into:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/2974577.xml">
Added mass</link> forces due to having to accelerate the water along with the ship.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<equation wordnetid="106669864" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<vibration wordnetid="100345926" confidence="0.8">
<motion wordnetid="100331950" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<mathematical_statement wordnetid="106732169" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/495563.xml">
Damping</link></mathematical_statement>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</motion>
</vibration>
</action>
</change>
</event>
</equation>
</message>
</statement>
 forces due to the oscillations creating outgoing waves which carry energy away from the ship.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/7953419.xml">
Restoring forces</link> due to bringing the buoyancy/weight equilibrium out of balance. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In the above "Ship" must be interpreted widely to also include other forms of floating structures. The obvious problem in the above method is the neglection of viscous forces which contribute heavily in modes of motion like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/5456327.xml">
surge</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/5456327.xml">
roll</link>.</p>
<p>

On a computer the above algorithm was first introduced by using <link>
strip theory</link>. Today strip theory is still used if the need for fast calculations outweigh the need for precise results and the ship designer knows the limitations of strip theory. The more advanced programs that are used today may not use the exact algorithm outlined above and may also include the effects of viscosity. The insight into the forces that governs the seakeeping behaviour of a ship gained from the above are of course still valid.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/5456327.xml">
Ship motions</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/187377.xml">
Ship design</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/76653.xml">
Naval architecture</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ultramarine.com/hdesk/runs/samples/sea_keep/doc.htm">
Ultramarine Inc. web page</weblink> illustrating RAO curves and describing their uses (note: contains content aimed at ship design professionals)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Faltinsen, O. M.&#32;(1990). Sea Loads on Ships and Offshore Structures.&#32;[Cambridge University Press]]. ISBN 0-521-45870-6.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
