<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:28:23[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<division  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108220714">
<administrative_unit  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108077292">
<branch  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108401248">
<header>
<title>Mathematical sociology</title>
<id>4771336</id>
<revision>
<id>215953593</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-30T12:37:56Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mdd</username>
<id>113850</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Branches of sociology</category>
<category>Applied mathematics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Mathematical sociology</b> is the usage of mathematics to construct social theories. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/18717981.xml">
sociology</link>, in general, the connection between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link> and sociology is confined to problems of data analysis; employing statistical models.  Many sociological theories are strong in intuitive content, but weak from a formal point of view. In mathematical sociology, the preferred style is encapsulated in the phrase "constructing a mathematical model."   This means making specified assumptions about some mathematical objects and providing an empirical interpretation for the ideas.  It also means deducing properties of the model and comparing these with relevant empirical data.  
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Starting in the late 1940s, <citizen wordnetid="109923673" confidence="0.8">
<obstructionist wordnetid="110349243" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<national wordnetid="109625401" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<disputant wordnetid="109615465" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/992039.xml">
Anatol Rapoport</link></causal_agent>
</academician>
</theorist>
</disputant>
</educator>
</professional>
</scientist>
</adult>
</intellectual>
</national>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</obstructionist>
</citizen>
 and others developed a probabilistic approach to the characterization of large social networks in which the nodes are persons and the links are acquaintanceship.  During these years, formulas were derived that connected local parameters such as closure of contacts – if A is linked to both B and C, then there is a greater than chance probability that B and C are linked to each other – to the global network property of connectivity.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  </p>
<p>

Moreover, acquaintanceship is a <it>positive tie</it>, but what about <it>negative ties</it> such as animosity among persons?  To tackle this problem, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
graph theory</link>, which is the mathematical study of abstract representations of networks of points and lines, can be extended to include these two types of links and thereby to create models that represent both positive and negative sentiment relations.  This effort led to an important and non-obvious Structure Theorem, as developed by Cartwright and Harary in 1956, which says that if a network of interrelated positive and negative ties is balanced, e.g. as illustrated by the psychological consistency of "my friend's enemy is my enemy", then it consists of two subnetworks such that each has positive ties among its nodes and negative ties between nodes in distinct subnetworks.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  The imagery here is of a social system that splits into two cliques. There is, however, a special case where one of the two subnetworks is empty, which might occur in very small networks. </p>
<p>

In these two developments we have mathematical models bearing upon the analysis of structure.  Other early influential developments in mathematical sociology pertained to process.  For instance, in 1952 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../205/14205.xml">
Herbert Simon</link></scientist>
</person>
 produced a mathematical formalization of a published theory of social groups by constructing a model consisting of a deterministic system of differential equations.  A formal study of the system led to theorems about the dynamics and the implied <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/265823.xml">
equilibrium state</link>s of any group.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further developments</st>
<p>

The model constructed by Simon raises a question: how can one connect such theoretical models to the data of sociology, which often take the form of surveys in which the results are expressed in the form of proportions of people believing or doing something.  This suggests deriving the equations from assumptions about the chances of an individual changing state in a small interval of time, a procedure well known in the mathematics of stochastic processes.</p>
<p>

Sociologist, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/612754.xml">
James S. Coleman</link> embodied this idea in his 1964 book <it>Introduction to Mathematical Sociology</it>, which showed how stochastic processes in social networks could be analyzed in such a way as to enable testing of the constructed model by comparison with the relevant data.   In addition, Coleman employed mathematical ideas drawn from economics, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/45938.xml">
general equilibrium theory</link>, to argue that general social theory should begin with a concept of purposive action and, for analytical reasons, approximate such action by the use of rational choice models (Coleman, 1990).  This argument provided impetus for the emergence of a good deal of effort to link rational choice thinking to more traditional sociological concerns involving social structures.</p>
<p>

Meanwhile, structural analysis of the type indicated earlier received a further extension to social networks based on institutionalized social relations, notably those of kinship.  The linkage of mathematics and sociology here involved abstract algebra, in particular, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/41890.xml">
group theory</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.  This, in turn, led to a focus on a data-analytical version of homomorphic reduction of a complex social network (which along with many other techniques is presented in Wasserman and Faust 1994<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>).</p>
<p>

Some programs of research in sociology employ experimental methods to study social interaction processes.  Joseph Berger and his colleagues initiated such a program in which the central idea is the use of the theoretical concept "expectation state" to construct theoretical models to explain interpersonal processes, e.g., those linking external status in society to differential influence in local group decision-making. Much of this theoretical work is linked to mathematical model building (Berger 2000).</p>
<p>

The generations of mathematical sociologists that followed Rapoport, Simon, Harary, Coleman, White and Berger, among others, drew upon their work in a variety of ways.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Texts and journals</st>
<p>

Mathematical sociology textbooks cover a variety of models, usually explaining the required mathematical background before discussing important work in the literature (Fararo 1973, Leik and Meeker 1975).   The <it>Journal of Mathematical Sociology</it> (started in 1971) has been open to papers covering a broad spectrum of topics employing a variety of types of mathematics, especially through frequent special issues. Articles in <it>Social Networks,</it> a journal devoted to social structural analysis, very often employ mathematical models and related structural data analyses.  In addition, and this is important as an indicator of the penetration of mathematical model building into sociological research, the major comprehensive journals in sociology, especially <it>The American Journal of Sociology</it> and <it>The American Sociological Review,</it> regularly publish articles featuring mathematical formulations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Rapoport, Anatol. (1957).  "Contributions to the Theory of Random and Biased Nets." <it>Bulletin of Mathematical Biophysics</it> 19: 257-277.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Cartwright, Dorwin &amp; Harary, Frank. (1956).  "Structural Balance: A Generalization of Heider's Theory."  <it>Psychological Review</it> 63:277-293.</entry>
<entry id="3">
White, Harrison C. 1963. An Anatomy of Kinship. Prentice-Hall</entry>
<entry id="4">
Wasserman, S., &amp; Faust, K.. Social Network Analysis: Methods and Applications. New York and Cambridge, ENG: Cambridge University Press.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Berger, Joseph. 2000.  "Theory and Formalization: Some Reflections on Experience."  <it>Sociological Theory</it> 18(3):482-489.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Berger, Joseph, Bernard P. Cohen, J. Laurie Snell, and Morris Zelditch, Jr. 1962.  <it>Types of Formalization in Small Group Research.</it>  Houghton-Mifflin.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Coleman, James S.  1964.  <it>An Introduction to Mathematical Sociology.</it>  Free Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

_____.  1990.  <it>Foundations of Social Theory.</it>  Harvard University Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Edling, Christofer R. 2002.  "Mathematics in Sociology," <it>Annual Review of Sociology.''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fararo, Thomas J.  1973.  <it>Mathematical Sociology.</it>  Wiley.  Reprinted by Krieger, 1978.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

_____.  1984.  Editor.   <it>Mathematical Ideas and Sociological Theory.</it>  Gordon and Breach.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lave, Charles and James March. 1975. <it>An Introduction to Models in the Social Sciences.</it>  Harper and Row.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Leik, Robert K. and Barbara F. Meeker.  1975.  <it>Mathematical Sociology.</it>  Prentice-Hall.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Simon, Herbert A.  1952.  "A Formal Theory of Interaction in Social Groups."  <it>American Sociological Review</it> 17:202-212.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wasserman, Stanley and Katherine Faust.  1994.  <it>Social Network Analysis: Methods and Applications.</it>  Cambridge University Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

White, Harrison C.  1963.  <it>An Anatomy of Kinship.</it>  Prentice-Hall.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<branch wordnetid="108401248" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/984692.xml">
Computational sociology</link></branch>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<sociologist wordnetid="110620758" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4756214.xml">
Harrison White</link></scholar>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</alumnus>
</sociologist>
</educator>
</professional>
</scientist>
</adult>
</social_scientist>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/7273911.xml">
Interpersonal ties</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/73650.xml">
Duncan Watts</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/612754.xml">
James S. Coleman</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<sociologist wordnetid="110620758" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/4777874.xml">
James D. Montgomery</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</sociologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<sociologist wordnetid="110620758" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/4854950.xml">
Thomas Fararo</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</sociologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
Social network</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/soc/groups/mathsoc/index.php">
Mathematical Sociology Section Home Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/soc/faculty/bonacich/textbook.htm">
Mathematical Sociology</weblink> - an indepth explanation by Phil Bonacich</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</branch>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</article>
