<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:09:04[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<operation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100955060">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<attack  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100972621">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Traffic analysis</title>
<id>480015</id>
<revision>
<id>238758292</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-16T06:55:04Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Adamantios</username>
<id>650655</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with Alice and Bob explanations</category>
<category>Military communications</category>
<category>Cryptographic attacks</category>
<category>Intelligence analysis</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Traffic analysis</b> is the process of intercepting and examining messages in order to <b>deduce information from patterns</b> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/5177.xml">
communication</link>. It can be performed even when the messages are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encrypt</link>ed and cannot be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/5715.xml">
decrypted</link>. In general, the greater the number of messages observed, or even intercepted and stored, the more can be inferred from the traffic. Traffic analysis can be performed in the context of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/146678.xml">
military intelligence</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/238030.xml">
counter-intelligence</link>, and is a concern in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
computer security</link>.<p>

Traffic analysis tasks may be supported by dedicated computer software programs, including commercially available programs such as those offered by i2, Visual Analytics, Memex, Orion Scientific, Pacific Northwest National Labs, Genesis EW's GenCOM Suite and others. Advanced traffic analysis techniques may include various forms of social network analysis.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 In military intelligence </st>

<p>

In a military context, traffic analysis is a  basic part of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/29122.xml">
signals intelligence</link>, and can be a source of information about the intentions and actions of the enemy. Representative patterns include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frequent communications — can denote planning</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rapid, short, communications — can denote negotiations</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A lack of communication — can indicate a lack of activity, or completion of a finalized plan</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frequent communication to specific stations from a central station — can highlight the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/227954.xml">
chain of command</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Who talks to whom — can indicate which stations are 'in charge' or the 'control station' of a particular network. This further implies something about the personnel associated with each station</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Who talks when — can indicate which stations are active in connection with events, which implies something about the information being passed and perhaps something about the personnel/access of those associated with some stations</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Who changes from station to station, or medium to medium — can indicate movement, fear of interception</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

There is a close relationship between traffic analysis and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/5715.xml">
cryptanalysis</link> (commonly called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/5715.xml">
codebreaking</link>). <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/2797722.xml">
Callsign</link>s and addresses are frequently <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encrypt</link>ed, requiring assistance in identifying them. Traffic volume can often be a sign of an addressee's importance, giving hints to pending objectives or movements to cryptanalysts.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="GenCOM_EOB_snapshot.GIF" type="frame">
<caption>

An example of an EOB geo-spectral analysis, automatically produced by the Genesis EW's GenCOM EOB, showing the geo-locations of different emitters and the connections between them. This examples the practical use of COMINT metadata/Traffic Analysis: <b>While intercepting, processing and analyzing electromagnetic emission only, we can see the locations of different army units and the connections between them, without the need to monitor, translate and process their communications</b>.
</caption>
</image>
 </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Traffic flow security</st>
<p>

<b>Traffic-flow security</b> is the use of measures that conceal the presence and properties of valid messages on a network to prevent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/480015.xml">
traffic analysis</link>. This can be done by operational procedures or by the protection resulting from features inherent in some cryptographic equipment. Techniques used include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 changing radio <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/2797722.xml">
callsign</link>s frequently</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 encryption of a message's sending and receiving addresses (<b>codress messages</b>) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 causing the circuit to appear busy at all times or much of the time by sending dummy <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/43081.xml">
traffic</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 sending a continuous encrypted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/41703.xml">
signal</link>, whether or not traffic is being transmitted. This is also called <b>masking</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Traffic-flow security is one aspect of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/40922.xml">
communications security</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 COMINT metadata analysis </st>

<p>

The <b>Communications' Metadata Intelligence</b>, or <b>COMINT metadata</b> is a term in <link>
COMINT</link> referring to the concept of producing intelligence by analyzing only the technical metadata, hence, is a great practical example for traffic analysis in intelligence. </p>
<p>

While traditionally information gathering in COMINT is derived from intercepting transmissions, tapping the target's communications and monitoring the content of conversations, <b>the metadata intelligence is not based on content but on technical communicational data</b>. </p>
<p>

Non content COMINT is usually used to figure information about the user of a certain transmitter, such as locations, contacts, activity volume, routine and its exceptions. </p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Examples</st>

<p>

For example, if a certain emitter is known as the radio transmitter of a certain unit, and by using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/820724.xml">
DF (direction finding)</link> tools, the position of the emitter is locatable; hence the changes of locations can be monitored. That way we're able to understand that this certain unit is moving from one point to another, without listening to any orders or reports. If we know that this unit reports back to a command on a certain pattern, and we know that another unit reports on the same pattern to the same command, than the two units are probably related, and that conclusion is based on the metadata of the two units' transmissions, and not on the content of their transmissions.</p>
<p>

Using all, or as many of the metadata available is commonly use in order to build up an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/29122.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Electronic+Order+of+Battle%22])">
Electronic Order of Battle</link> (EOB) – mapping different entities in the battlefield and their connections. Of course the EOB could be built by tapping all the conversations and trying to understand which unit is where, but using the metadata with an automatic analysis tool enables a much faster and accurate EOB build-up that alongside tapping builds a much better and complete picture. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
World War I</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 British analysts in <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/4764461.xml">
World War I</link></conflict>
 noticed that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/2797722.xml">
call sign</link> of German Vice Admiral <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/361451.xml">
Reinhard Scheer</link>, commanding the hostile fleet, had been transferred to a land-based station. Admiral <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/1337381.xml">
Beattie</link>, ignorant of Scheer's practice of changing callsigns upon leaving harbor, dismissed its importance and disregarded <location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/652467.xml">
Room 40</link></location>
 analysts' attempts to make the point. The German fleet sortied, and the British were late in meeting them at the <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/4563.xml">
Battle of Jutland</link></conflict>
. If traffic analysis been taken more seriously, the British might have done better than a 'draw'.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
World War II</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In early <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
World War II</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
aircraft carrier</link> <career wordnetid="100583246" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<image wordnetid="105928118" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/485395.xml">
HMS <it>Glorious''</it></link></feature>
</image>
</career>
 was evacuating pilots and planes from <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/21241.xml">
Norway</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
. Traffic analysis produced indications <career wordnetid="100583246" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<image wordnetid="105928118" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/99785.xml">
<it>Scharnhorst''</it></link></feature>
</image>
</career>
 and <career wordnetid="100583246" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<image wordnetid="105928118" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/249943.xml">
<it>Gneisenau''</it></link></feature>
</image>
</career>
 were moving into the North Sea, but the Admiralty dismissed the report as unproven. The captain of <it>Glorious</it> did not keep sufficient lookout, and was subsequently surprised and sunk. <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/1811564.xml">
Harry Hinsley</link></military_officer>
</scholar>
</historian>
</serviceman>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
, the young <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<science_museum wordnetid="104147364" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<depository wordnetid="103177349" confidence="0.8">
<museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/4037.xml">
Bletchley Park</link></museum>
</depository>
</facility>
</science_museum>
</artifact>
 liaison to the Admiralty, later said his reports from the traffic analysts were taken much more seriously thereafter<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 During the planning and rehearsal for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/60098.xml">
attack on Pearl Harbor</link>, very little traffic passed by radio, subject to interception. The ships, units, and commands involved were all in Japan and in touch by phone, courier, signal lamp, or even flag. None of that traffic was intercepted, and could not be analyzed<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The espionage effort against Pearl Harbor before December didn't send an unusual number of messages; Japanese vessels regularly called in Hawaii and messages were carried aboard by consular personnel. At least one such vessel carried some Japanese Navy Intelligence officers. Such messages cannot be analyzed. It has been suggested<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>, however, the volume of diplomatic traffic to and from certain <link>
consular stations</link> might have indicated places of interest to Japan, which might thus have suggested locations to concentrate traffic analysis and decryption efforts.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/195975.xml">
Admiral Nagumo</link>'s Pearl Harbor Attack Force sailed under radio silence, with its radios physically locked down. It is unclear if this deceived the U.S.; Pacific Fleet intelligence was unable to locate the Japanese carriers in the days immediately preceding the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/60098.xml">
attack on Pearl Harbor</link> <cite class="inline">(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//cite[@id=%22CITEREF_Kahn%22])">
Kahn</link>)</cite>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <military_unit wordnetid="108198398" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/236104.xml">
Japanese Navy</link></military_unit>
 played radio games to inhibit traffic analysis (see Examples, below) with the attack force after it sailed in late November.  Radio operators normally assigned to carriers, with a characteristic Morse Code "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/187553.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Key's+influence+on+sender's+personal+characteristics%22])">
fist</link>", transmitted from inland Japanese waters, suggesting the carriers were still near Japan <cite class="inline">(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//cite[@id=%22CITEREF_Kahn%22])">
Kahn</link>)</cite><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>



</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 In computer security </st>

<p>

Traffic analysis is also a concern in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
computer security</link>. An attacker can gain important information by monitoring the frequency and timing of network packets. A timing attack on the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/28814.xml">
SSH</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 protocol used timing information to deduce information about <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/24304.xml">
password</link>s (Song et al, 2001). How? During interactive sessions, SSH transmits each key stroke as a message. The time between keystroke messages can be studied using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/98770.xml">
hidden Markov model</link>s.  The authors claim that it can recover the password fifty times faster than a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/53784.xml">
brute force attack</link>.</p>
<p>

<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/424617.xml">
Onion routing</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 systems are used to gain anonymity.  Traffic analysis can be used to attack anonymous communication systems like the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/18582150.xml">
Tor anonymity network</link></software>
. Steven J. Murdoch and George Danezis from University of Cambridge presented  
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> 
research showing that traffic-analysis allows adversaries to infer which nodes relay the anonymous streams.  This reduces the anonymity provided by Tor. They have shown that otherwise unrelated streams can be linked back to the same initiator.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/54666.xml">
Remailer</link> systems can also be attacked via traffic analysis. If a message is observed going to a remailing server, and an identical-length (if now anonymized) message is seen exiting the server soon after, a traffic analyst may be able (automatically) connect the sender with the ultimate receiver. Variations of remailer operations exist that can make traffic analysis less effective.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Countermeasures </st>

<p>

It is difficult to defeat traffic analysis without both encrypting messages and masking the channel.  When no actual messages are being sent, we can <b>mask</b>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> the channel by sending dummy traffic, similar to the encrypted traffic, thereby keeping the channel 100% busy
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>. "It is very hard to hide information about the size or timing of messages. The known solutions require <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/679079.xml">
Alice</link> to send a continuous stream of messages at the maximum <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/15612827.xml">
bandwidth</link> she will ever use...This might be acceptable for military applications, but it is not for most civilian applications." The military-versus-civilian problems applies in situations where the user is charged for the volume of information sent. </p>
<p>

Even for Internet access, where there is not a per-packet charge, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/100245.xml">
ISPs</link> make statistical assumption that connections from user sites will not be busy 100% of the time. The user cannot simply increase the bandwidth of the link, since masking would fill that as well. If masking, which often can be built into end-to-end encryptors, becomes common practice, ISPs will have to change their traffic assumptions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/29122.xml">
SIGINT</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/29122.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Electronic+Order+of+Battle%22])">
Electronic Order of Battle</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
ELINT</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1039587.xml">
Network analysis</link></network>
</group>
</method>
</know-how>
</system>
</technique>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<pronouncement wordnetid="106727616" confidence="0.8">
<declaration wordnetid="106725877" confidence="0.8">
<directive wordnetid="107170080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/2233763.xml">
Telecommunications data retention</link></directive>
</declaration>
</pronouncement>
</message>
</statement>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/7990.xml">
Data warehouse</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <operation wordnetid="100955060" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/4738443.xml">
Zendian Problem</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</event>
</operation>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/9282.xml">
ECHELON</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Howland, Vernon W.&#32;(2007-10-01).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.warship.org/no11994.htm">
The Loss of HMS Glorious: An Analysis of the Action</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-26</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Kahn, David&#32;(1974). The Codebreakers: The Story of Secret Writing.&#32;Macmillan. Kahn-1974.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Costello, John&#32;(1995). Days of Infamy: Macarthur, Roosevelt, Churchill-The Shocking Truth Revealed : How Their Secret Deals and Strategic Blunders Caused Disasters at Pear Harbor and the Philippines.&#32;Pocket.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Layton, Edwin T.;&#32;Roger Pineau, John Costello&#32;(1985). "And I Was There": Pearl Harbor And Midway -- Breaking the Secrets..&#32;William Morrow &amp; Co.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
Murdoch, Steven J.&#32;(2005).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/users/sjm217/papers/oakland05torta.pdf">
Low-Cost Traffic Analysis of Tor</weblink>".&#32;<it>2005 IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy</it>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://students.cs.tamu.edu/xinwenfu/paper/ICCNMC03_Fu.pdf">
Active Traffic Analysis Attacks and Countermeasures</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-06</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Niels Ferguson and Bruce Schneier&#32;(2003). Practical Cryptography.&#32;John Wiley &amp; Sons.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ferguson, Niels, Schneier, Bruce. <it>Practical Cryptography</it>, 2003. p114. ISBN 0-471-22357-3.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dawn Xiaodong Song, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<professor wordnetid="110480730" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/298253.xml">
David Wagner</link></professor>
</person>
 and Xuqing Tian, Timing Analysis of Keystrokes and Timing Attacks on SSH, 10th USENIX  Security Symposium, 2001.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 X. Y. Wang, S. Chen and S. Jajodia <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ise.gmu.edu/~xwangc/Publications/CCS05-VoIPTracking.pdf">
“Tracking Anonymous Peer-to-Peer VoIP Calls on the Internet”</weblink>. In Proceedings of the  12th ACM Conference on Computer Communications Security (CCS 2005), November 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fmv.se/upload/Bilder%20och%20dokument/Vad%20gor%20FMV/Uppdrag/LedsystT/FMLS/FMLS_Generic%20Design/LT1K%20P06-0035%20SD%20Provide%20Streaming%20Data%202.0%20-%20c.pdf">
FMV Sweden</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/Xplore/login.jsp?url=/iel5/6676/18015/00832361.pdf">
Multi-source data fusion in NATO coalition operations</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seeker.dice.com/jobsearch/servlet/JobSearch?op=101&amp;dockey=xml/4/5/4562220fc28ae47508f252d9212a80b6@endecaindex&amp;c=1&amp;source=20">
request for COMINT metadata analysts</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>
 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.totse.com/en/privacy/161755.html">
Interception Capabilities 2000 - study by Duncan Campbell </weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.onr.navy.mil/02/baa/docs/07-026_07_026_industry_briefing.pdf</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.totse.com/en/hack/understanding_the_internet/162925.html">
Intelligence Community Markup Language</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://freehaven.net/anonbib/">
Anonymity bibliography at freehaven</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/13979889.xml">
Intelligence cycle management</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/13979372.xml">
Intelligence
collectionmanagement</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
HUMINT/
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/151848.xml">
Human Intelligence</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/14193830.xml">
Clandestine HUMINT</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/14711181.xml">
recruiting</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/14338661.xml">
operational techniques</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/14590408.xml">
Covert action</link>&nbsp;·  <operation wordnetid="114008806" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="114006945" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/14366593.xml">
Direct action</link></action>
</state>
</operation>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/14558092.xml">
Clandestine cell system</link>)<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<influence wordnetid="105194151" confidence="0.8">
<force wordnetid="105194578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/14230108.xml">
Special reconnaissance</link></force>
</influence>
</power>
 (<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<influence wordnetid="105194151" confidence="0.8">
<force wordnetid="105194578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/14196333.xml">
organizations</link></force>
</influence>
</power>
)<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/10501.xml">
Espionage</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/1256171.xml">
Agent handling</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<operation wordnetid="114008806" confidence="0.8">
<operation wordnetid="100955060" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="114006945" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/1462488.xml">
Black bag operation</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</method>
</action>
</state>
</event>
</know-how>
</operation>
</operation>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/655741.xml">
Concealment device</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
Cryptography</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/14006036.xml">
Cut-out</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/655639.xml">
Dead drop</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/372656.xml">
Eavesdropping</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/1575931.xml">
False flag operations</link></group>
</collection>
</method>
</know-how>
</law>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/14711181.xml">
Honeypot</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/848358.xml">
Non-official cover</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/220414.xml">
Interrogation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/156704.xml">
Numbers messaging</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/1253622.xml">
One-way voice link</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/28733.xml">
Steganography</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/87231.xml">
Surveillance</link>)</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
SIGINT/
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/29122.xml">
Signals Intelligence</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/13762670.xml">
SIGINT by Alliances, Nations and Industries</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/13801445.xml">
SIGINT Operational Platforms by Nation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/13813961.xml">
SIGINT in Modern History</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/184781.xml">
TEMPEST</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/820724.xml">
Direction finding</link>&nbsp;·  <operation wordnetid="100955060" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/480015.xml">
Traffic analysis</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</event>
</operation>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
MASINT/
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/488880.xml">
Measurement andSignature Intelligence</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/13789881.xml">
Electro-optical</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/13784530.xml">
Nuclear</link>&nbsp;·  <process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<consequence wordnetid="111410625" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/13793754.xml">
Geophysical</link></consequence>
</phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/13789744.xml">
Radar</link>&nbsp;·  <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/13782970.xml">
Radiofrequency</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/13783270.xml">
Materials</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/17177677.xml">
Casualty estimation</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Others</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
OSINT/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/387199.xml">
Open Source Intelligence</link>&nbsp;·  IMINT/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/159746.xml">
Imagery Intelligence</link>&nbsp;·  FININT/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/7453481.xml">
Financial Intelligence</link>&nbsp;·  TECHINT/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/335324.xml">
Technical intelligence</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/13980190.xml">
Intelligence
analysismanagement</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/4448253.xml">
Intelligence analysis</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/14549316.xml">
Cognitive traps for intelligence analysis</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/17068561.xml">
Words of Estimative Probability</link>&nbsp;·  <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/6308558.xml">
Analysis of Competing Hypotheses</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/17159890.xml">
Intelligence cycle (target-centric approach)</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/14026762.xml">
Intelligence
disseminationmanagement</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/14103867.xml">
Intelligence cycle security</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/238030.xml">
Counter-intelligence</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/14093104.xml">
Counter-intelligence and counter-terrorism organizations</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/14114439.xml">
List of counterintelligence organizations</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/14093807.xml">
Counterintelligence failures</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</event>
</operation>
</article>
