<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:09:09[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Collaborative filtering</title>
<id>480289</id>
<revision>
<id>244467737</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T23:11:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jacksheep</username>
<id>8051865</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All pages needing cleanup</category>
<category>Social Information Processing</category>
<category>Collective intelligence</category>
<category>Articles with disputed statements </category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Collaborative filtering (CF)</b>  is the process of filtering for information or patterns using techniques involving collaboration among multiple agents, viewpoints, data sources, etc.  Applications of collaborative filtering typically involve very large data sets.   Collaborative filtering methods have been applied to many different kinds of data including sensing and monitoring data - such as in mineral exploration, environmental sensing over large areas or multiple sensors; financial data - such as financial service institutions that integrate many financial sources; or in electronic commerce and web 2.0 applications  where the focus is on user data, etc.  The remainder of this discussion focuses on collaborative filtering for user data, although some of the methods and approaches may apply to the other major applications as well.<p>

The method of making automatic predictions (filtering) about the interests of a user by collecting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/1974810.xml">
taste</link> information from many users (collaborating). The underlying assumption of CF approach is that those who agreed in the past tend to agree again in the future. For example, a collaborative filtering or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/596646.xml">
recommendation system</link> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/18839.xml">
music</link> tastes could make predictions about which music a  should like given a partial list of that user's tastes (likes or dislikes). Note that these predictions are specific to the user, but use information gleaned from many users. This differs from the more simple approach of giving an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/60167.xml">
average</link> (non-specific) score for each item of interest, for example based on its number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/99860.xml">
vote</link>s.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Methodology</st>
<p>

Collaborative filtering systems usually take two steps:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Look for users who share the same rating patterns with the active user (the user whom the prediction is for).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Use the ratings from those like-minded users found in step 1 to calculate a prediction for the active user</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Alternatively, item-based collaborative filtering popularized by <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<shop wordnetid="104202417" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<mercantile_establishment wordnetid="103748162" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<bookshop wordnetid="102871525" confidence="0.8">
<place_of_business wordnetid="103953020" confidence="0.8">
<establishment wordnetid="103297735" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/90451.xml">
Amazon.com</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</establishment>
</place_of_business>
</bookshop>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</mercantile_establishment>
</structure>
</shop>
</computer>
 (users who bought x also bought y)  and first proposed in the context of rating-based collaborative filtering by Vucetic and Obradovic in 2000, proceeds in an item-centric manner:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Build an item-item matrix determining relationships between pairs of items</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Using the matrix, and the data on the current user, infer his taste</entry>
</list>

See, for example, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/3854278.xml">
Slope One</link> item-based collaborative filtering family.</p>
<p>

Another form of collaborative filtering can be based on implicit observations of normal user behavior (as opposed to the artificial behavior imposed by a rating task).  In these systems you observe what a user has done together with what all users have done (what music they have listened to, what items they have bought) and use that data to predict the users behavior in the future or to predict how a user might like to behave if only they were given a chance.  These predictions then have to be filtered through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/157004.xml">
business logic</link> to determine how these predictions might affect what a business system ought to do.  It is, for instance, not useful to offer to sell somebody some music if they already have demonstrated that they own that music.</p>
<p>

In the age of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/14774.xml">
information explosion</link> such techniques can prove very useful as the number of items in only one category (such as music, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/10571.xml">
movies</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/3778.xml">
books</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/22041.xml">
news</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/34063.xml">
web page</link>s) have become so large that a single person cannot possibly view them all in order to select relevant ones. Relying on a scoring or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/465183.xml">
rating</link> system which is averaged across all users ignores specific demands of a user, and is particularly poor in tasks where there is large variation in interest, for example in the recommendation of music. Obviously, other methods to combat information explosion exist such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
web</link> search, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/669675.xml">
data clustering</link>, and more.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

Collaborative filtering stems from the earlier system of information filtering, where relevant information is brought to the attention of the user by observing patterns in previous behaviour and building a user profile. This system was essentially unable to help with exploration of the web and suffered from the cold-start problem that new users had to build up tendencies before the filtering was effective.</p>
<p>

The first system to use collaborative filtering was the Information Tapestry project at <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/34154.xml">
Xerox PARC</link></company>
 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. This system allowed users to find documents based on previous comments by other users. There were many problems with this system as it only worked for small groups of people and had to be accessed through word specific queries which largely defeated the purpose of collaborative filtering. </p>
<p>

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/18588994.xml">
USENET Net news</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</group>
</act>
</service>
</gathering>
</rule>
</event>
</social_group>
</message>
</system_of_measurement>
</community>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</work>
 furthered collaborative filtering&#91;&#32; &ndash; &#93; such that it was available for a mass scale of users while having a simpler method for accessing articles. The system allowed users to rate material based on popularity, which then allowed other users to search for articles based on these</p>
<p>

One of the largest early collaborative filtering services for music recommendations widely available on the World Wide Web was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/3479393.xml">
Firefly</link>, which evolved from early <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/386540.xml">
MIT Media Lab</link> research projects. Firefly was bought by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
 in 1998. The service itself was closed down in 1999 with much of its technology and staff helping to create <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/1956327.xml">
Microsoft Passport</link></software>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Types </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Active filtering </st>

<p>

<b>Active filtering</b> is a method that in recent years has become increasingly popular due to an ever growing base of information available to users of the World Wide Web. With an exponentially growing amount of information being added to the Internet, finding efficient and valuable information is becoming more difficult. In recent years a basic search for information using the World Wide Web turns out thousands of results and a high percentage of this information is not effective and — more often than not — irrelevant as well. There are a large number of databases and search engines in the market today to use for searches but a majority of the population is not familiar with all the options available. This is where active filtering comes into effect. </p>
<p>

Active filtering differs from other methods of collaborative filtering because it uses a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/24107.xml">
peer-to-peer</link> approach. This means that it is a system where peers, coworkers, and people with similar interests rate products, reports, and other material objects, also sharing this information over the web for other people to see. It is a system based on the fact that people want to share consumer information with the other peers. The users of active filtering use lists of commonly used links to send the information over the web where others can view it and use the ratings of the products to make their own decisions.</p>
<p>

Active collaborative filtering can be useful to many people in many situations. This type of filtering can be extremely important and effective in a situation where a non-guided web search produces thousands of results that are not useful or effective for the person locating the information. In cases where people are not comfortable or knowledgeable about the array of databases that are available to them, active filtering is very useful and effective. </p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Advantages </st>
<p>

There are many advantages to using or viewing an Active collaborative filtering. One of these advantages is an actual rating given to something of interest by a person who has viewed the topic or product of interest. This produces a reasonable explanation and rank from a reliable source, being the person who has come into contact with the product. Another advantage of Active filtering is the fact that the people want to and ultimately do provide information regarding the matter at hand.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Disadvantages </st>
<p>

There are a few disadvantages of active filtering. One is that the opinion may be biased. Also, as providing feedback requires action by the user, less data may be available than with a passive approach, and user expectations may not be met.</p>
<p>

One of the main characteristics in Collaborative Filtering, compared to e.g. Content-Based Filtering, is that the method knows nothing about the items' true content or what they are about. This means that they only rely on preference values, such as ratings to generate the recommendations. This means that performance of penetration of each item is highly dependent on other users' ratings and might introduce averaging effects. Averaging effects cause the overall most popular items to be recommended more often which means that they will be consumed and rated more frequently as a result. </p>
<p>

Two other issues are generally well known and often associated with collaborative filtering: the First-Rater Problem and Cold-Start Problem. The First-Rater problem is caused by new items in the system that understandably have not yet received any ratings from any users. The system is therefore unable to generate semantic interconnections to these items and therefore are never recommended. Similarly, the Cold-Start Problem is caused by new users in the system which have not submitted any ratings. Without any information about the user the system is not able to guess the user's preferences and generate recommendations until a few items have been rated.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Passive filtering </st>

<p>

A method of collaborative filtering that is thought to have great potential in the future is passive filtering, which collects information implicitly. A web browser is used to record a user’s preferences by following and measuring their actions. These implicit filters are then used to determine what else the user will like and recommend potential items of interest. 
Implicit filtering relies on the actions of users to determine a value rating for specific content, such as:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Purchasing an item</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Repeatedly using, saving, printing an item</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Referring or linking to a site</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Number of times queried</entry>
</list>

An important feature of passive collaborative filtering is using the time aspect to determine whether a user is scanning a document or fully reading the material. The greatest strength of the system is that it takes away certain variables from the analysis that would normally be present in active filtering. For example, only certain types of people will take the time to rate a site, in passive collaborative filtering anyone accessing the site has automatically given data.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Item based filtering </st>

<p>

Item based filtering is another method of collaborative filtering in which items are rated and used as parameters instead of users.  This type of filtering uses the ratings to group various items together in groups so consumers can compare them as well as a rating scale that is available to manufacturers so they can locate where their product stands in the market in a consumer based rating scale.</p>
<p>

Through this method of filtering, users or user groups use and test the product and give it a rating that is relevant to the product and the product class in which it falls.  These users test many products and with the results, the products are classified based on the information which the rating holds.  The products are used and tested by the same user or group in order to get an accurate rating and eliminate some of the error that is possible in the tests that take place under this type of filtering.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Explicit versus implicit filtering</st>
<p>

Within active and passive filtering there are explicit and implicit methods for determining user preferences. Explicit collection of user preferences requires the evaluator to indicate a value for the content on a rating scale. This creates a cognitive aspect to collaborative filtering, but can mean that the feedback received is more accurate.
Implicit collection does not involve the direct input of opinion by the user, but instead it is assumed that their opinion is implied by their actions. This reduces variability amongst users and reduces the demand on the user, which can mean that much more data is available.  However, this behaviour data does not necessarily accurately represent the user's true opinion of an item.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Applications </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 In commercial systems </st>
<p>

Commercial sites that implement collaborative filtering systems include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<shop wordnetid="104202417" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<mercantile_establishment wordnetid="103748162" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<bookshop wordnetid="102871525" confidence="0.8">
<place_of_business wordnetid="103953020" confidence="0.8">
<establishment wordnetid="103297735" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/90451.xml">
Amazon</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</establishment>
</place_of_business>
</bookshop>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</mercantile_establishment>
</structure>
</shop>
</computer>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/191875.xml">
Barnes and Noble</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/12436744.xml">
Baynote</link></institution>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</company>
</event>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/18718081.xml">
Collarity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/2076932.xml">
Digg.com</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/1600550.xml">
half.ebay.com</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/694314.xml">
Hollywood Video</link></institution>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</company>
</event>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/11521740.xml">
iLike</link> - music</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/186266.xml">
iTunes</link> - music</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/612330.xml">
Last.fm</link></software>
 - music</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/4538455.xml">
LibraryThing</link></group>
</property>
</community>
</gathering>
</possession>
</social_group>
 - books</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loomia.com/">
Loomia</weblink> - media, content and retail sites</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/533884.xml">
Musicmatch</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/11979099.xml">
MyStrands</link> - developer of social recommendation technologies</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/175537.xml">
Netflix</link></company>
 - In order to improve its algorithm Netflix has launched a competition, the <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/9399111.xml">
Netflix Prize</link></psychological_feature>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Minekey</link> - Online recommendations service.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.photoree.com/">
Photoree</weblink> - image recommendation system</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/759881.xml">
StumbleUpon</link></software>
 - websites</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/2769499.xml">
Threadless</link></company>
 - T-shirt</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/30936.xml">
TiVo</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tastekid.com/">
Taste Kid</weblink> - music, films and books recommendation service</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 In non-commercial systems </st>
<p>

Non-commercial sites that implement collaborative filtering systems include:</p>
<p>

<table style="empty-cells:show;" class="wikitable sortable">
<row>
<header>
Service</header>
<header>
Type</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/878095.xml">
AmphetaRate</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/93489.xml">
RSS</link>articles</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/4097569.xml">
Everyone's a Critic</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</col>
<col>
movies</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/3177315.xml">
GiveALink.org</link></col>
<col>
websites</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/975738.xml">
Gnomoradio</link></software>
</col>
<col>
music (free)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link>
iRATE radio</link></col>
<col>
music (free)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/1435849.xml">
Musicmobs</link></group>
</community>
</gathering>
</social_group>
</col>
<col>
music</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/1402040.xml">
Rate Your Music</link></web_site>
</col>
<col>
music</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Innovations in Collaborative Filtering </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 New algorithms have been developed for CF as a result of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/9399111.xml">
NetFlix prize</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cross-System Collaborative Filtering where user profiles across multiple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/596646.xml">
recommender systems</link> are combined in a privacy preserving manner.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Robust Collaborative Filtering, where recommendation is stable towards efforts of manipulation. This research area is still active and not completely solved.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/2939955.xml">
Attention Profiling Mark-up Language (APML)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/9391536.xml">
Cold start</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/47284.xml">
Collective intelligence</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/11375922.xml">
Customer engagement</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/2596491.xml">
Preference elicitation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/596646.xml">
Recommendation system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/3940868.xml">
Reputation system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/1385393.xml">
The Long Tail</link></group>
</collection>
</law>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Goldberg, David; David Nichols, Brain M. Oki, Douglas Terry&#32;(1992).&#32;"Using collaborative filtering to weave an information tapestry". <it>Communications of the ACM</it>&#32;<b>35</b>&#32;(12): 61–70. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145%2F138859.138867">
10.1145/138859.138867</weblink>. <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<identifier wordnetid="107270601" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/234930.xml">
ISSN</link></system_of_measurement>
</identifier>
</signal>
</standard>
</symbol>
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://worldcat.org/issn/0001-0782">
0001-0782</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1297240</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Broom_icon.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 
The content of this section may be in violation of  and needs to be integrated into the body of the article.
 of  and  entries should be converted into where possible.</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.predictad.com">
PredictAd is a collaborative filtering Search Assist service for blogs and websites</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.andreas-ittner.de/index_rs.html">
Collection of research papers</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.barnesandnoble.com/booksearch/isbnInquiry.asp?z=y&amp;EAN=9780446530033&amp;itm=1">
Word of Mouse: The Marketing Power of Collaborative Filtering</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jamesthornton.com/cf/">
Collaborative Filtering bibliography by James Thornton</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pespmc1.vub.ac.be/COLLFILT.html">
<it>Collaborative Filtering</it> by Francis Heylighen</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.adastral.ucl.ac.uk/~junwang/CollaborativeFiltering.html">
<it>Collaborative Filtering Resources</it> by Jun Wang</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=1423975">
 Toward the next generation of recommender systems: a survey of the state-of-the-art and possible extensions</weblink>. Adomavicius, G. and Tuzhilin, A. IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering 06.2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ectrl.itc.it/home/laboratory/meeting/download/p5-l_herlocker.pdf">
Evaluating collaborative filtering recommender systems</weblink> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.doi.org/">
DOI</weblink>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/963770.963772">
10.1145/963770.963772</weblink>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.grouplens.org/publications.html">
GroupLens research papers</weblink>.  <link>
GroupLens</link> is one of the research labs that did a lot of pioneering research in collaborative filtering.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/ml/publication/paper.cgi?paper=cbcf-aaai-02.ps.gz">
Content-Boosted Collaborative Filtering for Improved Recommendations. Prem Melville, Raymond J. Mooney, and Ramadass Nagarajan</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/shardanand95social.html">
'Social Information Filtering: Algorithms for Automating "Word of Mouth"' by Upendra Shardanand</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://homepages.cwi.nl/~robu">
'Learning utility graphs for multi-issue negotiation using collaborative filtering' - Valentin Robu</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://agents.media.mit.edu/projects.html">
A collection of past and present "information filtering" projects (including collaborative filtering) at MIT Media Lab</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.orgnet.com/divided.html">
Collaborative filtering visualized as a network using Amazon data on political book purchases</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ieor.berkeley.edu/~goldberg/pubs/eigentaste.pdf">
Eigentaste: A Constant Time Collaborative Filtering Algorithm. Ken Goldberg, Theresa Roeder, Dhruv Gupta, and Chris Perkins. Information Retrieval, 4(2), 133-151. July 2001.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/datamining/Publications/p8734-schein.pdf">
Methods and Metrics for Cold-Start Recommendations </weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mystrands.com/corp/summerschool06.vm">
Recommenders06: Summer School on The Present and Future of Recommender Systems</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://recsys.acm.org/">
RecSys: ACM Recommender Systems 2007</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Software libraries </st>

<p>

Below are links to software libraries that allow developers to add collaborative filtering to applications or web sites:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://taste.sf.net">
Taste</weblink> - open-source, Java</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nongnu.org/cofi/">
Cofi</weblink> - open-source, Java</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eecs.oregonstate.edu/iis/CoFE/">
CoFE</weblink> - open-source, Java</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://colfi.wz.cz/">
ColFi</weblink> - open-source, Java</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.daniel-lemire.com/fr/abstracts/COLA2003.html">
RACOFI</weblink> - open-source, Java</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-users.cs.umn.edu/~karypis/suggest/">
SUGGEST</weblink> - Free, written in C.  (A library, not open source.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.daniel-lemire.com/fr/abstracts/TRD01.html">
Rating-Based Item-to-Item</weblink> - public domain, PHP</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vogoo-api.com/">
Vogoo PHP Lib</weblink> - open-source, PHP</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://exogen.case.edu/projects/consensus/">
consensus</weblink> - open-source, Python</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-2.cs.cmu.edu/~lebanon/IR-lab.htm">
C/Matlab Toolkit for Collaborative Filtering</weblink> - open-source, Matlab, C</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/jrennie/matlab/">
Fast Maximum Margin Matrix Factorization</weblink> - Matlab/Octave</entry>
</list>
</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
