<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:24:48[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<body  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107965085">
<university  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108286163">
<social_group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107950920">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<header>
<title>University of Faisalabad</title>
<id>4802812</id>
<revision>
<id>240957864</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-25T18:35:37Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>The Anomebot2</username>
<id>1979668</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Universities and colleges in Faisalabad District</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>The University of Faisalabad</b> was established to cater to the educational and technological need emerging in the progressive scenario of the country in general and Faisalabad and surrounding areas in particular, with a missionary spirit, commitment and fervors in line with the Government’s policies and priorities.  The distinguished University aspires for an appropriate balance between the emerging disciplines of science and technology and prevalent fields of humanities and social sciences.<p>

The heart of Pakistan Textile Industry -- Faisalabad suffered educational negligence for decades.  Then Madina Foundation took the challenge of facilitating common man and pave the path of success through educational enlightenment. On March 17, 2002, Madina Foundation, renowned for extending services in the social sector, launched a visionary colossal project to overcome the quality education deficit of the area.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Location </st>

<p>

The University of Faisalabad is chartered under Ordinance LX of 2002 promulgated by Government of the Punjab and recognized by Higher Education Commission as a degree awarding University. The MBBS program has NOC from the Pakistan Medical &amp; Dental Council.  The University campus is located on Sargodha Road, 4 km from the city center.  It is also accessible from Motorway through Pindi Bhattian Interchange. The purpose built campus is equipped with state-of-the-art facilities for proficient teaching and learning.
In early 2007 The Boys were transferred to a new campus On canal Road along side sarghoda road.
The Main campus was renamed for Women campus and New campus (Previously known as Allah-Rakhi Hospital) was devoted to boys alone.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 About the university </st>

<p>

The University of Faisalabad not only focuses on intellectual growth, professional competence and technical excellence of the students, but also, development of higher ethics, zest for community service and preservation of our cultural values.  It strives incessantly to build congenial learning environment, leavened with Islamic ethos and strengthened with free and open enquiry.  The management of the University as a team puts in diligent efforts to make learning experience at the University not only challenging but also enjoyable and exciting.  
The University of Faisalabad offers a diverse range of courses leading to under graduate, graduate and post graduate degrees.   The courses are taught by highly qualified and professionally competent faculty with a vision to provide leadership in education.  The curricula of the study disciplines are at par with the international standards, trends and market demands.   </p>
<p>

All modern facilities like high-tech computer laboratories equipped with latest equipment, multimedia, overhead projectors etc are provided to facilitate learning process and analytical academic environment. The University has a computer network of more than 200 nodes.  All end-user PCs have high tech Pentium 4 processors. </p>
<p>

A well stocked library has been established on the campus to promote reading culture and gaining knowledge about recent developments in science, technology and liberal sciences. The library has excellent collection of books, journals and also a computer network for open usage of students.  Besides, access to approximately 14,000 books and journals is available on line through Digital Library.</p>
<p>

The University provides a doorway to its graduates aspiring to enter into professional fields by expert career counseling and job placement. It has established professional links with organizations and institutes of repute regarding job placement of its graduates.
A well furnished cafeteria with facilities of hygienic food and snacks is available.  The centrally air-conditioned cafeteria is supervised by expert professionals for quality control.  A sports complex and play ground serve to promote corporate life on campus.</p>
<p>

What sets The University of Faisalabad supreme is unconditional commitment to quality education, sincere teaching endeavors, exclusive skill development, lucrative facilities, dynamism to improve and competent management team with vivid future vision.  We proudly groom the youth of Pakistan to launch upon an exciting professional career by inculcating a sense of achievement for meeting competitive global challenges.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/48361.xml">
Coordinates</link>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stable.toolserver.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=University_of_Faisalabad&amp;params=31_29_43.98_N_73_04_25.03_E_region:PK_type:city">
31°29′43.98″N 73°04′25.03″E﻿ / ﻿31.49555, 73.0736194</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/401880.xml">
Faisalabad</link></location>
</area>
</region>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/3100354.xml">
Faisalabad International Airport</link></airport>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/125315.xml">
Lahore</link></village>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <subdivision wordnetid="108674251" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/24751.xml">
Punjab (Pakistan)</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</region>
</subdivision>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/23235.xml">
Pakistan</link></country>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tuf.edu.pk/">
http://www.tuf.edu.pk/</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
</article>
