<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:25:01[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Massachusetts health care reform</title>
<id>4860610</id>
<revision>
<id>242506880</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T14:57:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Andy Marchbanks</username>
<id>2900330</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles with dead external links</category>
<category>Government of Massachusetts</category>
<category>Medicare and Medicaid (United States)</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Articles with dead external links since March 2008</category>
<category>Healthcare in the United States</category>
<category>Health care reform</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Government agency</name>
<parameters>
<logo_width>
70px</logo_width>
<logo>
Connectorroundlogo.gif‎</logo>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mahealthconnector.org">
www.mahealthconnector.org</weblink></website>
<logo_caption>
Connector Logo</logo_caption>
<chief1_position>
Executive Director</chief1_position>
<agency_name>
Commonwealth Health Insurance Connector Authority</agency_name>
<headquarters>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/3775.xml">
Boston</link> , <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1645518.xml">
Massachusetts</link></country>
</headquarters>
<chief1_name>
Jon Kingsdale</chief1_name>
<formed>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/1009.xml">
April 12</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link></formed>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>Massachusetts health care reform</b> law was enacted in 2006. It requires nearly every resident of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1645518.xml">
Massachusetts</link></country>
 to obtain <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/15343730.xml">
health insurance</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 coverage. Through the law, Massachusetts provides subsidized health care for residents earning up to 100% of the <condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<problem wordnetid="114410605" confidence="0.8">
<difficulty wordnetid="114408086" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/170584.xml">
Federal Poverty Level</link></difficulty>
</problem>
</state>
</condition>
, and partially subsidized health care those earning up to 300% of the FPL, depending on an income-based sliding scale. The law is credited with covering an additional 439,000 Massachusetts residents as of April 1, 2008.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The law established an independent public authority, the <it>Commonwealth Health Insurance Connector Authority,</it> also known as the Health Connector, which offers the subsidized coverage and facilitates the selection and purchase of private insurance plans by individuals and small businesses.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  Incentives for residents to obtain health insurance coverage include tax penalties for failing to obtain an insurance plan. In 2007, Massachusetts tax filers who failed to enroll in a health insurance plan that was deemed affordable for them lost the $219 personal exemption on their income tax. In 2008, penalties increase by monthly increments, and are based on half of the cost of a health insurance plan.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><p>

The reform law was enacted as Chapter 58 of the Acts of 2006 of the Massachusetts Legislature, entitled: <it>An Act Providing Access to Affordable, Quality, Accountable Health Care.</it>   In October 2006, January 2007, and November 2007, bills were enacted that amended and made technical corrections  to the statute (Chapters 324 and 450 of the Acts of 2006, and chapter 205 of the Acts of 2007).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Background</st>
<p>

Estimates of the number of Massachusetts residents who were uninsured in 2006 range from 395,000<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> to 653,000.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> Due to their lack of health <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
insurance</link> coverage, uninsured residents commonly utilize <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/177163.xml">
emergency rooms</link> as a source of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/532491.xml">
primary care</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> Massachusetts <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/18994221.xml">
hospitals</link> are required to provide care even if a patient cannot pay for it regardless of residency status.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> As a result, hospitals faced unpaid bills and mounting expenses to care for the uninsured.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

In Massachusetts, a fund of approximately $700 million, known as the <link>
Uncompensated Care Pool</link> (or "free care pool"), was used to partially reimburse hospitals and health centers for these expenses and the expenses of non-residents.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> The fund was raised through an annual assessment on insurance providers and hospitals, plus contributions of state and federal tax revenue. By implementing the health reform law, expenses incurred by services to the uninsured would decrease as the number of covered Massachusetts residents increased. In 2006, MIT professor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<economist wordnetid="110043643" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/18618495.xml">
Jonathan Gruber</link></scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</economist>
</physical_entity>
 determined that there was enough money in the "free care pool" to pay for reform legislation without requiring additional funding or taxes.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Reform coalitions </st>

<p>

In November 2004, political leaders began advocating for major reforms of the Massachusetts health care system to expand coverage. First, the Senate President <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.8">
<lawgiver wordnetid="110249270" confidence="0.8">
<legislator wordnetid="110253995" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/2975034.xml">
Robert Travaglini</link></legislator>
</lawgiver>
</senator>
</causal_agent>
</leader>
</person>
</politician>
</physical_entity>
 called for a plan to reduce the number of uninsured by half. A few days later, the Governor, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<governor wordnetid="110140314" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/426208.xml">
Mitt Romney</link></governor>
</person>
, announced that he would propose a plan to cover virtually all of the uninsured.</p>
<p>

At the same time, the ACT (Afforable Care Today) Coalition introduced a bill that expanded <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/4736160.xml">
MassHealth</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/55794.xml">
Medicaid</link>) coverage and increased health coverage subsidy programs and required employers to either provide coverage or pay an assessment to the state. The coalition began gathering signatures to place their proposal on the ballot in November 2006 if the legislature did not enact comprehensive health care reform, resulting in the collection of over 75,000 signatures on the MassACT ballot proposal. The Blue Cross Blue Shield Foundation also sponsored a study, "Roadmap to Coverage," to expand coverage to everyone in the Commonwealth.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>
<p>

Attention focused on the House when Speaker DiMasi, speaking at a Blue Cross Blue Shield Foundation Roadmap To Coverage forum in October 2005, pledged to pass a bill through the House by the end of the session. At the forum, the Foundation issued a series of reports on reform options, all of which include an individual mandate.  At the end of the month, the Joint Committee on Health Care Financing approved a reform proposal crafted by House Speaker DiMasi, Committee co-chair Walrath and other House members.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

Massachusetts also faced pressure from the federal government to make changes to the federal waiver that allows the state to operate an expanded Medicaid program. Under the existing waiver, the state was receiving $385 million in federal funds to reimburse hospitals for services provided to the uninsured.  The free care pool had to be restructured so that individuals, rather than institutions, received the funding.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Legislation </st>
<p>

In fall 2005 as the House and Senate each passed health care reform bills.</p>
<p>

The legislature made a number of changes to Governor Romney's original proposal, including expanding  MassHealth (Medicaid) coverage to low-income children and restoring funding for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/463734.xml">
public health</link> programs. The most controversial change was adding a provision charging firms with 11 or more workers that do not provide "fair and reasonable" health coverage to their workers. The charge, initially $295 annually per worker, is intended to equalize the free care pool charges imposed on employers who do and do not cover their workers. The legislature also rejected Governor Romney's proposal to permit even higher-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/636959.xml">
deductible</link>, lower benefit health plans.</p>
<p>

On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/1009.xml">
April 12</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link> Governor <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<governor wordnetid="110140314" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/426208.xml">
Mitt Romney</link></governor>
</person>
 signed the health legislation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>  He vetoed 8 sections of the health care legislation, including the employer assessment.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>  Romney also vetoed provisions providing <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/6111114.xml">
dental</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 benefits to poor residents on the Medicaid program, and providing health coverage to senior and disabled legal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/4599312.xml">
immigrant</link>s not eligible for federal Medicaid.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>
The legislature promptly overrode six of eight gubernatorial section vetoes, on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/19351.xml">
May 4</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>, and by mid-June 2006 had overridden the remaining two.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Statute</st>

<p>

The enacted statute,  chapter 58 of the acts of 2006, established a system to mandate individuals, with a few exceptions, to obtain health insurance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> Chapter 58 has several key provisions: the creation of the Health Connector; the establishment of the subsidized Commonwealth Care Health Insurance Program; the employer Fair Share Contribution and Free Rider Surcharge; and a requirement that each individual must show evidence of coverage on their income tax return or face a tax penalty, unless coverage was deemed unaffordable.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> The statute also expands MassHealth (Medicaid and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/635422.xml">
SCHIP</link>) coverage for children of low income parents and restores MassHealth benefits like dental care and eyeglasses. A merger of the individual (non-group) insurance market into the small group market will allow individuals to get lower group insurance rates. Payment rates are increased to hospitals and physicians, and a new "Quality and Cost Council," will issue quality standards and publicize provider performance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> Chapter 58 also sets up a Disparities Council, funds automated prescription ordering in hospitals, and implements changes to the public health council, state insurance laws, mandated benefit requirements, and other health-related programs. The following are the most prominent features.</p>
<p>

On October 26, 2006, the Commonwealth enacted chapter 324 of the acts of 2006, legislation making adjustments and technical corrections to chapter 58. The statute contains 82 sections and includes sections amending effective dates for many of the private insurance provisions of chapter 58. Another technical corrections bill, chapter 450 of the acts of 2006, was enacted on January 3, 2007. The statute includes more adjustments to effective dates. A third technical corrections statute was enacted on November 29, 2007, as chapter 205 of the acts of 2007.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Commonwealth Health Insurance Connector Authority</st>
<p>

The Health <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mahealthconnector.org">
Connector</weblink> is designed as a clearinghouse for insurance plans and payments. It performs the following functions:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

It administers the Commonwealth Care program for low-income residents (up to 300% of the FPL) who do not qualify for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/4736160.xml">
MassHealth</link> and meet certain eligibility guidelines.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

It offers for purchase health insurance plans for individuals who:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

are not working</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

are employed by a small business (less than 50 employees) that uses the Connector to offer health insurance. These residents will purchase insurance with pre-tax income.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

are not qualified under their large employer plan</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

are self-employed, part-time workers, or work for multiple employers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

It sets premium subsidy levels for Commonwealth Care.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

It defines "affordability" for purposes of the individual mandate</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The Health Connector is run by the Commonwealth Health Insurance Connector Authority, an independent agency with a 10-member board. The Health Connector will make health insurance portable by allowing employees to keep the same plan even if they leave an employer. The Health Connector will also allow employees to aggregate the contributions of multiple employers, e.g. if they are part-time workers or work for multiple employers, and apply them to one insurance plan.
The Health Connector is currently managed by former Tufts Associated Health Plans executive Jon Kingsdale, who serves as its executive director.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Commonwealth Care Health Insurance Program</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://macommonwealthcare.com">
Commonwealth Care</weblink> is one of the newest subsidized health insurance programs offered by the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1645518.xml">
Commonwealth</link></country>
, and is a key part of Health Care Reform in Massachusetts.  It is designed primarily for income-eligible Massachusetts adult residents who are not otherwise eligible for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/4736160.xml">
Masshealth</link>, who either do not work or who work for employers that do not offer health insurance.  Specifically, it allows eligible residents access to certain subsidized private insurance health plans&nbsp;&ndash;  currently a <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/Qhic/docs/CCplanchart_030107.pdf">
choice of four plans</weblink>&nbsp;&ndash;  for individuals without health insurance who make below 300% of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/19283913.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Recent+poverty+rate+and+guidelines+%22])">
 federal poverty level</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> There are no deductibles.  For individuals below 150% of the federal poverty level, no premiums will be charged; for those below the poverty level, dental insurance is also provided.  For those above 150% of the federal poverty level, a sliding scale premium schedule based on income is used to determine the amount of money a person contributes to their policy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> Commonwealth Care for those below poverty has been available through the Connector since October 1, 2006. Plans for those between 100% and 300% of the poverty line have been available since January 1, 2007. As of Dec. 1, 2007, over 158,000 people have enrolled in Commonwealth Care.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Employer Taxes</st>
<p>

Employers with more than ten employees must provide a "fair and reasonable contribution" to the premium of health insurance for employees.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> Employers who do not will be assessed an annual fair share contribution that will not exceed $295 per employee per year.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> The fair share contribution will be paid into the Commonwealth Care Trust Fund to fund Commonwealth Care and other health reform programs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> The Division of Health Care Finance and Policy defined by regulation what contribution level meets the "fair and reasonable" test in the statute. The regulation imposes two tests. First, employers are deemed to have offered "fair and reasonable" coverage if at least 25% of their full-time workers are enrolled in the firm's health plan. Alternatively, a company meets the standard if it offers to pay at least 33% of the premium cost of an individual health plan.</p>
<p>

There is an additional Free Rider Surcharge that can be assessed to the employer.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> This surcharge is different from the fair share contribution. The surcharge is applied when an employer does not arrange for a pre-tax payroll deduction system for health insurance, and has employees who receive care that is paid from the <link>
uncompensated care pool</link>, renamed in October 2007 as the Health Safety Net.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> If an employee receives free care more than three times or all of an employer's employees use free care a total of five times, then the employer must pay a portion of the health care costs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Individual taxes</st>
<p>

Residents of Massachusetts must have health insurance coverage under Chapter 58.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref> Residents must indicate on their tax forms for the 2007 tax year if they had insurance on December 31 2007, have a waiver for religious reasons, or have a waiver from the Connector. The Connector waiver can be obtained if the resident demonstrates that there is no available coverage that is defined by the Connector as affordable.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> In March 2007, the Connector adopted an affordability schedule that allows residents to seek a waiver.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref> If a resident does not have coverage and does not have a waiver, the Department of Revenue will enforce the insurance requirement by imposing a penalty. In 2007, the penalty was the loss of the personal exemption. Beginning in 2008, the penalty will be up to half the cost of the lowest available yearly premium which will be enforced as an assessed addition to the individual's income tax, up to $912 a year.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Young Adult Coverage</st>
<p>

Starting January 1, 2007, insurers' family coverage plans are required to cover young adults up to age 25 for up to two years past the young adult's loss of dependent status. Beginning in July 2007, the Connector offers reduced benefit plans for young adults up to age 26 who do not have access to employer-based coverage.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Implementation</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Newlycovered.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Composition of Newly Covered as of 1/1/08
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Dropuninsured.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Drop in Uninsurance Significant Across Income Strata
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Taxpayers.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Detail of Uninsured Taxpayers
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="HealthReform.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Non-Group Reform Results
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The implementation of chapter 58 began in June, 2006, with the appointment of members of the Connector board, and the naming of Jon Kingsdale, a Tufts Health Plan official, as executive director of the Connector. The Board started meeting biweekly. On July 1, MassHealth began covering dental care and other benefits, and began enrolling children between 200% and 300% of the poverty level.</p>
<p>

The federal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/215745.xml">
Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services</link> approved the state's waiver application on July 26, 2006, allowing the state to begin enrolling 10,500 from the waitlist for the MassHealth Essential program, which provides Medicaid coverage to long-term unemployed adults below the poverty line.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref></p>
<p>

In September, 2006, the Division of Health Care Finance and Policy issued regulations defining "fair and reasonable" for the fair share assessment. The regulations provide that companies with 11 or more full-time equivalent employees will meet the “fair and reasonable” test if at least 25 percent of those employees are enrolled in that firm’s health plan and the company is making a contribution toward it. A business that fails that test may still be deemed to offer a “fair and reasonable” contribution if the company offers to pay at least 33 percent of an individual’s health insurance premium.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref></p>
<p>

Also in September, the Connector Board set premium levels and co-payments for the state subsidized Commonwealth Care plans. Premiums will vary from $18 per month, for individuals with incomes 100%-150% of the poverty line, to $106 per month for individuals with incomes 250%-300% of poverty. The Connector approved two co-payment schemes for plans for people 200%-300% of poverty. One plan will have higher premiums and lower co-payments, while a second choice will have lower premiums and higher co-payments.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref> Four managed care plans began offering Commonwealth Care on November, 1, 2006. Coverage for people above 100% of poverty up to 300% of poverty began on February 1, 2007. As of December 1, 2007, around 158,000 people were enrolled in Commonwealth Care plans.</p>
<p>

Initial bids received by the Connector showed a likely cost for the minimum insurance plan of about $380 per month. The Connector rejected those bids, and asked insurers to propose less expensive plans. New bids were announced on March 3, 2007. The Governor announced that "the average uninsured Massachusetts resident will be able to purchase health insurance for $175 per month."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref> But plan costs will vary greatly depending on the plan selected, age and geographic location, ranging from just over $100 per month for plans for young adults with high copayments and deductibles to nearly $900 per month for comprehensive plans for older adults with low deductibles and copayments.  Co-payments, deductibles and out-of-pocket contributions may vary among plans. The proposed minimum creditable coverage plan would have a deductible no higher than $2,000 per individual, $4,000 per family, and would limit out-of-pocket expenses to a $5,000 maximum for an individual and $7,500 for a family. Before the deductible applies, the proposed plan includes preventive office visits with higher co-payments, but would not include emergency room visits if the person was not admitted.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2237%22])">37</ref></p>
<p>

In February 2008 the Boston Globe reported that Commonwealth Care covered 169,000 people and had a projected cost of $618 million for the fiscal year.  By June 2011 enrollment is projected to grow to 342,000 people at an annual expense of $1.35 billion.  The original projections were for the program to ultimately cover approximately 215,000 people at a cost of $725 million.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2238%22])">38</ref>  Enrollment in the Commonwealth Care Health Insurance Program reached approximately 170,000 by April 1 of 2008.  Enrollment in the Commonwealth Choice Plans, offered through the Commonwealth Health Insurance Connector, was almost 18,000 by the same date.  Enrollment in the Commonwealth's Medicare program, MassHealth, was up by 50,000 by January 2008.  Data from the Massachusetts Association of Health plans suggest that enrollment in employer-sponsored health insurance was up by 85,000, but the number of people with individual coverage increased by less than 10,000.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref></p>
<p>

In March 2008 the <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/30068.xml">
Boston Globe</link></newspaper>
 reported that some "safety-net" hospitals serving low-income individuals in urban areas were facing budget shortfalls due to the combination of reduced "free-care" payments from the state and low enrollment in Commonwealth Care.  The reduced state payments anticipated that by reducing the number of uninsured people Commonwealth Care would reduce the amount of charity care provided by hospitals.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref> In a subsequent story that same month the Globe reported that Commonwealth Care faced a short-term funding gap of $100 million and the need to obtain a new three-year funding commitment from the federal government of $1.5 billion.  The Globe reported that a number of alternatives were under consideration for raising additional funding, including a $1 per pack increase in the state's cigarette tax.  Health care costs in the state were rising at an annual rate of 10 percent, and the state budget deficit was $1.3 billion.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2241%22])">41</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Possible legal challenges</st>
<p>

A legal challenge to the law may arise under the presumption that it is an attempt to preempt the federal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/889160.xml">
Employee Retirement Income Security Act</link> (ERISA).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref>  A somewhat similar law with respect to employer spending on health insurance in Maryland was struck down by a federal judge on July 19, 2006.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref> The law in question had required employers with more than 10,000 employees to spend no less than 8% of their payroll on health insurance benefits.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref> The ruling effectively delineated that states cannot interfere in the administration of employer provided benefits to their employees and such interference was a violation of federal law.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref>  However, some policy analysts argue that the Massachusetts reform differs in that it does not mandate business to change coverage, but rather, simply imposes a tax&nbsp;&ndash;  one of the states' rights guaranteed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/31662.xml">
10th amendment</link> of the Constitution.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2243%22])">43</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/889160.xml">
Employee Retirement Income Security Act (ERISA)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/55794.xml">
Medicaid</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/58353.xml">
Medicare (United States)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../966/4378966.xml">
Massachusetts general election, 2006</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/12733996.xml">
California Speaks</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</group>
</event>
 - Citizen discussion on similar legislation in California, 2007</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <legislation wordnetid="106535222" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/7054921.xml">
United States National Health Insurance Act</link></legislation>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Lazar, Kay&#32;(August 20, 2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2008/08/20/439000_more_get_health_coverage/">
439,000 more get health coverage</weblink>", <it>Boston Globe</it>, pp.&nbsp;1.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-20</link>.&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="2">
LeBlank, Steve&#59;&#32;(Associated Press)&#32;(November 9, 2007).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2007/11/09/timing_of_health_care_laws_penalties_could_pose_risks_for_romney/\">
Timing of health care law's penalties could pose risks for Romney</weblink>", <it>Boston Globe</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-18</link>.&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="3">
 Rainey, James&#32;(November 13, 2007).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.latimes.com/features/health/la-na-romney13nov13,1,4228006,full.story">
Romney casts a cool eye on a former triumph</weblink>", <it>Los Angeles Times</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-18</link>.&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="4">
 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mahealthconnector.org/portal/site/connector/template.PAGE/menuitem.55b6e23ac6627f40dbef6f47d7468a0c/?javax.portlet.tpst=ab2ef98d75886742e902ac100ce08041&amp;javax.portlet.prp_ab2ef98d75886742e902ac100ce08041_viewID=MY_PORTAL_VIEW&amp;javax.portlet.begCacheTok=com.vignette.cachetoken&amp;javax.portlet.endCacheTok=com.vignette.cachetoken">
Find Insurance: Individuals &amp; Families: Act Now</weblink>".&#32;<it>Commonwealth Health Insurance Connector</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-15</link>. </entry>
<entry id="5">
Dembner, Alice&#32;(November 15, 2007).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/news/health/blog/2007/11/insurance_deadl.html?p1=MEWell_Pos3">
Insurance deadlines – Nov. 20 and Dec. 31</weblink>", <it>Boston Globe</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-18</link>.&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="6">
For text of the laws, provided by <it>The  General Court of The Commonwealth of Massachusetts</it> 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/legis/summary.pdf">
 Summary of the Massachusetts Health Reform Law</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/legis/laws/seslaw06/sl060058.htm">
Chapter 58 of the Chapter 58 of the Acts of 2006</weblink> An Act Providing Access to Affordable, Quality Accountable Health Care</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

and subsequent amendments and technical corrections bills enacted in the same legislative session:</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/legis/laws/seslaw06/sl060324.htm">
  Chapter 324 of the Acts of 2006</weblink> An Act Relative to Health Care Access.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/legis/laws/seslaw06/sl060450.htm">
Chapter 450 of the Acts of 2006 </weblink> An Act Further Regulating Health Care Access.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mass.gov/legis/laws/seslaw07/sl070205.htm">
Chapter 205 of the Acts of 2007</weblink> An Act Further Regulating Health Care Access.</entry>
</list>
</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/Eeohhs2/docs/dhcfp/r/pubs/08/hh_survey_07.ppt">
Massachusetts Division of Health Care Finance and Policy, June 2008</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
http://www.census.gov/hhes/www/hlthins/hlthin06/p60no233_table8.pdf U.S. Census Bureau, August 2007]</entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.businessweek.com/investor/content/apr2006/pi20060404_152510.htm">
In Massachusetts, Health Care for All?</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bphc.org/howto/ins_mucp.asp">
Boston Public Health Commission - How To Access Health Care - Massachusetts Uncompensate (Free) Care Pool</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5330854">
NPR: Romney's Mission: Massachusetts Health Care</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/Eeohhs2/docs/dhcfp/p/ucp/pfy05_utilization.doc">
Uncompensated Care Pool PFY05 Utilization Report</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opinionjournal.com/editorial/feature.html?id=110008213">
The Wall Street Journal Online - Featured Article</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.roadmaptocoverage.org">
Roadmap to Coverage - Research on providing health coverage for the uninsured in Massachusetts</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hcfama.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=Page.viewPage&amp;pageId=840&amp;parentID=839&amp;grandparentID=737&amp;nodeID=2">
ACT Health Care Reform Timeline</weblink></entry>
<entry id="17">
http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/massachusetts_health;_ylt=AkMg0NHWbbPPMpo5ese19mKs0NUE;_ylu=X3oDMTA2Z2szazkxBHNlYwN0bQ--</entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.umassmed.edu/uploadedFiles/CHC_HealthReformMassachusetts.ppt">
Health Care Reform in Massachusetts</weblink></entry>
<entry id="19">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://today.reuters.co.uk/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=healthNews&amp;storyID=2006-04-12T222644Z_01_N12342304_RTRIDST_0_HEALTH-MASSACHUSETTS-DC.XML&amp;archived=False">
http://today.reuters.co.uk/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=healthNews&amp;storyID=2006-04-12T222644Z_01_N12342304_RTRIDST_0_HEALTH-MASSACHUSETTS-DC.XML&amp;archived=False</weblink>&#91;&#93;</entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2005/11/04/house_approves_healthcare_overhaul/">
House approves healthcare overhaul - The Boston Globe</weblink></entry>
<entry id="21">
http://news.bostonherald.com/localPolitics/view.bg?articleid=134877
</entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thetranscript.com/headlines/ci_3706699">
North Adams Transcript - Romney signs health care bill</weblink></entry>
<entry id="23">
2006 Mass. Acts Chp. 58</entry>
<entry id="22">
 See chapter 58 text for overrides. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/legis/laws/seslaw06/sl060058.htm">
Chapter 58, Acts of 2006</weblink>: The six prompt overrides were noted at the foot of the chapter: Approved (in part) April 12, 2006. Disapproved sections 5, 27, 29, 47, 112, 113, 134 and 137  'Sections 5, 29, 47, 113, 134 and 137 overridden on May 4, 2006.
</entry>
<entry id="25">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opinionjournal.com/editorial/feature.html?id=110008213">
Mitt Romney, "Health Care for Everyone?" <it>Wall Street Journal</it> (April 11, 2006)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="24">
Report from Massachusetts Secretary of Health and Human Services Timothy Murphy, to the Massachusetts General Court, "Chapter 58 Implementation Update" (June 12, 2006).</entry>
<entry id="27">
2006 Mass. Act Chp. 58, sec. 47</entry>
<entry id="26">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/eoaf/pressreleases/new_healthcare_director.html">
Administration and Finance</weblink></entry>
<entry id="29">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hcfama.org/_uploads/documents/live/HCReformFAQ.pdf">
Massachusetts General Court, Committee on Health Care Financing, "Health Care FAQ" (April 4, 2006) PDF</weblink></entry>
<entry id="28">
2006 Mass. Acts Chp. 58, sec. 44</entry>
<entry id="31">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mahealthconnector.org/portal/site/connector/template.MAXIMIZE/menuitem.3ef8fb03b7fa1ae4a7ca7738e6468a0c/?javax.portlet.tpst=2fdfb140904d489c8781176033468a0c_ws_MX&amp;javax.portlet.prp_2fdfb140904d489c8781176033468a0c_viewID=content&amp;javax.portlet.prp_2fdfb140904d489c8781176033468a0c_docName=affordability%20tool%202008&amp;javax.portlet.prp_2fdfb140904d489c8781176033468a0c_folderPath=/FindInsurance/Individual/Affordability%20Calculator/&amp;javax.portlet.begCacheTok=com.vignette.cachetoken&amp;javax.portlet.endCacheTok=com.vignette.cachetoken">
http://www.mahealthconnector.org/portal/site/connector/template.MAXIMIZE/menuitem.3ef8fb03b7fa1ae4a7ca7738e6468a0c/?javax.portlet.tpst=2fdfb140904d489c8781176033468a0c_ws_MX&amp;javax.portlet.prp_2fdfb140904d489c8781176033468a0c_viewID=content&amp;javax.portlet.prp_2fdfb140904d489c8781176033468a0c_docName=affordability%20tool%202008&amp;javax.portlet.prp_2fdfb140904d489c8781176033468a0c_folderPath=/FindInsurance/Individual/Affordability%20Calculator/&amp;javax.portlet.begCacheTok=com.vignette.cachetoken&amp;javax.portlet.endCacheTok=com.vignette.cachetoken</weblink>, Affordability Schedule.</entry>
<entry id="30">
2006 Mass. Acts Chp. 58, sec. 12</entry>
<entry id="34">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mass.gov/?pageID=pressreleases&amp;agId=Eeohhs2&amp;prModName=eohhspressrelease&amp;prFile=pr_060908_fair_share.xml">
Press Release on Fair Share regulations, September 8, 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry id="35">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hcfama.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=Page.viewPage&amp;pageID=587">
Health Care For All's Commonwealth Care page</weblink></entry>
<entry id="32">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hcfama.org/_uploads/documents/live/MA%20Health%20Reform%20Law.pdf">
Health Care for All "Massachusetts's Health Care Reform Law Fact Sheet" PDF</weblink></entry>
<entry id="33">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/?pageID=pressreleases&amp;agId=Agov2&amp;prModName=gov2pressrelease&amp;prFile=gov_pr_060726_fed_approved_HC_.xml">
Press Release on waiver approval, July 28, 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry id="38">
Alice Dembner, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/news/health/articles/2008/02/03/subsidized_care_plans_cost_to_double/">
"Subsidized care plan's cost to double: Enrollment is outstripping state's estimate,"</weblink> The Boston Globe, February 3, 2008</entry>
<entry id="39">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kff.org/uninsured/upload/7777.pdf">
"Massachusetts Health Care Reform: Two Years Later,"</weblink> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/4423394.xml">
Kaiser Family Foundation</link>, May 2008</entry>
<entry id="36">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hcfama.org/_uploads/documents/live/HealthInsurancePressRelease.pdf">
Press release on minimum creditable coverage plans, March 3, 2007</weblink></entry>
<entry id="37">
  Dembner, Alice. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/news/globe/city_region/breaking_news/2007/01/outline_for_new_1.html">
Outline for new insurance plan proposed</weblink> Boston Globe. January 19, 2007. Retrieved January 19, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="42">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.usatoday.com/money/industries/retail/2006-07-19-walmart-healthcare_x.htm">
 USA Today July 19, 2006: Walmart Healthcare Litigation</weblink></entry>
<entry id="43">
Butler, Patricia. "Fact Sheet: ERISA Implications for State Pay or Play Laws." California HealthCare Foundation.
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://64.233.169.104/search?q=cache:quk36Rm3KOkJ:calhealthreform.org/pdf/ERISAfactsheetButlerP.pdf+massachusetts+state+mandate+tax+ERISA&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=2&amp;gl=us">
http://64.233.169.104/search?q=cache:quk36Rm3KOkJ:calhealthreform.org/pdf/ERISAfactsheetButlerP.pdf+massachusetts+state+mandate+tax+ERISA&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=2&amp;gl=us</weblink></entry>
<entry id="40">
Jeffrey Krasner, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/business/healthcare/articles/2008/03/18/safety_net_hospitals_strained_by_reform/">
"Safety net hospitals strained by reform,"</weblink> <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/30068.xml">
The Boston Globe</link></newspaper>
, March 18, 2008</entry>
<entry id="41">
Alice Dembner, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2008/03/26/healthcare_cost_increases_dominate_mass_budget_debate/?page=full">
"Healthcare cost increases dominate Mass. budget debate,"</weblink> <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/30068.xml">
The Boston Globe</link></newspaper>
, March 26, 2008</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mahealthconnector.org">
Commonwealth Health Insurance Connector Authority</weblink> Official web site. Describes the Massachusetts health reform act, authorized health insurance plans, regulations issued, board members and board minutes.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hcfama.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=Page.viewPage&amp;pageId=839&amp;parentID=736&amp;nodeID=2">
Health Reform Timeline</weblink> Month-by-month chronology of the passage and implementation of the Massachusetts health reform law.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://usliberals.about.com/od/healthcare/i/MassHealthIns.htm">
About.com's Pros &amp; Cons of Massachusetts' Mandatory Health Insurance Program</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hcfama.org/act/about.asp">
Affordable  Coverage Today</weblink>  Health Care for All. (A health care advocacy group in Massachusetts)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mass.gov/?pageID=eohhs2terminal&amp;L=4&amp;L0=Home&amp;L1=Government&amp;L2=Special+Commissions+and+Initiatives&amp;L3=Healthcare+Reform&amp;sid=Eeohhs2&amp;b=terminalcontent&amp;f=eohhs_healthcare_reform_rpts_legislature&amp;csid=Eeohhs2">
EOHHS Health Reform Reports to Massachusetts legislature</weblink> Bi-monthly progress reports on the implementation of Massachusetts health reform.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bcbsmafoundation.org/foundationroot/en_US/documents/2006HealthReformPollingreport.pdf">
The Massachusetts Health Reform Law: Public Opinion and Perception</weblink> A Report for the Blue Cross Blue Shield of Massachusetts Foundation. November 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.newamerica.net/files/MA%20HC%20Reform%20Lessons%20Learned%20to%20Date%20Aug%2007%20FINAL1.pdf">
Lessons learned to date from the Massachusetts Healthcare Reform</weblink> by Celia Wcislo (August 2007)  (Celia Wcislo, is a Board Member of the Massachusetts Commonwealth Health Insurance Connector Authority)  Publisher:  Local 1199 Service Employees International Union (SEIU) United Healthcare Workers East.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.heritage.org/Press/Events/ev012606b.cfm">
 Presentation by Governor Mitt Romney, January 26, 2006</weblink> Massachusetts Health Care Reform.  The Heritage Foundation, Washington D.C. (Using Power Point visuals. Available as video, or audio MP3)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bela Gorman, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soa.org/library/newsletters/health-watch-newsletter/2008/january/hsn-2008-iss57.pdf">
"Update on Massachusetts Health Care Financing Reform,"</weblink> Health Watch, Issue No. 57, <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/337198.xml">
Society of Actuaries</link></organization>
, January 2008</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
