<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:22:00[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<agency  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108337324">
<header>
<title>Alternatives</title>
<id>4880236</id>
<revision>
<id>220748214</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-21T11:29:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Eubot</username>
<id>231599</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>International development agencies</category>
<category>1994 establishments</category>
<category>Organizations based in Montreal</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For the Canadian environmental magazine, see <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/16931909.xml">
Alternatives Journal</link></magazine>
.
Founded in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/18948337.xml">
1994</link>, <b>Alternatives</b>, Action and Communication Network for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/385745.xml">
International Development</link>, is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/46539.xml">
non-governmental</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/197661.xml">
international solidarity</link> organization based in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/7954681.xml">
Montreal</link></village>
, <district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/7954867.xml">
Quebec</link></district>
, <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
.<p>

Alternatives works to promote justice and equality amongst individuals and communities located in the North and the South. Active in over 35 countries, Alternatives supports local, community-based initiatives working towards the greater economic, social, and political rights of people and communities affected by poverty, discrimination, exploitation, and violence.</p>
<p>

The organization publishes the <it>Journal Alternatives</it> newsletter, a publication inserted once per month in Montreal's French daily <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/326379.xml">
Le Devoir</link></newspaper>
.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
International program</st>

<p>

Alternatives is present in Latin America, Africa, Europe and the Middle East, as well as Central, South and Southeast Asia.</p>
<p>

In each of these regions, the organisation work in direct partnership with groups of women and men who are struggling for progress, respect and justice, as well as the peace and sustainable development of their community, their environment, and their region.</p>
<p>

Alternatives supports network creation between groups so that they can benefit from their shared experiences and successes. Network formation is crucial since it allows for deepened analysis and comprehension of the conflicts affecting their communities from the outside.</p>
<p>

Alternatives’ and its partners’ international solidarity projects are centred on:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The environment and sustainable development</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Democracy</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rehabilitation of communities affected by war</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Good governance</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Socio-economic justice and equality</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Civil, political, economic, social and human rights</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The fight against poverty</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Women’s rights, equality between genders, the inclusion of women in all spheres of society</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Education and inclusion of youth</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Civil society development, management, and autonomy</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Freedom of organization, of information, of the press, and of religion</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Youth Internship Programs</st>

<p>

Every year, Alternatives organizes overseas youth internship programs, with the aim of developing in young men and women a sense of solidarity and curiosity about other regions than their own. These internships emphasize understanding Third World realities, encouraging actions that will advance Alternatives’ message of justice. Thanks to the internships, hundreds of young people have had the opportunity to participate in a professional, cultural, and human experience of unrivalled interest.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Alternatives in Quebec and Canada</st>

<p>

Alternatives is an organization that produces and participates in many conferences, that publishes a newspaper and several Web sites, and that organizes educational and informational activities.</p>
<p>

The Alternatives newspaper, a monthly compendium of international, national, and cultural news, has a distribution of 50,000, creating a window of alternative information on our world.</p>
<p>

Whether in Quebec, Canada, or the world, Alternatives works to raise public awareness of international and local policy debates and keep people informed of the links between them. Through its information and educational campaigns, reflecting our concerns with equality and justice for the South, Alternatives goes beyond the general public to reach policymakers. At the local level, our work involves environmental concerns, participatory democracy, out-reach and solidarity programs with immigrant communities, as well as promotion of pro-social policies.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Finances</st>

<p>

Approximately 50% of Alternatives funds come from government sources(principally the Canadian International Development Agency). The remainder is a combination of support from over 50,000 donors and members, as well as partner organizations working alongside Alternatives including major unions and church groups.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Supporters</st>

<p>

Over 50,000 individuals across Canada contribute to Alternatives either as donors, members, or by subscribing to the newspaper.</p>
<p>

Many activists, journalists, and public figures from Quebec, Canada, and the world support Alternatives. Among these are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Monique Simard, documentary film producer and activist</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Judy Rebick, politically engaged writer and researcher</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Françoise David, leader of Québec Solidaire, ex-President of the Quebec Federation of Women, co-founder of the World March of Women</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gil Courtemanche, activist journalist and writer</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Madeleine Parent, feminist and long-time union leader</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ariane Émond, General Director of Culture Montréal, journalist and researcher</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Stanley Péan, writer and cultural broadcaster for Radio-Canada</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bishop Desmond Tutu, Nobel Peace Prize winner</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Asmaa Jangir, Human Rights Commission of Pakistan</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Contacts</st>
<p>

<b>Head Office</b></p>
<p>

3720 Parc Ave., #300
Montreal (Quebec)
H2X 2J1
Phone number: (514) 982-6606
Toll free: 1-800-982-6646
Fax: (514) 982-6122
e-mail: alternatives@alternatives.ca</p>

<p>

<b>Quebec City Office</b></p>
<p>

266 St-Vallier West
Quebec (Quebec)
G1K 1K2
Phone number: (418) 521-4000
Fax number :(418) 521-4000
e-mail: quebec@alternatives.ca</p>

</ss1>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alternatives.ca/en">
Alternatives website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</agency>
</organization>
</article>
