<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:22:02[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Exploratory search</title>
<id>4881262</id>
<revision>
<id>218179530</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-09T14:33:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dtunkelang</username>
<id>5293022</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Information retrieval</category>
<category>Information science</category>
<category>Human-computer_interaction</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Exploratory search</b> is a specialization of information exploration, which represents the activities carried out by searchers who are either [1]: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a) unfamiliar with the domain of their goal (ie need to learn about the topic in order to understand how to achieve their goal)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 b) unsure about the ways to achieve their goals (either the technology or the process)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 c) or even unsure about their goals in the first place.</entry>
</list>
<p>

Consequently, <b>Exploratory Search</b> covers a broader class of activities (compared to typical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
Information Retrieval</link>), such as investigating, evaluating, comparing, and synthesizing, where new information is sought in a defined conceptual area; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/416589.xml">
exploratory data analysis</link> is another example of an information exploration activity. Typically, therefore, such users generally combine querying and browsing strategies to foster learning and investigation.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

<b>Exploratory Search</b> is a topic that has grown from the fields of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
Information Retrieval</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/9586885.xml">
Information seeking</link>, but has become more and more concerned with the alternative scenarios of search that have received the majority of focus (returning the most relevant documents to a Google-like keyword search). The research is motivated by questions like "what if the user doesn't know which keywords to use?" or "what if the user isn't looking for a single answer?". Consequently, research has begin to focus on defining the broader set of <it>Information Behaviors</it> in order to learn about the situations when a user is, or feels, limited by only having the ability to perform a keyword search.</p>
<p>

In the last few years, a series of workshops have been held at various related and key events. In 2005, the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/~ryenw/xsi/index.html">
Exploratory Search Interfaces workshop</weblink> focused on beginning to define some of the key challenges in the field. Since then a series of other workshops have been held at related conferences: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/~ryenw/eess/index.html">
Evaluating Exploratory Search</weblink> at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir2006.org">
SIGIR06</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/~ryenw/esi/index.html">
Exploratory Search and HCI</weblink> at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chi2007.org">
CHI07</weblink> (in order to meet with the experts in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/13516.xml">
Human Computer Interaction</link>).</p>
<p>

In March 2008, a Information Processing and Management <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/03064573">
Special Issue</weblink> [2] has focused particularly on the challenges of evaluating Exploratory Search, given the reduced assumptions that can be made about scenarios of use.</p>
<p>

In June 2008, the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/157427.xml">
National Science Foundation</link></agency>
 is sponsoring an <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ils.unc.edu/ISSS_workshop/">
invitational workshop</weblink> to identify a research agenda for Exploratory Search and similar fields for the coming years.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Key Research Challenges</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Important Scenarios</st>
<p>

With the majority of research in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
Information Retrieval</link> community focusing on typical keyword search scenarios, one challenge for Exploratory Search is to further understand the scenarios of use for when keyword search is not sufficient. An example scenario, often used to motivate the research by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mspace.fm">
mSpace</weblink> states: if a user does not know much about classical music, how should they even begin to find a piece that they might like.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Designing New Interfaces</st>
<p>

With one of the motivations being to support users when keyword search is not enough, some research has focused on identifying alternative user interfaces and interaction models that support the user in different ways. An example is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/796657.xml">
faceted search</link> which presents diverse category-style options to the user, so that they can choose from a list instead of guess a possible keyword query.</p>
<p>

Many of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/14473878.xml">
interactive forms of search</link>, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/10715937.xml">
Faceted browser</link>s, are being considered for their support of exploratory search conditions.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Evaluating Exploratory Search Interfaces</st>
<p>

As the tasks and goals involved with Exploratory Search are largely undefined or unpredictable, it is very hard to evaluate systems with the measures often used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
Information Retrieval</link>. Accuracy was typically used to show that a user had found a correct answer, but when the user is trying to summarize a domain of information, the <it>correct</it> answer is near impossible to identify, if not entirely subjective (for example: possible hotels to stay in Paris). In exploration, it is also arguable that spending more time (where time efficiency is typically desirable) researching a topic shows that a system provides increased support for investigation. Finally, and perhaps most importantly, giving study participants a well specified task could immediately prevent them from exhibiting exploratory behavior.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Major Figures</st>

<p>

Key figures, including experts from both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/9586885.xml">
Information seeking</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/13516.xml">
Human Computer Interaction</link>, are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ryen White</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gary Marchionini</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nicholas Belkin</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

m.c. schraefel</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

White, R.W., Kules, B., Drucker, S.M., and schraefel, m.c. (2006). <it>Supporting Exploratory Search</it>, Introduction to Special Section of Communications of the ACM, Vol. 49, Issue 4, (2006), pp. 36-39.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Ryen W. White, Gary Marchionini, Gheorghe Muresan (2008). <it>Evaluating exploratory search systems: Introduction to special topic issue of information processing and management</it> Vol. 44, Issue 2, (2008), pp. 433-436</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
