<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:10:25[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<type  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105840188">
<header>
<title>Health insurance</title>
<id>490201</id>
<revision>
<id>244436731</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T20:10:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Anthon.Eff</username>
<id>653666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Health economics</category>
<category>Types of insurance</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The term <b>health insurance</b> is generally used to describe a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
insurance</link> that pays for medical expenses.  It is sometimes used more broadly to include insurance covering <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/8840098.xml">
disability</link> or <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/1160191.xml">
long-term nursing or custodial care</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 needs.  It may be provided through a government-sponsored <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/1550826.xml">
social insurance</link> program, or from private insurance companies. It may be purchased on a group basis (e.g., by a firm to cover its employees) or purchased by individual consumers. In each case, the covered groups or individuals pay premiums or taxes to help protect themselves from high or unexpected healthcare expenses. Similar benefits paying for medical expenses may also be provided through social welfare programs funded by the government. <p>

Health insurance works by estimating the overall risk of healthcare expenses and developing a routine finance structure (such as a monthly premium or annual tax) that will ensure that money is available to pay for the healthcare benefits specified in the insurance agreement. The benefit is administered by a central organization, most often either a government agency or a private or not-for-profit entity operating a health plan.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
History and evolution</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/16307870.xml">
History of insurance</link></it>
</indent>
The concept of health insurance was proposed in 1694 by Hugh the Elder Chamberlen from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/1646148.xml">
Peter Chamberlen</link> family. In the late 19th century, "accident insurance" began to be available, which operated much like modern <it>disability</it> insurance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.This payment model continued until the start of the 20th century in some jurisdictions (like California), where all laws regulating health insurance actually referred to disability insurance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  </p>
<p>

Accident insurance was first offered in the United States by the Franklin Health Assurance Company of Massachusetts.  This firm, founded in 1850, offered insurance against injuries arising from railroad and steamboat accidents.  Sixty organizations were offering accident insurance in the US by 1866, but the industry consolidated rapidly soon thereafter.  While there were earlier experiments, the origins of sickness coverage in the US effectively date from 1890.  The first employer-sponsored group disability policy was issued in 1911.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

Before the development of medical expense insurance, patients were expected to pay all other health care costs out of their own pockets, under what is known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/5370913.xml">
fee-for-service</link> business model. During the middle to late 20th century, traditional disability insurance evolved into modern health insurance programs. Today, most comprehensive private health insurance programs cover the cost of routine, preventive, and emergency health care procedures, and also most prescription drugs, but this was not always the case.</p>
<p>

Hospital and medical expense policies were introduced during the first half of the 20th century. During the 1920s, individual hospitals began offering services to individuals on a pre-paid basis, eventually leading to the development of Blue Cross organizations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  The predecessors of today's Health Maintenance Organizations (HMOs) originated beginning in 1929, through the 1930s and on during World War II.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
How it works</st>

<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/80381.xml">
Health</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
insurance</link> policy is a contract between an insurance company and an individual. The contract can be renewable annually or monthly. The type and amount of health care costs that will be covered by the health plan are specified in advance, in the member contract or Evidence of Coverage booklet.  The individual policy-holder's payment obligations may take several forms<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Premium:</b> The amount the policy-holder pays to the health plan each month to purchase health coverage.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Deductible:</b> The amount that the policy-holder must pay out-of-pocket before the health plan pays its share.  For example, a policy-holder might have to pay a $500 deductible per year, before any of their health care is covered by the health plan.  It may take several doctor's visits or prescription refills before the policy-holder reaches the deductible and the health plan starts to pay for care.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Copayment:</b> The amount that the policy-holder must pay out of pocket before the health plan pays for a particular visit or service.  For example, a policy-holder might pay a $45 copayment for a doctor's visit, or to obtain a prescription.  A copayment must be paid each time a particular service is obtained.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Coinsurance:</b> Instead of paying a fixed amount up front (a copayment), the policy-holder must pay a percentage of the total cost.  For example, the member might have to pay 20% of the cost of a surgery, while the health plan pays the other 80%.  Because there is no upper limit on coinsurance, the policy-holder can end up owing very little, or a significant amount, depending on the actual costs of the services they obtain.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Exclusions:</b> Not all services are covered.  The policy-holder is generally expected to pay the full cost of non-covered services out of their own pocket.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Coverage limits:</b> Some health plans only pay for health care up to a certain dollar amount.  The policy-holder may be expected to pay any charges in excess of the health plan's maximum payment for a specific service.  In addition, some plans have annual or lifetime coverage maximums.  In these cases, the health plan will stop payment when they reach the benefit maximum, and the policy-holder must pay all remaining costs.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Out-of-pocket maximums:</b> Similar to coverage limits, except that in this case, the member's payment obligation ends when they reach the out-of-pocket maximum, and the health plan pays all further covered costs.  Out-of-pocket maximums can be limited to a specific benefit category (such as prescription drugs) or can apply to all coverage provided during a specific benefit year.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Capitation:</b> An amount paid by an insurer to a health care provider, for which the provider agrees to treat all members of the insurer.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>In-Network Provider:</b>  A health care provider on a list of providers preselected by the insurer.   The insurer will offer discounted coinsurance or copayments, or additional benefits, to a plan member to see an in-network provider.  Generally, providers in network are providers who have a contract with the insurer to accept rates further discounted from the "usual and customary" charges the insurer pays to out-of-network providers.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Prescription drug plans are a form of insurance offered through some employer benefit plans in the US, where the patient pays a copayment and the prescription drug insurance part or all of the balance for drugs covered in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/6744844.xml">
formulary</link> of the plan.</p>
<p>

Some, if not most, health care providers in the United States will agree to bill the insurance company if patients are willing to sign an agreement that they will be responsible for the amount that the insurance company doesn't pay.  The insurance company pays out of network providers according to "reasonable and customary" charges, which may be less than the provider's usual fee.  The provider may also have a separate contract with the insurer to accept what amounts to a discounted rate or capitation to the provider's standard charges.  It generally costs the patient less to use an in-network provider.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Health plan vs. health insurance</st>
<p>

Historically, HMOs tended to use the term "health plan", while commercial insurance companies used the term "health insurance".  A health plan can also refer to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/259338.xml">
subscription</link>-based medical care arrangement offered through health maintenance organization, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/59097.xml">
HMO</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/1184035.xml">
PPO</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/7146035.xml">
POS plan</link>. These plans are similar to pre-paid dental, pre-paid legal, and pre-paid vision plans. Pre-paid health plans typically pay for a fixed number of services (for instance, $300 in preventive care, a certain number of days of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/275509.xml">
hospice</link> care or care in a skilled nursing facility, a fixed number of home health visits, a fixed number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/2231005.xml">
spinal manipulation</link> charges, etc.) The services offered are usually at the discretion of a <link>
utilization review</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/55300.xml">
nurse</link> who is often contracted through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/1183870.xml">
managed care</link> entity providing the subscription health plan. This determination may be made either prior to or after hospital admission (concurrent utilization review).</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Comprehensive vs. scheduled</st>
<p>

Comprehensive health insurance pays a percentage (may be 100, 90, 80, 70, 60, 50, percent) of the cost of hospital and physician charges after a deductible (usually applies to hospital charges) or a co-pay (usually applies to physician charges, but may apply to some hospital services) is met by the insured. These plans are generally expensive because of the high potential benefit payout &mdash; $1,000,000 to 5,000,000 is common &mdash; and because of the vast array of covered benefits.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

Scheduled health insurance plans are not meant to replace a traditional comprehensive health insurance plans and are more of a basic policy providing access to day-to-day health care such as going to the doctor or getting a prescription drug. In recent years, these plans have taken the name mini-med plans or association plans. These plans may provide benefits for hospitalization and surgical, but these benefits will be limited. Scheduled plans are not meant to be effective for catastrophic events. These plans cost much less then comprehensive health insurance. They generally pay limited benefits amounts directly to the service provider, and payments are based upon the plan's "schedule of benefits". Annual benefits maximums for a typical scheduled health insurance plan may range from $1,000 to $25,000.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss1>
<st>
Inherent problems with insurance</st>
<p>

Insurance systems must typically deal with two inherent challenges: adverse selection, which affects any voluntary system, and ex-post moral hazard, which affects any insurance system in which a third party bears major responsibility for payment, whether that is an employer or the government.  Some national systems with compulsory insurance utilize systems such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/15336425.xml">
risk equalization</link> and <link>
community rating</link> to overcome these inherent problems.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Adverse selection</st>
<p>

Insurance companies use the term "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/309452.xml">
adverse selection</link>" to describe the tendency for only those who will benefit from insurance to buy it.  Specifically when talking about health insurance, unhealthy people are more likely to purchase health insurance because they anticipate large medical bills.  On the other side, people who consider themselves to be reasonably healthy may decide that medical insurance is an unnecessary expense; if they see the doctor once a year and it costs $250, that's much better than making monthly insurance payments of $40. (example figures).</p>
<p>

The fundamental concept of insurance is that it balances costs across a large, random sample of individuals (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/2875461.xml">
risk pool</link>). For instance, an insurance company has a pool of 1000 randomly selected subscribers, each paying $100 per month.  One person becomes very ill while the others stay healthy, allowing the insurance company to use the money paid by the healthy people to pay for the treatment costs of the sick person. However, when the pool is self-selecting rather than random, as is the case with individuals seeking to purchase health insurance directly, adverse selection is a greater concern.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>  A disproportionate share of health care spending is attributable to individuals with high health care costs.  In the US the 1% of the population with the highest spending accounted for 27% of aggregate health care spending in 1996.  The highest-spending 5% of the population accounted for more than half of all spending.  These patterns were stable through the 1970s and 1980s, and some data suggest that they may have been typical of the mid-to-early 20th century as well.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>  A few individuals have extremely high medical expenses, in extreme cases totaling a half million dollars or more.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>  Adverse selection could leave an insurance company with primarily sick subscribers and no way to balance out the cost of their medical expenses with a large number of healthy subscribers.</p>
<p>

Because of adverse selection, insurance companies employ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/6691129.xml">
medical underwriting</link>, using a patient's medical history to screen out those whose pre-existing medical conditions pose too great a risk for the risk pool. Before buying health insurance, a person typically fills out a comprehensive medical history form that asks whether the person smokes, how much the person weighs, whether the person has been treated for any of a long list of diseases and so on. In general, those who present large financial burdens are denied coverage or charged high premiums to compensate.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> One large US industry survey found that roughly 13 percent of applicants for comprehensive, individually purchased health insurance who went through the medical underwriting in 2004 were denied coverage. Declination rates increased significantly with age, rising from 5 percent for individuals 18 and under to just under a third for individuals aged 60 to 64.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> Among those who were offered coverage, the study found that 76% received offers at standard premium rates, and 22% were offered higher rates.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> On the other side, applicants can get discounts if they do not smoke and are healthy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Moral hazard</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/175590.xml">
Moral hazard</link></it>
</indent>
Moral hazard occurs when an insurer and a consumer enter into a contract under symmetric information, but one party takes action, not taken into account in the contract, which changes the value of the insurance. A common example of moral hazard is third-party payment&mdash;when the parties involved in making a decision are not responsible for bearing costs arising from the decision. An example is where doctors and insured patients agree to extra tests which may or may not be necessary. Doctors benefit by avoiding possible malpractice suits, and patients benefit by gaining increased certainty of their medical condition. The cost of these extra tests is borne by the insurance company, which may have had little say in the decision. Co-payments, deductibles, and less generous insurance for services with more elastic demand attempt to combat moral hazard, as they hold the consumer responsible.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other factors affecting insurance prices</st>
<p>

A recent study by PriceWaterhouseCoopers examining the drivers of rising health care costs in the US pointed to increased utilization created by increased consumer demand, new treatments, and more intensive diagnostic testing, as the most significant driver.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> People in developed countries are living longer. The population of those countries is aging, and a larger group of senior citizens requires more intensive medical care than a young healthier population. Advances in medicine and medical technology can also increase the cost of medical treatment. Lifestyle-related factors can increase utilization and therefore insurance prices, such as: increases in obesity caused by insufficient <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/189037.xml">
exercise</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/64083.xml">
unhealthy food choices</link>; excessive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/1014.xml">
alcohol</link> use, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/73298.xml">
smoking</link>, and use of street <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/3137601.xml">
drugs</link>. Other factors noted by the PWC study included the movement to broader-access plans, higher-priced technologies, and cost-shifting from Medicaid and the uninsured to private payers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health insurance in Australia</st>

<p>

The public health system is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/58499.xml">
Medicare</link>.  It ensures free universal access to hospital treatment and subsidised out-of-hospital medical treatment.  It is funded by a 1.5% tax levy.  </p>
<p>

The private health system is funded by a number of private health insurance organisations.  The largest of these is <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/7002229.xml">
Medibank Private</link></company>
, which is government-owned, but operates as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/204768.xml">
government business enterprise</link> under the same regulatory regime as all other registered private health funds.  The <party wordnetid="108256968" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/1051313.xml">
Coalition</link></party>
 <chancellor wordnetid="109906986" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/4689709.xml">
Howard</link></person>
</chancellor>
 government had announced that Medibank would be privatised if it won the <election wordnetid="100181781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/1056082.xml">
2007 election</link></election>
, however they were defeated by the <party wordnetid="108256968" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/1495.xml">
Australian Labor Party</link></party>
 under <chancellor wordnetid="109906986" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/380965.xml">
Kevin Rudd</link></chancellor>
 which had already pledged that it would remain in government ownership.</p>
<p>

Some private health insurers are 'for profit' enterprises, and some are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
non-profit organization</link>s such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/8715497.xml">
HCF Health Insurance</link></company>
.   Some have membership restricted to particular groups, but the majority have open membership.</p>
<p>

Most aspects of private health insurance in Australia are regulated by the <it>Private Health Insurance Act 2007</it>.</p>
<p>

The private health system in Australia operates on a "community rating" basis, whereby premiums do not vary solely because of a person's previous medical history, current state of health, or (generally speaking) their age (but see Lifetime Health Cover below).  Balancing this are waiting periods, in particular for pre-existing conditions (usually referred to within the industry as PEA, which stands for "pre-existing ailment").  Funds are entitled to impose a waiting period of up to 12 months on benefits for any medical condition the signs and symptoms of which existed during the six months ending on the day the person first took out insurance.  They are also entitled to impose a 12-month waiting period for benefits for treatment relating to an obstetric condition, and a 2-month waiting period for all other benefits when a person first takes out private insurance.  Funds have the discretion to reduce or remove such waiting periods in individual cases.  They are also free not to impose them to begin with, but this would place such a fund at risk of "adverse selection", attracting a disproportionate number of members from other funds, or from the pool of intending members who might otherwise have joined other funds.  It would also attract people with existing medical conditions, who might not otherwise have taken out insurance at all because of the denial of benefits for 12 months due to the PEA Rule.  The benefits paid out for these conditions would create pressure on premiums for all the fund's members, causing some to drop their membership, which would lead to further rises, and a vicious cycle would ensue.  </p>
<p>

There are a number of other matters about which funds are not permitted to discriminate between members in terms of premiums, benefits or membership - these include racial origin, religion, sex, sexual orientation, nature of employment, and leisure activities.  Premiums for a fund's product that is sold in more than one state can vary from state to state, but not within the same state.  </p>
<p>

The Australian government has introduced a number of incentives to encourage adults to take out private hospital insurance.  These include:  </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Lifetime Health Cover</b>:  If a person has not taken out private hospital cover by the 1st July after their 30th birthday, then when (and if) they do so after this time, their premiums must include a loading of 2% per annum.  Thus, a person taking out private cover for the first time at age 40 will pay a 20 per cent loading.  The loading continues for 10 years.  The loading applies only to premiums for hospital cover, not to ancillary (extras) cover.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Medicare Levy Surcharge</b>: People whose taxable income is greater than a specified amount (currently $50,000 for singles and $100,000 for families) and who do not have an adequate level of private hospital cover must pay a 1% surcharge on top of the standard 1.5% Medicare Levy.  The rationale is that if the people in this income group are forced to pay more money one way or another, most would choose to purchase hospital insurance with it, with the possibility of a benefit in the event that they need private hospital treatment - rather than pay it in the form of extra tax as well as having to meet their own private hospital costs. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The Australian government announced in May 2008 that it proposes to increase the thresholds, to $100,000 for singles and $150,000 for families.  These changes require legislative approval.   A bill to change the law has been introduced but has not yet been passed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> There have been criticisms that this proposed change will cause many people to drop their private health insurance, causing a further burden on the public hospital system, and a rise in premiums for those who stay with the private system.  Other commentators believe the effect will be minimal.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Private Health Insurance Rebate</b>:  The government subsidises the premiums for all private health insurance cover, including hospital and ancillary (extras), by 30%, 35% or 40%.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health insurance in Canada</st>

<p>

Most health insurance in Canada is administered by each province, under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/369449.xml">
Canada Health Act</link>, which requires all people to have free access to basic health services.  Collectively, the public provincial health insurance systems in Canada are frequently referred to as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/58354.xml">
 Medicare</link>.  Private health insurance is allowed, but the provincial governments allow it only for services that the public health plans do not cover; for example, semi-private or private rooms in hospitals and prescription drug plans. Canadians are free to use private insurance for elective medical services such as laser vision correction surgery, cosmetic surgery, and other non-basic medical procedures.  Some 65% of Canadians have some form of supplementary private health insurance; many of them receive it through their employers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>  Private-sector services not paid for by the government account for nearly 30 percent of total health care spending.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> </p>
<p>

In 2005, the Supreme Court of Quebec ruled, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/2039116.xml">
Chaoulli v. Quebec</link>, that the province's prohibition on private insurance for health care already insured by the provincial plan could constitute an infringement of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/468580.xml">
right to life</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../094/5001094.xml">
security</link> if there were long wait times for treatment as happened in this case. Certain other provinces have legislation which financially discourages but does not forbid private health insurance in areas covered by the public plans. The ruling has not changed the overall pattern of health insurance across Canada but has spurred on attempts to tackle the core issues of supply and demand and the impact of wait times.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref> </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health insurance in the Netherlands</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/15297282.xml">
Health care in the Netherlands</link></it>
</indent>

In 2006, a new system of health insurance came into force in the Netherlands. This new system avoids the two pitfalls of adverse selection and moral hazard associated with traditional forms of health insurance by using a combination of regulation and an insurance <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/15282066.xml">
equalization pool</link>. Moral hazard is avoided by mandating that insurance companies provide at least one policy which meets a government set minimum standard level of coverage, and all adult residents are obliged by law to purchase this coverage from an insurance company of their choice. All insurance companies receive funds from the equalization pool to help cover the cost of this government-mandated coverage. This pool is run by a regulator which collects salary-based contributions from employers, which make up about 50% of all health care funding, and funding from the government to cover people who cannot afford health care, which makes up an additional 5%.</p>
<p>

The remaining 45% of health care funding comes from insurance premiums paid by the public, for which companies compete on price, though the variation between the various competing insurers is only about 5%. However, insurance companies are free to sell additional policies to provide coverage beyond the national minimum. These policies do not receive funding from the equalization pool, but cover additional treatments, such as dental procedures and physiotherapy, which are not paid for by the mandatory policy.</p>
<p>

Funding from the equalization pool is distributed to insurance companies for each person they insure under the required policy. However, high-risk individuals get more from the pool, and low-income persons and children under 18 have their insurance paid for entirely. Because of this, insurance companies no longer find insuring high risk individuals an unappealing proposition, avoiding the potential problem of adverse selection.</p>
<p>

Insurance companies are not allowed to have co-payments, caps, or deductibles, or to deny coverage to any person applying for a policy, or to charge anything other than their nationally set and published standard premiums. Therefore, every person buying insurance will pay the same price as everyone else buying the same policy, and every person will get at least the minimum level of coverage.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health insurance in the United Kingdom</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/16462572.xml">
National Health Service</link></it>
</indent>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1048927.xml">
UK</link>'s National Health Service (NHS) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/325717.xml">
publicly funded healthcare</link> system that provides coverage to everyone normally resident in the UK. It is not strictly insurance system because (a) there are no premiums collected, (b) costs are not charged at the patient level and (c) costs are not pre-paid from a pool. However, it does achieve the main aim of insurance which is to spread financial risk arising from ill-health. The costs of running the NHS (est. £104 billion in 2007-8)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> are met directly from general taxation.</p>
<p>

Private health care has continued parallel to the NHS, paid for largely by private insurance, but it is used by less than 8% of the population, and generally as a top-up to NHS services. </p>
<p>

The NHS provides the majority of health care in the UK, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/532491.xml">
primary care</link>,  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/18994221.xml">
in-patient care</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/3118704.xml">
long-term health care</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/56153.xml">
ophthalmology</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/8005.xml">
dentistry</link>.   Recently the private sector has been increasingly used to increase NHS capacity despite a large proportion of the British public opposing such involvement.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref>. According to the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/33583.xml">
World Health Organization</link></organization>
, government funding covered 86% of overall health care expenditures in the UK as of 2004, with private expenditures covering the remaining 14%.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health insurance in the United States</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main articles: <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/15343730.xml">
Health insurance in the United States</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
&#32;and&#32;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/1147240.xml">
Health care in the United States</link></it>
</indent>

The US <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/48852.xml">
market-based</link> health care system relies heavily on private and not-for-profit health insurance, which is the primary source of coverage for most Americans. According to the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/57070.xml">
United States Census Bureau</link></agency>
, approximately 84% of Americans have health insurance; some 60% obtain it through an employer, while about 9% purchase it directly. Various government agencies provide coverage to about 27% of Americans (there is some overlap in these figures).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> </p>
<p>

Public programs provide the primary source of coverage for most seniors and for low-income children and families who meet certain eligibility requirements. The primary public programs are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/58353.xml">
Medicare</link>, a federal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/1550826.xml">
social insurance</link> program for seniors and certain disabled individuals, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/55794.xml">
Medicaid</link>, funded jointly by the federal government and states but administered at the state level, which covers certain very low income children and their families, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/635422.xml">
SCHIP</link>, also a federal-state partnership that serves certain children and families who do not qualify for Medicaid but who cannot afford private coverage. Other public programs include military health benefits provided through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/2996627.xml">
TRICARE</link> and the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<medical_building wordnetid="103739518" confidence="0.8">
<hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/832283.xml">
Veterans Health Administration</link></hospital>
</medical_building>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 and benefits provided through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/1707982.xml">
Indian Health Service</link>.  Some states have additional programs for low-income individuals.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref></p>
<p>

In 2006, there were 47 million people in the United States (16% of the population) who were without health insurance for at least part of that year.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> About 37% of the uninsured live in households with an income over $50,000.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> </p>
<p>

In 2004, US health insurers directly employed almost 470,000 people at an average salary of $61,409.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref>  (As of the fourth quarter of 2007, the total US labor force stood at 153.6 million, of whom 146.3 million were employed.  Employment related to all forms of insurance totaled 2.3 million.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref> Mean annual earnings for full-time civilian workers as of June 2006 were $41,231; median earnings were $33,634.)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref> The insurance industry also represents a significant lobbying group in the US.  For the 2007-2008 election cycle insurance was the 8th among industries in political contributions to members of Congress, giving $13,411,561, of which 56% was given to Democrats (lawyers and law firms were number 1, giving $59,205,616, of which 80% went to Democrats). The top recipient of insurance industry contributions was Senator Christopher Dodd (D-CT).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref>  The leading contributor from the insurance industry &mdash; as measured by total political contributions &mdash; was AFLAC, Inc., which contributed $907,150 in 2007.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/13777254.xml">
Injury cover</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/4223273.xml">
Economic capital</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/22105.xml">
Government ownership</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/265753.xml">
Health economics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/59097.xml">
Health maintenance organization</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/13250.xml">
Healthcare reform</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/8519821.xml">
Self-funded health care</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/253845.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22insurance%22])">
List of insurance topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/7260701.xml">
Physicians for a National Health Program</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/463734.xml">
Public health</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/1678483.xml">
Social health insurance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<plan wordnetid="105898568" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/27691.xml">
Social security</link></plan>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/3332250.xml">
Social welfare</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/261925.xml">
Health care</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/8695082.xml">
Health care politics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/15475369.xml">
Philosophy of Healthcare</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes and references</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kff.org/insurance/upload/How-Private-Insurance-Works-A-Primer-Report.pdf">
How Private Insurance Works: A Primer</weblink> by Gary Claxton, Institution for Health Care Research and Policy, Georgetown University, on behalf of the Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://health.howstuffworks.com/health-insurance1.htm">
Howstuffworks: How Health Insurance Works</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ca.encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761576408_8/Health_Insurance.html#s49">
Encarta: Health Insurance</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
See California Insurance Code Section 106 (defining disability insurance).<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cacodes/ins/100-124.5.html">
http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cacodes/ins/100-124.5.html</weblink>  In 2001, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/425922.xml">
California Legislature</link> added subdivision (b), which defines "health insurance" as "an individual or group disability insurance policy that provides coverage for hospital, medical, or surgical benefits."</entry>
<entry id="4">
Fundamentals of Health Insurance: Part A, Health Insurance Association of America, 1997, ISBN 1-879143-36-4</entry>
<entry id="5">
Thomas P. O'Hare, "Individual Medical Expense Insurance," The American College, 2000, page 7, ISBN 1-57996-025-1</entry>
<entry id="6">
Managed Care: Integrating the Delivery and Financing of Health Care - Part A, Health Insurance Association of America, 1995, page 9 ISBN 1-879143-26-1</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahrq.gov/consumer/insuranceqa/">
AHRQ: "Questions and Answers About Health Insurance: A Consumer Guide"</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.healthinsurancequotesamerica.com/comprehensivevsscheduledplans.html">
"Comprehensive Health Insurance vs. Scheduled Health Insurance"</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cahi.org/article.asp?id=415">
"Mini Medical Plans On The Move"</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
"Wading Through Medical Insurance Pools: A Primer," <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/3697300.xml">
American Academy of Actuaries</link></organization>
 September 2006 http://www.actuary.org/pdf/health/pools_sep06.pdf</entry>
<entry id="11">
Marc L. Berk and Alan C. Monheit, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.healthaffairs.org/cgi/content/abstract/20/2/9">
"The Concentration Of Health Care Expenditures, Revisited"</weblink>, <it>Health Affairs</it>, Volume 20, Number 2, March/April 2001. Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/11310.xml">
February 27</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Marc L. Berk and Alan C. Monheit, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.healthaffairs.org/cgi/content/abstract/11/4/145">
"Datawatch: The Concentration Of Health Expenditures: An Update"</weblink>, <it>Health Affairs</it>, Winter 1992. Accessed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/11310.xml">
February 27</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soa.org/research/health/research-medical-large-claims-experience-study.aspx">
"1997–1999 Group Medical Insurance Database and Analysis Report,"</weblink> <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/337198.xml">
Society of Actuaries</link></organization>
, 2004</entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.actuary.org/pdf/health/bottom_risk_0501.pdf">
"The Bottom Line on Risk Classification in Individually Purchased Voluntary Medical Expense Insurance,"</weblink> <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/3697300.xml">
American Academy of Actuaries</link></organization>
, February 1999</entry>
<entry id="15">
Teresa Chovan, Hannah Yoo and Tom Wildsmith,<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahipresearch.org/pdfs/Individual_Insurance_Survey_Report8-26-2005.pdf">
"Individual Health Insurance: A Comprehensive Survey of Affordability, Access, and Benefits"</weblink> <link>
America’s Health Insurance Plans</link>, August 2005.</entry>
<entry id="17">
Task Force on Genetic Testing in Health Insurance,<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.actuary.org/pdf/health/risk.pdf">
"Risk Classification in Individually Purchased Voluntary Medical Expense Insurance,"</weblink> <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/3697300.xml">
American Academy of Actuaries</link></organization>
, February 1999</entry>
<entry id="16">
Teresa Chovan, Hannah Yoo and Tom Wildsmith,<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahipresearch.org/pdfs/Individual_Insurance_Survey_Report8-26-2005.pdf">
Individual Health Insurance: A Comprehensive Survey of Affordability, Access, and Benefits</weblink>, <link>
America’s Health Insurance Plans</link>, Table 7, page 11 (Note that the remainder, roughly 2%, received other types of offers, such as policies with condition waivers).</entry>
<entry id="19">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.australianunity.com.au/au/hins/Misc/MedicareSurcharge.asp#">
http://www.australianunity.com.au/au/hins/Misc/MedicareSurcharge.asp#</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://parlinfoweb.aph.gov.au/piweb/Repository/Legis/Bills/Linked/27050802.pdf">
http://parlinfoweb.aph.gov.au/piweb/Repository/Legis/Bills/Linked/27050802.pdf</weblink></entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahipbelieves.com/media/The%20Factors%20Fueling%20Rising%20Healthcare%20Costs.pdf">
The Factors Fueling Rising Healthcare Costs 2006</weblink>, PriceWaterhouseCoopers for America's Health Insurance Plans, 2006, accessed 2007-10-08</entry>
<entry id="21">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(2004) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=oUM39nDp2s4C&amp;dq=employer+provided+private+health+insurance+in+canada">
Private Health Insurance in OECD Countries</weblink>.&#32;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/493793.xml">
OECD</link> Health Project. Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-19</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/08/12/2332647.htm">
http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/08/12/2332647.htm</weblink></entry>
<entry id="23">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hadorn, D.&#32;(2005-08-02).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cmaj.ca/cgi/content/full/173/3/271?etoc">
The Chaoulli challenge: getting a grip on waiting lists</weblink>". <it>Canadian Medical Association Journal</it>&#32;<b>173</b>: 271. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1503%2Fcmaj.050812">
10.1503/cmaj.050812</weblink>. PMID 16076823.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="22">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://secure.cihi.ca/cihiweb/dispPage.jsp?cw_page=PG_876_E&amp;cw_topic=876&amp;cw_rel=AR_31_E">
National Health Expenditure Trends, 1975-2007</weblink>".&#32;  Canadian Institute for Health Information&#32;(2007-11-13).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-11-19</link>.</entry>
<entry id="25">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bma.org.uk/ap.nsf/AttachmentsByTitle/PDFnhssystreform2007/$FILE/48751Surveynhsreform.pdf">
Survey of the general public's views on NHS system reform in England</weblink>"&#32;(2007-06-01).</entry>
<entry id="24">
HM Treasury&#32;(2007-03-21).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/media/3/4/bud07_completereport_1757.pdf">
Budget 2007</weblink>"&#32;21.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-05-11</link>.</entry>
<entry id="27">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/prod/2007pubs/p60-233.pdf">
"Income, Poverty, and Health Insurance Coverage in the United States: 2006."</weblink> U.S. Census Bureau. Issued August 2007.</entry>
<entry id="26">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/whosis/database/core/core_select.cfm">
World Health Organization Statistical Information System: Core Health Indicators</weblink></entry>
<entry id="29">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahipresearch.org/PDFs/StateData/StateDataFullReport.pdf">
"Health Insurance: Overview and Economic Impact in the States,"</weblink> <link>
America’s Health Insurance Plans</link>, November 2007</entry>
<entry id="28">
U.S. Census Bureau,<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/hhes/www/hlthins/hlthinstypes.html">
"CPS Health Insurance Definitions"</weblink></entry>
<entry id="31">
U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics,<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bls.gov/ncs/ocs/sp/ncbl0910.pdf">
"National Compensation Survey: Occupational Wages in the United States, June 2006,"</weblink> June 2007</entry>
<entry id="30">
U.S. <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<index wordnetid="106639674" confidence="0.8">
<fact wordnetid="106636259" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/72528.xml">
Bureau of Labor Statistics</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</fact>
</index>
</information>
</message>
</work>
,<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bls.gov/news.release/pdf/empsit.pdf">
"THE EMPLOYMENT SITUATION: JANUARY 2008,"</weblink> February 1, 2008</entry>
<entry id="32">
The Center for Responsive Politics, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opensecrets.org/industries/mems.asp">
Top Industries Giving to Members of Congress: 2008 Cycle</weblink>, accessed May 6th, 2008</entry>
<entry id="33">
Health Insurance.org, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.health-insurance.org/health-insurance-lobbyists">
"Health Care and Insurance Dominate the Washington Lobby,"</weblink> April 2008</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Navigating your health benefits for dummies. Charles M Cutler MD  Tracey A Baker CFP (c)2006 ISBN-13:978-0-470-08354-3</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</type>
</article>
