<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:28:21[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Services menu</title>
<id>4903417</id>
<revision>
<id>224730439</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-10T04:22:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>TMC1221</username>
<id>27322</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Mac OS X user interface</category>
<category>NeXT</category>
<category>GNUstep</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Services menu</b> (or simply <b>Services</b>) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/45249.xml">
user interface</link> element in a computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>. The services are programs that accept input from the user selection, process it, and optionally put the result back in the clipboard. The concept originated in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/40642.xml">
NeXTSTEP</link> operating system, from which it was carried over into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link> and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/55891.xml">
GNUstep</link></software>
. Similar features can be emulated on other operating systems.
<sec>
<st>
 Mac OS X </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/856.xml">
Apple</link> advertises the Services menu in connection with other features of its operating system. For example, it's possible to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../156/1274156.xml">
desktop search</link> for a piece of text by selecting it with the mouse and using the service from <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/878210.xml">
Spotlight</link></software>
. Other central services are <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/3385603.xml">
Grab</link></software>
 for taking screenshots, and the system <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/605869.xml">
spell checker</link>. The concept is similar to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
GUI</link> equivalent of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../117/1236117.xml">
Unix pipe</link>, allowing arbitrary data to be processed and passed between programs.</p>
<p>

Services can be implemented as <b>application services</b>, which expose a portion of the functionality of an application to operate on selected data, usually without displaying an interface, or they may be <b>standalone services</b> which are small utilities to manipulate data, such as transforming the case of selected text or cropping an image to use as an icon. Their simple, one-purpose nature and not requiring a GUI to be designed makes writing a standalone services a popular beginner's Mac OS X programming project</p>
<p>

Since many applications install their entries without asking the user, the OS X services menu tends to clog up with dozens of entries quickly. Most users only will ever use a small subset of the possible options, therefore cutting down and customizing the menu makes it both faster and more pleasant to use. Third party software is required to do this, however.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Emulation </st>

<p>

From the point of view of software, the Services menu is a means of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/152106.xml">
inter-process communication</link>. To the user, it is an interface for executing actions on selected data. The emulation of the Services menu is based on the fact that there are several ways this can be achieved in an operating system. Even in Mac OS X, there is an alternative system called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/7450.xml">
context menu</link> handler, which is carried over from <link>
classic Mac OS</link>.</p>
<p>

In the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/34147.xml">
X Window System</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
, any data selected in an application is available to all other programs. Thus the Services menu can be an application which retrieves the current selection, and lets the user choose an action. Missing is the part about returning the processed data back to the originating application. Instead, the service can open a new window to show the results.</p>
<p>

Alternatively, the service could replace the current cut buffer with the results of the operation, leaving the user only to perform a paste (since different toolkits implement copy/select and paste commands differently, and probably not under external program control).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://developer.apple.com/documentation/Cocoa/Conceptual/SysServices/">
Introduction to System Services</weblink> at Apple Developer Connection</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://iki.fi/Tuukka/software/services">
Services menu emulation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.manytricks.com/servicescrubber/">
Service Scrubber</weblink> OS X utility for customizing the services menu</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wafflesoftware.net/thisservice/">
ThisService</weblink> OS X utility that can create a service from either an <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../392/88392.xml">
AppleScript</link></language>
 or <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/28938.xml">
Shell script</link></language>
</entry>
</list>



</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
