<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:22:41[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Medical education in Hong Kong</title>
<id>4905614</id>
<revision>
<id>177423616</id>
<timestamp>2007-12-12T13:16:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Medical education in Hong Kong</category>
<category>Education in Hong Kong</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Medical education in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/13404.xml">
Hong Kong</link></country>
</b> is concerned with both the basic training of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../156/2509156.xml">
medical practitioner</link>s and further post-graduate training.
<sec>
<st>
Medical school</st>
<p>

Undergraduate-entry program typically last five years, and permit entry from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/554992.xml">
secondary school</link> matriculation. Entry to the two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medical</link> faculties of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/13404.xml">
Hong Kong</link></country>
 requires completion of the HKALE or its equivalent (e.g GCE "A" Levels). </p>
<p>

Prospective medical students may apply through the JUPAS (Joint University Programmes Admission System) exercise that takes place yearly. Increasingly, form six students who have done exceptionally well in their HKCEE level examination will be granted entry. The undergraduate intake is about 125 in each university (HKU and CUHK). Mature students or students who already possess a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/2463359.xml">
undergraduate degree</link> may apply to each individual university, and they will join the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/217289.xml">
undergraduate</link> class.</p>
<p>

In early years, theoretical domains of study predominate, with increasing clinical focus during the program. However, early clinical exposure — in which students commence clinical skills from very early in the course, concurrently with theoretical study — is a component of many degrees, most notably the graduate medical programs. Hong Kong University there has been a move away from the more traditional methods of teaching with a shift towards the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/362386.xml">
Problem Based Learning</link> (PBL) pedagogy.  </p>
<p>

After graduation medical students enter paid employment, but they are still a year away from obtaining full registration and obtaining their degrees During this year trainees are legally only able to work in certain highly supervised jobs (designated F1 jobs) and cannot legally practise independently.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Internship</st>
<p>

Recently qualified medical practitioners must successfully undertake and complete at least one year of supervised practice, generally known as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/298221.xml">
internship</link>. Internship is undertaken in hospital positions accredited for this purpose.</p>
<p>

A new medical graduate's first job will be as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/3551018.xml">
Pre-registration house officer</link> (PRHO), during which they will complete the first year of <it>Foundation Training</it> (F1 Year).  Although by this time, they have graduated from the university, it is the responsibility of the medical school they attended to supervise this year until they are fully registered with the Hong Kong  Medical Council.  Therefore, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/3551018.xml">
Pre-registration house officer</link> year forms the final year of medical school.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Residency</st>

<p>

Upon successful conclusion of the intern year, doctors qualify for a full registration in the Medical Board  and are licensed to engage in independent medical practice.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Specialist training</st>
<p>

A trainee has to undergo six years of supervised specialist training and pass in the final examinations held by <link>
Hong Kong Academy of Medicine</link>. Passing the final examination is a prerequisite to Fellowship of the Academy.</p>
<p>

At the same time as working in hospitals, registrars also prepare for examinations for admission into specialist medical colleges.</p>
<p>

Those successful in completing the requirements of their college program become a fellow of the academy and "specialists" in the case of most areas of medicine (and typically work in specialist private practice and/or as a "consultant" in a hospital); an exception are fellows of the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<college wordnetid="108278169" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/4127096.xml">
Royal Australian College of General Practitioners</link></administration>
</group>
</college>
</association>
</social_group>
</body>
, who are <it>general practitioners</it>, not specialists.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/3731638.xml">
Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine</link></institution>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/4905404.xml">
Faculties of Medicines in Hong Kong</link></institution>
</educational_institution>
</school>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hku.hk/facmed/index.html">
School of Medicine, Hong Kong University</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hkam.org.hk/">
Hong Kong Academy of Medicine</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
