<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:23:26[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Simmcast</title>
<id>4931027</id>
<revision>
<id>225844560</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-15T17:43:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Marinho.barcellos</username>
<id>7481143</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Java platform protocol simulation software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Simmcast</b> is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/22757.xml">
object-oriented</link> simulation <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/1173145.xml">
framework</link> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/83235.xml">
protocol</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/5652.xml">
network</link> research. Its design is focused towards simplicity and extensibility. Simmcast has specific support for group communication: allowing a spectrum of experiments that range from evaluation of abstract group communication models to simulation of more detailed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/738077.xml">
unicast</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/20407.xml">
multicast</link> protocol behavior. It is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/81193.xml">
cross-platform</link> and written in <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
.<p>

Simmcast employs a process-based discrete-event model on which building blocks are combined and extended in order to create new simulation environments. Network and protocol parameters are given in terms of numeric distributions (fixed or probabilistic), which can be replaced without recompilation. This extensive use of numeric distributions combined to the extendible <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/1173145.xml">
framework</link> structure allow an abstract experiment to evolve into a detailed one by progressively increasing the level of detail and sources of non-determinism of the constituting blocks.</p>
<p>

The software results from a research effort which begun in 2001, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/3965914.xml">
Unisinos</link> University, Brazil. The corresponding research project was led by Prof. Marinho P. Barcellos, with funding from Brazilian Research Agencies <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/2701365.xml">
CNPq</link> and FAPERGS. Many people have contributed to the project, including André Detsch, Lucas A. Seewald, Giovani Facchini, Guilherme B. Bedin, Rosana Casais, Rodolfo S. Antunes, and Ruthiano S. Munaretti. In particular, Simmcast has benefited from Hisham H. Muhammad's ideas of frameworks and extensibility, as well as its realization into a well-documented, full-fledged protocol simulation framework.</p>

<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/4931165.xml">
Viewcast</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simmcast.org/">
Official site of simmcast and viewcast (http://simmcast.org/)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://p2p-sec.org/marinho">
Prof. Marinho P. Barcellos (Principal Investigator, contacting author)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
