<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:11:17[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Information overload</title>
<id>495664</id>
<revision>
<id>242313970</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T19:23:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Zazaban</username>
<id>448402</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Library and information science</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from September 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Information overload</b> refers to excess amounts of information being provided, making the processing and absorbing tasks very difficult for the individual because we cannot see the validity behind the information (Yang, 2003 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>).
As the world moves into a new era of globalization, an increasing number of people are logging onto the internet to conduct their own research (Internet World Stats.com, 2008)<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.internetworldstats.com/stats.htm">
http://www.internetworldstats.com/stats.htm</weblink><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> and are given the ability to produce as well as consume the data accessed on an increasing number of websites (Bonfield, 2007 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>; Russo &amp; Watkins, 2005<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>). As of February 2007 there were over 108 million distinct websites and increasing (Boutell, 2007)<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boutell.com">
http://www.boutell.com</weblink><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Users’ are now classified as active users (Benbunan-Fich &amp; Koufaris, 2008<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>) because more people in society are participating in the Digital and Information Age (Jones, 1993 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>). More and more people are considered to be active writers and viewers because of their participation (Jenkins, 2006 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>). This flow has created a new life where we are now dependant on access to information (Cheng &amp; Vassileva, 2006<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> ; Baxter, 2008<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>). Therefore we see an information overload from the access to so much information, almost instataneously, without knowing the validity of the content and the risk of misinformation (Flew, 2008<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>; Graham, 1999<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>).<p>

People nowadays are logging in to the net not only to surf or browse but to donate or share a piece of information.  According to Sohora Jha, journalists are using the web to conduct their research, getting information regarding interviewing sources and press releases, updating news online, and thus it shows the gradual shifts in attitudes because of the rapid increase in the Internet.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>
<p>

As a result, there is a downfall or a negative impact within this issue (Centaur Communications Limited, 2006 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>). Together with the amount of information being produced from various people on the net, the problem of Information Overload arises. The implication arises from the psychological field, society and individual (Schick &amp; Haka, 1990<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>).</p>

<sec>
<st>
Definition from other Sources</st>

<p>

According to Steve Beller, “I’m defining information overload as a state of having more information available that one can readily assimilate, that is, people have difficulty absorbing the information into their base of knowledge. This hinders decision-making and judgment by causing stress and cognitive impediments such as confusion, uncertainty and distraction” 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

-“A symptom of the high-tech age, which is too much for one human being to absorb in an expanding world of people and technology. It comes from all sources including TV, newspapers, magazines as well as wanted and unwanted regular e-mail and faxes. It has been exacerbated enormously because of the formidable number of results obtained from web search engines.” <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
General causes</st>

<p>

The general causes of information overload include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A rapidly increasing rate of <b>new information</b> being produced</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <b>ease of duplication and transmission</b> of data across the Internet</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An <b>increase in the available channels</b> of incoming information (e.g. telephone, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
e-mail</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/55951.xml">
instant messaging</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/93489.xml">
rss</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Large amounts of <b>historical information</b> to dig through</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Contradictions and inaccuracies</b> in available information</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A low <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/41706.xml">
signal-to-noise ratio</link></b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <b>lack of a method for comparing and processing</b> different kinds of information</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>E-mail</b> remains a major source of information overload, as people struggle to keep up with the rate of incoming messages. As well as filtering out unsolicited commercial messages (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/459847.xml">
spam</link>), users also have to contend with the growing use of e-mail <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/170084.xml">
attachments</link> in the form of lengthy reports, presentations and media files.</p>
<p>

A December 2007 New York Times blog post described E-mail as "a $650 Billion Drag on the Economy"<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>, and the New York Times reported in April 2008 that "E-MAIL has become the bane of some people’s professional lives" due to information overload, yet "none of [the current wave of high-profile Internet startups focused on email] really eliminates the problem of e-mail overload because none helps us prepare replies".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

Technology investors reflect similar concerns.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>
<p>

In addition to e-mail, the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
 has provided access to billions of pages of information. In many offices, workers are given unrestricted access to the Web, allowing them to manage their own research. The use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link>s helps users to find information quickly. However, information published online may not always be reliable, due to the lack of authority-approval or a compulsory accuracy check before publication. This results in people having to cross-check what they read before using it for decision-making, which takes up more time.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Analysis of General Causes</st>

<p>

1). <b>New Information</b>
-New information is being produced day by day. When there are latest gossips, or latest advertisements, latest phone models, news concerning fashion and top models, news regarding the politic and economic environment of a country, or celebrity scandals, almost everybody reports it on their journals, blogs and websites and publish them on net. Information is being shaped rapidly as everything happens in the world today becomes a topic and subject where people pond and discuss upon. In this way, there is mass production of information in the Internet and it is hard to verify the credibility or whether the article is high in validation. This creates misconception on certain issues and thus creates a world of uncertainty and doubt.</p>
<p>

2. <b>Increase on the available channels</b>
- Since there is an increase of information, more and more channels are broadcasted in order to published news and reports to public and society. Channels like BBC and CNN are examples of channels that provide information and sources to the public and the world. But the question is how far are they providing us the information? There are certain issues which are not discussed in channels as they are entirely based on the government policy implemented on to the mass media. Information channels like these only gives out information depending on the policy and regulations. That’s when the active users’ writes and reports it out in their sites and people tend to rely on online information rather than broadcasting news channel. Other than that, further channels continue to increase like YouTube and Metacafe.com within the cyberspace. Alongside with the increase of information being produced in various different channels, people are able to speak up and construct their own system of points and views. However, this contributes to the intervening of information. As the number of channels and information grows, people no longer know which information to rely, depend and trust anymore. Information seems to contradict each other and there is no way to find out the right and wrong data as everybody has different responses and varieties of information.</p>
<p>

3. <b>Historical Information</b>
- In this era, users’ are capable of surfing the net effortlessly and discover information on the subject of history which occurred centuries ago. History can be preserved easily with the rising of the information and digital age. However, some histories are not interpreted accordingly because everybody is able to share and upload information without proper referencing and therefore history becomes a big question mark to how far the details are true? In the following website, it displays wrong and incorrect history being published and it raises comments and dissatisfaction.</p>
<p>

http://boards.historychannels.com/ thread.jspa?threadID=800037818&amp;start=15&amp;mod=1208884789147</p>
<p>

4. <b>Contradictions and Inaccuracies</b>
As mentioned in the earlier general causes, information uploaded in the net and sites and the ones being broadcasted are contradicting. For example in this website, http://answers.yahoo.com/questions/index?qid=20061020140615AALWo5p,  A girl asks a question and random people spring out advices. Clearly, these advices are inaccurate and all of them are contradicting to one another. Consequently, people receive wrong information and this result in a negative impact. There is no one to blame as the cyberspace is wide and it is hard to trace.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Effects and Implications of Information Overload</st>

<p>

1. <b>Psychological Effects</b></p>
<p>

As people are faced with growing levels of information overload, the inability to make clear and accurate decisions can increase their hormones.
An article in the <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/39431.xml">
New Scientist</link></magazine>
 magazine claimed that exposing individuals to an information overloaded environment resulted in lower <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/14892.xml">
IQ</link> scores than exposing individuals to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/1481886.xml">
marijuana</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>, although these results are contested<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref>.  The same article also notes that a night <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/18597893.xml">
without sleep</link> can be as debilitating as over-exposure to information.  </p>
<p>

Part of the problem of information overload can be traced to <b>interruptions</b> in the workplace. Interruptions include incoming <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
e-mail</link> messages, phone calls and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/55951.xml">
instant messaging</link> - all of which break mental focus, and redirect it to the source of the interruption. The person has to deal with the interruption, then redirect their attention back to the original task (Crovitz, 2008 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref>).</p>
<p>

In 2005, research firm "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.basex.com">
Basex</weblink>" calculated the cost of unnecessary interruptions and related recovery time at "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1147136-2,00.html">
$588 billion</weblink>" per annum in the U.S. alone. That figure was updated to "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.businessweek.com/careers/content/jul2007/ca20070719_880333.htm">
$650 billion</weblink>" in early 2007.</p>
<p>

There are many other negative effects caused by information overload. Alvin Toffler who is a futurologist studied the negative and psychological effects of information overload. According to Toffler, information overload will lead to ‘future shock syndrome’ as an individual will suffer severe physical and mental disturbances. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref></p>
<p>

The world is moving so fast into technology and with the help of information; everything in the world seems to be multiplying which makes people prone to helplessness and inadequacy.</p>
<p>

2. <b>Impact on society</b></p>
<p>

<b>Negative</b>- 	 People are provided with wrong information about economics, politics and business. Hence, problems like misunderstanding arise in a society, and this creates havoc and madness. Since information is different, people tend to react differently according to their set of beliefs corroborating with the information available.
- For example, if there are blogs or websites discussing about culture and if certain numbers of people are not happy with its contents published, hence a peaceful realm will be shaken into the falls of stones and rocks.</p>
<p>

<b>Positive</b>-		The increase of information growth provides opportunity for interaction and communication to take place. Individual are able to converse about certain issues with different information hence bringing up a discussion. For example, in www.murdoch.edu.au, an LMS site is provided in which unit discussions within students takes place. One of the questions that are being asked is, “Is Second Life the New Life”. As we know, students have a range of information and thus, with their own set of knowledge from journals, books and website references, they argue their points out with one another hence improving the students to think critically and beyond the box. In the midst of this discussion, unintentionally interaction and communication takes place. Though it is taking place virtually yet it is achieving one of the main objective in this century. The social interaction enhances communication as the main tool.</p>
<p>

3. <b>Impact on Individual</b>
Wurman says that an individual will feel a loss of control when there is a huge number of information circulating, and they don’t really distinguish what is missing and therefore miss out on potentially important information. (Wurman,1990), <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref></p>
<p>

- In this new era of globalization, everything is moving around quickly as the strike of lightning and a blink of an eye. Cultures are changing and new trends are developing. The more you know about something, society regard you as someone witty and smart. An example can be drawn from the very famous Television series, “F.R.I.E.N.D.S”. The character Joey seems to be lost each time the others discuss about a certain topic. Hence, the other characters terms Joey as a dumb character. An in one of the episode, we as the audiences are able to observe how he was upset about it from his reminiscence and thus buys an encyclopedia to gain more information and knowledge but in the end, the other characters discusses something else which they have watched on the Television. It shows how information travels and individuals suffer from depression because not knowing what is happening in today’s world. Information is not only available in books or mass media but it is travelling to the world of cyberspace. Pressure increases as everybody wants to know more. Hence, individuals logs into websites, watches television and reads articles and newspapers just to gather as much facts and data they can to stay in the information age intensity.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Responses</st>

<p>

1.<b>Response of business and government</b> </p>
<p>

Many academics, corporate decision-makers, and federal policy-makers recognize the magnitude and growing impact of this phenomenon. In June 2008 a group of interested researchers from a diverse set of corporations, smaller companies, academic institutions and consultancies created the Information Overload Research Group (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iorgforum.org">
IORG</weblink>), a non-profit interest group dedicated to raising awareness, sharing research results and promoting the creation of solutions around Information Overload.</p>
<p>

Recent research suggests that an "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/3260249.xml">
attention economy</link>" of sorts will naturally emerge from information overload, allowing Internet users greater control over their online experience with particular regard to communication mediums such as e-mail and instant messaging. This could involve some sort of cost being attached to e-mail messages. For example, managers charging a small fee for every e-mail received - e.g. $5.00 - which the sender must pay from their budget. The aim of such charging is to force the sender to consider the necessity of the interruption.</p>
<p>

2. <b>Media</b></p>
<p>

Media like the internet are conducting research to promote awareness of information overload. In <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://informationr.net/ir/12-4/paper326.html">
http://informationr.net/ir/12-4/paper326.html</weblink> , Kyunghye Kim, Mia Liza A. Lustria, Darrell Burke, and Nahyun Kwon conducted a research regarding people who have suffered from information overload and what the result of the disease. The conclusion drawn from the research discusses about healthy information should be distributed and information campaigns should be held to prevent irrelevant or incorrect information being circulated in the world.           </p>
<p>

Other than that, there are many books published to encourage awareness of Information Overload. Books like “Surviving Information Overload” by Kevin A. Miller and “Managing Information Overload” by Lynn Lively. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Related terms</st>

<p>

A similar term "<b>information pollution</b>" was coined by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<adviser wordnetid="109774266" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/349587.xml">
Jakob Nielsen</link></adviser>
</person>
. The term "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/d0f71fb6-3243-11db-ab06-0000779e2340,dwp_uuid=4e612cca-6707-11da-a650-0000779e2340,print=yes.html">
interruption overload</weblink>" has begun to appear in newspapers such as the <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/136566.xml">
Financial Times</link></newspaper>
.</p>
<p>

=Conclusion=</p>
<p>

Information Overload is something that is evolving in the Web 2.0 and the world today. Though there are some positive levels to this problem yet the disadvantages are in the highest chart. Therefore, society should learn how to manage the system of information overload and provide a better understanding and reasonability. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>



<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Yang, C.C. (2003) Decision Support Systems. Amsterdam. April 2003. Volume 35, Issue 1, p89. URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed on 5th September 2008).</entry>
<entry id="2">
Internet World Stats (2008)INTERNET USAGE STATISTICS
The Internet Big Picture - World Internet Users and Population Stats 2000-2008. URL: http://internetworldstats.com/stats.htm (accessed on 5th September 2008).</entry>
<entry id="3">
Bonfield, B. (2007)Consuming Information Library Journal, New York: Oct 15th 2007, Volume 137, Issue 17, p26 (1 page). URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed on 5th september 2008).</entry>
<entry id="4">
Russo, A. &amp; Watkins, J. (2005) Intenational Journal of Education and Development using Information and communication technology, Bridgetown: Dec 2005, Volume 1, Issue 4, p4 (14 pages). URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed on 5th September).</entry>
<entry id="5">
Boutell (2007) 'WWW FAQS: How many web sites are there?' URL: http://www.boutell.com (accessed on 5th September 2008).</entry>
<entry id="6">
Benbunan-Fich, R. &amp; Koufaris, M. (2008) Electronic Markets, London: May 2008, Volume 18, Issue 2, p150. URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed on 5th September 2008)</entry>
<entry id="7">
Jones, B. (1993), "An Age of Discontinuity", in Sleepers Wake! Technology and the Future of Work, 3rd Ed., Melbourne, Oxford University Press, pp. 11-45</entry>
<entry id="8">
Jenkins, H. (2006) Fans, Bloggers and Gamers: Exploring Participatory Culture, New York University Press</entry>
<entry id="9">
Cheng, R &amp; Vassileva (2006) Design and Evaluation of an adoptive incentive mecahanism for sustained educational online communities, User modelling and user-adapted interaction. Dordrecht. Sep 2006, Volume 16, Issue 3-4, p321. URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed on 5th September 2008)</entry>
<entry id="10">
Baxter, A. (2008) Better interactivity benefits student faculty, Financial Times, London (UK) March 17th 2008, p4 URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed 27th August 2008</entry>
<entry id="11">
Flew, T. (2008) New Media: An Indroduction, Third Edition, Oxford University Press: Australia</entry>
<entry id="12">
Graham, G (1999) The Internet: A Philosophical Inquiry, Rotledge: London</entry>
<entry id="13">
Sonora Jha, 2007, Social Movements, The Internet and The Press, Journalism and Mass Communication Quaterly-New Media, Volume 84, No.1, pg 42</entry>
<entry id="14">
Centaur Communications Limited (2006) Data Retention: Information Overload. New Media Age. London: March 16th 2006, p25. URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed on 27th August 2008).</entry>
<entry id="15">
Schick, A.G. &amp; Haka, S. (1990) Accounting, organizations and society, Oxford, Volume 15, Issue 3, p199 (22 pages) URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed on 27th August 2008).</entry>
<entry id="17">
http://www.pcmag.com, The Independence Guide to Technology</entry>
<entry id="16">
http://curinghealthcare.blogspot.com, “Information Overload and Health Decision-Making Part 1”, Saturday September 11, 2006</entry>
<entry id="19">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/20/technology/20digi.html?_r=2&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin">
Struggling to Evade the E-Mail Tsunami</weblink>".&#32;  New York Times&#32;(<link>
2008-04-20</link>).</entry>
<entry id="18">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/12/20/is-information-overload-a-650-billion-drag-on-the-economy">
Is Information Overload a $650 Billion Drag on the Economy?</weblink>".&#32;  New York Times&#32;(<link>
2007-12-20</link>).</entry>
<entry id="21">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn7298">
Info-mania dents IQ more than marijuana</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foundrygroup.com/blog/archives/2008/04/did-darwin-skip-over-email.php">
Did Darwin Skip Over Email?</weblink>".&#32;  Foundry Group&#32;(<link>
2008-04-28</link>).</entry>
<entry id="23">
Crovitz, G.L. (2008) The information age: Unloading Information overload, Wall Street Journal (Eastern Edition), New York, N.Y. July 7th 2008, pA.11. URL: http://il.proquest.com (accessed on 27th August 2008).</entry>
<entry id="22">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/002493.html">
Language Log: An apology</weblink></entry>
<entry id="25">
Francis Heylighen, 2002, Information Overload, Complexity and Information Overload in Society: Why increasing efficiency leads to decreasing control, http://pespmc1.vub.ac.be/papers/info-overload.pdf</entry>
<entry id="24">
http://pespmc1.vub.ac.be/chinneg.html, Alvin Toffler 1970&amp;gt;, “Individual Effects of Change” in Change and Information Overload: Negative Effects, in Principal Cybernatics Web, F.Heylighen, February 19th 1999</entry>
<entry id="26">
http://books.google.com.my/books?q=information+overload</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/14774.xml">
Information explosion</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/482371.xml">
Glass cockpit</link></instrument>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iorgforum.org">
Information Overload Research Group</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/20030811.html">
Information Pollution</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.infogineering.net/articles/understanding-information-overload.htm">
Understanding Information Overload</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=991165">
Conceptualizing Information Systems and Cognitive Sustainability in 21st Century 'Attention' Economies (Includes Syllabus)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=653682">
The Role of Contextual Clues in the Creation of Information Overload (PDF)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eprints.rclis.org/archive/00002248/">
Information overload, retrieval strategies and Internet user empowerment.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bul.unisi.ch/cerca/bul/pubblicazioni/com/pdf/wpca0301.pdf">
A Literature Review on Information Overload Studies in Marketing, Organization, MIS, Accounting and related disciplines (PDF)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w-uh.com/articles/030308-tyranny_of_email.html">
The Tyranny of Email</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hbswk.hbs.edu/item.jhtml?id=4438&amp;t=srobbins">
Tips for Mastering E-mail Overload</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www2.una.edu/psychology/alatalk.htm">
Assessing and Managing Technostress</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tiac.net/~sw/2003/01/overload.html">
Too many anagrams for "Information Overload"</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cfo.com/article.cfm/9389205/c_9394789.html">
Tangled Up in Tasks</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pespmc1.vub.ac.be/CHINNEG.html">
Change and Information Overload: negative effects</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.managingio.com">
Information Overload blog</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=323877&amp;intsrc=hm_ts_head">
Information overload: Is it time for a data diet?</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.technology-essays.com/essays/information_overload.htm">
Information Overload Essay</weblink> Information, knowledge and power in contemporary society.</entry>
</list>

</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
