<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:29:02[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Modular building</title>
<id>4968621</id>
<revision>
<id>228646603</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-29T18:04:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Positaville</username>
<id>7558014</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles to be merged since March 2008</category>
<category>Building</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Merge-arrow.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrow
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  into . ()</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Bd_3.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Modular Home in Sutton Alaska
</caption>
</image>

<b>Modular buildings</b> are sectional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/5754502.xml">
prefabricated buildings</link> that are manufactured in a plant, and delivered to the customer in one or more complete modular sections. Modular buildings are considerably different from <link>
mobile homes</link>. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Uses </st>
<p>

Modular buildings have a wide variety of uses. They will either be used for long-term temporary or permanent facilities. Such uses include construction camps, schools and classrooms, civilian and military housing needs, and industrial facilities. Modular buildings are a perfect solution in remote and rural areas where conventional construction may not be reasonable or even possible. One example would be the housing facilities used by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/18998720.xml">
BP</link></company>
 in the oil fields of the <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/500309.xml">
Alaska North Slope</link></location>
</region>
.  Other uses have also been found for modular buildings including churches, health care facilities, sales and retail offices<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, fast food restaurants and cruise ship construction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Modular Homes vs. Mobile Homes</st>
<p>

Differences include the building codes that govern the construction, types of material used and how they are appraised by banks for lending purposes. The codes that govern the construction of modular homes are the exact same codes that govern the construction of any site constructed home. In the United States, all modular homes are constructed according the Uniform Building Code (UBC), IRC, BOCA or the code that has been adopted by the local jurisdiction. Mobile home (manufactured homes) are constructed according to the HUD Code and are generally considered lesser quality. The materials are the same as site constructed homes. Wood frame floors, walls and roof is the most typical. Some modulars even included brick or stone exteriors, granite counters and steeply pitched roofs. All modulars are designed to sit on a perimeter foundation or basement. Mobile homes are constructed with a steel chassis that is integral to the integrity of the floor system. Lending institutions and appraisers consider a modular home the same as they consider a site built home, with the same life expectancy and value. Mobile homes often require special lenders. Most companies have standard plans. However, all modular buildings can be custom built to a clients specifications. Today's designs include multi-story units, multi-family units and entire apartment complexes. The negative stereotype commonly associated with mobile homes and has prompted some manufacturers to start using the term Off-Site Construction <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Expense / Benefit </st>
<p>

Modular buildings are very affordable because of the factory construction of these buildings. They are a very cost effective compared to conventional construction. These units are typically constructed in an enclosed facility, therefore weather is not a factor in the construction time line. Material delivery fees are also out of the equation because an ample amount of material will always be available at the facility, as opposed to being delivered in limited quantities to the job site, nearly eliminating construction delays, and theft of building materials from the site.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/625059.xml">
Modular home</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mobilemodularrents.com/modular/Sales_and_Retail_Mobile_Offices.asp">
Mobile Sales &amp; Retail Offices</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-29</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.modulartoday.com/modular-history.html">
History of Modular Buildings</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-11-01</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.modtech.com">
Modular Buildings &amp; Off-Site Construction term</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-03-20</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
 </p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
