<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:29:43[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Whole foods</title>
<id>4994513</id>
<revision>
<id>244076807</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T06:19:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Disagreeableneutrino</username>
<id>7860467</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Diets</category>
<category>NPOV disputes from December 2007</category>
<category>Articles with specifically-marked weasel-worded phrases</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="ambox_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section has been nominated to be checked for its .</b>
Discussion of this nomination can be found on the . <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>"Whole Foods" redirects here. See also, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/620343.xml">
Whole Foods Market</link></company>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/104444.xml">
Whole food supplements</link></it>.
</indent>

<b>Whole foods</b> are those that are unprocessed and unrefined, or processed and refined as little as possible before being consumed. They typically do not contain added ingredients, such as sugar, salt, or fat.</p>
<p>

Often confused with "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/17345999.xml">
organic food</link>" (i.e., organically-grown food), whole foods are not necessarily organic, nor are organic foods necessarily whole, although they do share a number of traits, such as an avoidance of chemically-assisted agricultural techniques. Because of the lack of basic processing, many whole foods have a very short shelf life and are not easily sold outside of farmers' markets.</p>
<p>

Examples of whole foods include unpolished grains; fruits and vegetables; unprocessed meat, poultry, and fish; and non-homogenized milk.  For some&#91;&#93;, it is preferable to eat whole foods raw to obtain the maximum nutritional benefit, although this raises concerns of food poisoning.</p>
<p>

Whole foods are easily assimilated and absorbed readily by the body.  Whole foods are nutrient rich and are thought to promote health because they are a natural source of vitamins and minerals .</p>
<p>

The term “Whole Food” has been known to describe any food that offers a complete balance in nutritional value while in its natural state. Whole foods typically include any raw fruits and vegetables, as well as nutrient-dense nuts, seeds and sprouts. Some contend that it is preferable to eat whole foods raw in order to obtain their maximum nutritional benefit.</p>
<p>

There are several ways to meet the body's needs with respect to whole foods. One way is to consume a variety of fresh raw fruits and vegetables every day. For some this can be very inconvenient and difficult, especially considering those who live a fast-paced lifestyle.</p>
<p>

Many ardent consumers &#91;&#93; of whole foods advocate "juicing" as a means to obtain the whole food nutrition provided by fresh raw fruits and vegetables. Proponents &#91;&#93; claim many benefits, including ease of consumption and the dense concentration of nutrients in fresh juice products.  </p>
<p>

Yet another popular means of obtaining whole food nutrition is through taking nutritional supplements. Advocates of whole foods &#91;&#93; urge caution, however, claiming that most nutritional supplements on the market have been overprocessed, thus eliminating their whole food benefits.    </p>

<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/3133549.xml">
Natural foods</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/104444.xml">
Whole food supplements</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/641274.xml">
Raw foodism</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wholefoods.blogspot.com">
 Wholefoods ...for health</weblink> - "The independent health food and whole food news site presenting nutritional news, views, products and links."</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wholefoods101.blogspot.com">
 Whole Foods~Healthy Foods</weblink> - Articles and blogging focused on whole food nutrition. Comments welcome.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.herbalgram.org">
Web site for the American Botanical Council</weblink> - Information on herbs, medicinal botanicals, scientific information, and news.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.elephantjournal.com/2008/02/whole-foods-secret-to-success/">
Video interview with Bud Sorenson, Whole Foods board member</weblink></entry>
</list>

</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
