<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:31:15[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<painter  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110391653">
<artist  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109812338">
<creator  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109614315">
<header>
<title>Jacek Andrzej Rossakiewicz</title>
<id>5043636</id>
<revision>
<id>144879764</id>
<timestamp>2007-07-15T22:51:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cydebot</username>
<id>1215485</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Polish painters</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Rossakiewicz_PietaPD.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Pieta   oil on canvas, 200x190 cm, 1990 
Musée d’Art Contemporain de Dunkerque
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Jacek Andrzej Rossakiewicz</b> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/34672.xml">
1956</link>) is a <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/22936.xml">
Polish</link></country>
 painter, theoretician of art, philosopher and interior architect.</p>
<p>

His first paintings were created in the 1980s. The paintings were inspired by the Pure Form Theory of Stanislaw Ignacy Witkiewicz (Witkacy) and entrenched in the tradition of 20th century European Art. Beginning in 1985, J.A.R. showed in his paintings the social and political context associated with the criticism of the political regime instantiated in Poland after the martial law (Dec. 1980). The contemplation of the different functions of this art led to the artist’s formulation of the theory Art as a Freedom (1985). Mostly inspired by Witkacy’s grasp of the visible universe, in which the composition introduced the intended and directional tension, led Rossakiewicz to one interpretation of reality. The continuation of this philosophy led him in 1987 to the manifestation of social problems in his art. The next chapter of his art, The Everlasting Art, - 1989 was directly inspired from the readings of Old Testament and the New Testament. After 1989, Rossakiewicz started to create a series of evangelical paintings: Passion of Dunkirk and Saint John Passion. The Passion of Dunkirk is in the collection at the Modern Art Museum in Dunkirk, France.</p>
<p>

Rossakiewicz about his art: 
"In my understanding, to express man’s spiritual life is to create art. The subject of the painting doesn’t matter. But the art has to originate in the inside, it has to be a result of man's life experiences. It cannot be simply planned; how to shock, how to draw attention to one's self, it cannot be done for money either. Because the spiritual and emotional state of an artist while painting, or working on a different work of art, is encoded in the painting and this energy is emanating from it." </p>


<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rossakiewicz.pl/">
Official Website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

<b>Saint John Passion</b> 
The cycle of 15 paintings (oil on canvas, 245x140 cm) with the prologue: <b>The Transfiguration</b> 
<image width="150px" src="Rossakiewicz_Last_Supper.jpg">
<caption>

The Last Supper, 1989 (1),  the classic composition was replaced by positioning the table vertically, which subconsciously suggested the shape of crucifix.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Rossakiewicz_Prayer.jpg">
<caption>

The Prayer of Jesus, 1990 (3)
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Rossakiewicz_CrucifixionSJP.jpg">
<caption>

The Crucifixion, 2000 (6), Painted in ancient olive green – color choosing was inspired by biblical sentence: “For if men do these things when the tree is green, what will happen when it is dry?” (Luke, 23:31)
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Rossakiewicz_Deposition.jpg">
<caption>

The Deposition, 1990 (7), Painting dominant color is also green – but muted. There is no life in ‘HIM’ anymore.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Rossakiewicz_Tomb.jpg">
<caption>

The Tomb Guards, 1990 (8), The painting is a depiction of total destruction. The paint was scraped off and burnt – this is also author’s reflection of our modern times
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Rossakiewicz_Angel.jpg">
<caption>

The Angel of the Lord, 1990 (9)
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Rossakiewicz_Appear.jpg">
<caption>

Jesus Appears to Thomas, 1990 (13)
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Rossakiewicz_Tyberiada.jpg">
<caption>

By the Sea of Tiberias, 1990 (14)
</caption>
</image>
</p>










</sec>
</bdy>
</creator>
</artist>
</painter>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
