<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:12:25[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Segmentation (image processing)</title>
<id>505717</id>
<revision>
<id>242232749</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T12:38:34Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Etienne Decenciere</username>
<id>5040037</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Image processing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/6596.xml">
computer vision</link>, <b>segmentation</b> refers to the process of partitioning a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/503726.xml">
digital image</link> into multiple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/55633.xml">
region</link>s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/26691.xml">
sets</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link>s).  The goal of segmentation is to simplify and/or change the representation of an image into something that is more meaningful and easier to analyze.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  Image segmentation is typically used to locate objects and boundaries (lines, curves, etc.) in images.  <p>

The result of image segmentation is a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/55633.xml">
region</link>s that collectively cover the entire image, or a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/650086.xml">
contour</link>s extracted from the image (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/331680.xml">
edge detection</link>).  Each of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link>s in a region are similar with respect to some characteristic or computed property, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/5921.xml">
color</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/41993.xml">
intensity</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/146903.xml">
texture</link>.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/1651508.xml">
Adjacent</link> regions are significantly different with respect to the same characteristic(s).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Some of the practical applications of image segmentation are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/234714.xml">
Medical Imaging</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Locate tumors and other pathologies</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Measure tissue volumes</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Computer-guided surgery</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Diagnosis</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Treatment planning</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Study of anatomical structure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Locate objects in satellite images (roads, forests, etc.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../595/486595.xml">
Face recognition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/3409790.xml">
Fingerprint recognition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Automatic traffic contolling systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/172088.xml">
Machine vision</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Several general-purpose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s and techniques have been developed for image segmentation.  Since there is no general solution to the image segmentation problem, these techniques often have to be combined with domain knowledge in order to effectively solve an image segmentation problem for a problem domain.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Clustering Methods </st>

<p>

The <information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<datum wordnetid="105816622" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/1860407.xml">
K-means algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</datum>
</rule>
</event>
</information>
 is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/68833.xml">
iterative</link> technique that is used to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/669675.xml">
partition</link> an image into <it>K</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link>s.  The basic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> is:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pick <it>K</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link> centers, either <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
random</link>ly or based on some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Assign each <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> in the image to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link> that minimizes the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/32344.xml">
variance</link> between the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link> center</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Re-compute the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link> centers by averaging all of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link>s in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Repeat steps 2 and 3 until <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/349779.xml">
convergence</link> is attained (e.g. no <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link>s change <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link>s)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In this case, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/32344.xml">
variance</link> is the squared or absolute difference between a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link> center.  The difference is typically based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/5921.xml">
color</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/41993.xml">
intensity</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/146903.xml">
texture</link>, and location, or a weighted combination of these factors.  <it>K</it> can be selected manually, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
random</link>ly, or by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link>.</p>
<p>

This <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> is guaranteed to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/237696.xml">
converge</link>, but it may not return the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/914285.xml">
optimal</link> solution.  The quality of the solution depends on the initial set of clusters and the value of <it>K</it>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Histogram-Based Methods </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/13266.xml">
Histogram</link>-based methods are very efficient when compared to other image segmentation methods because they typically require only one pass through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link>s.  In this technique, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/13266.xml">
histogram</link> is computed from all of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link>s in the image, and the peaks and valleys in the histogram are used to locate the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link>s in the image.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/5921.xml">
Color</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/41993.xml">
intensity</link> can be used as the measure.</p>
<p>

A refinement of this technique is to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/54798.xml">
recursive</link>ly apply the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/13266.xml">
histogram</link>-seeking method to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link>s in the image in order to divide them into smaller clusters.  This is repeated with smaller and smaller <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link>s until no more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/55431.xml">
cluster</link>s are formed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  </p>
<p>

One disadvantage of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/13266.xml">
histogram</link>-seeking method is that it may be difficult to identify significant peaks and valleys in the image. In this technique of image classification  distance metric and integrated region matching are familiar.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Edge Detection Methods </st>

<p>

Edge detection is a well-developed field on its own within image processing. Region boundaries and edges are closely related, since there is often a sharp adjustment in intensity at the region boundaries. Edge detection techniques have therefore been used as the base of another segmentation technique.</p>
<p>

The edges identified by edge detection are often disconnected. To segment an object from an image however, one needs closed region boundaries. Discontinuities are bridged if the distance between the two edges is within some predetermined threshold.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Region Growing Methods </st>

<p>

The first <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/17985602.xml">
region growing</link> method was the seeded region growing method. This method takes a set of seeds as input along with the image. The seeds mark each of the objects to be segmented. The regions are iteratively grown by comparing all unallocated neighbouring pixels to the regions. The difference between a pixel's intensity value and the region's mean, <math>\delta</math>, is used as a measure of similarity. The pixel with the smallest difference measured this way is allocated to the respective region. This process continues until all pixels are allocated to a region.</p>
<p>

Seeded <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/17985602.xml">
region growing</link> requires seeds as additional input. The segmentation results are dependent on the choice of seeds. Noise in the image can cause the seeds to be poorly placed. Unseeded region growing is a modified algorithm that doesn't require explicit seeds. It starts off with a single region <math>A_1</math> – the pixel chosen here does not significantly influence final segmentation. At each iteration it considers the neighbouring pixels in the same way as seeded <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/17985602.xml">
region growing</link>. It differs from seeded <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/17985602.xml">
region growing</link> in that if the minimum <math>\delta</math> is less than a predefined threshold <math>T</math> then it is added to the respective region <math>A_j</math>. If not, then the pixel is considered significantly different from all current regions <math>A_i</math> and a new region <math>A_{n+1}</math> is created with this pixel.</p>
<p>

One variant of this technique, proposed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/1751978.xml">
Haralick</link> and Shapiro (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/34846.xml">
1985</link>),<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> is based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/41993.xml">
intensities</link>.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/612.xml">
mean</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/1736112.xml">
scatter</link> of the region and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/41993.xml">
intensity</link> of the candidate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> is used to compute a test statistic.  If the test statistic is sufficiently small, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> is added to the region, and the region’s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/612.xml">
mean</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/1736112.xml">
scatter</link> are recomputed.  Otherwise, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> is rejected, and is used to form a new region.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Level Set Methods </st>

<p>

Curve propagation is a popular technique in image analysis for object extraction, object tracking, stereo reconstruction, etc. The central idea behind such an approach is to evolve a curve towards the lowest potential of a cost function, where its definition reflects the task to be addressed and imposes certain smoothness constraints. Lagrangian techniques are based on parameterizing the contour according to some sampling strategy and then evolve each element according to image and internal terms. While such a technique can be very efficient, it suffers from various limitations like deciding on the sampling strategy, estimating the internal geometric properties of the curve, changing its topology, addressing problems in higher dimensions, etc.</p>
<p>

The level set method was initially proposed to track moving interfaces by Osher et Sethian in 1988 and has spread across various imaging domains in the late nineties. It can be used to efficiently address the problem of curve/surface/etc. propagation in an implicit manner. The central idea is represent the evolving contour using a signed function, where its zero level corresponds to the actual contour. Then, according to the motion equation of the contour, one can easily derive a similar flow for the implicit surface that when applied to the zero-level will reflect the propagation of the contour. The level set method encodes numerous advantages: it is implicit, parameter free, provides a direct way to estimate the geometric properties of the evolving structure, can change the topology and is intrinsic. Furthermore, they can be used to define an optimization framework as proposed by Zhao, Merriman &amp; Osher in 1996. Therefore, one can conclude that it is a very convenient framework to address numerous applications of computer vision and medical image analysis.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Graph Partitioning Methods </st>

<p>

The “normalized cuts” method was first proposed by <b>Shi</b> and <b>Malik</b> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/34601.xml">
1997</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>  In this method, the image being segmented is modelled as a weighted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/325806.xml">
undirected graph</link>.  Each <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/638899.xml">
node</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/557931.xml">
graph</link>, and an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/54483.xml">
edge</link> is formed between every pair of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixel</link>s.  The weight of an edge is a measure of the similarity between the pixels.  The image is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/669675.xml">
partition</link>ed into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/39359.xml">
disjoint sets</link> (segments) by removing the edges connecting the segments.  The optimal partitioning of the graph is the one that minimizes the weights of the edges that were removed (the “cut”).  <b>Shi’s</b> algorithm seeks to minimize the “normalized cut”, which is the ratio of the “cut” to all of the edges in the set. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Watershed Transformation </st>

<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/11878679.xml">
watershed transformation</link> considers the gradient magnitude of an image as a topographic surface. Pixels having the highest gradient magnitude intensities (GMIs) correspond to watershed lines, which represent the region boundaries. Water placed on any pixel enclosed by a common watershed line flows downhill to a common local intensity minima (LMI). Pixels draining to a common minimum form a catchment basin, which represent the regions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Model based Segmentation </st>

<p>

The central assumption of such an approach is that structures of interest/organs have a repetitive form of geometry. Therefore, one can seek for a probabilistic model towards explaining the variation of the shape of the organ and then when segmenting an image impose constraints using this model as prior. Such a task involves (i) registration of the training examples to a common pose, (ii) probabilistic representation of the variation of the registered samples, and (iii) statistical inference between the model and the image. State of the art methods in the literature for knowledge-based segmentation involve active shape and appearance models, active contours and deformable templates and level-set based methods.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Multi-scale Segmentation </st>

<p>

Image segmentations are computed at multiple scales in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/1703661.xml">
scale-space</link> and sometimes propagated from coarse to fine scales; see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/5479282.xml">
scale-space segmentation</link>.</p>
<p>

Segmentation criteria can be arbitrarily complex and may take into account global as well as local criteria. A common requirement is that each region must be connected in some sense.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Semi-automatic Segmentation </st>

<p>

In this kind of segmentation, the user outlines the region of interest with the mouse clicks and algorithms are applied so that the path that best fits the edge of the image is shown. </p>
<p>

Techniques like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/7480315.xml">
Livewire</link> or Intelligent Scissors are used in this kind of segmentation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Neural Networks Segmentation </st>

<p>

Neural Network segmentation relies on processing small areas of an image using a neural network or a set of neural networks. After such processing the decision-making mechanism marks the areas of an image accordingly to the category recognized by the neural network. A type of network designed especially for this, is the <link>
Kohonen map</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Open Source Software </st>

<p>

Several <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link> software packages are available for performing image segmentation</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/3745271.xml">
ITK</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/13697814.xml">
ITK-SNAP</link> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
GUI</link> tool that combines manual and semi-automatic segmentation with level sets.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/12628.xml">
GIMP</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/2617125.xml">
VXL</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/8318184.xml">
ImageMagick</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mitk.org/slicebasedsegmentation.html">
MITK</weblink> has a program module for manual segmentation</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

There are also free academic software packages:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/10970590.xml">
GemIdent</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/6596.xml">
Computer Vision</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/669675.xml">
Data clustering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/11585545.xml">
Range image segmentation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<datum wordnetid="105816622" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/1860407.xml">
K-means algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</datum>
</rule>
</event>
</information>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
Graph Theory</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/13266.xml">
Histogram</link>s</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/17985602.xml">
Region growing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/6107563.xml">
Pulse-coupled networks</link></entry>
</list>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Linda G. Shapiro and George C. Stockman (2001):  “Computer Vision”, pp 279-325, New Jersey, Prentice-Hall, ISBN 0-13-030796-3</entry>
<entry id="2">
Dzung L. Pham, Chenyang Xu, and Jerry L. Prince (2000):  “Current Methods in Medical Image Segmentation”, <it>Annual Review of Biomedical Engineering</it>, volume 2, pp 315-337</entry>
<entry id="3">
Ron Ohlander, Keith Price, and D. Raj Reddy (1978):  “Picture Segmentation Using a Recursive Region Splitting Method”, <it>Computer Graphics and Image Processing</it>, volume 8, pp 313-333</entry>
<entry id="4">
S. Osher &amp; N. Paragios. 
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mas.ecp.fr/vision/Personnel/nikos/osher-paragios/">
Geometric Level Set Methods in Imaging Vision and Graphics</weblink>, Springer Verlag, ISBN 0387954880, 2003.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Jianbo Shi and Jitendra Malik (1997):  "Normalized Cuts and Image Segmentation", <it>IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</it>, pp 731-737</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://instrumentation.hit.bg/Papers/2008-02-02%203D%20Multistage%20Entropy.htm">
3D Entropy Based Image Segmentation</weblink></p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
