<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:12:33[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Professional diving</title>
<id>506443</id>
<revision>
<id>241910489</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T01:26:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Uncle G</username>
<id>164776</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with limited geographic scope</category>
<category>Underwater diving</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<indent level="1">

<b><it>Hardhat diving</it></b><it> redirects here. Often, "hardhat diving" is used to specifically mean diving in the old-type <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<clothing wordnetid="103051540" confidence="0.8">
<consumer_goods wordnetid="103093574" confidence="0.8">
<garment wordnetid="103419014" confidence="0.8">
<suit wordnetid="104350905" confidence="0.8">
<covering wordnetid="103122748" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/488208.xml">
Standard diving dress</link></covering>
</suit>
</garment>
</consumer_goods>
</clothing>
</commodity>
</artifact>
.</it>
</indent>
<b>Professional Diving</b> is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1266475.xml">
diving</link> where the divers are paid for their work. There are several branches of professional diving, the most well known of which is probably commercial diving. Any person wishing to become a professional diver normally requires specific training that satisfies <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/51913.xml">
legislation</link>, such as that set by the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/361308.xml">
Health and Safety Executive</link>. Due to the dangerous nature of some professional diving disciplines, specialized equipment such as a diver to surface communication system is often required by law.
<image location="right" width="300px" src="KB_Bandmask.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Diver with <link>
KB Bandmask</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
</caption>
</image>

<sec>
<st>
Equipment</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Web_051026-N-0000X-001.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

US Navy Diver using Kirby Morgan diving helmet
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Diving suit</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/326538.xml">
Diving suit</link></it>
</indent>
Depending on the water temperature and length of dive, the diver will either use a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/177213.xml">
wetsuit</link>, where <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/217524.xml">
neoprene</link> provides thermal insulation but the diver gets wet, a hot water diving suit which is similar to a wetsuit but is flooded with warm water from the surface through an umbilical, or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/291791.xml">
drysuit</link>, which keeps the diver totally dry and relies on either the suit material or the air trapped in thermal undergarments to insulate the diver. Certain applications require a specific type of dive suit; long dives into deep, cold water normally require a hot water suit, whilst diving into potentially contaminated environments requires a drysuit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Breathing apparatus</st>
<p>

A number of factors dictate the type of breathing apparatus used by the diver.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Typical considerations include the length of the dive, water contamination, space constraints and vehicle access for support vehicles.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Some disciplines will very rarely use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/488213.xml">
surface supplied diving</link>, such as military clearance divers, whilst commercial divers will rarely use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/28502.xml">
SCUBA equipment</link>.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Scuba</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1266475.xml">
Scuba diving</link></it>
</indent>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1266475.xml">
SCUBA</link> equipment is normally used by media and military divers, often utilizing specialized equipment such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/294126.xml">
rebreather</link>s, which are closed circuit SCUBA equipment that recycles breathing gas instead of releasing it into the water. It is the "re-breathing" of gas that makes rebreathers ideal for long duration dives, efficient decompression when the gas mix is adjustable, and for the observation of animals in the wild due to the lack of noisy bubbles. These characteristics also make rebreathers ideal for military use, such as when military divers are engaged in covert action or when performing mine clearance where bubbles could potentially set off an explosion.</p>
<p>

<link>
Open circuit scuba</link> equipment is occasionally used by commercial divers working on sites where surface supplied equipment is unsuitable, such as around raised structures like a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/44958.xml">
water tower</link>, or in remote locations where it is necessary to carry equipment to the dive site. Normally, for comfort and for practicality, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/494877.xml">
full face mask</link> such as those manufactured by Kirby Morgan will be used to allow torches and video cameras to be mounted onto the mask. The benefit of full-face masks is that they can normally be used with surface supplied equipment as well, removing the need for the diver or the company to have two sets of expensive equipment.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Surface supplied</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/488213.xml">
Surface supplied diving</link></it>
</indent>
<image width="Surface-supplied divers from 1873 ([[Illustrated London News]], February 8th)|thumb|270px" src="Divers_-_Illustrated_London_News_Feb_6_1873-2.PNG">
</image>

This is, perhaps, the most common type of equipment used in professional diving, and the one most recognised by the public, made familiar through films such as <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/45568.xml">
The Abyss</link></movie>
</it>.<image location="left" width="150px" src="US_Navy_Air_Line.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

US Navy tender with umbilical - A typical surface supplied diving situation
</caption>
</image>
Surface Supplied equipment can be used with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/494877.xml">
full face mask</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/488252.xml">
diving helmet</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Helmets are normally to be found fitted with diver to surface communication equipment, and often with light sources and video equipment. The use of a full-face mask or a full diving helmet is down to requirements and personal preference, however the impact protection and warmth offered by a full diving helmet makes it popular for underwater construction sites and cold water work.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/459471.xml">
Breathing gas</link> for the diver is piped down from the surface, through a long, flexible hose, called an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/4484716.xml">
umbilical</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> In addition to breathing gas, the umbilical may have additional hoses and cables for such things as communications equipment or hot water should the diver be using a hot water suit. The diver's breathing gas can is pumped down from either <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/460321.xml">
high pressure tanks</link> or through a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/508504.xml">
gas compressor</link>.</p>
<p>

If the diver is to be working at extreme depths for a long period, the diver may live in a special underwater habitat called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/2388344.xml">
diving chamber</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> This type of surface supplied diving is known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/489941.xml">
saturation diving</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> The same technique for supplying breathing gas as regular surface supplied diving is used, with the diving bell receiving breathing gas and electricity from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/989004.xml">
diving support vessel</link> on the surface.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Due to the often extreme depths the diver is working at, specialised <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/13256.xml">
helium</link>-based breathing gas mixtures are often used to prevent both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/21937.xml">
nitrogen narcosis</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/462421.xml">
oxygen toxicity</link> which occurs at these extreme depths.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Branches of professional diving</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Commercial diving</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Offshore diving</st>
<p>

Offshore diving is the most well known branch of commercial diving, with divers working in support of the exploration and production sector of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/2152848.xml">
oil and gas industry</link> in places such as the <body_of_water wordnetid="109225146" confidence="0.8">
<gulf wordnetid="109296121" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/13166.xml">
Gulf of Mexico</link></gulf>
</body_of_water>
 in the United States and the <ocean wordnetid="109376198" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/21179.xml">
North Sea</link></ocean>
 in the United Kingdom and Norway. The work in this area of the industry typically revolves around the maintenance of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/163806.xml">
oil platform</link>s and the building of underwater structures used in the production process.</p>
<p>

For many newly qualified divers, this is the entry point to the industry, the lack of experienced divers and the excess of qualified divers within the industry push down wages for younger, less experienced divers beginning their careers. The low wages, relative inexperience of the workforce combined with difficult and dangerous operating conditions make offshore diving the most dangerous area of employment for professional divers.</p>
<p>

Equipment used for offshore diving tends to be surface supplied equipment but this does vary depending on the nature of the work and location, for instance Gulf of Mexico based divers may use wetsuits whilst North Sea divers need drysuits or even hot water suits due to the temperature of the water.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Inland / onshore diving</st>
<p>

Inland or onshore diving is very similar to offshore diving in terms of the nature of work and the equipment used, the work often being in support of land based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ar)/5762_(H$ebrew_year).xml">
civil engineering</link> projects, with the majority of the work either underwater <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/167741.xml">
survey</link> or engineering work. The number of dive sites this covers is varied however, and divers can be found working in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/13475.xml">
harbour</link>s and lakes,on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/381399.xml">
hydroelectric dams</link>, in rivers and around <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/3397.xml">
bridge</link>s and <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/13490247.xml">
pontoons</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
, with the bulk of this work being undertaken in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/230001.xml">
freshwater</link>. Onshore divers typically earn less per hour than their colleagues who work offshore, but the ability to work from home for many divers is an advantage.</p>
<p>

The equipment used does depend on the nature of the work and location, but normally a mixture of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/28502.xml">
SCUBA</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/488213.xml">
Surface supplied diving</link> equipment is used by divers and their employers.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
HAZMAT diving</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Web_050911-N-5345W-092.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

US Navy Diver being decontaminated after a dive.
</caption>
</image>

HAZMAT diving is widely regarded as the most dangerous branch of the commercial diving industry, employing highly skilled and experienced staff.</p>
<p>

Typical work involves diving into raw sewage or dangerous chemicals, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/1460891.xml">
paper pulp</link>, liquid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/6670.xml">
cement</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/955072.xml">
oil sludge</link>. This causes special requirements:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The divers need to be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/32473.xml">
vaccinated</link> against diseases such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/38238.xml">
hepatitis</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/45831.xml">
tetanus</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The dive company needs to have specialist plans in place for decontamination of the diver and equipment after a dive.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A way to recover the diver if something goes wrong.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The diver's weighting may need to be adjusted, if he is diving in a liquid whose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/8429.xml">
density</link> is much different from the density of water.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The main tasks a diver can be found to be doing include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Essential maintenance of underwater valves and sluice gates.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Repairing damaged pipelines.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
Pollution</link> control work to contain, control, and clean up after a pollution incident.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Some divers are required to dive into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/211285.xml">
landfill</link> sites to maintain the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/23617.xml">
pump</link>ing equipment, vital in preventing landfill sites from filling up with rainwater and contaminating the water table.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Welding inside live <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/51062.xml">
sewer</link>s or working in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/217773.xml">
septic tank</link>s.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Miscellaneous repairs and finding lost objects.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Finding bodies.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Sewer diving</b> is often considered the most dangerous of all the HAZMAT jobs due to the diseases contained in raw sewage and because <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/147923.xml">
syringe</link>s and glass find their way into the raw sewage, creating risks of contracting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/8072.xml">
diseases</link>.</p>
<p>

Divers working in an environment harmful to their health will always wear a full drysuit with thick gloves which are attached directly to the suit, the helmet and boots will also attach directly to the drysuit, this allows the gloves, boots, suit and helmet to be pressured in order to prevent ingress of liquid should a puncture occur. Normally, to achieve this, a diver will use a free flow diving helmet which continually supplies enough air for the diver to breathe plus an additional amount to pressurise the suit; a free flow helmet has a much lower chance of leakage through the exhaust valve compared with a demand helmet where the exhaust valve is dormant during the inhalation stage of the diver breathing.</p>
<p>

The drysuit will be made from a material resistant to whatever hazard the diver faces: normally the diver wears a vulcanised rubber <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/291791.xml">
drysuit</link>, but occasionally a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/217524.xml">
neoprene</link> or tri-laminate suit is needed. Often, a diver will wear extra protection over their drysuit to decrease the chance of a puncture: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/18062.xml">
leather</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/24458.xml">
PVC</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/21490.xml">
nylon</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/554255.xml">
coverall</link>s are used for this purpose.</p>
<p>

In such diving light is often very scarce, so most such divers rely on touch to guide them, and are usually connected via rope to the surface.</p>
<p>

Links:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://the.honoluluadvertiser.com/article/2004/Mar/12/ln/ln18a.html">
Diver enjoys doing the dirty work,  Robbie Dingeman, Honolulu Advertiser, March 12, 2004</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=279698">
Divers to give deep tunnel a much-needed deep cleaning,  Steve Schultze - Marie Rohde, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel, Nov 29, 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A45322-2004Aug29.html">
Deep-Slime Divers Keep Vast and Smelly Sewers Flowing, Mary Jordan, Washington Post, August 30, 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oceans.com.au/oefun-mexico.html">
Getting down and dirty in México City, Marla Dickerson, Los Angeles Times</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/mexico/20061219-0947-mexico-sewers.html">
Mexican sewage divers submerge in murky world, Monica Medel - Reuters, San Diego Union-Tribune, December 19, 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/07/16/1089694567129.html">
Sewage divers keep city's bowels in working order, Jo Tuckman, Sydney Morning Herald, July 17, 2004</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Nuclear diving</st>
<p>

Nuclear diving is similar to HAZMAT diving; the difference is the exposure to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/25856.xml">
radiation</link> instead of a water borne contaminant. To this end, different precautions are required for nuclear diving, mainly, equipment which will not absorb radiation and pose a disposal problem after several dives. </p>
<p>

Heat stress can also be a danger for the diver, in which case a cold water suit may be used: the cold water suit is a special canvas coverall which floods the outside of the diver's drysuit with chilled water, countering the dangerously high ambient water temperature. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/40363.xml">
dosimeter</link> is used to ensure that the diver does not receive a dangerous dose of radiation during the dive, assisting in calculating the maximum length of the dive. In addition the dosimeter can also be used to find radiation hotspots, which can indicate areas in need of repair.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Scientific diving</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Scale_drawing_underwater.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A scientific diver at work
</caption>
</image>

Scientific diving is the use of diving techniques by scientists to study underwater what would normally be studied by scientists on land.  Scientific divers are normally qualified scientists first and divers second, who use diving equipment and techniques as their way to get to the location of their fieldwork. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/51795.xml">
Underwater archeology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/20021.xml">
marine biology</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/12207.xml">
geology</link> are examples of sciences pursued underwater. Some scientific diving is carried out by universities in support of undergraduate or postgraduate research programs.  In the United States scientific diving is permitted by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/227123.xml">
Occupational Safety and Health Administration</link> to operate under an alternative consensual standard of practice that is maintained by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/8499982.xml">
American Academy of Underwater Sciences</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>  The perspectives on the regulation of scientific diving of two founders of the American Academy of Underwater Sciences: Lloyd Austin and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/547193.xml">
Phil Sharkey</link> can be found in <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/freeabs_all.jsp?arnumber=1152066">
OCEANS Volume: 15, pp460- 463</weblink>. </p>
<p>

To be able to avail itself of the Scientific Diving Exemption the institution under whose auspices the work is carried out must meet four tests:
<indent level="1">

1. The Diving Control Board consisting of a majority of active scientific divers must have autonomous and absolute authority over the scientific diving program's operations.
</indent>
:2. The purpose of all projects using scientific diving is the advancement of science; therefore, information and data resulting from the project are non-proprietary.
<indent level="1">

3. The tasks of a scientific diver are those of an observer and data gatherer. Construction and trouble-shooting tasks traditionally associated with commercial diving are not included within scientific diving.
</indent>
:4. Scientific divers, based on the nature of their activities, must use scientific expertise in studying the underwater environment and, therefore, are scientists or scientists in training.</p>
<p>

Government bodies such as the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
United States Environmental Protection Agency</link></agency>
 and the UK <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/529059.xml">
Environment Agency</link></administration>
</group>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
</social_group>
</body>
 carry out scientific diving to recover samples of water, marine organisms and sea, lake or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/3573718.xml">
riverbed</link> material to examine for signs of pollution.</p>
<p>

Equipment used varies widely in this field, but surface supplied equipment though quite uncommon in the UK is growing in popularity in the U.S.  The short number of dives made by scientific divers in normally quite shallow water, and the UK governmental regulations that make surface supplied equipment cumbersome, when combined with a need for easy transportation make surface supplied gear uneconomic and undesirable for UK scientists to use.</p>
<p>

The two standard references for Scientific Diving Operations are:</p>
<p>

Flemming, N. C., Ed.; Max, M. D. (Ed) Code of Practice for Scientific Diving: Principles for the Safe Practice of Scientific Diving in Different Environments. UNESCO Technical Papers in Marine Science 53.</p>
<p>

Joiner James T. (ed), NOAA Diving Manual: Diving for Science and Technology, Fourth Edition, 2001, U.S.Department of Commerce, National Technical Information Service, (ISBN: 0941332705)</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Media diving</st>
<p>

Media Diving is a term that covers <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/291260.xml">
underwater photography</link> and underwater filming. Media Diving is often carried out in support of television documentaries, such as the <network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/19344654.xml">
BBC</link></network>
 series <album wordnetid="106591815" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<documentary wordnetid="106616806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/4039424.xml">
Planet Earth</link></documentary>
</album>
 or Hollywood blockbusters, with feature films such as <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/52371.xml">
Titanic</link></movie>
 and <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/3618333.xml">
The Perfect Storm</link></movie>
 featuring underwater photography or footage. Media divers are normally highly trained camera operators who use diving as a method to reach their workplace, although some underwater photographers may start as recreational divers and move on to make a living from their hobby.</p>
<p>

Equipment in this field is varied with SCUBA and surface supplied equipment used, depending on requirements, but <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/294126.xml">
rebreathers</link> are often used for wildlife related work as they are normally quiet, release few or no bubbles and allow the diver a lengthy bottom time with a reduced risk of frightening off the subject at hand.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Military and naval diving</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="US_Navy_explosive_ordnance_disposal_(EOD)_divers.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

AUS Navy Clearance Divers defusing a MK17 Buoyant Mine pic: WOCD Paul Darcey
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/2245298.xml">
Clearance Diver</link></it>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/297113.xml">
Frogman</link></it>
</indent>
Military diving covers all types of diving carried out by military personnel.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> There are a number of different specialisations for a military diver to choose, some depend on which branch of the military they've joined or where the military needs more divers. Typical offensive activities include underwater demolition, infiltration and sabotage, this being the type of work elite regiments such as the UK <military_unit wordnetid="108198398" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/154105.xml">
Special Boat Service</link></military_unit>
 or the USA <military_unit wordnetid="108198398" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/38188.xml">
Navy Seals</link></military_unit>
 carry out. Defensive activities are centered around countering the threat of enemy <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/160415.xml">
special forces</link> and enemy anti-shipping measures, and typically involve defusing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/22102.xml">
mines</link>, searching for explosive devices attached to the hulls of ships, and locating enemy <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/297113.xml">
frogmen</link> in the water.</p>
<p>

Military divers need equipment which hides their position and prevents explosives from being set-off, and to this end, they use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/294126.xml">
rebreathers</link> which produce few or no bubbles on the surface, and which contain no <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/19716.xml">
magnetic</link> components, this continues down to the design of their diving suit, which will normally have a non-magnetic zip, and the face-mask may be fitted with special anti-reflective glass. Some navies have gone further and given their divers special <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/74845.xml">
contact lens</link>es instead of large face-masks to cut down on the risk of a reflection.</p>
<p>

Naval diving is the military term for commercial diving, and is drastically different from military diving. Naval divers work to support maintenance and repair operations on ships and military installations. Typical tasks include changing propellers or fitting replacement <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
anodes</link>.  Naval divers may also work to recover downed aircraft, submarines, missiles and other military hardware. Their equipment is derived from commercially available equipment, with the US Navy using versions of the Kirby Morgan helmets and full-face masks amongst other equipment.</p>
<p>

Experimental diving, is conducted by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/19267843.xml">
US Navy's Experimental Diving Unit</link> (NEDU) and involves meeting military needs through the research and development of diving practices and diving equipment, testing new types equipment and finding new and safer ways to perform dives and related activities. The US NEDU was responsible for much of the early experimental diving work to calculate <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/291794.xml">
decompression tables</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 and has since worked on such developments as heated diving suits powered by radioactive isotopes and mixed gas diving equipment, while the British equivalent (The Admiralty Experimental Diving Unit) perfected the Mark 10 submarine escape suits utilized by both the Royal Navy and the US Navy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Police diving</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/506473.xml">
Police diving</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</it>
</indent>
Police divers are normally police officers who have been trained in the use of diving techniques to recover <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/5236854.xml">
evidence</link> and occasionally bodies from rivers, canals and the sea. They may also be employed in searching shipping for contraband substances fitted to the outside of <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/13755.xml">
hull</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
s to avoid detection. The equipment they use depends on requirements, but the requirement for communications at some sites does often require the use of full-face masks with communication equipment, either with SCUBA or surface supplied equipment.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Dive instruction</st>
<p>

There are two differing types of dive instructor. Some train recreational divers while others train professional divers.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/494840.xml">
Recreational dive</link> instructors differ from other types of professional divers as they normally don't require a professional level qualification, but a relevant recreational qualification from a recognised <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/496866.xml">
training agency</link> such as <link>
GUE</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/344644.xml">
NAUI</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/39883.xml">
PADI</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/163216.xml">
SSI</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/87241.xml">
YMCA</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/496988.xml">
BSAC</link>, which permits them to teach. Dive instructors teach a wide variety of skills from entry-level <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/460367.xml">
diver training</link> for beginners, to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/2499082.xml">
diver rescue</link> for intermediate level divers and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/291242.xml">
technical diving</link> for more experienced divers. They often operate from dedicated dive centres at coastal sites or through hotels in popular holiday resorts or simply from local swimming pools. Initial training is carried out mainly on conventional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/28502.xml">
SCUBA equipment</link> but with the increasing use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/294126.xml">
rebreather</link>s, their use is also taught. Not all dive instructors are professionals; many instructors are amateurs with careers outside the diving industry.</p>
<p>

Commercial dive instructors normally require professional diving qualifications. They typically teach trainee commercial divers how to operate types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/490009.xml">
diving equipment</link> and typical underwater tools they will use in the course of their work. Commercial dive instructors will use similar equipment to commercial divers in the course of their work.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Training</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="46px" src="Globe_important.svg">
<caption>

Globe icon
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The examples and perspective in this article or section may not represent a  of the subject.
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Professional_diving&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> or discuss the issue on the .</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

In the UK, any person diving at work is required to hold a relevant qualification approved by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/361308.xml">
Health and Safety Executive</link> (HSE). In the UK, diving schools work towards a standard HSE approved qualification, whilst divers who have trained overseas may find their existing qualifications meet the necessary HSE standards, if not, additional training may be required. HSE approved qualifications are well known around the world and due to the stringent requirements of HSE qualifications, most diving qualifications around the world are designed to meet HSE standards, allowing any trained diver to work in the UK, an important location due to the <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/858340.xml">
North Sea oil</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</field>
</region>
 industry. The stringent requirements of the HSE qualifications make then a common requirement around the world for employers looking for new staff.</p>
<p>

There are several different HSE qualifications, each focusing on a different type of equipment or type of diving activity, for instance the HSE Scuba qualification allows the holder to use only SCUBA equipment. Training usually takes place at a residential school, with courses taking anything between 9 and 13 weeks although divers with existing qualifications, such as former military divers can take courses which build on their existing knowledge and experience. During training, divers will be taught how to use common types of diving equipment (nearly every school trains divers to use the Kirby Morgan equipment) and how to carry out underwater <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/239038.xml">
construction</link> techniques such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/44883.xml">
welding</link> and cutting.</p>
<p>

In addition to physical training, there is a large amount of classroom work, with divers being trained subjects such as basic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../209/48209.xml">
gas laws</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/291794.xml">
decompression tables</link>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/11296.xml">
First Aid</link> courses are normally also a requirement for trainee divers, with the emphasis placed on dealing with decompression and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/460448.xml">
diving related injuries</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Junker, DL and Mazzone, RW&#32;(1996).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/7499">
Evaluation of Diving System International (DSI) KMB-28B Bandmask.</weblink>". <it>US Naval Experimental Diving Unit Technical Report</it>&#32;<b>NEDU-TR-10-96</b>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Nishi, R. Y.&#32;(1989).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/3922">
Proceedings of the DCIEM Diver Thermal Protection Workshop</weblink>". <it>Defence and Civil Institute of Environmental Medicine, Toronto, CA</it>&#32;<b>DCIEM 92-10</b>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://yosemite.epa.gov/r10/oea.nsf/af6d4571f3e2b1698825650f0071180a/4abeef6113935aff88256e5f00640500/$FILE/USN_Guidance_For_Diving_in_Contaminated_Waters_(1_Aug.,_2004).pdf">
US Environmental Protection Agency Guidance For Contaminated Environment Diving</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">US Naval Sea Systems Command&#32;(2004).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/6158">
Guidance for diving in contaminated waters.</weblink>". <it>US Navy Contaminated Water Manual</it>&#32;<b>SS521-AJ-PRO-010</b>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(2006) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.supsalv.org/00c3_publications.asp?destPage=00c3&amp;pageID=3.9">
US Navy Diving Manual, 6th revision</weblink>.&#32;United States:&#32;US Naval Sea Systems Command. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Stanek, SJ and Hedricks, CS&#32;(2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/3541">
Evaluation of the KMS 48 Full Face Mask with the Viper Very Shallow Water Underwater Breathing Apparatus</weblink>". <it>US Naval Experimental Diving Unit Technical Report</it>&#32;<b>NEDU-TR-03-06</b>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Beyerstein, G&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/4661">
Commercial Diving: Surface-Mixed Gas, Sur-D-O2, Bell Bounce, Saturation.</weblink>". <it>In: Lang, MA and Smith, NE (eds). Proceedings of Advanced Scientific Diving Workshop</it>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Wilkins, JR&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/4660">
US Navy Diving Program: Diving to 300 Ft Depths Using Surface-Supplied and Saturation Fly-Away Diving Systems.</weblink>". <it>In: Lang, MA and Smith, NE (eds). Proceedings of Advanced Scientific Diving Workshop</it>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gerth, WA&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/4654">
Decompression Sickness and Oxygen Toxicity in US Navy Surface-Supplied He-O2 Diving.</weblink>". <it>In: Lang, MA and Smith, NE (eds). Proceedings of Advanced Scientific Diving Workshop</it>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hicks, RE&#32;(1997).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/4642">
The Legal Scope of "Scientific Diving": An Analysis of the OSHA Exemption.</weblink>". <it>In: EJ Maney, Jr and CH Ellis, Jr (Eds.) Diving for Science...1997.</it>&#32;<b>Proceedings of the American Academy of Underwater Sciences</b>&#32;(17th Annual Scientific Diving Symposium). Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.history.navy.mil/faqs/faq100-1.htm">
US Navy History Site</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Carter Jr, R. C.&#32;(1977).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/4799">
Pioneering Inner Space: The Navy Experimental Diving Unit's First 50 Years</weblink>". <it>US Naval Experimental Diving Unit Technical Report</it>&#32;<b>NEDU-1-77</b>. Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

For scientific and archaeological applications for which diving is needed see: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/51795.xml">
Underwater archaeology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/20021.xml">
Marine ecology</link></entry>
</list>

For other diving activities
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1266475.xml">
Diving activities</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.shipwrecks.com/federalcodediving.htm">
USA Government Regulations for Commercial Diving (federal code)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/diving/index.htm">
UK Health and Safety Executive Website (UK Government)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.adas.org.au/">
Australia Diver Accreditation Scheme Website (Australian Government)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.divingheritage.com/nuclear.htm">
Diving Heritage Life of a nuclear diver</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.shipwrecks.com">
Sea Research Society</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.DDRC.org/">
Diving Diseases Research Centre</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.divinglore.com/Commercial.htm">
History of Commercial Diving</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.underwater.com.au/article.php/id/7492/">
Becoming a Commercial Diver - a report</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.divinglore.com/Commercial_Diving.htm">
Brief history and overview of Commercial Diving</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.offshorediver.com">
Site with extensive information about commercial diving</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 OSHA.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.osha.gov/pls/oshaweb/owadisp.show_document?p_id=9986&amp;p_table=STANDARDS">
Commercial Diving Regulations (Standards - 29 CFR) - Mixed-gas diving. - 1910.426</weblink>".&#32;  U.S. Department of Labor, Occupational Safety &amp; Health Administration.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-29</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
