<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:35:40[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<social_event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107288639">
<contest  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107456188">
<game  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100456199">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<header>
<title>Peanuts (game)</title>
<id>5124584</id>
<revision>
<id>179797410</id>
<timestamp>2007-12-23T16:19:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>J. Spencer</username>
<id>568400</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Solitaire card games</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<indent level="1">

<it>This article is about a card game. For the hand-bending game, see <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/7419543.xml">
Mercy (game)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
 For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/4869276.xml">
Peanut (disambiguation)</link></it>
</indent>

<b>Peanuts</b> is one of many forms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/27891.xml">
double solitaire</link> played in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
. It is very similar to <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../282/37282.xml">
Klondike</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
, but with an extra scoring feature as well as being played by two and with two decks.
<p>

<table style="clear: left; margin-bottom: .5em; float: left; padding: .5em 1.4em .8em 0; background: none; width: auto;" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>
__TOC__</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
Preliminaries</st>
<p>

Two players use two standard 52-card decks ranking <b>K Q J 10 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 A</b>. Each deck <b>must</b> have a <b>different back</b> so as to identify which cards came from which deck. Players sit facing each other and should leave enough space to allow for expansive solitaire layouts on the able.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Deal</st>

<p>

Each player shuffles his or her deck and prepares to distribute it into three categories:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<b>The Tableau</b> of 7 face up cards arranged side-by-side in a horizontal row</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<b>The Peanut Pile</b> of 21 cards stacked face down with the top card turned up</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<b>The Stock</b>, another face down pile made up of the remaining 24 cards</entry>
</list>

To deal this arrangement, each player lays a card face up for the tableau, then deals three cards to the peanut pile, then one face up, three to the peanut pile, and so on until each has a row of seven cards in front of them, plus their piles of 21 and 24. There should be enough space between the two rows for a third row to fit between them.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Play</st>

<p>

The object of the game is to get rid on one's peanut pile while playing as many cards the middle as possible. Play is as follows:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Cards are initially played from the top of each player's <b>peanut pile</b> and from any exposed cards in their respective tableaus.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Any exposed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/142293.xml">
ace</link> forms one of eight shared <b>building piles</b> in a row in between the two players' tableaus.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Cards may be added to building piles if they are the <b>same suit</b> and <b>one rank higher</b> than the card beneath tem (2♣ on A♣, 3♣ on 2♣, etc.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Cards may be layered to form columns on the tableau if they are <b>one rank lower</b> and the <b>opposite color</b> (black/red) of the card beneath them (so J♠ can be placed on Q♥, and 10♥ on J♠, etc.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

An empty space in a player's tableau is filled in by the top card of that player's <b>peanut pile</b>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Once any desired plays are made from peanut pile and tableau, players may play from their stock by counting out 3 cards and turning them face up. The top face up card may now be played exposing the card beneath it. Players continue to turn up cards from their stocks, 3 at a time and playing any playable cards desired. When the stock is exhausted, it is turned over and gone through again.</entry>
</list>

Note that the only shared cards between players are the middle row of building piles. Players never play to each other's tableaus or touch each other's stocks or peanut piles.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ending</st>
<p>

Game ends when either:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Neither player is able to play a card to the building piles, or</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 A player successfully plays the last card of the peanut pile, and says <b>Peanuts!</b></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Scoring</st>
<p>

Tableaus are cleared and cards are divided and counted from the building piles (hence the varied backs) and each player subtracts the number of cards left in his or her peanut pile from the number of cards successfully played to building piles. High score wins.</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</article>
