<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:30:24[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<danger  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114541044">
<hazard  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="114541852">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<header>
<title>Over-illumination</title>
<id>5146334</id>
<revision>
<id>242661795</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T03:17:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Nirvelli</username>
<id>194275</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Health risks</category>
<category>Light pollution</category>
<category>Low-energy building</category>
<category>Articles with limited geographic scope</category>
<category>Environmental science</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
<category>Lighting</category>
<category>USA-centric</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Globe_important.svg">
<caption>

Globe icon
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section deals primarily with the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 and does not represent a  of the subject.
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Over-illumination&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> or discuss the issue on the .</col>
</row>
</table>


<image location="right" width="240px" src="Cosmeticsrazorback.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

This <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/158015.xml">
cosmetics</link> store has lighting levels over twice recommended levels<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Over-illumination</b> is the presence of lighting intensity (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/773153.xml">
illuminance</link>) beyond that required for a specified activity. Over-illumination was commonly ignored between 1950 and 1995,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> especially in office and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/183515.xml">
retail</link> environments; only since then has the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/573174.xml">
interior design</link> community begun to reconsider this practice. </p>
<p>

The concept of over-illumination encompasses two separate but related concerns:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Use of more artificial illumination than required is expensive and energy-intensive. This includes consideration both of the appropriate level of illumination when spaces are in use, and when they are unoccupied.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Some people find excessive levels of artificial light to be irritating. These effects may depend on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/29329.xml">
spectra</link> of the light as well as the overall illuminance.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Lighting accounts for roughly 9% of U.S. residential electricity use.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Areas where energy and financial savings could be realized include unneeded overnight lighting of office buildings, forsaking available natural light, underutilization of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/1022935.xml">
occupancy sensor</link>s, and under-using discretionary light controls.  In response to these concerns, the design and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/903378.xml">
architecture</link> communities are making greater use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/2301573.xml">
indirect sunlight</link> in modern commercial buildings.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Numerical definition</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Bigboxrazorback.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Some big-box retail stores have over-illumination.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Generally speaking, over-illumination occurs indoors when light levels exceed 500 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/155869.xml">
lux</link> for incidental lighting, 800 lux for general office use, or 1,600 lux for special purpose use such as microchip etching quality control. For comparison, the midday sun provides about 32,000 to 100,000 lux depending on latitude, time of year and cloud cover. The term over-illumination first came into reasonably broad use in the early 1990s, when the lighting, health and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/478933.xml">
energy conservation</link> fields realized its effects.  Production of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/7497745.xml">
glare</link> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/43594.xml">
de facto</link> indication of over-illumination, since that causes optical processing conflicts and confusion to the brain in processing optical inputs. Over-illumination is sometimes grouped with unnatural spectra because negative health effects may result from the excess illumination, and also because certain artificial lights (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/144056.xml">
fluorescent lamp</link>s) provide intense illumination in certain frequency bands, unlike daylight, whose <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/1320360.xml">
spectral power distribution</link> is fairly even over the visible spectrum. The most desirable spectrum is that of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/6800733.xml">
natural light</link>, which the body is attuned to and uses to set the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/56565.xml">
circadian rhythm</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Related phenomena</st>
<p>

Over-illumination can contribute to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/18279.xml">
light pollution</link>, where stray light illuminates the outdoors or others' property, where it is unwanted. Over-illumination is a topic normally addressed in the process of building design, whereas light pollution is normally addressed by zoning regulations.</p>
<p>

Furthermore, over-illumination generally does not refer to the extreme conditions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/240096.xml">
snowblindness</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/240093.xml">
arc eye</link>, in which ultraviolet light can induce physical damage to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/311888.xml">
cornea</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Causes</st>
<p>

Lighting unoccupied areas is responsible for significant energy wastage.  A 2005 survey of commercial buildings indicates that only about five percent of structures utilize any form of occupancy sensor, a device that has been available for over 15 years.  More remarkably office buildings are often illuminated overnight and on weekends.  A survey of building managers indicates this practice was primarily for the convenience of the janitors, so that they would not have to bother turning lights on and off during night shifts when janitorial work was carried out.  Timers are also available to switch light banks off at prescribed times, a practice particularly useful to prevent outdoor lights from staying on during daylight.  One survey of 156 California building managers revealed that average daylight use of outdoor lighting was one to two hours, and the reason for such wastage was most commonly attributed to the failure of building maintenance personnel to reset timers for each season (i.e. quarterly reprogramming that takes approximately two minutes per timer).</p>
<p>

<image location="left" width="180px" src="Montecitorazorback.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>Forsaking use of sunlight</b> is often a design decision made by the architect or their subcontractor.  Overlooking opportunities for skylights is a major defect of many building designs, but lack of coordination of interior light banks with indirect sunlight is an even more common error.  At a minimum, the building design should offer sufficient independent light banks so that building occupants may select the most suitable combination of natural to augmented light.  Very frequently entire floors of office buildings are designed with only one switch, so that perimeter areas near natural light are illuminated with the same level of man-made light as the dimmest interior zones.  This lack of independent controls also would require an entire office floor of say 10,000&nbsp;square feet (1,000&nbsp;m2) to be fully illuminated if one office worker stays late for evening work.  This can occur with even the most eminent of architects. <architect wordnetid="109805475" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/10683.xml">
Frank Lloyd Wright</link></architect>
 designed <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/2964342.xml">
Marin County Civic Center</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 in 1957 with only one or two switches serving  very large floor footprint office pools.  This cost  <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/82017.xml">
Marin County</link></county>
 several thousands of dollars per annum in unneeded electricity costs.  </p>
<p>

<b>Omitting occupancy sensors</b> is an error primarily for bathrooms, conference rooms and storage areas.  This is an energy wastage issue and not a health issue.  The payback time of most occupancy sensors is in the range of two to five years, and yet first cost economics prevent the installation of occupancy sensors in the majority of cases where they would save energy and lighting maintenance costs.</p>
<p>

<b>Failure to delamp or use available lighting controls</b> is a common issue associated with over-illuminated buildings.  Many instances of  “designed in” over-illumination can be corrected by simple actions of building managers, following an illumination survey.  In many instances over-illumination can be solved by removing a fraction of the lights or fixtures from a ceiling lighting system.  In other cases a lighting retrofit can be conducted to replace older, less energy efficient fixtures with newer ones.  Lighting retrofits can also be designed to reduce over-illumination; retrofits have typical payback periods of two to four years.  In simpler cases many fluorescent ceiling illumination systems have multiple switch settings that allow tuning of the light intensity delivered,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> the most common version of this control being the "three-way switch".  Much of the benefit of the excess illumination reduction comes from a better ratio of natural light to fluorescent light that can result from any of the above changes.  Research has been conducted showing worker productivity gains in settings where each worker selects his or her own lighting level.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health effects</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Headaches, fatigue, stress and performance effects</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="210px" src="FluorescentT8razorback.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Common T8 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/11555.xml">
fluorescent</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/188386.xml">
lighting</link> fixture frequently used in office environments
</caption>
</image>

Health effects of over-illumination or improper spectral composition of light include increased <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/69893.xml">
headache</link> incidence, worker <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/235562.xml">
fatigue</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/146072.xml">
medically defined stress</link>, decrease in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/15179951.xml">
sexual</link> function and increase in anxiety.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> The health consequences are particularly significant of improperly matching the color spectrum of sunlight when illuminating the workplace.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Clinical studies documented in the foregoing references have been conducted for each of these health effects, except for sexual dysfunction, in which case only a linkage has been suggested through the decreased endothelial function associated with hypertensive increase. </p>
<p>

<b>Migraine headaches</b> are known to be triggered by excessive light. In one survey over-illumination was listed as the number two trigger for migraines, with 47% of the respondents reporting bright light as the principal trigger of their migraine episode.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Not only does bright light induce headache, but incorrect spectra (for example, too great an emphasis upon fluorescent (as opposed to sunlight) contribute to incidence of headache.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

<b>Fatigue</b> is a common complaint from individuals exposed to over-illumination, especially with fluorescent media.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Some studies have shown that the flicker and over-illumination combined in some fluorescent systems yield particularly high fatigue incidence.  Research on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/56565.xml">
circadian rhythm</link> in humans indicates that one reason for fatigue stems from the incorrect color spectrum of fluorescent light.  </p>
<p>

<b>Stress and anxiety</b> are frequent outcomes from working in a setting of intense (especially fluorescent) lighting. Research has shown that annoyance from bright light leads to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/146072.xml">
medical stress</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> It is clear that brighter, less spectrally correct light induces clinically measurable stress,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> and it is suggested that for children this over-illumination may interfere with the learning process. For example, children experiencing any form of stress are more likely to suffer from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/1119334.xml">
dysgraphia</link>, a problem in learning to write. Task performance can also be compromised for people conducting work under artificial (e.g. fluorescent as opposed to natural light).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> The annoyance with purely artificial light and preference by office workers for natural light has been demonstrated by a number of studies spanning eastern and western cultures.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> Fluorescent lighting has also been linked to aggravating other psychological disorders such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/57723.xml">
agoraphobia</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Circulatory and circadian rhythm effects</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/77432.xml">
Hypertension</link> effects of over-illumination can lead to aggravation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/512662.xml">
cardiovascular disease</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/14783.xml">
erectile dysfunction</link>, which impacts are outcomes of  long term cumulative exposure and associated systematic increases in blood pressure. The mechanism of this effect seems to be stress by related <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/553121.xml">
upregulation</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/10250.xml">
adrenaline</link> production akin to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/470843.xml">
fight-or-flight response</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> When adrenalin is released into the bloodstream it causes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../G$O$$/DO$T$G$O$.xml">
vasoconstriction</link>, a known precursor to both hypertension and erectile dysfunction. Analogous female <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/15179951.xml">
sexual</link> side effects are thought to result in the female anatomy from reduced blood flows.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/56565.xml">
Circadian rhythm</link> disruption is primarily caused by the wrong timing of light in reference to the circadian phase. It can also be affected by too much light, too little light, or incorrect spectral composition of light. This effect is driven by stimulus (or lack of stimulus) to photosensitive ganglion cells in the retina. The "time of day", the circadian phase, is signalled to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/285152.xml">
pineal gland</link>, the body’s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/862694.xml">
photometer</link>, by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/608162.xml">
suprachiasmatic nucleus</link>. Bright light in the evening or in the early morning shifts the phase of the production of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/285157.xml">
melatonin</link> (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/1556918.xml">
Phase response curve</link>, PRC). Wrong melatonin rhythm can worsen <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/5562.xml">
cardiac arrhythmia</link>s and increase <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/66313.xml">
oxidized</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/17940.xml">
lipid</link>s in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/490305.xml">
ischemic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/36808.xml">
heart</link>. Melatonin also reduces <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/92447.xml">
superoxide</link> production and myeloperoxide (an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/9257.xml">
enzyme</link> in neutrophils which produces <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/578099.xml">
hypochlorous acid</link>) during ischemia-reperfusion.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> </p>
<p>

In practice, adverse outcomes seem to arise most commonly among workers subject to intense fluorescent light, which is poorly matched to the spectrum of sunlight. According to one set of researchers, the body translates this condition as "total darkness" and resets the circadian clock incorrectly.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Not only does this result in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/235562.xml">
fatigue</link>, but also immuno-suppressive behavior that has been shown to be linked to increased <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer</link>s. The research indicates that increasing the ratio of natural light to artificial solves much of the problem, provided the total illumination level is not driven excessively high. Many of these health impacts may be primarily due to the spectrum of the light rather than the overall level of illumination, but more research is required to establish this.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Energy and economic considerations</st>
<p>

The total worldwide energy wastage from over-illumination is roughly 1.5 billion barrels of oil per annum. Most of the excess occurs in the U.S. and Europe. Excessive energy usage is often tolerated because the person who bears the cost is usually not the one making day to day decisions about lighting. Building managers and not building owners usually structure such things as janitorial use of lighting, setting or installation of timers, or the choice of lighting fixtures. Another poor management practice in the U.S. is a leasing structure where the tenant, who makes operational decisions on lighting use, pays none of the electricity costs, a form of lease common in about one half of the situations today.</p>
<p>

There are also myths which continue to propagate, occluding better lighting decisions.  One myth is that there is a greater cost of turning on fluorescent systems than keeping them running. In particular, according to the U.S. Department of Energy: "The amount of electricity consumed to supply the inrush current [for turning a fluorescent light on] is equal to a few seconds or less of normal light operation. Turning off fluorescent lights for more than five seconds will save more energy than will be consumed in turning them back on again."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>
&#91;&#93;</p>
<p>

Another myth is that electrical costs of lighting are a constant and not a variable. However, hundreds of buildings in the U.S. have been audited and had their lighting use altered, with a demonstrated 30 to 50 percent reduction in lighting costs. One California study indicated that generally 40 to 80 percent of lighting energy costs could be eliminated,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> sometimes requiring hardware investment with an average payback time of less than two years. The highest savings can be generated for buildings in the planning stage or where major remodeling will occur.</p>
<p>

A final myth is that more light is better. Health data disprove such an assertion, and this statement only has applicability in rare situations today where the original lighting is very low or where unusual technological manufacturing processes (such as microchip etching) demand high illumination levels.</p>
<p>

Architectural design can identify technological aspects of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/49400.xml">
window</link> design where window angles can be calculated to minimize interior glare and reduce interior over-illumination, while at the same time reducing solar heat loading and subsequent demand for air conditioning as energy conservation techniques. For the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/6450437.xml">
Dakin Building</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/108102.xml">
Brisbane, California</link></village>
 the angled window projections effectively provide permanent sunscreens, obviating any need for interior blinds or shades.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/478933.xml">
Energy conservation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/77432.xml">
Hypertension</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<danger wordnetid="114541044" confidence="0.8">
<hazard wordnetid="114541852" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/18279.xml">
Light pollution</link></causal_agent>
</hazard>
</danger>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/66811.xml">
Seasonal affective disorder</link></disease>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/9058630.xml">
World energy resources and consumption</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Peter Tregenza and David Loe, <it>The Design of Lighting</it>, Routledge, New York (1996)</entry>
<entry id="2">
 M.D. Simpson, <it>A flexible approach to lighting design</it>, Proc. CIBSE National Lighting Conference, Cambridge, 8-11 April, 1990, 182-189, Chartered Institution of Building Services Engineers</entry>
<entry id="3">
Department of Energy, http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/recs/recs2001/enduse2001/enduse2001.html</entry>
<entry id="4">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2008/02/080208162238.htm">
Changing Our Clocks: New Research Explores How Our Bodies Keep Time</weblink>".&#32;  Science Daily&#32;(2008-02-11).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-09</link>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
H. Juslen, M. Wouters M and A. Tenner, <it>The influence of controllable task-lighting on productivity: a field study in a factory</it>,  Appl Ergon., Mar 7;  2006</entry>
<entry id="6">
Susan L. Burks, <it>Managing your Migraine</it>, Humana Press, New Jersey (1994) ISBN 0-89603-277-9</entry>
<entry id="7">
<it>Cambridge Handbook of Psychology, Health and Medicine</it>, edited by Andrew Baum, Robert West, John Weinman, Stanton Newman, Chris McManus, Cambridge University Press (1997) ISBN 0-521-43686-9</entry>
<entry id="8">
L. Pijnenburg, M. Camps and G. Jongmans-Liedekerken, <it>Looking closer at assimilation lighting</it>, Venlo, GGD, Noord-Limburg (1991)</entry>
<entry id="9">
Igor Knez, <it>Effects of colour of light on nonvisual psychological processes</it>, Journal of Environmental Psychology, Volume 21, Issue 2, June 2001, Pages 201-208</entry>
<entry id="10">
Lumina Technologies, Santa Rosa, Ca., <it>Survey of 156 California commercial buildings energy use</it>, August, 1996</entry>
<entry id="11">
Peter Boyce and Boyce R Boyce, <it>Human Factors in Lighting</it>, 2nd ed., Taylor &amp; Francis, London (2003) ISBN 0-7484-0950-5</entry>
<entry id="12">
M.R Basso Jr., <it>Neurobiological relationships between ambient lighting and the startle response to acoustic stress in humans</it>, Int J Neurosci. 2001;110(3-4):147-57,</entry>
<entry id="13">
E. Nagy, Sachiko Yasunaga and Satoshi Kose, <it>Japanese office employees' psychological reactions to their underground and above-ground offices</it>, Building Research Institute, Ministry of Construction, 1 Tatehara, Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki-ken 305, Japan, Revised 13 April 1995. Available online 20 May 2004.</entry>
<entry id="14">
J. Hazell and A.J. Wilkins, <it>A contribution of fluorescent lighting to agoraphobia</it>, . Psychol Med. 1990 Aug;20(3):591-6</entry>
<entry id="15">
Narisada Kohei and Duco Schreude, <it>Light Pollution Handbook</it>, Springer, Netherlands (2004) ISBN 1-4020-2665-X</entry>
<entry id="17">
R.J. Reiter, Cardiovascular Research; 58:10-19 (2003)</entry>
<entry id="16">
<it>Biological Effects of Power Frequency Electric and Magnetic Fields</it>, Office of Technology Assessment, U.S. Congress, University Press of the Pacific (2002) ISBN 0-89875-974-9</entry>
<entry id="19">
Ray, C. Claiborne&#32;(2007-09-04).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/04/science/04qna.html?ex=1346558400&amp;en=fb20488ad5a46f3c&amp;ei=5124&amp;partner=permalink&amp;exprod=permalink">
Lights Off!</weblink>", <it>New York Times</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-06</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
<it>A Consumers Guide to Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy</it>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/62866.xml">
U.S. Department of Energy</link>, Washington DC (2006)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.labour.gov.hk/eng/public/oh/OHB50.pdf">
Government of Hong Kong Health Effects of Lighting in the Workplace</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iea.org/w/bookshop/add.aspx?id=302">
International Energy Agency's Policies for Energy-efficient Lighting</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foe.org.hk/welcome/geten.asp?id_path=1,%207,%2028,%20150,%203524,%203685">
Case study on interior lighting of optical stores, 16 June 2007, Friends of the Earth (Hong Kong)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tristate.apogee.net/lite/bblevel.asp">
Lighting levels recommended by the IES</weblink> (multiply footcandles by 10.76 to convert to lux)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</causal_agent>
</hazard>
</danger>
</physical_entity>
</article>
