<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:41:26[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Dynamic network analysis</title>
<id>5162898</id>
<revision>
<id>235725672</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-02T02:17:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Terrillfrantz</username>
<id>6378350</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> Computer network analysis</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Dynamic network analysis (DNA)</b> is an emergent scientific field that brings together traditional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network analysis</link> (SNA), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1039587.xml">
link analysis</link> (LA) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/938833.xml">
multi-agent systems</link> (MAS). There are two aspects of this field. The first is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistical analysis</link> of DNA data. The second is the utilization of simulation to address issues of network dynamics.  DNA networks vary from traditional social networks in that are larger dynamic multi-mode, multi-plex networks, and may contain varying levels of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/63778.xml">
uncertainty</link>.<p>

DNA statistical tools are generally optimized for large-scale networks and admit the analysis of multiple networks simultaneously in which, there are multiple types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/998116.xml">
nodes</link> (multi-node) and multiple types of links (multi-plex).In contrast, SNA statistical tools focus on single or at most two mode data and facilitate the analysis of only one type of link at a time.</p>
<p>

DNA statistical tools tend to provide more measures to the user, because they have measures that use data drawn from multiple networks simultaneously. From a computer simulation perspective, nodes in DNA are like atoms in quantum theory, nodes can be, though need not be, treated as probabilistic.  Whereas nodes in a traditional SNA model are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/181091.xml">
static</link>, nodes in a DNA model have the ability to learn.  Properties change over time; nodes can adapt: A company's employees can learn new skills and increase their value to the network; Or, capture one terrorist and three more are forced to improvise. Change propagates from one node to the next and so on.  DNA adds the element of a network's evolution and considers the circumstances under which change is likely to occur.
<image location="right" width="340px" src="DynamicNetworkAnalysisExample.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

An example of a multi-entity, multi-network, dynamic network diagram
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>Illustrative problems that people in the DNA area work on -</b></p>
<p>

•	Developing metrics and statistics to assess and identify change within and across networks.</p>
<p>

•	Developing and validating simulations to study network change, evolution, adaptation, decay... See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/5957183.xml">
Computer Simulation and Organizational Studies</link> </p>
<p>

•	Developing and validating formal models of network generation and evolution  </p>
<p>

•	Developing and testing theory of network change, evolution, adaptation, decay...</p>
<p>

•	Developing techniques to visualize network change overall or at the node or group level  </p>
<p>

•	Developing statistical techniques to see whether differences observed over time in networks are due to simply different samples from a distribution of links and nodes or changes over time in the underlying distribution of links and nodes  </p>
<p>

•	Developing control processes for networks over time</p>
<p>

•	Developing algorithms to change distributions of links in networks over time</p>
<p>

•	Developing algorithms to track groups in networks over time.</p>
<p>

•	Developing tools to extract or locate networks from various data sources such as texts.  </p>
<p>

•	Developing statistically valid measurements on networks over time.  </p>
<p>

•	Examining the robustness of network metrics under various types of missing data  </p>
<p>

•	Empirical studies of multi-mode multi-link multi-time period networks </p>
<p>

•	Examining networks as probabilistic time-variant phenomena</p>
<p>

•	Forecasting change in existing networks  </p>
<p>

•	Identifying trails through time given a sequence of networks.</p>
<p>

•	Identifying changes in node criticality given a sequence of networks anything else related to multi-mode multi-link multi-time period networks.</p>
<p>

<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/17363635.xml">
Kathleen Carley</link></scientist>
, of <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/48093.xml">
Carnegie Mellon University</link></university>
, is the leading authority in this field.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kathleen M. Carley, 2003, “Dynamic Network Analysis” in Dynamic Social Network Modeling and Analysis: Workshop Summary and Papers, Ronald Breiger, Kathleen Carley, and Philippa Pattison, (Eds.) Committee on Human Factors, National Research Council, National Research Council. Pp. 133-145, Washington, DC. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kathleen M. Carley, 2002, “Smart Agents and Organizations of the Future”  The Handbook of New Media. Edited by Leah Lievrouw and Sonia Livingstone, Ch. 12, pp. 206-220, Thousand Oaks, CA, Sage.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kathleen M. Carley, Jana Diesner, Jeffrey Reminga, Maksim Tsvetovat, 2008, Toward an Interoperable Dynamic Network Analysis Toolkit, DSS Special Issue on Cyberinfrastructure for Homeland Security: Advances in Information Sharing, Data Mining, and Collaboration Systems. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/01679236">
Decision Support Systems</weblink> 43(4):1324-1347 (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6V8S-4KGG5P7-1&amp;_user=4422&amp;_coverDate=08%2F31%2F2007&amp;_rdoc=20&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=browse&amp;_srch=doc-info(%23toc%235878%232007%23999569995%23665759%23FLA%23display%23Volume)&amp;_cdi=5878&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;_ct=52&amp;_acct=C000059600&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=4422&amp;md5=9459e84d7a8863039c7abd5065266250">
article 20</weblink>)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/17590563.xml">
Network dynamics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/17590530.xml">
Sequential dynamical system</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eecs.harvard.edu/%7Eparkes/RadcliffeSeminar.htm">
Radcliffe Exploratory Seminar on Dynamic Networks</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/">
Center for Computational Analysis of Social and Organizational Systems (CASOS)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
