<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:35:39[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Holographic associative memory</title>
<id>5176484</id>
<revision>
<id>227625011</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-24T13:32:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>WriterHound</username>
<id>266293</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Miscellaneous articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing context</category>
<category>Wikipedia introduction cleanup</category>
<category>Computing articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Holographic memory</category>
<category>Articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Pages needing expert attention</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The introduction to this article provides <b>insufficient context</b> for those unfamiliar with the subject.
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Holographic_associative_memory&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink> with a .</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.</b><p>

  may be able to help recruit one.
If a more appropriate  or 
portalexists, please adjust this template accordingly.</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>Holographic Associative Memory</b> is part of the family of analog, correlation-based, associative, stimulus-response memories, where information is mapped onto the phase orientation of complex numbers operating.  It can be considered as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/5826.xml">
complex</link> valued <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
artificial neural network</link>. The holographic associative memory exhibits some remarkable characteristics. Holographs have been shown to be effective for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/433011.xml">
associative memory</link> tasks, generalization, and pattern recognition with changeable attention. Ability of dynamic search localization is central to natural memory. For example, in visual perception, humans always tend to focus on some specific objects in a pattern. Humans can effortlessly change the focus from object to object without requiring relearning. It provides a computational model which can mimic this ability by creating representation for focus. At the heart of this new memory lies a novel bi-modal representation of pattern and a hologram-like complex spherical weight state-space. Besides the usual advantages of associative computing, this technique also has excellent potential for fast optical realization because the underlying hyper-spherical computations can be naturally implemented on optical computations.</p>

<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4236510.xml">
Holographic Memory</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/17770991.xml">
AND Corporation</link></institution>
</company>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Bibliography</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sutherland, J., Holographic Models of Memory, Learning and Expression, <it>International J. of Neural Systems</it>, 1(3), 1990, pp356-267</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 J. I. Khan. <it>Attention Modulated Associative Computing and Content-Associative Search in Image Archive</it>. PhD thesis, University of Hawaii, August 1995.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 K. I. Khan and D. Y. Yun. Characteristics of Multidimensional Holographic Associative Memory in Retrieval with Dynamically Localizable Attention. <it>IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks</it>, 9(3):389–406, May 1998.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HE Michel, AAS Awwal, Enhanced artificial neural networks using complex numbers , <it>Neural Networks</it>, 1999. Proceedings. 1999 IEEE International Joint Conference on</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 R Stoop, J Buchli, G Keller, WH Steeb, Stochastic resonance in pattern recognition by a holographic neuron model, <it>Physical Review E</it>, 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Y Hendra, RP Gopalan, MG Nair, A method for dynamic indexing of large image databases, <it>Systems, Man, and Cybernetics</it>, 1999. IEEE SMC'99.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HE Michel, S Kunjithapatham, Processing Landsat TM data using complex-valued neural networks, <it>Proceedings of SPIE</it>, the International Society for Optical, 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 RP Gopalan, G Lee , Indexing of Image Databases Using Untrained 4D Holographic Memory Model, <it>15th Australian Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence</it>, - Springer Page 1. RI McKay and J. Slaney (Eds.): AI 2002, LNAI 2557, pp. 237–248. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 RWTH Aachen, IH Ney, Approaches to Invariant Image Object Recognition, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.i6.informatik.rwth-aachen.de">
http://www.i6.informatik.rwth-aachen.de</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
