<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:35:50[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<work  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100575741">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<service  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100577525">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Office of Field Operations</title>
<id>5181341</id>
<revision>
<id>240315239</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-22T23:05:10Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bankbryan</username>
<id>3484992</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>United States Department of Homeland Security</category>
<category>Customs services</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/757040.xml">
U.S. Customs and Border Protection</link> <b>Office of Field Operations</b> directs the activities of more than 25,000 employees, including more than 20,000 CBP Officers and Agriculture Specialists, and oversees the programs and operations at 20 Field Operations offices, 317 ports of entry and 14 preclearance stations in Canada, Ireland and the Caribbean. <p>

The office with an operating budget of $2.5 billion is responsible for Immigration Policy and Programs that includes all immigration issues related to the admission and exclusion of aliens as well as agricultural inspection at all ports of entry to protect the health of U.S. plant and animal resources and the facilitation of their movement in the global market place.</p>
<p>

Additionally, it is responsible for Border Security and Facilitation, including Interdiction and Security, Passenger Operations, Targeting and Analysis and Canine Enforcement and for Trade Compliance and Facilitation which includes Cargo Entry and Release, Summary Operations, Trade Risk Management and Enforcement, and Seizures and Penalties as well as expanding Trade operations to focus on Anti-Terrorism.</p>
<p>

The Office is headed by Assistant Commissioner Thomas S. Winkowski.</p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbp.gov/xp/cgov/toolbox/about/organization/assist_comm_off/field_operations.xml">
Official site</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</article>
