<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:38:28[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Katchalski-Katzir algorithm</title>
<id>5198590</id>
<revision>
<id>231035084</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-10T15:46:46Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Tristan Morin</username>
<id>531375</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Molecular modelling</category>
<category>Computational chemistry</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Katchalski-Katzir algorithm</b> is an algorithm for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/2292623.xml">
docking</link> of rigid molecules, developed by <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/1006658.xml">
Ephraim Katchalski/Katzir</link></president>
.<p>

It is a purely geometric algorithm, but some extensions of it also implement electrostatics.</p>
<p>

The algorithm's first step is mapping the molecules onto grids, with each point of a grid being marked as either:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 outside the molecule</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 on the molecule's surface</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 inside the molecule</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The algorithm increases the surface contact and minimizes volume overlap. It is straightforward to compute such a score for a single alignment, but there are too many possible ways to align the molecules to simply iterate over them all.</p>
<p>

To compute the scores for many alignments efficiently, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/11512.xml">
Fast Fourier Transform</link> is applied to both grids. Having the grids in FFT form let the scoring to be computed for many different alignments very quickly.</p>
<p>

The Katchalski-Katzir algorithm is a fast but rather limited algorithm. It is usually used to quickly filter out the obviously wrong candidate structures. A structure may have good Katchalski-Katzir score (that is, fit well geometrically), but be a very bad fit overall, for example due to unfavourable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/368328.xml">
electrostatic</link> interactions or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/14136.xml">
hydrophobic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/79293.xml">
hydrophilic</link> groups facing each other. This is not a serious problem, as such structures can be filtered out later. A bigger issue is when a favourable structure is rejected by the algorithm. Some cases where this may happen include bad geometric fit being overcome by very strong attractive forces, or where the shape of the target changes because of the interactions (<link>
induced fit</link>).</p>
<p>

A popular program that implements the Katchalski-Katzir algorithm is <link>
FTDock</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/53268.xml">
convolution theorem</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/734256.xml">
Molecular modelling</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Katchalski-Katzir E, Shariv I, Eisenstein M, Friesem AA, Aflalo C, and Vakser IA (1992). Molecular surface recognition: determination of geometric fit between proteins and their ligands by correlation techniques. <it>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</it>, <b>89</b>:2195–2199.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
