<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:22:43[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Cipher</title>
<id>5244</id>
<revision>
<id>240039359</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-21T17:42:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SDC</username>
<id>181435</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since May 2008</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Ciphers</category>
<category>Cryptography</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Mergefrom.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that  be  into this article or section. ()</col>
</row>
</table>


For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/8122971.xml">
Cipher (disambiguation)</link>.
"Ciphers" redirects here. For the ambient album, see <album wordnetid="106591815" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/5240031.xml">
Ciphers (album)</link></album>
.
In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
cryptography</link>, a <b>cipher</b> (or <b>cypher</b>) is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> for performing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
decryption</link> &mdash; a series of well-defined steps that can be followed as a procedure. An alternative term is <b>encipherment</b>. In non-technical usage, a “cipher” is the same thing as a “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/838989.xml">
code</link>”; however, the concepts are distinct in cryptography. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/705892.xml">
classical cryptography</link>, ciphers were distinguished from codes.  
Codes operated by substituting according to a large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/530786.xml">
codebook</link> which linked a random string of characters or numbers to a word or phrase.  For example, “UQJHSE” could be the code for “Proceed to the following coordinates”. When using a cipher the original information is known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/157935.xml">
plaintext</link>, and the encrypted form as <b>ciphertext</b>. The ciphertext message contains all the information of the plaintext message, but is not in a format readable by a human or computer without the proper mechanism to decrypt it; it should resemble random gibberish to those not intended to read it.<p>

The operation of a cipher usually depends on a piece of auxiliary information, called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/53039.xml">
key</link> or, in traditional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/21939.xml">
NSA</link> parlance, a <b>cryptovariable.</b> The encrypting procedure is varied depending on the key, which changes the detailed operation of the algorithm. A key must be selected before using a cipher to encrypt a message. Without knowledge of the key, it should be difficult, if not nearly impossible, to decrypt the resulting cipher into readable plaintext.</p>
<p>

Most modern ciphers can be categorized in several ways:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 By whether they work on blocks of symbols usually of a fixed size (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/4594.xml">
block cipher</link>s), or on a continuous stream of symbols (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/49007.xml">
stream cipher</link>s).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 By whether the same key is used for both encryption and decryption (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/53042.xml">
symmetric key algorithm</link>s), or if a different key is used for each (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
asymmetric key algorithm</link>s). If the algorithm is symmetric, the key must be known to the recipient and to no one else. If the algorithm is an asymmetric one, the encyphering key is different from, but closely related to, the decyphering key. If one key cannot be deduced from the other, the asymmetric key algorithm has the public/private key property and one of the keys may be made public without loss of confidentiality. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/352709.xml">
Feistel cipher</link> uses a combination of substitution and transposition techniques. Most block cipher algorithms are based on this structure.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
Etymology of “Cipher”</st>
<p>

“Cipher” (Middle French as <it>cifre</it> and Medieval Latin as <it>cifra,</it> from the Arabic <it>sifr</it> = zero) is alternatively spelled “cypher” (however, this variant is now uncommon); similarly “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
ciphertext</link>” and “<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
cyphertext</link>”, and so forth. </p>
<p>

The word “cipher” in former times meant “zero” and had the same origin (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/34513.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Etymology%22])">
Zero — Etymology</link>), and later was used for any decimal digit, even any number. There are these theories about how the word “cipher” may have come to mean encoding:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Encoding often involved numbers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/25657.xml">
Roman number system</link> was very cumbersome because there was no concept of zero (or empty space). The concept of zero (which was also called “cipher”), which we all now think of as natural, was very alien in medieval Europe, so confusing and ambiguous to common Europeans that in arguments people would say “talk clearly and not so far fetched as a cipher”. Cipher came to mean concealment of clear messages or encryption.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The French formed the word “chiffre” and adopted the Italian word “zero”.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The English used “zero” for “0”, and “cipher” from the word “ciphering” as a means of computing.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The Germans used the words “Ziffer” (digit, “Zahl”) and “Chiffre”.</entry>
</list>

Dr. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/8622924.xml">
Al-Kadi</link> (ref-3) concluded that the Arabic word <it>sifr</it>, for the digit zero, developed into the European technical term for encryption.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ciphers versus codes</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/838989.xml">
Code (cryptography)</link></it>
</indent>
In non-technical usage, a “(secret) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/838989.xml">
code</link>” typically means a “cipher”. Within technical discussions, however, the words “code” and “cipher” refer to two different concepts. Codes work at the level of meaning — that is, words or phrases are converted into something else and this chunking generally shortens the message. </p>
<p>

An example of this is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/679207.xml">
Telegraph Code</link> which were used to shorten long telegraph messages which resulted from entering into commercial contracts using exchanges of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/30010.xml">
Telegram</link>s.</p>
<p>

Ciphers, on the other hand, work at a lower level: the level of individual letters, small groups of letters, or, in modern schemes, individual bits. Some systems used both codes and ciphers in one system, using  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/1062541.xml">
superencipherment</link> to increase the security. In some cases the terms codes and ciphers are also used synonymously to substitution and transposition. </p>
<p>

Historically, cryptography was split into a dichotomy of codes and ciphers; and coding had its own terminology, analogous to that for ciphers: “<it>encoding</it>, <it>codetext</it>, <it>decoding</it>” and so on.</p>
<p>

However, codes have a variety of drawbacks, including susceptibility to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/5715.xml">
cryptanalysis</link> and the difficulty of managing a cumbersome <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/530786.xml">
codebook</link>. Because of this, codes have fallen into disuse in modern cryptography, and ciphers are the dominant technique.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Types of cipher</st>
<p>

There are a variety of different types of encryption. Algorithms used earlier in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/520066.xml">
history of cryptography</link> are substantially different from modern methods, and modern ciphers can be classified according to how they operate and whether they use one or two keys.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Historical ciphers</st>
<p>

Historical pen and paper ciphers used in the past are sometimes known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/705892.xml">
classical cipher</link>s. They include simple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/48356.xml">
substitution cipher</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/48358.xml">
transposition cipher</link>s. For example “GOOD DOG” can be encrypted as “PLLX XLP” where “L” substitutes for “O”, “P” for “G”, and “X” for “D” in the message.  Transposition of the letters “GOOD DOG” can result in “DGOGDOO”. These simple ciphers and examples are easy to crack, even without plaintext-ciphertext pairs.</p>
<p>

Simple ciphers were replaced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/157918.xml">
polyalphabetic substitution</link> ciphers which changed the substitution alphabet for every letter.  For example “GOOD DOG” can be encrypted as “PLSX TWF” where “L”, “S”, and “W” substitute for “O”.  With even a small amount of known or estimated plaintext, simple polyalphabetic substitution ciphers and letter transposition ciphers designed for pen and paper encryption are easy to crack.</p>
<p>

During the early twentieth century, electro-mechanical machines were invented to do encryption and decryption using transposition, polyalphabetic substitution, and a kind of “additive” substitution.  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/196223.xml">
rotor machine</link>s, several rotor disks provided polyalphabetic substitution, while plug boards provided another substitution. Keys were easily changed by changing the rotor disks and the plugboard wires. Although these encryption methods were more complex than previous schemes and required machines to encrypt and decrypt, other machines such as the British <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/615354.xml">
Bombe</link></machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
 were invented to crack these encryption methods. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Modern ciphers</st>
<p>

Modern encryption methods can be divided by two criteria: by type of key used, and by type of input data.</p>
<p>

By type of key used ciphers are divided into:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/53042.xml">
symmetric key algorithm</link>s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/53042.xml">
Private-key cryptography</link>), where the same key is used for encryption and decryption, and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
asymmetric key algorithm</link>s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
Public-key cryptography</link>), where two different keys are used for encryption and decryption.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In a symmetric key algorithm (e.g., <cipher wordnetid="106254239" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/7978.xml">
DES</link></cipher>
 and <cipher wordnetid="106254239" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/1260.xml">
AES</link></cipher>
), the sender and receiver must have a shared key set up in advance and kept secret from all other parties; the sender uses this key for encryption, and the receiver uses the same key for decryption. In an asymmetric key algorithm (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/25385.xml">
RSA</link>), there are two separate keys: a <it>public key</it> is published and enables any sender to perform encryption, while a <it>private key</it> is kept secret by the receiver and enables only him to perform correct decryption.</p>
<p>

Type of input ciphers data can be distinguished into two types:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/4594.xml">
block cipher</link>s, which encrypt block of data of fixed size, and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/49007.xml">
stream cipher</link>s, which encrypt continuous streams of data</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<image location="center" width="550px" src="Cipher-taxonomy.svg">
</image>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Key Size and Vulnerability</st>
<p>

In a pure mathematical attack (i.e., lacking any other information to help break a cipher), three factors above all, count:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mathematical advances that allow new attacks or weaknesses to be discovered and exploited.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Computational power available, i.e., the computing power which can be brought to bear on the problem. It is important to note that average performance/capacity of a single computer is not the only factor to consider. An adversary can use multiple computers at once, for instance, to increase the speed of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/103127.xml">
exhaustive search</link> for a key (i.e., “brute force” attack) substantially.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/5749.xml">
Key size</link>, i.e., the size of key used to encrypt a message. As the key size increases, so does the complexity of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/103127.xml">
exhaustive search</link> to the point where it becomes infeasible to crack encryption directly.</entry>
</list>

Since the desired effect is computational difficulty, in theory one would choose an algorithm and desired difficulty level, thus decide the key length accordingly.</p>
<p>

An example of this process can be found at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.keylength.com/">
Key Length</weblink> which uses multiple reports to suggest that a symmetric cipher with 128 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/3364.xml">
bit</link>s, an asymmetric cipher with 3072 bit keys, and an elliptic curve cipher with 512 bits, all have similar difficulty at present.</p>
<p>

<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/5693.xml">
Claude Shannon</link></scientist>
 proved, using information theory considerations, that any theoretically unbreakable cipher must have keys which are at least as long as the plaintext, and used only once: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/22210.xml">
one-time pad</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Helen Fouché Gaines, “Cryptanalysis”, 1939, Dover. ISBN 0-486-20097-3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/8622924.xml">
Ibrahim A. Al-Kadi</link>, “The origins of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/5143.xml">
cryptology</link>: The Arab contributions”, <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/542527.xml">
Cryptologia</link></publication>
</periodical>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
, 16(2) (April 1992) pp. 97–126.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ibrahim A. Al-Kadi, “Cryptography and Data Security: Cryptographic Properties of Arabic”, proceedings of the Third Saudi Engineering Conference. Riyadh, Saudi Arabia: Nov 24-27, Vol 2:910-921., 1991.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<journalist wordnetid="110224578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/578052.xml">
David Kahn</link></journalist>
</scholar>
</historian>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
, <it>The Codebreakers - The Story of Secret Writing</it> (ISBN 0-684-83130-9) (1967)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<cryptanalyst wordnetid="109981540" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<decoder wordnetid="109995398" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/477032.xml">
Abraham Sinkov</link></decoder>
</scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</cryptanalyst>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <it>Elementary Cryptanalysis: A Mathematical Approach</it>, Mathematical Association of America, 1966. ISBN 0-88385-622-0</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/966625.xml">
William Stallings</link></writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
, <it>Cryptography and Network Security, principles and practices, 4th Edition</it></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/6594053.xml">
Cover-coding</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/3176372.xml">
Cryptography Classification</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/2285143.xml">
Encryption software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/449381.xml">
Famous ciphertexts</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/17176456.xml">
Kish cypher</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/23080.xml">
Pretty Good Privacy</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/28733.xml">
Steganography</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/679207.xml">
Telegraph code</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wiktionary-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wiktionary
</caption>
</image>

Look up  in <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/156658.xml">
Wiktionary</link></web_site>
, the free dictionary.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.securitydocs.com/Encryption">
SecurityDocs Resource for encryption whitepapers</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xml-dev.com/lurker/list/crypto.en.html">
Accumulative archive of various cryptography mailing lists.</weblink> Includes Cryptography list at metzdowd and SecurityFocus Crypto list.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hf-ssb-transceiver.at-communication.com/en/secure/seu_8210_tactical.html">
Voice and Data Ciphering</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks  " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#ccf;" class="navbox-title">
&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
Cryptography</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/520066.xml">
History of cryptography</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/5715.xml">
Cryptanalysis</link> | 
Cryptography portal | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/449585.xml">
Topics in cryptography</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/53042.xml">
Symmetric-key algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/4594.xml">
Block cipher</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/49007.xml">
Stream cipher</link> | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
Public-key cryptography</link> | <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<primitive wordnetid="109627462" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/439526.xml">
Cryptographic hash function</link></primitive>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/567523.xml">
Message authentication code</link> | <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/182249.xml">
Random numbers</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 | <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/28733.xml">
Steganography</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
