<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:43:25[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Observational learning</title>
<id>52462</id>
<revision>
<id>244188450</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T18:32:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>VolkovBot</username>
<id>3035831</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Social learning theory</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/330176.xml">
Social learning</link>.
<b>Observational learning</b> (also known as: <b>vicarious learning</b> or <b>social learning</b> or <b>modeling</b> or <b>monkey see, monkey do</b>) is learning that occurs as a function of observing, retaining and, in the case of imitation learning, replicating novel behavior executed by others. It is most associated with the work of psychologist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/237253.xml">
Albert Bandura</link>, who implemented some of the seminal studies in the area and initiated <b>social learning theory</b>.  It involves the process of learning to copy or model the action of another through observing another doing it. Further research has been used to show a connection between observational learning and both classical and operant conditioning.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

There are 4 key processes of observational learning.
1.) Attention: To learn through observation, you must pay attention to another person's behavior and its consequences.
2.) Retention: Store a mental representation of what you have witnessed in your memory.
3.) Reproduction: Enacting a modeled response depends on your ability to reproduce the response by converting your stored mental images into overt behavior.
4.) Motivation: Finally, you are unlikely to reproduce an observed response unless you are motivated to do so. Your motivation depends on whether you get benefits from responding that action. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Many mistake observational learning with imitation.  The two terms are different in the sense that observational learning leads to a change in behavior due to observing a model.  This does not mean that the behavior exhibited by the model is duplicated.  It could mean that the observer would do the opposite of the model behavior because he or she has learned the consequence of that particular behavior. Consider the case of learning what NOT to do. In such a case, there is observational learning without imitation.</p>
<p>

Although observational learning can take place at any stage in life, it is thought to be particularly important during <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/167331.xml">
childhood</link>, particularly as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/170653.xml">
authority</link> becomes important. The best role models are those a year or two older for observational learning.  Because of this, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/330102.xml">
social learning theory</link> has influenced debates on the effect of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/29831.xml">
television</link> violence and parental <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/178653.xml">
role model</link>s. Bandura's <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<scientific_research wordnetid="100641820" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="100639556" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<research wordnetid="100636921" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/540025.xml">
Bobo doll experiment</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</research>
</act>
</investigation>
</experiment>
</event>
</scientific_research>
</work>
 is widely cited in psychology as a demonstration of observational learning and demonstrated that children are more likely to engage in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/46112.xml">
violent</link> play with a life size rebounding doll after watching an adult do the same. However, it may be that children will only reproduce a model's behavior if it has been reinforced. This may be the problem with television because it was found, by Otto Larson and his coworkers (1968), that 56% of the time children's television characters achieve their goals through violent acts.</p>
<p>

Observational learning allows for learning without any change in behavior and has therefore been used as an argument against strict <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/540801.xml">
behaviorism</link> which argued that behavior change must occur for new behaviors to be acquired. Bandura noted that "social imitation may hasten or short-cut the acquisition of new behaviors without the necessity of reinforcing successive approximations as suggested by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/4868.xml">
Skinner</link></scientist>
 (1953)."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> </p>
<p>

It is possible to treat observational learning as merely a variation of operant training.  According to this view, first proposed by Neal Miller and John Dollard, the changes in an observer's behavior are due to the consequences of the <it>observer's</it> behavior, not those of the model. "<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>"</p>
<p>

As an interesting aside, there are a number of variables which have confounded the study of observational learning in animals.  One of these is the Venus Effect in which animals are sexually stimulated by the model and this interferes with the ability to observe behavior thereby limiting the ability to make associations based on the behavior of the model.  (See Warden and Jackson 1935)</p>

<sec>
<st>
Required conditions</st>

<p>

Bandura called the process of social learning <it>modeling</it> and gave four conditions required for a person to successfully model the behavior of someone else:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Attention to the model</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

A person must first pay attention to a person engaging in a certain behavior (the model). </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Retention of details</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

Once attending to the observed behavior, the observer must be able to effectively remember what the model has done.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Motor reproduction</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The observer must be able to replicate the behavior being observed. For example, juggling cannot be effectively learned by observing a model juggler if the observer does not already have the ability to perform the component actions (throwing and catching a ball).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Motivation and Opportunity</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

The observer must be motivated to carry out the action they have observed and remembered, and must have the opportunity to do so. For example, a suitably skilled person must want to replicate the behavior of a model juggler, and needs to have an appropriate number of items to juggle at hand.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Effect on behavior</st>

<p>

Social learning may affect behavior in the following ways:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Teaches new behaviors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Increases or decreases the frequency with which previously learned behaviors are carried out</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Can encourage previously forbidden behaviors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Can increase or decrease similar behaviors. For example, observing a model excelling in piano playing may encourage an observer to excel in playing the saxophone.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/237253.xml">
Albert Bandura</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<scientific_research wordnetid="100641820" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="100639556" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<research wordnetid="100636921" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/540025.xml">
Bobo doll experiment</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</research>
</act>
</investigation>
</experiment>
</event>
</scientific_research>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/5647658.xml">
Cognitive imitation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/183403.xml">
learning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/464804.xml">
social cognition</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/317465.xml">
inference</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/10332.xml">
educational psychology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/1944675.xml">
educational technology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/19356049.xml">
Emulation (observational learning)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/577858.xml">
Imitation</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References and external links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bandura, Albert, Ross, Dorothea, &amp; Ross, Sheila A. (1961). Transmission of aggressions through imitation of aggressive models. <it>Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology</it>, 63, 575-582 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Bandura/bobo.htm">
Full text</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bandura, A. (1977) <it>Social Learning Theory</it>. New Jersey: Prentice Hall. Hardback: ISBN 0-13-816744-3, Paperback: ISBN 0-13-816751-6</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vicariouslearning.com/blog/">
Vicarious Learning Blog</weblink>: Vicarious Learning, Observational Learning, Knowledge Management and eLearning.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading on animal social learning</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Galef, B.G. &amp; Laland, K.N. (2005). Social learning in animals: Empirical studies and theoretical models. <it>Bioscience, 55,</it> 489-499. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://anthropology.tamu.edu/faculty/alvard/ANTH689%20Fall%202005/week%204/GALEF%20%20AND%20LALAND%202005.pdf">
Full text</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Zentall, T.R. (2006). Imitation: Definitions, evidence, and mechanisms. <it>Animal Cognition, 9,</it> 335-353. (A thorough review of different types of social learning) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cogs.indiana.edu/spackled/imitation.pdf">
Full text</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Westen, D., Burton, L. &amp; Kowalski, R. (2006) Psychology: Australian and New Zealand Edition. Milton, QLD. John Wiley and Sons.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Wayne Weiten,Thomson Wadsworth.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Bandura, A., Ross, D., &amp; Ross, S. A. (1961). Transmission of aggressions through imitation of aggressive models. <it>Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology, 63</it>, 575-582. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www3.georgetown.edu/departments/psychology/resources/researchmethods/examples/9304.html">
Full text</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
Chance, Paul, (2006) Learing and behavior,289-290,</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
