<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:14:14[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Sousveillance</title>
<id>528064</id>
<revision>
<id>242521921</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T16:10:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Atlantima</username>
<id>110228</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Culture jamming techniques</category>
<category>Civil disobedience</category>
<category>Sociology</category>
<category>French words and phrases</category>
<category>Technology in society</category>
<category>Blogs</category>
<category>Surveillance</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Sousveillance-necklace.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

This wearable wireless webcam captures a recording of the wearer's personal experience.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Sousveillance</b> (IPA:&nbsp;, original <it>French</it> [suvɛjɑ̃s]) as well as <b>inverse surveillance</b> are terms coined by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/88785.xml">
Steve Mann</link> to describe the recording of an activity from the perspective of a participant in the activity,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> typically by way of small portable or wearable recording devices that often stream continuous live video to the Internet.</p>
<p>

<b>Inverse surveillance</b> is a proper subset of sourveillance with a particular emphasis on "watchful vigilance from underneath" and a form of surveillance inquiry or legal protection involving the recording, monitoring, study, or analysis of surveillance systems, proponents of surveillance, and possibly also recordings of authority figures and their actions.  Inverse surveillance is typically an activity undertaken by those who are generally the subject of surveillance, and may thus be thought of as a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/152626.xml">
ethnography</link> or <link>
ethnomethodology</link> study (i.e. an analysis of the surveilled from the perspective of a participant in a society under surveillance).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Sousveillance typically involves community-based recording from first person perspectives, without necessarily involving any specific political agenda, whereas inverse-surveillance is a form of sousveillance that is typically directed at, or used to collect data to analyze or study, surveillance or its proponents.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Etymology </st>


<p>

The term "sousveillance" stems from the contrasting French words <it>sur</it>, meaning "above", and <it>sous</it>, meaning "below", i.e. "surveillance" denotes the "eye-in-the-sky" watching from above, whereas "sousveillance" denotes bringing the camera or other means of observation down to human level, either physically (mounting cameras on people rather than on buildings), or hierarchically (ordinary people doing the watching, rather than higher authorities or architectures doing the watching).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Inverse surveillance </st>

<p>

Inverse surveillance is a type of sousveillance.  The more general concept of sousveillance goes beyond just inverse surveillance and the associated twentieth century political "us <it>versus</it> them" framework for citizens to photograph <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/23627.xml">
police</link>,  shoppers to photograph shopkeepers, or passengers to photograph taxicab drivers. (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thefeature.com/article?articleid=100537">
Rheingold</weblink> notes that it's much like the pedestrian-driver concept, i.e. these are roles that many of us take both sides of, from time to time.)</p>
<p>

One of the things that brought inverse surveillance to light was the reactions of security guards to <link>
electric seeing aid</link>s and similar sousveillance practices.  It seemed, early on, that the more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/52648.xml">
camera</link>s that were in an establishment, the more the guards disliked the use of an electric seeing aid, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/563320.xml">
EyeTap</link> eyeglasses, by the public.  It was through simply wearing electric seeing aids, as a passive observer, that it was discovered that surveillance and sousveillance can cause conflict and sometimes confrontation.  This led some researchers to explore why the perpetuators of surveillance are suspicious of sousveillance, and thus defined the notion of inverse surveillance as a new and interesting facet of studies in sousveillance.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Personal sousveillance </st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="WearableWirelessWebcamSteveMannVisualFilter1994December13th.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Steve Visual Filter for continuous live webcast as well as viewing (i.e. visual reality modification in realtime).
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Dsc090pq.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Sousveillance devices for <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
ACM</link></organization>
's CFP2005.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Personal sousveillance is the art, science, and technology of personal experience capture, processing, storage, retrieval, and transmission, such as lifelong audiovisual recording by way of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/5904.xml">
cybernetic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/72750.xml">
prosthetics</link>, such as seeing-aids, visual memory aids, and the like. Even today's personal sousveillance technologies like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/667163.xml">
camera phone</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/33645.xml">
weblogs</link> tend to build a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/3130789.xml">
sense of community</link>, in contrast to surveillance that some have said is corrosive to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/5695.xml">
community</link>.</p>
<p>

The legal, ethical, and policy issues surrounding personal sousveillance are largely yet to be explored, but there are close parallels to the social and legal norms surrounding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/91221.xml">
recording of telephone conversations</link>.  When one or more parties to the conversation record it, we call that sousveillance, whereas when the conversation is recorded by a person who is not a party to the conversation (such as a prison guard violating a client-lawyer relationship), we call the recording "surveillance". </p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
the United States of America</link>, audio sousveillance is allowed in most states, and by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/77749.xml">
U.S. Federal law</link>, and this allowance for recording by at least one party is also true in most other countries.</p>
<p>

"Targeted sousveillance" refers to sousveillance of a specific individual by one or more other individuals.  Usually the targeted individual is a representative or proponent of surveillance, so targeted sousveillance is often Inverse Surveillance (<b>hierarchical sousveillance</b>).</p>
<p>

"Hierarchical sousveillance" refers, for example, to citizens photographing police, shoppers photographing shopkeepers, or taxicab passengers photographing cab drivers.  So, for example, targeting former White House security official Admiral <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/65504.xml">
John Poindexter</link></person>
 with sousveillance follows this more political narrative. Classy's Kitchen describes sousveillance as  "another way to add further introspection to the commons that keeps society open but still makes the world smaller and safer". In this way sousveillance may be regarded as a possible replacement for surveillance.  In this sur/sousveillance replacement, one can consider an operative social norm that would require cameras to be attached to a human operator.  Under such a scenario, objections to the camera can be raised by another human more easily than it is to interact with a lamp post upon which is mounted a surveillance camera.  Thus the argument is that cameras attached to people ought to be less offensive than cameras attached to inanimate objects, because there is at least one responsible party present to operate the camera.  This responsible-party argument is analogous to that used for operation of a motor vehicle, where a responsible driver is present, in contrast to remote or automated operation of a motor vehicle.</p>
<p>

Beyond the political or breaching of hierarchical structure explored in academia, the more rapidly emerging discourse on sousveillance within industry is "personal sousveillance", namely the recording of an activity by a participant in the activity. In this sense, the <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../601/168601.xml">
Rodney King</link></person>
 video was captured serendipitously by a citizen participating in a civil society. There was no political motive (i.e. the officers who were beating King were not targeted), and the material was captured more serendipitously. </p>
<p>

As the technologies get smaller and easier to use, the capture, recording, and playback of everyday life gets that much easier. For example, David Ollila, a manufacturer of video camera equipment, was trapped for four hours aboard a <airline wordnetid="102690081" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/253035.xml">
Comair</link></airline>
 plane at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/97218.xml">
JFK Airport</link> in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/645042.xml">
New York City</link></village>
. When he filmed an interview with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/66691.xml">
pilot</link> about the situation, the pilot called the police who removed Ollila for questioning and removed everyone from the plane.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

In the limit, when the effort falls low enough, personal experience capture can be done without conscious thought or effort, wherein the person capturing the information becomes a "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/6838.xml">
cyborg</link>" in the <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<inventor wordnetid="110214637" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<pianist wordnetid="110430665" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/14907770.xml">
Manfred Clynes</link></pianist>
</inventor>
</artist>
</scientist>
</person>
 sense. The "Sensecam" works this way, as does Gordon Bell's project at <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
. A logfile made in this way, with zero effort, is known as a <link>
CyborgLog</link>. </p>
<p>

The most widespread sousveillance has spread without conscious design. Camera phones, digital cameras and digital video cameras have proliferated, affording the opportunity of easy, unobtrusive documentation using snapshots, videos and audio. The simplicity of a wearable camera phone makes cyborglogging possible simply by walking around in ordinary day-to-day life.  Other devices such as a Holter heart monitor can add additional tracks to an audiovisual cyborglog that make the 'glog useful for personal safety and health monitoring.</p>
<p>

Recording a situation is only part of the sousveillance process. Communicating is also important. This is where video-sharing sites such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/3524766.xml">
YouTube</link></company>
 and photo-sharing sites such as <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/1178458.xml">
Flickr</link></web_site>
 are important. For example, police <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/485005.xml">
agent provocateur</link>s</it> were quickly revealed on YouTube when they infiltrated a demonstration in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/512220.xml">
Montebello</link> <district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/7954867.xml">
Quebec</link></district>
 against the leaders of <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
, <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/3966054.xml">
Mexico</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 and the United States (August <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>). When the head of the Quebec police publicly stated that there was no police presence, a sousveillance video showed him to be wrong. When he revised his statement to say that the police provocateurs were peaceful observers, the same video showed them to be masked, wearing police boots, and holding a rock.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=St1-WTc1kow">
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=St1-WTc1kow</weblink>.  There are many similar examples, such as the widely-viewed <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/3524766.xml">
YouTube</link></company>
 video of UCLA campus policemen tasering a <controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/7974318.xml">
student</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</disagreement>
</dispute>
</event>
</controversy>
 (November <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>): <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AyvrqcxNIFs">
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AyvrqcxNIFs</weblink>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Industrial interest in sousveillance </st>

<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
 is also exploring cyborglogs, as are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/13973.xml">
Hewlett Packard</link>, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/21242.xml">
Nokia</link></company>
, and many others.  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../484/617484.xml">
Joi Ito</link></person>
's use of the camera phone approaches the idea of a cyborglog, in the sense that his images are sent often, and with little conscious thought or effort.
Ito is part of the Program Committee for the <link>
International Conference on Sousveillance</link>, along with the attendees of the <link>
International Workshop on Inverse Surveillance</link>.</p>
<p>

The recent industrial and corporate interest in sousveillance has led to a recent satire of the sousveillance industry.  Thus it appears there may be two different "sousveillance factions", one using it as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../729/162729.xml">
detournement</link> (in the Situationist tradition) to subvert the Panoptic gaze, while the other using it in a more commercial everyday sense.  Of course the two "factions" are not necessarily irreconcileable, in the sense that high-art culture and "low-art" culture are often held to be indistinguishable in the postmodern world.  In other words, the  co-opting of the subversive nature of sousveillance by industry may well be just another example of art-in-action.  Conversely many artists are using the commercialization of sousveillance itself as a social commentary, thus creating a detournement of a detournement of the detournement of surveillance.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Social software as surveillance and sousveillance </st>
<p>

<image width="200px" src="BikeCamera.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Cameras can easily be mounted on bicycles, to record sports activities.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/222034.xml">
Social software</link> such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/7529378.xml">
Facebook</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/1270655.xml">
MySpace</link></company>
 aid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/87231.xml">
surveillance</link> by encouraging people to publish their interests and their friendship networks. They also aid sousveillance by making this information available to peer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
networks</link> as well as to the authorities.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Sousveillance activism as a form of inverse surveillance </st>

<p>

Since the year <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/8359.xml">
December 24</link>th has been <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/2813472.xml">
World Sousveillance Day</link> with groups of participants in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/8210131.xml">
New York</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/64646.xml">
Toronto</link></village>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/3775.xml">
Boston</link>, <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/18933066.xml">
Florida</link></symbol>
, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/32706.xml">
Vancouver</link></village>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/15573.xml">
Japan</link>, <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, and the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
.  However, this designated day focuses only on hierarchical sousveillance, whereas there are a number of groups around the world working on combining the two forms of sousveillance.  One such group is the group organized by Dr. Stefanos Pantagis, a New York <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/23315.xml">
physician</link>, who leads a group of approximately 25 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/23885.xml">
poet</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/1212.xml">
artist</link>s, and other hospital workers on experiments in <link>
'glogging</link>.  Among the New York 'gloggers are some blind poets making a cyborglog called "shootingblind".  There is a certain irony in the blind exploring the all seeing eye of the Panopticon.  This has given rise to some interesting debates within the poetry communities in New York, and around the world.</p>
<p>

Sousveillance of a state by its citizens has been credited with addressing many problems such as election fraud or electoral misdeeds, as well as providing good governance. For example, mobile phones were used in Sierra Leone and Ghana in 2007 for checking malpractices and intimidation during elections.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sify.com/finance/fullstory.php?id=14555113">
http://sify.com/finance/fullstory.php?id=14555113</weblink></p>
<p>

A recent area of research further developed at IWIS was the equilibrium between surveillance and sousveillance.  Current "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/2632126.xml">
equiveillance</link> theory" holds that sousveillance, to some extent, often reduces or eliminates the need for surveillance.  In this sense it is possible to replace the Panoptic God's eye view of surveillance with a more community-building ubiquitous personal experience capture.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/5785.xml">
Crime</link>s, for example, might then be solved by way of collaboration among the citizenry rather than through the watching over the citizenry from above.   But it is not so black-and-white as this dichotomy.  Rather, there is a simple shift in the equiveillant point, as, for example, more camera phones enter widespread use, we  might be able, as a society, to be more self-reliant, on our own communities to keep an electronic neighbourhood watch.  This variation of sousveillance ("personal sousveillance") has been referred to as "coveillance" by Mann, Nolan and Wellman. </p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/4484964.xml">
Copwatch</link> is a network of <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
US</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 and <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canadian</link></region>
 volunteer organizations that "police the police." Copwatch groups usually engage in monitoring of the police, videotaping police activity, and educating the public about police misconduct.</p>
<p>

In 2008, Cambridge UK researchers (in the MESSAGE project) have teamed with bicycle couriers to measure and transmit air pollution indicators as they travel the town.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<collaboration wordnetid="101205156" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<cooperation wordnetid="101202904" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<novel wordnetid="106367879" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/526665.xml">
The Light of Other Days</link></novel>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</cooperation>
</fiction>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</literary_composition>
</event>
</collaboration>
</group_action>
</it> — A novel set in a world with a complete lack of privacy; anyone can view the activities of anyone or anything else, including looking into the past.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/158680.xml">
The Transparent Society</link></book>
''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/3624359.xml">
Lacey and his Friends</link></it> — A novel set in a world where nothing is private, where privacy is illegal and where private acts are monitored by camera continuously.  Some of these records are unavailable except to authorized investigators.  Small exceptions for passwords and other authorization systems are allowed (boxes over keyboards), etc.  David Drake basically envisions a world without any privacy whatsoever, where the privacy of the powerful is regarded as a threat by the society.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><knowledge_domain wordnetid="105999266" confidence="0.8">
<literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<life_science wordnetid="106037298" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<eugenics wordnetid="106042486" confidence="0.8">
<discipline wordnetid="105996646" confidence="0.8">
<novel wordnetid="106367879" confidence="0.8">
<science wordnetid="105999797" confidence="0.8">
<natural_science wordnetid="106000400" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/2513627.xml">
The Neanderthal Parallax</link></natural_science>
</science>
</novel>
</discipline>
</eugenics>
</fiction>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</life_science>
</literary_composition>
</knowledge_domain>
</it> — A parallel-worlds novel, in which <chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<hominid wordnetid="102471762" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<placental wordnetid="101886756" confidence="0.8">
<primate wordnetid="102469914" confidence="0.8">
<mammal wordnetid="101861778" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/45347.xml">
Neanderthal</link></animal>
</mammal>
</primate>
</placental>
</vertebrate>
</hominid>
</chordate>
s inhabit the alternate Earth.  Their justice system (and part of the plot) depends on an embedded forearm implant that continuously records everything in your environment and transmits it to the <it>alibi archive</it>, accessible by your word or by court order. Thus any observer or close relative of a victim can report a crime and open that part of the archive to investigators, effectively ending most serious crime.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<novel wordnetid="106367879" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/665839.xml">
Earth</link></novel>
</fiction>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</literary_composition>
</it> — A novel set in the future, where personal cameras are ubiquitous and privacy is at best rare and often unavailable.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/5541013.xml">
Freeze Frame</link></movie>
</it> — Is a film featuring Sousveillance.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/1020511.xml">
The Final Cut</link></movie>
</it> - Another film featuring sousveillance.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
[http://www.anonequity.org/weblog/archives/2006/01/exploring_equiv_1.php EXPLORING EQUIVEILLANCE, University of Ottawa Faculty of Law, Anonequity Project</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wearcam.org/sousveillance.pdf">
Sousveillance: Inventing and Using Wearable Computing Devices for Data Collection in Surveillance Environments, Surveillance &amp; Society 1(3): 331-355</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wearcam.org/sousveillance.pdf">
Sousveillance: Inventing and Using Wearable Computing Devices for Data Collection in Surveillance Environments, Surveillance &amp; Society 1(3): 331-355</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
Douglas McArthur, "Flights of Fancy", <it>Toronto Globe and Mail</it>, December 29, 2007, p. R16</entry>
<entry id="5">
Clark, Campbell&#59;&#32;Ingrid Peritz, Ian Bailey&#32;(<link>
2007-08-25</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20070825.wyoutube25/BNStory/National/home">
Sûreté du Québec to review practices</weblink>", <it>Globe and Mail</it>, pp.&nbsp;A5.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-08-31</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
http://technology.newscientist.com/article/dn13130-cyclists-cellphones-help-monitor-
air-pollution.html</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.anonequity.org/weblog/archives/2006/01/exploring_equiv_1.php">
Over and under the Valences of Veillance (Exploring Equiveillance)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.idtrail.org/content/view/618/42/">
Cyborglogging with Camera Phones: Steps Toward Equiveillance, Proceedings of the ACM Multimedia 2006, Santa Barbara, California, Oct. 23-27, 2006.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/CARPE2004/">
CARPE 2004, Continuous Archival and Retrieval of Personal Experiences</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wearcam.org/glaw.htm">
University of Ottawa Cyborg Law Project, Sousveillance Workshop, and Special Issue on Cyborg Law, etc.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://reason.com/0311/source.shtml">
"MIT Media Lab are doing their bit to help make ours a sousveillance society" (Reason online)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Steve Mann, Jason Nolan and <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/1203090.xml">
Barry Wellman</link></network>
</group>
</system>
. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.surveillance-and-society.org/articles1(3)/sousveillance.pdf">
Sousveillance: Inventing and Using Wearable Computing Devices for Data Collection in Surveillance Environments</weblink>. <it>Surveillance &amp; Society</it> 1(3): 331-355</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wearcam.org/leonardo/award2004.htm">
Existential Technology</weblink>, Leonardo 36(1), 2003, pp19-26, explores the fundamental philosophical question of inverse bureaucracy, i.e. "Can humans being clerks make clerks be human?".</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/CARPE2004/">
Microsoft is also exploring cyborglogs</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://joi.ito.com/moblog">
Joi Ito's use of the camera phone</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wearcam.org/iwis/">
International Workshop on Inverse Surveillance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wetware.com/drieux/PR/sell_Sousveillance.html">
satire of the sousveillance industry</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wearcam.org/wsd.htm">
World Sousveillance Day</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wearcam.org/wsd_stefanos_pantagis_pictures/shootingblind/">
shootingblind</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sniggle.net/perfart.php">
Performance Art (The Surveillance Camera Players and others)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://research.microsoft.com/CARPE2004/">
The First ACM Workshop on Continuous Archival and Retrieval of Personal Experiences</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sousveillance.org">
Sousveillance Blog: Thought and images from Stefanos and the NYC sousveillance crew.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wearcam.org/cfp2005/">
Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) CFP 2005, opening keynote (plenary panel) on equiveillance, along with the Bell Canada Sousveillance Tour, April 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://glogger.mobi">
Free-running sousveillance program for camera phones</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://k0a1a.net/snappy">
Open-source DIY mobile time-lapse camera</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findthecameras.com">
Find The Cameras</weblink> — A student-run sousveillance project at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/394901.xml">
SUNY Purchase College</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
