<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:15:06[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Software law</title>
<id>529931</id>
<revision>
<id>113238177</id>
<timestamp>2007-03-07T03:55:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DevastatorIIC</username>
<id>245294</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computer law</category>
<category>Software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Software law</b> refers the to legal remedies available to protect software-based assets.  Software may, under various circumstances and in various countries, be restricted by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/23273.xml">
patent</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/5278.xml">
copyright</link> or both. Most commercial software is sold under some kind of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/803810.xml">
software license</link>.<p>

A patent normally covers the design of something with a function such as a machine or process. Copyright restricts the right to make and distribute copies of something written or recorded, such as a song or a book of recipes. Software has both these aspects - it embodies functional design in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s and data structures it uses and it could also be considered as a recording which can be copied and "performed" (run).</p>
<p>

"Look and feel" lawsuits attempt to monopolize well-known command languages; some have succeeded. Copyrights on command languages enforce gratuitous incompatibility, close opportunities for competition, and stifle incremental improvements.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/76266.xml">
Software patent</link>s are even more dangerous; they make every design decision in the development of a program carry a risk of a lawsuit, with draconian pretrial seizure. It is difficult and expensive to find out whether the techniques you consider using are patented; it is impossible to find out whether they will be patented in the future.</p>
<p>

The proper use of copyright is to prevent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/18935579.xml">
software piracy</link> - unauthorised duplication of software. This is completely different from copying the idea behind the program in the same way that photocopying a book differs from writing another book on the same subject.</p>
<p>

<it>This article was originally based on material from the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<wordbook wordnetid="106418693" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<dictionary wordnetid="106418901" confidence="0.8">
<reference_book wordnetid="106417598" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/11324.xml">
Free On-line Dictionary of Computing</link></publication>
</reference_book>
</dictionary>
</book>
</wordbook>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
, which is  under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/18938782.xml">
GFDL</link>.</it></p>

</bdy>
</article>
