<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:15:10[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Non-heart-beating donation</title>
<id>530572</id>
<revision>
<id>236725667</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-06T21:10:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Stevenfruitsmaak</username>
<id>247845</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Donation</category>
<category>Medical ethics</category>
<category>Giving</category>
<category>Transplantation medicine</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

Prior to the introduction of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/187262.xml">
brain-stem death</link> into law in the mid to late 1970s, all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/167166.xml">
organ transplant</link>s from cadaveric donors came from <b>non-heart beating donors</b> (NHBD). <p>

Brain-stem dead donors, however, led to better results as the organs were perfused with oxygenated blood until the point of perfusion and cooling at organ retrieval, and so non-heart beating donors were generally no longer used except in Japan, where brain-stem death was not legally (until very recently) or culturally (still) recognized.</p>
<p>

However, a growing discrepancy between demand for organs and their availability from brain-stem dead donors has led to a re-examination of using non-heart beating donors, and many centres are now using such donors to expand their potential pool of organs.</p>
<p>

Tissue donation (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/311888.xml">
cornea</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/234803.xml">
heart valve</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/27978.xml">
skin</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/4099.xml">
bone</link>) has always been possible for non-heart beating donors, and many centres now have established programmes for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/17025.xml">
kidney</link> transplants from such donors. A few centres have also moved into NHBD <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/17384301.xml">
liver</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/36863.xml">
lung</link> transplants. Many lessons have been learnt since the 1970s, and results from current NHBD transplants are comparable to transplants from brain-stem dead donors.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Maastricht classification</st>
<p>

NHBDs are grouped by the Maastricht classification (1995; amended 2003):</p>
<p>

<table align="center">
<row>
<col>
<b>I</b></col>
<col>
Brought in dead</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<b>II</b></col>
<col>
Unsuccessful resuscitation</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<b>III</b></col>
<col>
Awaiting cardiac arrest</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<b>IV</b></col>
<col>
Cardiac arrest after brain-stem death</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<b>V</b></col>
<col>
Cardiac arrest in a hospital inpatient <it>(new category, 2003)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

Categories I, II and IV are termed <it>uncontrolled</it> and categories III and V are <it>controlled</it>. Only tissues can be taken from category I donors. Category II donors are patients who have had a witnessed cardiac arrest outside hospital, have cardiopulmonary resusciation by CPR-trained providers commenced within 10 minutes but who cannot be successfully resuscitated. Category III donors are patients on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/299014.xml">
intensive care</link> units with non-survivable injuries who have treatment withdrawn; where such patients wished in life to be organ donors, the transplant team can attend at the time of treatment withdrawal and retrieve organs after cardiac arrest has occurred.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Organs that can be used</st>
<p>

Kidneys can be used from category II donors, and all organs except the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/36808.xml">
heart</link> can potentially be used from category III, IV and V donors.  An unsuccessful kidney recipient can remain on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/56511.xml">
dialysis</link>, unlike recipients of some other organs, meaning that a failure will not result in death.  </p>
<p>

Kidneys from uncontrolled (category II) donors must be assessed with care as there is otherwise a high rate of failure. Many centres have protocols for formal viability assessment. Relatively few centres worldwide retrieve such kidneys, and leaders in this field include the transplant units in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/20125.xml">
Maastricht</link></village>
 (the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/21148.xml">
Netherlands</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
), <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/70348.xml">
Newcastle upon Tyne</link></site>
 and <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/51155.xml">
Leicester</link></village>
 (United Kingdom), <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/18642444.xml">
Madrid</link></village>
 (<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
), and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/108956.xml">
Washington, DC</link> (<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
).</p>
<p>

Livers and lungs for transplant can only be taken from controlled donors, and are still somewhat experimental as they have only been performed successfully in relatively few centres. In the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, NHBD liver transplants are currently performed in <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/452084.xml">
King's College Hospital</link></hospital>
 <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/17867.xml">
London</link></village>
, <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/8262427.xml">
Leeds</link></site>
, <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/70348.xml">
Newcastle upon Tyne</link></site>
, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/13882056.xml">
Birmingham</link></village>
 and the Scottish Liver Transplant Unit in Edinburgh. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nhbd2008.org">
The International Meeting on Transplantation from Non-Heart Beating Donors</weblink> is organised in the UK every 2 years and brings together specialists in transplantation including transplant physicians, surgeons, fellows, nurses, coordinators, intensive care physicians, perfusion technicians, ethicists, and researchers interested in the aspects of retrieval, preservation and  transplantation of DCD thoracic and abdominal organs and cells.
Lectures are held by experts on the most challenging themes such as clinical outcomes of transplantation of controlled and uncontrolled
DCD organs, progress made on machine perfusion of kidneys, livers, lungs and hearts and ethics and legal issues regarding donation after cardiac death. The 4th Meeting will be held in London the 15th and 16th of May 2008.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Procedure for uncontrolled donors</st>
<p>

Following declaration of death, cardiopulmonary resusciation (CPR) is continued until the transplant team arrive. A <it>stand-off</it> period is observed after cessation of CPR to ensure that death has occurred; this is usually from 5 to 10 minutes in length and varies according to local protocols.</p>
<p>

Once the stand-off period has elapsed, a cut down is performed over the femoral artery, and a <b>double-balloon triple-lumen</b> (DBTL) catheter is inserted into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/239675.xml">
femoral artery</link> and passed into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../80s/2080s.xml">
aorta</link>. The balloons are inflated to occlude the aorta above and below the renal arteries (any donor blood specimens required can be taken before the top balloon is inflated). A pre-flush with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/917920.xml">
streptokinase</link> or another <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/490334.xml">
thrombolytic</link> is given through the catheter, followed by 20 litres of cold kidney perfusion fluid; the opening of the lumen is between the balloons so that most of the flush and perfusion fluid goes into the kidneys. Another catheter is inserted into the femoral vein to allow venting of the fluid.</p>
<p>

Once full formal consent for organ donation has been obtained from relatives, and other necessary formalities such as identification of the deceased by the police and informing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/95356.xml">
Coroner</link> (in the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
UK</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
), the donor is taken to the operating room, and the kidneys and heart valves retrieved.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Procedure for controlled donors</st>
<p>

If the liver or lungs are felt to be suitable for transplantation, then the donor is usually taken directly to the operating room after cardiac arrest, and a rapid retrieval operation is performed once a 10 minute stand-off period has elapsed. It seems this stand-off period has been reduced to as short as 75 seconds based on a recent article by the CBC. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbc.ca/health/story/2008/08/13/cardiac-death-donations.html">
http://www.cbc.ca/health/story/2008/08/13/cardiac-death-donations.html</weblink>.  This is now causing an ethical debate as to whether physicians will declare death sooner than is currently required. This is similar to a normal multi-organ retrieval, but prioritises rapid cannulation, perfusion and cooling with ice, with dissection following later.</p>
<p>

If only the kidneys are suitable for retrieval, either rapid retrieval or cannulation with DBTL catheter can be used. Use of a DBTL catheter allows relatives of the deceased to see them after death, but the donor must be taken to the operating room as soon as possible.</p>
<p>

The formalities necessary for donation can usually be carried out prior to treatment withdrawal in controlled donation, so early retrieval should be possible.</p>
<p>

Category IV donors (who are already brain-stem dead), should either proceed as for a normal multi-organ retrieval &ndash; if this has already started &ndash; or should be managed as a category II or III as appropriate to the circumstances of cardiac arrest.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Results of NHBD transplantation</st>
<p>

NHBD kidney transplantation, from both controlled and uncontrolled donors, has been shown to have almost identical graft survival times and long-term function as kidneys from brain-stem dead donors. In the short-term they are prone to <it>delayed graft function</it> of around 7-14 days (this does not affect long term function in NHBD kidneys) and have a failure rate of around 5-10% (compared to 3-5% for kidneys from brain-stem dead donors).</p>
<p>

There is not as much long-term data for NHBD liver transplants, but published results are promising. Unlike in kidneys, where delayed graft function simply means a need for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/56511.xml">
dialysis</link>, delayed graft function in livers can be fatal, which is why only controlled donors are used for livers. Intra-hepatic biliary strictures are a complication more common in NHBD livers than in brain-stem dead donors. Many transplant surgeons feel that NHBD livers should not be used to transplant acutely sick patients with acute liver failure.</p>
<p>

Long-term data on NHBD lung transplants is not yet available.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Ethical issues</st>
<p>

Certain ethical issues are raised by NHBD transplantation, and require due sensitivity to ensure that ethical standards are maintained.</p>
<p>

In category II uncontrolled donors, the donor may die and the transplant team arrive before the donor's next-of-kin can be contacted. It is controversial whether cannulation and perfusion can be started in these circumstances. On one hand, it can be considered a violation of the potential donor's autonomy to cannulate before their in-life wishes are known. On the other hand, delay in cannulation may mean that a patient's strongly-held wish to be donor cannot be respected. Many ethicists also feel that a doctor's duty of care to the still living outweighs any duty of care to the dead. The compromise reached is usually to cannulate if there is any evidence of a wish to donate (such as a donor card or registration as a donor) even in the absence of next-of-kin.</p>
<p>

For category III donors, treatment is being withdrawn from a living person, who will then die and become a donor. It is important that the decisions that injuries are non-survivable, continued treatment is futile and that withdrawal is in the patient's best interests be made completely independently of any consideration of suitability as an organ donor.  Only after such decisions have been firmly made should a patient be considered as a potential organ donor. Although such treatment can be continued until the transplant team arrive, no additional treatment should be started to improve the organs &ndash; until the point of death, the patient should be treated exactly as any other dying patient.</p>
<p>

In recent years this has been termed Donation after Cardiac Death (DCD) or Donation after Cardiac Determination of Death (DCDD) in the United States, although Non-Heart Beating Donation is the more widely used term internationally.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://www.nhbd2008.org<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nhbd2008.org">
http://www.nhbd2008.org</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

2. Ethical Implication of NBHD <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wf-f.org/02-3-OrganDonation.html">
http://www.wf-f.org/02-3-OrganDonation.html</weblink></p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/167166.xml">
Organ transplant</link>ation</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Types</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/530867.xml">
Allograft</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/2956311.xml">
Alloplant</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/796144.xml">
Allotransplantation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/3324299.xml">
Autotransplantation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/779111.xml">
Xenotransplantation</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Organs and&nbsp;tissues</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/2518882.xml">
Bone</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/575810.xml">
Bone marrow</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/1425134.xml">
Corneal</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/1000053.xml">
Face</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/902715.xml">
Hand</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/417958.xml">
Heart</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/795923.xml">
Heart-lung</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/1584036.xml">
Kidney</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/517879.xml">
Liver</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/3310752.xml">
Lung</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/249969.xml">
Pancreas</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/8047738.xml">
Penis</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/740463.xml">
Skin</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/7410975.xml">
Spleen</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/8784037.xml">
Uterus</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Related topics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/5130923.xml">
Biomedical tissue</link>&nbsp;·  <disorder wordnetid="114052403" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<inclination wordnetid="106196584" confidence="0.8">
<bias wordnetid="106201908" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<partiality wordnetid="106201136" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/5517244.xml">
Cellular memory</link></activity>
</partiality>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</bias>
</inclination>
</physical_condition>
</state>
</event>
</condition>
</disorder>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../430/3889430.xml">
Edmonton protocol</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/2882345.xml">
Eye bank</link>&nbsp;·  <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/575888.xml">
Graft-versus-host disease</link></disease>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/249958.xml">
Immunosuppressive drugs</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/6580862.xml">
Islet cell transplantation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/1910996.xml">
Implants</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/517879.xml">
Living donor liver transplantation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/7637500.xml">
Lung allocation score</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/3626600.xml">
Machine perfusion</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/740468.xml">
Medical grafting</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/530572.xml">
Non-heart beating donation</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/43846.xml">
Organ donation</link>&nbsp;·  <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/530362.xml">
Post-transplant lymphoproliferative disorder</link></disease>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/12223647.xml">
Repugnant market</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/2900961.xml">
Total body irradiation</link>&nbsp;·  <disorder wordnetid="114052403" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/529578.xml">
Transplant rejection</link></physical_condition>
</state>
</condition>
</disorder>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Organizations</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/10008306.xml">
Halachic Organ Donor Society</link>&nbsp;·  <body wordnetid="105216365" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/2186920.xml">
Human Tissue Authority</link></natural_object>
</body>
&nbsp;·  <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/7430201.xml">
National Marrow Donor Program</link></company>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/4797409.xml">
United Network for Organ Sharing</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
People</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/7015.xml">
Christiaan Barnard</link></person>
&nbsp;·  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/4829979.xml">
Michael Woodruff</link></scientist>
</person>
&nbsp;·  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/1051.xml">
Alexis Carrel</link></person>
&nbsp;·  <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/2515890.xml">
Norman Shumway</link></scientist>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<surgeon wordnetid="110679174" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<medical_practitioner wordnetid="110305802" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<health_professional wordnetid="110165109" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/3342295.xml">
Jean-Michel Dubernard</link></doctor>
</professional>
</adult>
</health_professional>
</causal_agent>
</medical_practitioner>
</person>
</surgeon>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/8338783.xml">
List of notable organ transplant donors and recipients</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/9728362.xml">
Charity</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/367725.xml">
Donation</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/43846.xml">
Organ donation</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/12687113.xml">
Organ donation under Jewish law</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/530572.xml">
Non-heart beating donation</link>•</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other biologic donations</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
Gamete donation (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/1765384.xml">
Egg donation</link>, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<benefactor wordnetid="109608709" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<good_person wordnetid="110138767" confidence="0.8">
<donor wordnetid="110025730" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/2557514.xml">
Sperm donation</link></causal_agent>
</donor>
</good_person>
</person>
</benefactor>
</physical_entity>
) • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/1510374.xml">
Embryo donation</link> • <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/505536.xml">
Blood donation</link></commodity>
</merchandise>
</artifact>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/3251004.xml">
Body donation</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/844785.xml">
Car donation</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
