<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:40:19[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>David Forsyth (computer scientist)</title>
<id>5307878</id>
<revision>
<id>227720327</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-24T22:54:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cydebot</username>
<id>1215485</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>David Forsyth</b> is an <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
American</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 computer scientist and full professor at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/384695.xml">
University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</link></university>
, born in South Africa. He is married to <link>
Margaret Fleck</link>, who is also a professor at the University of Illinois.<p>

He holds a BSc and an MSc in Electrical Engineering from the University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, and an MA and
D.Phil from Oxford University. He was a full professor at U.C. Berkeley before moving to the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
He co-authored, with UIUC CS Professor <link>
Jean Ponce</link>, 2002's "Computer Vision: A Modern Approach", one of the leading publications addressing the topic. He has published over 100 papers on computer vision, computer graphics and machine learning. He served as program co-chair for IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition in 2000, general co-chair for IEEE CVPR 2006, program co-chair for ECCV 2008, and is a regular member of the program committee of all major international conferences on computer vision. He served on the NRC Committee on "Protecting Kids from Pornography and other Inappropriate Material on the Internet", which sat for three years and produced a study widely praised for its sensible content. He has received best paper awards at the International Conference on Computer Vision and at the European Conference on Computer Vision.</p>
<p>

David Forsyth's research interest also includes graphics and machine learning, he served as a committee member of ICML 2008.</p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://luthuli.cs.uiuc.edu/~daf/">
David Forsyth's Home Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.uiuc.edu/news/articles.php?id=2006Mar29-153">
Professor David Forsyth receives IEEE Technical Achievement Award</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
