<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:14:45[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<company  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108058098">
<contest  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107456188">
<header>
<title>TopCoder</title>
<id>532303</id>
<revision>
<id>235216592</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-30T17:33:41Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Reb42</username>
<id>1223857</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Programming contests</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Company</name>
<parameters>
<location>
&nbsp;(incorporated in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/8933.xml">
Delaware</link>)</location>
<company_type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/7485.xml">
Corporation</link></company_type>
<company_name>
TopCoder, Inc.</company_name>
<foundation>
April, 2001</foundation>
<industry>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/661641.xml">
Information Technology Staffing</link>  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/1875574.xml">
Software</link>  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/235890.xml">
Outsourcing services</link></industry>
<founder>
Jack Hughes<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></founder>
<location_country>
USA</location_country>
<location_city>
Glastonbury, Connecticut</location_city>
<homepage>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.topcoder.com">
www.topcoder.com</weblink></homepage>
<num_employees>
75 (2006)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></num_employees>
<company_logo>
<image width="150px" src="TopCoder_logo.gif">
<caption>

TopCoder logo.gif
</caption>
</image>
</company_logo>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>TopCoder</b> is a company which administers contests in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/5311.xml">
computer programming</link>.  TopCoder hosts weekly online algorithm competitions &mdash; known as SRMs or "single round matches" &mdash; as well as weekly competitions in design and development.  The work in design and development produces useful software which is licensed for profit by TopCoder.  Competitors involved in the creation of these components are paid royalties based on these sales.  The software resulting from algorithm competitions &mdash; and the less-frequent marathon matches &mdash; is not usually directly useful, but sponsor companies sometimes provide money to pay the victors.  Statistics (including an overall "rating" for each developer) are tracked over time for competitors in each category.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Types of competitions</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Algorithms</b> (competition length about 2 hours): Competitors are given a set (usually three) of algorithmic problems and have 75 minutes to correctly solve as many as they can.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Design</b> (competition length 1 week): Competitors are given a set of user requirements and attempt to convert them into a usable software design specification.  Their efforts are judged on a variety of "real-world" criteria on how correct and practical their design is.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Development</b> (competition length 1 week): Competitors are given a set of design specification and attempt to write software components that match those specification.  These components are judged on their functionality and coding style.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Marathon Matches</b> (competition length 1 or 2 weeks): Contestants are given a particularly difficult algorithmic problem.  The scoring is done by computer based on criteria specifically suited to the problem.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Studio</b> (competition length ?): Contestants are asked to show off their creative skills in a competitive environment.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Newly added competitions</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Architecture</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Assembly</b> TopCoder has created Assembly Competitions as an extension of Component Design and Development Competitions. Through these competitions, competitors create high quality applications using completed components and TopCoder's established competitive method.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Testing</b></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Bug Races</b> Project teams, clients and members are able to log bugs they find in software developed and supported by TopCoder. TopCoder will communicate these bugs to the member community. Bugs that are open to the community will be posted on the Active Bug Races page.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Algorithm competitions</st>

<p>

TopCoder has been hosting algorithm competitions since <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>. Current SRMs consist of four phases:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Coding phase</b> (75 minutes): Coders write programs to solve three short problems using <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/72038.xml">
C++</link></programming_language>
, <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
, <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/2356196.xml">
C#</link></programming_language>
, or <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/6097382.xml">
Visual Basic</link></programming_language>
. Each problem set consists of an easy, medium, and hard question, the difficulty of which is reflected in each problem's point value.  The problems' point values vary from match to match; a common point value distribution is 250-500-1000.  Also, the quicker a coder writes a given problem, the more points that coder gets.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Intermission</b> (5 minutes): After the coding phase ends, there is a short break before the challenge phase begins. This time can be used to think of challenge cases.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Challenge phase</b> (15 minutes): Coders can challenge the submitted problems of other participants in their room by constructing test cases in an attempt to generate erroneous output. The challenger receives 50 points for a successful challenge (the challenged coder loses all his points for that problem), and loses 25 points for an unsuccessful challenge. Each successful challenge is added to the set of tests to be run during the system testing phase.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>System-testing phase</b>: Each problem that survives through the challenge phase is run on many test cases. If a coder's solution fails the system tests, that coder receives no points for the problem.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

At the end of the contest, ratings are updated to incorporate each participating coder's performance.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Component design and development competitions</st>

<p>

TopCoder hosts design and development competitions in which coders can compete to create <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/2816674.xml">
component</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/454746.xml">
applications</link> that are either generally useful, or that third parties have contracted for.</p>
<p>

TopCoder design and development competitions are week-long competitions.  New components are posted every Thursday and coders can choose a component from a list of <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
 and <link>
.NET</link> components, and they have a week to design or develop their chosen component.  Each week new components are posted.  Development components are generally components that have been designed in a previous component design contest.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Marathon matches</st>

<p>

Larger problems than are asked during a traditional TopCoder algorithm round are posted. They provide a more flexible competition format with an extended timeline. Since June 2008, the Marathon Matches will focus on encryption technology.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Tournaments</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>TopCoder Open</b>: An annual event which features algorithm, design, and development competitions in a tournament structure, culminating in a live finale for the top competitors.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>TopCoder Collegiate Challenge</b>: An annual event in which college students compete for money and school glory. In 2008, TopCoder decided not to continue this tournament. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>TopCoder High School</b>: An annual event in which high school students compete for scholarship and school glory. This tournament was started in 2007</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Prizes</st>
<p>

TopCoder initially awarded money every week to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/23716.xml">
coders</link> who did well in the weekly competitions, or Single Round Matches (SRMs). For a while, prize money was only awarded twice a year to winners and finalists of the TopCoder Collegiate Challenge (TCCC, which is in the spring) and the TopCoder Open (formerly the Invitational, which is in the fall).  As of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/1490052.xml">
June 2005</link>, some weekly SRMs began to once again award prize money, being sponsored by outside companies such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo!</link></company>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Statistics</st>
<p>

As of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/16181.xml">
July 23</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link> 163,351 people have registered at the TopCoder website. 17.3% of those registered have participated in at least one Algorithm competition, 0.3% in Design, 0.7% in Development and 1.5% in Marathon Matches.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Competitions, ratings, and divisions</st>

<p>

In the early days, the <it>Iron Man</it> system was set up under which coders were grouped into rooms of ten according to skill level (determined by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.topcoder.com/index?t=support&amp;c=ratings">
rating</weblink>, similar to <record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/70421.xml">
ELO chess rating</link></evidence>
</indication>
</record>
), in order to encourage newcomers (who would have little hope of beating out the best coders for prize money) to stay and compete.  After the contest, the 3 highest scoring coders in each room were paid according to the skill level of the room (winners in the room of contestants with the top 10 ratings were paid more than those in the room with coders 11-20, and so on).  This created some paradoxical situations such as the possibility of coming fourth in the whole contest and getting no money, while the 111th placed contestant got paid, and gave rise to <it>ratings diving</it>.  Ratings diving, or taking a <it>ratings dive</it> was accomplished simply by doing very poorly on purpose in a particular contest (by opening and not submitting any problems or submitting incorrect challenges).  As a result, a contestant would, in their next contest, be placed in a room with 9 coders among whom they had a good chance of winning some money.  The idea was that the dramatically increased chance of winning money made up for the fact that the money to be won was a lesser amount given the lower average rating of the room.</p>
<p>

Coders have since been divided into two divisions, Division I and Division II.  Division I consists of all coders with a rating of at least 1200, and Division II consists of all coders with a rating of 1199 or less.  Coders are grouped in rooms with other members of their division, in groups of up to 20 coders in such a way that within each division, the average coder ratings in each of the rooms are roughly equal.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Past Tournament Winners </st>
<p>

Here are the past tournament winners in all 5 categories: Algorithm, Design, Development, Marathon and Studio:</p>
<p>

<table style="text-align:center" class="wikitable">
<row>
<header>
Tournament</header>
<header>
Algorithm</header>
<header>
Design</header>
<header>
Development</header>
<header>
Marathon</header>
<header>
Studio</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
2001 Collegiate Challenge</col>
<col>
qubits</col>




</row>
<row>
<col>
2001 Invitational</col>
<col>
jonmac</col>




</row>
<row>
<col>
2002 Collegiate Challenge</col>
<col>
dmwright</col>




</row>
<row>
<col>
2002 Invitational</col>
<col>
John Dethridge</col>




</row>
<row>
<col>
2003 Collegiate Challenge</col>
<col>
dgarthur</col>




</row>
<row>
<col>
2003 Open</col>
<col>
tomek</col>
<col>
Pops</col>
<col>
rnielsen</col>


</row>
<row>
<col>
2004 Collegiate Challenge</col>
<col>
tomek</col>
<col>
aksonov</col>
<col>
roma</col>


</row>
<row>
<col>
2004 Open</col>
<col>
tomek</col>
<col>
adic</col>
<col>
Standlove</col>


</row>
<row>
<col>
2005 Collegiate Challenge</col>
<col>
mathijs</col>
<col>
adic</col>
<col>
gladius</col>


</row>
<row>
<col>
2005 Open</col>
<col>
Eryx</col>
<col>
nicka81</col>
<col>
visualage</col>


</row>
<row>
<col>
2006 Open</col>
<col>
Petr</col>
<col>
Pops</col>
<col>
sindu</col>


</row>
<row>
<col>
2006 Collegiate Challenge</col>
<col>
Petr</col>
<col>
nicka81</col>
<col>
PE</col>


</row>
<row>
<col>
2007 High School</col>
<col>
Burunduk2</col>




</row>
<row>
<col>
2007 Open</col>
<col>
Jan_Kuipers</col>
<col>
kyky</col>
<col>
hefeng</col>
<col>
Mojito1</col>
<col>
yiming</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
2007 Collegiate Challenge</col>
<col>
Petr</col>
<col>
nicka81</col>
<col>
PE</col>
<col>
paranoia</col>
<col>
abedavera</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
2008 High School</col>
<col>
ahyangyi</col>




</row>
<row>
<col>
2008 Open</col>
<col>
tomek</col>
<col>
Pops</col>
<col>
romanoTC</col>
<col>
Psyho</col>
<col>
oninkxronda</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
TopCoder as a business</st>

<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/39864.xml">
business plan</link> behind TopCoder comprises several objectives.  One goal is to be a recruitment center where companies can come to find programmers who are proven to be highly skilled, and where talented programmers can display their skills to a worldwide audience.  Large companies sponsor TopCoder events to gain credibility with and exposure to talented developers.  TopCoder also sells software licenses to use the growing body of components that have been developed in competition.  Finally, TopCoder acts as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/235890.xml">
outsourcing</link> center, allowing companies to farm out custom design and development tasks to TopCoder competitors.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/520121.xml">
ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest</link></psychological_feature>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
 (ICPC)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/2997987.xml">
ICFP Programming Contest</link></psychological_feature>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://forums.topcoder.com/?module=Thread&amp;threadID=616032">
The TCCC: A Difficult Decision</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.topcoder.com/tc?module=Static&amp;d1=about&amp;d2=management">
TopCoder management team</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-11-27</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hotjobs.yahoo.com/Company-Profiles/T/Topcoder-Jobs_49476">
Topcoder Jobs and Profile</weblink>".&#32;<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/2945769.xml">
Yahoo! HotJobs</link></it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-11-29</link>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.topcoder.com">
Official TopCoder website</weblink>".</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Business data</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://finance.google.com/finance?cid=5757753">
TopCoder Inc.</weblink> at <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/4465875.xml">
Google Finance</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://biz.yahoo.com/ic/125/125740.html">
TopCoder Inc.</weblink> at <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo Finance</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hoovers.com//--ID__125740--/free-co-factsheet.xhtml">
TopCoder Inc.</weblink> at <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/1524585.xml">
Hoover's</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sec.gov/cgi-bin/browse-edgar?action=getcompany&amp;CIK=1156077">
TopCoder Inc.</weblink> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/864507.xml">
SEC filings</link> at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/55097.xml">
Securities and Exchange Commission</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</contest>
</company>
</article>
