<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:49:05[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Ring signature</title>
<id>5376829</id>
<revision>
<id>240099901</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-21T22:33:02Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cryptography</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
cryptography</link>, a <b>ring signature</b> is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/59644.xml">
digital signature</link> that can be performed by any member of a group of users that each have <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/53039.xml">
keys</link>.  Therefore, a message signed with a ring signature is endorsed by someone in a particular group of people.  One of the security properties of a ring signature is that it should be difficult to determine <it>which</it> of the group members' keys was used to produce the signature.  Ring signatures are similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/3347478.xml">
group signature</link>s but differ in two key ways: first, there is no way to revoke the anonymity of an individual signature, and second, any group of users can be used as a group without additional setup.
Ring signatures were invented by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/68057.xml">
Ron Rivest</link></scientist>
</person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/57314.xml">
Adi Shamir</link></scientist>
</person>
, and <link>
Yael Tauman</link>, and introduced at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/4229573.xml">
ASIACRYPT</link> in 2001.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  The name "ring signature" comes from the ring-like structure of the signature <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>.
<sec>
<st>
Definition</st>

<p>

Suppose that a group of entities each have public/private key pairs, (<it>PK</it>1, <it>SK</it>1), (<it>PK</it>2, <it>SK</it>2), ... ,(<it>PKn</it>, <it>SKn</it>).  Party <it>i</it> can compute a ring signature σ on a message <it>m</it>, on input (<it>m</it>, <it>SKi</it>, <it>PK</it>1, ... , <it>PKn</it>).  Anyone can check the validity of a ring signature given σ, <it>m</it>, and the public keys involved, <it>PK</it>1, ... , <it>PKn</it>.  If a ring signature is properly computed, it should pass the check.  On the other hand, it should be hard for anyone to create a valid ring signature on any message for any group without knowing any of the secret keys for that group.  </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications</st>

<p>

In the original paper, Rivest, Shamir, and Tauman described ring signatures as a way to leak a secret.  For instance, a ring signature could be used to provide an anonymous signature from "a high-ranking <building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/33057.xml">
White House</link></building>
 official", without revealing which official signed the message.  Ring signatures are right for this application because the anonymity of a ring signature cannot be revoked, and because the group for a ring signature can be improvised.</p>
<p>

Another application, also described in the original paper, is for <link>
deniable signature</link>s.  A ring signature where the group is the sender and the recipient of a message will only seem to be a signature of the sender to the recipient: anyone else will be unsure whether the recipient or the sender was the actual signer.  Thus, such a signature is convincing, but cannot be transferred beyond its intended recipient.  </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springerlink.com/content/kxkndv9rgk8lu3h9/">
<it>How to leak a secret''</it></weblink>, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/68057.xml">
Ron Rivest</link></scientist>
</person>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/57314.xml">
Adi Shamir</link></scientist>
</person>
, and <link>
Yael Tauman</link>, ASIACRYPT 2001.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
