<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:42:59[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<union  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108233056">
<header>
<title>Federation of European Film Directors</title>
<id>5381778</id>
<revision>
<id>197673110</id>
<timestamp>2008-03-12T07:53:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Penubag</username>
<id>1857053</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Entertainment industry unions</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>All pages needing to be wikified</category>
<category>Film directors</category>
<category>Wikify from March 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Union</name>
<parameters>

<image width="150px" src="">

</image>
<office>
Brussels, Belgium</office>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ferainfo.org/">
www.ferainfo.org</weblink></website>
<people>
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/18738.xml">
Liv Ullmann</link></actor>
</person>
, PresidentCécile Despringe, CEO (Déléguée générale)Peter Carpentier (Germany), Chair and Vice PresidentTrish McAdam (Ireland), Vice PresidentAnne Théron (France), Vice PresidentKurt Mayer (Austria), Honorary TreasurerGyörgy Gém (Hungary)Igor Korsic (Slovenia)Birgitte Stærmose (Denmark)</people>
<founded>
1980 in Venice</founded>
<name>
FERA</name>
<native_name>
Fédération Européenne des Réalisateurs de l'Audiovisuel</native_name>
<members>
32 European national film director's associations</members>
<full_name>
Federation of European Film Directors</full_name>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Wikitext.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please  this article or section.</b>
Help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Federation_of_European_Film_Directors&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by adding  . <it>(March 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/559676.xml">
FERA</link>.</p>


<p>

<b>La Fédération Européenne des Réalisateurs de l'Audiovisuel</b> (FERA) (<it>Federation of European FIlm Directors</it> in <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English</link></language>
) represents the interests of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/10571.xml">
film</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/29831.xml">
television</link> directors in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link>an motion picture industry.</p>

<p>

FERA is the European Federation for national associations of television and cinema directors. It was established in Venice in 1980 and now represents 32 associations as full members (and associated members) in 28 European countries.</p>

<p>

<b>MISSION STATEMENT</b></p>
<p>

FERA is dealing with issues of major importance in the creation and promotion of audiovisual works. FERA’s mission is to enhance the recognition of the cultural significance of audiovisual works and to defend their integrity in 21st century Europe. FERA represents directors as the primary creators of audiovisual works. The director, as the creative decision maker in a collaborative artistic process, has the final responsibility for the aesthetic cohesion and artistic integrity of the work. FERA regards safeguarding the craft, artistry and the creative and economic rights of the director as essential components to the diversity of the European audiovisual culture.</p>
<p>

<b>FERA activities are primarily focused on:</b> fostering exchanges and common actions within an active network of national associations of directors: lobbying the European parliament, politicians and committees, the media, film professionals and their representative bodies on issues of concern to directors, creativity and culture across all audiovisual media.</p>

<p>

<b>I.	A NETWORK OF DIRECTORS’ ASSOCIATIONS</b></p>
<p>

With a growing membership in 23 of the 27 countries of the European Union (Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, France, Greece, Germany, Netherlands, Hungary, Ireland, Latvia, Lithuania, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Spain, Slovakia, Slovenia, Sweden and the UK) FERA represents the main audiovisual markets including new Member States who entered EU in 2004 and 2007. FERA’s network is open to all countries across the geographical continent of Europe or as defined by the <administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/5865.xml">
Council of Europe</link></administration>
.  </p>
<p>

<b>An active network</b>, this unique network in Europe is very lively, extremely motivated and reactive. At the Annual General Assembly, which takes place in a different member country each year, members meet to discuss key issues. Whenever possible, regional meetings are organised in the framework of festivals or established events in the audiovisual field. Besides these meetings, members keep in touch through the FERA office based in Brussels, via electronic information exchanges and a web site where information on FERA activities and position papers are stored and regularly updated. </p>
<p>

The network is organised by the CEO who implements policy and maintains contact with the membership. The Executive Committee meets at least four times a year to develop this policy and strategy with the CEO. </p>
<p>

<b>The representative power of directors</b>: FERA's representation of the broad spectrum of directors across the majority of European countries, large and small, makes it a highly influential body with a legitimate mandate to defend the rights of directors and cultural and creative importance European audiovisual media.</p>
<p>

Furthermore, the global reputation of European directors for innovation, intellectual engagement and creativity strengthens the visibility and popularity of the actions and proposals of FERA towards media, professionals and politicians at the European and international levels.</p>

<p>

<b>II.	A  STRENGTH OF PROPOSAL RECOGNISED AT THE EUROPEAN LEVEL</b>
Whether at the Commission or at the Council or the <parliament wordnetid="108319198" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/9581.xml">
European Parliament</link></parliament>
, FERA can gain direct access to political officials and FERA's views are frequently solicited before a European position is published.</p>
<p>

FERA’s recognition extends beyond the European institutions (<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/5865.xml">
Council of Europe</link></administration>
, <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/31901.xml">
UNESCO</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/33294.xml">
WIPO</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/33873.xml">
WTO</link>) even though contacts with these institutions remain a priority. </p>
<p>

In 2006, FERA has made several written contributions including some analysis and proposals on the following subjects :</p>
<p>

- Action program and priorities for 2006 in a press release issued at the <film_festival wordnetid="100517418" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/101460.xml">
Cannes Film Festival</link></film_festival>
. (May 2006)
- Contribution to the public consultation on private copying levies (July 2006) and campaign of protest of European directors against the draft recommendation on private copying. (October-December 2006)
- Position on the review of the Television without Frontiers directive to the attention of the <parliament wordnetid="108319198" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/9581.xml">
European Parliament</link></parliament>
. (July 2006)
- Contribution to the public consultation on Content Online. (October 2006)
- Open Letter to the Contact Committee for the Media programme: analysis of the programme from the point of view of the directors’ needs. (October 2006)
- Contribution to a public consultation on Culture and Europe. (October 2006)</p>
</bdy>
</union>
</article>
