<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:45:29[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Herbicide</title>
<id>53916</id>
<revision>
<id>242201624</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T08:56:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Nono64</username>
<id>2313206</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Herbicides</category>
<category>Soil contamination</category>
<category>Lawn care</category>
<category>Toxicology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>herbicide</b> is used to kill unwanted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/23208.xml">
plant</link>s. Selective herbicides kill specific targets while leaving the desired <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/7500259.xml">
crop</link> relatively unharmed. Some of these act by interfering with the growth of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/19653902.xml">
weed</link> and are often synthetic "imitations" of plant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/13311.xml">
hormones</link>. Herbicides used to clear waste ground, industrial sites, railways and railway embankments are non-selective and kill all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/23208.xml">
plant</link> material with which they come into contact. Some plants produce natural herbicides, such as the genus <it>Juglans</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/165140.xml">
walnut</link>s).  They are applied in total <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/216226.xml">
vegetation</link> control (TVC) programs for maintenance of highways and railroads.  Smaller quantities are used in forestry, pasture systems, and management of areas set aside as wildlife <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/1596317.xml">
habitat</link>.<p>

Herbicides are widely used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/627.xml">
agriculture</link> and in landscape turf management.  In the U.S., they account for about 70% of all agricultural pesticide use.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  </p>

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

Prior to the widespread use of chemical herbicides, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/239032.xml">
cultural controls</link>, such as altering soil pH, salinity, or fertility levels, were used to control weeds. Mechanical control (including tillage) was also (and still is) used to control weeds. </p>
<p>

The first widely used herbicide was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/1624512.xml">
2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid</link>, often abbreviated 2,4-D.  It was first commercialized by the Sherwin-Williams Paint company and saw use in the late 1940s.  It is easy and inexpensive to manufacture, and kills many broadleaf plants while leaving grasses largely unaffected (although high doses of 2,4-D at crucial growth periods can harm grass crops such as maize or cereals).  The low cost of 2,4-D has led to continued usage today and it remains one of the most commonly used herbicides in the world.  Like other acid herbicides, current formulations utilize either an amine salt (usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/1620404.xml">
trimethylamine</link>) or one of many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/9675.xml">
ester</link>s of the parent compound.  These are easier to handle than the acid.</p>
<p>

2,4-D exhibits relatively good <it>selectivity</it>, meaning, in this case, that it controls a wide number of broadleaf weeds while causing little to no injury to grass crops at normal use rates.  A herbicide is termed selective if it affects only certain types of plants, and nonselective if it inhibits a very broad range of plant types. Other herbicides have been more recently developed that achieve higher levels of selectivity than 2,4-D.</p>
<p>

The 1950s saw the introduction of the triazine family of herbicides, which includes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/1762549.xml">
atrazine</link>, which have current distinction of being the herbicide family of greatest concern regarding groundwater contamination.  Atrazine does not break down readily (within a few weeks) after being applied to soils of above neutral pH.  Under alkaline soil conditions atrazine may be carried into the soil profile as far as the water table by soil water following rainfall causing the aforementioned contamination.  Atrazine is said to have <it>carryover,</it> a generally undesirable property for herbicides.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/294295.xml">
Glyphosate</link>, frequently sold under the brand name <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/93831.xml">
Roundup</link>, was introduced in 1974 for non-selective weed control. It is now a major herbicide in selective weed control in growing crop plants due to the development of crop plants that are resistant to it. The pairing of the herbicide with the resistant seed contributed to the consolidation of the seed and chemistry industry in the late 1990s.</p>
<p>

Many modern chemical herbicides for agriculture are specifically formulated to decompose within a short period after application.  This is desirable as it allows crops which may be affected by the herbicide to be grown on the land in future seasons. However, herbicides with low residual activity (i.e., that decompose quickly) often do not provide season-long weed control.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health effects</st>

<p>

Certain herbicides affect metabolic pathways and systems unique to plants and not found in animals making many modern herbicides among the safest crop protection products having essentially no effect on mammals, birds, amphibians or reptiles.  </p>
<p>

Some herbicides cause a range of health effects ranging from skin rashes to death {ref needed}.  The pathway of attack can arise from intentional or unintentional direct consumption, improper application resulting in the herbicide coming into direct contact with people or wildlife, inhalation of aerial sprays, or food consumption prior to the labeled pre-harvest interval.  Under extreme conditions herbicides can also be transported via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/4400374.xml">
surface runoff</link> to contaminate distant water sources. Most herbicides decompose rapidly in soils via soil microbial decomposition, hydrolysis, or photolysis. Some herbicides are more persistent with longer soil <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/13606.xml">
half-lives</link> {ref needed}.  Other alleged health effects include chest pain, headaches, nausea,  and fatigue.  </p>
<p>

All organic and non-organic herbicides must be extensively tested prior to approval for commercial sale and labeling by the Environmental Protection Agency.  However, because of the large number of herbicides in use, there is significant concern regarding health effects.  Some of the herbicides in use are known to be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/20359.xml">
mutagenic</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/6445.xml">
carcinogenic</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/223011.xml">
teratogen</link>ic {ref needed}.</p>
<p>

Some herbicides may have therapeutic uses. There is current research into the use of herbicides as an <link>
 anti-malaria</link> drug that targets the plant-like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/7748561.xml">
apicoplast</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/153522.xml">
plastid</link> in the malaria-causing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/43937.xml">
parasite</link> <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/544177.xml">
Plasmodium falciparum</link></it>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Classification of herbicides </st>

<p>

Herbicides can be grouped by activity, use, chemical family, mode of action, or type of vegetation controlled.</p>
<p>

By activity:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Contact</b> herbicides destroy only the plant tissue in contact with the chemical.  Generally, these are the fastest acting herbicides.  They are less effective on perennial plants, which are able to regrow from rhizhomes, roots or tubers. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Systemic</b> herbicides are translocated through the plant, either from foliar application down to the roots, or from soil application up to the leaves. They are capable of controlling perennial plants and may be slower acting but ultimately more effective than contact herbicides.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

By use:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Soil-applied</b> herbicides are applied to the soil and are taken up by the roots and/or hypocotyl of the target plant. The following two categories are examples of soil-applied herbicides.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Pre-plant incorporated</b> herbicides are soil applied prior to planting and mechanically incorporated into the soil. The objective for incorporation is to prevent dissipation through photo decomposition and/or volatility.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/5795637.xml">
Preemergent herbicides</link></b> are applied to the soil before the crop emerges and prevent germination or early growth of weed seeds.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Post-emergent herbicides are applied after the crop has emerged.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Their classification by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/5105731.xml">
mechanism of action</link> (MOA) indicates the first enzyme, protein, or biochemical step affected in the plant following application. The main mechanisms of action are:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>ACCase inhibitors</b> are compounds that kill grasses. Acetyl coenzyme A carboxylase (ACCase) is part of the first step of lipid synthesis. Thus, ACCase inhibitors affect cell membrane production in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/227682.xml">
meristems</link> of the grass plant. The ACCases of grasses are sensitive to these herbicides, whereas the ACCases of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/54149.xml">
dicot</link> plants are not.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b> ALS inhibitors</b>: the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/9719331.xml">
acetolactate synthase</link> (ALS) enzyme (also known as acetohydroxyacid synthase, or AHAS) is the first step in the synthesis of the branched-chain amino acids (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/63554.xml">
valine</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/63546.xml">
leucine</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/63543.xml">
isoleucine</link>). These herbicides slowly starve affected plants of these <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link>s which eventually leads to inhibition of DNA synthesis. They affect grasses and dicots alike. The ALS inhibitor family includes sulfonylureas (SUs), imidazolinones (IMIs), triazolopyrimidines (TPs), pyrimidinyl oxybenzoates (POBs), and sulfonylamino carbonyl triazolinones (SCTs).  ALS is a biological pathway that exists only in plants and not in animals thus making the ALS-inhibitors among the safest herbicides.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>EPSPS inhibitors</b>: The enolpyruvylshikimate 3-phosphate synthase enzyme EPSPS is used in the synthesis of the amino acids <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/58358.xml">
tryptophan</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/38001.xml">
phenylalanine</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/31349.xml">
tyrosine</link>. They affect grasses and dicots alike. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/294295.xml">
Glyphosate</link> (Roundup) is a systemic EPSPS inhibitor but inactivated by soil contact.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Synthetic auxin</b> inaugurated the era of organic herbicides. They were discovered in the 1940s after a long study of the plant growth regulator <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/496667.xml">
auxin</link>. Synthetic auxins mimic this plant hormone. They have several points of action on the cell membrane, and are effective in the control of dicot plants. 2,4-D is a synthetic auxin herbicide.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Photosystem II inhibitors</b> reduce electron flow from water to NADPH2+ at the photochemical step in photosynthesis. They bind to the Qb site on the D1 protein, and prevent quinone from binding to this site. Therefore, this group of compounds cause electrons to accumulate on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/6985.xml">
chlorophyll</link> molecules. As a consequence, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/66313.xml">
oxidation</link> reactions in excess of those normally tolerated by the cell occur, and the plant dies. The triazine herbicides (including atrazine) and urea derivatives (diuron) are photosystem II inhibitors.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Organic Herbicides </st>
<p>

Almost all herbicides in use today are considered "organic" herbicides in that they contain carbon as a primary molecular component.  A notable exception would be the arsenical class of herbicides.  Sometimes they are referred to as synthetic organic herbicides.  Recently the term "organic" has come to imply products used in <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="100949134" confidence="0.8">
<technology wordnetid="100949619" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<profession wordnetid="100609953" confidence="0.8">
<use wordnetid="100947128" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/72754.xml">
organic</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</use>
</profession>
</event>
</technology>
</application>
</occupation>
 farming.   Under this definition an organic herbicide is one that can be used in a farming enterprise that has been classified as organic. Organic herbicides are expensive and may not be affordable for commercial production. They are much less effective than synthetic herbicides and are generally used along with cultural and mechanical weed control practices.  </p>
<p>

Organic herbicides include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/26897.xml">
Spice</link>s are now effectively used in patented herbicides.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/32762.xml">
Vinegar</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> is effective for 5-20% solutions of acetic acid with higher concentrations most effective but mainly destroys surface growth and so respraying to treat regrowth is needed. Resistant plants generally succumb when weakened by respraying.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/27693.xml">
Steam</link> has been applied commercially but is now considered uneconomic and inadequate.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> It kills surface growth but not underground growth and so respraying to treat regrowth of perennials is needed.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/212427.xml">
Flame</link> is considered more effective than steam but suffers from the same difficulties.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

D-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/1779163.xml">
limonene</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/52136.xml">
citrus</link> oil), which is the active ingredient in Nature's Avenger Organic Herbicide<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. D-limonene (citrus oil) is a natural degreasing agent that strips the waxy skin or cuticle from weeds, causing dehydration and ultimately death. Environmentally safe, Nature’s Avenger Organic Herbicide is registered by the EPA - (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</link>), and approved for use in organic production by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/70896.xml">
USDA</link> - (United States Department of Agriculture) and is OMRI - Organic Materials Review Institute<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> listed.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Application </st>

<p>

Most herbicides are applied as water-based sprays using ground equipment.  Ground equipment varies in design, but large areas can be sprayed using self-propelled sprayers equipped with a long boom, of  60 to 80 feet (20 to 25 m) with flat fan nozzles spaced about every 20 in (500 mm).  Towed, handheld, and even horse-drawn sprayers are also used.</p>
<p>

Synthetic organic herbicides can generally be applied aerially using helicopters or airplanes, and can be applied through irrigation systems (<link>
chemigation</link>).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Terminology </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Control</b> is the destruction of unwanted weeds, or the damage of them to the point where they are no longer competitive with the crop.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Suppression</b> is incomplete control still providing some economic benefit, such as reduced competition with the crop.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Crop Safety</b>, for selective herbicides, is the relative absence of damage or stress to the crop.  Most selective herbicides cause some visible stress to crop plants.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Major herbicides in use today</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/1624512.xml">
2,4-D</link>, a broadleaf herbicide in the phenoxy group used in turf and in no-till field crop production.  Now mainly used in a blend with other herbicides that allow lower rates of herbicides to be used, it is the most widely used herbicide in the world, third most commonly used in the United States. It is an example of synthetic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/496667.xml">
auxin</link> (plant hormone).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/18391570.xml">
aminopyralid</link> is a broadleaf herbicide in the pyridine group, used to control broadleaf weeds on grassland, such as docks, thistles and nettles. Notorious for its ability to persist in compost. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/1762549.xml">
atrazine</link>, a triazine herbicide used in corn and sorghum for control of broadleaf weeds and grasses.  Still used because of its low cost and because it works extrodinarily well on a broad spectrum of weeds common in the U.S. corn belt,  Atrazine is commonly used with other herbicides to reduce the over-all rate of atrazine and to lower the for potential groundwater contamination, it is a photosystem II inhibitor.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/263399.xml">
clopyralid</link> is a broadleaf herbicide in the pyridine group, used mainly in turf, rangeland, and for control of noxious thistles.  Notorious for its ability to persist in compost. It is another example of synthetic auxin. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/9521234.xml">
dicamba</link>, a persistent broadleaf herbicide active in the soil, used on turf and field corn. It is another example of synthetic auxin.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/11336168.xml">
Glufosinate ammonium</link>, a broad-spectrum contact herbicide and is used to control weeds after the crop emerges or for total vegetation control on land not used for cultivation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Fluroxypyr</link>, a systemic, selective herbicide used for the control of broad-leaved weeds in small grain cereals, maize, pastures, range land and turf. It is a synthetic auxin. In cereal growing, fluroxypyr's key importance is control of cleavers, <it>Galium aparine</it>. Other key broad-leaved weeds are also controlled. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/294295.xml">
Glyphosate</link>, a systemic non-selective (it kills any type of plant) herbicide used in no-till burndown and for weed control in crops that are genetically modified to resist its effects. It is an example of an EPSPs inhibitor.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/19320593.xml">
Imazapyr</link>, is a non-selective herbicide used for the control of a broad range of weeds including terrestrial annual and perennial grasses and broadleaved herbs, woody species, and riparian and emergent aquatic species.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Imazapic</link>, is a selective herbicide for both the pre- and post-emergent control of some annual and perennial grasses and some broadleaf weeds.  Imazapic kills plants by inhibiting the production of branched chain amino acids (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/63554.xml">
valine</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/63546.xml">
leucine</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/63543.xml">
isoleucine</link>), which are necessary for protein synthesis and cell growth.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Linuron</link>, is a non-selective herbicide used in the control of grasses and broadleafed weeds. It works by inhibiting photosynthesis.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/10568323.xml">
Metolachlor</link>, a pre-emergent herbicide widely used for control of annual grasses in corn and sorghum; it has largely replaced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/1762549.xml">
atrazine</link> for these uses.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/1065741.xml">
Paraquat</link>, a nonselective contact herbicide used for no-till burndown and in aerial destruction of marijuana and coca plantings.  More acutely toxic to people than any other herbicide in widespread commercial use.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/2910512.xml">
picloram</link>, a pyridine herbicide mainly used to control unwanted trees in pastures and edges of fields. It is another synthetic auxin.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/618819.xml">
Triclopyr</link>, a systemic, foliar herbicide in the pyridine group. It is used to control broadleaf weeds while leaving grasses and conifers unaffected.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Herbicides of historical interest</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/2986016.xml">
2,4,5-Trichlorophenoxyacetic acid</link> (2,4,5-T) was a widely used broadleaf herbicide until being phased out starting in the late 1970s.  While 2,4,5-T itself is of only moderate toxicity, the manufacturing process for 2,4,5-T contaminates this chemical with trace amounts of  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/51357.xml">
2,3,7,8-tetrachlorodibenzo-p-dioxin</link> (TCDD).  TCDD is extremely toxic to humans.  With proper temperature control during production of 2,4,5-T, TCDD levels can be held to about .005 ppm.  Before the TCDD risk was well understood, early production facilities lacked proper temperature controls.  Individual batches tested later were found to have as much as 60 ppm of TCDD.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2,4,5-T was withdrawn from use in the USA in 1983, at a time of heightened public sensitivity about chemical hazards in the environment.  Public concern about <waste wordnetid="114856263" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<carcinogen wordnetid="114793812" confidence="0.8">
<compound wordnetid="114818238" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<heterocyclic_compound wordnetid="115025397" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<pollutant wordnetid="114857278" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/51357.xml">
dioxins</link></material>
</pollutant>
</part>
</heterocyclic_compound>
</chemical>
</compound>
</carcinogen>
</substance>
</substance>
</waste>
 was high, and production and use of other (non-herbicide) chemicals potentially containing TCDD contamination was also withdrawn.  These included <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/1250286.xml">
pentachlorophenol</link> (a wood preservative) and <retardant wordnetid="109408250" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<waste wordnetid="114856263" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<carcinogen wordnetid="114793812" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="109190918" confidence="0.8">
<pollutant wordnetid="114857278" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/48230.xml">
PCB</link></material>
</pollutant>
</agent>
</part>
</causal_agent>
</carcinogen>
</substance>
</substance>
</waste>
</physical_entity>
</retardant>
s (mainly used as stabilizing agents in transformer oil).  Some feel that the 2,4,5-T withdrawal was not based on sound science.  2,4,5-T has since largely been replaced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/9521234.xml">
dicamba</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/618819.xml">
triclopyr</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/2547.xml">
Agent Orange</link> was a herbicide blend used by the U.S. military in Vietnam between January 1965 and April 1970 as a defoliant.  It was a 50/50 mixture of the <it>n</it>-butyl esters of 2,4,5-T and 2,4-D.    Because of TCDD contamination in the 2,4,5-T component, it has been blamed for serious illnesses in many veterans and Vietnamese people who were exposed to it.  However, research on populations exposed to its dioxin contaminant have been inconsistent and inconclusive.  Agent Orange often had much higher levels of TCDD than 2,4,5-T used in the US.  The name <it>Agent Orange</it> is derived from the orange color-coded stripe used by the Army on barrels containing the product. It is worth noting that there were other blends of synthetic auxins at the time of the <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/32611.xml">
Vietnam War</link></conflict>
 whose containers were recognized by their colors, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/2048040.xml">
Agent Purple</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/3015704.xml">
Agent Pink</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/1132329.xml">
Bioherbicide</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/1630338.xml">
Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act</link> (FIFRA) of the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 (covers herbicides despite title)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/154347.xml">
List of environmental health hazards</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/16334333.xml">
Pesticide application</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<consequence wordnetid="111410625" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/1429257.xml">
Pesticide toxicity to bees</link></consequence>
</phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/9239161.xml">
Rainbow Herbicides</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<danger wordnetid="114541044" confidence="0.8">
<issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<hazard wordnetid="114541852" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/4229946.xml">
Soil contamination</link></causal_agent>
</hazard>
</issue>
</danger>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/4400374.xml">
Surface runoff</link></phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/19653902.xml">
Weed Science</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Kellogg RL, Nehring R, Grube A, Goss DW, and Plotkin S (February 2000), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nrcs.usda.gov/Technical/land/pubs/eip_pap.html">
Environmental indicators of pesticide leaching and runoff from farm fields</weblink>. United States Department of Agriculture Natural Resources Conservation Service. Retrieved on <link>
2007-10-03</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Stryer, Lubert&#32;(1995). Biochemistry, 4th Edition.&#32;W.H. Freeman and Company,&#32;pp. 670. ISBN 0-7167-2009-4.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ars.usda.gov/is/pr/2002/020515.htm">
Spray Weeds With Vinegar?</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ipm.ucdavis.edu/PMG/PESTNOTES/pn7441.html">
Weed Management in Landscapes</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nswg.org/tomlanini.htm">
Organic Weed Management in Vineyards</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
Kolberg, Robert L., and Lori J. Wiles. 2002. Effect of steam application on cropland weeds. <it>Weed Technology</it>. Vol. 16, No. 1. p. 43–49</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://attra.ncat.org/attra-pub/flameweedveg.html">
Flame weeding for vegetable crops</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://naturesavenger.com/faqs.html">
Nature's Avenger Organic Herbicide - FAQs</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.omri.org/OMRI_who.html">
The Organic Materials Review Institute</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pan-uk.org/pestnews/actives/glufosin.htm">
Fact sheet</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>


<ss1>
<st>
General Information</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://npic.orst.edu">
National Pesticide Information Center</weblink>, Information about pesticide-related topics</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nass.usda.gov">
National Agricultural Statistics Service</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Regulatory policy</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov">
US EPA</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pesticides.gov.uk">
UK Pesticides Safety Directorate</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://europa.eu.int/comm/food/plant/protection/evaluation/index_en.htm">
European Commission pesticide information</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pmra-arla.gc.ca">
Pest Management Regulatory Agency of Canada</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Other Reading </st>
<p>

<b><it>A Brief History of On-track Weed Control in the N.S.W. SRA during the Steam Era</it></b> Longworth, Jim <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/6958687.xml">
Australian Railway Historical Society Bulletin</link></publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</press>
</creation>
</print_media>
</magazine>
</product>
</work>
, April, 1996 pp99-116</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
