<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:40:28[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>MDL Information Systems</title>
<id>5427131</id>
<revision>
<id>215894496</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-30T04:29:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Chemhistorian</username>
<id>7195773</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles with possible conflicts of interest</category>
<category>Information science</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Unbalanced_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>A major contributor to this article or its creator appears to have a  with its subject.</b>
It may require  to comply with Wikipedia's content policies, particularly . Please discuss further on the . <it>(January 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>MDL Information Systems</b>, a provider of R&amp;D informatics offerings for the life sciences and chemicals industries and acquired by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/275883.xml">
Symyx Technologies</link></company>
, Inc. in 2007, was launched as a computer-aided drug design firm (originally named Molecular Design Limited, Inc.) in January 1978 in Hayward, CA.<p>

The company was founded by Stuart Marson and W. Todd Wipke.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  "In other industries, aircraft and electronics, for example, automated design is taken for granted, so why not chemistry?" said Wipke. "But parts of such a system already exist, and Wipke,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> after 15 years of research on computer synthesis at the University of California, Santa Cruz, and Marson, fresh from a Ph.D. at Stanford University and a postdoctoral stint at the University of California, Berkeley, are convinced that the current state of the art will support computer-assisted molecular design as a commercial enterprise."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.  Employee #3 was Stephen Peacock, a colleague of Marson, and #4 was Jim Dill, a graduate student from Princeton, as was #5, Doug Hounshell, also a graduate of Princeton.
MDL was the first company to provide interactive graphical registry and full and substructural retrieval.  The company's initial products were first-of-their-kind systems for storing and retrieving molecules as graphical structures and for managing databases of chemical reactions and related data. These systems revolutionized the way scientists accessed and managed chemical information in the 1980s.</p>
<p>

From its initial pioneering of computer handling of graphical chemical structures with MACCS (Molecular ACCess System) in 1979, MDL continued at the forefront of the field now known as cheminformatics. Innovations include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial system for interactive molecular modeling (PRXBLD, 1979)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial system for computer handling of chemical reactions (REACCS, 1982)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial system integrating chemical structures with data (MACCS-II, 1984)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 PC-based chemistry database system, the Chemist's Personal Software Series (CPSS: ChemBase, ChemTalk/ChemHost, 1985)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial system integrating chemistry drawing and word processing (ChemText, 1986) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial 3D structure database (MACCS-3D, 1988)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial system for storing structures of mixtures and formulations (MACCS-II Substance Module, 1989)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial client-server system for managing chemical and biological information (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/framework/isis/index.jsp">
MDL ISIS</weblink>, 1991)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial system for structure-based handling of generic structures (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/framework/central_lib/index.jsp">
MDL Central Library</weblink>, 1996)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Searchable, "live" chemical structures in Web pages (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/3939419.xml">
MDL Chime</link> plug-in, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/framework/chemscape/index.jsp">
MDL Chemscape</weblink> server, 1996)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Commercial system dynamically linking citations to electronic journal articles and patents (MDL LitLink, 1999)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Web-based commercial system indexing multiple structure databases and linking to synthetic methodology databases and major reference works (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/knowledge/discoverygate/index.jsp">
DiscoveryGate</weblink>, 2002)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Software application for predicting potential carcinogenic risk of compounds based on their structures (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/predictive/carc_module/index.jsp">
MDL Carcinogenicity Module</weblink>, 2003)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Complete, open, flexible and scalable n-tier informatics system supporting enterprise-wide business process, data and application integration for the life sciences (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/framework/isentris/index.jsp">
MDL Isentris</weblink>, 2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Advanced structure drawing with All-Purpose Drawing Tool and custom template toolbars, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/framework/mdl_draw/index.jsp">
MDL Draw</weblink>, 2004)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Structure-searchable patent chemistry information (Patent Chemistry Database, 2004) and online pharmacological information (xPharm, 2004) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Key laboratory workflow applications (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/experiment/mdl_logistics/index.jsp">
MDL Logistics</weblink> reagent management application and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/experiment/mdl_notebook/index.jsp">
MDL Notebook</weblink> electronic laboratory notebook, 2005)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Isentris-based application for building and managing compound registries (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/experiment/mdl_registration/index.jsp">
MDL Registration</weblink>, 2006)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 First electronically searchable FDA Drug Approval Packages (PharmaPendium, 2006)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Out-of-the-box Reaction Planner for exploring precursor steps, integration of proprietary and commercial data (Isentris 2.0 and 3.0, 2007).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In 1985, MDL moved its corporate headquarters from Hayward to a larger campus in San Leandro, CA. In 1987, MDL was purchased by Maxwell Communications Corporation. In 1993, the company was publicly offered as MDL Information Systems, Inc. (MDLI) on the NASDAQ stock exchange. In 1997, the company was purchased by Reed Elsevier, the Anglo-Dutch publisher and information provider, becoming a wholly owned subsidiary of Elsevier, a publisher of scientific, technical and medical information. In February 2006, Elsevier MDL moved its corporate headquarters from San Leandro to San Ramon, CA.</p>
<p>

In October 2007, Elsevier MDL was acquired by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/275883.xml">
Symyx Technologies, Inc.</link></company>
, an R&amp;D productivity company offering software, modular workflow tools and research services to global enterprises in the life sciences, chemicals, energy and consumer products industries. MDL has been merged with Symyx Software, and the new combined organization is based in San Ramon, CA. (Following the sale to Symyx of the infrastructure-related software applications and databases of MDL, the content assets of MDL retained by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/420561.xml">
Elsevier</link></company>
 — including CrossFire Beilstein, CrossFire Gmelin, the Patent Chemistry Database, xPharm and PharmaPendium — were integrated within Elsevier's Science &amp; Technology operations.)</p>
<p>

The August 2007 press release announcing Symyx Technologies' acquisition of MDL indicates that combining Symyx and MDL offerings creates an expanded set of software solutions and services to enhance R&amp;D productivity in the life sciences, chemicals and energy industries. The press release states: "With this solution set, Symyx will be able to accelerate its customers' move toward paperless labs by integrating content, collaborative desktops, automation and information management for users, workgroups and the enterprise."</p>

<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Waldrop, Mitch: "Company offers computer-assisted chemistry", p 29, C&amp;EN, June 18, 1979</entry>
<entry id="2">
Corey and Wipke, "Computer-Asssisted Design of Complex Organic Syntheses, Science, 166, p 178, 1969</entry>
<entry id="3">
C&amp;EN, June 18, 1979</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/6019.xml">
Computational chemistry</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/3218783.xml">
Drug development</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/571274.xml">
Drug discovery</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/7474102.xml">
Drug Discovery Hit to Lead</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/575697.xml">
Cheminformatics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/1131357.xml">
Pre-clinical development</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/579414.xml">
Drug design</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/579414.xml">
Rational drug design</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/9387033.xml">
Compound management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/734256.xml">
Molecular modeling</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/company/news/press_releases/2007/pr_mdl_symyx_10aug07.jsp	Symyx">
Technologies to Acquire MDL Information Systems from Elsevier (August 10, 2007)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/company/news/press_releases/2007/pr_acquisition_02oct07.jsp">
Symyx Technologies, Inc. Closes Acquisition of MDL Inormation Systems (October 2, 2007)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/company/news/newsmagazine/pdfs/molconwinter2003.pdf">
Molecular Connection 25th Anniversary</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com">
Official Web site - MDL</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.symyx.com">
Official Web site - Symyx Technologies</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/framework/chime/index.jsp">
MDL Chime</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdl.com/products/framework/mdl_draw/index.jsp">
MDL Draw</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.discoverygate.com">
DiscoveryGate</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
