<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:45:40[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>AgMES</title>
<id>5465589</id>
<revision>
<id>220273267</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-19T01:59:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Earle Martin</username>
<id>9867</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Agriculture</category>
<category>Library cataloging and classification</category>
<category>Semantic Web</category>
<category>Knowledge representation</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>AgMES</b> is the abbreviation for <b>Agricultural Metadata Element Set</b>. AgMES is the metadata standard developed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/11107.xml">
Food and Agriculture Organization</link> (FAO) of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/31769.xml">
United Nations</link>  for the description and discovery of agricultural information resources. It provides a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> elements that can be used to describe all types of information resources in the areas of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/627.xml">
Agriculture</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/53912.xml">
Forestry</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/307491.xml">
Fisheries</link>, Food Security, and other related domains. <p>

There are numerous other metadata schemas for different types of information resources. The following list contains a list of a few examples: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Document-like Information Objects (DLIOs): <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/8742.xml">
Dublin Core</link></format>
</information>
</message>
, Agricultural Metadata Element Set (AgMES)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Events: <link>
VCalendar</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Geographic and Regional Information: Geographic information -- Metadata <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://isotc.iso.org/livelink/livelink/fetch/2000/2489/Ittf_Home/PubliclyAvailableStandards.htm">
ISO/IEC 11179 Standards</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Persons: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/2652901.xml">
 Friend-of-a-friend</link> (FOAF), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/285478.xml">
vCard</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Plant Production and Protection: Darwin Core (1.0 and 2.0) (DwC)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

AgMES as a namespace is designed to include agriculture specific extensions for terms and refinements from established standard metadata namespaces like <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/8742.xml">
Dublin Core</link></format>
</information>
</message>
, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.naa.gov.au/recordkeeping/gov_online/agls/summary.html">
AGLS</weblink> etc. Thus to be used for Document-like Information Objects, for example like publications, articles, books, web sites, papers, etc., it will have to be used in conjunction with the standard namespaces mentioned before.  The AgMES initiative strives to achieve improved interoperability between information resources in agricultural domain by enabling means for exchange of information. </p>
<p>

Describing a DLIO with AgMES means exposing its major characteristics and contents in a standard way that can be reused easily in any information system. The more institutions and organizations in the agricultural domain that use AgMES to describe their DLIOs, the easier it will be to interchange data in between information systems like digital libraries and other repositories of agricultural information. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Use of AgMES </st>
<p>

Metadata on agricultural Document-like Information Objects (DLIOs) can be created and stored in various formats: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 embedded in a web site (in the manor as with the HTML meta tag)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 in a separate metadata database</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 in an XML file</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 in an RDF file</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

AgMES defines elements that can be used to describe a DLIO that can be used together with other metadata standards such as the Dublin Core, the Australian Government Locator Service. A complete list of all elements, refinements and schemes endorsed by AgMES is available from the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/aims/agmes_elements.jsp">
AgMES website</weblink>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Creating application profiles </st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/5475989.xml">
Application profile</link>s are defined as schemas which consist of data elements drawn from one or more namespaces, combined by implementers, and optimized for a particular local application. Application profiles share the following four characteristics: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 They draw upon existing pool of metadata definition standards to extract suitable application- or requirement oriented elements. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An application profile cannot create new elements. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Application profiles specify the application specific details such as the schemes or controlled vocabularies. An application profile also contains information such as the format for the element value, cardinality or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/93817.xml">
data type</link>. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lastly, an application profile can refine standardized definitions as long as it is "semantically narrower or more specific". This capability of application profiles caters to situations where a domain specific terminology is needed to replace a more general one.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Sample application profiles using AgMES </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/docrep/008/ae909e/ae909e00.htm">
AGRIS Application Profile</weblink> is a standard created specifically to enhance the description, exchange and subsequent retrieval of agricultural Document-like Information Objects (DLIOs). It is a format that allows sharing of information across dispersed bibliographic systems and is based on well-known and accepted metadata standards.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/aims/ap_applied.jsp">
Event Application Profile</weblink> is a standard created to allow members of the Agricultural community to 'know' about an upcoming event and guide them to the event Web site where they can find further information. The information communicated is thus minimum yet interoperable across domains and organizations.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The AgMES metadata tool </st>
<p>

The AgMESMeta tool creates AgMES-compliant metadata for Web Pages and other document-like resources. Once you are satisfied with the content of each element, cut and paste the generated metadata in the  section of your HTM(L) file. The tool also allows you to harvest existing metadata from a webpage for further editing.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 AgMES and the semantic web </st>

<p>

One of the advantages of the AgMES metadata schema is the ability to link between the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/40992.xml">
 metadata element</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/1850719.xml">
 controlled vocabularies</link>. The use of controlled vocabulary provides a "known" set of options to the indexer (and the search programmer) as to how the field can be filled out. Often the values may come from a specific thesaurus (e.g. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/5465574.xml">
AGROVOC</link>) or classification schemes (e.g. the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/aims/index_en.jsp?callingPage=ag_classifschemes.jsp">
AGRIS/CARIS classification scheme</weblink>)etc. </p>
<p>

Thanks to the possibility to use controlled vocabularies for metadata elements, the user is provided with the most precise information. In this context, work is also being carried out on exploiting the power of controlled vocabularies expressed as using URIs and machine-understandable semantics.  In this context, FAO is promoting the <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/5465607.xml">
Agricultural Ontology Service</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (AOS) initiative with the objective of expressing more semantics within the traditional thesaurus AGROVOC and build a <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/aims/cs.htm">
Concept Server</weblink> as a repository from which it will be always possible to extract traditional KOS.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/5465607.xml">
Agricultural Ontology Service</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/5465574.xml">
AGROVOC</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/5465644.xml">
 Agricultural Information Management Standards website</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/aims/agmes_intro.jsp">
AgMES Website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dublincore.org/">
Dublin Core Metadata Initiative</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dublincore.org/documents/abstract-model/">
Dublin Core Abstract Model</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://xml.coverpages.org/ni2003-05-12-a.html">
FAO's AgMES Project Releases a New Application Profile for Encoding Metadata.</weblink> (<it>Cover Pages</it>, May 2003) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/documents/advanced_s_result.asp?FORM_C=AND&amp;SERIES=339">
Agricultural Information and Knowledge Management Papers</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/nems/rss/rss_nems_results.asp?owner=615&amp;status=10&amp;dateto=31/12/2006&amp;lang=en&amp;sites=1">
RSS feed of news and events</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dgroups.org/groups/fao/agstandards/index.cfm?op=dsp_join">
Agstandards Discussion List</weblink>: This is a forum established for discussing metadata standards and the development of multilingual thesauri and ontologies.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
