<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:16:50[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Chemical database</title>
<id>553787</id>
<revision>
<id>241848502</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-29T20:15:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Kbdankbot</username>
<id>6505923</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cheminformatics</category>
<category>Chemical databases</category>
<category>Computational chemistry</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>chemical database</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> specifically designed to store <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/575697.xml">
chemical information</link>.  Most chemical databases store information on stable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/19555.xml">
molecule</link>s. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/474009.xml">
Chemical structure</link>s are traditionally represented using lines indicating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/5993.xml">
chemical bonds</link> between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/902.xml">
atoms</link> and drawn on paper (2D <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/191985.xml">
structural formula</link>e). While these are ideal visual representations for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/5636.xml">
chemist</link>, they are unsuitable for computational use and especially for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/28249.xml">
search</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/5300.xml">
storage</link>. Small molecules (also called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/18589.xml">
ligands</link> in drug design applications), are usually represented using lists of atoms and their connections. Large molecules such as proteins are however more compactly represented using the sequences of their amino acid building blocks.<p>

Large chemical databases are expected to handle the storage and searching of information on millions of molecules taking <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/30657.xml">
terabytes</link> of physical memory.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Representation </st>

<p>

There are two principal techniques for representing chemical structures in digital databases</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 As connection tables / <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/244463.xml">
adjacency matrices</link> / lists with additional information on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/5993.xml">
bond</link> (edges) and atom attributes (nodes) eg: </entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/1516624.xml">
MDL Molfile</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/102505.xml">
PDB</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/697229.xml">
CML</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 As a linear string notation based on <algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/97034.xml">
depth first</link></algorithm>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/97026.xml">
breadth first traversal</link> eg: </entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/28569.xml">
SMILES</link></format>
/SMARTS, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/3718479.xml">
SLN</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/8463705.xml">
WLN</link>, <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/1995749.xml">
InChI</link></database>
</wordnet>
</format>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

These approaches have been refined to allow representation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/28756.xml">
stereochemical</link> differences and charges as well as special kinds of bonding such as those seen in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/22526.xml">
organo-metallic</link> compounds.  The principal advantage of a computer representation is the possibility for increased storage and fast, flexible search.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Search </st>

<ss1>
<st>
Substructure</st>
<p>

Chemists can search databases using parts of structures, parts of their <link>
IUPAC</link> names as well as based on constraints on properties. Chemical databases are particularly different from other general purpose databases in their support for sub-structure search. This kind of search is achieved by looking for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/450062.xml">
subgraph isomorphism</link> (sometimes also called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/59538.xml">
monomorphism</link>) and is a widely studied application of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
Graph theory</link>.  The algorithms for searching are computationally intensive, often of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/44578.xml">
O</link> (<it>n</it>3) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/44578.xml">
O</link> (<it>n</it>4) time complexity (where <it>n</it> is the number of atoms involved). The intensive component of search is called atom-by-atom-searching (ABAS), in which a mapping of the search substructure atoms and bonds with the target molecule is sought. ABAS searching usually makes use of <link>
Ullman's algorithm</link> or variations of it. Speedups are achieved by <link>
time amortization</link>, that is, some of the time on search tasks are saved by using precomputed information. This pre-computation typically involves creation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/3087412.xml">
bitstring</link>s representing presence or absence of molecular fragments. By looking at the fragments present in a search structure it is possible to eliminate the need for ABAS comparison with target molecules that do not possess the fragments that are present in the search structure. This elimination is called screening (not to be confused with the screening procedures used in drug-discovery). The bit-strings used for these applications are also called structural-keys. The performance of such keys depends on the choice of the fragments used for constructing the keys and the probability of their presence in the database molecules. Another kind of key makes use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/13790.xml">
hash-code</link>s based on fragments derived computationally. These are called 'fingerprints' although the term is sometimes used synonymously with structural-keys. The amount of memory needed to store these structural-keys and fingerprints can be reduced by 'folding', which is achieved by combining parts of the key using bitwise-operations and thereby reducing the overall length.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Conformation</st>
<p>

Search by matching 3D conformation of molecules or by specifying spatial constraints is another feature that is particularly of use in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/579414.xml">
drug design</link>. Searches of this kind can be computationally very expensive, however new algorithms such as the <it>Ultrafast Shape Recognition</it> algorithm devised by Pedro Ballester and Graham Richards of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/31797.xml">
Oxford University</link> help speed up search by encoding shape parameters into a small set of parameters such as the first three moments (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/19192.xml">
mean</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/32344.xml">
variance</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/28212.xml">
skewness</link>) of the distributions of interatomic distances.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Descriptors</st>
<p>

All properties of molecules beyond their structure can be split up into either physico-chemical or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/24354.xml">
pharmacological</link> attributes also called descriptors. On top of that, there exist various artificial and more or less standardized naming systems for molecules that supply more or less ambiguous names and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/67396.xml">
synonym</link>s. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/3141503.xml">
IUPAC name</link> is usually a good choice for representing a molecule's structure in a both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/359250.xml">
human-readable</link> and unique <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/27701.xml">
string</link> although it becomes unwieldy for larger molecules. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/889940.xml">
Trivial name</link>s on the other hand abound with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/148126.xml">
homonym</link>s and synonyms and are therefore a bad choice as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/6850099.xml">
defining database key</link>. While physico-chemical descriptors like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/60034.xml">
molecular weight</link>, (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/344948.xml">
partial</link>) charge, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/59497.xml">
solubility</link>, etc. can mostly be computed directly based on the molecule's structure, pharmacological descriptors can be derived only indirectly using involved multivariate statistics or experimental (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/1928867.xml">
screening</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/47489.xml">
bioassay</link>) results. All of those descriptors can for reasons of computational effort be stored along with the molecule's representation and usually are.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Similarity </st>

<p>

There is no single definition of molecular similarity, however the concept may be defined according to the application and is often described as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/45199.xml">
inverse</link> of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/39378.xml">
measure of distance</link> in descriptor space. Two molecules might be considered more similar for instance if their difference in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/60034.xml">
molecular weight</link>s is lower than when compared with others. A variety of other measures could be combined to produce a multi-variate distance measure. Distance measures are often classified into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/53932.xml">
Euclidean measure</link>s and non-Euclidean measures depending on whether the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/53941.xml">
triangle inequality</link> holds. </p>
<p>

Chemicals in the databases may be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/39172.xml">
clustered</link> into groups of 'similar' molecules based on similarities. Both hierarchical and non-hierarchical clustering approaches can be applied to chemical entities with multiple attributes. These attributes or molecular properties may either be determined empirically or computationally derived <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/14286667.xml">
descriptors</link>. One of the most popular clustering approaches is the <link>
Jarvis-Patrick algorithm</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/1775388.xml">
k-nearest neighbours algorithm</link>).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/24354.xml">
pharmacological</link>ly-oriented chemical repositories, similarity is usually defined in terms of the biological effects of compounds (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/826690.xml">
ADME</link>/tox) that can in turn be semiautomatically inferred from similar combinations of physico-chemical descriptors using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/826669.xml">
QSAR</link> methods.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Registration systems </st>

<p>

Databases systems for maintaining unique records on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/144412.xml">
chemical compound</link>s are termed as Registration systems. These are often used for chemical indexing, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/23273.xml">
patent</link> systems and industrial databases.</p>
<p>

Registration systems usually enforce uniqueness of the chemical represented in the database through the use of unique representations. By applying rules of precedence for the generation of stringified notations, one can obtain unique/'<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/328150.xml">
canonical</link>' string representations such as 'canonical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/28569.xml">
SMILES</link>'. Some registration systems such as the CAS system make use of algorithms to generate unique <link>
hash code</link>s to achieve the same objective.</p>
<p>

A key difference between a registration system and a simple chemical database is the ability to accurately represent that which is known, unknown, and partially known.  For example, a chemical database might store a molecule with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/28756.xml">
stereochemistry</link> unspecified, whereas a chemical registry system requires the registrar to specify whether the stereo configuration is unknown, a specific (known) mixture, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/75089.xml">
racemic</link>.  Each of these would be considered a different record in a chemical registry system.</p>
<p>

Registration systems also preprocess molecules to avoid considering trivial differences such as differences in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/13258.xml">
halogen</link> ions in chemicals.</p>
<p>

An example is the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/585185.xml">
Chemical Abstracts Service</link></organization>
 (CAS) registration system <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cas.org/EO/regsys.html">
http://www.cas.org/EO/regsys.html</weblink>. See also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/160815.xml">
CAS registry number</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Tools </st>

<p>

The computational representations are usually made transparent to chemists by graphical display of the data. Data entry is also simplified through the use of chemical structure editors. These editors internally convert the graphical data into computational representations.</p>
<p>

There are also numerous algorithms for the interconversion of various formats of representation. An open-source utility for conversion is <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/3706998.xml">
OpenBabel</link></software>
. These search and conversion algorithms are implemented either within the database system itself or as is now the trend is implemented as external components that fit into standard relational database systems. Both Oracle and <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/23824.xml">
PostgreSQL</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 based systems make use of <b>cartridge technology</b> that allows user defined datatypes. These allow the user to make <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/29004.xml">
SQL</link> queries with chemical search conditions (For example a query to search for records having a benzene ring in their structure represented as a SMILES string in a SMILESCOL column could be </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 SELECT * FROM CHEMTABLE WHERE SMILESCOL.CONTAINS('c1ccccc1').
</indent>

Algorithms for the conversion of <link>
IUPAC</link> names to structure representations and vice versa are also used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/318439.xml">
extracting structural information from text</link>. However there are difficulties due to the existence of multiple dialects of IUPAC. Work is on to establish a unique IUPAC standard (See <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/1995749.xml">
InChI</link></database>
</wordnet>
</format>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
).</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/17077434.xml">
Comparative Toxicogenomics Database</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/2335158.xml">
Beilstein database</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/2863723.xml">
PubChem</link></association>
</institute>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/3408731.xml">
DrugBank</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/10468561.xml">
ChemSpider</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/7920748.xml">
LOLI database</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Cummings, Maxwell D.; Maxwell, Alan C.; DesJarlais, Renee L. (2007) Processing of Small Molecule Databases for Automated Docking. Medicinal Chemistry 3(1):107-113</entry>
<entry id="2">
Ballester, P. J. &amp; W. G. Richards (2007) Ultrafast shape recognition for similarity search in molecular databases. Proc R Soc A, 463:1307-1321</entry>
<entry id="3">
Butina, Darko (1999) Unsupervised Data Base Clustering Based on Daylight’s Fingerprint and Tanimoto Similarity: A Fast and Automated Way To Cluster Small and Large Data Sets.  Chem. Inf. Comput. Sci. 39:747-750</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Discussion group </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/2907947.xml">
Computational Chemistry List</link> : Email discussion group </entry>
</list>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Database and registration software</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cdk.sourceforge.net/">
CDK a Java open source library for chemical data handling</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acdlabs.com/products/chem_dsn_lab/chemfolder/">
Chemfolder, a PC-based software application for structure and reaction database manipulation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chemadvisor.com">
ChemADVISOR, Inc.</weblink>, creator of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/7920748.xml">
LOLI Database</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/joelib/">
JOELib</weblink>, a Java chemical data handling software library</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chemaxon.com/jchem/">
JChem:</weblink> a Java-based suite <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
API</link> toolkits for structure management, search, editing and other things cheminformatic - free for Academic teaching and research and for free web pages </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://openbabel.sourceforge.net">
OpenBabel</weblink>, a program to interconvert different chemical formats</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cactus.nci.nih.gov/ncidb2">
NCI database browser</weblink>, enhanced CACTVS-based Browser of the National Cancer Institute open database</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Databases of chemical structures</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chemsynthesis.com">
Synthesis references database</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eChemPortal.eu">
www.eChemPortal.eu</weblink>, a global portal to information on Chemical Substances</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://chem.sis.nlm.nih.gov/chemidplus">
NLM ChemIDplus</weblink>, biomedical chemicals searchable by name and structure.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cas.org">
Chemical Abstracts Service</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.orgsyn.org/">
Organic synthesis database</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blaster.docking.org/zinc/">
ZINC</weblink>, a free database for virtual screening</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jchem.info/">
JCHEM.INFO</weblink>, Free Organic And Inorganic Chemicals Database, Compound Physical Data</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chemspider.com/">
ChemSpider</weblink>, Free access to &amp;gt; 10 Million Chemical Structures, Physical Property Data and Systematic Identifiers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mms.dsfarm.unipd.it/MMsINC/search/">
MMsINC</weblink>, a free web-oriented database of commercially available compounds for virtual screening and chemoinformatic applications</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Databases of chemical names</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.saglasie.com/tr/chemical/">
Chemical Substances Database</weblink>, a free database of chemical names, mainly useful for translation of names between Japanese and English.  More than 37,000 entries.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://chemsub.online.fr">
ChemSub Online</weblink>, the free Chemical Portal, 8 languages names. </entry>
</list>
</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
