<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:45:54[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104377057">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<header>
<title>Disk partitioning</title>
<id>55380</id>
<revision>
<id>241955384</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T06:45:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Johnny039</username>
<id>7963864</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>DOS on IBM PC compatibles</category>
<category>Disk file systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="300px" src="GParted.png" type="thumb">
</image>

<b>Disk partitioning</b> is the creation of separate divisions of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard disk drive</link> using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/4665083.xml">
partition editor</link>s. Once a disk is divided into several partitions, directories and files of different categories may be stored in different partitions. More partitions provide more control but too many become cumbersome. The way space management, access permissions and directory searching are implemented depends upon the type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/1010280.xml">
file system</link> installed on a partition. Careful consideration of the size of the partition is necessary as the ability to change the size depends on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/1010280.xml">
file system</link> installed on the partition.<p>

Purposes for partitioning:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Separation of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> files from user files</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Having an area for operating system <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/32354.xml">
virtual memory</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/311193.xml">
swapping/paging</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Keeping frequently used programs and data near each other.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Having cache and log files separate from other files. These can change size dynamically and rapidly, potentially making a file system full.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/494756.xml">
multi boot</link>ing setups, which allow users to have more than one operating system on a single computer. For example, one could install <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> or others on different partitions of the same hard disk  and have a choice of booting into any operating system (supported by the hardware) at power-up.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Protecting or isolating files, to make it easier to recover a corrupted file system or operating system installation. If one partition is corrupted, none of the other file systems are affected, and the drive's data may still be salvageable. Having a separate partition for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/304378.xml">
read-only</link> data also reduces the chances of the file system on this partition becoming corrupted.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Raising overall computer performance on systems where smaller file systems are more efficient. For instance, large hard drives with only one <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/39184.xml">
NTFS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 file system typically have a very large sequentially-accessed Master File Table (MFT) and it generally takes more time to read this MFT than the smaller MFTs of smaller partitions.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
PC BIOS partition types</st>
<p>

This section describes partitions as used in <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/20027.xml">
MS-DOS</link></O>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> and <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/49803.xml">
PC compatible</link> computer systems; for examples of partitioning schemes used in other operating systems, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/6200040.xml">
Slice (disk)</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/5377176.xml">
BSD disklabel</link>.</p>
<p>

A PC hard disk can contain up to <b>four</b> partitions. Each of them can be a <it>primary</it> partition and at most one can be an <it>extended</it> one. All these partitions are described by 16-byte entries that constitute the <b>Partition Table</b> which is (normally) located in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/55389.xml">
Master Boot Record</link>.</p>
<p>

The "type" of a partition is identified by a 1-byte code found in its partition table entry. Some of these codes (such as 0x05 and 0x0F) may be used to indicate the presence of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/3968527.xml">
extended partition</link>, but most are used by operating systems that examine partition tables to decide if a partition contains a file system they can <it>mount/access</it> for reading or writing data.   </p>
<p>

Once a specific partition's <it>type</it> has been identified, additional information about its purpose and probable contents may be found (see: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.win.tue.nl/~aeb/partitions/partition_types-1.html">
List of partition identifiers for PCs</weblink> as one such resource). For example, some <it>type codes</it> are used to <it>hide</it> a partition's contents from various operating systems. However, if an OS or some partitioning tool has been programmed to also examine the boot sectors of any partition, then its file system may no longer remain hidden. (Note: There are no <it>officially assigned</it> partition types; thus, more than one kind of file system may <it>lay claim</it> to the same code value.) </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Primary (or <it>logical</it>)</st>
<p>

A primary (or logical) partition contains one file system. In <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/20027.xml">
MS-DOS</link></O>
 and earlier versions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> systems, the first partition (C:) must be a "primary partition". Other operating systems may not share this limitation; however, this can depend on other factors, such as a PC's <generic wordnetid="107899976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/Form_4473.xml">
BIOS</link></generic>
 (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Boot_sequence_on_standard_PC_(IBM-PC_compatible)%22])">
Boot sequence on standard PC</link> for more information).</p>
<p>

The "partition type" code for a primary or <it>logical</it> partition can either correspond to a file system contained within (e.g. 0x07 means either an <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/39184.xml">
NTFS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 or an OS/2 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/81598.xml">
HPFS</link> file system) or indicate the partition has a special use (e.g. code 0xBC may mean an <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/11066141.xml">
Acronis Secure Zone</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 and code 0x82 usually indicates a Linux <it>swap</it> partition). The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/53045.xml">
FAT16 and FAT32</link> file systems have made use of quite a number of partition type codes over time due to the limits of various DOS and Windows OS versions. Though a Linux operating system may recognize a number of different file systems (ext2, ext3, reiserfs, etc.), they have all consistently used the same partition type code: 0x83 (Linux native).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Extended</st>
<p>

An extended partition is secondary to the primary partition(s). A hard disk may contain only one extended partition; which can then be sub-divided into <it>logical drives</it>, each of which is (under DOS and Windows) assigned additional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../424/55424.xml">
drive letter</link>s.</p>
<p>

For example, under either DOS or Windows, a hard disk with one primary partition and one extended partition, the latter containing two logical drives, would typically be assigned the three drive letters: C: for the primary partition, and D: and E: for the two logical drives.</p>
<p>

See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/3968527.xml">
extended boot record</link> for information on the structure of an extended partition.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Compressed disks </st>
<p>

Hard disks are sometimes compressed to create additional space.  Under <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../027/20027.xml">
MS-DOS</link></O>
 and early Microsoft Windows, programs such as STACKER (DR-DOS except 6), SuperStor (DR-DOS 6), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/3524206.xml">
DoubleSpace</link>, or DriveSpace (Windows 95) were used. This compression was done by creating a very large file on the partition, then storing the disk's data in this file. At startup, device drivers opened this file and assigned it a separate letter. Frequently, to avoid confusion, the original partition and the compressed drive had their letters swapped, so that the compressed disk is C:, and the uncompressed area (often containing system files) is given a higher name. (SuperStor required a separate device driver to be loaded, DEVSWAP.COM).</p>
<p>

Versions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Windows</link> using the NT kernel, including the most recent versions, XP and Vista, contain intrinsic disk compression capability. The use of separate disk compression utilities has declined sharply.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Partitioning schemes </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 DOS, OS/2, and Windows </st>
<p>

With DOS, <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/22409.xml">
OS/2</link></O>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link>, the standard partitioning scheme is to create a single active primary partition, the C: drive, where the operating system, utilities, applications, user data, and page/swap file all reside. Some users, however, prefer to create multiple partitions so that the operating system can be stored separately from other kinds of data. Proponents of multiple partitions generally point to the benefit of being able to erase a single partition (typically the operating system itself) while retaining the other data. When used in conjunction with third-party partition management programs such as <link>
Acronis Disk Director</link>, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/504123.xml">
Norton PartitionMagic</link></software>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/640080.xml">
Norton Ghost</link>, or specialized recovery programs that come with computers manufactured by most major manufacturers, the use of multiple partitions allows computer users to quickly recover from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/18994196.xml">
viruses</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/223942.xml">
rootkit</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/30056.xml">
trojan horse</link>s or an otherwise damaged, corrupt or compromised operating system. </p>
<p>

<version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/2289648.xml">
Windows Vista</link></version>
 includes an inbuilt 'Disk Management' program which allows for the creation, deletion and movement of partitions.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Unix </st>
<p>

For <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
-based and <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/31815.xml">
Unix-like</link></family>
 operating systems such as <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/6097297.xml">
Linux</link></O>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/20640.xml">
Mac OS X</link>, the creation of separate partitions for /boot, /home, /tmp, /usr, /var, /opt, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/311193.xml">
swap</link> and all remaining files under the "/" (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/158871.xml">
root directory</link>) is possible. (The same is true for Sun  operating systems, except their partitions are called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/6200040.xml">
slices</link>.) Such a scheme has a number of potential advantages: if one <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/1010280.xml">
file system</link> gets corrupted, the rest of the data (the other file systems) stay intact, minimizing data loss; partitions can be accessed read-only and the execution of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/1054629.xml">
setuid</link> files disabled thus enhancing security; performance may be enhanced due to less disk head travel. This method has the disadvantage of subdividing the drive into fixed-size partitions, so  a user could run out of hard drive space in his or her /home partition, even though other partitions still have plenty of usable space. A good implementation requires the user to predict how much space each partition will need, which may be a difficult task; especially for new users. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/438425.xml">
Logical Volume Management</link>, often used in servers, increases flexibility by allowing data in volumes to expand into separate physical disks (which can be added when needed); another option is to resize existing partitions when necessary. Typical desktop systems are often comprised of a single "/" (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/158871.xml">
root directory</link>) containing the entire filesystem plus a much smaller <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/311193.xml">
swap partition</link>. By default, Mac OS X systems use a single "/" (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/158871.xml">
root directory</link>) containing the entire filesystem (including the swap file) as a point of simplicity (but other setup options do exist).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Partition recovery </st>
<p>

When a partition is deleted, in general, only its partition table entry is removed from a table; and although the data is no longer accessible, it still remains on the disk until being overwritten. Specialized recovery utilities, (such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/4888642.xml">
TestDisk</link></software>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/11503444.xml">
gpart</link>), can locate <it>lost</it> file systems and recreate a partition table which includes entries for these recovered file systems. However, some disk utilities may also overwrite a number of beginning sectors of a partition they delete. For example, if Windows Disk Management (Windows 2000/XP, etc.) is used to delete a partition, it will overwrite the first sector (relative sector 0) of the partition before removing it. It may be possible to restore a <link>
FAT32</link> or <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/39184.xml">
NTFS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 partition if a backup boot sector is available.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/3788449.xml">
Apple Partition Map</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../118/4637118.xml">
Boot Camp</link></software>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml">
Booting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/5377176.xml">
BSD disklabel</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/6200040.xml">
Slice (disk)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/305743.xml">
Disk formatting</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/3968527.xml">
Extended boot record</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/1010280.xml">
File system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/787836.xml">
fstab</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/2543892.xml">
GUID Partition Table</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/346185.xml">
ISO image</link></format>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/6377470.xml">
List of disk partitioning software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/438425.xml">
Logical volume management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/55389.xml">
Master boot record</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/16545643.xml">
RawWrite for Windows</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<copycat wordnetid="109964411" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/599647.xml">
ROM image</link></causal_agent>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</copycat>
</person>
</system>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/2346717.xml">
Volume (computing)</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Stéphane Martineau, Jens Olsson, Nick Roberts&#32;(<link>
2002-11-02</link>).&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.adaos.net./aodps/aodps.html">
The Alt-OS-Development Partition Specification (AODPS)</weblink></it>". &#32;0.4.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Andries Brouwer&#32;(1995&ndash;2004).&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.win.tue.nl/~aeb/partitions/partition_types-1.html">
List of partition identifiers for PCs</weblink></it>".</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Andries Brouwer&#32;(<link>
1999-09-16</link>).&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.win.tue.nl/~aeb/partitions/partition_tables.html">
Minimal Partition Table Specification</weblink></it>".</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 &#32;(<link>
1998-08-05</link>).&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ranish.com/part/primer.htm">
partitioning primer</weblink></it>". &#32;Ranish.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Allen Smith.&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.allensmith.net/Storage/HDDlimit/Address.htm">
ATA (EIDE) Drive Capacity and Addressing</weblink></it>".</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Microsoft&#32;(<link>
2005-06-03</link>).&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/storage/GPT-on-x64.mspx">
Using GPT Drives</weblink></it>".</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.partition-tool.com/easeus-partition-manager/help/partitioning-basics.htm">
Partitioning Basics</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://home.pacbell.net/dbk4297/fdiskformat.html">
FDISK and FORMAT instructions for any hard drive</weblink> Simple partition instructions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Partition/index.html">
Linux Partition HOWTO</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.linfo.org/partition.html">
Partition Definition</weblink> - by The Linux Information Project (LINFO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://partitionlogic.org.uk/">
Partition Logic</weblink> is an OS-independent free/open source partition tool.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gparted-livecd.tuxfamily.org">
GParted</weblink> Open source GParted powered Live CD</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lissot.net/partition/partition-03.html">
Partition Types</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.win.tue.nl/~aeb/partitions/partition_types.html">
Properties of partition tables</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://technodata.blogspot.com/2007/01/how-can-you-make-partitions-with-fdisk.html">
The Technology Info</weblink> Disk Partitioning with fdisk</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.viralpatel.net/taj/tutorial/partition_table.php">
List of partition tables file system codes.</weblink> </entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</article>
