<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:54:47[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<agent  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="109190918">
<header>
<title>Polyphenol antioxidant</title>
<id>5538293</id>
<revision>
<id>244644451</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T21:12:11Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Winetype</username>
<id>4516997</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles to be merged since December 2007</category>
<category>Flavonoids</category>
<category>Cardiovascular system</category>
<category>Chemopreventive agents</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Phenols</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Merge-arrow.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrow
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  into . ()</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Apigenin.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Molecular structure of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/4220091.xml">
apigenin</link>, a <b>polyphenol antioxidant</b>
</caption>
</image>

A <b>polyphenol antioxidant</b> is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
antioxidant</link> containing a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/362892.xml">
polyphenol</link>ic substructure.  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/80381.xml">
human health</link> these compounds, numbering over 4000 distinct species, are thought to be instrumental in combating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/2150549.xml">
oxidative stress</link>, a syndrome causative of some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/908423.xml">
neurodegenerative disease</link>s and some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/512662.xml">
cardiovascular disease</link>s.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Sources of polyphenol antioxidants</st>
<p>

The main source of polyphenol antioxidants is nutritional, since they are found in a wide array of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/472231.xml">
phytonutrient</link>-bearing foods.  For example, most <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/305286.xml">
legume</link>s; fruits such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18978754.xml">
apple</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/72339.xml">
blackberries</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/17598541.xml">
blueberries</link>,  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/79713.xml">
cantaloupe</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/54773.xml">
cherries</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/7025.xml">
cranberries</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/12436.xml">
grape</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/24278.xml">
pear</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/56884.xml">
plum</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/276409.xml">
raspberries</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/2455842.xml">
strawberries</link>; and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/5791492.xml">
vegetable</link>s such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/66556.xml">
broccoli</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/55115.xml">
cabbage</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/6535.xml">
celery</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/51258.xml">
onion</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/23206.xml">
parsley</link> are rich in polyphenol antioxidants. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/32961.xml">
Red wine</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/7089.xml">
chocolate</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/262676.xml">
green tea</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/1291577.xml">
bee pollen</link> and many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/6700.xml">
grain</link>s are alternative sources.  The principal benefit of ingestion of antioxidants seems to stem from the consumption of a wide array of phytonutrients; correspondingly, the role of dietary supplements as a method of realizing these health benefits is the subject of considerable discussion.
<image width="200px" src="Blackberry_fruits10.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Biochemical regulation</st>
<p>

The regulation chemistry consists of a polyphenol antioxidant’s ability to scavenge <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/235028.xml">
free radical</link>s  and up-regulate certain metal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/175641.xml">
chelation</link> reactions.  That is to say various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/640697.xml">
reactive oxygen species</link> must be continually removed from cells to maintain healthy metabolic function.  Some specific free radicals affected are the reactive oxygen species <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/1898647.xml">
singlet oxygen</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/3171425.xml">
peroxynitrite</link> and  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/14403.xml">
hydrogen peroxide</link>.  Diminishing the concentrations of reactive oxygen species can have several benefits.  Since reactive oxygen species are linked to mobilization of ion transport systems, they are known to have roles in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/4629362.xml">
redox signaling</link>. In particular, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/196121.xml">
platelets</link> involved in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/338154.xml">
wound</link> repair and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/3997.xml">
blood</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/13980.xml">
homeostasis</link> can release reactive oxygen species to recruit platelets to sites of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/515534.xml">
injury</link>. These also provide a link to the adaptive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/14958.xml">
immune system</link> via the recruitment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../480/144480.xml">
leukocytes</link>.  When polyphenols down-regulate reactive oxygen species formation, they also contribute to improved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/532570.xml">
endothelial</link> health through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/726241.xml">
anti-inflammatory</link> action.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Biological consequences</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Macrophage.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/169270.xml">
macrophage</link> stretching its arms to engulf two particles. Reactive oxygen species promote oxidized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/51521.xml">
LDL</link> and polyphenol antioxidants combat this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/70425.xml">
inflammatory response</link>.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Occurrence of an abundance of polyphenol antioxidants is associated with several salutary effects in higher animal species:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Reduction in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/70425.xml">
inflammatory</link> effects such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/5876.xml">
coronary artery disease</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> including specific medical research into the pathways of improved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/532570.xml">
endothelial</link> health via downregulation of oxidative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/51521.xml">
LDL</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

More generally the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/29969.xml">
tea</link> polyphenol (medically known as TP) antioxidant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/11179644.xml">
epigallocatechin gallate</link>, has been shown to reduce reactive oxygen species levels <it>in vivo</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>  Reactive oxygen species are important <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/4584230.xml">
markers</link> for inflammatory diseases. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Some polyphenol antioxidants, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/342649.xml">
resveratrol</link>, inhibit occurrence and/or growth of mammalian <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/31214.xml">
tumor</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A variety of other beneficial health effects have been attributed to consumption of foods rich in polyphenolic antioxidants.  Among these salutary effects discussed are anti-aging consequences such as slowing the process of skin wrinkling.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>  For some of the side-benefits (such as prevention of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/489173.xml">
peripheral artery disease</link>), further research is continuing to clarify the role polyphenol antioxidants may have.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Difficulty in analyzing effects of specific chemicals</st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="190px" src="Close_up_grapes.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>

It is difficult to evaluate the medical effects of specific polyphenolic antioxidants, since such a large number of individual compounds may occur even in a single food.  For example, over sixty different chemically distinct flavonoids are known to occur in a given <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/32961.xml">
red wine</link>.  Numerous scientific studies have been conducted to attempt to arrive at one consistent index for food antioxidant power.  Since it has been proved that the dietary intake of compounds having antioxidant activity is medically  important, various chemical, biological, and electrochemical methods have been proposed to evaluate the antioxidant power of compounds such as polyphenols. Wine, although <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/529854.xml">
nonessential</link>, has a high polyphenol content up to two to three grams per liter in red wines obtained by traditional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/1455948.xml">
maceration</link>. The polyphenol content of wines is usually evaluated by the <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/9745483.xml">
Folin-Ciocalteu reagent</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
, which provides an appropriate response to the requirements of wine manufacturers. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
Statistical</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/82359.xml">
least squares</link> analysis has been conducted to demonstrate the Folin method correlates well with alternative chemical and biological procedures for determining antioxidant potential.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>  Therefore, there is some reason to believe more universally accepted protocols may be forthcoming to permit quantitative evaluation of antioxidant strength of polyphenol antioxidant compounds.</p>
<p>

Other more detailed chemical research has been conducted elucidating the difficulty of isolating individual polyphenolic antioxidants.  Fajardo-Lirai et al. have demonstrated that significant variation in polyphenol content among various brands of tea can explain<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> the inconsistency in previous epidemiological studies that have tried to correlate beneficial health effects of polyphenol antioxidants using specific <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/262676.xml">
green tea</link> blends.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/2832162.xml">
Oxygen Radical Absorbance Capacity</link> (ORAC) test is a possible emerging standard by which science measures antioxidant power in foods and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/104444.xml">
dietary supplement</link>s</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Practical aspects of dietary polyphenol antioxidants</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Cacao-pod-k4636-14.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>

There is  debate regarding the total body absorption of dietary intake of polyphenolic compounds.  While individual studies seem to demonstrate the favourable health effects of certain specific polyphenols, more research is needed to understand the interactions between a variety of these chemicals acting in concert within the human body.  In particular there is evidence that some combinations of foods may inhibit efficient intestinal transfer of certain polyphenol antioxidants; refined sugars, for example, have been shown to impede this uptake under certain circumstances.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>  Furthermore caution should be exercised in attempting diets depending largely on dietary supplements as opposed to a broad array of food sources, since the quality and concentrations of beneficial chemicals in some commercial products is subject to question, given lack of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/11632.xml">
Food and Drug Administration</link> (FDA) regulation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Topical application of polyphenol antioxidants</st>
<p>

There is some data that reactive oxygen species play a role in the process of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/16413778.xml">
aging</link>. The skin is exposed to various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/790775.xml">
exogenous</link> sources of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/2150549.xml">
oxidative stress</link>, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/31990.xml">
ultraviolet</link> radiation. These spectral components are generally viewed as responsible for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/2387330.xml">
extrinsic</link> type of skin aging, sometimes termed photo-aging. It has been shown not only that increased levels of protective low molecular weight antioxidants through a diet rich in phytochemicals, but also by direct topical dermal application<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>  have proved that a few low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/60034.xml">
molecular weight</link> antioxidants, notably <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/32509.xml">
vitamins C</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/54104.xml">
E</link>, as well as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/81648.xml">
lipoic acid</link>, exert protective effects against oxidative stress.  However, controlled long-term studies on the efficacy of low molecular weight antioxidants in the prevention or treatment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/27978.xml">
skin</link> aging in humans are lacking.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Félicien Breton&#32;(2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.frenchscout.com/polyphenols">
Polyphenol antioxidants in red wine</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="2">
M.F. Muldoon and S.B. Kritchevsky, <it>Flavonoids and heart disease</it>. Brit Med J 312:458-459	(1996)</entry>
<entry id="3">
John P. Cooke, The Cardiovascular Cure, Random House Inc., New York (2002) ISBN 0-7679-0881-3</entry>
<entry id="4">
Serafini M, Laranjinha JA, Almeida LM, Maiani G, <it>Inhibition of human LDL lipid peroxidation by phenol-rich beverages and their impact on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/212240.xml">
plasma</link> total <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3277.xml">
antioxidant</link> capacity in humans</it>, J Nutr Biochem 2000 Nov;11(11-12):585-590</entry>
<entry id="5">
Yuying Mei,  Dongzhi We and  Jianwen Liu, <it>Reversal of Multidrug Resistance in <link>
KB Cells</link> with Tea Polyphenol Antioxidant Capacity</it>,  Journal of Cancer Biology and Therapy, Vol: 4 | Issue: 4 | April 2005 | pgs: 468-473</entry>
<entry id="6">
M. Jang, L. Cai, G.O. Dean, K.V. Slowing, C.F. Thomas, C.W.W. Beecher , H.H.S. Fong, N.R, Farnsworth, A.D. Kinghorn, R.G. Mehta, R.C. Moon and J.M.  Pezzuto, <it>Cancer chemopreventive activity of reseveratrol, a natural product derived from grapes</it> Science 275:218-220 (1997)</entry>
<entry id="7">
Vieira O, Escargueil-Blanc I, Meilhac O, Basile JP, Laranjinha J, Almeida L, Salvayre R, Negre-Salvayre, <it>A Effect of dietary phenolic compounds on apoptosis of human cultured endothelial cells induced by oxidized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/51521.xml">
LDL</link></it>; Br J Pharmacol 1998 Feb; 123(3): 565-73</entry>
<entry id="8">
Owen RW, Giacosa A, Hull WE, Haubner R, Spiegelhalder B, Barstch H, <it>The antioxidant/anticancer potential of phenolic compounds isolated from olive oil</it>, Eur J Cancer 2000 Jun;36(10):1235-47</entry>
<entry id="9">
 Fito M, Covas MI, Lamuela-Raventos RM, Vila J, Torrents L, de la Torre C, Marrugat, <it>Protective effect of olive oil and its phenolic compounds against low density lipoprotein oxidation</it>, J; Lipids 2000 Jun; 35(6): 633-8</entry>
<entry id="10">
Oreste V. Brenna and Ella Pagliarini, Department of Food Science and Microbiology, University of Milan, Italy <it>Multivariate Analysis of Antioxidant Power and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/362892.xml">
Polyphenol</link>ic Composition in Red Wines</it>, American Chemical Society, July 5, 2001</entry>
<entry id="11">
 C. Fajardo-Lirai, S. M. Henning, H. W. Lee, V. L. W. Go, and D. Heber,. Department Family Environmental Sciences/Nutrition, Dietetics &amp; Food Science, California State University,, Northridge and, UCLA Center for Human Nutrition, Session 46C, 2002 Annual meeting of Food Expo, Anaheim, Ca</entry>
<entry id="12">
Lotito SB, Frei B.,  Linus Pauling Institute, Oregon State University, Corvallis, Or, <it>Relevance of apple polyphenols as antioxidants in human plasma: contrasting </it>in vitro<it> and </it>in vivo<it> effects</it>  Free Radic Biol Med. 2004 Jan 15;36(2):201-11</entry>
<entry id="13">
Clin Exp Dermatol. 2001 Oct;26(7):578-82 There is increasing evidence that reactive oxygen species play a pivotal role in the process of aging. The skin, as the outermost barrier of the body, is exposed to various exogenous sources of oxidative stress, in particular UV-irradiation. These are believed to be responsible for the extrinsic type of skin aging, termed photo-aging. It therefore seems possible to increase levels of protective low molecular 
may produce anti-aging effects on human skin. Indeed, various <it>in vitro</it> and animal studies</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4533264.xml">
Asymmetric dimethylarginine</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/5876.xml">
Coronary artery disease</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/51521.xml">
Low density lipoprotein</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/235287.xml">
Nitric oxide</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</agent>
</article>
