<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:17:20[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<utensil  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="104516672">
<header>
<title>Cutting board</title>
<id>554516</id>
<revision>
<id>232153778</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-15T18:29:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Food utensils</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="Chopping_Board.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A wooden chopping board with a chef's knife.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

A <b>cutting board</b> is a durable board used to place material on to be cut.  Most common is the kitchen cutting board for use preparing food, but other types exist for cutting raw materials such as leather or plastic.  Kitchen cutting boards are often made of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/33550.xml">
wood</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/23883.xml">
plastic</link>. There are also chopping boards made of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/12581.xml">
glass</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/27058.xml">
steel</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/19054.xml">
marble</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/3290373.xml">
corian</link>, which are easier to clean than wooden or plastic ones, but tend to damage knives. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Sanitation and care</st>
<p>

Regardless of the material, regular maintenance of a cutting board is important.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sanitation with cutting boards is a delicate process, because bacteria can reside in grooves produced by cutting, or in liquids left on the board. For this reason, it is often advised to cut raw <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/18940.xml">
meat</link> on separate cutting boards from cooked meat, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/5791492.xml">
vegetable</link>s or other foods. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A very dilute <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/12873937.xml">
bleach</link> solution is best for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/478185.xml">
disinfecting</link> cutting boards.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

To remove odors, rinse the board and then rub with coarse salt and let stand for several minutes. Wipe board and then rinse clean. This procedure will also smooth out minor imperfections in the wood.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wood boards should never be placed in the dishwasher, or left immersed for long periods, as the wood or glue may be affected.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A light food grade <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/212419.xml">
mineral oil</link> is a good preservative for wooden cutting boards as it helps keep water from seeping into the grain. Alternatively, one may also use a food grade <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/752713.xml">
drying oil</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/1208398.xml">
poppyseed oil</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../335/1050335.xml">
tung oil</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/295711.xml">
linseed oil</link>. The first two dry much faster than linseed. Note that most commercially available linseed and tung oil are not “food grade” as they contain metallic driers. In general, edible savory vegetable or olive oils are not recommended because they tend to go rancid, causing the board to smell and your food to pick up the rancid taste.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cutting boards should be treated when they start looking dry to prevent cracking. A standard recommendation is 5-7 times a year, or as needed.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

When heavily or deeply scored, wood or plastic cutting boards should be resurfaced as scoring can harbor bacteria, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/382649.xml">
mildew</link> in the case of plastic boards. Wood can be easily resurfaced with various woodworking tools, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/812240.xml">
scrapers</link> or <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<tool wordnetid="104451818" confidence="0.8">
<implement wordnetid="103563967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/452991.xml">
planes</link></implement>
</tool>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/400975.xml">
Sandpaper</link> is to be avoided however, as it leaves residual abrasives in the surface, which will dull knives. Resurfacing a plastic cutting board is more difficult and replacing it is recommended instead.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Materials</st>
<p>

In choosing a cutting surface, there are pros and cons to each depending on application.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Wood</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="LemonChicken2.jpg" type="thumb">
</image>

Wood has some advantages over plastic in that it is somewhat self healing; shallow cuts in the wood will close up on their own. Wood also has natural anti-septic properties.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Hardwoods with tightly grained wood and small pores are best for wooden cutting boards. Good hardness and tight grain helps reduce scoring of the cutting surface and absorption of liquid and dirt into the surface. Red <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/39696.xml">
oak</link> for example, even though a hardwood, has large pores so it retains dirt, even after washing, making it a poor choice for cutting board material. </p>
<p>

Care must be taken when selecting wood, especially tropical hardwood, for use as a cutting board as some species contain toxins or allergens. </p>
<p>

Although technically a grass, laminated strips of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/39029.xml">
bamboo</link> also make an attractive and durable cutting board material.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Plastic</st>
<p>

While plastic is theoretically a more sanitary material than wood for cutting boards, testing has shown this may not be the case. The softer surface of plastic boards is scored by knives, and the resulting grooves and cuts in the surface harbour bacteria even after being well washed.  However, unlike wood, plastic boards do allow rinsing with harsher cleaning chemicals such as bleach and other disinfectants without damage to the board or retention of the chemicals to later contaminate food.</p>
<p>

Semi-disposable thin flexible cutting boards also ease transferring their contents to a cooking or storage vessel. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Glass</st>
<p>

The advantages of glass cutting boards are ease of cleaning (including being dishwasher safe), and durability.  While easier to clean than wood or plastic, glass cutting boards damage knives, precisely because of their durability. Since glass is harder than the steel of even the highest quality knives, cutting on glass tends to dent, roll or even chip edges.  Additionally, if used incorrectly, glass can break or chip itself, introducing glass to the food.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Steel</st>
<p>

Steel shares the advantages of the durability and ease of cleaning with glass, as well as the tendency to damage knives. Depending on the exact steel and heat treatment used, at best a steel cutting board will wear the edge on knives quickly, at worst chip dent or roll it like glass.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Marble</st>
<p>

Most marble “cutting boards” are not actually intended for cutting, but for rolling dough or use as serving boards, such as for cheese.  Aside from sharing the edge damaging properties of glass and steel, marble is in fact also abrasive, and when exposed to some food acids such as tomato juice or vinegar, will slowly dissolve.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Corian</st>
<p>

<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/3290373.xml">
Corian</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
 or other counter materials know as “solid surface” are composed of a polymer binder and a filler, acrylic polymer and alumina trihydrate in the case of <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/201829.xml">
DuPont</link></company>
 Corian.  They are again hard enough to damage edges, and the powdered alumina is abrasive, so slicing strokes will wear the edge quickly.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/3842275.xml">
butcher block</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ak N, Cliver D, Kaspari C&#32;(1994).&#32;"Cutting Boards of Plastic and Wood Contaminated Experimentally with Bacteria". <it>Journal of Food Protection</it>&#32;<b>57</b>&#32;(1): 16–22.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://culinaryarts.about.com/od/culinarytools/p/cuttingboards.htm">
Cutting Board Basics page from About.com</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cookingforengineers.com/article.php?id=17&amp;title=Cutting+Boards">
Cooking For Engineers' Cutting Boards Article</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.helpful-kitchen-tips.com/kitchen-cutting-boards.html">
Cutting Boards</weblink> - Useful tips for choosing kitchen cutting boards.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</utensil>
</article>
