<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:49:08[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<engine  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103287733">
<motor  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103789946">
<device  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103183080">
<machine  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103699975">
<header>
<title>Vertical search</title>
<id>5560995</id>
<revision>
<id>242810799</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T19:31:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Kaze0010</username>
<id>1045039</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Internet search engines</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Searching</category>
<category>Internet search</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Vertical search</b>, part of a larger subgrouping known as "specialized" search, is a relatively new tier in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
Internet search</link> industry consisting of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link>s that focus on specific slices of content. The type of content in special focus may be based on topicality or information type. For example, a medical search engine would clearly be specialized in terms of its topical focus, whereas a video search engine would seek out results within content that is in a video format. So vertical search may focus on all manner of differentiating criteria, such as particular locations, multimedia object types and so on.</p>


<sec>
<st>
Origins of vertical search</st>
<p>

Niche search engines are not new. Web sites that help users find people, shop and get business information have existed for years. But the number of these search engines being introduced has greatly increased in recent years. Local search is already a burgeoning subset, with Google Local and many newspapers offering this functionality. </p>
<p>

Like consumers, businesses use the Internet for a variety of needs. Sometimes they’re looking for all the information they can get, and for that the likes of Google and the Yahoo search engines are used. But more often they’re looking for something very specific related to their businesses. That’s where vertical search sites come in. Vertical search engines deliver to businesses what the big sites can’t without the use of complex keyword combinations: relevant and essential content versus an exhaustive return of information.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Vertical search vs. broad-based search</st>
<p>

Broad-based search engines such as Google or Yahoo fetch very large numbers of documents using a <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/33120.xml">
Web crawler</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
. Another program called an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/7602386.xml">
indexer</link> then reads these documents and creates a search index based on words contained in each document. Each search engine uses a proprietary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> to create its indexes so that, ideally, only meaningful results are returned for each query.</p>
<p>

Vertical search engines, on the other hand, send their spiders out to a highly refined database, and their indexes contain information about a specific topic. As a result, they are of most value to people interested in a particular area; what’s more, the companies that advertise on these search engines reach a very focused audience. For example, there are search engines for veterinarians, doctors, patients, job seekers, house hunters, recruiters, travelers and corporate purchasers, to name a few.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The vertical search user</st>
<p>

As the broad-based search engines have gotten broader, so have their search results. This has become increasingly frustrating to users who have turned to search engines to find information on a specialized topic, be it local information, travel sites or specific business channels. </p>
<p>

This is especially true of the latter. In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/4301279.xml">
business marketing</link> profession, terms that have very specific meanings in certain industries will yield a host of irrelevant results when used as keywords on the big search engines. For example, say a dentist is looking for information on ceramics, a common material used in dental work. If the dentist performs a Google search on the keyword "ceramics", Google will serve up millions of results, but most of the entries on the first few pages will concern hobbies like pottery. On the other hand, if the dentist performs the same search on DentalProducts.net, a well-regarded media company Web site, it will return much more relevant results. </p>
<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/216901.xml">
LookSmart</link></company>
, an online media and technology company that has launched more than 180 vertical search sites, contends that Web users will increasingly use the Internet the way they do cable television, opting for specialized channels that speak directly to their concerns. This company says vertical search engines will chip away at Google’s and Yahoo’s audiences the same way cable TV channels such as <group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/169414.xml">
TLC</link></group>
 and the <channel wordnetid="106259898" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/925639.xml">
National Geographic Channel</link></channel>
 have eaten into network audiences.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The buyer in vertical search marketing</st>
<p>

On the simplest level, the vertical search buyer is a marketer that wants to be found by the user of one of these specialized search engines. When a business person searches the Web through a search engine or a directory, that person is considered to be in "hunt mode". Marketers understand that this hunt mode means the searcher may very well be somewhere in the buying cycle. That makes search engine results some of the best sources of targeted traffic, whether that traffic originates from "organic" unpaid search listings or paid advertising listings.  </p>
<p>

To take advantage of this phenomenon some sites have combined vertical search with comparison shopping (e.g. thefind.com, ninjatickets.com).  This enhances the quality of traffic originating from these sites, as well as the "power" of the search engine itself. </p>
<p>

Vertical search engines unite the motivations of the ad space buyer (to be exposed to a targeted audience) with those of the user (to be able to search across an entire vertical market). In achieving these goals, it allows users to collaborate in reviewing search results, and buyers to collaborate in attaining better ranking in universal search engine like Google, and thus lowering their cost of online ad spend. </p>
<p>

"Vertical search providers will play an important role in the paid search market in the next five years," said Zia Wigder, vice president and research director at JupiterResearch, a division of JupiterMedia. "Search marketers must establish a robust management strategy and an efficient testing and inclusion process to profit from this growth."</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Growth in vertical search</st>
<p>

Advertisers on vertical sites are able to reach potential customers who are much closer to making a purchase decision than the average user on Google or Yahoo, according to Greg Sterling, an analyst with The Kelsey Group. He told Forbes.com that that’s the whole motivation for advertising on vertical sites. For example, he said someone doing a search on <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/3995811.xml">
Edmunds.com</link></institution>
</web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</company>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
, an automobile search engine, is probably more serious about buying a car than someone doing a car search on a general search engine. The cost of advertising on the large search engines is also likely to drive more marketers to vertical search.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Vertical search design and advertising models</st>
<p>

In terms of design and implementation, several models are emerging in vertical search:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>The vertical search engine as a destination or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/54293.xml">
portal</link></b>. Often media companies that own these destination sites optimize them and buy keywords on Google to drive their audience to visit.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Vertical search as a complementary Web site application</b>: This model entails embedding a search engine box on an existing, already trafficked site. One example is CertMag.com. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Parametric search</b>: This tool, more prevalent in engineering and other product-specific, information-intensive, procurement-driven industries, often allows for side-by-side product and manufacturer comparison. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In terms of revenue that these vertical search engines generate, a variety of advertising programs are gaining favor, including: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/1545004.xml">
Cost per click</link>, in which the advertiser pays only for each time that a user clicks on the ad. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/1874573.xml">
Cost per thousand</link>/cost per impression/cost per view, the standardized, traditional method of online advertising, is now emerging as an option in vertical search environments. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Cost per action,</b> an emerging model in which the advertiser pays, not on click, or for impressions, but only if the consumer performs a specific action, such as purchases a good.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Flat fee/fixed fee</b>, the most popular early ad model for most of the vertical search engines. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Web order entry/self-service</b>, a system whereby marketers can buy, monitor and revise their ad campaigns themselves simply by entering their credit card information through a password-protected interface. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Paid inclusion</b>, the practice of inserting “editorial-like” ads or more traditional ads into the actual organic search results. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Paid listing</b>, in which ads appear on top of or beside organic listings and are clearly identified as sponsored links.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Free, plus</b>, in which the site is completely free for both those listing and those searching, with additional features available for those who pay.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/429700.xml">
List of search engines</link></p>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<follower wordnetid="110099375" confidence="0.8">
<flatterer wordnetid="110095869" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<sycophant wordnetid="110684827" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/11442799.xml">
Focused crawler</link></procedure>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</causal_agent>
</rule>
</event>
</sycophant>
</algorithm>
</flatterer>
</follower>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>


</p>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jupitermedia.com/corporate/releases/06.02.27-newjupresearch.html/">
“Engine Selection Strategies: Campaign Expansion Demands Management Tools,”</weblink> JupiterResearch, 2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2005/04/04/BUGJ9C20VU1.DTL">
“New Search Engines Narrowing Their Focus,”</weblink> Verne Kopytoff, <it><newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/319442.xml">
San Francisco Chronicle</link></newspaper>
</it>, April 4, 2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emarketer.com/Report.aspx?search_feb05">
“Search Engine Marketing: Search Users and Usage,”</weblink> <it><link>
eMarketer</link></it>, March 2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sempo.org/learning_center/research/sempo_research/state_of_sem_2005/">
“The State of Search Engine Marketing 2005,”</weblink> SEMPO, 2006</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.forbes.com/home/entrepreneurstechnology/2006/01/18/yahoo-google-microsoft-cx_tt_0118straightup.html/">
“Straight Up: One-Stop Search,”</weblink> Tom Taulli, <it><link>
Forbes.com</link></it>, January 18, 2006</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tmlr.net/jump/?c=22884&amp;a=296&amp;m=4108&amp;p=0&amp;t=164">
“Vertical Search for Health Gets Sexy,”</weblink> <it><link>
Health IT World News</link></it>, October 5, 2006</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ecommercetimes.com/story/41982.html">
“Vertical Search Market Quickly Becoming Crowded,”</weblink> Keith Regan, <it><link>
E-Commerce Times</link></it>, April 4, 2005</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/search_20_what_is_next.php">
"Search 2.0 — What's Next?"</weblink>, Read/WriteWeb, December 13, 2006</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>



</sec>
</bdy>
</machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</article>
