<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:17:16[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104377057">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<instrumentality  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103575240">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Dendral</title>
<id>557912</id>
<revision>
<id>220473496</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-20T01:06:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Sir Lothar</username>
<id>1160434</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cheminformatics</category>
<category>Expert systems</category>
<category>History of artificial intelligence</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Dendral</b> was an influential pioneer project in artificial intelligence (AI) of the 1960s, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
computer software</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/10136.xml">
expert system</link> that it produced. Its primary aim was to help <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/22208.xml">
organic chemists</link> in identifying unknown organic molecules, by analyzing their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/283810.xml">
mass spectra</link> and using knowledge of chemistry.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  It was done at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/26977.xml">
Stanford University</link></university>
 by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/307517.xml">
Edward Feigenbaum</link></scientist>
</person>
, <link>
Bruce Buchanan</link>, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/494457.xml">
Joshua Lederberg</link></scientist>
, and <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/574479.xml">
Carl Djerassi</link></scientist>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  It began in 1965 and spans approximately half the history of AI research.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  <p>

The software program Dendral is considered the first expert system because it automated the decision-making process and problem-solving behavior of organic chemists.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  It consists of two sub-programs, <b>Heuristic Dendral</b> and <b>Meta-Dendral</b>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>. It was written in <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/18016.xml">
Lisp (programming language)</link></programming_language>
, which was considered the language of AI.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  </p>
<p>

Many systems were derived from Dendral, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/649929.xml">
MYCIN</link>, MOLGEN, <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/303734.xml">
MACSYMA</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
, PROSPECTOR, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/3234557.xml">
XCON</link>, and STEAMER.</p>
<p>

The name <it>Dendral</it> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/16823212.xml">
portmanteau</link> of the term "Dendritic Algorithm".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Heuristic Dendral</st>
<p>

Heuristic Dendral is a program that uses mass spectra or other experimental data together with knowledge base of chemistry, to produce a set of possible chemical structures that may be responsible for producing the data.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>  A mass spectrum of a compound is produced by a mass spectrometer, and is used to determine its molecular weight, the sum of the masses of its atomic constituents. For example, the compound water (H2O), has a molecular weight of 18 since hydrogen has a mass of 1.01 and oxygen 16.00, and its mass spectrum has a peak at 18 units. Heuristic Dendral would use this input mass and the knowledge of atomic mass numbers and valence rules, to determine the possible combinations of atomic constituents whose mass would add up to 18.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>  As the weight increases and the molecules become more complex, the number of possible compounds increases drastically. Thus, a program that is able to reduce this number of candidate solutions through the process of hypothesis formation is essential.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Meta-Dendral</st>
<p>

Meta-Dendral is a knowledge acquisition system that receives the set of possible chemical structures and corresponding mass spectra as input, and proposes a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/14281.xml">
hypotheses</link> to explain correlation between some of the proposed structures and the mass spectrum.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> These hypotheses would be fed back to Heuristic Dendral to test their applicability.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>  Thus, "Heuristic Dendral is a performance system and Meta-Dendral is a learning system".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>  The program is based on two important features: the plan-generate-test paradigm and knowledge engineering.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Plan-generate-test paradigm</st>
<p>

The plan-generate-test paradigm is the basic organization of the problem-solving method, and is a common paradigm used by both <b>Heuristic Dendral</b> and <b>Meta-Dendral</b> systems.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> The <b>generator</b> generates potential solutions for a particular problem, which are then expressed as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/14240178.xml">
chemical graph</link>s in Dendral.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> However, this is feasible only when the number of candidate solutions is minimal. When there are large numbers of possible solutions, Dendral has to find a way to put constraints that rules out large sets of candidate solutions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> This is the primary aim of Dendral <b>planner</b>, which is a “hypothesis-formation” program that employs “task-specific knowledge to find constraints for the generator”.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> Last but not least, the <b>tester</b> analyzes each proposed candidate solution and discards those that fail to fulfill certain criteria.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> This mechanism of plan-generate-test paradigm is what holds Dendral together.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Knowledge Engineering</st>
<p>

The primary aim of knowledge engineering is to attain a productive interaction between the available knowledge base and problem solving techniques.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> This is possible through development of a procedure in which large amounts of task-specific information is encoded into heuristic programs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> Thus, the first essential component of knowledge engineering is a large <b>“knowledge base.”</b> The knowledge base would include specific knowledge about the mass spectrometry technique, large amount of information that forms the basis of chemistry and graph theory, and any information that might be helpful in finding the solution of a particular chemical structure elucidation problem.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> Through knowledge engineering Dendral is able to use this “knowledge base” to both determine the set of possible chemical structures that correspond to the input data, and form new “general rules” that helps it reduce the number of candidate solutions. Thus, at the end the user is now provided with a minimal number of possible solutions, which can now be tested by any non-expert user to find the right solution.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Heuristics </st>

<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/63452.xml">
heuristic</link> is a rule of thumb, an algorithm that does not guarantee a solution, but reduces the number of possible solutions by discarding unlikely and irrelevant solutions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref>  The use of heuristics to solve problems is called "heuristics programming", and was used in Dendral to allow it to replicate in machines the process through which human experts induce the solution to problems via rules of thumb and specific information.</p>
<p>

Heuristics programming was a major approach and a giant step forward in artificial intelligence,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> as it allowed scientists to finally automate certain traits of human intelligence. It became prominent among scientists in the late 1940s through <link>
George Polya</link>’s book, <it>How to Solve It: A New Aspect of Mathematical Method</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref>  As <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../205/14205.xml">
Herbert Simon</link></scientist>
</person>
 said in <it>The Sciences of the Artificial</it>, "if you take a heuristic conclusion as certain, you may be fooled and disappointed; but if you neglect heuristic conclusions altogether you will make no progress at all."</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

During mid 20th century, the question "can machines think?" became intriguing and popular among scientists, primarily to add humanistic characteristics to machine behavior. <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/308362.xml">
John McCarthy</link></scientist>
</person>
, who was one of the prime researchers of this field, termed this concept of machine intelligence as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link>" (AI) during the Dartmouth summer in 1956. AI is usually defined as the capacity of a machine to perform operations that are analogous to human cognitive capabilities.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref> Much research to create AI was done during the 20th century.</p>
<p>

Also around mid 20th century, science, especially biology, faced a fast-increasing need to develop a "man-computer symbiosis", to aid scientists in solving problems.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> For example, the structural analysis of <link>
myogoblin</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/13483.xml">
hemoglobin</link>, and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link>s relentlessly needed instrumentation development due to its complexity.</p>
<p>

In the early 1960s, Joshua Lederberg started working with computers and quickly became tremendously interested in creating interactive computers to help him in his <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/2787.xml">
exobiology</link> research.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> Specifically, he was interested in designing computing systems that to help him study alien organic compounds.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> As he was not an expert in either chemistry or computer programming, he collaborated with Stanford chemist Carl Djerassi to help him with chemistry, and Edward Feigenbaum with programming, to automate the process of determining chemical structures from raw mass spectrometry data.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref> Feigenbaum was an expert in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/23015.xml">
programming language</link>s and heuristics, and helped Lederberg design a system that replicated the way Carl Djerassi solved structure elucidation problems.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref> They devised a system called <b>Dendritic Algorithm</b> (Dendral) that was able to generate possible chemical structures corresponding to the mass spectrometry data as an output.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref></p>
<p>

Dendral then was still very inaccurate in assessing spectra of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/16803.xml">
ketone</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/1014.xml">
alcohols</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/19600339.xml">
isomer</link>s of chemical compounds.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref> Thus, as seen in figure 1, Djerassi "taught" general rules to Dendral that could help eliminate most of the "chemically implausible" structures, and produce a set of structures that could now be analyzed by a "non-expert" user to determine the right structure.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref> Figure 2 shows how Dendral operates without an expert, after all the general rules were entered into Dendral's knowledge base.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref></p>
<p>

The Dendral team recruited Bruce Buchanan to refine Feigenbaum’s Lisp program.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref>  Buchanan had similar ideas and interests as Feigenbaum and Lederberg, but his special interest was hypothesis formation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2237%22])">37</ref>  As Joseph November said in <it>Digitizing Life: The Introduction of Computers to Biology and Medicine</it>, "(Buchanan) wanted the system (Dendral) to make discoveries on its own, not just help humans make them". Buchanan designed "Meta-Dendral", which was a "hypothesis maker".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2238%22])">38</ref>  Meta-Dendral and Dendral were fused together to create Heuristic Dendral" in 1966-67.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref>  The prime difference was that Heuristic Dendral "would serve as a template for similar systems in other areas" rather than just concentrating in the field of organic chemistry.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="2">
Lederberg, 1987</entry>
<entry id="3">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="4">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="5">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="6">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="7">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="8">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="9">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="10">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="11">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="12">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="13">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="14">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="15">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="17">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="16">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="19">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="18">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="21">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="20">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="23">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="22">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="25">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="24">
Lindsay et al., 1980</entry>
<entry id="27">
Lederberg, 1963</entry>
<entry id="26">
Berk, 1985</entry>
<entry id="29">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="28">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="31">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="30">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="34">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="35">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="32">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="33">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="38">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="39">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="36">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="37">
November, 2006</entry>
<entry id="40">
November, 2006</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Berk, A A. LISP: the Language of Artificial Intelligence. New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold Company, 1985. 1-25.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Lederberg, Joshua. An Instrumentation Crisis in Biology. Stanford University Medical School. Palo Alto, 1963.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Lederberg, Joshua. How Dendral Was Conceived and Born. ACM Symposium on the History of Medical Informatics, 5 November 1987, Rockefeller University. New York: National Library of Medicine, 1987.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Lindsay, Robert K., Bruce G. Buchanan, Edward A. Feigenbaum, and Joshua Lederberg. Applications of Artificial Intelligence for Organic Chemistry: The Dendral Project. McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1980.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 November, Joseph A. “Digitizing Life: The Introduction of Computers to Biology and Medicine.” Doctoral dissertation, Princeton University, 2006.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</article>
