<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:18:45[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Laboratory information management system</title>
<id>570749</id>
<revision>
<id>243246516</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T19:47:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rich Farmbrough</username>
<id>82835</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Laboratory Information Management System</category>
<category>Health software</category>
<category>Information systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A "Laboratory Information Management System" (LIMS) is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
computer software</link> that is used in the laboratory for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/19881.xml">
management</link> of samples, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/173351.xml">
laboratory</link> users, instruments, standards and other laboratory functions such as invoicing, plate management, and work flow automation.  A LIMS and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/1286541.xml">
Laboratory Information System</link> (LIS) perform similar functions.  The primary difference is that LIMS are generally targeted toward environmental, research or commercial analysis, such as pharmaceutical or petrochemical, and LIS are targeted toward the clinical market (hospitals and other clinical labs).<p>

Today's trend is to move the whole process of information gathering, decision making, calculation, review and release out into the workplace and away from the office. The goal is to create a seamless organization where:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Instruments used are integrated in the lab network; receive instructions and worklists from the LIMS and return finished results including raw data back to a central repository where the LIMS can update relevant information to external systems such as a Manufacturing Execution System or Enterprise Resource Planning application.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lab personnel will perform calculations, documentation and review results using online information from connected instruments, reference databases and other resources using electronic lab notebooks (ELN's) connected to the LIMS.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Management can supervise the lab process, react to bottlenecks in workflow and ensure regulatory demands are met.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 External participants (department, company) can place work requests and follow up on progress, review results and print out analysis certificates and other documentation (perhaps even historically).</entry>
</list>

In fact, with the advent of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/371444.xml">
SOA</link> and other <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<meme wordnetid="105985126" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<acculturation wordnetid="105984936" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/1555022.xml">
Web 2.0</link></acculturation>
</activity>
</meme>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
 technologies, today's (2007) LIMS is being defined as a complete <link>
ERP</link> for the laboratory, no longer restricted to sample monitoring and results entry. Although it can be client-server or PC-based, it is increasingly web browser-based and provides a large assortment of functionality.</p>


<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/962908.xml">
Change control</link></entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
