<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:59:00[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<work  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100575741">
<examination  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100635850">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<survey  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100644503">
<investigation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100633864">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>New pedestrianism</title>
<id>5759893</id>
<revision>
<id>232846606</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-19T05:53:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Anthony Appleyard</username>
<id>119438</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>New Urbanism</category>
<category>Urban studies and planning</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>New Pedestrianism (NP)</b> is a more idealistic variation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/158951.xml">
New Urbanism</link> in urban planning theory, founded in 1999 by <artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/5734284.xml">
Michael E. Arth</link></artist>
, an American artist, urban/home/landscape designer, futurist, and author. NP addresses the problems associated with New Urbanism and is an attempt to solve various social, health, energy, economic, aesthetic, and environmental problems, with special focus on reducing the role of the automobile. A neighborhood or new town utilizing NP is called a <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/17586014.xml">
Pedestrian Village</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
. Pedestrian Villages can range from being nearly car-free to having automobile access behind nearly every house and business, but pedestrian lanes are always in front. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

To a large extent New Urbanism is a revival of traditional street patterns and urban design. New Pedestrianism also respects traditional town design, but seeks to further reduce the negative impact of the automobile, the use of which has increased dramatically since WWII. By eliminating the front street and replacing it with a tree-lined pedestrian lane, emphasis is placed on low-impact alternative travel such as walking and cycling. Pedestrian lanes are usually 12 to 15&nbsp;feet (5&nbsp;m) wide, with one smooth side for rolling conveyances such as bicycles, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/29083.xml">
Segways</link>, and skates and the other, narrower, textured side for pedestrians and wheelchairs. Eliminating the automobile street from the front allows for intimate scale plazas, fountains, pocket parks, as well as an unspoiled connection to natural features such as lakes, streams, and forests that may border or be included in a Pedestrian Village. A vast public realm is created that is free from the sight, smell, and sound of automobiles, yet automobiles are still served on a separate network. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

New Pedestrianism has been proposed for Kisima Kaya, a new town in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/188171.xml">
Kenya</link></country>
, for Tiger Bay Village, FL as a solution to the homeless problem, and for new towns and neighborhoods that can be built anywhere whether as rehabilitation of existing neighborhoods, infill, edge-of-town neighborhoods, or new towns. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
The automobile</st>

<p>

To a large extent, NP is a reaction to the way in which the automobile has impacted the environment and reshaped the cities. Arth writes: “Our quality of life is dependent on achieving a spectrum of physical and psychological needs in a clean, safe, and beautiful environment that can only be accomplished with highly integrated urban design and planning. As long as vehicles, roads, parking lots, garages, and automobile-related businesses cover a significant portion of the landscape and determine the design of nearly everything else, most American cities will continue to be dysfunctional and degraded slumscapes, choked with traffic.” <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Over six million motor vehicle related accidents result in almost three million injuries, and over 42,000 deaths each year in the United States alone. Worldwide, approximately half a million deaths occur each year from motor vehicle accidents. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Over-reliance on the automobile, coupled with the lack of a pedestrian-friendly environment, has contributed to two-thirds of adult Americans being overweight or obese. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  
Americans spend about $33 billion a year trying to lose weight, yet 300,000 still die every year because of weight-related problems. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> 
Degradation of the urban and rural landscape caused by sprawl also has wide-ranging negative effects on the environment and contributes to high maintenance costs to the infrastructure. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

Most Americans spend as much of their income on transportation as on housing, with residents of more automobile-dependent cities spending as much as three times as much of their Gross Regional Product (GRP). People in Houston, Atlanta, Dallas-Ft.Worth spend about 23% of their GRP on transportation compared to 9% in Honolulu, New York City, and Baltimore, and 7% in Toronto. These statistics are from the late 90’s before the huge runup in oil prices, and do not include some of the hidden costs of oil consumption. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Energy</st>

<p>

Oil production peaked in the U.S. in 1970 and today only 35% of oil consumed is produced domestically. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> 
The U.S. has grown increasingly dependent on obtaining oil that lies beneath areas populated by people who are hostile to American interests. This is assumed by Arth and many others to have led to increased U.S. militarism in oil rich countries and a growing trade deficit. NP seeks to reduce oil consumption by designing neighborhoods and towns that require far less automobile travel. Most daily trips and recreation in a Pedestrian Village would be within pleasant walking or bicycling distance. New Pedestrianism asserts that it is necessary only to connect village centers to create a highly efficient public transportation system. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

New Pedestrianism, in its ideal form, reduces the need for oil and other limited energy sources by reducing consumption and utilizing renewable energy. It is anticipated, especially as the cost of photovoltaic cells drops, that individual homes would be equipped with solar panels and solar water heaters, and that solar parks would harvest energy for the whole community. Reducing energy needs and moving away from oil dependency would presumably address health, social, economic, and environmental problems. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
New Pedestrianism for the homeless</st>
<p>

In January 2007 Arth proposed that a Pedestrian Village be built for the adult homeless in Volusia County, FL as a prototype for a national solution that would cost less than what he calls the “current Band-Aid approach to the problem.”<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>  Tiger Bay Village would be nearly car free and provide six kinds of housing, ranging from multi-bed barracks in buildings that look like traditional two story homes, to <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/10644858.xml">
Katrina Cottage</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
s. It would have a lake, swimming lagoon, pool, hiking trails, parks, community gardens and orchards. The residents would help build and maintain the village, and it would also serve as a permanent home for those with mental disabilities who are unable to reintegrate into outside society. All the needs of both temporary and permanent residents would be available on site, and the village would be located on a major bus route. Amenities would also include a labor service that would provide pre-screened workers to the public.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> The village was designed under a master plan, but the purpose and design of the buildings could be reassessed as it was built in stages over the years.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> The proposal fueled a national debate about what to do about the homeless while also garnering derision from some quarters by being called either a “resort for the homeless” or a “gulag reservation.”<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> Arth has been careful to explain that this is not a solution for low income housing, which should be integrated into the community.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Aesthetics</st>

<p>

New Pedestrianism replaces unsightly and dangerous front streets with tree-lined pedestrian lanes that form a linear park system that directly connects all homes and businesses to each other, as well as to parks, greenbelts, plazas, courtyards, water features, schools, recreation, and other amenities. This presumably raises the value of all property because the public and private properties are no longer devalued by the appearance and danger of excessive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/10958185.xml">
automobile dependency</link>. A separate, tree-lined, street grid for cars also exists, but it always relegated to the rear, and the pedestrian/bike grid as the primary transportation network ensures that unsightly, noisome traffic is vastly reduced on the rear streets. In Pedestrian Villages, density increases because buildings can be built close to quiet, car-free lanes without the need for huge setbacks that are typical in suburban sprawl. This, in turn, places more emphasis on building design, peaceful and intimate public spaces, and aesthetics that is scaled for pedestrians.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

Like New Urbanism, New Pedestrianism has its roots in compact, mixed-use neighborhoods common in the United States (and elsewhere) during and prior to the first quarter of the 20th century. New Pedestrianism borrows and then expands upon earlier experiments in urban design that focused on separating pedestrians from vehicular traffic. </p>
<p>

In a few beachside communities in Southern California, including <link>
Venice, California</link>, "walk streets" were constructed around 1905 in a few blocks near the beach. Houses faced pedestrian lanes that ranged between 3 and 10  feet wide.  Narrow alleys in the rear handled cars and parking. The canals in Venice, California, built during the same period, also had both sidewalks and canals in front of the houses.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Urban planners <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<planner wordnetid="110438172" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/202171.xml">
Ebenezer Howard</link></causal_agent>
</planner>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/512240.xml">
Sir Patrick Geddes</link> were an earlier influence on the design of <position wordnetid="108621598" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<landmark wordnetid="108624891" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/194187.xml">
Radburn, New Jersey</link></urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</village>
</point>
</landmark>
</city>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</position>
, built at the dawn of the automobile age in 1929. Radburn had pedestrian lanes in front and vehicular access at the rear on cul-de-sacs that protruded into large multi-use blocks. A study done in 1970 by John Lansing of the University of Michigan showed that 47% of its residents did their grocery shopping on foot, compared to 8% for a conventional subdivision nearby. He also determined that, overall, Radburn residents drove far less than in any other areas he studied. The Radburn plan has been copied in various forms in Sweden, England, Japan, New Zealand, and Australia. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

The <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<show wordnetid="106619065" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<attraction wordnetid="106615561" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/1928836.xml">
San Antonio River Walk</link></attraction>
</psychological_feature>
</show>
</social_event>
</event>
, also known as "Paseo del Rio," was initiated in 1929. In this case, the San Antonio River underwent flood control measures and was turned into a peaceful canal lined on both sides with lively pedestrian promenades, plazas, sidewalk cafes, restaurants, clubs, shops, hotels, and other attractions that are completely separate from any vehicles. The promenades pass underneath the roads since Paseo del Rio is one level below the street and vehicular access to buildings is one story above the river. </p>
<p>

Village Homes in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/9123.xml">
Davis, California</link></village>
 was founded in 1975 by Michael and Judy Corbett. The 70 acre subdivision has 225 homes and 20 apartments. Solar design and solar panels are utilized for heating. The homes have walkways passing through an extensive greenbelt system on one side of the houses with automobile access on the other side. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

Some streets in the New Urbanist development of <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/1469339.xml">
Rosemary Beach, Florida</link></group>
</community>
</gathering>
</social_group>
 also have boardwalks in front of some of the homes. </p>
<p>

In 2005 New Pedestrianism was offered by Arth as part of the solution to the rebuilding of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/53842.xml">
New Orleans</link>.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Films about New Pedestrianism</st>

<p>

<it>New Urban Cowboy: Toward a New Pedestrianism</it>, produced in 2008, is a feature length documentary that tells the story of Arth's struggle to retrofit a crack slum into a Pedestrian Village while also explaining the philosophy of New Pedestrianism. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

<it>The Labors of Hercules: Modern Solutions to 12 Herculean Problems</it>. Projected for release in 2009, this feature-length documentary follows the book of the same title and will address societal issues that also relate to New Pedestrianism. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Examples</st>

<p>

These are examples of New Pedestrianism-style Pedestrian Villages that represent the various types: <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  <b>Two Harbors, Calif., USA</b>: Proposed car-free Pedestrian Village on Catalina Island. 1999.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  <b>Paseo Del Mar in Santa Barbara, Calif., USA</b>. Pedestrian Village with parking hidden below. 1999. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  <b>Garden Village in Austin, Texas, USA</b>. Proposed infill Pedestrian Village to replace former site of Mueller airport.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  <b>Downtown DeLand, Florida, USA (Historic Garden District)</b>. Infill retrofit of existing neighborhood, 2001-2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  <b>Kisima Kaya, Kenya</b>. New town proposed near <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/21482.xml">
Nairobi</link></village>
, Kenya, in 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  <b>Tiger Bay Village, Florida, USA</b>. Proposed nearly car free Pedestrian Village as a solution to homelessness. 2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  <b>Mackinac Island, Michigan, USA</b>.  While not created with the specific idea of New Pedestrianism in mind, the island has 523 permanent residents and attracts hundreds of thousands of tourists per year.  No motor vehicles have been allowed on the island since the end of the 1800s.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/5734284.xml">
Michael E. Arth</link></artist>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/158951.xml">
New Urbanism</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 Michael E. Arth, <it>The Labors of Hercules: Modern Solutions to 12 Herculean Problems.</it> 2007 Online edition. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://michaelearth.com/herc_IX.htm">
Labor IX: Urbanism</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="2">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pedestrianvillages.com/">
New Pedestrianism information</weblink>  </entry>
<entry id="3">
 Michael E. Arth, "Pedestrian Villages are the Antidote to Sprawl" The DeLand-Deltona Beacon, May 29, 2003. Page 1D.  </entry>
<entry id="4">
 Morris Sullivan, "Town designer solves problem areas." Daytona Beach News-Journal, January 15, 2006, p. 10H.   </entry>
<entry id="5">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nhtsa.dot.gov/">
National Highway &amp; Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA)</weblink>  </entry>
<entry id="6">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.transact.org/">
Surface Transportation Policy Project</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="7">
 NHANS National Health &amp; Nutrition Examination Survey (2003-2004) </entry>
<entry id="8">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/">
National Center for Health Statistics</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="9">
 The CTA-International Center for Technology Assessment. "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.icta.org/doc/rpg%20execsum.pdf/">
The Real Price of Gasoline, Executive Summary</weblink>" 1998. </entry>
<entry id="10">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eia.doe.gov/">
U.S. Energy Information Administration (EIA)</weblink>, “U.S. Product Supplied for Crude Oil and Petroleum Products,” Petroleum Navigator </entry>
<entry id="11">
 Michael E. Arth, "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.orlandosentinel.com/news/local/volusia/orl-vol-arthessay012007,0,3658819.story?coll=orl-news-headlines-volusia/">
A National Solution to Homelessness That Begins Here.</weblink>" Orlando Sentinel, January 20, 2007</entry>
<entry id="12">
 Tom Leonard, "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2007/01/23/wdaytona23.xml">
Daytona may give vagrants their own resort.</weblink>" Telegraph.co.uk,  January 24, 2007</entry>
<entry id="13">
 Etan Horowitz, "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.orlandosentinel.com/orl-varth2707jan27,0,3612065.story?track=rss/">
Developer defends homeless-village concept.</weblink>" Orlando Sentinel, January 27, 2007</entry>
<entry id="14">
 Rebbecca Mahoney, "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.orlandosentinel.com/news/local/volusia/orl-mhomeless2007jan20,0,1951442.story?coll=orl-news-headlines-volusia">
Homeless village or leper colony?</weblink>" Orlando Sentinel, January 20, 2007</entry>
<entry id="15">
 John B. Lansing, Robert W. Marans and Robert B. Zehner, <it>Planned Residential Environments</it> (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan, 1970), p. 213 </entry>
<entry id="17">
 Michael E. Arth "New Orleans is Opportunity for Better Urban Planning," The Dayton News-Journal, Section B, October 30, 2005.  </entry>
<entry id="16">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.villagehomesdavis.org">
Village Homes</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="19">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://GoldenApplesMedia.com/">
 NewUrbanCowboy.com</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="18">
 Michael E. Arth "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.seasidefl.com/newsStory.asp?releaseId=1047/">
New Orleans Offers Chance for Better Planning</weblink>"  </entry>
<entry id="20">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://GoldenApplesMedia.com/">
Golden Apples Media</weblink> </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.michaelearth.com/">
Michael E. Arth's website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pedestrianvillages.com/">
Pedestrian Villages website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://michaelearth.com/herc_IX.htm">
Philosophy behind New Pedestrianism</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worldcarfree.net/">
World Carfree Network</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.villagehomesdavis.org/">
Village Homes, Davis, California</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.transact.org/">
Surface Transportation Policy Partnership (STPP)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnu.org/">
Congress for New Urbanism</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
</article>
