<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:03:05[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<relationship  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113780719">
<header>
<title>Attachment in adults</title>
<id>5761650</id>
<revision>
<id>241495478</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-28T08:49:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>16@r</username>
<id>839108</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Human development</category>
<category>Psychoanalysis</category>
<category>Interpersonal relationships</category>
<category>Attachment theory</category>
<category>Love</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="float:right; margin-left:0.5em; width:15.0em; border:1px solid #BEBEBE; text-align:center;" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header style="background:#D4DDE9; line-height:95%;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/161744.xml">
Close relationships</link></header>
<col>
 <image location="center" width="90px" src="KarenWhimseyValentineMain.png">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding:0 0.5em; background:#F4FBFF; font-size:90%;"><p>

<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/6131623.xml">
Affinity</link></relationship>
&nbsp;·  
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/5761650.xml">
Attachment</link></relationship>
&nbsp;·  
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/3829592.xml">
Bonding</link></relationship>
 &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/572511.xml">
Boyfriend</link>&nbsp;·  
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../067/11444067.xml">
Casual</link></relationship>
&nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/36527.xml">
Cohabitation</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/1372276.xml">
Compersion</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/7016.xml">
Concubinage</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/644092.xml">
Consort</link>&nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/37022.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22In+modern+times%22])">
Courtesan</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/411659.xml">
Courtship</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/40147.xml">
Divorce</link>&nbsp;·  
<right wordnetid="105174653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/220426.xml">
Domestic partnership</link></right>
 &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/3044226.xml">
Dower</link>&nbsp;/ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/234516.xml">
Dowry</link>&nbsp;/ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/234511.xml">
Bride price</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/10401954.xml">
Family</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/17157119.xml">
Friendship</link>&nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/19614149.xml">
Girlfriend</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/4318352.xml">
Husband</link>&nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/634932.xml">
Infatuation</link>&nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/224513.xml">
Intimacy</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/170586.xml">
Jealousy</link>&nbsp;·  
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/154147.xml">
Limerence</link></relationship>
&nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/17547.xml">
Love</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19728.xml">
Marriage</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/20477.xml">
Monogamy</link> &nbsp;·  
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../233/5555233.xml">
Psychology of monogamy</link></relationship>
 &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/335325.xml">
Serial monogamy</link>&nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/1271787.xml">
Nonmonogamy</link> &nbsp;·  
<feeling wordnetid="100026192" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<emotion wordnetid="107480068" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/1329397.xml">
Passion</link></emotion>
</state>
</feeling>
&nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/19629641.xml">
Pederasty</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/286012.xml">
Platonic love</link> &nbsp;·  
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/24591.xml">
Polyamory</link></relationship>
 &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/419724.xml">
Polyfidelity</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/24475.xml">
Polygamy</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/424739.xml">
Relationship abuse</link> &nbsp;·  
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/519576.xml">
Relationship breakup</link></relationship>
 &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/285141.xml">
Romance</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/2371889.xml">
Romantic friendship</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/98214.xml">
Separation</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/14337.xml">
Sexuality</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/661047.xml">
Same-sex relationship</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/232643.xml">
Significant other</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/889841.xml">
Soulmate</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/12166425.xml">
Teen dating violence</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/32893.xml">
Wedding</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/254879.xml">
Widowhood</link> &nbsp;·  
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/177428.xml">
Wife</link>&nbsp;·</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
<b>Attachment in adults</b> deals with the theory of attachment in adult romantic relationships.<p>

Attachment theory was extended to adult romantic relationships in the late 1980s. Four styles of attachment have been identified in adults: secure, anxious-preoccupied, dismissive-avoidant, and fearful-avoidant. Investigators have explored the organization and the stability of mental <it>working models</it> that underlie these attachment styles. They have also explored how attachment impacts relationship outcomes and how attachment functions in relationship dynamics.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Extending attachment theory</st>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/1065890.xml">
John Bowlby</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/4040297.xml">
Mary Ainsworth</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 founded modern attachment theory on studies of children and their caregivers. Children and caregivers remained the primary focus of attachment theory for many years. Then, in the late 1980s, Cindy Hazan and Phillip Shaver applied attachment theory to adult romantic relationships.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> 
Hazan and Shaver noticed that interactions between adult romantic partners shared similarities to interactions between children and caregivers. For example, romantic partners desire to be close to one another. Romantic partners feel comforted when their partners are present and anxious or lonely when their partners are absent. Romantic relationships serve as a secure base that help partners face the surprises, opportunities, and challenges life presents. Similarities such as these led Hazan and Shaver to extend attachment theory to adult romantic relationships.</p>
<p>

Of course, relationships between adult romantic partners differ in many ways from relationships between children and caregivers. The claim is not that these two kinds of relationships are identical. The claim is that the core principles of attachment theory apply to both kinds of relationships. </p>
<p>

Investigators tend to describe the core principles of attachment theory in light of their own theoretical interests. Their descriptions seem quite different on a superficial level. For example, Fraley and Shaver<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> describe the "central propositions" of attachment in adults as follows: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The emotional and behavioral dynamics of infant-caregiver relationships and adult romantic relationships are governed by the same biological system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The kinds of individual differences observed in infant-caregiver relationships are similar to the ones observed in romantic relationships.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Individual differences in adult attachment behavior are reflections of the expectations and beliefs people have formed about themselves and their close relationships on the basis of their attachment histories; these "working models" are relatively stable and, as such, may be reflections of early care giving experiences.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Romantic love, as commonly conceived, involves the interplay of attachment, care giving and sex.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Compare this to the five "core propositions" of attachment theory listed by Rholes and Simpson:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Although the basic impetus for the formation of attachment relationships is provided by biological factors, the bonds that children form with their caregivers are shaped by interpersonal experience.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Experiences in earlier relationships create internal working models and attachment styles that systematically affect attachment relationships.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The attachment orientations of adult caregivers influence the attachment bond their children have with them.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Working models and attachment orientations are relatively stable over time, but they are not impervious to change.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Some forms of psychological maladjustment and clinical disorders are attributable in part to the effects of insecure working models and attachment styles.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

While these two lists clearly reflect the theoretical interests of the investigators who created them, a closer look reveals a number of shared themes. The shared themes claim that:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 People are biologically driven to form attachments with others, but the process of forming attachments is influenced by learning experiences.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Individuals form different kinds of attachments depending on the expectations and beliefs they have about their relationships. These expectations and beliefs constitute internal "working models" used to guide relationship behaviors.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Internal "working models" are relatively stable even though they can be influenced by experience.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Individual differences in attachment can contribute positively or negatively to mental health and to quality of relationships with others.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

No doubt these themes could be described in a variety of ways (and other themes added to the list). Regardless of how one describes the core principles of attachment theory, the key insight is that the same principles of attachment apply to close relationships throughout the lifespan. The principles of attachment between children and caregivers are fundamentally the same as the principles of attachment between adult romantic partners.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Attachment styles</st>
<p>

Adults have four attachment styles: secure, anxious-preoccupied, dismissive avoidant, and fearful avoidant. The secure attachment style in adults corresponds to the secure attachment style in children. The anxious-preoccupied attachment style in adults corresponds to the anxious/ambivalent attachment style in children. However, the dismissive avoidant attachment style and the fearful avoidant attachment style, which are distinct in adults, correspond to a single avoidant attachment style in children. The descriptions of adult attachment styles offered below are based on the relationship questionnaire devised by Bartholomew and Horowitz<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> and on a review of studies by Pietromonaco and Barrett.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

There are several attachment-based treatment approaches that can be used with adults.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>  In addition, there is an approach to treating couples based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/884589.xml">
attachment theory</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Secure attachment</st>
<p>

Securely attached people tend to agree with the following statements: "It is relatively easy for me to become emotionally close to others. I am comfortable depending on others and having others depend on me. I don't worry about being alone or having others not
accept me." This style of attachment usually results from a history of warm and responsive interactions with relationship partners. Securely attached people tend to have positive views of themselves and their partners. They also tend to have positive views of their relationships. Often they report greater satisfaction and adjustment in their relationships than people with other attachment styles. Securely attached people feel comfortable both with intimacy and with independence. Many seek to balance intimacy and independence in their relationships.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Anxious-preoccupied attachment</st>
<p>

People who are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/922.xml">
anxious</link> or preoccupied with attachment tend to agree with the following statements: "I want to be completely emotionally intimate with others, but I often find that others are reluctant to get as close as I would like. I am uncomfortable being without close relationships, but I sometimes worry that others don't value me as much as I value them." People with this style of attachment seek high levels of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/224513.xml">
intimacy</link>, approval, and responsiveness from their partners. They sometimes value intimacy to such an extent that they become overly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/1425439.xml">
dependent</link> on their partners—a condition colloquially termed <it>clinginess</it>. Compared to securely attached people, people who are anxious or preoccupied with attachment tend to have less positive views about themselves. They often <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/306291.xml">
doubt</link> their worth as a partner and blame themselves for their partners' lack of responsiveness. They also have less positive views about their partners because they do not <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/850663.xml">
trust</link></issue>
 in people's good intentions. People who are anxious or preoccupied with attachment may experience high levels of emotional expressiveness, worry, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/14511650.xml">
impulsiveness</link> in their relationships.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Dismissive-avoidant attachment</st>
<p>

People with a dismissive style of avoidant attachment tend to agree with these statements: "I am comfortable without close emotional relationships. It is very important to me to feel independent and self-sufficient, and I prefer not to depend on others or have others depend on me." People with this attachment style desire a high level of independence. The desire for independence often appears as an attempt to avoid attachment altogether. They view themselves as self-sufficient and invulnerable to feelings associated with being closely attached to others. They often deny needing close relationships. Some may even view close relationships as relatively unimportant. Not surprisingly, they seek less intimacy with relationship partners, whom they often view less positively than they view themselves. Investigators commonly note the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/8989.xml">
defensive</link> character of this attachment style. People with a dismissive-avoidant attachment tend to suppress and hide their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/10763158.xml">
feelings</link>, and they tend to deal with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/1038620.xml">
rejection</link> by distancing themselves from the sources of rejection (i.e., their relationship partners).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fearful-avoidant attachment</st>
<p>

People with a fearful style of avoidant attachment tend to agree with the following statements: "I am somewhat uncomfortable getting close to others. I want emotionally close relationships, but I find it difficult to trust others completely, or to depend on them. I sometimes worry that I will be hurt if I allow myself to become too close to others." People with this attachment style have mixed feelings about close relationships. On the one hand, they desire to have emotionally close relationships. On the other hand, they tend to feel uncomfortable with emotional closeness. These mixed feelings are combined with negative views about themselves and their partners. They commonly view themselves as unworthy of responsiveness from their partners, and they don't trust the intentions of their partners. Similarly to the dismissive-avoidant attachment style, people with a fearful-avoidant attachment style seek less intimacy from partners and frequently suppress and hide their feelings.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Working models</st>
<p>

Bowlby theorized that children learn from their interactions with caregivers. Over the course of many interactions, children form expectations about the accessibility and helpfulness of their caregivers. These expectations reflect children's thoughts about themselves and about their caregivers:</p>
<p>

"Confidence that an attachment figure is, apart from being accessible, likely to be responsive can be seen to turn on at least two variables: (a) whether or not the attachment figure is judged to be the sort of person who in general responds to calls for support and protection; (b) whether or not the self is judged to be the sort of person towards whom anyone, and the attachment figure in particular, is likely to respond in a helpful way. Logically, these variables are independent. In practice they are apt to be confounded. As a result, the model of the attachment figure and the model of the self are likely to develop so as to be complementary and mutually confirming." (Bowlby, 1973, p. 238)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

Children's thoughts about their caregivers, together with thoughts about themselves as deserving good caregivers, form <it>working models</it> of attachment. Working models help guide behavior by allowing children to anticipate and plan for caregiver responses. Once formed, Bowlby theorized that working models remain relatively stable. Children usually interpret experiences in light of their working models rather than change their working models to fit new experiences. Only when experiences cannot be interpreted in light of working models do children modify their working models. </p>
<p>

When Hazen and Shaver extended attachment theory to adults, they included the idea of working models. Research into adult working models has focused on two issues. First, how are the thoughts that form working models organized in the mind? Second, how stable are working models across time? These questions are briefly discussed below.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Organization of working models</st>
<p>

Bartholomew and Horowitz have proposed that working models consist of two parts.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> 
One part deals with thoughts about the self. The other part deals with thoughts about others. They further propose that a person's thoughts about self are generally positive or generally negative. The same applies to a person's thoughts about others. Thoughts about others are generally positive or generally negative. In order to test these proposals, Bartholomew and Horowitz have looked at the relationship between attachment styles, self-esteem, and sociability. The diagram below shows the relationships they observed:
<image location="center" width="150px" src="Four_Category_Model_Tested.png">
<caption>

Security based strategy of affect regulation.
</caption>
</image>

The secure and dismissive attachment styles are associated with higher self-esteem compared to the anxious and fearful attachment styles. This corresponds to the distinction between positive and negative thoughts about the self in working models. The secure and anxious attachment styles are associated with higher sociability than the dismissive or fearful attachment styles. This corresponds to the distinction between positive and negative thoughts about others in working models. These results suggested working models indeed contain two distinct domains--thoughts about self and thoughts about others--and that each domain can be characterized as generally positive or generally negative.</p>
<p>

Baldwin and colleagues have applied the theory of relational schemas to working models of attachment. Relational schemas contain information about the way partners regularly interact with each other.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> 
For each pattern of interaction that regularly occurs between partners, a relational schema is formed that contains:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 information about the self</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 information about the partner</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 information about the way the interaction usually unfolds.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

For example, if a person regularly asks his or her partner for a hug or kiss, and the partner regularly responds with a hug or kiss, the person forms a relational schema representing the predictable interaction. The schema contains information about the self (e.g., "I need lots of physical affection"). It also contains information about the partner (e.g., "My partner is an affectionate person"). And it contains information about the way the interaction usually unfolds, which can be summarized by an IF-THEN statement (e.g., "IF I ask my partner for a hug or kiss, THEN my partner will respond with a hug or kiss and comfort me"). Relational schemas help guide behavior in relationships by allowing people to anticipate and plan for partner responses.</p>
<p>

Baldwin and colleagues have proposed that working models of attachment are composed of relational schemas. The fact that relational schemas contain information about the self and information about others is consistent with previous conceptions of working models. The unique contribution of relational schemas to working models is the information about the way interactions with partners usually unfold. Relational schemas add the IF-THEN statements about interactions to working models. To demonstrate that working models are organized as relational schemas, Baldwin and colleagues created a set of written scenarios that described interactions dealing with trust, dependency and closeness.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>  
For example, the scenarios for closeness included:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 You want to spend more time with your partner.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 You reach out to hug or kiss your partner.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 You tell your partner how deeply you feel for him or her.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Following each scenario, people were presented with two options about how their partners might respond. One option was "he/she accepts you." The other option was "he/she rejects you." People were asked to rate the likelihood of each response on a seven point scale. Ratings of likely partner responses corresponded to people's attachment styles. People with secure attachment styles were more likely to expect accepting responses from their partners. Their relational schema for the third closeness scenario would be, "IF I tell my partner how deeply I feel for him or her, THEN my partner will accept me." People with other attachment styles were less likely to expect accepting responses from their partners. Their relational schema for the third closeness scenario would be, "IF I tell my partner how deeply I feel for him or her, THEN my partner will reject me." Differences in attachment styles reflected differences in relational schemas. Relational schemas may therefore be used to understand the organization of working models of attachment, as has been demonstrated in subsequent studies.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

The relational schemas involved in working models are likely organized into a hierarchy. According to Baldwin: </p>
<p>

"A person may have a general working model of relationships, for instance, to the effect that others tend to be only partially and unpredictably responsive to one's needs. At a more specific level, this expectation will take different forms when considering different role relationships, such as customer or romantic partner. Within romantic relationships, expectations might then vary significantly depending on the specific partner, or the specific situation, or the specific needs being expressed." (Baldwin, 1992, p. 429).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

The highest level of the hierarchy contains very general relational schemas that apply to all relationships. The next level of the hierarchy contains relational schemas that apply to particular kinds of relationships. The lowest level of the hierarchy contains relationship schemas that apply to specific relationships. </p>
<p>

In fact, several theorists have proposed a hierarchical organization of working models.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> 
Pietromonaco and Barrett note:</p>
<p>

"From this perspective, people do not hold a single set of working models of the self and others; rather, they hold a family of models that include, at higher levels, abstract rules or assumptions about attachment relationships and, at lower levels, information about specific relationships and events within relationships. These ideas also imply that working models are not a single entity but are multifaceted representations in which information at one level need not be consistent with information at another level." (Pietromonaco &amp; Barrett, 2000, page 159)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>
<p>

Every hierarchy for working models includes both general working models (higher in the hierarchy) and relationship-specific working models (lower in the hierarchy). Studies have supported the existence of both general working models and relationship-specific working models. People can report a general attachment style when asked to do so, and the majority of their relationships are consistent with their general attachment style.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> A general attachment style indicates a general working model that applies to many relationships. Yet, people also report different styles of attachments to their friends, parents and lovers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> 
Relationship-specific attachment styles indicate relationship-specific working models. Evidence that general working models and relationship-specific working models are organized into a hierarchy comes from a study by Overall, Fletcher and Friesen.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref> 
Findings from this study support a three-tier hierarchy of working models. The highest level of the hierarchy consists of a global working model. The next level of the hierarchy contains working models for different types of relationships (e.g., friends, parents, lovers). The lowest level in the hierarchy consists of working models for each specific relationship.</p>
<p>

In summary, the mental working models that underlie attachment styles appear to contain information about self and information about others organized into relational schemas. The relational schemas are themselves organized into a three-tier hierarchy. The highest level of the hierarchy contains relational schemas for a general working model that applies to all relationships. The middle level of the hierarchy contains relational schemas for working models that apply to different types of relationships (e.g., friends, parents, lovers). The lowest level of the hierarchy contains relational schemas for working models of specific relationships.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Stability of working models</st>
<p>

Investigators study the stability of working models by looking at the stability of attachment styles. Attachment styles reflect the thoughts and expectations that constitute working models. Changes in attachment styles therefore indicate changes in working models.</p>
<p>

Around 70-80 percent of people experience no significant changes in attachment styles over time.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> The fact that attachment styles do not change for a majority of people indicates working models are relatively stable. Yet, around 20-30 percent of people do experience changes in attachment styles. These changes can occur over periods of weeks or months. The number of people who experience changes in attachment styles, and the short periods over which the changes occur, suggest working models are not rigid personality traits. </p>
<p>

Why attachment styles change is not well understood. Waters, Weinfield and Hamilton propose that negative life experiences often cause changes in attachment styles.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref> 
Their proposal is supported by evidence that people who experience negative life events also tend to experience changes in attachment styles.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref> 
Davila, Karney and Bradbury have identified four sets of factors that might cause changes in attachment styles: (a) situational <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/9451.xml">
event</link>s and circumstances, (b) changes in relational <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/1058555.xml">
schema</link>, (c) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/177648.xml">
personality</link> variables, and (d) combinations of personality variables and situational events.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref> They conducted a study to see which set of factors best explained changes in attachment styles. Interestingly, the study found that all four sets of factors cause changes in attachment styles. Changes in attachment styles are complex and depend on multiple factors.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Relationship outcomes</st>
<p>

Adult romantic relationships vary in their outcomes. The partners of some relationships express more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/169423.xml">
satisfaction</link> than the partners of other relationships. The partners of some relationships stay together longer than the partners of other relationships. Does attachment influence the satisfaction and duration of relationships?</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Satisfaction</st>
<p>

Several studies have linked attachment styles to relationship satisfaction. People who have secure attachment styles usually express greater satisfaction with their relationships than people who have other attachment styles.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2237%22])">37</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2238%22])">38</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2241%22])">41</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref></p>
<p>

Although the link between attachment styles and marital satisfaction has been firmly established, the mechanisms by which attachment styles influence marital satisfaction remain poorly understood. One mechanism may be communication. Secure attachment styles may lead to more constructive communication and more intimate self-disclosures, which in turn increase relationship satisfaction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2243%22])">43</ref> Other mechanisms by which attachment styles may influence relationship satisfaction include emotional expressiveness,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2244%22])">44</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2245%22])">45</ref> strategies for coping with conflict,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref> and perceived support from partners.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2246%22])">46</ref> Further studies are needed to better understand how attachment styles influence relationship satisfaction.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Duration</st>
<p>

Some studies suggest people with secure attachment styles have longer-lasting relationships.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2247%22])">47</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2248%22])">48</ref> This may be partly due to commitment. People with secure attachment styles tend to express more commitment to their relationships. People with secure attachment styles also tend to be more satisfied with their relationships, which may encourage them to stay in their relationships longer. However, secure attachment styles are by no means a guarantee of long-lasting relationships. </p>
<p>

Nor are secure attachment styles the only attachment styles associated with stable relationships. People with anxious-preoccupied attachment styles often find themselves in long-lasting, but unhappy, relationships.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2249%22])">49</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2250%22])">50</ref> Anxious-preoccupied attachment styles often involve anxiety about being abandoned and doubts about one's worth as a relationship partner. These kinds of feelings and thoughts may lead people to stay in unhappy relationships.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Relationship dynamics</st>
<p>

Attachment plays a role in the way partners interact with one another. A few examples include the role of attachment in affect regulation, support, intimacy, and jealousy. These examples are briefly discussed below. Attachment also plays a role in many interactions not discussed in this article, such as conflict, communication and sexuality.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2251%22])">51</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2252%22])">52</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2253%22])">53</ref> </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Affect regulation</st>
<p>

Bowlby has observed that certain kinds of events trigger anxiety in children, and that children try to relieve their anxiety by seeking closeness and comfort from caregivers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2254%22])">54</ref> 
Three main sets of conditions trigger anxiety in children:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Conditions of the child (fatigue, hunger, illness, pain, cold, etc.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Conditions involving the caregiver (caregiver absent, caregiver departing, caregiver discouraging of proximity, caregiver giving attention to another child, etc.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Conditions of the environment (alarming events, criticism or rejection by others)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The anxiety triggered by these conditions motivates children to engage in behaviors that bring them physically closer to caregivers. A similar dynamic occurs in adults. Conditions involving personal well-being, conditions involving a relationship partner, and conditions involving the environment can trigger anxiety in adults. Adults try to alleviate their anxiety by seeking physical and psychological closeness to their partners. </p>
<p>

Mikulincer, Shaver and Pereg have developed a model for this dynamic.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2255%22])">55</ref> According to the model, when people experience anxiety, they try to reduce their anxiety by seeking closeness with relationship partners. However, the partners may accept or reject requests for greater closeness. This leads people to adopt different strategies for reducing anxiety. People engage in three main strategies to reduce anxiety.</p>
<p>

The first strategy is called the <it>security based</it> strategy. The diagram below shows the sequence of events in the security based strategy. 
<image location="center" width="150px" src="Attachment_Theory_Security_Based.png">
<caption>

Security based strategy of affect regulation.
</caption>
</image>

A person perceives something that provokes anxiety. The person tries to reduce the anxiety by seeking physical or psychological closeness to her or his partner. The partner responds positively to the request for closeness, which reaffirms a sense of security and reduces anxiety. The person returns to her or his everyday activities. </p>
<p>

The second strategy is called the <it>attachment avoidance</it> strategy. The following diagram shows the sequence of events in the attachment avoidance strategy.
<image location="center" width="150px" src="Attachment_Theory_Attachment_Avoidance.png">
<caption>

Attachment avoidance strategy of affect regulation.
</caption>
</image>

The events begin the same way as the security based strategy. A person perceives something that triggers anxiety, and the person tries to reduce anxiety by seeking physical or psychological closeness to her or his partner. But the partner is either unavailable or rebuffs the request for closeness. The lack of responsiveness fuels insecurity and heightens anxiety. The person gives up on getting a positive response from the partner, suppresses her or his anxiety, and distances herself or himself from the partner. </p>
<p>

The third strategy is called the <it>hyperactivation</it> strategy. The diagram below shows the sequence of events in the hyperactivation strategy. 
<image location="center" width="150px" src="Attachment_Theory_Hyperactivation.png">
<caption>

Hyperactivation strategy of affect regulation.
</caption>
</image>

The events begin the same way. Something provokes anxiety in a person, who then tries to reduce anxiety by seeking physical or psychological closeness to a partner. The partner rebuffs the request for greater closeness. The lack of responsiveness increases feelings of insecurity and anxiety. The person then gets locked into a cycle with the partner: the person tries to get closer, the partner rejects the request for greater closesness, which leads the person to try even harder to get closer, followed by another rejection from the partner, and so on. The cycle ends only when the person shifts to a security based strategy (because the partner finally responds positively) or to an attachment avoidant strategy (because the person gives up on getting a positive response from the partner).</p>
<p>

Mikulincer, Shaver, and Pereg contend these strategies of regulating attachment anxiety have very different consequences.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2255%22])">55</ref> The security based strategy leads to more positive thoughts, such as more positive explanations of why others behave in a particular way and more positive memories about people and events. More positive thoughts can encourage more creative responses to difficult problems or distressing situations. The attachment avoidance and hyperactivation strategies lead to more negative thoughts and less creativity in handling problems and stressful situations. From this perspective, it would benefit people to adopt security based strategies for dealing with anxiety.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Support</st>
<p>

People feel less anxious when close to their partners because their partners can provide support during difficult situations. Support includes the comfort, assistance, and information people receive from their partners. </p>
<p>

Attachment influences both the perception of support from others and the tendency to seek support from others. People with secure attachment styles seek more support and get more support from their relationship partners, while people with other attachment styles seek less support and get less support from their relationships partners.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2256%22])">56</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2257%22])">57</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2258%22])">58</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2259%22])">59</ref> People with secure attachment styles may trust their partners to provide support because their partners have reliably offered support in the past. They may be more likely to ask for support when it's needed. People with insecure attachment styles often do not have a history of supportive responses from their partners. They may rely less on their partners and be less likely to ask for support when it's needed. Keep in mind, however, that attachment is only one of many factors that influence how people perceive support and whether or not they choose to seek support.</p>
<p>

Changes in the way people perceive attachment tend to occur with changes in the way people perceive support. One study looked at college students' perceptions of attachment to their mothers, fathers, same-sex friends, and opposite-sex friends.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2260%22])">60</ref> When students reported changes in attachment for a particular relationship, they usually reported changes in support for that relationship as well. Changes in attachment for one relationship did not affect the perception of support in other relationships. The link between changes in attachment and changes in support was relationship-specific.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Intimacy</st>
<p>

Attachment theory has always recognized the importance of intimacy. Bowlby writes:</p>
<p>

"Attachment theory regards the propensity to make intimate emotional bonds to particular individuals as a basic component of human nature, already present in germinal form in the neonate and continuing through adult life into old age." (Bowlby, 1988, pp. 120–121)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2261%22])">61</ref> </p>
<p>

The desire for intimacy has biological roots and, in the great majority of people, persists from birth until death. The desire for intimacy also has important implications for attachment. Relationships that frequently satisfy the desire for intimacy lead to more secure attachments between partners. Relationships that rarely satisfy the desire for intimacy lead to less secure attachments between partners.</p>
<p>

Collins and Feeney have examined the relationship between attachment and intimacy in detail.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2262%22])">62</ref> 
They define intimacy as a special set of interactions in which a person discloses something important about himself or herself, and a partner responds to the disclosure in a way that makes the person feel validated, understood, and cared for. These interactions usually involve verbal self-disclosure. But intimate interactions can also involve non-verbal forms of self-expression such as touching, hugging, kissing, and sexual behavior. From this perspective, intimacy requires the following:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 willingness to disclose one's true thoughts, feelings, wishes, and fears</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 willingness to rely on a partner for care and emotional support</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 willingness to engage in physical intimacy</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Collins and Feeney review a number of studies showing how each attachment style relates to the willingness to self-disclose, the willingness to rely on partners, and the willingness to engage in physical intimacy. The secure attachment style is generally related to more self-disclosure, more reliance on partners, and more physical intimacy than other attachment styles. However, the amount of intimacy in a relationship can vary due to personality variables and situational circumstances, so each attachment style may function to adapt an individual to the particular context of intimacy in which they live.</p>
<p>

Mashek and Sherman report some interesting findings on the desire for less closeness with partners.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2263%22])">63</ref> 
Sometimes too much intimacy can be suffocating. People in this situation desire less closeness with their partners. On the one hand, the relationship between attachment styles and desire for less closeness is predictable. People who have fearful-avoidant and anxious-preoccupied attachment styles typically want greater closeness with their partners. People who have dismissive-avoidant attachment styles typically want less closeness with their partners. On the other hand, the relatively large numbers of people who admit to wanting less closeness with their partners (up to 57% in some studies) far outnumbers the people who have dismissive-avoidant attachment styles. This suggests people who have secure, anxious-preoccupied, or fearful-avoidant attachment styles sometimes seek less closeness with their partners. The desire for less closeness is not determined by attachment styles alone.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Jealousy</st>
<p>

Jealousy refers to the thoughts, feelings, and behaviors that occur when a person believes a valued relationship is threatened by a rival. A jealous person experiences anxiety about maintaining support, intimacy, and other valued qualities of her or his relationship. Given that attachment relates to anxiety regulation, support, and intimacy, as discussed above, it is not surprising that attachment also relates to jealousy.   </p>
<p>

Bowlby observed that attachment behaviors in children can be triggered by the presence of a rival:</p>
<p>

"In most young children the mere sight of mother holding another baby in her arms is enough to elicit strong attachment behaviour. The older child insists on remaining close to his mother, or on climbing on to her lap. Often he behaves as though he were a baby. It is possible that this well-known behaviour is only a special case of a child reacting to mother's lack of attention and lack of responsiveness to him. The fact, however, that an older child often reacts in this way even when his mother makes a point of being attentive and responsive suggests that more is involved; and the pioneer experiments of Levy (1937) also indicate that the mere presence of a baby on mother's lap is sufficient to make an older child much more clinging." (Bowlby, 1969/1982, page 260)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2254%22])">54</ref></p>
<p>

When children see a rival contending for a caregiver's attention, the children try to get close to the caregiver and capture the caregiver's attention. Attempts to get close to the caregiver and capture the caregiver's attention indicate the attachment system has been activated. But the presence of a rival also provokes jealousy in children. The jealousy provoked by a sibling rival has been described in detail.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2264%22])">64</ref> Recent studies have shown that a rival can provoke jealousy at very young ages. The presence of a rival can provoke jealousy in infants as young as six months old.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2265%22])">65</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2266%22])">66</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2267%22])">67</ref> Attachment and jealousy can both be triggered in children by the presence of a rival.</p>
<p>

Attachment and jealousy can be triggered by the same perceptual cues in adults, too.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2268%22])">68</ref> The absence of a partner can trigger both attachment and jealousy when people believe the partner is spending time with a rival. The presence of a rival can also trigger attachment and jealousy.</p>
<p>

Differences in attachment styles influence both the frequency and the pattern of jealous expressions. People who have anxious-preoccupied or fearful-avoidant attachment styles experience jealousy more often and view rivals as more threatening than people who have secure attachment styles.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2268%22])">68</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2269%22])">69</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2270%22])">70</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2271%22])">71</ref> People with different attachment styles also express jealousy in different ways. One study found that:</p>
<p>

"Securely attached participants felt anger more intensely than other emotions and were relatively more likely than other participants to express it, especially toward their partner. And although anxious participants felt anger relatively intensely, and were as likely as others to express it through irritability, they were relatively unlikely to actually confront their partner. This might be attributable to feelings of inferiority and fear, which were especially characteristic of the anxiously attached and which might be expected to inhibit direct expressions of anger. Avoidants felt sadness relatively more intensely than did secures in both studies. Further, avoidants were relatively more likely than others to work to maintain their self-esteem and, perhaps as a consequence, relatively unlikely to be brought closer to their partner." (Sharpsteen &amp; Kirkpatrick, 1997, page 637)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2268%22])">68</ref></p>
<p>

A subsequent study has confirmed that people with different attachment styles experience and express jealousy in qualitatively different ways.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2270%22])">70</ref> Attachment thus plays an important role in jealous interactions by influencing the frequency and the manner in which partners express jealousy.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<table style="background:transparent; width:100%;" cellpadding="0" class=" multicol" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col align="left" width="" valign="top">
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/884589.xml">
Attachment theory</link></relationship>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/5761568.xml">
Attachment in children</link></relationship>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/5761692.xml">
Attachment measures</link></relationship>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/707323.xml">
Attachment disorder</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/740176.xml">
Reactive attachment disorder</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/5885283.xml">
Attachment therapy</link></relationship>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/14068386.xml">
Attachment-based psychotherapy</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
<col align="left" width="" valign="top"><p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5343419.xml">
Affectional bond</link></relationship>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/3829592.xml">
Human bonding</link></relationship>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/170586.xml">
Jealousy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/20477.xml">
Monogamy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/910662.xml">
Object relations theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</institution>
</educational_institution>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</school>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/5115061.xml">
Terms of endearment</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/12835695.xml">
Emotionally Focused Therapy</link></relationship>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
</col>
<col align="left" width="" valign="top"><p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/4040297.xml">
Mary Ainsworth</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/1065890.xml">
John Bowlby</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/437099.xml">
Erik Erikson</link></scientist>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/26743.xml">
Sigmund Freud</link></scientist>
</person>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/7737804.xml">
Jerome Kagan</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/157854.xml">
Melanie Klein</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/95274.xml">
Jean Piaget</link></philosopher>
</person>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hazan C, Shaver P&#32;(March 1987).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/52/3/511">
Romantic love conceptualized as an attachment process</weblink>". <it>J Pers Soc Psychol</it>&#32;<b>52</b>&#32;(3): 511–24. PMID 3572722.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
Hazan, C., &amp; Shaver, P. R. (1990). Love and work: An attachment theoretical perspective. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 59, 270-280.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Hazan, C., &amp; Shaver, P. R. (1994). Attachment as an organizational framework for research on close relationships. Psychological Inquiry, 5, 1-22.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Fraley, R. C. &amp; Shaver, P. R. (2000). Adult romantic attachment: Theoretical developments, emerging controversies, and unanswered questions. Review of General Psychology, 4, 132-154.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Rholes, W. S. &amp; Simpson, J. A. (2004). Attachment theory: Basic concepts and contemporary questions. In W. S. Rholes and J. A. Simpson (Eds.), Adult Attachment: Theory, Research, and Clinical Implications, pp. 3-14. New York, NY: Guilford Press.</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Bartholomew K, Horowitz LM&#32;(August 1991).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/61/2/226">
Attachment styles among young adults: a test of a four-category model</weblink>". <it>J Pers Soc Psychol</it>&#32;<b>61</b>&#32;(2): 226–44. PMID 1920064.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Pietromonaco PR, Barrett LF&#32;(December 1997).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/73/6/1409">
Working models of attachment and daily social interactions</weblink>". <it>J Pers Soc Psychol</it>&#32;<b>73</b>&#32;(6): 1409–23. PMID 9418285.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
Sable, P., (2000).  Attachment &amp; Adult Psychotherapy.  Northvale NJ: Aaronson.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Johnson, S., (2002).  Emotionally Focused Couples Therapy with Trauma Survivors. NY: Guilford.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Bowlby, J. (1973). Separation: Anxiety &amp; Anger, Volume 2 of Attachment and loss London: Hogarth Press; New York: Basic Books; Harmondsworth: Penguin (1975).</entry>
<entry id="11">
Baldwin, M. W. (1992). Relational schemas and the processing of social information. Psychological Bulletin, 112, 461-484.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Baldwin, M. W. (1997). Relational schemas as a source of if-then self-inference procedures. Review of General Psychology, 1, 326-335.</entry>
<entry id="13">
Baldwin, M. W., Fehr, B., Keedian, E., Seidel, M., &amp; Thompson, D. W. (1993). An exploration of the relational schemata underlying attachment styles: self-report and lexical decision approaches. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/11582751.xml">
Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</link>, 19, 746-754.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Baldwin, M. W., &amp; Fehr, B. (1995). On the Instability of Attachment Style Ratings. Personal Relationships, 2, 247-261.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Baldwin, M. W., Keelan, J. P. R., Fehr, B., Enns, V., &amp; Koh-Rangarajoo, E. (1996). Social-cognitive conceptualization of attachment working models: Availability and accessibility effects. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 71, 94-109.</entry>
<entry id="17">
Bowlby, J. (1980) Loss: Sadness &amp; Depression, in Vol. 3 of Attachment and loss, London: Hogarth Press. New York: Basic Books; Harmondsworth: Penguin (1981).</entry>
<entry id="16">
Baldwin, M. W., &amp; Meunier, J. (1999). The Cued Activation of Attachment Relational Schemas. Social Cognition, 17, 209-227.</entry>
<entry id="19">
Bretherton, I. (1990). Open communication and internal working models: Their role in the development of attachment relationships. In R. A. Thompson (Ed.), Nebraska Symposium on Motivation, 36, 57-113. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.</entry>
<entry id="18">
Bretherton, I. (1985). Attachment theory: Retrospect and prospect. Monographs of the Society for Research in Child Development, 50 (1-2, Serial No. 209).</entry>
<entry id="21">
Main, M., Kaplan, K., &amp; Cassidy, J. (1985). Security in infancy, childhood, and adulthood: A move to the level of representation. Monographs of the Society for Research in Child Development, 50 (1-2, Serial No. 209).</entry>
<entry id="20">
Collins, N., &amp; Read, S. J. (1994). Cognitive representations of attachment: The structure and function of working models. In D. Perlman &amp; K. Bartholomew (Eds.), Advances in personal relationships (Vol. 5, pp. 53-90). London: Jessica Kingsley.</entry>
<entry id="23">
Trinke, S. J., &amp; Bartholomew, K. (1997). Hierarchies of attachment relationships in young adulthood. Journal of Social and Personal Relationships, 14, 603-625.</entry>
<entry id="22">
Pietromonaco, P. R., &amp; Barrett, L. F. (2000). The internal working models concept: What do we really know about the self in relation to others? Review of General Psychology, 4, 155-175.</entry>
<entry id="25">
Overall, N. C., Fletcher, G. J. O., &amp; Friesen, M. D. (2003). Mapping the intimate relationship mind: Comparisons between three models of attachment representations. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/11582751.xml">
Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</link>, 29, 1479-1493.</entry>
<entry id="24">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">La Guardia JG, Ryan RM, Couchman CE, Deci EL&#32;(September 2000).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/79/3/367">
Within-person variation in security of attachment: a self-determination theory perspective on attachment, need fulfillment, and well-being</weblink>". <it>J Pers Soc Psychol</it>&#32;<b>79</b>&#32;(3): 367–84. PMID 10981840.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="27">
Kirkpatrick, L., &amp; Hazen, C. (1994). Attachment styles and close relationships: A four year prospective study. Personal Relationships, 1, 123-142.</entry>
<entry id="26">
Waters, E., Merrick, S., Treboux, D., Crowell, J., &amp; Albersheim, L. (2000). Attachment security in infancy and early adulthood: A twenty-year longitudinal study. Child Development, 71, 684-689.</entry>
<entry id="29">
Scharfe, E., &amp; Bartholomew, K. (1994). Reliability and stability of adult attachment patterns. Personal Relationships, 1, 23-43.</entry>
<entry id="28">
Feeney, J., &amp; Noller, P. (1992). Attachment style and romantic love: Relationship dissolution. Australian Journal of Psychology, 44, 69-74.</entry>
<entry id="31">
Hamilton, C. E. (2000). Continuity and discontinuity of attachment from infancy through adolescence. Child Development, 71, 690-694.</entry>
<entry id="30">
Waters, E., Weinfield, N. S., &amp; Hamilton, C. E. (2000). The stability of attachment styles from infancy to adolescence and early adulthood: General discussion. Child Development, 71, 703-706.</entry>
<entry id="34">
Brennan, K. A., &amp; Shaver, P. R. (1995). Dimensions of adult attachment, affect regulation, and romantic relationship functioning. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/11582751.xml">
Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</link>, 21, 267–283.</entry>
<entry id="35">
Feeney, J. A. (1994). Attachment style, communication patterns and satisfaction across the life cycle of marriage. Personal Relationships, 1, 333–348.</entry>
<entry id="32">
Weinfield, N. S., Sroufe, L. A., &amp; Egelund, B. (2000). Attachment from infancy to early adulthood in a high-risk sample: Continuity, discontinuity, and their correlates. Child Development, 71, 695-702.</entry>
<entry id="33">
Davila, J., Karney, B. R., &amp; Bradbury, T. N. (1999). Attachment change processes in the early years of marriage. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 76, 783-802.</entry>
<entry id="38">
Fuller, T. L., &amp; Fincham, F. D. (1995). Attachment style in married couples: Relation to current marital functioning, stability over time, and method of assessment. Personal Relationships, 2, 17–34.</entry>
<entry id="39">
Lussier, Y., Sabourin, S., &amp; Turgeon, C. (1997). Coping strategies as moderators of the relationship between attachment and marital adjustment. Journal of Social and Personal Relationships, 14, 777–791.</entry>
<entry id="36">
Feeney, J. A. (1996). Attachment, caregiving, and marital satisfaction. Personal Relationships, 3, 401–416.</entry>
<entry id="37">
Feeney, J. A., Noller, P., &amp; Callan, V. J. (1994). Attachment style, communication and satisfaction in the early years of marriage. In K. Bartholomew &amp; D. Perlman (Eds.), Advances in personal relationships: Attachment processes in adulthood (Vol. 5, pp. 269–308). London: Jessica Kingsley.</entry>
<entry id="42">
Senchak, M., &amp; Leonard, K. E. (1992). Attachment styles and marital adjustment among newlywed couples. Journal of Social and Personal Relationships, 9, 51-64.</entry>
<entry id="43">
Keelan, J. P. R., Dion, K. K., &amp; Dion, K. L. (1998). Attachment style and relationship satisfaction: Test of a self-disclosure explanation. Canadian Journal of Behavioural Science, 30, 24–35.</entry>
<entry id="40">
Meyers, S. A., &amp; Landsberger, S. A. (2002). Direct and indirect pathways between adult attachment style and marital satisfaction. Personal Relationships, 9, 159–172.</entry>
<entry id="41">
Collins, N. L., &amp; Read, S. J. (1990). Adult attachment, working models and relationship quality in dating couples. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 58, 644-663.</entry>
<entry id="46">
Cobb, R. J., Davila, J., &amp; Bradbury, T. N. (2001). Attachment security and marital satisfaction: The role of positive perceptions and social support. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/11582751.xml">
Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</link>, 27, 1131-1143.</entry>
<entry id="47">
Simpson, J. A. (1990). Influence of attachment styles on romantic relationships. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 59, 971-980.</entry>
<entry id="44">
Feeney, J. A. (1999). Adult attachment, emotional control, and marital satisfaction. Personal Relationships, 6, 169–185.</entry>
<entry id="45">
Davila, J., Bradbury, T. N., &amp; Fincham, F. (1998). Negative affectivity as a mediator of the association between adult attachment and marital satisfaction. Personal Relationships, 5, 467-484.</entry>
<entry id="51">
Rholes, W. S., Simpson, J. A., &amp; Stevens, J. G. (1998). Attachment orientations, social support, and conflict resolution in close relationships. In W. S. Rholes &amp; J. A. Simpson (Eds.), Attachment Theory and Close Relationships (pp.166-188). New York, NY: Guilford Press.</entry>
<entry id="50">
Davila, J., &amp; Bradbury, T. N. (2001). Attachment insecurity and the distinction between unhappy spouses who do and do not divorce. Journal of Family Psychology, 15, 371-393.</entry>
<entry id="49">
Kirkpatrick, L. A., &amp; Davis, K. E. (1994). Attachment style, gender, and relationship stability: A longitudinal analysis. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 66, 502-512.</entry>
<entry id="48">
Duemmler, S. L., &amp; Kobak, R. (2001). The development of commitment and attachment in dating relationships: attachment security as relationship construct. Journal of Adolescence, 24, 401-415.</entry>
<entry id="55">
Mikulincer, M., Shaver, P. R., &amp; Pereg, D. (2003). Attachment theory and affect regulation: The dynamics, development, and cognitive consequences of attachment-related strategies. Motivation and Emotion, 27, 77-102.</entry>
<entry id="54">
Bowlby, J. (1969/1982) Attachment, Vol. 1 of Attachment and loss. London: Hogarth Press. New York: Basic Books (1982).</entry>
<entry id="53">
Feeney, J. A. &amp; Noller, P. (2004). Attachment and sexuality in close relationships. In J. H. Harvey, A. Wenzel, and S. Sprecher (Eds.), The Handbook of Sexuality in Close Relationships. (pp. 183-201) Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</entry>
<entry id="52">
Anders, S. L., &amp; Tucker, J. S. (2000). Adult attachment style, interpersonal communication competence, and social support. Personal Relationships, 7, 379-389.</entry>
<entry id="59">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Florian V, Mikulincer M, Bucholtz I&#32;(November 1995).&#32;"Effects of adult attachment style on the perception and search for social support". <it>J Psychol</it>&#32;<b>129</b>&#32;(6): 665–76. PMID 7500299.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="58">
Simpson, J. A., Rholes, W. S., &amp; Nelligan, J. S. (1992). Support seeking and support giving within couples in an anxiety provoking situation: The role of attachment styles". <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 62, 434-446.</entry>
<entry id="57">
Mikulincer, M., Florian, V., &amp; Weller, A. (1993). Attachment styles, coping strategies, and post-traumatic psychological distress: The impact of the Gulf War in Israel. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 64, 817-826.</entry>
<entry id="56">
Kobak, R. R., &amp; Sceery, A. (1988). Attachment in late adolescence: Working models, affect regulation, and representations of self and others. Child Development, 59, 135-146.</entry>
<entry id="63">
Mashek, D. J., &amp; Sherman, M. D. (2004). Desiring less closeness with initimate others. In A. Aron and Mashek, D. J. (Eds.), Handbook of Closeness and Intimacy (pp. 343-356). Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</entry>
<entry id="62">
Collins, N. L. &amp; Freeney, B. C. (2004). An Attachment Theory Perspective on Closeness and Intimacy. In D. J. Mashek &amp; A. Aron (Eds.), Handbook of Closeness and Intimacy, pp. 163-188. Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</entry>
<entry id="61">
Bowlby, J. (1988). A secure base. New York: Basic Books.</entry>
<entry id="60">
Asendorpf, J. B., &amp; Wilpers, S. (2000). Attachment security and available support: Closely linked relationship qualities. Journal of Social and Personal Relationships, 17, 115-138.</entry>
<entry id="68">
Sharpsteen, D. J., &amp; Kirkpatrick, L. A. (1997). Romantic jealousy and adult romantic attachment. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/8309381.xml">
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</link>, 72, 627-640.</entry>
<entry id="69">
Buunk, B. P. (1997).Personality, birth order and attachment styles as related to various types of jealousy. Personality and Individual Differences, 23, 997-1006.</entry>
<entry id="70">
Guerrero, L. K. (1998). Attachment-style differences in the experience and expression of romantic jealousy. Personal Relationships, 5, 273-291.</entry>
<entry id="71">
Radecki-Bush, C., Farrell, A. D., &amp; Bush, J. I. (1993). Predicting jealous responses: The influence of adult attachment and depression on threat appraisal. Journal of Social and Personal Relationships, 10, 569-588.</entry>
<entry id="64">
Volling, B. L., McElwain, N. L., &amp; Miller, A. L. (2002). Emotion regulation in context: The jealousy complex between young siblings and its relations with child and family characteristics. Child Development, 73, 581-600.</entry>
<entry id="65">
Hart, S. (2002). Jealousy in 6-month-old infants. Infancy, 3, 395-402.</entry>
<entry id="66">
Hart, S. (2004). When infants lose exclusive maternal attention: Is it jealousy? Infancy, 6, 57-78.</entry>
<entry id="67">
Harris, C.R. (2004). The evolution of jealousy. American Scientist, 92, 62-71.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Bibliography</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Andersson, P. (2006) [https://www.abo.fi/library/aapub/svf_952121677_8_buy.html ''Determinants of Individual Vulnerability to Heroin Addiction – A Psychosocial Study'']. The Doctoral thesis, Åbo Akademi University. ISBN 952-12-1677-8.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cassidy, J., &amp; Shaver, P., (Eds). (1999) <it>Handbook of Attachment: Theory, Research, and Clinical Applications</it>. Guilford Press, NY.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Greenberg, MT, Cicchetti, D., &amp; Cummings, EM., (Eds) (1990) <it>Attachment in the Preschool Years: Theory, Research and Intervention</it> University of Chicago, Chicago.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Greenspan, S. (1993) <it>Infancy and Early Childhood</it>.  Madison, CT: International Universities Press.  ISBN 0-8236-2633-4.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Holmes, J. (1993) <it>John Bowlby and Attachment Theory</it>. Routledge. ISBN 0-415-07730-3.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Holmes, J. (2001) <it>The Search for the Secure Base: Attachment Theory and Psychotherapy</it>. London: Brunner-Routledge. ISBN 1-58391-152-9.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Karen R (1998) <it>Becoming Attached: First Relationships and How They Shape Our Capacity to Love</it>. Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-511501-5.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Parkes, CM, Stevenson-Hinde, J., Marris, P., (Eds.) (1991) <it>Attachment Across The Life Cycle</it> Routledge. NY.  ISBN 0-415-05651-9</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Siegler R., DeLoache, J. &amp; Eisenberg, N. (2003) <it>How Children develop</it>. New York: Worth. ISBN 1-57259-249-4.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.helpguide.org/mental/parenting_bonding_reactive_attachment_disorder.htm">
Parenting: Attachment, Bonding and Reactive Attachment Disorder</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.helpguide.org/mental/relationship_advice_adult_attachment.htm">
Relationship Advice: How Understanding Adult Attachment Can Help</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.web-research-design.net/cgi-bin/crq/crq.pl">
Attachment Questionnaire</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.richardatkins.co.uk/atws">
Details of authors, publications, measures and books on attachment psychology</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bindungsdiagnostik.de">
Attachment Diagnostics (German)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brensgumbyland.com/adconnection_link_page.htm">
A support forum for adults with attachment disorder or attachment related issues.. welcome!</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/884589.xml">
Attachment theory</link></relationship>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Theory</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5343419.xml">
Affectional bond</link></relationship>
 • <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/5761650.xml">
Attachment in adults</link></relationship>
 • <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/5761568.xml">
Attachment in children</link></relationship>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/707323.xml">
Attachment disorder</link> • <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/5761692.xml">
Attachment measures</link></relationship>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/569641.xml">
Attachment parenting</link> • 
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/884589.xml">
Attachment theory</link></relationship>
 • <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/3829592.xml">
Human bonding</link></relationship>
 • <relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/13746790.xml">
Maternal deprivation</link></relationship>
 • <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/910662.xml">
Object relations theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</institution>
</educational_institution>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</school>
</process>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/740176.xml">
Reactive attachment disorder</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Notable Theorists</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/4040297.xml">
Mary Ainsworth</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 • <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/1065890.xml">
John Bowlby</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 • <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/437099.xml">
Erik Erikson</link></scientist>
 • <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/26743.xml">
Sigmund Freud</link></scientist>
</person>
 • <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/839100.xml">
Harry Harlow</link></scientist>
 • <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/7737804.xml">
Jerome Kagan</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/157854.xml">
Melanie Klein</link> • <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/17077.xml">
Konrad Lorenz</link></scientist>
</person>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/7852318.xml">
Tinbergen</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/3989774.xml">
Rene Spitz</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Controversy</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/5885283.xml">
Attachment therapy</link></relationship>
 • <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/3762721.xml">
Candace Newmaker</link></person>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Clinical Applications</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/19654750.xml">
Attachment-based therapy (children)</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/14068386.xml">
Attachment-based psychotherapy</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</relationship>
</article>
