<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:45:50[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<standard  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107260623">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<system_of_measurement  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113577171">
<procedure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101023820">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Common Criteria</title>
<id>57625</id>
<revision>
<id>241993964</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T12:13:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>FlaBot</username>
<id>228773</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Evaluation</category>
<category>ISO standards</category>
<category>CISSP</category>
<category>Computer security procedures</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Common Criteria for Information Technology Security Evaluation</b> (abbreviated as <b>Common Criteria</b> or <b>CC</b>) is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/15402.xml">
international standard</link> (<organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/14934.xml">
ISO</link></organization>
/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/15144.xml">
IEC</link> 15408) for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
computer security</link>. <p>

Common Criteria is based upon a framework in which computer system users can <it>specify</it> their security requirements, vendors can then <it>implement </it> and/or make claims about the security attributes of their products, and testing laboratories can <it>evaluate</it> the products to determine if they actually meet the claims. In other words, Common Criteria provides assurance that the process of specification, implementation and evaluation of a computer security product has been conducted in a rigorous and standard manner.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Key Concepts </st>

<p>

Common Criteria evaluations are performed on computer security products and systems.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Target Of Evaluation (TOE)</b> - the product or system that is the subject of the evaluation.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The evaluation serves to validate claims made about the target. To be of practical use, the evaluation must verify the target's security features. This is done through the following:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/6440859.xml">
Protection Profile</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
 (PP)</b> - a document, typically created by a user or user community, which identifies security requirements relevant to that user for a particular purpose. A PP effectively defines a class of security devices (for example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/59957.xml">
smart card</link>s used to provide <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/59644.xml">
digital signature</link>s, or network <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1362296.xml">
firewalls</link>). Product vendors can choose to implement products that comply with one or more PPs, and have their products evaluated against those PPs. In such a case, a PP may serve as a template for the product's ST (Security Target, as defined below), or the authors of the ST will at least ensure that all requirements in relevant PPs also appear in the target's ST document. Customers looking for particular types of products can focus on those certified against the PP that meets their requirements.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Security Functional Requirements (SFRs)</b> - specify individual security <b>functions</b> which may be provided by a product. The Common Criteria presents a standard catalogue of such functions. For example, an SFR may state <b>how</b> a user acting a particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../519/1841519.xml">
role</link> might be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authenticated</link>. The list of SFRs can vary from one evaluation to the next, even if two targets are the same type of product.  Although Common Criteria does not prescribe any SFRs to be included in an ST, it identifies dependencies where the correct operation of one function (such as the ability to limit access according to roles) is dependent on another (such as the ability to identify individual roles).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/15353784.xml">
Security Target</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
 (ST)</b> - the document that identifies the security <it>properties</it> of the target of evaluation. Each target is evaluated against the SFRs established in its ST, no more and no less. This allows vendors to tailor the evaluation to accurately match the intended capabilities of their product. This means that a network firewall does not have to meet the same functional requirements as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> management system, and that different firewalls may in fact be evaluated against completely different lists of requirements. The ST is usually published so that potential customers may determine the specific security features that have been certified by the evaluation.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The evaluation process also tries to establish the level of confidence that may be placed in the product's security features through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/305224.xml">
quality assurance</link> processes:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Security Assurance Requirements</b> (SARs) - descriptions of the measures taken during development and evaluation of the product to assure compliance with the claimed security functionality. For example, an evaluation may require that all source code is kept in a change management system, or that full functional testing is performed. The Common Criteria provides a catalogue of these, and the requirements may vary from one evaluation to the next. The requirements for particular targets or types of products are documented in the ST and PP, respectively.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/1013680.xml">
Evaluation Assurance Level</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
 (EAL)</b> - the numerical rating describing the depth and rigor of an evaluation. Each EAL corresponds to a package of security assurance requirements (SARs, see above) which covers the complete development of a product, with a given level of strictness. Common Criteria lists seven levels, with EAL&nbsp;1 being the most basic (and therefore cheapest to implement and evaluate) and EAL&nbsp;7 being the most stringent (and most expensive). Normally, an ST or PP author will not select assurance requirements individually but choose one of these packages, possibly 'augmenting' requirements in a few areas with requirements from a higher level. Higher EALs <it>do not</it> necessarily imply "better security", they only mean that the claimed security assurance of the TOE has been more extensively validated.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

So far, most PPs and most evaluated STs/certified products have been for IT components (e.g., firewalls, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>s, smart cards). 
Common Criteria certification is sometimes specified for IT procurement. Other standards containing, e.g, interoperation, system management, user training, supplement CC and other product standards. Examples include the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/11675192.xml">
ISO 17799</link> (Or more properly BS 7799-2, which is now <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/11675192.xml">
ISO/IEC 27002</link>) or the German handbuch.</p>
<p>

Details of cryptographic implementation within the TOE are outside the scope of the CC. Instead, national standards, like <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/885948.xml">
FIPS 140-2</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 give the specifications for cryptographic modules, and various standards specify the cryptographic algorithms in use.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

CC originated out of three standards:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/3568104.xml">
ITSEC</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
 - The European standard, developed in the early 1990s by <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
, the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/21148.xml">
Netherlands</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1048927.xml">
UK</link>. It too was a unification of earlier work, such as the two UK approaches (the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/12884.xml">
CESG</link> UK Evaluation Scheme aimed at the Defence/Intelligence market and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/304272.xml">
DTI</link> Green Book aimed at commercial use), and was adopted by some other countries, e.g. Australia.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/210635.xml">
CTCPEC</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
 - The Canadian standard followed from the US DoD standard, but avoided several problems and was used jointly by evaluators from both the U.S. and Canada. The CTCPEC standard was first published in May 1993.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/6687300.xml">
TCSEC</link> - The United States <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/7279897.xml">
Department of Defense</link></agency>
 DoD 5200.28 Std, called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/60389.xml">
Orange Book</link> and parts of the <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/2207479.xml">
Rainbow Series</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
. The Orange Book originated from Computer Security work including the Ware Report, done by the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/21939.xml">
National Security Agency</link></agency>
 and the National Bureau of Standards (the NBS eventually became <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/21888.xml">
NIST</link>) in the late 1970s and early 1980s. The central thesis of the Orange Book follows from the work done by Dave Bell and Len Lapadula for a set of protection mechanisms.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

CC was produced by unifying these pre-existing standards, predominantly so that companies selling computer products for the government market (mainly for Defence or Intelligence use) would only need to have them evaluated against one set of standards. The CC was developed by the governments of Canada, France, Germany, the Netherlands, the UK, and the U.S.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Common Criteria Testing Organizations </st>
<p>

All Testing Laboratories must comply with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/3768176.xml">
ISO 17025</link>, and Certification Bodies will normally be approved against either ISO/IEC Guide 65 or BS EN 45011. </p>
<p>

The compliance with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/3768176.xml">
ISO 17025</link> is typically demonstrated to a National approval authority:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In Canada, the <body wordnetid="105216365" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/4552879.xml">
Standards Council of Canada</link></natural_object>
</body>
 (SCC) accredits Common Criteria Evaluation Facilities</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In the UK the United Kingdom Accreditation Service (UKAS) accredits Commercial Evaluation Facilities (CLEF)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In the US, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/21888.xml">
National Institute of Standards and Technology</link> (NIST) <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/6467986.xml">
National Voluntary Laboratory Accreditation Program</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (NVLAP) accredits Common Criteria Testing Laboratories (CCTL)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Mutual Recognition Arrangement </st>
<p>

As well as the Common Criteria standard, there is also a sub-treaty level Common Criteria MRA (Mutual Recognition Arrangement), whereby each party thereto recognizes evaluations against the Common Criteria standard done by other parties. Originally signed in 1998 by Canada, France, Germany, the United Kingdom and the United States, Australia and New Zealand joined 1999, followed by Finland, Greece, Israel, Italy, the Netherlands, Norway and Spain in 2000. The Arrangement has since been renamed <b>Common Criteria Recognition Arrangement</b> (<b>CCRA</b>) and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/members.html">
membership continues to expand</weblink>.  Within the CCRA only evaluations up to EAL 4 are mutually recognized (Including augmentation with flaw remediation).  The European countries within the former ITSEC agreement typically recognize higher EALs as well. Evaluations at EAL5 and above tend to involve the security requirements of the host nation's government.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Issues</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Requirements</st>

<p>

Common Criteria does not provide a list of product security requirements or features that products must contain: this follows the approach taken by <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/3568104.xml">
ITSEC</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
, but has been a source of debate to those used to the more prescriptive approach of other earlier standards such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/6687300.xml">
TCSEC</link> and <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/1539324.xml">
FIPS 140</link></activity>
</procedure>
</system_of_measurement>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</standard>
-2.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Value of Certification</st>

<p>

If a product is Common Criteria certified, it doesn't necessarily mean it is completely secure, for example <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
 <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/33941.xml">
Windows 2000</link></version>
 is a certified product of EAL4+, but regular security patches for security vulnerabilities are still published by Microsoft for Windows 2000. This is possible because the process of obtaining a Common Criteria certification allows a vendor to make certain assumptions about the operating environment and the strength of threats, if any, faced by the product in that environment. Based on these assumptions, the claimed security functions of the product are evaluated. Since Microsoft Windows 2000 has been EAL4+ certified, it should only be considered secure in the assumed, specified circumstances, also known as the evaluated configuration, specified by Microsoft.</p>
<p>

Whether you run Microsoft Windows 2000 in the precise evaluated configuration or not, you should apply Microsoft's security patches for the vulnerabilities in Windows 2000 as they continue to appear. If any of these security vulnerabilities are exploitable in the product's evaluated configuration, the product's Common Criteria certification should be voluntarily withdrawn by the vendor.  Alternatively, the vendor should re-evaluate the product to include application of the patches to fix the security vulnerabilities within the evaluated configuration. Failure by the vendor to take either of these steps would result in involuntary withdrawal of the product's certification by the certification body of the country in which the product was evaluated.  </p>
<p>

Microsoft Windows 2000 remains at EAL4+ without including the application of any Microsoft security vulnerability patches in its evaluated configuration. This shows both the limitation and strength of an evaluated configuration.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Criticisms</st>

<p>

In August 2007, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/684896.xml">
Government Computing News (GCN)</link> columnist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/17642273.xml">
William Jackson</link> critically examined Common Criteria methodology and its US implementation by the CCEVS.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> In the column executives from the security industry, researchers, and representatives from NIAP were interviewed. Objections outlined in the article include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Evaluation is a costly process (often measured in hundreds of thousands of US dollars) -- and the vendor's return on that investment is not necessarily a more secure product</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Evaluation focuses primarily on assessing the evaluation documentation, not on the technical correctness or merits of the product itself (for US evaluations at EAL5 and higher, experts from the National Security Agency participate in the analysis)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The effort and time necessary to prepare evaluation evidence and other evaluation-related documentation is so cumbersome that by the time the work is completed, the product in evaluation is generally obsolete</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Industry input, including that from organizations such as the <link>
Common Criteria Vendor's Forum</link>, generally has little impact on the process as a whole</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In a 2006 research paper, computer specialist <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<computer_user wordnetid="109951274" confidence="0.8">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.8">
<engineer wordnetid="109615807" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/68247.xml">
David A. Wheeler</link></causal_agent>
</engineer>
</programmer>
</computer_user>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 suggested that the Common Criteria process discriminates against <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/1721496.xml">
FOSS</link>-centric organizations and development models.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Common Criteria assurance requirements tend to be inspired by the traditional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/33980.xml">
waterfall</link> software development methodology. In contrast, much FOSS software is produced using modern <belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<doctrine wordnetid="105943300" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/639009.xml">
agile</link></doctrine>
</belief>
 paradigms. Although some have argued that both paradigms do not align well<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>, others have attempted to reconcile both paradigms.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Alternative Approaches </st>

<p>

Throughout the lifetime of CC, it has not been universally adopted even by the creator nations, with, in particular, cryptographic approvals being handled separately, such as by the Canadian / US implementation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/1539324.xml">
FIPS-140</link>, and the <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/12884.xml">
CESG</link> Assisted Products Scheme</b> (<b>CAPS</b>)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> in the UK.</p>
<p>

The UK has also produced a number of alternative schemes when the timescales, costs and overheads of mutual recognition have been found to be impeding the operation of the market:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/12884.xml">
CESG</link> <b>System Evaluation</b> (<b>SYSn</b>) and <b>Fast Track Approach</b> (<b>FTA</b>) schemes for assurance of government systems rather than generic products and services, which have now been merged into the <b>CESG Tailored Assurance Service</b> (<b>CTAS</b>) <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/15145052.xml">
CSIA Claims Test Mark</link> (<b>CCT Mark</b>), which is aimed at handling less exhaustive assurance requirements for products and services in a cost and time efficient manner</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gcn.com/print/26_21/44857-1.html">
Under Attack: Common Criteria has loads of critics, but is it getting a bum rap</weblink> Government Computer News, retrieved 2007-12-14</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/oss_software_assurance.pdf">
Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS) and Software Assurance</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
Wäyrynen, J., Bodén, M., and Boström, G., <it>Security Engineering and eXtreme Programming: An Impossible Marriage</it>?</entry>
<entry id="4">
Beznosov, Konstantin and Kruchten, Philippe, <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://konstantin.beznosov.net/professional/doc/papers/Towards_Agile_Security_Assurance--preproceedings_version.pdf">
Towards Agile Security Assurance</weblink></it>, retrieved 2007-12-14</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cesg.gov.uk/site/caps/index.cfm">
CAPS: CESG Assisted Products Scheme</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cesg.gov.uk/site/iacs/index.cfm?menuSelected=3&amp;displayPage=3">
Infosec Assurance and Certification Services (IACS)</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/423866.xml">
Bell-LaPadula model</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/32288.xml">
Usability testing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/467996.xml">
ISO 9241</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
ISO/IEC 18045</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/3585535.xml">
ISO/IEC 27001</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
Semantic web</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/13144608.xml">
Verification and Validation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/6444716.xml">
Information Assurance</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/">
The official website of the Common Criteria Project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.niap-ccevs.org/cc-scheme/cc_docs/">
The Common Criteria standard documents</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.niap-ccevs.org/cc-scheme/">
Compliance evaluation in the United States</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/products.html">
List of Common Criteria evaluated products</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://konstantin.beznosov.net/professional/works/shared/biblio_view.php?bibid=104&amp;tab=home">
Towards Agile Security Assurance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 You may <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://isotc.iso.org/livelink/livelink/fetch/2000/2489/Ittf_Home/PubliclyAvailableStandards.htm">
download ISO/IEC 15408</weblink> for free because it is a publicly available standard.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</procedure>
</system_of_measurement>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</standard>
</article>
