<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:21:35[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<protocol  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106665108">
<direction  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106786629">
<rule  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106652242">
<header>
<title>Key exchange</title>
<id>578092</id>
<revision>
<id>235549992</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-01T08:21:53Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Acdx</username>
<id>721886</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cryptographic protocols</category>
<category>Articles needing sections</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b> should be added to this article or its part, to conform with .</b>
Please discuss this issue on the .</col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Key exchange</b> is any method in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
cryptography</link> by which <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/53039.xml">
cryptographic key</link>s are exchanged between users, allowing use of a cryptographic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>. <p>

If Alice and Bob wish to exchange encrypted messages, each must be equipped to decrypt received messages and to encrypt sent messages. The nature of the information they require to do so depends on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> technique they might use. If they use a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/5225.xml">
code</link>, both will require a copy of the same <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/530786.xml">
codebook</link>. If they use a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/5244.xml">
cipher</link>, they will need appropriate keys. If the cipher is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/53042.xml">
symmetric key cipher</link>, both will need a copy of the same key. If an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
asymmetric key cipher</link> with the public/private key property, both will need the other's public key. </p>
<p>

The <b>key exchange problem</b> is how to exchange whatever keys or other information needed so that no one else can obtain a copy. Traditionally, this required trusted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/551824.xml">
courier</link>s (with or without briefcases handcuffed to their wrists), or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/580297.xml">
diplomatic bag</link>s, or some other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/592935.xml">
secure channel</link>. With the advent of public key / private key cipher algorithms, the encrypting key (aka public key) could be made public, since (at least for high quality algorithms) no one without the decrypting key (aka, the private key) could decrypt the message. </p>
<p>

In principle, then, the only remaining problem was to be sure (or at least confident) that a public key actually belonged to its supposed owner. Because it is possible to '<accomplishment wordnetid="100035189" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<feat wordnetid="100036762" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../209/503209.xml">
spoof</link></feat>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</event>
</accomplishment>
' another's identity in any of several ways, this is not a trivial or easily solved problem, particularly when the two users involved have never met and know nothing about each other.</p>
<p>

In 1976, Whitfield Diffie and Martin Hellman published a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/591994.xml">
cryptographic protocol</link>, (<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/7903.xml">
Diffie-Hellman key exchange</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
), which allows users to establish 'secure channels' on which to exchange keys, even if an Opponent is monitoring that communication channel. However, D-H key exchange did not address the problem of being sure of the actual identity of the person (or 'entity').</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/194112.xml">
Public key infrastructure</link>s have been proposed as a way around this problem of identity authentication. In their most usual implementation, each user applies to a '<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/296370.xml">
certificate authority</link>' for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/223796.xml">
digital certificate</link> which serves for other users as a non-tamperable authentication of identity. Several countries and other jurisdictions have passed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/51913.xml">
legislation</link> or issued regulations encouraging PKIs by giving (more or less) legal effect to these digital certificates. Several commercial firms, and not a few government departments, have established such certificate authorities. <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/319632.xml">
VeriSign</link></company>
 is the most prominent commercial firm. For those new to such things, these arrangements are best thought of as electronic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/21481.xml">
notary</link> endorsements that "this public key belongs to this user". As with notary endorsements, there can be mistakes or misunderstandings in such vouchings. There have been several high profile public failures by assorted certificate authorities. </p>
<p>

At the other end of the conceptual range is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/296356.xml">
web of trust</link> system, which avoids central Certificate Authorities entirely. Each user is responsible for vetting any certificate from another before using that certificate to communicate with, vet digital signatures from, ... the user claimed to be associated with the particular public key in a certificate. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/683446.xml">
PGP</link> (and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/54711.xml">
GPG</link>, an implementation of the <link>
OpenPGP</link> Internet Standard) employ just such a web of trust mechanism. Together they are the most widely used high quality crypto system in the world.</p>
<p>

The problem of key exchange has not yet been solved. In particular, it has not yet been solved for the modern situation of two previously unknown users attempting to communicate electronically, as, for instance, in electronic commerce. Some of the existing work-around designs work, more or less, but are not fully satisfactory. </p>


<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/53039.xml">
Key (cryptography)</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
</article>
