<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:46:58[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Soap</title>
<id>57875</id>
<revision>
<id>244244091</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T22:56:57Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Idioma-bot</username>
<id>2964546</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Salts</category>
<category>Skin care</category>
<category>Soaps</category>
<category>Surfactants</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Decorative_Soaps.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A collection of decorative soaps used for human hygiene purposes. This type of soap is typically found inside <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/14276.xml">
hotel</link>s.
</caption>
</image>

For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/29168.xml">
Soap (disambiguation)</link>.
<p>

<b>Soap</b> is an anionic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/133176.xml">
surfactant</link> used in conjunction with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/33306.xml">
water</link> for washing and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/373677.xml">
cleaning</link> that historically comes in solid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/605211.xml">
bars</link> but also in the form of a thick <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/18993825.xml">
liquid</link>. </p>
<p>

Soap, consisting of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/26826.xml">
sodium</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/155726.xml">
soda ash</link>) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/23055.xml">
potassium</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/56509.xml">
potash</link>) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/1605200.xml">
salt</link>s of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>s is obtained by reacting fat with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/212330.xml">
lye</link> in a process known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/268331.xml">
saponification</link>. The fats are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/14385.xml">
hydrolyzed</link> by the base, yielding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
alkali</link> salts of fatty acids (crude soap) and glycerol. </p>
<p>

Many cleaning agents today are technically not soaps, but <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/92514.xml">
detergent</link>s, which are less expensive and easier to manufacture.</p>

<sec>
<st>
How soap works</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Soapfunction1.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

a diagram of the function of soap
</caption>
</image>

Soaps are useful for cleaning because soap <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/19555.xml">
molecule</link>s attach readily to both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/361038.xml">
nonpolar</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/19555.xml">
molecule</link>s (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
grease</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
oil</link>) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/361038.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Polar+molecules%22])">
polar</link> molecules (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/33306.xml">
water</link>). Although grease will normally adhere to skin or clothing, the soap molecules can attach to it as a "handle" and make it easier to rinse away. Applied to a soiled surface, soapy water effectively holds particles in suspension so the whole of it can be rinsed off with clean water.</p>
<p>

(fatty end)  :CH3-(CH2)n  -  COONa:  (water soluble end)  </p>
<p>

The hydrocarbon ("fatty") portion dissolves dirt and oils, while the ionic end makes it soluble in water. Therefore, it allows water to remove normally-insoluble matter by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/10290.xml">
emulsification</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Soapmaking</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Soap_P1140887.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Handmade soaps sold at a shop in <link>
Hyères</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>

</caption>
</image>

The most popular soapmaking process today is the cold process method, where fats such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link> react with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/57877.xml">
lye</link>. Soapmakers sometimes use the melt and pour process, where a premade soap base is melted and poured in individual molds.  While some people think that this is not really soap-<it>making</it>, the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.soapguild.org/">
Hand Crafted Soap Makers Guild</weblink> does recognize this as a legitimate form of soap making or soap crafting. Some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/1393365.xml">
soaper</link>s also practice other processes, such as the historical hot process, and make special soaps such as clear soap (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/2732767.xml">
glycerin soap</link>), which must be made through the melt and pour process.</p>
<p>

Handmade soap differs from industrial soap in that, usually, an excess of fat is sometimes used to consume the alkali (<it>superfatting</it>), and in that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/172732.xml">
glycerin</link> is not removed leaving a naturally moisturising soap and not pure detergent. Superfatted soap, soap which contains excess fat, is more skin-friendly than industrial soap; though, if not properly formulated, it can leave users with a "greasy" feel to their skin.  Often, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/188678.xml">
emollient</link>s such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/262116.xml">
jojoba</link> oil or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/1347993.xml">
shea butter</link> are added 'at trace' (the point at which the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/268331.xml">
saponification</link> process is sufficiently advanced that the soap has begun to thicken), after most of the oils have saponified, so that they remain unreacted in the finished soap.  Superfatting can also be accomplished through a process called superfat discount, where, instead of putting in extra fats, the soap maker puts in less lye.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Lye</st>
<p>

Reacting fat with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/57877.xml">
sodium hydroxide</link> will produce a hard soap.</p>
<p>

Reacting fat with potassium hydroxide will produce a soap that is either soft or liquid. Historically, the alkali used was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/235343.xml">
potassium hydroxide</link> made from the deliberate burning of vegetation such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/66560.xml">
bracken</link>, or from wood ashes.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fat</st>
<p>

<image width="200px" src="Savon_de_Marseille.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Handicraft made Marseille soap
</caption>
</image>

Soap is derived from either vegetable or animal fats. <it><substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<compound wordnetid="114818238" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<salt wordnetid="115010703" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/305115.xml">
Sodium tallowate</link></salt>
</material>
</part>
</chemical>
</compound>
</substance>
</it>, a common ingredient in many soaps, is derived from <link>
rendered</link> beef fat. Soap can also be made of vegetable oils, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/57561.xml">
palm oil</link>, and the product is typically softer. If soap is made from pure <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link> it may be called Castile soap or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/9397546.xml">
Marseille soap</link>. Castile is also sometimes applied to soaps with a mix of oils, but a high percentage of olive oil.</p>
<p>

An array of oils and butters are used in the process such as olive, coconut, palm, cocoa butter, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/324632.xml">
hemp oil</link> and shea butter to provide different qualities.  For example, olive oil provides mildness in soap; coconut oil provides lots of lather; while coconut and palm oils provide hardness.  Sometimes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/172190.xml">
castor oil</link> can also be used as an ebullient.  Most common, though, is a combination of coconut, palm, and olive oils.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Process</st>
<p>

In both cold-process and hot-process soapmaking, heat may be required for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/268331.xml">
saponification</link>. </p>
<p>

Cold-process soapmaking takes place at a temperature sufficiently above room temperature to ensure the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../648/20648.xml">
liquification</link> of the fat being used, and requires that the lye and fat be kept warm after mixing to ensure that the soap is completely saponified.</p>
<p>

Unlike cold-processed soap, hot-processed soap can be used right away because lye and fat saponify more quickly at the higher temperatures used in hot-process soapmaking.</p>
<p>

Hot-process was used when the purity of lye was unreliable, and can use natural lye solutions such as potash. The main benefit of hot processing is that the exact concentration of the lye solution does not need to be known to perform the process with adequate success.</p>
<p>

Cold-process requires exact measurement of lye to fat using saponification charts to ensure that the finished product is mild and skin-friendly. Saponification charts can also be used in hot-process soapmaking, but are not as necessary as in cold-process.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Hot process</entry>
</list>

In the hot-process method, lye and fat are boiled together at 80&ndash;100 °C until saponification occurs, which the soapmaker can determine by taste (the bright, distinctive taste of lye disappears once all the lye is saponified) or by eye (the experienced eye can tell when gel stage and full saponification have occurred).</p>
<p>

After saponification has occurred, the soap is sometimes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/286262.xml">
precipitated</link> from the solution by adding salt, and the excess liquid drained off.</p>
<p>

The hot, soft soap is then spooned into a mold.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Cold process</entry>
</list>

A cold-process soapmaker first looks up the saponification value of the fats being used on a saponification chart, which is then used to calculate the appropriate amount of lye. Excess unreacted lye in the soap will result in a very high pH and can burn or irritate skin. Not enough lye, and the soap is greasy. Most soap makers formulate their recipes with a 4-10% discount of lye so that all of the lye is reacted and that excess fat is left for skin conditioning benefits.</p>
<p>

The lye is dissolved in water.  Then oils are heated, or melted if they are solid at room temperature.  Once both substances have cooled to approximately 100-110°F (37-43°C), and are no more than 10°F (~5.5°C) apart, they may be combined.  This lye-fat mixture is stirred until "trace" (modern-day amateur soapmakers often use a stick blender to speed this process).  There are varying levels of trace.  Depending on how your additives will affect trace, they may be added at light trace, medium trace or heavy trace.  After much stirring, the mixture turns to the consistency of a thin pudding. </p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/281028.xml">
Essential oil</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/1712211.xml">
fragrance oil</link>s, botanicals, herbs, oatmeal or other additives are added at light trace, just as the mixture starts to thicken.</p>
<p>

The batch is then poured into molds, kept warm with towels or blankets, and left to continue saponification for 18 to 48 hours. Milk soaps are the exception. They do not require insulation. Insulation may cause the milk to burn. During this time, it is normal for the soap to go through a "gel phase" where the opaque soap will turn somewhat transparent for several hours before turning opaque again. The soap will continue to give off heat for many hours after trace.</p>
<p>

After the insulation period the soap is firm enough to be removed from the mold and cut into bars.  At this time, it is safe to use the soap since saponification is complete.  However, cold-process soaps are typically cured and hardened on a drying rack for 2-6 weeks (depending on initial water content) before use.  If using caustic soda it is recommended that the soap is left to cure for at least 4 weeks.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Purification and finishing</st>
<p>

The common process of purifying soap involves removal of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/80207.xml">
sodium chloride</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/57877.xml">
sodium hydroxide</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/172732.xml">
glycerol</link>. These components are removed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/52636.xml">
boiling</link> the crude soap <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/214287.xml">
curd</link>s in water and re-precipitating the soap with salt.</p>
<p>

Most of the water is then removed from the soap. This was traditionally done on a chill roll which produced the soap flakes commonly used in the 1940s and 1950s. This process was superseded by spray dryers and then by vacuum dryers. </p>
<p>

The dry soap (approximately 6-12% moisture) is then compacted into small pellets. These pellets are now ready for soap finishing, the process of converting raw soap pellets into a salable product, usually bars.</p>
<p>

Soap pellets are combined with fragrances and other materials and blended to homogeneity in an amalgamator (mixer). The mass is then discharged from the mixer into a refiner which, by means of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/1204580.xml">
auger</link>, forces the soap through a fine wire screen. From the refiner the soap passes over a roller mill (French milling or hard milling) in a manner similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/1313623.xml">
calendering</link> paper or plastic or to making <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/1217251.xml">
chocolate liquor</link>. The soap is then passed through one or more additional refiners to further plasticize the soap mass. Immediately before extrusion it passes through a vacuum chamber to remove any entrapped air. It is then extruded into a long log or blank, cut to convenient lengths, passed through a metal detector and then stamped into shape in refrigerated tools. The pressed bars are packaged in many ways.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/18994037.xml">
Sand</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/230364.xml">
pumice</link> may be added to produce a  soap. This process is most common in creating soaps used for human hygiene. The scouring agents serve to remove dead skin cells from the surface being cleaned. This process is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/3825580.xml">
exfoliation</link>. Many newer materials are used for exfoliating soaps which are effective but do not have the sharp edges and poor size distribution of pumice.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<ss1>
<st>
Early history</st>

<p>

The earliest recorded evidence of the production of soap-like materials dates back to around 2800 BC in Ancient <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/19720404.xml">
Babylon</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</tract>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</site>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> A formula for soap consisting of water, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
alkali</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/1911560.xml">
cassia</link> oil was written on a Babylonian clay tablet around 2200 BC. </p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/339885.xml">
Ebers papyrus</link> (Egypt, 1550 BC) indicates that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/874.xml">
ancient Egypt</link>ians bathed regularly and combined animal and vegetable oils with alkaline salts to create a soap-like substance. Egyptian documents mention that a soap-like substance was used in the preparation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/38431.xml">
wool</link> for weaving.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Roman history</st>
<p>

It had been reported that a factory producing soap-like substances was found in the ruins of <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/24405.xml">
Pompeii</link></site>
 (AD 79). However, this has proven to be a misinterpretation of the survival of some soapy mineral substance, probably <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/44718.xml">
soapstone</link> at the <link>
Fullonica</link> where it was used for dressing recently cleansed textiles. Unfortunately this error has been repeated widely and can be found in otherwise reputable texts on soap history.  The ancient Romans were generally ignorant of soap's detergent properties, and made use of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/842181.xml">
strigil</link> to scrape dirt and sweat from the body. The word "soap" (Latin <it>sapo</it>) appears first in a European language in <skilled_worker wordnetid="110605985" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<commissioned_naval_officer wordnetid="109943541" confidence="0.8">
<flag_officer wordnetid="110094584" confidence="0.8">
<commissioned_officer wordnetid="109942970" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.8">
<botanist wordnetid="109868270" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<admiral wordnetid="109771204" confidence="0.8">
<serviceman wordnetid="110582746" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<enlisted_person wordnetid="110058777" confidence="0.8">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.8">
<soldier wordnetid="110622053" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/44920.xml">
Pliny the Elder</link></scholar>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</biologist>
</communicator>
</soldier>
</military_officer>
</enlisted_person>
</scientist>
</serviceman>
</admiral>
</intellectual>
</botanist>
</philosopher>
</person>
</commissioned_officer>
</flag_officer>
</commissioned_naval_officer>
</physical_entity>
</skilled_worker>
's <it>Historia Naturalis</it>, which discusses the manufacture of soap from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/212396.xml">
tallow</link> and ashes, but the only use he mentions for it is as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/1086271.xml">
pomade</link> for hair; he mentions rather disapprovingly that among the <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108654360" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<people wordnetid="107942152" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/36545.xml">
Gaul</link></people>
</district>
</group>
</state>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/231549.xml">
Germans</link> men are likelier to use it than women.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>   </p>
<p>

A story encountered in some places claims that soap takes its name from a supposed "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/2062045.xml">
Mount Sapo</link>" where <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/521555.xml">
ancient Romans</link> sacrificed animals.  Rain would send a mix of animal tallow and wood ash down the mountain and into the clay soil on the banks of the <river wordnetid="109411430" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/30359.xml">
Tiber</link></river>
. Eventually, women noticed that it was easier to clean clothes with this "soap".  The location of Mount Sapo is unknown, as is the source of the "ancient Roman legend" to which this tale is typically credited.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.algebralab.org/passage/passage.aspx?file=Chemistry_Soaps.xml">
http://www.algebralab.org/passage/passage.aspx?file=Chemistry_Soaps.xml</weblink>  In fact, the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/17730.xml">
Latin</link></language>
 word <it>sapo</it> simply means "soap"; it was borrowed from a Celtic or Germanic language, and is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/6328.xml">
cognate</link> with Latin <it>sebum</it>, "tallow", which appears in Pliny the Elder's account.  Roman animal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/80329.xml">
sacrifice</link>s usually burned only the bones and inedible entrails of the sacrificed animals; edible meat and fat from the sacrifices were taken by the humans rather than the gods.  Animal sacrifices in the ancient world would not have included enough fat to make much soap.  The legend about Mount Sapo is probably <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/1288.xml">
apocryphal</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Muslim history</st>
<p>

True soaps made from vegetable oils (such as olive oil), aromatic oils (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/29968.xml">
thyme</link> oil) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/57877.xml">
lye</link> (<it>al-Soda al-Kawia</it>) were first produced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/8770201.xml">
Muslim chemists</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/649824.xml">
medieval Islamic world</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The formula for soap used since then hasn't changed. From the beginning of the 7th century, soap was produced in Nablus (West Bank, Palestine), Kufa (Iraq) and Basra (Iraq). Soaps, as we know them today, are descendants of historical Arabian Soaps. Arabian Soap was perfumed and colored, some of the soaps were liquid and others were solid. They also had special soap for shaving. It was sold for 3 Dirhams (0.3 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/247922.xml">
Dinars</link>) a piece in 981 AD. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/24607.xml">
Persian</link> chemist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../209/78209.xml">
Al-Razi</link> wrote a manuscript on recipes for true soap. A recently discovered manuscript from the 13th century details more recipes for soap making; e.g. take some sesame oil, a sprinkle of potash, alkali and some lime, mix them all together and boil. When cooked, they are poured into molds and left to set, leaving hard soap.</p>
<p>

In semi-modern times soap was made by mixing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/188557.xml">
animal fat</link>s with lye. Because of the caustic lye, this was a dangerous procedure (perhaps more dangerous than any present-day home activities) which could result in serious <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/628093.xml">
chemical burn</link>s or even <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/3433.xml">
blindness</link>. Before commercially-produced lye (sodium hydroxide) was commonplace, potash, potassium hydroxide, was produced at home from the ashes of a hardwood fire.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Modern history</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/2060478.xml">
Castile soap</link> was later produced in Europe from the <painting wordnetid="103876519" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/34568.xml">
16th century</link></painting>
.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Palmolive_soap_1922_advertisement_ladies_home_journal.jpeg" type="thumb">
<caption>

1922 magazine advertisement for Palmolive Soap
</caption>
</image>

In modern times, the use of soap has become universal in industrialized nations due to a better understanding of the role of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/147020.xml">
hygiene</link> in reducing the population size of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/24358.xml">
pathogenic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/20377.xml">
microorganisms</link>. Manufactured bar soaps first became available in the late nineteenth century, and advertising campaigns in Europe and the United States helped to increase popular awareness of the relationship between cleanliness and health. </p>
<p>

Rarely, conditions allow for corpses to naturally turn in to a soap-like substance, such as the Soap Lady on exhibit in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/1242709.xml">
Mutter Museum</link>.</p>
<p>

<image width="220px" src="Azul_e_Branco.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/11040667.xml">
Azul e Branco Soap</link>) - A bar of blue-white offenbach soap
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Commercial soap production</st>
<p>

Until the <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/14914.xml">
Industrial Revolution</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
, soap-making was done on a small scale and the product was rough. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<inventor wordnetid="110214637" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/12295039.xml">
Andrew Pears</link></creator>
</inventor>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 started making a high-quality, transparent soap in 1789 in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/17867.xml">
London</link></village>
. With his grandson, Francis Pears, they opened a factory in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/94126.xml">
Isleworth</link></site>
 in 1862. <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/9234145.xml">
William Gossage</link></scientist>
 produced low-price good quality soap from the 1850s. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/8329051.xml">
Robert Spear Hudson</link> began manufacturing a soap powder in 1837, initially by grinding the soap with a mortar and pestle. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/1307869.xml">
William Hesketh Lever</link> and his brother, James, bought a small soap works in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/411738.xml">
Warrington</link></village>
 in 1885 and founded what is still one of the largest soap businesses, now called <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/240220.xml">
Unilever</link></company>
. These soap businesses were among the first to employ large scale <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/2861.xml">
advertising</link> campaigns.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

General</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/591668.xml">
Saponin</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/3502066.xml">
Unsaponifiable</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/1393365.xml">
Soaper</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/2732767.xml">
Glycerin soap</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/2099350.xml">
Shikakai</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/9397546.xml">
Marseille soap</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/2060478.xml">
Castile soap</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Techniques for making new soap from existing soap</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/4047137.xml">
rebatching</link> <it>also known as French milled soap or Triple-milled soap''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/2498189.xml">
melt and pour</link></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Garzena, Patrizia - Tadiello, Marina (2004). Soap Naturally - Ingredients, methods and recipes for natural handmade soap. Programmer Publishing. ISBN 978-0-9756764-0-0.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

| cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" class=" multicol" style="background:transparent; width:100%;"</p>
<p>

| width="" align="left" valign="top" |
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sdahq.org/cleaning/history/">
Soap History</weblink> The Soap and Detergent Association</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pharmj.com/Editorial/19991218/articles/soap.html">
A short history of soap</weblink> The Pharmaceutical Journal</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://candleandsoap.about.com">
Information about soap-making - history, recipes, techniques</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uduko.com/topic_detail/details/29">
Link collection on how to make soap at home</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
