<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:19:53[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Gene prediction</title>
<id>579390</id>
<revision>
<id>232624324</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-18T05:08:27Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SpBot</username>
<id>7016748</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Mathematical biology</category>
<category>Bioinformatics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Gene finding</b> typically refers to the area of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/149353.xml">
computational biology</link> that is concerned with algorithmically identifying stretches of sequence, usually <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/12388.xml">
genomic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
DNA</link>, that are biologically functional. This especially includes protein-coding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/4250553.xml">
gene</link>s, but may also include other functional elements such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/196493.xml">
RNA gene</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/240060.xml">
regulatory regions</link>. Gene finding is one of the first and most important steps in understanding the genome of a species once it has been <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/28615.xml">
sequenced</link></method>
</know-how>
.<p>

In its earliest days, "gene finding" was based on painstaking experimentation on living cells and organisms. Statistical analysis of the rates of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/2631477.xml">
homologous recombination</link> of several different genes could determine their order on a certain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/6438.xml">
chromosome</link>, and information from many such experiments could be combined to create a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/274192.xml">
genetic map</link> specifying the rough location of known genes relative to each other. Today, with comprehensive genome sequence and powerful computational resources at the disposal of the research community, gene finding has been redefined as a largely computational problem.</p>
<p>

Determining that a sequence <it>is functional</it> should be distinguished from determining <it>the function</it> of the gene or its product. The latter still demands <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../187/15187.xml">
in vivo</link></it> experimentation through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/89242.xml">
gene knockout</link> and other assays, although frontiers of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link> research are making it increasingly possible to predict the function of a gene based on its sequence alone.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Extrinsic Approaches </st>

<p>

In extrinsic (or evidence-based) gene finding systems, the target genome is searched for sequences that are similar to extrinsic evidence in the form of the known sequence of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/20232.xml">
messenger RNA</link> (mRNA) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link> product. Given an mRNA sequence, it is trivial to derive a unique genomic DNA sequence from which it had to have been <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../544/167544.xml">
transcribed</link>. Given a protein sequence, a  family of possible coding DNA sequences can be derived by reverse translation of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/12385.xml">
genetic code</link>. Once candidate DNA sequences have been determined, it is a relatively straightforward algorithmic problem to efficiently search a target genome for matches, complete or partial, and exact or inexact. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/363695.xml">
BLAST</link> is a widely used system designed for this purpose.</p>
<p>

A high degree of similarity to a known messenger RNA or protein product is strong evidence that a region of a target genome is a protein-coding gene. However, to apply this approach systemically requires extensive sequencing of mRNA and protein products. Not only is this expensive, but in complex organisms, only a subset of all genes in the organism's genome are expressed at any given time, meaning that extrinsic evidence for many genes is not readily accessible in any single cell culture. Thus, in order to collect extrinsic evidence for most or all of the genes in a complex organism, many hundreds or thousands of different cell types must be studied, which itself presents further difficulties. For example, some human genes may be expressed only during development as an embryo or fetus, which might be difficult to study for ethical reasons.</p>
<p>

Despite these difficulties, extensive transcript and protein sequence databases have been generated for human as well as other important model organisms in biology, such as mice and yeast. For example, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/15179244.xml">
RefSeq</link> database contains transcript and protein sequence from many different species, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/2039930.xml">
Ensembl</link> system comprehensively maps this evidence to human and several other genomes. It is, however, likely that these databases are both incomplete and contain small but significant amounts of erroneous data..</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 <it>Ab Initio</it> Approaches </st>

<p>

Because of the inherent expense and difficulty in obtaining extrinsic evidence for many genes, it is also necessary to resort to <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/373769.xml">
ab initio</link></it> gene finding, in which <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/55170.xml">
genomic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/331535.xml">
DNA sequence</link> alone is systematically searched for certain tell-tale signs of protein-coding genes.  These signs can be broadly categorized as either <it>signals</it>, specific sequences that indicate the presence of a gene nearby, or <it>content</it>, statistical properties of protein-coding sequence itself. <it>Ab initio</it> gene finding might be more accurately characterized as gene <it>prediction</it>, since extrinsic evidence is generally required to  conclusively establish that a putative gene is functional.</p>
<p>

In the genomes of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/19172225.xml">
prokaryotes</link>, genes have specific and relatively well-understood <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/24888.xml">
promoter</link> sequences (signals), such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/576246.xml">
Pribnow box</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/31474.xml">
transcription factor</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/529613.xml">
binding site</link>s, which are easy to systematically identify. Also, the sequence coding for a protein occurs as one contiguous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/1174560.xml">
open reading frame</link> (ORF), which is typically many hundred or thousands of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/4292.xml">
base pair</link>s long. The statistics of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/28639.xml">
stop codon</link>s are such that even finding an open reading frame of this length is a fairly informative sign. (Since 3 of the 64 possible codons in the genetic code are stop codons, one would expect a stop codon approximately every 20-25 codons, or 60-75 base pairs, in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/48256.xml">
random sequence</link>.) Furthermore, protein-coding DNA has certain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/821728.xml">
periodicities</link> and other statistical properties that are easy to detect in sequence of this length. These characteristics make prokaryotic gene finding relatively straightforward, and well-designed systems are able to achieve high levels of accuracy. </p>
<p>

<it>Ab initio</it> gene finding in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/19172475.xml">
eukaryotes</link>, especially complex organisms like humans, is considerably more challenging for several reasons. First, the promoter and other regulatory signals in these genomes are more complex and less well-understood than in prokaryotes, making them more difficult to reliably recognize. Two classic examples of signals identified by eukaryotic gene finders are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/198952.xml">
CpG island</link>s and binding sites for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/616901.xml">
poly(A) tail</link>. </p>
<p>

Second, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/53512.xml">
splicing</link> mechanisms employed by eukaryotic cells mean that a particular protein-coding sequence in the genome is divided into several parts (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/10238.xml">
exons</link>), separated by non-coding sequences (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/15343.xml">
introns</link>). (Splice sites are themselves another signal that eukaryotic gene finders are often designed to identify.) A typical protein-coding gene in humans might be divided into a dozen exons, each less than two hundred base pairs in length, and some as short as twenty to thirty. It is therefore much more difficult to detect periodicities and other known content properties of protein-coding DNA in eukaryotes.</p>
<p>

Advanced gene finders for both prokaryotic and eukaryotic genomes typically use complex <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/27576.xml">
probabilistic model</link>s, such as <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/98770.xml">
Hidden Markov Models</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, in order to combine information from a variety of different signal and content measurements. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/1854663.xml">
GLIMMER</link> system is a widely used and highly accurate gene finder for prokaryotes. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/14771927.xml">
GeneMark</link> is another popular approach. Eukaryotic <it>ab initio</it> gene finders, by comparison, have achieved only limited success; notable examples are the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/18089057.xml">
GENSCAN</link> and <link>
geneid</link> programs. A few programs like CONTRAST also use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link> approaches like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/65309.xml">
support vector machines</link> for successful gene prediction.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Other Signals</st>
<p>

Among the derived signals used for prediction are statistics resulting from the sub-sequence statistics like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/10573305.xml">
k-mer</link> statistics, <mathematical_relation wordnetid="113783581" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<operator wordnetid="113786413" confidence="0.8">
<function wordnetid="113783816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/52247.xml">
Fourier transform</link></function>
</operator>
</concept>
</idea>
</mathematical_relation>
 of a pseudo-number-coded DNA, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/9131931.xml">
Z-curve</link> parameters and certain run features.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

It has been suggested that signals other than those directly detectable in sequences may improve gene prediction. For example, the role of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/28691.xml">
secondary structure</link> in the identification of regulatory motifs has been reported.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> In addition, it has been suggested that RNA secondary structure prediction helps splice site prediction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Comparative Genomics Approaches </st>

<p>

As the entire genomes of many different species are sequenced, a promising direction in current research on gene finding is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/917868.xml">
comparative genomics</link> approach. This is based on the principle that the forces of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/21147.xml">
natural selection</link> cause genes and other functional elements undergo mutation at a slower rate than the rest of the genome, since mutations in functional elements are more likely to negatively impact the organism than mutations elsewhere. Genes can thus be detected by comparing the genomes of related species to detect this evolutionary pressure for conservation. This approach was first applied to the mouse and human genomes, using programs such as SLAM, SGP and Twinscan/N-SCAN.</p>
<p>

Comparative gene finding can also be used to project high quality annotations from one genome to another. Notable examples include Projector, GeneWise and GeneMapper. Such techniques now play a central role in the annotation of all genomes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.genefinding.org</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.binf.ku.dk/users/krogh/genefinding.html</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.swbic.org/links/1.4.3.2.php</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://bio.math.berkeley.edu/slam/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nslij-genetics.org/gene/">
Bibliography on computational gene recognition by Wentian Li</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://genome.imim.es/software/geneid/">
geneid</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://genome.imim.es/software/sgp2/">
SGP2</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://cbcb.umd.edu/software/glimmer</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://cbcb.umd.edu/software/GlimmerHMM</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://bio.math.berkeley.edu/genemapper/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.genomethreader.org</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://genes.mit.edu/GENSCAN.html">
GENSCAN</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mblab.wustl.edu/software/twinscan/">
Twinscan/N-SCAN</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scfbio-iitd.res.in/research/genepredictor.htm">
CHEMGENOME</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://opal.biology.gatech.edu/GeneMark/">
GeneMark</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cebitec.uni-bielefeld.de/groups/brf/software/gismo/">
Gismo</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Saeys Y, Rouzé P, Van de Peer Y&#32;(2007).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/23/4/414">
In search of the small ones: improved prediction of short exons in vertebrates, plants, fungi and protists</weblink>". <it>Bioinformatics</it>&#32;<b>23</b>&#32;(4): 414–420. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fbioinformatics%2Fbtl639">
10.1093/bioinformatics/btl639</weblink>. PMID 17204465.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hiller M, Pudimat R, Busch A, Backofen R&#32;(2006).&#32;"Using RNA secondary structures to guide sequence motif finding towards single-stranded regions". <it>Nucleic Acids Res</it>&#32;<b>34</b>&#32;(17): e117. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fnar%2Fgkl544">
10.1093/nar/gkl544</weblink>. PMID 16987907. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16987907">
 16987907</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Patterson DJ, Yasuhara K, Ruzzo WL&#32;(2002).&#32;"Pre-mRNA secondary structure prediction aids splice site prediction". <it>Pac Symp Biocomput</it>: 223–234. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=11928478">
 11928478</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Marashi SA, Goodarzi H, Sadeghi M, Eslahchi C, Pezeshk H&#32;(2006).&#32;"Importance of RNA secondary structure information for yeast donor and acceptor splice site predictions by neural networks". <it>Comput Biol Chem</it>&#32;<b>30</b>&#32;(1): 50–57. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.compbiolchem.2005.10.009">
10.1016/j.compbiolchem.2005.10.009</weblink>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16386465">
 16386465</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Marashi SA, Eslahchi C, Pezeshk H, Sadeghi M&#32;(2006).&#32;"Impact of RNA structure on the prediction of donor and acceptor splice sites". <it>BMC Bioinformatics</it>&#32;<b>7</b>: 297. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186%2F1471-2105-7-297">
10.1186/1471-2105-7-297</weblink>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/559212.xml">
Entrez PubMed</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16772025">
 16772025</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
Rogic, S (2006). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.ubc.ca/grads/resources/thesis/Nov06/Rogic_Sanja.pdf">
The role of pre-mRNA secondary structure in gene splicing in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</weblink>". <it>PhD Dissertation, University of British Columbia</it>.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/55170.xml">
Genomics</link>topics</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/323792.xml">
Genome project</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/2606560.xml">
Paleopolyploidy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../087/61087.xml">
Glycomics</link>&nbsp;·  <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/5219699.xml">
Human Genome Project</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/55172.xml">
Proteomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/1029211.xml">
Metabolomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/5168909.xml">
Chemogenomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/303101.xml">
Structural genomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/1889064.xml">
Pharmacogenetics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/1004486.xml">
Pharmacogenomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/1677333.xml">
Toxicogenomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/2571276.xml">
Computational genomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/575697.xml">
Cheminformatics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/467899.xml">
Systems biology</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
Major subfields of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biology</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/674.xml">
Anatomy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/2787.xml">
Astrobiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/3954.xml">
Biochemistry</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
Bioinformatics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/3878.xml">
Biostatistics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/4183.xml">
Botany</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/6339.xml">
Cell biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/56566.xml">
Chronobiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/8449.xml">
Developmental biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/9630.xml">
Ecology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/66997.xml">
Epidemiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/418101.xml">
Evolutionary biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/12266.xml">
Genetics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/55170.xml">
Genomics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/411951.xml">
Human biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/14959.xml">
Immunology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/20021.xml">
Marine biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/19909.xml">
Microbiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/19200.xml">
Molecular biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/21245.xml">
Neuroscience</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
Nutrition</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/19179706.xml">
Origin of life</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/23084.xml">
Paleontology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/383854.xml">
Parasitology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/48791.xml">
Pathology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/23597.xml">
Physiology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/467899.xml">
Systems biology</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/3036154.xml">
Taxonomy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/34413.xml">
Zoology</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>






</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
