<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:19:52[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<procedure  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="101023820">
<header>
<title>Episodic memory</title>
<id>579359</id>
<revision>
<id>244344004</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T10:30:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Kurohone</username>
<id>36760</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Memory processes</category>
<category>Neurology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Episodic memory</b> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/18844.xml">
memory</link> of unique personal experiences (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/9451.xml">
event</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../012/30012.xml">
time</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/586851.xml">
place</link>s, associated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/10406.xml">
emotion</link>s, and other conception-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/243391.xml">
knowledge</link>) that can be put in language. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/534400.xml">
Semantic</link> and episodic memory together make up the category of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/8295.xml">
declarative memory</link>, which is one of the two major divisions in memory. The counterpart to declarative, or explicit memory, is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/23730.xml">
procedural memory</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/527695.xml">
implicit memory</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<sec>
<st>
 Cognitive neuroscience </st>
<p>

The formation of new episodic memories requires the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/466322.xml">
medial temporal lobe</link>, a structure that includes the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml">
hippocampus</link>. Without the medial temporal lobe, one is able to form new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/23730.xml">
procedural memories</link> (such as playing the piano) but cannot remember the events during which they happened. See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Role+in+general+memory%22])">
the hippocampus and memory</link>.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/1967493.xml">
prefrontal cortex</link> (and in particular the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/3665897.xml">
left hemisphere</link>) is also involved in the formation of new episodic memories (also known as episodic encoding). Patients with damage to the prefrontal cortex can learn new information, but tend to do so in a disordered fashion. For example, they might show normal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/1208543.xml">
recognition</link> of an object they had seen in the past, but fail to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/236809.xml">
recollect</link> when or where it had been viewed (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=2797412&amp;query_hl=24">
Janowsky et al., 1989</weblink>). Some researchers believe that the prefrontal cortex helps organize information for more efficient storage, drawing upon its role in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/3704475.xml">
executive function</link>. Others believe that the prefrontal cortex underlies <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantic</link> strategies which enhance encoding, such as thinking about the meaning the study material or rehearsing it in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/33912.xml">
working memory</link> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=9448258&amp;query_hl=29">
Gabrieli et al., 1998</weblink>).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
The hippocampus's role in memory storage</st>
<p>

Researchers do not agree about how long episodic memories are stored in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml">
hippocampus</link>. Some researchers believe that episodic memories always rely on the hippocampus. Others believe the hippocampus only stores episodic memories for a short time, after which the memories are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/19703.xml">
consolidated</link> to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/487922.xml">
neocortex</link>. The latter view is strengthened by recent evidence that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/740746.xml">
neurogenesis</link> in the adult hippocampus may ease the removal of old memories and increase the efficiency of forming new memories (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15157417&amp;itool=iconabstr">
Deisseroth et al 2004</weblink>).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Relationship to semantic memory</st>
<p>

Episodic memory is thought of as being a "one-shot" learning mechanism. You only need one exposure to an episode to remember it.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/534400.xml">
Semantic memory</link>, on the other hand, can take into consideration multiple exposures to each referent - the semantic representation is updated on each exposure.</p>
<p>

Episodic memory can be thought of as a "map" that ties together items in semantic memory. For example, semantic memory will tell you what a "dog" looks and sounds like. All episodic memories concerning your dog will reference this single semantic representation of "dog" and, likewise, all new experiences with your dog will modify your single semantic representation of your dog.</p>
<p>

Some researchers believe that episodic memories are converted from episodic into semantic memories over time. In this process, most of the episodic information about a particular event is generalized and the context of the specific events is lost. One modification of this view is that episodic memories which are recalled often are remembered as a kind of monologue. If you tell and re-tell a story repeatedly, you may feel that you no longer remember the <it>event</it>, but that what you're recalling is a kind of pre-written story.</p>
<p>

Others believe that you always remember episodic memories <it>as</it> episodic memories. Of course, episodic memories do inform semantic knowledge and episodic memories are reliant upon semantic knowledge. The point is that some people do not believe that all episodic memories will inevitably distill away into semantic memory.</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Age differences</st>
<p>

Activation of specific brain areas (mostly the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml">
hippocampus</link>) seems to be different between young and older people upon episodic memory retrieval, as shown by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=12805116">
Maguire and Frith 2003</weblink>. Older people tend to activate both left and right <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml">
hippocampus</link>, while young people activate only the left one. For more information, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/4402098.xml">
aging and memory</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Relationship to emotion</st>
<p>

The relationship between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/4748184.xml">
emotion and memory</link> is complex, but generally, emotion tends to increase the likelihood that an event will be remembered later and that it will be remembered vividly.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/250199.xml">
Flashbulb memory</link> is one example of this.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Pharmacological enhancement</st>
<p>

In healthy adults, longterm visual episodic memory can be enhanced specifically<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> through administration of the Acetylcholine esterase inhibitor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="109190918" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/730754.xml">
Donepezil</link></agent>
</causal_agent>
</physical_entity>
, whereas verbal episodic memory can be improved in persons with the val/val genotype of the val158met polymorphism through administration of the CNS penetrant specific <single_nucleotide_polymorphism wordnetid="111493452" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/620616.xml">
 catecholamine-O-methyltransferase</link></single_nucleotide_polymorphism>
 inhibitor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<inhibitor wordnetid="114724436" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="109190918" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/3295261.xml">
Tolcapone</link></agent>
</inhibitor>
</causal_agent>
</substance>
</physical_entity>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Furthermore, episodic memory is enhanced through <link>
AZD3480</link>  a selective agonist at the neuronal alpha4beta2 nicotinic receptor, which is developed by the company Targacept.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Currently, there are several other products developed by several companies - including new catecholamine-O-methyltransferase inhibitors with fewer side effects - that aim for improving episodic memory.  A recent placebo controlled study of found that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/8807.xml">
DHEA</link>, which is a functional cortisol antagonist, improves episodic memory in healthy young men (Alhaj et al 2006)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Damage</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 One study suggests that there may be selective damage to the limbic-prefrontal episodic memory system in some people with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/25.xml">
autism</link> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=14584570&amp;query_hl=3&amp;itool=pubmed_docsum">
Ben Shalom, 1993</weblink>). Another study points to evidence of autistic deficits in the episodic or self-conscious memory of personally experienced events (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bu.edu/anatneuro/dcn/researchers_and_students/publications/self_ordered_pointing_final.pdf">
Joseph et al., 2003</weblink>).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The label "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/234950.xml">
Amnesia</link>" is most often given to patients with deficits in episodic memory.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/18914017.xml">
Alzheimer's Disease</link> tends to damage the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/53948.xml">
hippocampus</link> before other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/3717.xml">
brain</link> areas. This means that AD patients are often classed as amnesics.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A rare type of shell-fish poisoning called <pathological_state wordnetid="114051917" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<illness wordnetid="114061805" confidence="0.8">
<happening wordnetid="107283608" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<emergency wordnetid="107417405" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<crisis wordnetid="107417644" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<juncture wordnetid="107416714" confidence="0.8">
<ill_health wordnetid="114052046" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/5040533.xml">
Amnesic shellfish poisoning</link></ill_health>
</juncture>
</psychological_feature>
</crisis>
</physical_condition>
</emergency>
</state>
</event>
</happening>
</illness>
</condition>
</pathological_state>
 or "ASP" quite effectively and irreversibly damages the hippocampus, rendering one amnesic.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/332008.xml">
Korsakoff's syndrome</link></disease>
 is caused by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/30500.xml">
thiamin (vitamin B1)</link> deficiency, a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/258979.xml">
malnutrition</link> which can be precipitated by overconsumption of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/18948043.xml">
alcoholic beverage</link>s compared to other foods.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
In animals</st>

<p>

In 1997, there was little evidence for episodic memory outside of humans. This is probably due to the difficulty in testing for it in animals. To meet the criteria of episodic memory, as espoused by Tulving (1983), evidence of conscious recollection must be provided. But demonstrating episodic memory in the absence of language, and therefore in non-human animals, is impossible because there are no agreed non-linguistic behavioural indicators of conscious experience (Griffiths et al., 1999).</p>
<p>

Clayton &amp; Dickinson (1998) were the first to provide evidence that animals may possess episodic memory. They demonstrated that <bird wordnetid="101503061" confidence="0.8">
<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/214059.xml">
Western Scrub-jays</link></animal>
</vertebrate>
</chordate>
</bird>
 (<it>Aphelocoma californica</it>) remember where they cached different food types and discriminately recovered them, depending on the perishability of the item and the amount of time that elapsed since caching. Thus, scrub-jays appear to remember the ‘what-where-and-when’ of specific caching events in the past. Clayton &amp; Dickinson (1998) argued that such performance met the behavioural criteria for episodic memory. However, because the study did not address the phenomenological aspects of episodic memory, the authors referred to this ability as “episodic-like” memory.</p>
<p>

According to a study done by the University of Edinburgh in 2006 hummingbirds are the first animal to demonstrate two aspects of episodic memory - the ability to recall where certain flowers were located and how recently they were visited. Scientists tracked how often hummingbirds visited eight artificial flowers filled with a sucrose solution in the birds' feeding grounds. They refilled half the flowers at 10 minute intervals and the other half 20 minutes after they had been emptied. The birds' return to the flowers matched the refill schedules: flowers refilled at 10-minute intervals were visited sooner. "To our knowledge, this is the first demonstration that animals in the wild can remember both the locations of food sources and when they visited them," said Susan Healy, of the University of Edinburgh.</p>
<p>

Other studies have demonstrated this episodic-like memory in other animal species, which have brains more similar to humans. For example, Kart-Teke and colleagues have demonstrated rats' preference for items it sees which is dependent on what it saw, where it saw it and when it saw it (Kart-Teke et al, 2006). In addition, studies by Eacott and colleagues (Eacott et al, 2005) have shown rats can recall (remember without any cueing influences) what they saw and where depending on which past situation they are being asked to remember.</p>
<p>

Nonetheless, some scholars remain cautious about comparisons to human episodic memory (Suddendorf &amp; Busby, 2003). Purported episodic-like memory often seems fixed to a particular domain or could be explained in terms of procedural or semantic memory. The problem may be better tractable by studying episodic memory's adaptive counterpart: the capacity to flexibly imagine future events. Suddendorf (2006) argues that the emergence of the human capacity to travel mentally to past and future events may have been a prime mover in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/2556665.xml">
hominin</link> evolution.</p>
<p>

A recent experiment addressed one of Suddendorf and Busby (2003)'s specific criticisms (the Bischof-Köhler hypothesis, which states that nonhuman animals can only take actions based on immediate needs, as opposed to future needs<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>). Correia and colleagues demonstrated that Western scrub-jays can selectively cache different types of foods depending on which type of food they will desire at a future time,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> offering strong evidence against the Bischof-Köhler hypothesis by demonstrating that scrub-jays can flexibly adjust their behavior based on past experience of desiring a particular food.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Autobiographical vs. episodic memory </st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/3003160.xml">
Autobiographical memories</link> are memories of events that happened in the past. It is currently unknown if autobiographical memories are the same as episodic memories or if the autobiographical memories become converted to semantic memories with time.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Neural network models</st>
<p>

Episodic memories are stored in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/9054429.xml">
autoassociative neural network</link>s. An early model for episodic memory is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/1170097.xml">
Hopfield network</link> developed by John Hopfield in 1982. More refined models have later been developed.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://alicekim.ca/tulving.htm">
The Works of Endel Tulving - free access to papers and book chapters</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Deisseroth K, Singla S, Toda H, Monje M, Palmer TD, Malenka RC&#32;(2004).&#32;"Excitation-neurogenesis coupling in adult neural stem/progenitor cells". <it>Neuron</it>&#32;<b>42</b>&#32;(4): 535–52. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0896-6273%2804%2900266-1">
10.1016/S0896-6273(04)00266-1</weblink>. PMID 15157417.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tulving, E. (1972). Episodic and semantic memory. In E. Tulving &amp; W. Donaldson (Eds.), Organization of memory, (pp. 381-403). New York: Academic Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tulving, E. (1983). Elements of Episodic Memory. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Tulving E&#32;(2002).&#32;"Episodic memory: from mind to brain". <it>Annual review of psychology</it>&#32;<b>53</b>: 1–25. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146%2Fannurev.psych.53.100901.135114">
10.1146/annurev.psych.53.100901.135114</weblink>. PMID 11752477.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Griffiths D, Dickinson A, Clayton N&#32;(1999).&#32;"Episodic memory: what can animals remember about their past?"&#32;<b>3</b>&#32;(2): 74–80. PMID 10234230.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Clayton NS, Dickinson A&#32;(1998).&#32;"Episodic-like memory during cache recovery by scrub jays". <it>Nature</it>&#32;<b>395</b>&#32;(6699): 272–4. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038%2F26216">
10.1038/26216</weblink>. PMID 9751053.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Kart-Teke E, De Souza Silva MA, Huston JP, Dere E&#32;(2006).&#32;"Wistar rats show episodic-like memory for unique experiences". <it>Neurobiology of learning and memory</it>&#32;<b>85</b>&#32;(2): 173–82. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.nlm.2005.10.002">
10.1016/j.nlm.2005.10.002</weblink>. PMID 16290193.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Eacott MJ, Easton A, Zinkivskay A&#32;(2005).&#32;"Recollection in an episodic-like memory task in the rat". <it>Learn. Mem.</it>&#32;<b>12</b>&#32;(3): 221–3. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101%2Flm.92505">
10.1101/lm.92505</weblink>. PMID 15897259.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Suddendorf T, Busby J&#32;(2003).&#32;"Mental time travel in animals?". <it>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</it>&#32;<b>7</b>: 391–396. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS1364-6613%2803%2900187-6">
10.1016/S1364-6613(03)00187-6</weblink>. PMID 12963469.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Suddendorf T&#32;(2006).&#32;"Foresight and evolution of the human mind". <it>Science</it>&#32;<b>312</b>: 1006–1007. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126%2Fscience.1129217">
10.1126/science.1129217</weblink>. PMID 16709773.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Tulving, E. (1984). Precis of Elements of Episodic Memory. Behavioural and Brain Sciences, 7, 223 – 268.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=17433127">
Cholinergic enhancement of episodic memory in healthy young adults - Psychopharmacology vol. 182, pages 170-179</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Db=pubmed&amp;Cmd=ShowDetailView&amp;TermToSearch=17063156&amp;ordinalpos=11">
Tolcapone improves cognition and cortical information processing in normal human subjects -Neuropsychopharmacology 2007 May</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Db=pubmed&amp;Cmd=ShowDetailView&amp;TermToSearch=17225162">
Effects of TC-1734 (AZD3480), a selective neuronal nicotinic receptor agonist, on cognitive performance and the EEG of young healthy male volunteers - Psychopharmacology, May 2007</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
Alhaj HA, Massey AE, McAllister-Williams RH. Effects of DHEA administration on episodic memory, cortisol and mood in healthy young men: a double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Psychopharmacology (2006) 188: 541–551 DOI 10.1007/s00213-005-0136-y</entry>
<entry id="6">
Bischof-Kohler D. 1985. Zur Phylogenese menschticher Motivation [On the phylogeny of human motivation]. In L. H. Eckensberger &amp; E. D. Lantermann (Eds.), Emotion und Reflexivitat (pp. 3-47). Vienna: Urban &amp; Schwarzenberg.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Correia SP, Dickinson A, Clayton NS. 2007. Western scrub-jays anticipate future needs independently of their current motivational state. Curr Biol. 17(10):856-61.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/374304.xml">
Neurophysiology</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/18844.xml">
Memory</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: LightYellow;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/17995.xml">
Long-term memory</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/527695.xml">
Implicit memory</link>: <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/23730.xml">
Procedural memory</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
 - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/188540.xml">
Classical conditioning</link><p>

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/1717129.xml">
Explicit</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/8295.xml">
declarative memory</link>: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/579359.xml">
Episodic memory</link> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/534400.xml">
Semantic memory</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: LightYellow;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../944/28944.xml">
Short-term memory</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/33912.xml">
Working memory</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background-color: LightYellow;" class="navbox-group">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/338236.xml">
Sensory memory</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/1215674.xml">
Visual memory</link>&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/734667.xml">
Iconic memory</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/10269587.xml">
Echoic memory</link></activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</procedure>
</article>
