<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:59:22[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Volterra series</title>
<id>5811728</id>
<revision>
<id>225004545</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-11T12:23:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jitse Niesen</username>
<id>14515</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Mathematical series</category>
<category>Functional analysis</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Volterra series</b> and Volterra theorem was developed in 1887 by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/484093.xml">
Vito Volterra</link></scientist>
.  It is a model for non-linear behavior, similar to the <mathematical_relation wordnetid="113783581" confidence="0.8">
<function wordnetid="113783816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/30448.xml">
Taylor series</link></function>
</mathematical_relation>
.  It differs from the Taylor series in its ability to capture 'memory' effects.  The Taylor series can be used to approximate nonlinear response of a system to a given input; its output depends strictly on the input at that particular time.  In the <b>Volterra series</b> the output of the nonlinear system depends on the input to the system at ALL other times.  This provides the ability to capture the 'memory' effect of devices such as capacitors and inductors.<p>

It has been applied in the fields of medicine (biomedical engineering), biology, especially neuroscience.  It is also used in electrical engineering to model <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/590995.xml">
intermodulation</link> distortion in many devices including power amplifiers and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/482952.xml">
frequency mixers</link>.  Its main advantage lies in its generality: it can represent a wide range of systems. It is therefore sometimes referred to as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/9387252.xml">
non-parametric</link> model. </p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link>, a <b>Volterra series</b> denotes a functional expansion of a dynamic, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/146103.xml">
nonlinear</link>, time-invariant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/1374948.xml">
functional</link>. Volterra series are frequently used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/552466.xml">
system identification</link>.  The Volterra series, which is used to prove the Volterra theorem, is a series of infinite sum of multidimensional convolutional integrals.</p>
<p>

The series and theorem is analogous to the <mathematical_relation wordnetid="113783581" confidence="0.8">
<function wordnetid="113783816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/30448.xml">
Taylor series</link></function>
</mathematical_relation>
 for functions. </p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mathematical theory</st>
<p>

The theory of Volterra series can be viewed from two different perspectives: either one considers an operator mapping between two real or complex function spaces or a functional mapping from a real (complex) function space into the real (complex) numbers. The latter, functional perspective is in more frequent use, due to the assumed time-invariance of the system.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Continuous time</st>
<p>

A continuous time-invariant system with <it>x(t)</it> as input and <it>y(t)</it> as output can be expanded in Volterra series as:
<math>
y(t) = k_0 + \sum_{n=1}^{\infty} \frac{1}{n!} \int_{-\infty}^\infty \cdots \int_{-\infty}^\infty k_n(s_1, s_2, \ldots, s_n) x(t - s_1) x(t - s_2) \cdots x(t - s_n) ds_1 ds_2 \cdots ds_n
</math></p>
<p>

<it>kn</it> is called the <it>n</it>-th order <b>Volterra kernel</b> which can be seen as a higher-order impulse response of the system.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Discrete time</st>

<p>

Let F be a continuous functional, which is time-invariant and has finite memory. Then <link>
Fréchet</link>'s theorem states, that this system can be approximated uniformly and to an arbitrary degree of precision by a sufficiently high, but finite order Volterra series. The input set over which this approximation holds encompasses all equicontinuous, uniformly bounded functions. In physically realizable setting this constraint on the input set should always hold.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods to estimate the Kernel coefficients</st>
<p>

Estimating the Volterra coefficients individually is complicated since the basis functionals of the Volterra series (i.e. x^k, k=1,...,N) are correlated. This leads to the problem of simultaneously solving a set of integral-equations for the coefficients. Hence, estimation of Volterra coefficients is generally performed by estimating the coefficients of an orthogonalized series, e.g. the Wiener Series, and then recomputing the coefficients of the original Volterra series. The Volterra series main appeal over the orthogonalized series lies in its intuitive, canonical structure, i.e. all interactions of the input have one fixed degree. The orthogonalized basis functionals will generally be quite complicated.</p>
<p>

An important aspect, with respect to which the following methods differ is whether the orthogonalization of the basis functionals is to be performed over the idealized specification of the input signal (e.g. gaussian, white noise) or over the actual realization of the input (i.e. the pseudo-random, bounded, almost-white version of gaussian white noise, or any other stimulus). The latter methods, despite their lack of mathematical elegance, have been shown to be more flexible (as arbitrary inputs can be easily accommodated) and precise (due to the effect that the idealized version of the input signal is not always realizable).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Crosscorrelation method</st>
<p>

This method, developed by Lee &amp; Schetzen, orthogonalizes with respect to the actual mathematical description of the signal, i.e. the projection onto the new basis functionals is based on the knowledge of the moments of the random signal.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Exact orthogonal algorithm</st>
<p>

This method and its more efficient version (Fast Orthogonal Algorithm) were invented by Korenberg. In this method the orthogonalization is performed empirically over the actual input. It has been shown to perform more precisely than the Crosscorrelation method. Another advantage is that arbitrary inputs can be used for the orthogonalization and that fewer data-points suffice to reach a desired level of accuracy. Also, estimation can be performed incrementally until some criterion is fulfilled.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Linear regression</st>
<p>

Linear regression is a standard tool from linear analysis. Hence, one of its main advantages is the widespread existence of standard tools for solving linear regressions efficiently. It has some educational value, since it highlights the basic property of Volterra series: linear combination of non-linear basis-functionals. For estimation the order of the original should be known, since the volterra basis-functionals are not orthogonal and estimation can thus not be performed incrementally. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Kernel method</st>
<p>

This method was invented by Franz &amp; Schölkopf and is based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/1053303.xml">
statistical learning theory</link>. Consequently, this approach is also based on minimizing the empirical error (often called empirical risk minimization). Franz and Schölkopf proposed that the kernel method could essentially replace the Volterra series representation, although noting that the latter is more intuitive.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Differential sampling</st>
<p>

This method was developed by van Hemmen and coworkers and utilizes <link>
 Dirac delta function</link>s to sample the Volterra coefficients.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Wiener series</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Fast orthogonal algorithm</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Volterra and Wiener Theories of Nonlinear Systems, Martin Schetzen (1980)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Identification of Nonlinear Biological Systems: Volterra Kernel Approaches, Michael J. Korenberg, Ian W. Hunter, Annals Biomedical Engineering (1996), Volume 24.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bussgang, J.J.; Ehrman, L.; Graham, J.W., "Analysis of nonlinear systems with multiple inputs," Proceedings of the IEEE , vol.62, no.8, pp. 1088-1119, Aug. 1974</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
