<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:46:12[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Medicare (United States)</title>
<id>58353</id>
<revision>
<id>243495562</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T19:37:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Fratrep</username>
<id>4541225</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Medicare and Medicaid (United States)</category>
<category>Health care reform</category>
<category>Lyndon B. Johnson</category>
<category>Articles with excessive links </category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<indent level="1">

<it>This article refers to </it>'Medicare<b>, a United States health insurance program. For similarly named programs in other countries, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/55793.xml">
Medicare</link><it>.
</it></b></indent>
<image width="250px" src="Lyndon_Johnson_signing_Medicare_bill,_with_Harry_Truman,_30_July,_1965.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

President Johnson signing the Medicare amendment. <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<farmer wordnetid="110078806" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<clothier wordnetid="109930772" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/3418303.xml">
Harry Truman</link></clothier>
</businessperson>
</farmer>
</person>
</president>
 and his wife, <first_lady wordnetid="110092880" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<officeholder wordnetid="110371450" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/415556.xml">
Bess</link></officeholder>
</first_lady>
, are on the far right
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Medicare</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/1550826.xml">
social insurance</link> program administered  by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/195149.xml">
United States government</link>, providing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/490201.xml">
health insurance</link> coverage to people who are aged 65 and over, or who meet other special criteria. It was originally signed into law on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/15911.xml">
July 30</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/34750.xml">
1965</link>, by President <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/54533.xml">
Lyndon B. Johnson</link></person>
</president>
 as amendments to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/48728.xml">
Social Security</link> legislation. At the bill-signing ceremony President Johnson enrolled former President <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<farmer wordnetid="110078806" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<clothier wordnetid="109930772" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/3418303.xml">
Harry S. Truman</link></clothier>
</businessperson>
</farmer>
</person>
</president>
 as the first Medicare beneficiary and presented him with the first Medicare card.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>

<sec>
<st>
 Administration </st>

<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/215745.xml">
Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services</link> (CMS), a component of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/58250.xml">
Department of Health and Human Services</link> (HHS), administers Medicare, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/55794.xml">
Medicaid</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/635422.xml">
State Children's Health Insurance Program</link> (SCHIP), and the <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/3084621.xml">
Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (CLIA). Along with the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/44273.xml">
Departments of Labor</link></agency>
 and <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/53667.xml">
Treasury</link></agency>
, CMS also implements the insurance reform provisions of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/384064.xml">
Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act</link> of 1996 (HIPAA). The <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/220007.xml">
Social Security Administration</link></agency>
 is responsible for determining Medicare eligibility and processing premium payments for the Medicare program.</p>
<p>

The Chief Actuary of CMS is responsible for providing accounting information and cost-projections to the Medicare Board of Trustees in order to assist them in assessing the financial health of the program.  The Board is required by law to issue annual reports on the financial status of the Medicare Trust Funds, and those reports are required to contain a statement of actuarial opinion by the Chief Actuary.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Since the beginning of the Medicare program, CMS has contracted with private companies to assist with administration. These contractors are commonly already in the insurance or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/261925.xml">
health care</link> area. Contracted processes include claims and payment processing, call center services, clinician enrollment, and fraud investigation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Taxes imposed to finance Medicare </st>

<p>

Medicare is partially financed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/438978.xml">
payroll tax</link>es imposed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/560096.xml">
Federal Insurance Contributions Act</link> (FICA) and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/55815.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Social+Security+tax+on+wages+and+self-employment+income%22])">
Self-Employment Contributions Act</link> of 1954. In the case of employees, the tax is equal to 2.9% (1.45% withheld from the worker and a matching 1.45% paid by the employer) of the wages, salaries and other compensation in connection with employment. Until <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/8204.xml">
December 31</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/34598.xml">
1993</link>, the law provided a maximum amount of wages, etc., on which the Medicare tax could be imposed each year. Beginning <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
January 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/18948337.xml">
1994</link>, the compensation limit was removed. In the case of self-employed individuals, the entire 2.9% tax of self employed net earnings must be paid by the self-employed individual, however half of the tax can be deducted from the income calculated for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/50845.xml">
income tax</link> purposes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Eligibility </st>

<p>

In general, individuals are eligible for Medicare if they are a U.S. citizen or have been a permanent legal resident for 5 continuous years, <b>and</b> they are 65 years or older, <b>or</b> they are under 65, disabled and have been receiving either <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/48728.xml">
Social Security</link> or the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<independent_agency wordnetid="108338847" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/1165432.xml">
Railroad Retirement Board</link></independent_agency>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
 disability benefits for at least 24 months, <b>or</b> they get continuing dialysis for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/1471159.xml">
end stage renal disease</link> or need a kidney transplant, <b>or</b> they are eligible for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/5022853.xml">
Social Security Disability Insurance</link> and have <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/19375577.xml">
Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</link> (ALS-Lou Gehrig's disease). </p>
<p>

Many beneficiaries are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/1517011.xml">
dual-eligible</link>. This means they qualify for both Medicare and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/55794.xml">
Medicaid</link>. In some states for those making below a certain income, Medicaid will pay the beneficiaries' Part B premium for them (most beneficiaries have worked long enough and have no Part A premium), and also pay any drugs that are not covered by Part D.</p>
<p>

In 2007, Medicare provided health care coverage for 43 million Americans. Enrollment is expected to reach 77 million by 2031, when the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/8210419.xml">
baby boom</link> generation is fully enrolled.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Benefits </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Medicare.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A Medicare card, with several areas of the card obscured to protect privacy. There are separate lines with for Part A and Part B, each with its own date. There are no lines for Part C or D, as a separate card is issued for those benefits by the private insurance company.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The original Medicare program has two parts: Part A (Hospital Insurance), and Part B (Medical Insurance). Only a few special cases exist where <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/359238.xml">
prescription drug</link>s are covered by original Medicare, but as of January 2006, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/2870773.xml">
Medicare Part D</link> provides more comprehensive drug coverage. Medicare Advantage plans are another way for beneficiaries to receive their Part A, B and D benefits. All Medicare benefits are subject to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/5483190.xml">
medical necessity</link>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Part A: Hospital Insurance </st>

<p>

Part A covers <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/18994221.xml">
hospital</link> stays (including stays in a skilled nursing facility) if certain criteria are met:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The hospital stay must be at least three days, three midnights, not counting the discharge date.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The nursing home stay must be for something diagnosed during the hospital stay or for the main cause of hospital stay. For instance, a hospital stay for a broken hip and then a nursing home stay for physical therapy would be covered.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 If the patient is not receiving rehabilitation but has some other ailment that requires skilled nursing supervision then the nursing home stay would be covered.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The care being rendered by the nursing home must be skilled. Medicare part A does not pay for custodial, non-skilled, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/3118704.xml">
long-term care</link> activities, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/236137.xml">
activities of daily living</link> (ADLs) such as personal hygiene, cooking, cleaning, etc.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The maximum length of stay that Medicare Part A will cover in a skilled nursing facility per ailment is 100 days. The first 20 days would be paid for in full by Medicare with the remaining 80 days requiring a co-payment (as of 2008, $128.00 per day). Many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
insurance</link> companies have a provision for skilled nursing care in the policies they sell.</p>
<p>

If a beneficiary uses some portion of their Part A benefit and then goes at least 60 days without receiving facility-based skilled services, the 100-day clock is reset and the person qualifies for a new 100-day benefit period.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Part B: Medical Insurance </st>

<p>

Part B medical insurance helps pay for some services and products not covered by Part A, generally on an outpatient basis. Part B is optional and may be deferred if the beneficiary or their spouse is still actively working. There is a lifetime penalty (10% per year) imposed for not enrolling in Part B unless actively working.</p>
<p>

Part B coverage includes physician and nursing services, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/6856496.xml">
x-rays</link>, laboratory and diagnostic tests, influenza and pneumonia vaccinations, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../857/88857.xml">
blood transfusion</link>s, renal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/56511.xml">
dialysis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/2772885.xml">
outpatient hospital procedures</link>, limited ambulance transportation, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/249958.xml">
Immunosuppressive drug</link>s for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/167166.xml">
organ transplant</link> recipients, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/7172.xml">
chemotherapy</link>, hormonal treatments such as lupron, and other outpatient medical treatments administered in a doctor's office. Medication administration is covered under Part B only if it is administered by the physician during an office visit.</p>
<p>

Part B also helps with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/8052331.xml">
durable medical equipment</link> (DME), including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/410653.xml">
cane</link>s, walkers, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/106369.xml">
wheelchair</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/3042527.xml">
mobility scooter</link>s for those with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/56285.xml">
mobility impairment</link>s. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/72750.xml">
Prosthetic devices</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/484630.xml">
artificial limb</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/7066429.xml">
breast prosthesis</link> following <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/42047.xml">
mastectomy</link>, as well as one pair of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/74844.xml">
eyeglasses</link> following <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/1179794.xml">
cataract surgery</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/508455.xml">
oxygen</link> for home use is also covered.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Complex rules are used to manage the benefit, and advisories are periodically issued which describe coverage criteria. On the national level these advisories are issued by CMS, and are known as National Coverage Determinations (NCD). Local Coverage Determinations (LCD) only apply within the multi-state area managed by a specific regional Medicare Part B contractor, and Local Medical Review Policies (LMRP) were superseded by LCDs in 2003. Coverage information is also located in the CMS Internet-Only Manuals (IOM), the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/469120.xml">
Code of Federal Regulations</link></publication>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
 (CFR), the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/55815.xml">
Social Security Act</link>, and the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/606813.xml">
Federal Register</link></publication>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Part C: Medicare Advantage plans </st>

<p>

With the passage of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/6151372.xml">
Balanced Budget Act of 1997</link>, Medicare beneficiaries were given the option to receive their Medicare benefits through private <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/490201.xml">
health insurance</link> plans, instead of through the original Medicare plan (Parts A and B). These programs were known as "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/15404684.xml">
Medicare+Choice</link>" or "Part C" plans.  Pursuant to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/378922.xml">
Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act</link> of 2003, "Medicare+Choice" plans were made more attractive to Medicare beneficiaries by the addition of prescription drug coverage and became known as "Medicare Advantage" (MA) plans. </p>
<p>

Medicare has a standard benefit package that covers medically necessary care members can receive from nearly any hospital or doctor in the country. For people who choose to enroll in a Medicare Advantage health plan, Medicare pays the private health plan a capitated rate, or a set amount, every month for each member. Members typically also pay a monthly premium in addition to the Medicare Part B premium to cover items not covered by traditional Medicare (Parts A &amp; B), such as prescription drugs, dental care, vision care and gym or health club memberships.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

Medicare Advantage plans are required to offer coverage that meets or exceeds the standards set by the original Medicare program, but they do not have to cover every benefit in the same way. If a plan chooses to pay less than Medicare for some benefits, like skilled nursing facility care, the savings may be passed along to consumers by offering lower copayments for doctor visits. Medicare Advantage plans use a portion of the payments they receive from the government for each enrollee to offer supplemental benefits. Some plans limit their members’ annual out-of-pocket spending on medical care, providing insurance against catastrophic costs over $5,000, for example. Many plans offer dental coverage, vision coverage and other services not covered by Medicare Parts A or B, which makes them a good value for the health care dollar. </p>
<p>

In 2006 enrollees in Medicare Advantage Private Fee-for-Service plans were offered a net extra benefit value (the value of the additional benefits minus any additional premium) of $55.92 a month more than the traditional Medicare benefit package; enrollees in other Medicare Advantage plans were offered a net extra benefit value of $71.22 a month more.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> However, Medicare Advantage members receive additional coverage and medical benefits not enjoyed by traditional Medicare members, and savings generated by Medicare Advantage plans may be passed on to beneficiaries to lower their overall health care costs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> Other important distinctions between Medicare Advantage and traditional Medicare are that Medicare Advantage health plans encourage preventive care and wellness and closely coordinate patient care.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

<p>

Medicare Advantage Plans that also include Part D prescription drug benefits are known as a Medicare Advantage Prescription Drug plan or a MAPD.</p>
<p>

Enrollment in Medicare Advantage plans grew from 5.4 million in 2005 to 8.2 million in 2007.  Enrollment grew by an additional 800,000 during the first four months of 2008.  This represents 19% of Medicare beneficiaries.  A third of beneficiaries with Part D coverage are enrolled in a Medicare Advantage plan.  Medicare Advantage enrollment is higher in urban areas; the enrollment rate in urban counties is twice that in rural counties (22% vs. 10%).  Almost all Medicare beneficiaries have access to at least two Medicare Advantage plans; most have access to three or more.  The number of organizations offering Fee-for-Service plans has increased dramatically, from 11 in 2006 to almost 50 in 2008.  Eight out of ten beneficiaries (82%) now have access to six or more Private Fee-for-Service plans.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

Twenty percent of African-American and 32 percent of Hispanic Medicare Beneficiaries were enrolled in Medicare Advantage plans in 2006.  Almost half (48%) of Medicare Advantage enrollees had incomes below $20,000, including 71% of minority enrollees.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Part D: Prescription Drug plans </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/2870773.xml">
Medicare Part D</link></it>
</indent>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/2870773.xml">
Medicare Part D</link> went into effect on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
January 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>. Anyone with Part A or B is eligible for Part D. It was made possible by the passage of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/378922.xml">
Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act</link>. In order to receive this benefit, a person with Medicare must enroll in a stand-alone Prescription Drug Plan (PDP) or Medicare Advantage plan with prescription drug coverage (MA-PD). These plans are approved and regulated by the Medicare program, but are actually designed and administered by private health insurance companies. Unlike Original Medicare (Part A and B), Part D coverage is not standardized. Plans choose which drugs (or even classes of drugs) they wish to cover, at what level (or tier) they wish to cover it, and are free to choose not to cover some drugs at all. The exception to this is drugs that Medicare specifically excludes from coverage, including but not limited to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/4781.xml">
benzodiazepine</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/266226.xml">
cough suppressant</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/53663.xml">
barbiturate</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> Plans that cover excluded drugs are not allowed to pass those costs on to Medicare, and plans are required to repay CMS if they are found to have billed Medicare in these cases.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref></p>
<p>

It should be noted again for beneficiaries who are dual-eligible (Medicare and Medicaid eligible) Medicaid may pay for drugs not covered by part D of Medicare, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/4781.xml">
benzodiazepine</link>s, and other restricted controlled substances.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Out-of-pocket costs </st>

<p>

Neither Part A nor Part B pays for all of a covered person's medical costs. The program contains <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
premium</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/636959.xml">
deductible</link>s and coinsurance, which the covered individual must <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/6337653.xml">
pay out-of-pocket</link>. Some people may qualify to have other governmental programs (such as Medicaid) pay premiums and some or all of the costs associated with Medicare. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Premiums </st>

<p>

Most Medicare enrollees do not pay a monthly Part A premium, because they (or a spouse) have had 40 or more quarters in which they paid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/560096.xml">
Federal Insurance Contributions Act</link> taxes. Medicare-eligible persons who do not have 40 or more quarters of Medicare-covered employment may purchase Part A for a monthly premium of: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

$233.00 per month (2008) for those with 30-39 quarters of Medicare-covered employment, or</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

$423.00 per month (in 2008) for those with less than 30 quarters of Medicare-covered employment and who are not otherwise eligible for premium-free Part A coverage. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

All Medicare Part B enrollees pay an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
insurance premium</link> for this coverage; the standard Part B premium for 2008 is $96.40 per month. A new income-based premium <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/48031.xml">
schema</link> has been in effect for 2007, wherein Part B premiums are higher for beneficiaries with incomes exceeding $80,000 for individuals or $160,000 for married couples. Depending on the extent to which beneficiary earnings exceed the base income, these higher Part B premiums are $122.20, $160.90, $199.70, or $238.40 for 2008, with the highest premium paid by individuals earning more than $205,000, or married couples earning more than $410,000.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>  In September of 2008, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/215745.xml">
CMS</link> announced that Part B premiums would be unchanged  ($96.40 per month) in 2009 for 95 percent of Medicare beneficiaries.  This would be only the sixth year without a premium increase since Medicare was established in 1965.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>
<p>

Medicare Part B premiums are commonly deducted automatically from beneficiaries' monthly Social Security checks.</p>
<p>

Part C and D plans may or may not charge premiums, at the programs' discretion.  Part C plans may also choose to rebate a portion of the Part B premium to the member.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Deductible and coinsurance </st>

<p>

<b>Part A</b> &mdash; For each <link>
benefit period</link>, a beneficiary will pay:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A Part A deductible of $1,024 (in 2008) for a hospital stay of 1-60 days.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A $256 per day co-pay (in 2008) for days 61-90 of a hospital stay.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A $512 per day co-pay (in 2008) for days 91-150 of a hospital stay, as part of their limited <link>
Lifetime Reserve Days</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 All costs for each day beyond 150 days<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Coinsurance for a Skilled Nursing Facility is $128.00 per day (in 2008) for days 21 through 100 for each benefit period.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A blood deductible of the first 3 pints of blood needed in a calendar year, unless replaced. There is a 3 pint blood deductible for both Part A and Part B, and these separate deductibles do not overlap.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Part B</b> &mdash; After a beneficiary meets the yearly deductible of $135.00 (in 2008), they will be required to pay a co-insurance of 20% of the Medicare-approved amount for all services covered by Part B. They are also required to pay an excess charge of 15% for services rendered by non-participating Medicare providers.</p>
<p>

The deductibles and coinsurance charges for Part C and D plans vary from plan to plan.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Medicare supplement (Medigap) policies </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/3183394.xml">
Medigap</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</it>
</indent>

Some people elect to purchase a type of supplemental coverage, called a Medigap plan, to help fill in the holes in Original Medicare (Part A and B). These Medigap insurance policies are standardized by CMS, but are sold and administered by private companies. Some Medigap policies sold before 2006 may include coverage for prescription drugs.  Medigap policies sold after the introduction of Medicare Part D on January 1, 2006 are prohibited from covering drugs.</p>
<p>

Some have suggested that by reducing the cost-sharing requirements in the Medicare program, Medigap policies increase the use of health care by Medicare beneficiaries and thus increase Medicare spending.  One recent study suggests that this concern may have been overstated due to methodological problems in prior research.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Payment for services </st>

<p>

Medicare contracts with regional insurance companies who process over one billion fee-for-service claims per year. In 2003, Medicare accounted for almost 13% of the entire <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/3874731.xml">
federal budget</link>. Based on the CMS projections, 33 cents of every dollar spent on health care in the U.S. is paid by Medicare and Medicaid (including State funding). Looked at from three different perspectives, 61 cents of every dollar spent on nursing homes, 47 cents of every dollar received by U.S. hospitals, and 27 cents of every dollar spent on physician services is funded by Medicare or Medicaid.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Reimbursement for Part A services </st>

<p>

For institutional care such as hospital and nursing home care, Medicare uses prospective payment systems.  A prospective payment system is one in which the health care institution receives a set amount of money for each episode of care provided to a patient, regardless of the actual amount of care used. The actual allotment of funds is based on a list of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/195972.xml">
diagnosis-related group</link>s (DRG). The actual amount depends on the kind of diagnosis made at the hospital. There are some issues surrounding Medicare's use of DRGs because if the patient uses less care, the hospital gets to keep the remainder. This, in theory, should balance the costs for the hospital. However, if the patient uses more care, then the hospital has to cover its own losses. This results in the issue of "upcoding," when a physician makes a more severe diagnosis to hedge against accidental costs.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Reimbursement for Part B services </st>

<p>

Payment for physician services under Medicare has evolved since the program was created in 1965. Initially, Medicare compensated physicians based on the physician's charges, and allowed physicians to bill Medicare beneficiaries the amount in excess of Medicare's reimbursement. In 1975, annual increases in physician fees were limited by the Medicare Economic Index (MEI). The MEI was designed to measure changes in costs of physician's time and operating expenses, adjusted for changes in physician productivity. From 1984 to 1991, the yearly change in fees was determined by legislation. This was done because physician fees were rising faster than projected.</p>
<p>

The Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1989 made several changes to physician payments under Medicare.  Firstly, it introduced the Medicare Fee Schedule, which took effect in 1992.  Secondly, it limited the amount Medicare non-providers could balance bill Medicare beneficiaries. Thirdly, it  introduced the Medicare Volume Performance Standards (MVPS) as a way to control costs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
January 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/34669.xml">
1992</link>, Medicare introduced the Medicare Fee Schedule (MFS).  The MFS assigned Relative Value Units (RVUs) for each procedure from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/282037.xml">
Resource-Based Relative Value Scale</link> (RBRVS).  The Medicare reimbursement for a physician was the product of the RVU for the procedure, a Geographic Adjustment Factor (GAF) for geographic variations in payments, and a global Conversion Factor (CF) which converts RBRVS units to dollars.  </p>
<p>

From 1992 to 1997, adjustments to physician payments were adjusted using the MEI and the MVPS, which essentially tried to compensate for the increasing volume of services provided by physicians by decreasing their reimbursement per service.</p>
<p>

In 1998, Congress replaced the VPS with the Sustainable Growth Rate (SGR).  This was done because of highly variable payment rates under the MVPS.  The SGR attempts to control spending by setting yearly and cumulative spending targets. If actual spending for a given year exceeds the spending target for that year, reimbursement rates are adjusted downward by decreasing the Conversion Factor (CF) for RBRVS RVUs.</p>
<p>

Since 2002, actual Medicare Part B expenditures have exceeded projections.</p>
<p>

In 2002, payment rates were cut by 4.8%. In 2003, payment rates were scheduled to be reduced by 4.4%.  However, Congress boosted the cumulative SGR target in the Consolidated Appropriation Resolution of 2003 (P.L. 108-7), allowing payments for physician services to rise 1.6%. In 2004 and 2005, payment rates were again scheduled to be reduced.  The Medicare Modernization Act (P.L. 108-173) increased payments 1.5% for those two years.</p>
<p>

In 2006, the SGR mechanism was scheduled to decrease physician payments by 4.4%.  (This number results from a 7% decrease in physician payments times a 2.8% inflation adjustment increase.)  Congress overrode this decrease in the Deficit Reduction Act (P.L. 109-362), and held physician payments in 2006 at their 2005 levels.  Similary, another congressional act held 2007 payments at their 2006 levels, and HR 6331 held 2008 physician payments to their 2007 levels, and provided for a 1.1% increase in physician payments in 2009. Without further continuing congressional intervention, the SGR is expected to decrease physician payments from 25% to 35% over the next several years.</p>
<p>

MFS has been criticized for not paying doctors enough because of the low conversion factor. By adjustments to the MFS conversion factor, it is possible to make global adjustments in payments to all doctors.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Office medication reimbursement </st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../172/7172.xml">
Chemotherapy</link> and other medications dispensed in a physician's office are reimbursed according to the Average Sales Price, a number computed by taking the total dollar sales of a drug as the numerator and the number of units sold nationwide as the denominator.  The current reimbursement formula is known as "ASP+6" since it reimburses physicians at 106% of the ASP of drugs.  Pharmaceutical company discounts and rebates are included in the calculation of ASP, and tend to reduce it.  ASP+6 superseded Average Wholesale Price in 2005, after a 2004 front-page New York Times article drew attention to the inaccuracies of Average Wholesale Price calculations.  Average Wholesale Price (AWP) reimbursement tended to be more favorable for physicians, since it was an arbitrary number provided by the pharmaceutical company to CMS.  Since the change, some outpatient chemotherapy drugs are "underwater," since the wholesale price from drug distributors may be higher than ASP+6 for some drugs.  Stakeholders are involved in active discussions with the <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
United States Congress</link></legislature>
 to address this issue.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Costs and funding challenges </st>

<p>

<image width="400px" src="Medicare_and_Medicaid_GDP_Chart.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Medicare and Medicaid Spending as % GDP
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

According to the 2004 "Green Book" of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/465643.xml">
House Ways and Means Committee</link>, Medicare expenditures from the American government were $256.8 billion in fiscal year 2002.  Beneficiary premiums are highly subsidized, and net outlays for the program, accounting for the premiums paid by subscribers, were $230.9 billion.</p>
<p>

Medicare spending is growing steadily in both absolute terms and as a percentage of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/3874731.xml">
federal budget</link>.  Total Medicare spending reached $440 billion for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/5752099.xml">
fiscal year</link> 2007, or 16 percent of all federal spending.  The only larger categories of federal spending are Social Security and <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/7279897.xml">
defense</link></agency>
.  Given the current pattern of spending growth, maintaining Medicare's financing over the long-term may well require significant changes.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>
<p>

According to the 2008 report by the board of trustees for Medicare and Social Security, Medicare will spend more than it brings in from taxes this year (2008). The Medicare hospital insurance trust fund will become insolvent by 2019.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>  Shortly after the release of the report, the <link>
Chief Actuary</link> testified that the insolvency of the system could be pushed back by 18 months if Medicare Advantage plans that provide more health care services than traditional Medicare and pass savings onto beneficiaries were paid at the same rate as the traditional fee-for-service program.  He also testified that the 10-year cost of Medicare drug benefit is 37% lower than originally projected in 2003, and 17% percent lower than last year's projections.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref></p>
<p>

Spending on Medicare and Medicaid is projected to grow dramatically in coming decades.  While the same demographic trends that affect Social Security also affect Medicare, rapidly rising medical prices appear a more important cause of projected spending increases.  The <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<employee wordnetid="110053808" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/1053718.xml">
Congressional Budget Office</link></employee>
</causal_agent>
</agency>
</worker>
</administrative_unit>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 (CBO) has indicated that: "Future growth in spending per beneficiary for Medicare and Medicaid—the federal government’s major health care programs—will be the most important determinant of long-term trends in federal spending. Changing those programs in ways that reduce the growth of costs—which will be difficult, in part because of the complexity of health policy choices—is ultimately the nation’s central long-term challenge in setting federal fiscal policy."  Further, the CBO also projects that "total federal Medicare and Medicaid outlays will rise from 4 percent of GDP in 2007 to 12 percent in 2050 and 19 percent in 2082—which, as a share of the economy, is roughly equivalent to the total amount that the federal government spends today. The bulk of that projected increase in health care spending reflects higher costs per beneficiary rather than an increase in the number of beneficiaries associated with an aging population."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Financial viability</st>

<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.8">
<executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<corporate_executive wordnetid="109966255" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/8007435.xml">
Richard W. Fisher</link></scholar>
</head>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</corporate_executive>
</intellectual>
</administrator>
</leader>
</person>
</executive>
</president>
</physical_entity>
, President of the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<slope wordnetid="109437454" confidence="0.8">
<geological_formation wordnetid="109287968" confidence="0.8">
<bank wordnetid="109213565" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/2338776.xml">
Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas</link></bank>
</geological_formation>
</slope>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 has remarked that in order to "cover the unfunded liability" for the Medicare program today over an infinite time horizon, "you would be stuck with an $85.6 trillion bill" which is "more than six times the annual output of the entire U.S. economy."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref></p>
<p>

The present value of unfunded obligations under all parts of Medicare during FY 2007 over a 75-year forecast horizon is approximately $34.0 trillion. In other words, this amount would have to be set aside today such that the principal and interest would cover the shortfall over the next 75 years.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Aging of the population</st>
<p>

The fundamental problem is that the ratio of workers paying Medicare taxes to retirees drawing benefits is shrinking at the same time that the price of health care services per person is increasing.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref> Currently there are 3.9 workers paying taxes into Medicare for every older American receiving services. By 2030, as the baby boom generation retires, that is projected to drop to 2.4 workers for each beneficiary. Medicare spending is expected to grow by about 7 percent per year for the next 10 years.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref> As a result, the financing of the program is out of actuarial balance, presenting serious challenges in both the short-term and long-term.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fraud and waste</st>
<p>

Part of the cost of Medicare is attributable to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/58790.xml">
fraud</link>, which government auditors estimate costs Medicare billions of dollars a year.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref> The <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/199096.xml">
Government Accountability Office</link></agency>
 lists Medicare as a "high-risk" government program in need of reform, in part because of its vulnerability to fraud and partly because of its long-term financial problems.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref> A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/102226.xml">
Washington Post</link> story from June of 2008 reported that Medicare fraud is a growing problem.  Limited resources mean that fewer than 5% of Medicare claims are audited.  The annual cost to taxpayers of Medicare fraud is estimated to be over $60 billion.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Estimated net Medicare benefits for different worker categories</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="375px" src="Fig._169_-_Net_lifetime_Medicare_benefits.JPG" type="thumb">
</image>

In 2004, Urban Institute economists C. Eugene Steuerle and Adam Carasso created a Web-based Medicare benefits calculator.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref> Using this calculator it is possible to estimate net Medicare benefits (i.e., estimated lifetime Medicare benefits received minus estimated lifetime Medicare taxes paid, expressed in today's dollars) for different types of recipients.  In the book, <it>Democrats and Republicans - Rhetoric and Reality</it>, Joseph Fried used the calculator to create graphical depictions of the estimated net benefits of men and women who were at different wage levels, single and married (with stay-at-home spouses), and retiring in different years.  Three of these graphs are shown below, and they clearly show why Medicare (as currently formulated) is on the path to fiscal insolvency: No matter what the wage level, marital status, or retirement date, a man or woman can expect to receive benefits that will cost the system far more than the taxes he or she paid into the system.  </p>
<p>

In the first graph (Figure 169) we see that estimated net benefits range from $108,000 to $240,000 for single men and from $142,000 to $277,000 for single women.  Generally, the benefits are progressive.  Note that women usually get higher benefits due to their greater longevity.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2237%22])">37</ref>
<image location="right" width="375px" src="Fig._170_-_Comparison_of_Medicare_benefits.JPG" type="thumb">
</image>

In the next graph (Figure 170) we see a comparison of net Medicare benefits for a single woman versus a married woman (or man) with a stay-at-home spouse. The single woman can expect substantial net benefits, ranging from $142,000 to $277,000,  However, these benefits are dwarfed by the estimated net benefits of her married counterpart.  Due to a "spousal benefit" built into the Medicare formula, the married person will get net benefits ranging from $393,000 to $525,000. The impact of the spousal benefit can disrupt the intended progressivity of Medicare benefits.  For example, we see in Figure 170 that the married worker earning $95,000 is estimated to get net benefits of $393,000, while the single worker earning $5,000 is estimated to get $277,000.  In either case, the benefits paid to the worker greatly exceed the taxes paid by the worker (and pose a financial burden on the system); however, the high-earning married worker gets a better "return," so to speak, on each tax dollar paid into the system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2238%22])">38</ref></p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="375px" src="Fig._171_-_Medicare_benefits_of_men_at_different_wages_levels_and_retirement_dates.JPG" type="thumb">
</image>

The last graph shown (Figure 171) compares the net benefits of a single man retiring in 2005 with the net benefits of a man retiring in 2045.  It is clear that the future retiree is likely to get a far greater net benefit than the current retiree (and is likely to be a greater burden to the system).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref>  Interestingly, in the Social Security system we see the opposite pattern.  In that case, the future retiree can expect a much smaller net retirement benefit than the current retiree can expect.  See "Estimated net Social Security benefits under differing circumstances" in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/48728.xml">
Social Security (United States)</link></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Criticism </st>
<p>

Medicare faces continuing financial challenges. In its 2006 annual report to Congress, the Medicare Board of Trustees reported that the program's hospital insurance trust fund could run out of money by 2018. The trustees have made such projections in the past, but this one was bleaker than the outlook reported in 2005.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref></p>
<p>

Popular opinion surveys show that the public views Medicare’s problems as serious, but not as urgent as other concerns. In January 2006, the Pew Research Center found 62 percent of the public said addressing Medicare’s financial problems should be a high priority for the government, but that still put it behind other priorities.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2241%22])">41</ref> Surveys suggest that there’s no public consensus behind any specific strategy to keep the program solvent.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Quality of beneficiary services</st>
<p>

In a 2001 study by the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/199096.xml">
Government Accountability Office</link></agency>
 evaluated the quality of responses given by Medicare contractor customer service representatives to provider (physician) questions.  The evaluators assembled a list of questions, which they asked during a random sampling of calls to Medicare contractors.  The rate of complete, accurate information provided by Medicare customer service representatives was 15%.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2243%22])">43</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hospital accreditation</st>
<p>

In most states the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<medical_building wordnetid="103739518" confidence="0.8">
<hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../744/1644744.xml">
Joint Commission</link></hospital>
</medical_building>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
, a private, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
non-profit organization</link> for accrediting hospitals, possesses a monopoly over whether or not a hospital is able to participate in Medicare, as currently there are no competitor organizations recognized by CMS. An attempt by <link>
TÜV Healthcare Specialists</link> to provide a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/13371832.xml">
hospital accreditation</link> option was denied in 2006. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2244%22])">44</ref> Rebecca Wise, CEO of TÜVHS, has said "Choice and competition are the hallmarks of a free market.... Can you think of an industry with a more profound impact on our lives than healthcare? Yet there is a much higher chance of you getting the wrong dosage of medicine in a hospital than there is of a manufacturer putting the wrong chip on a circuit board. It’s a failure of the system not the people." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2245%22])">45</ref>  </p>
<p>

Beyond hospitals and hospital accreditation, there are now a number of alternative American organizations possessing healthcare-related deeming power for Medicare.  These include the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<medical_building wordnetid="103739518" confidence="0.8">
<hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/15162439.xml">
Community Health Accreditation Program</link></hospital>
</medical_building>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/15162543.xml">
Accreditation Commission for Health Care</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/15162636.xml">
the Compliance Team</link> and the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<medical_building wordnetid="103739518" confidence="0.8">
<hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/15162688.xml">
Healthcare Quality Association on Accreditation</link></hospital>
</medical_building>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Physician residency </st>
<p>

Medicare funds the vast majority of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/1147690.xml">
residency</link> training in the US.  This tax-based financing covers resident salaries and benefits through payments called Direct Medical Education payments.  Medicare also uses taxes for Indirect Medical Education, a subsidy paid to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/485700.xml">
teaching hospital</link>s in exchange for training resident physicians.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2246%22])">46</ref>  Overall funding levels, however, have remained frozen over the last ten years, creating a bottleneck in the training of new physicians in the US.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2247%22])">47</ref> Meanwhile, the US population continues to grow, leading to greater demand for physicians.  At the same time the cost of medical services continue rising rapidly and many geographic areas face physician shortages, both trends suggesting the supply of physicians remains too low.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2248%22])">48</ref> Medicare finds itself in the odd position of having assumed control of graduate medical education, currently facing major budget constraints, and as a result, freezing funding for graduate medical education, as well as for physician reimbursement rates.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2249%22])">49</ref>  This halt in funding in turn exacerbates the exact problem Medicare sought to solve in the first place: improving the availability of medical care. In response, teaching hospitals have resorted to alternative approaches to funding resident training, leading to the modest 4% total growth in residency slots from 1998-2004, despite Medicare funding having been frozen since 1996.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2249%22])">49</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Legislation and reform </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1960 &mdash; PL 86-778 <link>
Social Security Amendments of 1960</link> (Kerr-Mill aid)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1965 &mdash; PL 89-97 <link>
Social Security Amendments of 1965</link>, Establishing Medicare Benefits</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1988 &mdash; PL 100-360 <link>
Medicare Catastrophic Coverage Act of 1988</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1997 &mdash; PL 105-33 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/6151372.xml">
Balanced Budget Act of 1997</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2003 &mdash; PL 108-173 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/378922.xml">
Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

President <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<lawyer wordnetid="110249950" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/3356.xml">
Bill Clinton</link></lawyer>
</person>
</president>
 attempted an overhaul of Medicare through his <controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<drive wordnetid="104835724" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="104836074" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<trait wordnetid="104616059" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/1369907.xml">
health care reform plan</link></trait>
</speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</disagreement>
</enterprise>
</dispute>
</drive>
</event>
</controversy>
 in 1993-1994 but was unable to get the legislation passed by Congress.</p>
<p>

In 2003 <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
Congress</link></legislature>
 passed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/378922.xml">
Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act</link>, which President <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/3414021.xml">
George W. Bush</link></businessperson>
</person>
</president>
 signed into law on <time_off wordnetid="115118453" confidence="0.8">
<fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<vacation wordnetid="115137890" confidence="0.8">
<leisure wordnetid="115137676" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/8194.xml">
December 8</link></leisure>
</vacation>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
</time_off>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>. Part of this legislation included filling gaps in prescription-drug coverage left by the Medicare Secondary Payer Act that was enacted in 1980. The 2003 bill strengthened the Workers' Compensation Medicare Set-Aside Program (WCMSA) that is monitored and administered by CMS.</p>
<p>

On August 1, 2007, the U.S. House <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
United States Congress</link></legislature>
 voted to reduce payments to Medicare Advantage providers in order to pay for expanded coverage of children's health under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/635422.xml">
SCHIPS</link> program. As of 2008, Medicare Advantage plans cost, on average, 13 percent more per person insured than direct payment plans.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2250%22])">50</ref> Many health economists have concluded that payments to Medicare Advantage providers have been excessive.  The Senate, after heavy lobbying from the insurance industry, declined to agree to the cuts in Medicare Advantage proposed by the House.  President Bush subsequently vetoed the SCHIPS extension. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2251%22])">51</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Legislative oversight </st>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<row>
<header>
Cameral body</header>
<header>
Committee</header>
<header>
Leader</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Joint House/Senate</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/1610404.xml">
Joint Economic Committee</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/326708.xml">
Charles Schumer</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/465643.xml">
House Committee on Ways and Means</link></col>
<col>
 <link>
Charles Rangel</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/7505195.xml">
House Committee on Ways and Means Subcommittee on Health</link></col>
<col>
 <executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<congressman wordnetid="109955781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/408803.xml">
Pete Stark</link></congressman>
</executive>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/1635261.xml">
House Committee on Energy and Commerce</link></col>
<col>
 <congressman wordnetid="109955781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<lawyer wordnetid="110249950" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/386146.xml">
John Dingell</link></lawyer>
</congressman>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<subcommittee wordnetid="108325993" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/2588546.xml">
House Committee on Energy and Commerce Subcommittee on Health</link></subcommittee>
</committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <congressman wordnetid="109955781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<lawyer wordnetid="110249950" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/6477895.xml">
Frank Pallone</link></lawyer>
</congressman>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/11917620.xml">
House Committee on Energy and Commerce Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations</link></col>
<col>
 <congressman wordnetid="109955781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<lawyer wordnetid="110249950" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/468306.xml">
Bart Stupak</link></lawyer>
</congressman>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/446212.xml">
House Committee on Appropriations</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/408926.xml">
David Obey</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/7717809.xml">
House Committee on Appropriations Subcommittee on Labor, Health and Human Services, Education, and Related Agencies</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/408926.xml">
David Obey</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/3284644.xml">
House Small Business Committee</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/948525.xml">
Nydia Velazquez</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
House</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/1600169.xml">
House Budget Committee</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/862737.xml">
John Spratt</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/750795.xml">
Senate Committee on Finance</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/296933.xml">
Max Baucus</link></senator>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/838419.xml">
Senate Special Committee on Aging</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/1190558.xml">
Herb Kohl</link></senator>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/465705.xml">
Senate Committee on Appropriations</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<officeholder wordnetid="110371450" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/25408.xml">
Robert Byrd</link></officeholder>
</person>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/6260996.xml">
Senate Committee on Appropriations Subcommittee on Labor, Health and Human Services, Education, and Related Agencies</link></col>
<col>
 <senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/375268.xml">
Tom Harkin</link></senator>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/832830.xml">
Senate Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs</link></col>
<col>
 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/74456.xml">
Joe Lieberman</link></senator>
</person>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/11916710.xml">
Senate Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Subcommittee on Oversight of Government Management, the Federal Workforce, and the District of Columbia</link></col>
<col>
 <senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/296716.xml">
Daniel Akaka</link></senator>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/833223.xml">
Senate Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions</link></col>
<col>
 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<officeholder wordnetid="110371450" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/184136.xml">
Ted Kennedy</link></officeholder>
</person>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/11910738.xml">
Senate Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Subcommittee on Retirement Security and Aging</link></col>
<col>
 <senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/368402.xml">
Barbara Mikulski</link></senator>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<committee wordnetid="108324514" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/1052482.xml">
Senate Budget Committee</link></committee>
</administrative_unit>
</col>
<col>
 <senator wordnetid="110578471" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/379856.xml">
Kent Conrad</link></senator>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Senate</col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/11916602.xml">
Senate Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Subcommittee on Federal Financial Management, Government Information, and International Security</link></col>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/339186.xml">
Thomas Carper</link></col>
</row>
</table>

<indent level="1">

<it>This table incorporates information available on the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/OfficeofLegislation/COI/list.asp">
CMS Website</weblink></it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2252%22])">52</ref>
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<table style="background:transparent; width:100%;" cellpadding="0" class=" multicol" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col align="left" width="50%" valign="top">
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/1704507.xml">
Administration on Aging</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/15343730.xml">
Health insurance in the United States</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/8695082.xml">
Health care politics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/15162878.xml">
List of healthcare accreditation organisations in the USA</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/58499.xml">
Medicare (Australia)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/58354.xml">
Medicare (Canada)</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
<col align="left" width="50%" valign="top">
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/19485093.xml">
Medicare Rights Center</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/16462572.xml">
National Health Service</link> (<autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/15475369.xml">
Philosophy of Healthcare</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/1666023.xml">
Quality improvement organizations</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/892717.xml">
Stark Law</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>



<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ssa.gov/history/lbjsm.html">
Social Security Online History Pages</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.actuary.org/pdf/medicare/medicare_actuary_jan02.pdf">
"What Is the Role of the Federal Medicare Actuary?,"</weblink> <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/3697300.xml">
American Academy of Actuaries</link></organization>
, January 2002</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.actuarialstandardsboard.org/pdf/asops/asop032_062.pdf">
 "Social Insurance,"</weblink> Actuarial Standard of Practice No. 32, Actuarial Standards Board, January 1998</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/ReportsTrustFunds">
Trustees Report &amp; Trust Funds Overview</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uihealthcare.com/topics/aging/agin3390.html">
Medicare: Part A &amp; B</weblink>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/2631157.xml">
University of Iowa Hospitals and Clinics</link>, 2005.</entry>
<entry id="6">
National Center for Policy Analysis. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncpa.org/sub/dpd/index.php?Article_ID=14346">
Daily Policy Digest.</weblink> Retrieved 26 March 2007.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Mark Merlis, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kff.org/medicare/upload/7744.pdf">
"The Value of Extra Benefits Offered by Medicare Advantage Plans in 2006,"</weblink> The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/4423394.xml">
Kaiser Family Foundation</link>, January 2008</entry>
<entry id="8">
National Center for Policy Analysis. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncpa.org/sub/dpd/index.php?Article_ID=14346">
Daily Policy Digest.</weblink> Retrieved 26 March 2007.</entry>
<entry id="9">
America’s Health Insurance Plans. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahipresearch.org/PDFs/CPRMakingDifference.pdf">
Trends and Innovations in Chronic Disease Prevention and Treatment,</weblink> April 2008. Retrieved on 30 September 2008.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Marsha Gold, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kff.org/medicare/upload/7775.pdf">
"Medicare Advantage in 2008,"</weblink> The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/4423394.xml">
Kaiser Family Foundation</link>, June 2008</entry>
<entry id="11">
Christelle Chen, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahipresearch.org/pdfs/MALowIncomeReport2008.pdf">
"LOW-INCOME &amp; MINORITY BENEFICIARIES IN MEDICARE ADVANTAGE PLANS, 2006,"</weblink> <link>
America’s Health Insurance Plans</link>, September 2008</entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/PrescriptionDrugCovContra/Downloads/PartDDrugsPartDExcludedDrugs_04.19.06.pdf">
Product/Drug/Drug Category</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/PrescriptionDrugCovGenIn/Downloads/PartBandPartDdoc_07.27.05.pdf">
Relationship between Part B and Part D Coverage</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://oig.hhs.gov/oas/reports/region6/60600022.pdf">
Report on the Medicare Drug Discount Card Program Sponsor McKesson Health Solutions, A-06-06-00022</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
2008 Medicare &amp; You handbook, Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services.</entry>
<entry id="17">
KEVIN FREKING, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/national/1152ap_medicare_premiums.html">
"No rise in monthly Medicare premiums for 2009,"</weblink> <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/432612.xml">
Seattle Post-Intelligencer</link></newspaper>
, September 19, 2008</entry>
<entry id="16">
Victoria Colliver, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2008/09/20/BU1O131A2F.DTL&amp;hw=medicare+premiums&amp;sn=001&amp;sc=1000">
"For most, Medicare premiums won't rise in 2009,"</weblink> <newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/319442.xml">
San Francisco Chronicle</link></newspaper>
, September 20, 2008</entry>
<entry id="19">
Lauren A. McCormick,  Russel T. Burge.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0795/is_n2_v16/ai_16863013">
Diffusion of Medicare's RBRVS and related physician payment policies - resource-based relative value scale - Medicare Payment Systems: Moving Toward the Future</weblink> <it><link>
Health Care Financing Review</link></it>. Winter, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/18948337.xml">
1994</link>.</entry>
<entry id="18">
 Jeff Lemieux, Teresa Chovan, and Karen Heath, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.healthaffairs.org/cgi/reprint/27/2/469">
"Medigap Coverage And Medicare Spending: A Second Look,"</weblink> <link>
Health Affairs</link>, Volume 27, Number 2, March/April 2008</entry>
<entry id="21">
Lisa Potetz, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kff.org/medicare/upload/7731.pdf">
"Financing Medicare: an Issue Brief,"</weblink> the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/4423394.xml">
Kaiser Family Foundation</link>, January 2008</entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdoc.cfm?index=7425&amp;type=1">
Medicare's Physician Payment Rates and the Sustainable Growth Rate</weblink>.(PDF) <it>CBO TESTIMONY Statement of Donald B. Marron, Acting Director</it>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/15804.xml">
July 25</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>.</entry>
<entry id="23">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/ReportsTrustFunds/downloads/tr2008.pdf">
"2008 ANNUAL REPORT OF THE BOARDS OF TRUSTEES OF THE FEDERAL HOSPITAL INSURANCE AND FEDERAL SUPPLEMENTARY MEDICAL INSURANCE TRUST FUNDS,"</weblink> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/215745.xml">
Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services</link>, March 25, 2008</entry>
<entry id="22">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.californiahealthline.org/articles/2008/3/26/Annual-Federal-Report-Forecasts-Medicare-Funding-Gap-by-2019.aspx?topicID=37">
Annual Federal Report Forecasts Medicare Funding Gap by 2019 - California Healthline</weblink></entry>
<entry id="25">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kaisernetwork.org/daily_reports/rep_index.cfm?DR_ID=51311">
"Medicare: Paying Medicare Advantage Plans Same Rates as Traditional Medicare Would Delay Program Insolvency by 18 Months, Medicare Actuary Says,"</weblink> Kaiser Daily Health Policy Report, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/4423394.xml">
Kaiser Family Foundation</link>, April 02, 2008</entry>
<entry id="24">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.actuary.org/pdf/medicare/trustees_08.pdf">
"Medicare’s Financial Condition: Beyond Actuarial Balance,"</weblink> <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/3697300.xml">
American Academy of Actuaries</link></organization>
, March 2008</entry>
<entry id="27">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.8">
<executive wordnetid="110069645" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<administrator wordnetid="109770949" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<corporate_executive wordnetid="109966255" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head wordnetid="110162991" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/8007435.xml">
Richard W. Fisher</link></scholar>
</head>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</corporate_executive>
</intellectual>
</administrator>
</leader>
</person>
</executive>
</president>
</physical_entity>
&#32;(2008-05-28).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dallasfed.org/news/speeches/fisher/2008/fs080528.cfm">
Storms on the Horizon</weblink>".&#32;  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<slope wordnetid="109437454" confidence="0.8">
<geological_formation wordnetid="109287968" confidence="0.8">
<bank wordnetid="109213565" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/2338776.xml">
Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas</link></bank>
</geological_formation>
</slope>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-18</link>.&nbsp;"Medicare was a pay-as-you-go program from the very beginning, despite warnings from some congressional leaders—Wilbur Mills was the most credible of them before he succumbed to the pay-as-you-go wiles of Fanne Foxe, the Argentine Firecracker—who foresaw some of the long-term fiscal issues such a financing system could pose. Unfortunately, they were right. Please sit tight while I walk you through the math of Medicare. As you may know, the program comes in three parts: Medicare Part A, which covers hospital stays; Medicare B, which covers doctor visits; and Medicare D, the drug benefit that went into effect just 29 months ago. The infinite-horizon present discounted value of the unfunded liability for Medicare A is $34.4 trillion. The unfunded liability of Medicare B is an additional $34 trillion. The shortfall for Medicare D adds another $17.2 trillion. The total? If you wanted to cover the unfunded liability of all three programs today, you would be stuck with an $85.6 trillion bill. That is more than six times as large as the bill for Social Security. It is more than six times the annual output of the entire U.S. economy."</entry>
<entry id="26">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdocs/93xx/doc9385/06-17-LTBO_Testimony.pdf">
CBO Testimony</weblink></entry>
<entry id="29">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.publicagenda.org/charts/fewer-workers-projected-hi-beneficiary">
Public Agenda, Fewer Workers Projected Per HI Beneficiary</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 25, 2008.</entry>
<entry id="28">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gao.gov/financial/fy2007/07frusg.pdf">
2007 Report of the U.S. Government Page 47</weblink></entry>
<entry id="31">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/ReportsTrustFunds/downloads/tr2006.pdf">
2006 Annual Report of the Boards of Trustees of the Federal Hospital Insurance and Federal Supplimentary Medical Insurance Trust Funds, 1 May 2006 (PDF)</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="30">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.publicagenda.org/charts/medicare-costs-person">
Public Agenda, Medicare Costs Per Person</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 25, 2008.</entry>
<entry id="34">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/ReportsTrustFunds/downloads/tr2006.pdf">
"High-Risk Series: An Update" U.S. Government Accountability Office, January 2003 (PDF)</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on July 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="35">
Carrie Johnson, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/06/12/AR2008061203915.html">
"Medical Fraud a Growing Problem: Medicare Pays Most Claims Without Review,"</weblink> The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/102226.xml">
Washington Post</link>, June 13, 2008</entry>
<entry id="32">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gao.gov/docdblite/summary.php?rptno=GAO-05-656&amp;accno=A37738">
U.S. GAO - Report Abstract</weblink></entry>
<entry id="33">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d02546.pdf">
Medicare Fraud and Abuse: DOJ Continues to Promote Compliance with False Claims Act Guidance</weblink>, GAO Report to Congressional Committees, April 2002</entry>
<entry id="38">
Fried, Joseph, <it>Democrats and Republicans - Rhetoric and Reality</it> (New York: Algora Publishing, 2008), 216.</entry>
<entry id="39">
Fried, Joseph, <it>Democrats and Republicans - Rhetoric and Reality</it> (New York: Algora Publishing, 2008), 217.</entry>
<entry id="36">
C. Eugene Steuerle and Adam Carasso, "The USA Today Lifetime Social Security and Medicare Benefits Calculator," (Urban Institute, October 1, 2004)<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.urban.org/publications/900746.html">
http://www.urban.org/publications/900746.html</weblink></entry>
<entry id="37">
Fried, Joseph, <it>Democrats and Republicans - Rhetoric and Reality</it> (New York: Algora Publishing, 2008), 215.</entry>
<entry id="42">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.publicagenda.org/citizen/issueguides/medicare/publicview/redflags">
Medicare: Red Flags</weblink></entry>
<entry id="43">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d011141t.pdf">
Improvements Needed in Provider Communications and Contracting Procedures</weblink>, Testimony Before the Subcommittee on Health, Committee on Ways and Means, House of Representatives, 25 September 2001</entry>
<entry id="40">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/apps/media/press/release.asp?Counter=1846">
2006 MEDICARE TRUSTEES REPORT</weblink></entry>
<entry id="41">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.publicagenda.org/citizen/issueguides/medicare/publicview/people-concerns">
Medicare: People's Chief Concerns</weblink></entry>
<entry id="46">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1272/is_n2630_v126/ai_20004039">
 Medicare funding for medical education: a waste of money?</weblink></entry>
<entry id="47">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ama-assn.org/amednews/2006/01/30/prl20130.htm">
Innovative funding opens new residency slots</weblink></entry>
<entry id="44">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/QuarterlyProviderUpdates/APR2006/ItemDetail.asp?ItemID=CMS060161">
Quarterly Provider Updates</weblink></entry>
<entry id="45">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medlaw.com/healthlaw/HOSPITAL/6_3/new-competitor-takes-on-j.shtml">
MedLaw.com :: New Competitor Takes On JCAHO Accreditation</weblink></entry>
<entry id="51">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/02/health/policy/02health.html">
"House Passes Children’s Health Plan 225-204"</weblink>, <it>New York Times</it>, August 2, 2007]</entry>
<entry id="50">
Aliza Marcus, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601070&amp;sid=a8.4kZl7x03E&amp;refer=home">
"Senate Vote on Doctor Fees Carries Risks for McCain"</weblink>, <it>Bloomberg News</it>, July 9, 2008</entry>
<entry id="49">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ama-assn.org/amednews/2006/01/30/prl20130.htm">
 Innovative funding opens new residency slots</weblink></entry>
<entry id="48">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/295/9/1042">
 Shortages of Medical Personnel at Community Health Centers - JAMA, March 1, 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry id="52">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/OfficeofLegislation/COI/list.asp">
Congressional Committees of Interest</weblink>, CMS Website, accessed 2/15/07</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section contains an excessive number of external links.
According to Wikipedia , links should be kept to a minimum. It is not Wikipedia's purpose to include a comprehensive list of external links related to each topic.</b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Governmental links - current </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cms.hhs.gov">
CMS official web site</weblink> at cms.hhs.gov</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cms.hhs.gov/home/medicare.asp">
Medicare</weblink> at cms.hhs.gov</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.gov/">
Medicare.gov</weblink> &mdash; the official website for people with Medicare</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.gov/Publications/Search/SearchCriteria.asp">
Official Medicare publications</weblink> at Medicare.gov &mdash; includes official publications about current Medicare benefits</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.gov/Publications/Pubs/pdf/10050.pdf">
Medicare &amp; You handbook</weblink> for 2008 at Medicare.gov &mdash; includes information about current Medicare benefits</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.gov/callcenter.asp">
Information about the 1-800-MEDICARE helpline</weblink> from Medicare.gov &mdash; a 24X7 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/406726.xml">
toll-free number</link> to call with questions about Medicare</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.gov/medicarereform/default.asp">
Medicare Modernization Act</weblink> at Medicare.gov </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.gov/Choices/Overview.asp">
Medicare Plan Choices</weblink> at Medicare.gov &mdash; basic information about plan choices for Medicare beneficiaries, including MA Plans</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.gov/pdphome.asp">
Prescription Drug Coverage homepage</weblink> at Medicare.gov &mdash; a central location for Medicare's web-based information about the Part D benefit</entry>
<entry level="3" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.gov/medicarereform/map.asp">
Landscape of plans</weblink> &mdash; state-by-state breakdown of all plans available in an area, both stand-alone PDPs, as well as MA-PD plans</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mymedicare.gov/">
MyMedicare.gov</weblink> &mdash; Medicare's secure online service where beneficiaries can access their own personal Medicare information</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Governmental links - historical </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ssa.gov/history/lbjsm.html">
Medicare Is Signed Into Law</weblink> page from ssa.gov &mdash; material about the bill-signing ceremony</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ssa.gov/history/briefhistory3.html">
Historical Background and Development of Social Security</weblink> from ssa.gov &mdash; includes information about Medicare</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ssa.gov/history/chrono.html">
Detailed Chronology of SSA</weblink> from ssa.gov &mdash; includes information about Medicare</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ssa.gov/history/near65s.html">
Early Medicare poster</weblink> from ssa.gov</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Non-governmental links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search/?q=medicare&amp;t=fulltext&amp;nlow=&amp;nhi=">
Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports related to Medicare</weblink> from the University of Texas Libraries</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicareadvocacy.org">
Center for Medicare Advocacy</weblink> &mdash; National education &amp; advocacy organization.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicarerights.org">
Medicare Rights Center</weblink> &mdash; Education and advocacy organization.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicareinteractive.org">
Medicare Interactive</weblink> &mdash; Online Medicare reference guide created by the Medicare Rights Center.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicare.org">
Medicare.org</weblink> &mdash; Medicare information site including descriptions of Part A through D</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.agis.com/Eldercare-Basics/Legal-and-Financial/Medicare-and-Medicaid/">
Medicare &amp; Medicaid Resources</weblink> &mdash; Medicare information site</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kff.org/medicare">
Kaiser Family Foundation</weblink> &mdash; Wide range of free information, including a drug benefit calculator, about the Medicare program and other U.S. health issues.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.statehealthfacts.org">
State Health Facts</weblink> &mdash; Data on health care spending and utilization, including Medicare; provided by the Kaiser Family Foundation.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.allhealth.org/issues.asp?wi=7">
Medicare - Alliance for Health Reform</weblink> The nonpartisan, nonprofit Alliance for Health Reform offers information about health reform, in a number of formats, to elected officials and their staffs, journalists, policy analysts and advocates.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ssdrc.com/medicare.html">
Social Security and Disability News Resource Center</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.publicagenda.org/citizen/issueguides/medicare">
Issue Guide on Medicare</weblink> &mdash; Policy alternatives and public opinion analysis on Medicare from Public Agenda Online</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://health.howstuffworks.com/medicare.htm">
How Stuff Works - Medicare</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
