<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:55:22[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>ND-NOTIS</title>
<id>5851855</id>
<revision>
<id>215995799</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-30T16:39:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Business software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>ND-NOTIS</b> was a tightly integrated yet modular office automation suite by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/194777.xml">
Norsk Data</link></institution>
</company>
 introduced in the early 80s, running on the <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/3302313.xml">
SINTRAN III</link></O>
 platform on both <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/3502921.xml">
ND-100</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/3502981.xml">
ND-500</link> architectures. It was also available on MS Windows running in networks of Norsk Data servers.<p>

It was very successful, and was the main product line of the company for quite a while, cementing its position in the Norwegian government <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/5649998.xml">
office automation</link> market. It was also very popular in Germany and in the UK (local municipality, DHSS etc) </p>
<p>

The NOTIS family of products was presented to the British Computing Society by Jeremy Salter. Roger Tagg et al. (BCS, End User SG, 1985) and endorsed as the BCS model for user interface. The same endorsement was awarded to NOTIS-IR as a model for information storage and retrieval. the European Commission published in 1985 NOTIS-IR as reference model for document and information search and retrieval.</p>
<p>

Where it was offered it had no real competitors. There are still features and functionality that no other system supports - such as multilingual input and search.</p>
<p>

Norsk Data also sold custom-made <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/194787.xml">
Tandberg Data</link></company>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/5862357.xml">
TDV-2200</link> terminals as "NOTIS terminals" with special keys for text editing. Other terminals were "endorsed" and branded as "NOTIS Terminals" - including the Facit "Twist" - that would show a page standing.</p>
<p>

Components included:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-WP</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> <b>W</b>ord <b>P</b>rocessor, a full text editing environment optimized for word processing.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-DS</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> <b>D</b>ocument <b>S</b>tore, a database of documents based on the <link>
SIBAS</link> relational database.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-BS</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> <b>B</b>ackup <b>S</b>ystem, an advanced system used for automated and incremental backups of a DS document store.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-ID</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> mail system. Proprietary e-mail system. It was later interfaced to Notis-Mail (see below).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-Mail</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> full <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/363697.xml">
X.400</link></system_of_measurement>
</advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 e-mail system, including a <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/61366.xml">
X.500</link></system_of_measurement>
</advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 based directory service (implemented using <link>
SIBAS</link>) and TCP/IP based SMTP mail.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-TF</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> <b>T</b>ext <b>F</b>ormatter, a text formatting system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-RG</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> <b>R</b>eport <b>G</b>enerator, a powerful data extracting and modifying system. Often used together with database systems like Norsk Data SIBAS-II or Oracle.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-RP</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> <b>R</b>eport <b>P</b>roducer, closely integreated witn NOTIS-RG.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-CALC</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> Spreadsheet program, similar to VisiCalc and later successors like Microsoft Excel</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-ENCRYPT</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> Encryption software.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-IR</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> <b>I</b>nformation <b>R</b>etrieval, a document database with free text search allowing full multi-site search.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

 NOTIS-QUERY</entry>
<entry level="1" type="indent">

 <b>NOTIS</b> Database query and application generation program, similar to MS Access.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
General</st>

<p>

<b>NOTIS</b> was unique then and still is. It captured the notion of diffent user interfaces, or terminals; and managed a common user interface for all applications that used the platform. So a key on the keyboard would in all applications "mean" the same. </p>
<p>

It relied on an interface system "User Environment" to hold in one place all user profile and preferences. That is everything from log-in name and password, language preference, application skills and user rights to see, edit and change document - or data in applications. It came as a full "Document management" package, with full support for workflow - which was used by 3rd party application software. </p>
<p>

Another first was multi-lingual support, - also part of the user interface. Regardless of where you logged on, the system would know of your preferences, and allow you to resume last task. The system also supported full editing from right to left. All deliveries to the public sector required capability to use three language, and that in the same office, all three languages would be used. So to sell in its main market, it need multilingual support. That included all messages, error messages and user interaction. The error messages could also be adapter from "novice" to "expert".</p>
<p>

An important "first" was the full support for SGML - or "S-code". This allow the text editor to be used to edit and view the first HTML documents created - on hardware running NOTIS. The alternate character set - "T-code" was the CCITT, now ITU T.56 standard character set - used in all television sets to show teletext/"Text TV". So, the systems had full support for semi-graphical input and display, but just a few terminals supported this. Beware that an important customer was CERN, where they at the end of the 1980s worked on what you are now using - the WWW. ND-NOTIS had full support for HTML at that time.</p>
<p>

The main "first" - WYSIWYG - What you see is what you get. In 1983, most text editors used "codes" that had to be inserted in the text - and even in the early days of text editors on Windows, many text systems were like that. However, NOTIS had been around for some time, and shown where the line ended and a new page started for a decennium then.</p>
<p>

The "back-end" to all these modules were also flexible. You had direct file system exposure - that included network mounted files. However, with <it>NOTIS-DS</it> it included "Document Storage" and management - a full Electronic Document Management System (as found in systems such as Documentum and OpenText's Livelink today). The EDMS was based on a generic software interface, but only SIBAS was used commercially. This allowed fully localisation transparent document storage and retrieval. That of course demanded NOTIS-IR to search in all the documents. Software today used to power both Google and Altavista.</p>
<p>

NOTIS-ID was a "special" NOTIS-DS, with restricted functionalty, in that this would interface to "mail" exchanges only. So if you stored a document to an email-recipient, you sent an email. Likewise, if you received an email, this would appear in your mail-count, and you could read it in NOTIS-WP like any other document.</p>
<p>

Norsk Data needed <it>NOTIS</it> to avoid duplicating applications. So the software was used in professional text production systems, for newspaper and magazine production - by "NORTEXT". It was reviewed a number of times here and found to be "best of breed" by e.g. the Seybold Report on newspaper systems. Hence demanding users were close to the developers - which may explain the success.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications beside Text and Document Management</st>

<p>

The list here will become endless since <b>NOTIS</b> was linked to three application generators - beside the Query part. This was fully capable of making large applications system, that could also update databases. The most successful link was to "Unique" - an application package developed outside Norsk Data to support SIBAS but later was enhanced to interface to a number of RDBMS. The other platforms were "BIM" (Business Information Systems) and "ABM" (Application Building and Maintenance). A full interface was made to "Systemator" to provide full support to newspaper systems generated by this. Norsk Data marketed and sold the system as integrated with their offerings for the medical sector ("Infomedica") and hospital systems;- for local community in Scandinavia and the UK based on Unique(i.e.DIALOGUE-1); - for engineering documentation in Europe: CAD/CAM as Technovision and even to the F-16 Flight Simulator.</p>
<p>

NOTIS-QUERY - also marketed by Norsk Data as "Access-1" (and presented to Microsoft under this name - so you wonder), is still commercially available as "QBEvision" and has been licensed under several names with full product sold by CA.</p>
<p>

The NOTIS family was fully ported to Microsoft Windows, but was incredibly difficult to move with its huge customer base. For a time there were plans to include "Ami" into the family, to gain some market momentum - but its very difficult to move when your users do not want to make the change and are so happy with the way things are.</p>
<p>

The <it>NOTIS</it> family was ported to Norsk Data NDIX <family wordnetid="108078020" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
Unix</link></family>
 line, but here suffered because Unix had problems with coping with the key sequences required (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/10904051.xml">
terminfo</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/10904287.xml">
termcap</link> was incomplete by a mile or two).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External</st>

<p>

The NOTIS way of sorting was included in the first version of Sybase, which was acquired by Microsoft as DS1. This taught Microsoft to arrange sort sequences in Windows according to national character sets ("codepage").</p>
<p>

There is still no other system available that will grant you "only one user interface and make all into one system". You have to fill in the expense report in Oracle HR and type the letter summarising the reason for the expense in some other text editor. With Notis, you clicked on field for providing the information, and WP would fire up, allowing you to write the letter - not as in Wikipedia where you have to supply own mark-up, but with the document template ready. The complete document would then be stored in the application database, with the expense report data.</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
