<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:07:20[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<school  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276720">
<educational_institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276342">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>Newtownabbey Community High School</title>
<id>5874319</id>
<revision>
<id>225076480</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-11T19:38:38Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DinosaursLoveExistence</username>
<id>666342</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Schools damaged by arson</category>
<category>Secondary schools in County Antrim</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Newtownabbey Community High School</b> is a secondary school on <it>Rathcoole Drive</it> in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/1417436.xml">
Newtownabbey</link></site>
.
<sec>
<st>
Staff</st>
<p>

Principal: Mr. Robert Holmes B.Ed., B.A.(Hons.), Adv.Dip.Ed., M.A.
Chairperson of the Board of Governors: Mr. William Snoddy</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mission Statement</st>
<p>

Newtownabbey Community High School is a caring, well-ordered school committed to high standards and positive relationships within an actively involved community, offering opportunities for success to each child, while promoting excellence for all.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Newtownabbey Community High School, founded in 1994, is a controlled, co-educational school providing secondary level education for girls and boys of all ability levels.  The school occupies spacious buildings on a mature wooded site and its location on the Shore Road at Whitehouse allows easy access on foot, and by public transport from the Greater Newtownabbey area, Greenisland and Belfast.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
School in the Community</st>
<p>

The school seeks to serve its community through a Community Education Program for students of all ages, day and evening.  Much of this programme is facilitated by the school’s innovative, purpose built Community Education Centre.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Curriculum</st>
<p>

In line with the Northern Ireland Education Order, Newtownabbey Community High offers each child a broad and balanced curriculum.  At Key Stage 3 pupils are grouped by ability and all study the following subjects: Mathematics, English, Science, Art &amp; Design, French, Geography, History, Home Economics, Information &amp; Communication Technology, Learning for Life &amp; Work, Music, Physical Education, Religious Education, and Technology.  Pupils with special educational needs are given support by specialist teachers.  This may involve small group work or individual help.</p>
<p>

At Key Stage 4, in addition to the core curriculum, the school seeks to provide varied opportunities and experiences for its pupils by offering a wide range of subjects.  The school also provides a structured careers programme which includes a period of work experience.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Pastoral Care</st>
<p>

The school regards the well-being of each individual pupil as of the utmost importance. Each pupil has a Form Tutor who deals with day to day matters, and each year group has a Key Stage Head responsible for general welfare and guidance.  Parents can discuss their child’s progress and receive information through regular evening meetings with Subject Teachers, Form Tutors and Key Stage Heads.  Individual interviews with Key Stage Heads, Vice-Principal or Principal can also be arranged.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Extra Curricular Activities</st>
<p>

Newtownabbey Community High school values the place of extra-curricula activities. A wide range of clubs and societies is offered. These include Art Club, Choir, Craft Club, Educational trips to Europe, Environmental Club and Scripture Union, Sports activities include Athletics, Badminton, Basketball, Fitness Training, Football (Girls and Boys), Hockey, Netball, Rugby, and Swimming.  A supervised Homework Club also operates in the Community Education Centre and there are many after school GCSE classes.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Address: Rathcoole Drive, Whitehouse, Newtownabbey BT37 9AD</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nchs.info">
School website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/5230388.stm">
Arson attack July 30 2006</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</article>
