<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:08:59[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Toffy Musivand</title>
<id>5919512</id>
<revision>
<id>240635488</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-24T07:51:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Samm2009</username>
<id>7927663</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> Living people</category>
<category> Cardiologists</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Toffy Musivand</b> <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/11600.xml">
Persian</link></language>
: توفیق موسیوند (Born in <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/321158.xml">
Hamedan</link></city>
) is an <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/14653.xml">
Iranian</link></country>
 physician and engineer and a world class cardiologist residing in Canada.<p>

He studied Medicine and Engineering at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/159999.xml">
Tehran University</link> and <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/242057.xml">
University of Alberta</link></university>
. Toffy Musivand is known for the invention of Artificial Cardiac Pump. Cardiac pump or cardiac bypass pump or heart-lung machine temporarily takes over the function of breathing and pumping blood for a patient. It generally has two parts, the pump and the aerator.  Cardiac pumps are most often used in heart surgery, so that a patient's heart can be disconnected from the body for longer than the twenty minutes or so it takes a prepared patient to die. </p>
<p>

Tofy Mussivand received his undergraduate education and training in engineering and management. Following many successful years in senior positions in Canadian government, crown corporations, and the private sector, Dr. Mussivand went on to receive his doctorate in Medical Engineering and Medical Sciences at the University of Akron and Northeastern Ohio Universities College of Medicine. Thereafter, Dr. Mussivand joined the internationally acclaimed Cleveland Clinic Hospital and Research Foundation where he gained invaluable knowledge and experience in the development of medical devices, artificial hearts, and cardiac care. In 1989, Dr. Mussivand was invited to return to Canada to continue his pioneering work in the field of medical devices.</p>
<p>

Dr. Mussivand has achieved global recognition. His breakthroughs have resulted in the establishment of scientific eminence for Canada in the fields of medical devices, artificial hearts, remote power transfer, in situ sterilization, etc.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ottawaheart.ca/UOHI/bio/Tofy_Mussivand.jsp">
http://www.ottawaheart.ca/UOHI/bio/Tofy_Mussivand.jsp</weblink></p>
<p>

Presently, he is Professor of Surgery and Engineering at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/140699.xml">
University of Ottawa</link></university>
 and <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/209134.xml">
Carleton University</link></university>
; Chair and Director, Cardiovascular Devices Division of the <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/1020336.xml">
University of Ottawa Heart Institute</link></hospital>
 (UOHI); and Medical Devices Program of both the University of Ottawa and Carleton University. He is also an honorary member of Iranian Academy of Medical Sciences.</p>
<p>

Dr. Mussivand has published over 250 papers, books, and technical articles and supervised and taught over 300 students, residents, and postdoctoral Fellows.</p>

<p>

TOFFY IN ARABIC also is a type of sweet that is mainly made of milk sugar and cream..in English called toffee  
toffy also a brand name for an online store (http://toffy.zlio.net).it contain collection of great high qualities number 1 brands from famous and trusted companies that deals beauty , health and related products like ACCESSORIES ,books in the most affordable prices</p>
</bdy>
</article>
