<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:58:24[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<rule  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105846932">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<procedure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="101023820">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<algorithm  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105847438">
<header>
<title>Critical path method</title>
<id>5939406</id>
<revision>
<id>242950656</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-04T12:21:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Harda</username>
<id>227273</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Business terms</category>
<category>Management</category>
<category>Production and manufacturing</category>
<category>Operations research</category>
<category>Scheduling algorithms</category>
<category>Project management</category>
<category>Network theory</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<image width="309px" src="Pert_chart_colored.gif" type="thumb">
</image>
</p>
<p>

The <b>Critical Path Method</b>, abbreviated <b>CPM</b>, or <b>critical path analysis</b>, is a mathematically based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> for scheduling a set of project activities.  It is an important tool for effective <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/24042.xml">
project management</link>.  </p>
<p>

It was developed in the 1950s by the US Navy when trying to better organise the building of submarines and later, especially, when building nuclear submarines. Today, it is commonly used with all forms of projects, including construction, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> development, research projects, product development, engineering, and plant maintenance, among others.  Any project with interdependent activities can apply this method of scheduling.</p>
<p>

The essential technique for using CPM is to construct a model of the project that includes the following:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 A list of all activities required to complete the project (also known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/33598.xml">
Work breakdown structure</link>), </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The time (duration) that each activity will take to completion, and </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/206457.xml">
dependencies</link> between the activities.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Using these values, CPM calculates the longest path of planned activities to the end of the project, and the earliest and latest that each activity can start and finish without making the project longer.  This process determines which activities are "critical" (i.e., on the longest path) and which have "total float" (i.e., can be delayed without making the project longer).  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/24042.xml">
project management</link>, a <b>critical path</b> is the sequence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../941/752941.xml">
project network</link> activities which add up to the longest overall <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/1655471.xml">
duration</link>.  This determines the shortest time possible to complete the project. Any delay of an activity on the critical path directly impacts the planned project completion date (i.e. there is no <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/401024.xml">
float</link> on the critical path).  A project can have several, parallel, near critical paths.  An additional parallel path through the network with the total durations shorter than the critical path is called a sub-critical or non-critical path.</p>
<p>

These results allow managers to prioritize activities for the effective management of project completion, and to shorten the planned critical path of a project by pruning critical path activities, by "<b>fast tracking</b>" (i.e., performing more activities in parallel), and/or by "<b>crashing the critical path</b>" (i.e., shortening the durations of critical path activities by adding resources). </p>
<p>

Originally, the critical path method considered only logical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/206457.xml">
dependencies</link> between terminal elements.  Since then, it has been expanded to allow for the inclusion of resources related to each activity, through processes called activity-based resource assignments and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/8756738.xml">
resource leveling</link>.  A resource-leveled schedule may include delays due to resource bottlenecks (i.e., unavailability of a resource at the required time), and may cause a previously shorter path to become the longest or "resource critical" path.  A related concept is called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/183373.xml">
critical chain</link>, which attempts to protect activity and project durations from unforeseen delays due to resource constraints.</p>
<p>

Since project schedules change on a regular basis, CPM allows continuous monitoring of the schedule, allows the project manager to track the critical activities, and alerts the project manager to the possibility that non-critical activities may be delayed beyond their total float, thus creating a new critical path and delaying project completion.  In addition, the method can easily incorporate the concepts of stochastic predictions, using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/206886.xml">
Program Evaluation and Review Technique</link> (PERT) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/10061279.xml">
event chain methodology</link>.</p>
<p>

Currently, there are several software solutions available in industry that use the CPM method of scheduling, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/2265048.xml">
list of project management software</link>.  However, the method was developed and used  without the aid of computers.</p>
<p>

A schedule generated using critical path techniques often is not realized precisely, as estimations are used to calculate times: if one mistake is made, the results of the analysis may change.  This could cause an upset in the implementation of a project if the estimates are blindly believed, and if changes are not addressed promptly.  However, the structure of critical path analysis is such that the variance from the original schedule caused by any change can be measured, and its impact either ameliorated or adjusted for.  Indeed, an important element of project postmortem analysis is the As Built Critical Path (ABCP), which analyzes the specific causes and impacts of changes between the planned schedule and eventual schedule as actually implemented.    </p>

<sec>
<st>
Literature</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Project Management Institute&#32;(2003). A Guide To The Project Management Body Of Knowledge, 3rd ed.,&#32;Project Management Institute. ISBN 1-930699-45-X.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Klastorin-2003" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Klastorin, Ted&#32;(2003). Project Management: Tools and Trade-offs, 3rd ed.,&#32;Wiley. ISBN 978-0471413844.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Heerkens-2001" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Heerkens, Gary&#32;(2001). Project Management (The Briefcase Book Series).&#32;McGraw-Hill. ISBN 0-07-137952-5.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Kerzner-2003" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Kerzner, Harold&#32;(2003). Project Management: A Systems Approach to Planning, Scheduling, and Controlling, 8th Ed.,&#32;Wiley. ISBN 0-471-22577-0.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Lewis-2002" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Lewis, James&#32;(2002). Fundamentals of Project Management, 2nd ed.,&#32;American Management Association. ISBN 0-8144-7132-3.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Lev Virine &amp; Michael Trumper&#32;(2007). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.projectdecisions.org">
Project Decisions: The Art and Science</weblink>.&#32;Management Concepts. ISBN 978-1567262179.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Milosevic-2003" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Milosevic, Dragan Z.&#32;(2003). Project Management ToolBox: Tools and Techniques for the Practicing Project Manager.&#32;Wiley. ISBN 978-0471208228.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <cite id="Reference-Woolf-2007" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Woolf, Murray B.&#32;(2007). Faster Construction Projects with CPM Scheduling.&#32;McGraw Hill. ISBN 978-0071486606.</cite>&nbsp;Critical Path method</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/2265048.xml">
List of project management software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/400309.xml">
List of project management topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/206886.xml">
Program Evaluation and Review Technique</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/160483.xml">
Project</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/24042.xml">
Project management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/75500.xml">
Project planning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/33598.xml">
Work breakdown structure</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sporkforge.com/sched/critical_path.php">
Critical path web calculator</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pmhut.com/category/time-management/critical-path/">
A Few Critical Path Articles</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.slideshare.net/dmdk12/the-network-diagram-and-critical-path">
A good slide show explaining critical path concepts</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</article>
