<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:23:19[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Charitable contribution</title>
<id>596649</id>
<revision>
<id>239877027</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-20T22:41:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Andrew Kelly</username>
<id>7732267</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Charities</category>
<category>Taxation in the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Charitable contribution deductions</b> for <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/3136256.xml">
Federal Income Tax</link> purposes are defined in section 170(c) of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/1836327.xml">
Internal Revenue Code</link> as contributions to or for the use of certain nonprofit enterprises. See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/1836327.xml">
26 U.S.C.</link>&nbsp;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/26/170(c)..html">
|&nbsp;170(c).</weblink>
<sec>
<st>
 Organization Eligibility </st>
<p>

An organization must meet certain requirements set forth in the Code. Some organizations must also file a request with the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/15375.xml">
Internal Revenue Service</link></agency>
 to gain status as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/960403.xml">
tax-exempt</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
non-profit</link> charitable organization under section <link>
501(c)(3)</link> of the tax code.</p>
<p>

A non-exhaustive list of organizations that may meet the Federal requirements are as follows:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/48559.xml">
Synagogue</link>s, <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/6325.xml">
churches</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/25414.xml">
religious</link> organizations;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A fraternal order or lodge</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

An organization of war <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/327806.xml">
veterans</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Any level of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/12229.xml">
government</link> if the contribution is made for exclusively public purposes</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

An organization dedicated to the improvement of public health in the U.S. or abroad</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

There are both public and private charities.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.charitynavigator.org/">
Public charities</weblink> are far more common.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 General Statement on Benefit to Donor </st>
<p>

Contributions to charitable organizations are deductible to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/3553571.xml">
donor</link>, <it>unless</it> the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/367725.xml">
donee</link> organization uses any of its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/1076393.xml">
net earnings</link> to benefit a private shareholder, or if it attempts to in any way influence political campaigns or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/51913.xml">
legislation</link>.  </p>
<p>

A contribution to a charitable organization need not be fully a "gift" in the statutory sense of the word to be deductible to the donor.  However, the donor's allowable deduction will be reduced by the amount of the "substantial benefit" conferred upon her as a result of her contribution.</p>
<p>

To illustrate, suppose that the <financial_institution wordnetid="108054721" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="108406486" confidence="0.8">
<charity wordnetid="108406619" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/522681.xml">
American Cancer Society</link></institution>
</charity>
</foundation>
</financial_institution>
 is hosting a formal dance as a fund-raiser (the ACS is a certified charitable organization).  Further suppose that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/1436263.xml">
fair market value</link> of a ticket to the dance is 75 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/18717338.xml">
USD</link>, and the donor pays 375 USD to purchase a ticket thereto.  The donor may claim only a 300 USD deduction, because the amount contributed (375 USD) is reduced by the amount of the benefit that she received (75 USD, the fair market value of the ticket).  Bear in mind that this holds true even if the donor does not actually attend the dance.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Types of Contributions </st>
<p>

The particular tax consequences of a donor's charitable contribution depends on the <it>type</it> of contribution that she makes.  A taxpayer may contribute <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/181586.xml">
services</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/55336.xml">
cash</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/23626.xml">
property</link> to a charity.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Services </st>
<p>

If the donor is contributing her services to a charity, she is not entitled to a deduction for those services.  She is however, entitled to deduct her unreimbursed expenses that she incurred in rendering them (except for child care expenses, which are considered non-deductible personal expenses).</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Example</st>
<p>

Joy is a professional soccer player who lives in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/28504.xml">
San Diego</link>.  She decides to volunteer her time at a non-profit (certified charity) soccer camp, located in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/18110.xml">
Los Angeles</link></village>
 for a week.  In the ordinary course of things, Joy would charge 10,000 USD for these services, plus costs of transportation, board, and child care.  Assume that Joy's driving costs (gas money, oil change, etc) amount to 150 USD, the cost of a hotel room for the week is 400 USD, and the cost of child care for her two kids is 500 USD for the week.</p>
<p>

Joy is <b>not</b> entitled to deduct the 10,000 USD value of "free services" that she performed.  Nor is she entitled to deduct the 500 USD of child care expenses incurred in the week she was volunteering.  However, Joy <it>may</it> deduct the 150 USD car expenses, as well as the 400 USD hotel expenses incurred in her time volunteering at the camp, for a total deduction of 550 USD.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Cash </st>
<p>

If the donor is contributing cash to the charity, the general rule is that there is only one limitation on the total amount that she is entitled to deduct:  She may only deduct her contribution to the extent that it does not exceed 50% of her <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/1477090.xml">
adjusted gross income</link>.  Any amount not deducted in the year she makes the contribution may be carried forward and taken the next year for up to 5 years.  Ordinary assets and short-term capital gain assets (<it>see below</it>) are treated like cash for purposes of the 50 % cap.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Example</st>
<p>

To illustrate, suppose that the donor has an adjusted gross income of 100,000 USD.  In the year <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link>, she gives 60,000 USD in cash to the American Cancer Society.  The donor may deduct <it>only</it> 50,000 USD in 2004.  Why?  Because anything over that amount is in excess of 50% of her adjusted gross income (100,000 adjusted gross income * .50 % = 50,000).  The remaining 10,000 USD (60,000 total donation - 50,000 deducted in 2004 = 10,000) carries forward to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>, at which point she may deduct it.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Property </st>
<p>

If the donor is contributing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/100852.xml">
appreciated property</link>, she is entitled to deduct the <it>value</it> of that property on her tax return for that year.  Neither she nor the donee organization will pay tax on the appreciation in the property.</p>
<p>

As is common in federal income taxation, there are several special rules and  limitations that apply:</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Ordinary Income Producing Property and Short Term Capital Gain Property</st>
<p>

If the property that the donor is contributing would have produced either only an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/9337763.xml">
ordinary gain</link> or a <link>
short-term capital gain</link> had she sold it, then she may deduct only her <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/5530015.xml">
adjusted basis</link> in the contributed property.  The taxpayer may not deduct contributions in an amount greater than 50 % of her adjusted gross income (AGI) in the year of donation.  Any excess may be carried forward for up to 5 years and may be deducted subject to the same limitations.</p>

<ss3>
<st>
Example</st>
<p>

Abby, our taxpayer, owns a sporting goods store.  Her business is doing well so she decides to donate some of last season's inventory to <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenssportsfoundation.org">
The Women's Sports Foundation</weblink>, a certified charitable organization.  </p>
<p>

Abby's adjusted gross income this year is 700,000 USD.  The fair market value of Abby's donated inventory is 600,000 USD.  Her adjusted basis in the inventory is 400,000 USD.  If Abby had sold the inventory, she would have recognized an ordinary gain of 200,000 (fmv of 600,000 USD - adjusted basis of 400,000 USD = 200,000 USD).  </p>
<p>

To determine the amount that she may deduct as a charitable contribution, Abby must subtract the ordinary gain inherent in the inventory (the 200,000) from the inventory's fair market value (the 600,000).  Thus, the amount of Abby's gift is 400,000 (fmv of 600,000 USD  - inventory's inherent ordinary gain of 200,000 USD = 400,000 USD gift).</p>
<p>

But remember, Abby may not deduct any contributions over 50% of her adjusted gross income.  Recall that Abby's AGI is 700,000 USD.  The amount of her gift is 400,000 USD.  The result?   Since 50% of her AGI equals 350,000 USD (700,000 USD x .50 = 350,000 USD), Abby may only deduct 350,000 USD of the 400,000 gift in the year that she donated it.  However, assuming her AGI in year <it>two</it> remains <it>at least</it> 100,001 USD, and assuming that Abby makes no charitable contributions in year two, she may carry over the 50,000 USD (400,000 gift - 350,000 year one deduction = 50,000 carry over) to year two, and deduct it on her tax return that year.</p>

</ss3>
</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Long-Term Capital Gain Property</st>
<p>

Charitable donations to public charities and private foundations are subject to overall caps of 50% and 30%, respectively.  For example, if a taxpayer contributes cash or short term capital gain property to a public charity, and that cash and property is greater than 50% of his or her adjusted gross income, then any additionally contribution (including long term capital gain property) to any charity in that same year can not be deducted.  </p>
<p>

If a donor is contributing property that would have yielded a <link>
long-term capital gain</link> in a sale, then the deduction for the contribution is limited to 30% of her adjusted gross income in the year of donation if the donee is a public charitiy, and limited to 20% if the donee is a private foundation.  Contributions over the respective AGI thresholds may be carried forward for five years, and may be deducted in subsequent years pursuant to the same restrictions.  This restriction helps certain investors avoid giving themselves into such a low bracket that the tax value of the donation is impaired.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Short-Term Capital Gain Property</st>
<p>

A trap for the unwary U.S. investor with an asset on which there have been gains in value who contributes the asset before the gains become long-term.  The premature gift forfeits deduction of the short-term gains.  The asset can be deducted only up to the amount of its basis, and not up to the amount of its appreciated market value.  Only an investor who holds the asset until the capital gains have become long-term is allowed to deduct the appreciated market value.  </p>
<p>

I.R.C. 170(e)(1)(A) provides: </p>
<p>

(e)  Certain contributions of ordinary income and capital gain property </p>
<p>

(1) General rule
The amount of any charitable contribution of property otherwise taken into account under this section shall be reduced by the sum of—</p>
<p>

(A) the amount of gain which would not have been long-term capital gain if the property contributed had been sold by the taxpayer at its fair market value (determined at the time of such contribution) ...</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Short-Term Capital Loss Property</st>
<p>

A further trap awaits the unwary U.S. investor who donates depreciated assets -- assets on which there have been losses in value -- to charity.  The gift actually forfeit the tax deductibility of the capital losses, and only the depreciated (low) market value at the time of the gift is allowed to be deducted, rather than the higher basis.  However an investor can instead sell the depreciated assets before considering a donation.  An investor who sells can realize the resultant capital loss, which may then be deducted under the applicable capital loss rules.  The cash proceeds after liquidating the depreciated asset may of course be donated to charity and deducted following the sale, but the tax advantages of making such donation are no better or worse than in any cash donation to charity.  In any case, such a course leaves the investor more after-tax assets to donate if so inclined.</p>



<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:#FFFF00;" class="navbox-title">
Topics related to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/9728362.xml">
charity</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#FFFF00;;" class="navbox-group">
Main topics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/220050.xml">
Philanthropy</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/68636.xml">
Alms</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/438952.xml">
Tzedakah</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/34455.xml">
Zakat</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/336.xml">
Altruism</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/50021.xml">
Gift</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/367725.xml">
Donation</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/7902181.xml">
Alternative giving</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/11050437.xml">
Youth philanthropy</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../705/32705.xml">
Volunteer</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/596649.xml">
Charitable contribution</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/603385.xml">
Noblesse oblige</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#FFFF00;;" class="navbox-group">
Organization types</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/46539.xml">
Non-governmental organization</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/148565.xml">
Registered charity, Charitable trust</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/693306.xml">
Foundation</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/11727749.xml">
Private foundation</link> • <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
Non-profit organization</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/72487.xml">
Not-for-profit corporation</link> • <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<volition wordnetid="105652593" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<faculty wordnetid="105650329" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/1176679.xml">
Charitable organization</link></faculty>
</kind>
</volition>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:#FFFF00;;" class="navbox-group">
Additional topics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/3549998.xml">
Charity Navigator</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/8988662.xml">
Network for Good</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/11221159.xml">
Charity badge</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/10803306.xml">
List of charitable foundations</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/70140.xml">
Click-to-donate sites</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/17623732.xml">
Pushka</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/4610823.xml">
Halukka</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/18011002.xml">
Meshulach</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
