<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:05:32[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Mutual credit</title>
<id>5966367</id>
<revision>
<id>181090423</id>
<timestamp>2007-12-31T00:30:34Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Joel.a.davis</username>
<id>6087129</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Mutualism</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since December 2007</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Anarchist theory</category>
<category>Currency</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="150px" src="Merge-arrows.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrows
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  with . ()</col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<b>Mutual credit</b> is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/2384990.xml">
alternative currency</link> in which the currency used in a transaction can be created at the time of the transaction.  Typically this involves keeping track of each individual's credit or debit balance.  Although the effect is like a loan, no interest is charged, and since mutual credit allows for trading and cancelling balances with others, debts can be paid off indirectly.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Advantages and disadvantages</st>

<p>

One economic advantage of mutual credit is that the currency supply is self-regulating--the money supply expands and contracts as needed, without any managing authority.  The availability of interest-free loans is a great advantage to members of the system.  One major downside of mutual credit, as with any form of credit, is the possibility of exploiting the system by running up a negative balance and then leaving.  This problem is often addressed by caps on negative balance which can be raised as balances are paid off, or by limiting the system to a small, close-knit community based on trust, where the community holds people accountable.  For this reason, most mutual credit systems are small (under 2000 members).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Examples and types of systems</st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/78540.xml">
LETS</link> and the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/2435422.xml">
Cincinnati Time Store</link></institution>
</company>
 are examples of mutual credit systems.  A number of different mutual credit systems have been proposed.  Mutual credit can be combined with a number of features of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/2384990.xml">
alternative currency</link> systems.  For example, it is usually (but does not need to be) a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/55886.xml">
local currency</link>, and it can have a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/1507840.xml">
demurrage</link> fee for the holding of balances.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/2217004.xml">
Cost the limit of price</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 T.H. Greco.  "Money: understanding and creating alternatives to legal tender".  White River Junction, Vt: Chelsea Green Publishing, 2001.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
