<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:12:39[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<division  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108220714">
<belief  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105941423">
<administrative_unit  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108077292">
<branch  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108401248">
<doctrine  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105943300">
<header>
<title>Jointness</title>
<id>5999902</id>
<revision>
<id>235139195</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-30T06:47:55Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rhazs</username>
<id>7382376</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Psychodynamics</category>
<category>Military doctrines</category>
<category>Freudian psychology</category>
<category>Psychoanalysis</category>
<category>Military branches</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Jointness</b> is an expression coined by the US Services to describe cross service cooperation in all stages of the military processes, from research, through procurement and into operations.  Today, it is accepted by many advanced militaries including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/315904.xml">
Israeli Security Forces</link>.  Jointness is aimed at satisfying the requirements for increasing efficiency and economizing the security budget.<p>

According to its definition, "Jointness" is: "the integration of the strengths of at least two limbs of the military in a coordinated effort to achieve a common goal". Jointness is an important factor in developing Joint Operations. It enables flexible leadership for the commander of a group, increases effective functioning, and creates an involvement between military limbs.</p>
<p>

Jointness also creates the possibility for a new manner of warfare called Network-centric warfare. Network Centric Warfare is characterized by the representation and analysis of information, and its' transfer between agents and the center of command who may be distant from one another or even members of different units in the military. This new technology and outlook enable the military to improve operational efficiency in a way that was not possible in the past. What began as a gradual technological advancement within individual military limbs has grown to include several branches of the armed forces. </p>
<p>

This approach views Jointness as key for proceeding flexibly in a changing world. It stresses conceptual flexibility which is obtained through the development of new mindsets and which precedes flexibility of power and resource.  </p>

<sec>
<st>
Papers and Articles</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

   <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Shope, Virginia C. Jointness: A Selected Bibliography..&#32;U.S. Army War College Library.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Jointness (psychodynamics)</st>
<p>

<b>Jointness</b> is a term (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pep-web.org/document.php?id=psc.046.0337a">
1991</weblink>) in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/4254735.xml">
psychodynamics</link>, describing a new look at normal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/910662.xml">
object relation</link> that takes place in a third, joint, virtual space between entities (individuals)  that are separated from the beginning of life (mother and newborn). In this type of transitional space the individuals jointly determine the extent of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/2688303.xml">
rapprochement</link> between themselves while each of them is sensorily attentive to the strangeness and the separateness of the “non-self” that the other represents for him.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Papers and Articles</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Solan, Ronnie&#32;(1991).&#32;"Jointness as integration of merging and separateness in object relations and narcissism.".&#32;Psychoanal. Study of the Child, 46: 337-352..</cite>&nbsp; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pep-web.org/document.php?id=psc.046.0337a">
http://www.pep-web.org/</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Solan, Ronnie (1998) Narcissistic Fragility in the Process of Befriending the Unfamiliar. 1998 Psychoanal. Amer. J. Psycho-Anal., Vol. 58:(2)163-186. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springerlink.com/content/u7724v377q74g405/">
http://www.springerlink.com</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Solan, Ronnie (1998b). The Narcissitic Vulnerability to Change in Object Relation.  In Psychoan. In Israel (Theoriebildung  und therapeutische Praxis). BlatteR Band 9. Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht Gottingen.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Solan, Ronnie (1999). The  Interaction Between Self and Other: A Different Perspective on Narcissim. Psychoanal. Study of the Child, 54: 193-215.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Web Site</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ronniesolan.com">
 www.ronniesolan.com</weblink> </entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</doctrine>
</branch>
</administrative_unit>
</belief>
</division>
</article>
