<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:14:46[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<school  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276720">
<educational_institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108276342">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>Sanskriti School</title>
<id>6068253</id>
<revision>
<id>243046506</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-04T22:17:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rusavvy</username>
<id>8004865</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Schools in Delhi</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.sanskritischool.com</entry>
</list>

<b>Sanskriti School</b>, Dr. Radhakrishnan Marg, Chanakya Puri, New Delhi, has been established by the Civil Services Society, formed by the wives of the civil servants belonging to various branches of the Government of India. Sanskriti School was founded in the year 1998.</p>
<p>

The aim of the Society is to fulfill a felt need in the city of Delhi - the requirement of Schools offering quality education to wards of officers of All India and Allied Services and Defence Personnel coming on transfer. Students whose parents are in other services or professions may also apply.</p>
<p>

<b>The school's motto "Vidhyaya Cha Vimuchyate"</b> (Knowledge is Liberation) - is the cornerstone around which the character and personality of every child is built. The objectives of Sanskriti School are manifold: </p>
<p>

To provide a stimulating, purposeful, cheerful, safe and secure environment, enabling all children to develop academically and socially. 
To make students realize that striving for excellence, academic or otherwise must be the goal in life. 
To understand that each student is a unique individual with rights and responsibilities. 
To have small classes so that each student receives individual attention. 
To encourage students to take pride in their own achievements. 
To make students aware that a disciplined environment is conducive to successfully working towards a goal. 
To educate students about the importance of working in a team. 
To inculcate in students an awareness of how to apply knowledge, skills and concepts in reaching their full educational potential. 
To guide students to learn to appreciate and respect environment and become conscious of the need to protect and preserve nature. 
To help students discover that learning is an ongoing experience and thus become lifelong learners. 
To make education a partnership between teachers, students and parents. </p>
<p>

<b>FACULTY</b></p>
<p>

The First Principal of the school was Ms. Gowri Ishwaran who retired from the school in 2008 and the school was then taken over by Ms. Abha Sehgal.A motivated, dedicated and well qualified faculty oversee the well being of our students. A good teacher-student ratio (1:10) makes it possible for our faculty to monitor the progress of every child. </p>
<p>

<b>CURRICULUM</b></p>
<p>

School has the following wings: 
Early Childhood Development (Classes Nursery &amp; Prep) 
Junior School (Classes I – V) 
Middle School (Classes VI –VIII) 
Senior School (Classes IX – XII) 
The Academic Year is divided into two Semesters, at the end of which classes IV to XII appear for term exams. Unit Tests are held weekly starting from Class IV. Value Education is interwoven with the curriculum. There is a "Value of the Month" which is emphasized throughout the school, from Nursery to Class XII. Class teachers monitor the programme, and every subject teacher also reinforces the Value in their teachings. Activities and competitions also focus on the "value of the month". </p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="sanskriti.jpg">
<caption>

Caption1
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

INFRASTRUCTURE</p>

<p>

<b>LIBRARY</b> :A centrally air-conditioned circular building over three floors houses the junior, middle and senior school libraries. The library is located centrally in the school to facilitate ease of access. A wide range of books aims to help children rediscover the joy of reading. A very extensive references section helps students work on multi-dimensional projects.</p>
<p>

<b>CLASSROOMS</b>:Classrooms are large and airy with abundant natural light to provide the right ambience for an effective learning experience at school. A noticeboard is provided in every Classroom, which is decorated by both teachers and students for different events throughout the academic year. All Classrooms are equipped with student lockers.</p>
<p>

Junior classes also have an independant class library managed by the respective classteacher</p>
<p>

<b>AMPHITHEATRE</b> The Amphitheatre is the nerve centre of Sanskriti. Built strategically in the very centre of the school, all assemblies, special ceremonies, such as prize distributions, investiture ceremony, citation for the passing out batch of Class XII and other such events are held here. </p>
<p>

Built in a semi-circular style, it can seat around 600 people and the circular stage can easily accomodate 50 to 60 children during a performance.</p>
<p>

<b>SPORTS FACILITIES</b> The school offers a multipurpose gymnasium, a swimming pool of international standards, a wading pool and a playground as part of its sports complex. Indoor basketball and badminton courts, table-tennis facilities are available. The school is well-equipped to offer cricket, hockey, athletics, football, yoga, taekwando in its sports complex. 
<b>
CANTEEN</b> The School Cafeteria has a fully equipped modern kitchen and pantry and serves hygienic and nutritious food to the students. The school cafeteria is closely supervised by the school Doctor, and the environment club members. </p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</educational_institution>
</school>
</article>
