<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:15:06[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<institute  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108407330">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<think_tank  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108478702">
<association  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108049401">
<company  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108058098">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<institution  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108053576">
<header>
<title>National Institute for Latino Policy</title>
<id>6078553</id>
<revision>
<id>243516159</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T21:16:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Franamax</username>
<id>5177550</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Non-profit organizations</category>
<category>Think tanks based in the United States</category>
<category>Mexican-American organizations</category>
<category>Organizations based in the United States</category>
<category>Advocacy groups</category>
<category>Organizations established in 1982</category>
<category>Political advocacy groups in the United States</category>
<category>Latino organizations</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="NiLP_Logo.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

National Institute for Latino Policy logo
</caption>
</image>
<p>

The <b>National Institute for Latino Policy</b> (NiLP) was established in 1982 as the Institute for Puerto Rican Policy (IPR) in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/645042.xml">
New York City</link></village>
, United States as a non-profit and nonpartisan policy center focusing on critical Latino policy issues. </p>
<p>

Between 1999 and 2005, the Institute entered into a strategic alliance with the Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund (PRLDEF) during which it functioned as the Fund’s policy research arm. In November 2005, the Institute returned to its independent status and changed its name to the National Institute for Latino Policy. The name change more accurately reflected the national scope and pan-Latino nature of its work.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Smits_and_Rangel_at_Gala.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Jimmy Smits and Congressman Charles Rangel at NiLP's 25th Anniversary Gala
</caption>
</image>
The National Institute for Latino Policy focuses on developing state and local strategies to advocate for Latino community needs, and in this way complements the work of existing national Latino organizations in Washington, DC. NiLP's strategies include the creative use of the Internet to disseminate critical information and to mobilize constituencies. It is currently developing programs in three areas: 1. the National Latino Data Center, 2. the Latino Voting Rights Network, and 3, the Latino Municipal Priorities Program. NiLP's current scope of operations is the East Coast and the U.S. Caribbean, with plans to expand nationally over the next two to three years.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Background </st>

<p>

The Institute is a pioneer and innovator in the Latino community in conducting aggressive community-based policy.</p>
<p>

<image location="left" width="125px" src="FalconTV.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Institute President <link>
Angelo Falcón</link> on TV news program
</caption>
</image>
The Institute is actively involved in a number of coalitions and collaborations in the Latino community nationally. It is a founding member of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.defendthehonor.org">
Defend the Honor Campaign</weblink>, which in early 2007 is putting pressure on the Public Broadcasting System (PBS) and filmmaker Ken Burns to include the Latino experience in the forthcoming documentary on WWII, The War (scheduled to be aired on PBS on September 23, 2007). It is a member of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.latinopolicycoalition.org">
Latino Policy Coalition</weblink>, a collaboration of the leading progressive Latino thinks tanks and scholars in the country. The Institute also works closely with the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nhmc.org/">
National Hispanic Media Coalition</weblink> and the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nhmc.org/nlmc.htm">
National Latino Media Council</weblink> on a wide range of media policy issues affecting Latinos. In 2006, the Institute's President and Founder, <link>
Angelo Falcón</link>, was named one of the top 25 "New York Latino movers and shakers" by the <it>New York Post</it> (November 8, 2006).</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="NILP_Publications.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Institute Reports and Studies
</caption>
</image>
The National Institute for Latino Policy is funded primarily by foundations, corporations and individual contributions. In 2006-8 it received grants from The Ford Foundation, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/1964018.xml">
Carnegie Corporation</link> of New York, the Hispanic Federation, the Latino Policy Coalition/Metro Foundation, and the <financial_institution wordnetid="108054721" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<manner wordnetid="104928903" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="108406486" confidence="0.8">
<charity wordnetid="108406619" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/212204.xml">
United Way</link></institution>
</charity>
</foundation>
</manner>
</property>
</financial_institution>
 of New York City. In this period it also received the financial and inkind support from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/2168045.xml">
AriZona Beverage Company</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/37653.xml">
CBS Television Network</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/207299.xml">
Citi</link>, the <link>
City University of New York (CUNY)</link>, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/6310.xml">
Columbia University</link></ranking>
</university>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/899286.xml">
Con Edison</link>, the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/11095.xml">
Ford Motor Company</link></company>
, the Greater New York Hospital Association (GNYHA), the Herrera-Cristina Group Ltd, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/18622259.xml">
IBM Corporation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/374328.xml">
jetBlue Airways</link>, <network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../780/21780.xml">
NBC</link></network>
4-<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/10839777.xml">
Telemundo</link></network>
47, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/19572225.xml">
Nielsen Media Research</link></institution>
</company>
,the RAM Capital Group LLC, the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/289980.xml">
Scholastic Corporation</link></company>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/483275.xml">
SEIU</link> Local 32BJ and 1199, Tonio Burgos and Associates LLC, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/30984.xml">
Toyota Motor Company</link>, and Salsa Catering &amp; Special Events, Latino Sports, and the National Refrescos Import Company.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Organizational Timeline 1982-2007 </st>

<p>

<b>1982</b></p>
<p>

Publishes first report, on the issue of the extreme underrepresentation of Latinos in New York State government work force. It found that, although 10 percent of the state’s population, they were less than 3 percent of state government workers, making Latinos the most underrepresented group in the state.</p>
<p>

Publishes report on Latino voters in New York City, “Latino Voter Registration in NYC: Statistics for Action,” that finds Latinos as “electoral sleeping giant,“ estimating that there are 400,000 Latino eligible to vote but who are not registered</p>
<p>

<b>1983</b></p>
<p>

Publishes report “Simple Justice: Puerto Rican and Latino Government Employment in New York and the Failure of Affirmative Action.” </p>
<p>

Institute conducts first National Puerto Rican Opinion Survey of 1,500 stateside Puerto Rican leaders and activists.</p>
<p>

<b>1984</b></p>
<p>

In a special report on Hispanics, The Ford Foundation singles out the Institute as a “model” explaining that its reports “have attracted the attention of the press and have served to encourage policy debates . . . as well as to heighten the sensitivity of public officials to these concerns.” (pp. 54-55).</p>
<p>

Monitors NYS Mario Cuomo’s political appointments of Latinos to his Administration finding, based on state government records, that Latinos only made 3.2 percent of appointments compared to Cuomo’s claim of 10 percent.</p>
<p>

Working with Aspira of New York, monitors NYC Board of Education’s reporting of the Hispanic dropout rate as underreporting the problem under Puerto Rican Schools Chancellor, Nathan Quiñones.</p>
<p>

Critiques Raymond Carr book, “Puerto Rico: A Colonial Experiment.” In a letter to the New York Times, Angelo Falcón writes: “Mr. Carr and the Twentieth Century Fund have . . . produced a dangerous book.  It attempts, in Mr. Carr’s lucid and engaging prose, to elevate old notions of Puerto Ricans as unable to govern themselves, as welfare parasites, as devoid of any significant national culture, etc., to a level of respectability and of being part of the ‘common sense’ of the current policy discourse on United States-Puerto Rico relations. “ </p>
<p>

Institute hold first annual Friends of the Institute Benefit Dance featuring Ruben Blades and Los Seis de Solar, along with the Bad Street Boys, at the Marc Ballroom in Union Square in Manhattan.</p>
<p>

Criticizes Census Bureau proposal to combines Puerto Rican and other Latino national-origin groups into one Hispanic category in the 1990 Census.</p>
<p>

<b>1985</b></p>
<p>

Publishes “Black and Latino Politics in NYC: Race and Ethnicity in a Changing Urban Context,” which documents for the first time that New York City has become a “majority minority” city.</p>
<p>

Monitors NYS Governor Mario Cuomo’s responsiveness to Latino concerns; promotes establishment of Governor’s Advisory Committee on Hispanic Affairs</p>
<p>

Institute analysis presented in Albany, NY conference projects that Latino underrepresentation will worsen over time if left to current trends, projecting that by 1990, while Latinos will make up 11 percent of the NYS population, they will only make up 4 percent of state government employees. In 2006, while making up 15 percent of the state’s population, the Latino share of state government workers is only 4 percent.</p>
<p>

<b>1986</b></p>
<p>

Criticizes Governor Cuomo for his remarks that “when Puerto Ricans came her 10 or 15 years ago, some didn’t have a pair of shoes until they got to the airport.”</p>
<p>

Published pioneering study of Latino political contributors to NYC Mayor Koch and NYS Governor Mario Cuomo. It found that Latinos contributed $185,000 to both campaigns, making up 1.8 percent of contributions to Cuomo and 1.2 percent to Koch.</p>
<p>

Institute holds 2nd Annual National Planning Meeting.</p>
<p>

<b>1987</b></p>
<p>

Publishes analysis critical of report of the recommendations of Mayor Koch’s Commission on Hispanic Concerns.</p>
<p>

Institute leads campaign to appoint a Latino to the NYC Board of Education that had no Latino representation under the Koch Administration.</p>
<p>

<b>1988</b></p>
<p>

Institute hold major citywide conference at Fordham University on Puerto Rican and Latino issues in New York City in preparation for next year’s mayoral election.</p>
<p>

On the Presidential election and the Latino vote, Angelo Falcón tells the New York Times: “Dukakis as the advantage of speaking fluent and flawless Spanish. But he’s boring in any language.”</p>
<p>

Releases analysis of Democratic Presidential primary that found that Jesse Jackson received 53 percent of the Latino vote in New York. Based on this analysis, Angelo Falcón told Focus: The Monthly Magazine of the Joint Center for Political Studies that, “if Latinos vote against Koch next year at the same rate that they rejected Gore (Koch’s candidate), a black-Latino coalition might very well combine behind a challenge to defeat Koch in 1989.”</p>
<p>

Released analysis of Latino primary vote in NYC, “The Puerto Rican/Latino Vote in New York City Democratic Primaries of September 15, 1988,” that revealed Latino voter turnout rates comparable to whites, thus challenging stereotype of low Latino participation.</p>
<p>

New York Times covers Institute annual benefit dance in Club Broadway.</p>
<p>

<b>1989</b></p>
<p>

Holds major citywide conference on “The Dinkins Administration and the Puerto Rican Community: Lessons from the Experience of Puerto Ricans with African-American Mayors in Chicago and Philadelphia” at the New School for Social Research</p>
<p>

Publishes “Toward a Puerto Rican/Latino Agenda for New York City” aimed at mayoral candidates</p>
<p>

Publishes report on “Puerto Ricans and the 1989 Mayoral Election in New York City.”</p>
<p>

Publishes reports on NYC Charter Revision Commission: “Charter Revision and Racial Exclusion” and “The 1989 Mayoral Election and the Charter Revision Vote in New York City”</p>
<p>

<b>1990</b></p>
<p>

Monitoring of NYC Dinkins Administration begins. Angelo Falcón tells the New York Times that: “I don’t think anybody anticipated the Dinkins Administration would develop such a poor relationship with the Latino community. Their learning curve is a lot flatter than I think anybody anticipated.”</p>
<p>

Comments on Black-Latino relations in New York City and the lack of responsiveness by the Dinkins Administration in New York City</p>
<p>

Publishes reports monitoring the Dinkins Administration: “The Dinkins Administration and the Puerto Rican Community” and “The Dinkins Administration and the Puerto Rican /Latino Community: The First 100 Days.”</p>
<p>

<b>1991</b></p>
<p>

Institute-sponsored Latino Voting Rights Network becomes a player in redistricting process in New York and other Northeast states</p>
<p>

Leslie Gelb, New York Times columnist, writes that “Angelo Falcon, a leader in the Puerto Rican community, deserves a high position also” in the Dinkins Administration.</p>
<p>

Writes comments in New York Times on NYC budget situation: “There is a connection between poverty and racial tensions and an unfair distribution of services and city resources that fall along racial lines.”</p>
<p>

<b>1992</b></p>
<p>

Releases findings as part of research team of seminal Latino National Political Survey (LNPS), largest household survey ever conducted of Latino political attitudes and behavior in the United States; co-writes book on findings, “Latino Voices: Mexican, Puerto Rican &amp; Cuban Perspectives on American Politics.”</p>
<p>

Publishes “Puerto Ricans and the 1988 Election in New York City”</p>
<p>

Releases result of NYC Puerto Rican leadership survey that found Fernando Ferrer to be most influential leader in this community.</p>
<p>

Comments on assassination in New York City of former El Diario-La Prensa editor, Manuel de Dios Unanue, by Colombia drug ring.</p>
<p>

Publishes report on “Carrillo, the New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation and the Latino Community.”</p>
<p>

Publishes pamphlet, “Puerto Ricans and other Latinos in New York City Today: A Statistical Profile.”</p>
<p>

Leads Latino community-labor coalition against the North American Free Trade Agreement, publishing “NAFTA Resource Book: Northeast Puerto Rican/Latino Roundtable on the North American Free Trade Agreement.”</p>
<p>

Publishes report on “Latinos and the Redistricting Process in New York City.”</p>
<p>

<b>1993</b></p>
<p>

Publishes (through 1997) the monthly publication, “Crítica: A Journal of Puerto Rican Politics &amp; Policy.”</p>
<p>

Publishes a series of “Proceedings of the 1993 New York City Mayoral Election and the Puerto Rican Community: Issues and Prospects” on each Mayoral candidate.</p>
<p>

Publishes analysis of Census data on “The Status of Puerto Ricans in the U.S.”</p>
<p>

<b>1994</b></p>
<p>

Reprints 1978 study on Puerto Rican leadership, “The Puerto Rican Activist Stratum in New York City 1978.”</p>
<p>

Compiles and publishes the “Directory of Puerto Rican/Latino Associations in New York City 1994.”</p>
<p>

<b>1995</b></p>
<p>

Publishes 800-page “NYC Latino Neighborhoods Data Book” that maps and profiles, for the first time, the city’s 21 Latino neighborhoods and sub-neighborhoods.</p>
<p>

Holds citywide forum featuring Pablo ‘Yoruba’ Guzman on “The Young Lords Legacy: A Personal Account.”</p>
<p>

First publishes the “Soy Boricua” Calendar.</p>
<p>

<b>1996</b></p>
<p>

Publishes “Latino Immigrants and Electoral Participation: Puerto Ricans, Dominicans and South Americans in the New York City Political System.”</p>
<p>

New York Times asks Angelo Falcón to comment on state of New York City: “In terms of the cachet of New York, of New York being seen as social and cultural capital of the world, it’s back. But all that is geared to the well-to-do.”</p>
<p>

Publishes “Puerto Ricans in Post-liberal New York: The 1992 Presidential Election”
“New York City Latino Voter Handbook.”</p>
<p>

“Puerto Rican Politics in New York: Beyond ‘Secondhand’ Theory” Reprint of Jose Ramon Sanchez article.</p>
<p>

<b>1997</b></p>
<p>

Publishes, in collaboration with the Hispanic Research Center of Fordham University and with funding from The Ford Foundation, “Nuestra America en New York: The New Immigrant Hispanic Populations in New York City, 1980-90.”</p>
<p>

Publishes analysis of Latino underrepresentation in New York City municipal government jobs: while 24 percent of the city population, Latinos held on 13 percent of city jobs.</p>
<p>

Published article, “The End of Voting Rights?” in Hispanic Magazine about the lack of enforcement of the Federal Voting Rights Act in the Latino community.</p>
<p>

Writes a commentary in the New York Times on NYC Mayor Rudolph Giuliani on his third year in office, finding that “He has personalized New York City politics in a way that needlessly polarizes attitudes.”</p>
<p>

Ends publication of “Críitica: A Journal of Puerto Rican Policy &amp; Politics.” </p>
<p>

<b>1998</b></p>
<p>

Institute generates a major national discussion of the introduction of a “Puerto Rican Barbie Doll” from Mattel and its implications for Puerto Rican identity and politics.</p>
<p>

<b>1999</b></p>
<p>

Institute and Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund agree to a strategic alliance in which the Institute becomes the Fund’s Policy Division.</p>
<p>

Publishes “Beyond La Macarena: New York City Puerto Rican, Dominican, and South American Voters in the 1996 Election.”</p>
<p>

<b>2000</b></p>
<p>

Publishes the report “Beyond Bilingual Education: Meeting the Needs of English Language Learners in the New York City Public Schools,” which helped to transform the discourse on bilingual education from a defensive to a more pro-active position in New York City and broadening the scope of issues facing the education of Latino youth.</p>
<p>

<b>2001</b></p>
<p>

Identifies the problem of the underreporting of certain Latino subgroups in 2000 Census (Dominicans, Colombians and others) and joins campaign to get the Census Bureau to correct the problem.</p>
<p>

Publishes “Still on the Outside Looking In: Latino Employment in New York Broadcast Television” in collaboration with the National Hispanic Media Coalition  and put pressure on the city’s local television stations to address the problem of the underrepresentation of Latinos on their staffs. IPR also wrote a proposal for the National Hispanic Media Coalition that resulted in The Ford Foundation supporting the work of the Coalition’s Media Policy Project in 2004-5.</p>
<p>

Publishes “De’tras Pa’lante: The Future of Puerto Rican History in New York City – An Essay.” </p>
<p>

Publishes editorial comment, “Liberating Vieques,” in The Nation.</p>
<p>

Releases analysis of voting rights discrimination against Latinos in New York City redistricting plan for the City Council.</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón profiled in “Public Lives: A 20 Year Battler for Puerto Rican Pull,” by John Kifner, New York Times (June 20). </p>
<p>

<b>2002</b></p>
<p>

Publishes, in collaboration with the Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, “Opening the Courthouse Doors: The Need for More Hispanic Judges.” This is the first study of Latinos in the judiciary in the state and federal courts.</p>
<p>

<b>2003</b></p>
<p>

Challenges, in collaboration with the Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, the nomination of Miguel Estrada for federal district judge by the Bush Administration.</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón profiled on Hispanic Outlook on Higher Education.</p>
<p>

<b>2004</b></p>
<p>

Publishes “The Atlas of Stateside Puerto Ricans,” commissioned by the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico. This report found that the stateside Puerto Rican population was for the first larger than that of Puerto Rico, generating a new dsicussion on the relationship between Stateside and Island Puerto Ricans, and stimulated some new thinking about policy initiatives by the Government of Puerto Rico in working with Stateside Puerto Ricans.</p>
<p>

Co-edits the book, “Boricuas in Gotham: Puerto Ricans in the Making of Modern New York City.”</p>
<p>

Publishes “’Pues, At Least We Had Hillary’: Latino New York City, the 2000 Election, and the Limits of Party Loyalty.”</p>
<p>

<b>2005</b></p>
<p>

Institute and Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund announce agreement to separate.</p>
<p>

Releases report, in collaboration with the Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, entitled “Condition Critical: The Absence of Latinos Among Policymakers in New York City’s Voluntary Hospitals.” This is one of the first reports ever done critically examining the problem of the lack of diversity in health policy and practice governance.</p>
<p>

Testifies before NYS Assembly committee that Latino underrepresentation in NYS government jobs remains a serious problem.</p>
<p>

<b>2006</b></p>
<p>

Institute for Puerto Rican Policy officially changes name to National Institute for Latino Policy (NiLP).</p>
<p>

Conducts the first web-based national poll of over 500 Puerto Rican and other Latino community activists on issues affecting Puerto Ricans and Puerto Rico.</p>
<p>

In collaboration with the National Hispanic Media Coalition, conducts “Public Hearing on Diversity &amp; the Broadcasting Industry” with Federal Communications Commission (FCC) commissioners at Hunter College.</p>
<p>

Works with the City University of New York (CUNY) t create the Puerto Rican Faculty Recruitment Project to develop approaches to reverse the decline of Puerto Rican faculty at this institution.</p>
<p>

Institute comments widely in the media on the fiscal crisis in Puerto Rico.</p>
<p>

Institute presents 2006 Orgullo Latino Awards to Congresspersons Nydia Velazquez and Jose Serrano, civil rights attorney Juan Cartagena, media advocate Marta Garcia, and NiLP volunteer Joseph Luppens.</p>
<p>

<b>2007</b></p>
<p>

Publishes critical review of Herman Badillo’s controversial book, One Nation, One Standard: An Ex-Liberal on How Hispanics Can Succeed Just Like Other Immigrant Groups, entitled, “One Nation, Polarized? Herman Badillo and the Limits of Liberalism: Review of Herman Badillo’s One Nation, One Standard.”  The Institute also sponsored a major national online discussion on the Badillo book.</p>
<p>

Co-founded the Defend the Honor Campaign to include the Latino WW II experience in the Ken Burns PBS documentary, “The War.” </p>
<p>

Calls for investigation of National Puerto Rican Parade arrests in NYC of Latin Kings.</p>
<p>

Produces analysis of judicial selection process and diversity under the Lopez Torres case, published in El Diario-La Prensa and the Puerto Rican Bar Association publication.</p>
<p>

Publishes “The Diaspora Factor: Stateside Boricuas and the Future of Puerto Rico” in the NACLA Report on the Americas (November/December issue).</p>
<p>

Begins planning for publication in 2008 of new publication, “Crítica: A Journal of Latino Policy &amp; Politics,” to be based at the City College of New York.</p>
<p>

Institute celebrates 25th anniversary at gala reception co-hosting by Jimmy Smits and George Herrera, and honoring Kimberly Casiano, President and CEO of Casiano Communication, as the recipient of the 2007 Orgullo Latino Award, in New York City.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Selected publications </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Reports </st>

<p>

José A. García (ed.), <it>East Coast Latino Voting Rights Act Reauthorization Manual</it> (New York: National Institute for Latino Policy, 2006)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, <it>Atlas of Stateside Puerto Ricans</it> (Washington, DC: Puerto Rico Federal Affairs Administration, 2004)</p>
<p>

Annette Fuentes, <it>Condition Critical: The Absence of Latinos Among Policymakers in New York City’s Voluntary Hospitals</it> (New York: PRLDEF Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 2004)</p>
<p>

_______________, <it>Cracks in the Unity: The Impact of September 11th on New York Latinos – Redevelopment and Lessons for the Future</it> (New York: PRLDEF Institute for Latino Policy, 2003)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, <it>Opening the Courthouse Doors: The Need for More Hispanic Judges</it> (New York: Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, 2002).</p>
<p>

Shelley Rappaport, <it>Beyond Bilingual Education: Meeting the Needs of English Language Learners in the New York City Public Schools</it> (New York: PRLDEF Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 2002)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, <it>Still on the Outside Looking In: Latino Employment in New York Broadcast Television</it> (prepared for the National Hispanic Media Coalition) (New York: PRLDEF Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 2001)</p>
<p>

__________ (ed), <it>The State of Puerto Rican Politics Aqui y Allá: Proceedings of a November 21, 2000 Forum</it> (New York: PRLDEF Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, February 2001)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, <it>De’tras Pa’lante: The Future of Puerto Rican History in New York City – An Essay</it> (New York: PRLDEF Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, January 2001)</p>
<p>

Joseph A. Pereira with Michelle Rhonda, <it>The Latino Nonprofit Sector in the Eastern United States</it> (Prepared for Hispanics in Philanthropy’s Funders' Collaborative for Strong Latino Communities) (New York: PRLDEF Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 2000).</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón and Christopher Hanson-Sanchez, <it>Latino Immigrants and Electoral Participation: Puerto Ricans, Dominicans and South Americans in the New York City Political System</it> (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 1996)</p>
<p>

"The Status of Puerto Rican Children in the U.S.", <it>IPR Datanote on the Puerto Rican Community</it>, No. 18 (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, July 1996)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, Orlando Rodriguez, Rosemary Santana Cooney, Greta Gilbertson, Christopher Hanson, Arun Lobo, Joseph Salvo, Vicki Virgin and Kenneth Waltzer, <it>Nuestra America en Nueva York: The New Immigrant Hispanic Populations in New York City, 1980-1990</it> (New York: Fordham University Hispanic Research Center Report Series, 1995).</p>
<p>

Christopher Hanson-Sanchez, <it>New York City Latino Neighborhoods Databook</it> (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 1994)</p>
<p>

"The Distribution of Puerto Ricans and Other Selected Latinos in the US: 1990", <it>IPR Datanote on the Puerto Rican Community</it>, No. 11 (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, June 1992) </p>
<p>

John Santiago (ed.), <it>Redistricting, Race and Ethnicity in New York City: The Gartner Report and Its Critics</it> (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 1991)</p>
<p>

"The Health Status of Latinos in the United States: The 1984 Hispanic Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (HHA-NES)", <it>IPR Datanote on the Puerto Rican Community</it>, No. 7 (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, February 1990)</p>
<p>

Manuel del Valle and José Luis Morin, “Puerto Ricans and the Plebiscite on the Status of Puerto Rico – A Legal Brief (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 1989)</p>
<p>

<it>Towards a Puerto Rican-Latino Agenda for New York City 1989</it> (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 1989)</p>
<p>

Ronald Calitri, <it>Latino Voter Registration in NYC: Statistics for Action</it> (New York: Institute for Puerto Rican Policy, 1982)</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Books </st>

<p>

Gabriel Haslip-Viera, Angelo Falcón and Felix Matos Rodríguez (eds.), <it>Boricuas in Gotham: Puerto Ricans in the Making of Modern New York</it> (Princeton, NJ: Markus Wiener Publishers, 2004).</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, F. Chris Garcia and Rodolfo O. de la Garza (eds.), “Ethnicity and Politics: Evidence from the Latino National Political Survey,” Special Issue of the <it>Hispanic Journal of Behavioral Sciences</it>, Vol. 18, No. 2 (May 1996)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, Rodolfo O. de la Garza, Louis DeSipio, F. Chris Garcia, and John Garcia, <it>Latino Voices: Mexican, Puerto Rican &amp; Cuban Perspectives on American Politics</it> (Boulder: Westview Press, 1992)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón , F. Chris Garcia, John A. Garcia, Rodolfo O. de la Garza and Cara J. Abeyta, <it>Latinos and Politics: A Select Research Bibliography</it> (Austin: University of  Texas Press, 1991)</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Book chapters </st>

<p>

Angelo Falcón, “’Pues, At Least We Had Hillary’: Latino New York City, the 2000 Election, and the Limits of Party Loyalty” in Rodolfo O. de la Garza and Louis DeSipio (eds.), <it>Muted Voices: Latinos and the 2000 Elections</it> (New York: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers, 2004)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, Marilyn Aguirre-Molina and Carlos W. Molina, “Latino Health Policy: Beyond Demographic Determinism” and “Latino Health Policy: A Look to the Future” in Marilyn Aguirre-Molina, Carlos W. Molina and Ruth Enid Zambrana (eds), <it>Health Issues in the Latino Community</it> (San Francisco: Jossey-Bass, 2001)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, “Beyond La Macarena: New York City Puerto Rican, Dominican, and South American Voters in the 1996 Election” in Rodolfo O. de la Garza and Louis DeSipio (eds.), <it>Awash in the Mainstream: Latino Politics in the 1996 Election</it> (Boulder: Westview, 1999), pp. 239-248</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, Rodolfo O. de la Garza, John Hernandez, F. Chris García, and John A. García, “Mexican, Puerto Rican and Cuban Foreign Policy Perspectives: A Test of Competing Explanations” in F. Chris Garcia (ed.). <it>Pursuing Power: Latinos and the Political System</it> (Notre Dame, IN: Univ. Notre Dame Press, 1997)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, “Puerto Ricans in Postliberal New York: The 1992 Presidential Election” in Rodolfo O. de la Garza and Louis DeSipio (eds.), <it>Ethnic Ironies: Latino Politics in the 1992 Elections</it> (Boulder: Westview, 1996), pp. 185-210</p>
<p>

__________, “Puerto Ricans and the Politics of Racial Identity” in Herbert W. Harris, Howard C. Blue and E.H. Griffith (eds.), <it>Racial and Ethnic Identity: Psychological Development and Creative Expression</it> (New York: Routledge, 1995), pp. 193-208</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, Rodolfo O. de la Garza, F. Chris García and John A. García, “Mexican Immigrants, Mexican Americans, and American Political Culture” in Barry Edmondston and Jeffrey Passel (eds), <it>Immigration and Ethnicity: The Integration of America’s Newest Arrivals</it> (Washington, DC: Urban Institute Press, 1994)</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, “A Divided Nation: The Puerto Rican Diaspora in the United States and the Proposed Referendum,” in Edwin Meléndez and Edgardo Meléndez (eds.), <it>Colonial Dilemma: Critical Perspectives on Contemporary Puerto Rico</it> (Boston: South End, 1993), pp. 173-180.</p>
<p>

__________, “Puerto Ricans and the 1988 Election in New York City” in Rodolfo O. de la Garza and Louis DeSipio (eds.), <it>From Rhetoric to Reality: Latino Politics in the 1988 Elections</it> (Boulder: Westview, 1992), pp. 147-170</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Journal articles </st>

<p>

Angelo Falcón, "Book Review: One Nation, Polarized? Review of Herman Badillo's <it>One Nation, One Standard</it>," <it>Centro Journal</it> (New York: Centro de Estudios Puertorrqueños, Forthcoming 2007)</p>
<p>

_____________, "Book Review: Puerto Ricans in the United States: A Contemporary Portrait", <it>Centro Journal</it> (New York: Centro de Estudios Puertorrqueños, Fall 2006)</p>
<p>

_____________, Rodolfo O. de la Garza and F. Chris Garcia, “Will the Real Americans Please Stand Up: Anglo and Mexican American Support of Core American Values,” <it>American Journal of Political Science</it>, Vol. 40, No. 2 (May 1996), pp. 311-334</p>
<p>

_____________, F. Chris Garcia, John A. Garcia and Rodolfo O. de la Garza, “Attitudes Towards U.S. Immigration Policies,” <it>Migration World Magazine</it> Vol. 21: Issues 2-3 (1993), p. 13</p>
<p>

_____________, Rodolfo O. de la Garza, F. Chris Garcia, John Garcia, “Ethnicity and Attitudes Toward Immigration Policy: The Case of Mexicans, Puerto Ricans and Cubans in the United States” (Austin: Texas Population Research Center Papers, 1992-1993)</p>
<p>

_____________, “Time to Rethink the Voting Rights Act,” <it>Social Policy</it>, Vol. 23, No. 2 (Fall-Winter 1992), pp. 17-22</p>
<p>

_____________, F. Chris Garcia, John A. Garcia and Rodolfo O. de la Garza, “Studying Latino Politics: The Development of the Latino National Political Survey, “ <it>PS: Political Science and Politics</it>, Vol. 20, No. 4 (December 1989), pp. 848-852.</p>
<p>

_____________, “Puerto Ricans and the 1989 Mayoral Election in New York City,” <it>Hispanic Journal of Behavioral Sciences</it>, Vol. 11, No. 2 (August 1989), pp. 245-258.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Opinion pieces </st>

<p>

Angelo Falcón. "Opiníon: Selección judicial, diversidad y los latinos," <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/4029650.xml">
El Diario-La Prensa</link></it> (4 de abril 2007)</p>
<p>

__________, "Opiníon: El falso voto territorial en el Congreso," <it>El Diario-La Prensa</it> (7 de febrero 2007)</p>
<p>

__________, "One Nation, Polarized? Review of Herman Badillo's <it>One Nation, One Standard</it>" (New York: National Institute for Latino Policy, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
January 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>).</p>
<p>

__________, "Puerto Ricans: Thirty Years of Progress &amp; Struggle", <it>Puerto Rican Heritage Month 2006 Calendar Journal</it> (New York: Comité Noviembre, 2006).</p>
<p>

__________, “US Puerto Ricans Today,” <it>Tempo Magazine</it> (June 2005), a monthly supplement to the <it>New York Post</it>. </p>
<p>

__________, “La educación bilingüe en una encrucijada.” <it>El Diario-La Prensa</it> (25 de septiembre de 2004).</p>
<p>

__________, “Thirty Years After the Aspira Consent Decree, Bilingual Education Remains at Crossroads,” <it>Hispanic Link Weekly Report</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/28030.xml">
September 13</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link>), p. 1</p>
<p>

__________ and José A. García, “Census Bureau Still Hasn’t Restored Its Credibility,” <it>Hispanic Link Weekly Report</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/27990.xml">
September 5</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link>).</p>
<p>

Angelo Falcón, “Latino Voters Have Yet to Become a Strong Force,” <it>Newsday</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/16040.xml">
July 28</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link>).</p>
<p>

__________, “The End of the Puerto Rican? A Cautionary Tale,” <it>VIVA New York Magazine</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/15856.xml">
June 1</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>), pp. 34-38</p>
<p>

__________, “El Fracaso de la clase politica latina,” <it>El Diario-La Prensa</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/8359.xml">
December 24</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/35502.xml">
2002</link>), p. 11</p>
<p>

__________, “The Problem with Mayor Bloomberg,” <it>American Latino</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/19773.xml">
March 25</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/35502.xml">
2002</link>)</p>
<p>

__________, “Liberating Vieques,” <it>The Nation</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/16091.xml">
July 19</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>), p. 6</p>
<p>

__________, “Beyond NAFTA: A Forum,” <it>The Nation</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/19672.xml">
May 28</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>), p. 19</p>
<p>

__________, “Vote for me, amigos,” <it>The Nation</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/10882.xml">
February 14</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link>), p. 20</p>
<p>

__________, “Vieques and the U.S. Navy,” <it>The Nation</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8852.xml">
December 13</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link>), p. 5</p>
<p>

__________, “Clintons and Colonialism,” <it>The Nation</it> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../454/22454.xml">
October 4</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/34553.xml">
1999</link>), p. 6</p>
<p>

__________, “The End of Voting Rights?” <it>Hispanic Magazine</it>, Vol. 10, No. 11 (November 1997), p. 68</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Periodicals </st>

<p>

<it>Latino Policy</it> eNewsletter (February 2007-   ), edited by Angelo Falcón. </p>
<p>

<it>Critica: The Journal of Puerto Rican Policy &amp; Politics</it> (1994-1997), edited by Howard Jordan (1994-6) and Annette Fuentes (1996-7) - scheduled for republication by Markus Wiener Publishers in 2008 as <it>Crítica: A Journal of Latino Policy &amp; Politics</it> with historian [mailto:haslipviera@netzero.net Gabriel Haslip-Viera]as managing editor.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Board of Directors </st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Myra_Jose.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Institute Chair José R. Sánchez and VP Myra Estepa at Board meeting
</caption>
</image>

<b>Israel Colon</b> (Board Treasurer), Director, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.phila.gov/mayor/">
<b>Office of Multi-Cultural Affairs</b></weblink>, City of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA</p>
<p>

<b>Edgar de Jesus</b>, Area Organizing Director, AFSCME New Jersey-New England</p>
<p>

<b><link>
Angelo Falcón</link></b> (President), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.latinopolicy.org">
National Institute for Latino Policy</weblink>, New York, NY; and Adjunct Assistant Professor, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sipa.columbia.edu/academics/directory/amf71-fac.html">
Columbia University School of International and Public Affairs (SIPA)</weblink>, New York, NY</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.seiu32bj.org/au/biosSec.asp">
<b>Héctor Figueroa</b></weblink>, Secretary-Treasurer, SEIU Local 32BJ, New York, NY</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://law.newark.rutgers.edu/facbio/hernandez.html">
<b>Tanya Hernandez</b></weblink>, Professor of Law and Social Justice and Frederick Hall Scholar, Rutgers University School of Law School, New Brunswick, NJ</p>
<p>

<b>Eugene Rivera</b> (Board Secretary), Clinical Coordinator, Hill Health Center, Middletown, CT</p>
<p>

<b>Maria P. Salmeron-Rivera</b>, Managing Partner, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nationalrefrescos.com/">
National Refrescos Import Company</weblink>, Jersey City, NJ</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brooklyn.liu.edu/depts/urbanstudies/Faculty.html">
<b>José R. Sánchez</b></weblink>, (Board Chair) Associate Professor of Political Science and Chair, Urban Studies Department, Long Island University, Brooklyn, NY</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wagner.nyu.edu/faculty/facultyDetail.php?whereField=facultyID&amp;whereValue=38">
<b>Walter Stafford</b></weblink>, Professor of Urban Planning and Public Policy, Wagner Graduate School for Public Affairs, New York University, New York, NY and Principal Investigator, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wagner.nyu.edu/centers/wocpn.php">
Women of Color Policy Network</weblink>, New York, NY</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.latinopolicy.org/">
National Institute for Latino Policy</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</institution>
</group>
</company>
</association>
</think_tank>
</organization>
</institute>
</article>
