<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:04:17[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>IBM System/34, 36 System Support Program</title>
<id>6095951</id>
<revision>
<id>167698022</id>
<timestamp>2007-10-28T20:39:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jessemckay</username>
<id>360099</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>1977 introductions</category>
<category>IBM operating systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>System Support Program</b> (<b>SSP</b>) was an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link> for the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/18622259.xml">
IBM</link></company>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/256354.xml">
System/34</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/261654.xml">
System/36</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/20272.xml">
minicomputer</link>s. SSP was a command-based operating system released in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/34549.xml">
1977</link>, the days of <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/45146.xml">
CP/M</link></O>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/8146.xml">
DOS</link>, and the original <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/31642.xml">
UNIX</link>.<p>

SSP originally contained 60 or so commands that were implemented on the System/34 from 1977 to 1983 in different versions called releases. Release 1 was issued with the original S/34 in 1977. Release 9 was issued in 1981. In 1983, IBM repackaged SSP on a new computer called the IBM <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/261654.xml">
System/36</link>, which was not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/4722515.xml">
object-code compatible</link> with the S/34. In 1994, IBM repackaged SSP on an updated model of the S/36 called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/5122125.xml">
Advanced/36</link>. The A/36 was an IBM <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/39769.xml">
AS/400</link> which had the SSP implemented as a "virtual machine".</p>
<p>

Major releases of SSP include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/34 Release 1.0 - this was apparently shipped with the first S/34 in 1977.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/34 Release 8.0 - this seems to have been issued about 1980.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/34 Release 9.0 - this was the last release for the S/34 c.1980.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/36 Release 1.0 - this was apparently shipped with the first S/36 in 1983.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/36 Release 4.0 - this was the release where S/36 was given 5 job queues.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/36 Release 5.1 - this 1988 release was the last major change on 536X platforms.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/36 Release 6.0 - also known as the VASP or Value-Added Support Product, this release added functionality that allowed program calls in RPG, and it also provided software to calculate the size AS/400 that the user would need when upgrading. The VASP was controversial. Rumors circulated in the industry papers that the customer could not go back to 5.1 if 6.0 did not function adequately. Program calls with RPG CALL/PARM were inferior to RPGIII designs and inferior to customer add-on products.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/36 Release 7.1 - this 1994 release was shipped with the Advanced/36. The first A/36 machines would not function on a lower release and were also incompatible with 7.5. Rumors circulated that stated prior release compilers would not function on the Advanced/36, but they proved unfounded. There were reasons a programmer would rather use the 5.1 RPGII compiler instead of the presumably more advanced 7.x compiler.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 S/36 Release 7.5 - this 1995 release was shipped with the second and final wave of the Advanced/36. Functions like WRKSYSVL allowed the operator to change the system time on the fly, which was interesting because customer add-ons to do this through assembler subroutines did not function on the Advanced/36.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Using SSP, the operator can create, delete, and manage S/34-36 objects such as libraries, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/3136406.xml">
data file</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/406283.xml">
menus</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/40988.xml">
procedures</link>, source members, and security files.</p>
<p>

SSP contains <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/939133.xml">
modules</link> such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/3526696.xml">
DFU</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../453/2159453.xml">
SEU</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/694815.xml">
SDA</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/586884.xml">
WSU</link> that permits operators to build libraries and files, enter information into those files, produce simple reports, and maintain a menu structure that simplifies access to the information. The Advanced/36 does not support WSU. Password and resource security are also implemented through SSP, as are remote communications, which today is similar to dial-up <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/5652.xml">
networking</link>.</p>
<p>

SSP is a disk-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>. Computer programs can be run from the fixed disk, but not from diskette or tape. The complement of a System/34 5340, or System/36 5360/5362 is a fixed disk array of one to four fixed disks, at least one computer terminal, and an 8" diskette drive, optionally fitted with two magazine units that can contain 10 diskettes each and three diskette slots.. A S/36 5363/5364 has a 5-1/4" diskette drive. S/36 computers can be configured with an 8809 reel-to-reel tape drive or a 6157 1/4" cartridge (QIC) tape drive. A/36 computers have a high-density QIC drive but the 8" diskette drive (single) is optional.</p>
<p>

Basic SSP procedures include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HELP, to request an online form to assist with command entry.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 MENU, to display a user-created menu of commands, procedures, or OCL.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ALTERBSC, to change the binary synchronous communications profile.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ALOCFLDR(*), to reallocate a folder.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HISTORY, to report and optionally reset the system history file.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 BLDLIBR, to create a user library.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 BLDFILE, to create a file.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 KEYSORT, to reorganize an indexed file, rebuilding the key index area for greater efficiency.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CATALOG, to report the disk VTOC or media VTOC.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 INIT, to initialize diskette media.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 TAPEINIT, to initialize tape media.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 COPYDATA(*), to create a new file using records from an existing file.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 LISTDATA(*), to print unformatted records from an existing file.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 LISTLIBR, to print members within a library.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 LIBRLIBR, to copy members within a library.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 REMOVE, to remove members within a library.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ALOCLIBR(*), to change the size or directory size of a library.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DELETE, to remove files.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DFU, to start the interactive Data File Utility.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 ENTER, to enter new records into a defined file.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 UPDATE, to change records in a defined file.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 INQUIRY, to display records in a defined file.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 LIST, to report records from a defined file.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SEU, to start the interactive Source Entry Utility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SDA, to start the interactive Screen Design Aid.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 BLDMENU, to create a menu.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 CREATE, to create a message member.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 FORMAT, to create a display format member.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 WSU (**) , to start the interactive Work Station Utility.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SECDEF(*), to define security.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SECEDIT(*), to change security.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SECLIST(*), to report security.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SECSAVE(*), to copy security from disk to media.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SECREST(*), to copy security from media to disk.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SECDROP(*), to remove security.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 PROF(**), to edit password security.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 PRSRCID(**), to edit resource security.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 PRLIST (**), to print password or resource security.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HISTORY, to print or manage the System History file.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HISTCOPY (*), to copy the System History file to a disk file.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CNFIGSSP, to configure the system support product.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IPL, to restart the system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SAVE, to copy a disk file to media.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SAVELIBR, to copy a library to media.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 RESTORE, to copy a file from media to disk.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 RESTLIBR, to copy a library from media to disk.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 SAVEFLDR(*), to save a folder to media.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 RESTFLDR(*), to restore a folder from media.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 COMPRESS, to reorganize the disk for maximum space availability.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CONDENSE, to reorganize a library, or (*) a folder, for maximum space availability.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 WRKSYSVL(****), to view/change system values such as date and time.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CSALL (*), to cancel inactive sessions.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Basic SSP commands include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 ASSIGN (A), to temporarily switch workstation IDs.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CHANGE (G), to change the parameters of a spooled report.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CANCEL (C), to cancel a spooled report, or a session, or the job queue(***), or a user program.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 STOP (P), to stop a printer, or a session, or the job queue(***), or the system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 START (S), to start a printer, or a session, or the job queue(***), or the system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 STATUS (D), to see the status of a printer, or sessions, or communications.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HOLD (H), to place a spooled report on hold.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 RELEASE (L), to release a spooled report from hold.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 RESTART (T), to restart a stopped report from the beginning.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 REPLY (R), to reply to a message sent to the System Console, or to a subconsole, or to all informational messages, or to clear messages from the console or subconsole.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CONSOLE GIVE, to surrender the System Console to alternate consoles.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CONSOLE TAKE, to cause an alternate console to become System Console.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 COMMAND, to return to command mode from console/subconsole mode.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 INFOMSG (I), to set the suppression of informational console messages.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 VARY (V), to set the online state of a device.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 TIME, to request the current time and date.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 OFF, to end the current session.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DATE, to set the session date (not the system date).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 MSG, to send or retrieve messages.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 POWER, to power off the system.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

(*) These functions were created for the System/36. CSALL was created for the VASP.</p>
<p>

(**) These functions were discontinued on the System/36.</p>
<p>

(***) The System/34 was created with a single job queue. The System/36 was created with five job queues; therefore, where "job queue" is written above, the action can refer to a single job queue or all of them.</p>
<p>

(****) This function was added on the Advanced/36.</p>

<sec>
<st>
System utility programs</st>
<p>

SSP procedures utilize utility programs, which can in some cases be more useful to the computer programmer than the SSP procedures themselves. $MAINT is the library utility, used in ALOCLIBR, BLDLIBR, FROMLIBR, LIBRLIBR, REMOVE, CONDENSE, LISTLIBR, and TOLIBR. $COPY is the file utility used in SAVE, RESTORE, COPYDATA, and LISTDATA. There are many other utilities, including $FBLD, $LABEL, $DUPRD, $INIT, $DELET, $HIST, $CNFIG, #GSORT, $PACK, and $PROF, which are more flexible at the program level than associated SSP procedures can be.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Operational Control Language (OCL)</st>
<p>

High-level language programs require <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/5336178.xml">
OCL</link> to be activated.  OCL is used to load programs into the system's memory and start them (a process called execution) and assign resources such as disk files, printers, message members, memory, and disk space to those programs.  Other abilities, such as displaying text on the screen, pause messages, and so forth, make OCL more powerful.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Related operating systems</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/875417.xml">
System/3</link> (c. 1972) ran a card-based operating system called CCP ("Computer Control Program.") The IBM <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/600821.xml">
System/32</link> (1975) ran a disk-based operating system called SCP ("System Control Program.") The IBM <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/294646.xml">
System/38</link> (1978) ran an operating system called CPF ("Control Program Facility") that was much more advanced than SSP and not particularly similar.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Read more about SSP</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 IBM Publication SC21-8299, General Information for SSP Operating System.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
