<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:23:19[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<politics  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113840719">
<gossip  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107223170">
<scandal  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107223811">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<informing  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107212190">
<social_relation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100032823">
<report  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107217924">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<speech_act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107160883">
<header>
<title>Reconstruction of Iraq</title>
<id>610543</id>
<revision>
<id>241058814</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-26T04:17:47Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>FieldMarine</username>
<id>5113002</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>History of Iraq</category>
<category>Civil Affairs</category>
<category>Iraqi insurgency</category>
<category>Politics of Iraq</category>
<category>Political scandals</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Sindbad_Hotel_Complex_and_Conference_Center_Ashkouri.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A Rendering of the Sindbad Hotel Complex and Conference Center.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Reconstruction of Iraq</b> describes attempts by the international community to improve and repair the infrastructure of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/7515928.xml">
Iraq</link></country>
 in the aftermath of the 2003 invasion, when much was destroyed. Iraq was governed, after the 2003 invasion, by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/208316.xml">
Coalition Provisional Authority</link> and, after June 28, 2004 by a series of Iraq-led governments (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/14667.xml">
Politics of Iraq</link>). During this period efforts were made to repair and replace damaged Iraqi infrastructure, including: water supply systems, sewage treatment plants, electricity production, hospitals and health clinics, schools, housing, and transportation systems. Reconstruction efforts have also encompassed the promotion of economic development and government institutions such as the criminal justice system.</p>
<p>

Much reconstruction work in Iraq has been carried out by the Iraqi people in their own communities using local resources. International assistance for Iraq's reconstruction is the focus of this article.  A major benchmark for international assistance was the Madrid Conference on Reconstruction held in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 October 23-24, 2003 and attended by representatives from over 25 nations.  Funds assembled at this conference and from other sources have been administered by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/31769.xml">
United Nations</link> and the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/33309.xml">
World Bank</link></association>
</institute>
. This assistance has primarily funded large-scale projects.  </p>
<p>

While reconstruction efforts have produced some successes, problems have arisen with the implementation of internationally funded Iraq reconstruction efforts. These include inadequate security, pervasive corruption, insufficient funding and poor coordination among international agencies and local communities. Many suggest that the efforts were hampered by a poor understanding of Iraq on the part of the occupiers.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Funding for Iraq reconstruction</st>
<p>

Funding of reconstruction efforts began with the creation of the  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/2165533.xml">
Iraq Relief and Reconstruction Fund</link> (IRRF) in April 2003.  The IRRF is administered and funded by the United States.  An initial allocation of $2.5 billion was made for immediate food, medicine and water relief.   </p>
<p>

The “Madrid Conference on Reconstruction” held in Spain October 23-24, 2003 was organized by the United States to solicit donor pledges from the international community.  About $33 billion in grants and loans were pledged.  Of this, $18.4 billion was from the U.S. with another $5 billion from Japan, $812 million from the EU, $500 million from Kuwait and offers of loans from World Bank and the IMF amounting from $5.5 to $9.25 billion.  Some countries pledged to reduce the debt that Iraq owed to them and to provide direct donations in forms such as food and fuel.  The pledge by the United States was fulfilled in November 2003 by adding $18.4 billion to the IRRF.  </p>
<p>

Much of the non-U.S. pledged money is managed through two additional funds that have been created under the facilitation of the International Reconstruction Fund Facility for Iraq.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  The funds are managed by the United Nations Development Group (UNDG) and by the World Bank.  Twenty-six donor nations participate in this effort with total pledges, as of  June, 30 2006, of $1.4 billion.  The United States donates a small amount to these funds but does not control their disbursement.  </p>
<p>

As of December 30, 2005 the UNDG and World Bank Funds had expended about $0.51 billion and $0.39 billion, respectively.  The United States managed IRRF had expended about $11.4 billion as of March 2006.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Assessing reconstruction needs</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Abu_Hishma_3.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Soldiers unloading school supplies in January 2007.
</caption>
</image>

In preparation for the October 2003 Madrid Donor Conference, the joint United Nations/World Bank team conducted an assessment of funding needs for reconstruction in Iraq during the period 2004-2007.  The resulting report<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  identified 14 sectors and associated funding needs as shown in the Table below.  In addition to this US$36 billion, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/208316.xml">
Coalition Provisional Authority</link> estimated an additional US$20 billion in need including US$5 billion for security and police and US$8 billion for oil industry infrastructure.</p>
<p>

<table align="center" class="wikitable">
<header>
Sector</header>
<header>
Needs (US$billion)</header>
<row>
<col>
Government Institutions</col>
<col>
0.39</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Education</col>
<col>
4.81</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Health</col>
<col>
1.60</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Employment creation</col>
<col>
0.79</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Transport and telecommunications</col>
<col>
3.41</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Water, sanitation, solid waste</col>
<col>
6.84</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Electricity</col>
<col>
12.12</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Urban Management</col>
<col>
0.41</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Housing and Land Management</col>
<col>
1.42</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Agriculture and Water Resources</col>
<col>
3.03</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
State-Owned Enterprises</col>
<col>
0.36</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Financial Sector</col>
<col>
0.081</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Investment Climate</col>
<col>
0.34</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Mine Action</col>
<col>
0.23</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Total</col>
<col>
35.82</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Administration of Iraq reconstruction</st>

<p>

Funds for Iraq reconstruction are disbursed to Iraqi ministries, non-Iraqi government agencies and various non-governmental groups.  These entities then supervise the acquisition of materials and reconstruction work which is conducted by both foreign and Iraqi contractors.  </p>
<p>

Funds held by the United Nations Development Group are disbursed through United Nations agencies such as the World Health Organization, UNICEF and the UN Development Program.  These UN agencies directly contract with equipment suppliers and construction companies.  Disbursement of funds by the UN began in June 2004.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  	Funds held by the World Bank are disbursed directly to Iraqi government agencies including the Municipality of Baghdad and national ministries.  Granting of funds to Iraqi agencies began in December 2004.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Funds held by the US-operated Iraq Relief and Reconstruction Fund have been managed by a series of US agencies.  Beginning in May 2003, the Coalition Provisional Authority (CPA) began oversight of reconstruction efforts in Iraq.  Within the CPA the Project Management Office (PMO) was created to manage reconstruction projects.  Both the CPA and PMO were divisions of the US Department of Defense.  On June 28, 2004, the CPA was dissolved and the Iraqi interim government took power.  At this time, the management of reconstruction projects was transferred to the Iraq Reconstruction and Management Office (IRMO), a division of the US Department of State, and the Project and Contracting Office (PCO), a division of the Department of Defense, both under the oversight of the US State Department Mission to Baghdad.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> On December 4, 2005 the PCO was merged with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/83180.xml">
US Army Corps of Engineers</link>, Gulf Region Division. Since October 2004, contracting support for Iraq reconstruction has also been provided by the U.S. Army’s Joint Contracting Command-Iraq/Afghanistan.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Other U.S. Government agencies, including the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/140416.xml">
U.S. Agency for International Development</link></agency>
 (USAID) and the State Department, have also issued contracts funded by the Iraq Relief and Reconstruction Fund.</p>
<p>

Funds from the US-operated IRRF are largely disbursed through contracts to private firms.  Several US companies have been particularly prominent in receiving Iraq reconstruction funds.  <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/212120.xml">
Bechtel</link></company>
 of San Francisco, USA has been awarded over $2.4 billion for infrastructure rehabilitation through USAID contracts.  Flour AMEC, LLC, Greenville, South Carolina, USA has been awarded nearly $1 billion for water, sewer of solid waste management systems. <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/5640050.xml">
Parsons Corporation</link></institution>
</company>
 of Pasadena, California has been awarded $1.3 billion for construction services.  <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../588/5392588.xml">
Washington Group International</link></institution>
</company>
 of Boise, Idaho, USA has received awards of $580 million for water resource reconstruction projects.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/274263.xml">
Kellogg, Brown and Root</link> (KBR), a subsidiary of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../233/203233.xml">
Haliburton</link> of Houston, Texas has received awards of $580 million.  Another $1.2 billion has been distributed to Iraqi contractors. In 2005/2006  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/17533699.xml">
Symbion Power</link> of the US were awarded $250 million of competitively bid new fixed price electrical infrastructure work throughout the country. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/17533699.xml">
Symbion Power</link> is a privately owned engineering firm with an ownership structure that involves a security company Hart Security.The dollar figures provided here are as of July 2006.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Progress of Iraq reconstruction</st>

<p>

Reconstruction efforts have been plagued by poor management, mishandling of reconstruction funds, inadequate coordination with Iraqis and widespread attacks on construction sites and contractors.  In October, 2004, the U.S. Congress created the Office of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/3433053.xml">
Special Inspector General for Iraq Reconstruction</link> (SIGIR) which is charged with oversight of the use and potential misuse of the IRRF. The SIGIR conducts audits, investigations and inspections and issues quarterly reports to Congress.  The SIGIR reports and U.S. Congressional testimony of  Stuart Bowen, the Inspector General, are a primary source of information on the overall status of U.S. funded Iraq reconstruction.   The rate of disbursement of funds administered by the United Nations and World Bank has been slow.  Iraqi agencies and ministries are often unable to receive or process funds.  Many United Nations agencies have had great difficulty operating in Iraq due to the poor security situation. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Reprogramming reconstruction funds</st>

<p>

The original allocation of IRRF funds to the various sectors has undergone a series of reassignments.  These allocation changes have occurred in September and December, 2004 and March and December, 2005 and generally involved shifting money from water resources and sanitation and electricity sectors to meet  security needs and to provide training and operating funds for facilities already rehabilitated under IRRF funding.  The table below shows the changes that occurred in allocations (billions of $US) between September 2004<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> and December 2005.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>  While the administrative expenses are listed as separate category, an additional $0.60 billion, spread across sectors, was spent on administrative costs in fiscal years 2004 and 2005.  </p>
<p>

<table align="center" cellpadding="5" class="wikitable" border="1" cellspacing="0">
<header>
Sector</header>
<header>
Allocation Prior to 30 September 2004</header>
<header>
Allocation as of 31 December 2005</header>
<row>
<col>
Electricity</col>
<col>
5.46</col>
<col>
4.22</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Water Resources and Sanitation</col>
<col>
4.25</col>
<col>
2.13</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Security and Law Enforcement</col>
<col>
3.24</col>
<col>
5.04</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Justice, Public Safety Infrastructure and Civil Society</col>
<col>
1.48</col>
<col>
2.35</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Private Sector Development</col>
<col>
0.18</col>
<col>
0.45</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Iraq Debt Forgiveness</col>
<col>
0.00</col>
<col>
0.35</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Oil Infrastructure</col>
<col>
1.70</col>
<col>
1.74</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Health Care</col>
<col>
0.79</col>
<col>
0.74</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Transportation and Telecommunication</col>
<col>
0.50</col>
<col>
0.47</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Education, Refugees and Human Rights</col>
<col>
0.26</col>
<col>
0.41</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Roads, Bridges and Construction</col>
<col>
0.37</col>
<col>
0.33</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Administrative</col>
<col>
0.21</col>
<col>
0.21</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Total</col>
<col>
18.44</col>
<col>
18.44</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Reconstruction gap</st>

<p>

In October, 2005 the SIGIR introduced the concept of the “reconstruction gap” which was defined as the difference between the reconstruction planned and that which is actually delivered.  As of February 2006, the SIGIR reported that only 36% of water sector projects originally planned will be completed and only 70% of the originally-planned electricity sector projects will be completed.  This shortfall is attributed to IRRF reprogramming of funds from these sectors to meet security needs, poor cost estimates in the original reconstruction plan, increased material costs and lack of administrative oversight.  Estimates of the funds required to close the reconstruction gap are difficult to obtain because there is inadequate information on the cost-to-complete projects already in progress.  In addition to funds for reconstruction, SIGIR recommends that funds be allocated for sustaining the infrastructure that is reconstructed.  Without funding for supplies, technicians and fuel, the facilities that have been completed may fall into disuse.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Attacks on construction activities</st>

<p>

Attacks, murders, bombings and armed vandalism are routine threats to reconstruction contractors.  Since reconstruction began in March 2003, 1073 workers on U.S. funded projects have died, including 235 U.S. civilians, according to the U.S. Departments of Labor and State.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> The table below shows the number of worker deaths in each quarter starting with the first reporting by SIGIR.  In addition, there have been thousands of insurance claims by construction workers for injuries sustained in attacks.  The figures are probably mis-reported, especially among Iraqi contractors.  Intimidation of workers has delayed projects and reduced the availability of non-Iraqi expert technicians.  It is estimated that 25% of reconstruction funds have been used to provide security to construction workers and job sites.</p>
<p>

Attacks and vandalism have also affected completed projects including sabotage of oil pipelines and high-voltage electricity towers. However, the Commander of the Multi-National Force-Iraq, General David Petraeus, announced in May, 2008 that oil and electricity production have exceeded pre-war levels as the "surge" and enlistment of local Iraqis in security forces has brought calm to many areas of the nation.</p>
<p>

<table align="center" cellpadding="5" border="1" cellspacing="0">
<header>
Year</header>
<header>
Quarter 1</header>
<header>
Quarter 2</header>
<header>
Quarter 3</header>
<header>
Quarter 4</header>
<row>
<col>
2004</col>
<col>
NA</col>
<col>
NA</col>
<col>
22</col>
<col>
112</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
2005</col>
<col>
44</col>
<col>
54</col>
<col>
85</col>
<col>
52</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
2006</col>
<col>
52</col>
<col>
59</col>
<col>
91</col>
<col>
101</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
2007</col>
<col>
152</col>
<col>
79</col>
<col>
72</col>
<col>
NA</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Corruption</st>

<p>

It has been alleged that large amounts of American tax dollars and seized Iraqi revenues were lost by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/208316.xml">
Coalition Provisional Authority</link> (CPA). One audit put the total number as high as $8.8 billion.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> Fraudulent contractors such as <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<principal wordnetid="110474950" confidence="0.8">
<wrongdoer wordnetid="109633969" confidence="0.8">
<criminal wordnetid="109977660" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<bad_person wordnetid="109831962" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/3456777.xml">
Philip Bloom</link></bad_person>
</causal_agent>
</criminal>
</wrongdoer>
</principal>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 often bribed CPA officials in exchange for contracts that were never performed. 
An article in the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/30680.xml">
New York Times</link></it> describes "irregularities including millions of reconstruction dollars stuffed casually into footlockers and filing cabinets, an American soldier in the Philippines who gambled away cash belonging to Iraq, and three Iraqis who plunged to their deaths in a rebuilt hospital elevator that had been improperly certified as safe."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> While the US government has begun the process of prosecuting contractors that stole American tax dollars, the Iraqi government currently has no means of reacquiring Iraqi assets that were stolen by US contractors. This is partially due to a decree passed by the CPA that gives civilian contractors in Iraq immunity from all Iraqi jurisdiction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

There was also much controversy surrounding the granting of no-bid contracts to large American corporations like <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/203237.xml">
Halliburton</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/212120.xml">
Bechtel</link></company>
, both of which have made generous donations to President <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/3414021.xml">
George W. Bush</link></businessperson>
</person>
</president>
 and the <party wordnetid="108256968" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/32070.xml">
Republican Party</link></party>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> Halliburton in particular has been singled out for receiving what is perceived to be government favoritism for doing a shoddy job of rebuilding Iraq's oil infrastructure.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> When the Pentagon's own auditors determined that about $263 million of a Halliburton subsidiary's costs were potentially excessive, the Army still paid the company all but $10.1 million of the disputed costs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>
Bechtel Corp. became the first major U.S. contractor to announce that it was pulling out of Iraq in Fall 2006. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>
<p>

Some say that the reconstruction would have been both much more efficient and inexpensive if more contracts were granted to local Iraqi firms, many of whom were shut out of the process due to the fact that they were state-owned.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> Congressman <congressman wordnetid="109955781" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<lawyer wordnetid="110249950" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/408971.xml">
Henry Waxman</link></lawyer>
</congressman>
 was once told by members of the Iraqi governing council that paying Iraqi companies to rebuild Iraq instead of American ones would save American tax payers 90% of the costs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>
<p>

By Summer of 2008, oil and electricity levels returned to pre-invasion (i.e. pre-March, 2003) levels.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Current status of reconstruction</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Electricity</st>

<p>

General Petraeus noted in May, 2008 that electricity levels have exceeded pre-war production.
Current electricity levels of about 4000 MW have not yet reached the stated goal of nationwide production of 6000 MW. To compensate The estimated hours per day of electricity availability has shifted.  During the Saddam rule, Baghdad received electricity for between 16 and 24 hours per day  with 4 to 8 hours received outside of the capital. Information from the Brookings Institution (early 2007) indicates that Baghdad now receives electricity from 4 to 8 hours per day with the remainder of the nation receiving from 8 to 12 hours of electricity per day <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref>  </p>
<p>

Much of the efforts to rebuild Iraq's electrical infrastructure has been largely dependent on the repair and construction of transmission lines and substations by global engineering firms willing to work in hostile territories.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Food</st>
<p>

In May 2006, the United Nations <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/33582.xml">
World Food Program</link> (WFP) concluded its most recent food security survey <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref>. </p>
<p>

It found that 15 percent of the total Iraqi population (just over 4 million people) is food insecure and in dire need of different types of humanitarian assistance, including food, despite the rations they are receiving from the Public Distribution System (PDS). This is an increase from the estimated 11 percent (2.6 million people) deemed to be extremely poor in WFP’s first survey in September 2004. The May 2006 survey also indicated that a further 8.3 million people would be rendered food insecure if they were not provided with a PDS ration, compared to 3.6 million people in the previous survey.  An earlier survey, conducted in July 2005, found that acute malnutrition rates for children was nine percent overall, but with rates for children between 6 and 12 months old reaching 13 percent and 12 percent for those aged between one and two years.</p>
<p>

In 2007, the WFP continues to provide emergency food provisions to about 1.1 million Iraqis.  WFP has assisted in the establishment of a Food Security Unit, located in the Iraq Ministry of Planning and Development Cooperation, which collects food security information.  The PDS is still a major contributor in stabilizing the food supply in Iraq. For the poor and food insecure, the PDS represents by far the single most important food source in their diet. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Water, sanitation and solid waste</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="280px" src="BaghdadGutter.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A street rain gutter in Baghdad's <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/856542.xml">
Green Zone</link></district>
</location>
</region>
 (IZ) in March 2004.
</caption>
</image>
According to a U.N. survey taken in 2004, about 54% of Iraq had access to drinking water <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref>.  As of January 2007, <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> IRRF funded projects have resulted in the construction or rehabilitation of 21 potable water treatment facilities and 200 smaller water systems.  Major projects include the Nassriya Water Treatment Plant which will produce 240,000 cubic meters per day.  A new water canal to supply clean water to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/57580.xml">
Basrah</link> and Thi Qar was completed in April 2006. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> These projects have provided capacity to supply water to approximately 5.4 million people (1.67 million cubic meters per day).  This compares with the target capacity, at the completion of all IRRF funded water projects, of  2.37 million cubic meters per day needed to provide for 8.4 million people.  The water that actually reaches Iraqi citizens is difficult to determine because of significant water losses in the distribution systems.</p>
<p>

A modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/211285.xml">
landfill</link>, built to international environmental standards, is planned for southwest Baghdad, with the capacity to handle 2,230 cubic meters of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/19725148.xml">
waste</link> per day.  The construction was halted prior to completion in November 2005, due to security concerns.  There has been some limited utilization of the landfill, however full utilization has not yet been implemented. 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> </p>
<p>

Recent reports on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/3411618.xml">
waste collection</link>, 
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref> note that being a garbage collector may be one of the most dangerous jobs in Iraq.  Most of the 500 municipal workers who have been killed in Baghdad since 2005 have been <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/1660231.xml">
waste collector</link>s.  There are inadequate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/465689.xml">
waste collection vehicles</link> with only 380 presently in service.  Before the invasion there were 1200 working trucks.   Most of the vehicles were destroyed or lost in the looting that seized the capital after the American invasion.  The deputy mayor of Baghdad estimates the city needs 1,500 waste collection vehicles.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Oil</st>

<p>

Before the 2003 invasion, Iraqi crude oil production was about 2.5&nbsp;million barrels per day (400,000&nbsp;m³/d) (BPD).  Since 2003 production has not increased back to this level.  In 2006 Iraqi crude oil production averaged 2.12 million BPD. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref>  In mid-2006, the Iraqi oil minister, said that <it>"he expected output to rise to approximately 4 m BPD by 2010, increasing to 6 m BPD by 2012."</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref></p>
<p>

The situation has been characterized by some Oil Ministry officials as chaotic, with one official stating "We do not know the exact quantity of oil we are exporting, we do not exactly know the prices we are selling it for, and we do not know where the oil revenue is going to."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref></p>
<p>

In Summer, 2008, the nation's Parliament still had not produced a comprehensive "hydrocarbon law" (oil law) apportioning revenue between local governorates and the central government. While oil production in early 2008 exceeded pre-war levels and continued to climb, disagreements remained among oil-rich regions, oil-poor regions, and the national government over contracting rights and revenue-sharing.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Healthcare</st>

<p>

Until the early 1990s, Iraq's healthcare system was considered one of the most advanced in the Middle East. Following the <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/182000.xml">
Gulf War</link></conflict>
, it began to deteriorate. Prior to the <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/5043324.xml">
Iraq War</link></conflict>
, healthcare spending amounted to 50 cents (US) per Iraqi per year. Today, the Iraqi healthcare system has regressed to a chronic and smoldering condition. Infections are widespread, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/71617.xml">
infant mortality rate</link> has surged, and medical shortages all threaten the once functioning medical system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref>  US based NGO, Giving Children Hope, has an on-going healthcare development program in Iraq that equips hospitals and clinics with needed supplies and equipment in conjunction with the US military. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://71.6.192.13/healthcare-development-in-iraq1.html">
http://71.6.192.13/healthcare-development-in-iraq1.html</weblink></p>
<p>

However, the situation in <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/679693.xml">
Iraqi Kurdistan</link></region>
 (the three northern governorates with primarily <ethnic_group wordnetid="107967382" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/17068.xml">
Kurdish</link></ethnic_group>
 populations) is quite different. Due to their better stability, the Kurdish semi-autonomous area enjoys health care superior to that under Saddam. Health workers have not left the provinces for <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/7515849.xml">
Syria</link></country>
 or <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/7515964.xml">
Jordan</link></country>
, as they have in sectarian Iraq, and new programs for continuing professional education in major Iraqi Kurdish cities reflect the optimism of the area.</p>
<p>

With the primarily Sunni <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/467036.xml">
Al Anbar</link> governorate to the west experiencing increased stability due to the U.S. troop surge and the Sunni rejection of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/11214893.xml">
Al Qaeda in Iraq</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/15729059.xml">
International Health</link><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fhp.osd.mil/intlhealth/">
http://fhp.osd.mil/intlhealth/</weblink> analysts hope to see improved health care there, as well. It remains to be seen whether <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/46539.xml">
non-governmental organizations</link> and the Shiite-dominated central Iraqi government will take advantage of the enhanced security to enact sustainable services and other improvements. Local initiatives in June 2008 included contracting with the International Medical Corps for a comprehensive Anbar continuing medical education program, rights of return for expatriate health professionals, and an overhaul of nursing, with innovative programs paralleling the "diploma" nursing track of the West, and a goal of attracting women to nursing as a career (70% of Iraqi nurses are male).</p>
<p>

Until late 2007, the Ministry of Health had been apportioned by the new Shiite majority to politicians aligned with Moqtada Al Sadr, a minority Shiite party leader and head of a sect prominent in East Baghdad slums. Allegations abounded of abductions of Sunni patients, and Iraqi Security Force (Army and Police) patients, from their hospital beds. The Inspector General was prosecuted for corruption, and the Facilities Protective Service (FPS) commander was dismissed for running a Mafia-like organization, contributing weapons and manpower to terrorist and other gangs.</p>
<p>

At the close of 2007, a new Minister of Health, Saleh Al-Hasnawi, was appointed and began ministerial reforms. The Inspector General was replaced and a new openness was encouraged. In June, 2008, the Minister of Health convened a National Strategic Planning Conference in Baghdad. At this conference, attended by professionals, NGOs and <military_unit wordnetid="108198398" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/383026.xml">
Provincial Reconstruction Team</link></military_unit>
s from all over Iraq, he announced that Iraq would direct its own health reconstruction, funding it with Iraqi money according to Iraqi priorities. Although there is still a place for external expert advice, the determination of the Iraqis to direct their own health development was clear.</p>
<p>

There are sparse data on the role of private practice in Iraq. Estimates range as high as 70% of outpatient visits, compared to approximately 30% before the war. Iraq has included health care as a constitutional right; as government-sponsored care becomes more accessible, the future of private practice will likely change, but it is an ingrained feature of the Iraqi healthcare fabric.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Private sector development</st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="450px" src="BRP2.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<it>Layout of City Nodes of Development for Baghdad Renaissance Plan</it>,  Hisham n. Ashkouri/ARCADD, Inc. shows the proposed plan, to be built on reclaimed alluvial land, and intended "<it>to be self-sufficient, supporting its own growth as well as that of Baghdad</it>", according to its designer.
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Proposed Baghdad Renaissance Plan</st>
<p>

Some private sector developments have also been proposed.  One of these, The Proposed Baghdad Renaissance Plan <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.arcadd.com/baghdad-cbd.htm">
http://www.arcadd.com/baghdad-cbd.htm</weblink>,  is a 25-year scheme, designed by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/903378.xml">
architect</link> <architect wordnetid="109805475" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/11307556.xml">
Hisham N. Ashkouri</link></architect>
 to transform 9 km² of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/183243.xml">
silt deposits</link> into an "an up-market commercial and residential neighborhood" astride the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/31259.xml">
Tigris River</link> in central <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/4492.xml">
Baghdad</link></village>
, as well as nearby <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/11577930.xml">
Tahrir Square</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
.  Tahrir Square was originally part of the central business district of Baghdad, and Phase I of the plan focuses on the redevelopment of this area. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.menafn.com/qn_news_story_s.asp?storyid=64178">
http://www.menafn.com/qn_news_story_s.asp?storyid=64178</weblink> </p>
<p>

When finished, the "commerce, banking, medical, housing, broadcast and IT, exhibition, conventions and cultural centers" of which the plan is comprised would be occupied by up to one-half million people.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref>  The project received encouragement by the <link>
U.S. Department of Commerce</link> as well as other US and Middle East organizations. A smaller-scale proposal of Dr. Ashkouri's is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/11577962.xml">
Sindbad Hotel Complex and Conference Center</link>,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref> a high-rise hotel and movie theater complex which would be Baghdad's first skyscraper.</p>
<p>

Prevailing views are that political and social instability in the region are making such developments unduly risky, despite a high projected return on investment.  Security concerns during the survey and construction phases are currently a cost-prohibitive factor.</p>
<p>

<b>On the other hand</b>, this development is opposed by many Iraqi academics and architects due to its intentions of eliminating the urban fabric a historic parts of city which was created through centuries and replacing it with a commercial version of high rise buildings that lack any regional or local references. This project is one of the attempts to recreate a Dubai like boom to benefit certain groups and entities, ignoring on its way the traditional and historical heritage of a city like Baghdad.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/933377.xml">
History of Iraqi insurgency</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/228708.xml">
2003 occupation of Iraq</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<chronology wordnetid="106503224" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<timeline wordnetid="106504965" confidence="0.8">
<written_record wordnetid="106502378" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/184613.xml">
2003 Iraq war timeline</link></written_record>
</timeline>
</evidence>
</indication>
</chronology>
</record>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/1514912.xml">
Development Fund for Iraq</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/228708.xml">
Post-invasion Iraq, 2003-2006</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/1576797.xml">
New Iraqi Army</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/14668.xml">
Economy of Iraq</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/10041299.xml">
Iraq oil law (2007)</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</disagreement>
</dispute>
</event>
</controversy>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/11665672.xml">
International Compact with Iraq</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Flag_of_Iraq.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Iraq War&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Flag_of_Iraq.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Iraq&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irffi.org">
IRFFI</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://siteresources.worldbank.org/IRFFI/Resources/Joint+Needs+Assessment.pdf">
 UN/World Bank Joint Iraq Needs Assessment October 2003</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://siteresources.worldbank.org/IRFFI/64168382-1092419001661/20946870/UNDGITFThirdSix-monthlyProgressReportPartOne(final).pdf">
 UN Development Group Progress Report, Part 1, 11 May 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://siteresources.worldbank.org/IRFFI/64168382-1092419001661/20946872/UNDGITFThirdsixmonthlyreportPartTwo(final).pdf">
UN Development Group Progress Report, Part 2, 11 May 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://siteresources.worldbank.org/IRFFI/64168382-1092419012421/20947441/WBITFProgressReportDec2005.pdf">
 World Bank Progress Report, 31 December 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d05876.pdf">
 GAO Report to Congress: Rebuilding Iraq, July 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://armed-services.senate.gov/statemnt/2006/February/Bolton%2002-07-06.pdf">
Congressional Testimony of Asst. Sec. of the Army, Bolton, February 2006</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir.mil/reports/quarterlyreports/Jul06/Default.aspx">
SIGIR Report to Congress July 30, 2006 Appendix H</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir.mil/reports/quarterlyreports/Oct04/cpaig_october_30_report.pdf">
Report to Congress October 30, 2004 Table 8</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).</entry>
<entry id="10">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir.mil/reports/pdf/audits/06-004.pdf">
SIGIR Audit Report 06-004 April 28, 2006, Table 1</weblink>"&#32;(PDF).</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir.mil/reports/quarterlyreports/Jul06/Default.aspx">
SIGIR Report to Congress July 30, 2006 Appendix K</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir.mil/reports/quarterlyreports/Oct07/Default.aspx">
SIGIR Report to Congress October 30, 07 The Human Toll</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://edition.cnn.com/2005/WORLD/meast/01/30/iraq.audit/">
CNN.com - Audit: U.S. lost track of $9 billion in Iraq funds - Jan 30, 2005</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.warprofiteers.com/article.php?id=13161">
CorpWatch : IRAQ: Audit Describes Misuse of Funds in Iraq Projects</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.commondreams.org/headlines06/0416-02.htm">
US Firms Suspected of Bilking Iraq Funds</weblink></entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/25/world/middleeast/25pipeline.html?incamp=article_popular">
Rebuilding of Iraqi Pipeline as Disaster Waiting to Happen - New York Times</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opensecrets.org/news/rebuilding_iraq/index.asp">
Rebuilding Iraq</weblink></entry>
<entry id="19">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.truthout.org/docs_2006/111406G.shtml">
t r u t h o u t | Bechtel Bails on Iraq</weblink></entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/27/international/middleeast/27contract.html?ex=1298696400&amp;en=075a4c9d410f6860&amp;ei=5088&amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss">
Army to Pay Halliburton Unit Most Costs Disputed by Audit - New York Times</weblink></entry>
<entry id="21">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://zmagsite.zmag.org/Sept2004/cannon0904.html">
The Ruse of Reconstruction</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A10640-2004Feb26">
Iraqi Experts Tossed With The Water (washingtonpost.com)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="23">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.symbion-power.com/experience/line_al-qaim.html">
Transimission line restoration in Sunni Triangle</weblink></entry>
<entry id="22">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brookings.edu/fp/saban/iraq/index.pdf"></weblink></entry>
<entry id="25">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wfp.org/country_brief/indexcountry.asp?country=368">
WFP - Where we work - Iraq</weblink></entry>
<entry id="24">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.symbion-power.com/experience/sub_farabi.html">
Gas Insulated Substations reconstruction near Sadr City, Iraq</weblink></entry>
<entry id="27">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir.mil/reports/quarterlyreports/Jan07/pdf/Report_-_January_2007_Complete.pdf">
 SIGIR Report to Congress January 30, 2007</weblink></entry>
<entry id="26">
http://www.iq.undp.org/ILCS/infrastructure.htm</entry>
<entry id="29">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir.mil/reports/pdf/assessments/pa-06-067_baghdad_landfill.pdf">
 SIGIR Report 06-067 October 19, 2006</weblink></entry>
<entry id="28">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.grd.usace.army.mil/news/releases/recon040606.html">
Gulf Region Division</weblink></entry>
<entry id="31">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/5117170.stm">
BBC NEWS | Business | Iraq oil output hits a new high</weblink></entry>
<entry id="30">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iht.com/articles/2006/10/11/news/trash.php">
NYTimes 10/11/06</weblink></entry>
<entry id="34">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tufts.edu/home/feature/?p=ashkouri">
Profile: Hisham Ashkouri - Feature - Tufts University</weblink></entry>
<entry id="35">
http://www.cinemasindbad.com/pdf/CS%20Factsheet.pdf</entry>
<entry id="32">
Heiko Flottau&#32;(<link>
2005-12-07</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.isn.ethz.ch/news/sw/details.cfm?ID=13770">
Iraqi oil industry in crisis</weblink>", ISN.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-12-12</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="33">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://discovermagazine.com/2007/aug/iraq2019s">
Iraq’s Medical Meltdown | Health Policy | DISCOVER Magazine</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Links to Iraq reconstruction agencies</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irffi.org">
International Reconstruction Fund Facility for Iraq</weblink> Updates on reconstruction activities by the United Nations and World Bank.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.defenselink.mil/tfbso/">
Task Force to Improve Business and Stability Operations - Iraq</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rebuilding-iraq.net/">
U.S. Army Corps of Engineers</weblink> Weekly updates on Iraq reconstruction.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.usaid.gov/iraq">
USAID Assistance to Iraq Homepage</weblink> Updates and financial summaries on USAID managed reconstruction projects in Iraq.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sigir.mil/">
Special Inspector General for Iraq Reconstruction</weblink> Watchdog for fraud, waste, and abuse of U.S. funds intended for Iraq reconstruction.  Quarterly updates and expenditure progress. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.export.gov/iraq">
Iraq Investment and Reconstruction Task Force (U.S. Dept. of Commerce)</weblink> Assistance to the private sector for reconstruction and business opportunities.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.icrc.org/">
International Committee of the Red Cross</weblink> Operational updates for ICRC activities in Iraq.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ifrc.org/where/country/cn6.asp?countryid=87">
International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies</weblink> Updates on activities of the Iraqi Red Crescent Society.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External articles and references</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epic-usa.org/Default.aspx?tabid=2218">
The Ground Truth Project</weblink> -- A series of exclusive, in-depth interviews and other resources with Iraqis, aid workers, military personnel and others who have spent significant time working to rebuild Iraq from the inside. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.map-of-iraq.com">
Map of Iraq</weblink>- High resolution maps of Iraq.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.defendamerica.mil">
Defend America: U.S. Department of Defense News About the War on Terrorism</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.defenselink.mil/home/features/Iraq_Reports/Index.html">
Measuring Stability and Security: U.S. Department of Defense Measuring Stability and Security in Iraq Quarterly Reports</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://iraq.usembassy.gov/iraq/20060223_prt_fact_sheet.html">
Fact Sheet on Provincial Reconstruction Teams (PRTs)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 * Kenneth M. Pollack, "<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foreignaffairs.org/20040109faupdate83175/kenneth-m-pollack/after-saddam-assessing-the-reconstruction-of-iraq.html%E2%80%9D">
After Saddam: Assessing the Reconstruction of Iraq</weblink></it>". From foreignaffairs.org - author update, January 12, 2004.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iraqanalysis.org/info/125">
Iraq Analysis Economic Development Page</weblink> Comprehensive information source listings on reconstruction of Iraq</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alternet.org/waroniraq/20942/">
Dahar Jamail, "Iraq: The Devastation", AlterNet</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/file_on_4/4216853.stm">
Iraq reconstruction funds missing</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://atlas-real.atlas.uiuc.edu:8080/ramgen/ips/acdis/acdis_iraq_2005.04.20.rm">
Video Seminar on Iraq Coalition Politics</weblink>: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
April 20</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link>, sponsored by the Program in Arms Control, Disarmament, and International Security at the University of Illinois.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.arcadd.com/baghdad-cbd.htm">
 Baghdad Renaissance Plan</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iraqieconomy.org/home/bilecon/uae/2004.09.23">
UAE Investors Keen On Taking Part In Baghdad Renaissance Project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tufts.edu/home/feature/?p=ashkouri">
Man With A Plan: Hisham Ashkouri</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.arcadd.com/scholastic-article.htm">
Renaissance Plan In The News</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.arcadd.com">
ARCADD, Inc.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.symbion-power.com/">
Symbion Power</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background: lightsteelblue; font-size: 95%;" class="navbox-title">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/5043324.xml">
Iraq War</link></conflict>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background: gainsboro;;" class="navbox-group">
Prior events</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/66436.xml">
Disarmament crisis</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/155177.xml">
WMD claims</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/3891386.xml">
Rationale</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/183869.xml">
UN Security Council involvement</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background: gainsboro;;" class="navbox-group">
Invasion andoccupation</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<p>

<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/201936.xml">
Invasion</link></conflict>
&nbsp;· 
<position wordnetid="105079866" confidence="0.8">
<record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<chronology wordnetid="106503224" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<bodily_property wordnetid="104997988" confidence="0.8">
<timeline wordnetid="106504965" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<stance wordnetid="105082507" confidence="0.8">
<written_record wordnetid="106502378" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/243750.xml">
Occupation timeline</link></written_record>
</stance>
</property>
</timeline>
</bodily_property>
</evidence>
</indication>
</chronology>
</record>
</position>
&nbsp;· 
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<unfortunate wordnetid="109630641" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<victim wordnetid="110752093" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<casualty wordnetid="109899782" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/202089.xml">
Casualties</link></casualty>
</causal_agent>
</victim>
</person>
</unfortunate>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;· 
<unit_of_measurement wordnetid="113583724" confidence="0.8">
<definite_quantity wordnetid="113576101" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/5215751.xml">
Multinational force</link></definite_quantity>
</unit_of_measurement>
&nbsp;· 
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<neologism wordnetid="106294441" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<resistance wordnetid="101169317" confidence="0.8">
<word wordnetid="106286395" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<rebellion wordnetid="101177327" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<motion wordnetid="100331950" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/847626.xml">
Insurgency</link></language_unit>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</part>
</motion>
</act>
</rebellion>
</conflict>
</word>
</resistance>
</action>
</event>
</politics>
</group_action>
</neologism>
</social_relation>
</change>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/9326517.xml">
Terrorist attacks</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background: gainsboro;;" class="navbox-group">
Aftermath</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/208316.xml">
Coalition Provisional Authority</link>&nbsp;· 
<human_right wordnetid="105176846" confidence="0.8">
<right wordnetid="105174653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/8611907.xml">
Refugees</link></right>
</human_right>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/350279.xml">
Iraq Survey Group (Duelfer Report)</link>&nbsp;· 
<politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<gossip wordnetid="107223170" confidence="0.8">
<scandal wordnetid="107223811" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<informing wordnetid="107212190" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<report wordnetid="107217924" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/610543.xml">
Reconstruction</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</report>
</social_relation>
</informing>
</event>
</scandal>
</gossip>
</politics>
&nbsp;· 
<controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<human_right wordnetid="105176846" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<right wordnetid="105174653" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/612951.xml">
Human rights</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</right>
</act>
</human_right>
</disagreement>
</dispute>
</event>
</controversy>
&nbsp;· 
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/2372429.xml">
Civil war</link></conflict>
&nbsp;· 
<position wordnetid="105079866" confidence="0.8">
<bodily_property wordnetid="104997988" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<stance wordnetid="105082507" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/1032342.xml">
U.S. troop withdrawal</link></stance>
</property>
</bodily_property>
</position>
</p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background: gainsboro;;" class="navbox-group">

Stances and opinions regarding the 2003 Iraq conflict|Opinions</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<p>

<position wordnetid="105079866" confidence="0.8">
<bodily_property wordnetid="104997988" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<stance wordnetid="105082507" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/173750.xml">
Views on the invasion</link></stance>
</property>
</bodily_property>
</position>
&nbsp;· 
<controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/183867.xml">
Opposition</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</disagreement>
</dispute>
</event>
</controversy>
&nbsp;· 
<controversy wordnetid="107183151" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<dispute wordnetid="107181935" confidence="0.8">
<disagreement wordnetid="107180787" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/202304.xml">
Protests</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</disagreement>
</dispute>
</event>
</controversy>
&nbsp;· 
<position wordnetid="105079866" confidence="0.8">
<law wordnetid="108441203" confidence="0.8">
<issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<bodily_property wordnetid="104997988" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<stance wordnetid="105082507" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/3891667.xml">
Legitimacy</link></stance>
</group>
</collection>
</property>
</bodily_property>
</issue>
</law>
</position>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/205924.xml">
Associated people</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background: gainsboro;;" class="navbox-group">
Iraq since 2003</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/1063469.xml">
2003</link>&nbsp;· 
<record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<chronology wordnetid="106503224" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<timeline wordnetid="106504965" confidence="0.8">
<written_record wordnetid="106502378" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/434346.xml">
2004</link></written_record>
</timeline>
</evidence>
</indication>
</chronology>
</record>
&nbsp;· 
<record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<chronology wordnetid="106503224" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<timeline wordnetid="106504965" confidence="0.8">
<written_record wordnetid="106502378" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/1361579.xml">
2005</link></written_record>
</timeline>
</evidence>
</indication>
</chronology>
</record>
&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/4499412.xml">
2006</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/8708788.xml">
2007</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/15142001.xml">
2008</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";background: gainsboro;" class="navbox-abovebelow">
Iraq War at &nbsp;·  </col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</report>
</social_relation>
</informing>
</event>
</scandal>
</gossip>
</politics>
</article>
