<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:23:29[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<university  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="108286163">
<header>
<title>Sichuan University</title>
<id>614856</id>
<revision>
<id>235865305</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-02T18:40:23Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Camfordwiki</username>
<id>7761567</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Universities and colleges in Chengdu</category>
<category>Project 985</category>
<category>Project 211</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_University</name>
<parameters>
<president>
Xie Heping(谢和平)</president>
<students>
70,000 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></students>
<website>
http://www.scu.edu.cn/</website>
<state>
<state wordnetid="108654360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/65185.xml">
Sichuan</link></state>
</state>
<established>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/34668.xml">
1896</link></established>
<type>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/1640986.xml">
Public</link></type>
<city>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/170375.xml">
Chengdu</link></village>
</city>
<country>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5042862.xml">
China</link></country>
<staff>
11,357</staff>
<image_name>
Logescu.jpg</image_name>
<name>
Sichuan University</name>
<motto>
海纳百川 有容乃大</motto>
</parameters>
</template>



<p>

<b>Sichuan University</b> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/266210.xml">
traditional Chinese</link>: 四川大學; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/261949.xml">
simplified Chinese</link>: 四川大学; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../588/23588.xml">
pinyin</link>: Sìchuān Dàxué) is one of the oldest and prestigious <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/19725260.xml">
universities</link> in China ,located in the city of <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/170375.xml">
Chengdu</link></village>
, in the <state wordnetid="108654360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/65185.xml">
Sichuan</link></state>
 province of the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/5405.xml">
People's Republic of China</link></country>
. As one of the national key universities directly under <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/1241910.xml">
the State Ministry of Education (MOE)</link></agency>
 as well as one of the State <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/3417194.xml">
211 Project</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
 universities enjoying privileged construction in the Ninth <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/12911370.xml">
Five-Year Plan</link> period, the present Sichuan University (SCU) was first incorporated with <b>Chengdu University of Science and Technology (CUST)</b>, and later another national key university under <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/1241910.xml">
the Ministry of Education</link></agency>
 in 1994, and <b>West China University of Medical Science (WCUMS)</b>, a key university directly subordinate to the State <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/4792478.xml">
Ministry of Health</link></agency>
 in 2000. The present Secretary of the <b>Party</b> committee is Prof. Yang Quan-ming, and the President currently in office is Prof. <b>Xie He-ping</b> (academician of the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/4253959.xml">
Chinese Academy of Engineering</link></association>
</institute>
).</p>


<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

The former Sichuan Univ. was one of the earliest institutes of higher learning in China, with a history dating back to <b>Sichuan Zhong-Xi Xuetang (Sichuan Chinese and Western School)</b>, established in 1896, which was in a direct line of succession with <b>Jinjiang Shuyuan</b> and <b>Zunjing Shuyuan</b>, places for classical learning, set up in 1704 and 1875 respectively. 
By the eve of New China, Sichuan Univ. had developed into the biggest national multidisciplinary university with 6 colleges of literature, science, engineering, agriculture, law and teachers training, and 25 departments. Sichuan Univ. is one of the pioneers of modern Chinese higher education, playing a demonstrating role in the development of the modern higher education in West China. 
<image location="right" width="400px" src="gate_of_scu.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The Old SCU
</caption>
</image>

After the birth of New China, through the nationwide adjustment of colleges and departments, Sichuan Univ. grew out to be a dominant comprehensive university in literature, historiography, religion, math, biology, etc. In 1958, it was the only one (the other six in Beijing) that was identified by the Central Government as university directly under the State administration and guiding the others. The predecessor of <b>CUST</b> is <b>Chengdu Engineering College</b>, set up in 1954 as the result of the nation-wide college and department adjustment, with celebrated disciplines in materials, chemical engineering, hydroelectricity, mechanics, textile and light industry, etc. <b>WCUMS</b> originated from the private <b>Huaxi Xiehe College (West China Coordinated College)</b>, established in 1910 by five Christian missionary groups from U.S.A., UK and Canada, with disciplines in stomatology, biomedicine, basic medicine and clinical medicine greatly influential at home and abroad. 
Throughout its centennial history, SCU has been the cradle for a great number of celebrated revolutionaries, educators as well as scientists and men of letters enjoying a high reputation both at home and abroad. Among them, both <link>
Zhang Lan</link>, the famous social activist, educationist, and the former Vice-chairman of the Central Government, and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../412/10557412.xml">
Wu Yuzhang</link></person>
, the noted revolutionary and educationist, once took up office as the president successively. Marshal <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<preserver wordnetid="110466918" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<lawman wordnetid="110249459" confidence="0.8">
<defender wordnetid="109614684" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<marshal wordnetid="110295951" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/230932.xml">
Zhu De</link></marshal>
</causal_agent>
</defender>
</lawman>
</leader>
</preserver>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, one the founding fathers of the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/5405.xml">
People's Republic of China</link></country>
 and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/66890.xml">
People's Liberation Army</link>; <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<archeologist wordnetid="109804806" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/623736.xml">
Guo Moruo</link></scientist>
</archeologist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</person>
</anthropologist>
</physical_entity>
, a literary giant and the previous president of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/377856.xml">
Chinese Academy of Science</link>; <writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<novelist wordnetid="110363573" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/478078.xml">
Ba Jin</link></novelist>
</writer>
, a leading authority in literature, once studied here. Up to now, there are 45 academicians among the alumni. </p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Present </st>
<p>

SCU has the widest coverage of disciplines and the largest scale of operation in West China. There are 15 key disciplines at the national level, 14 <b><work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/3417194.xml">
"211 Project"</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
</b> key construction disciplines, 29 key disciplines at the provincial and ministerial level, 4 national bases for personnel training in basic disciplines and scientific research, and a teaching base for engineering courses. Besides, it has 12 first-class disciplines to grant Doctor’s degree and Master’s degree, 111 second-class disciplines to grant Doctor’s degree, 178 Master programs, 6 specialized degree programs, and 16 post-doctor stations. The 109 bachelor programs cover the major fields in liberal arts, sciences, engineering, medicine and agriculture. <b>SCU</b> has a current student population of more than 70 thousand. Ever since the birth of New China, it has cultivated over 200 thousand students, and therefore it has been identified by the MOE as the Collegiate Cultural Quality Education Base.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Teaching Force</st>
<p>

SCU has a current total staff of 11,357, among whom 1323 are professors, 2345 associate professors, 10 academicians of <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/377856.xml">
Chinese Academy of Sciences</link></group>
</association>
</society>
</social_group>
</institute>
 and <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/4253959.xml">
Chinese Academy of Engineering</link></association>
</institute>
, 434 tutors of doctor students, and 17 members of the <b>Academic Degrees Committee and the Discipline Appraisal Group</b> under the <b><link>
State Council</link></b>. Besides, the university has 14 posts of the <b>Yangtze River Scholar Award Plan</b> for specially engaged professors (9 engaged plus 1 lecture professor).</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Potentiality in Scientific Research</st>
<p>

There are in function 2 national key labs, 6 national engineering centers, 5 ministerial (MOE) key labs, 35 provincial key labs, 10 ministerial and provincial centers, 4 key research bases for humanities and social sciences, and 4 clinical research bases at the national level. SCU has undertaken and completed a considerable number of national, ministerial and regional major research projects, and has made many achievements, which are rated first class in China and bear significant international influence. The total value of the equipment applied to teaching, scientific research and medical treatment amounts to about 530 million RMB yuan and the annual publications of research papers exceed 4,000. In 2002, the university was supported with a total of 29 million RMB yuan for scientific research in natural science,  engineering and medicine; entrusted with 140 National Natural Science Foundation projects for a total of 29 million RMB yuan, 112 out of which were to hand, amounting to 29.5 million RMB yuan, ranking fifth among other universities in China. In addition, it was supported with another 29 million RMB yuan for research in humanities and social science. In that year, 3079 scientific papers were published at home and abroad, ranking seventh, among which 341 were included by SCI, ranking eleventh, and quoted by 391 times, ranking fifteenth. 2484 papers in science, engineering and medicine were published in China’s core periodicals, ranking sixth, and were quoted by 2644 times, ranking seventh. In the same year, 150-odd monographs and 1,500-odd papers in social science were published, with more than 40% indexed by CSSCI. Still in that year, the university succeeded in applying 121 patents, 102 out of which were invention-oriented, ranking eighth.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Facilities</st>
<p>

The University has four libraries with about 5.5 million volumes.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The libraries also serves as the Collection Center for English Publications under the National Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, <link>
MOE </link>Information Center for Liberal Arts Literature and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://opac.calis.edu.cn/">
CALIS</weblink> Southwest Sub-center, National University Scientific and Technological Projects and Achievements Consulting Center, and Center for Medical Literature Retrieval in Southwest China as well. The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scudm.cn/bwg/index.jsp">
University Museum</weblink> is the only one of its kind in China with a comprehensive collection of cultural relics over 40,000 pieces, and animal and plant specimens over 600,000 pieces, ranking first in its holdings among the others in China.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The University Stadium is fully and sophisticatedly equipped and once served as the main field for the Sixth National Collegiate Sports Meet. Other sub-divisions available are Campus Web Center, Analytic and Testing Center, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://archives.scu.edu.cn/">
University Archive Establishment</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scupress.com.cn/">
University Press</weblink>, National Foreign Language Examination Center and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cis.scu.edu.cn/">
Intensive Language Training Center</weblink>, 4 attached hospitals, and 1 attached health school. So far the university has published 37 academic periodicals to domestic and overseas subscribers.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Campus</st>
<p>

SCU is located in Chengdu, a culturally and historically noticeable city, adjacent to the <b>Jinjiang River</b> and its tributary <b>Jiang’an River</b>. The University consists of 3 Campuses of <b>Wangjiang</b>, <b>Huaxi</b> and <b>Jiang’an</b>, covering an area of over 7,000 Chinese <link>
 mu</link> (about 4.7 km²), with a total floorage of more than 2.7 million square meters.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Kuaihuo Forest (Merry Forest)</st>
<p>

Somebody don't know the exact meaning of this forest, but somebody certainly do. With the traditional point of view, the name derived from the feeling of those lovers, who experience merry and happy within the forest. Everybody in SCU know the forest located in the eastern part of Wangjiang Campus, around the NO.4 building. Some of the senior student may have heard of the history of a ghost story in the No.4 building. But this will not influence the feeling of happiness in the forest nearby. Merry, are in both mental and physical. It is really a great place for SCUers.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Colleges and Schools</st>
<p>

The University has over 30 colleges or schools in various disciplines<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scu.edu.cn/portal/colleges/H6020index_1.htm">
http://www.scu.edu.cn/portal/colleges/H6020index_1.htm</weblink>, including: </p>

<ss2>
<st>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://physics.scu.edu.cn/">
College of Physical Science and Technology</weblink></st>
<p>

The College of Physical Science and Technology is located in Wangjiang Campus, which is one of the most biggest and eldest college in the university. The Department of Physics was established in the year 1928, which means have a history more than 80 years. There are two key national deciplines, which is Atomic&amp;Mol. Physics and Nuclear Technology. Basically speaking, the Atomic&amp;Mol. Physics is studied in the western part of Wangjiang Campus, and the Nuclear Technology is carried out in the eastern part, in NO.1 Science Building. There're also professor focus on the study of Optics, Condense Matter, Theory. The Optics was originally a national decipline in 1980s, but not now. Condense Matter physics was famous for its research on mesoscopic electron transporation lab. And the leader of the laboratory, acadimician of Chinese Engineering Acadamy Prof. Jie Gao, now focus on the transportation of single electron with the aim of finding novelty ways to measure tiny electrical current. There is a material research group with the leader Prof. Tiecheng Lu, had great achievement in the invention of some peculiar materials.</p>

<ss3>
<st>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scdxart.com/2006/index.html">
Art College</weblink></st>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://flc.scu.edu.cn/">
College of Foreign Languages and Cultures</weblink></st>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://math.scu.edu.cn/">
College of Mathematics</weblink></st>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ce.scu.edu.cn/">
School of Chemical Engineering</weblink></st>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pharmacy.scu.edu.cn/">
School of Pharmacy</weblink></st>

</ss3>
<ss3>
<st>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hxkq.scu.edu.cn/">
College of Stomatology</weblink></st>


</ss3>
</ss2>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notable Persons associated with Sichuan University</st>
<p>

<link>
 Zhu De </link> 朱德</p>
<p>

<link>
Yang Shangkun </link> 杨尚昆</p>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<archeologist wordnetid="109804806" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/623736.xml">
Guo Moruo</link></scientist>
</archeologist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</person>
</anthropologist>
</physical_entity>
 郭沫若</p>
<p>

<link>
Ba Jin</link> 巴金</p>
<p>

<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/684707.xml">
Feng Youlan</link></scientist>
 冯友兰</p>
<p>

<link>
Wu Yuzhang</link> 吴玉章</p>
<p>

<link>
Tong Dizhou</link> 童第周</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/3585461.xml">
Zhu Guangqian</link> 朱光潜</p>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/1933119.xml">
Ke Zhao</link></educator>
</scholar>
</mathematician>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 柯召</p>


<ss2>
<st>
Sports and Arts</st>

<p>

<tennis_player wordnetid="110701180" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/2480964.xml">
Zheng Jie</link></tennis_player>
 郑洁</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/2905894.xml">
Yan Zi</link> 晏紫</p>
<p>

<marble wordnetid="103721047" confidence="0.8">
<game_equipment wordnetid="103414162" confidence="0.8">
<ball wordnetid="102778669" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<taw wordnetid="104396093" confidence="0.8">
<equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/15673746.xml">
Zhang Shan</link></equipment>
</taw>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</ball>
</game_equipment>
</marble>
 张山</p>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<volleyball_player wordnetid="110759047" confidence="0.8">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.8">
<contestant wordnetid="109613191" confidence="0.8">
<winner wordnetid="110782940" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<medalist wordnetid="110305062" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/12684881.xml">
Zhu Ling</link></medalist>
</causal_agent>
</winner>
</contestant>
</player>
</volleyball_player>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 朱玲</p>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<singer wordnetid="110599806" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/2605022.xml">
Zhang Liangying </link></actor>
</singer>
</person>
 张靓颖</p>



</ss2>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/2355207.xml">
List of universities in the People's Republic of China</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scu.org.cn/Resources/resource.asp">
Brief Introduction of the Library</weblink>
</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scu.org.cn/Resources/resource2.asp">
Introduction Of Sichuan University Museum</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scu.org.cn/Aboutscu/aboutscu.asp">
Sichuan University</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scu.edu.cn/">
Sichuan University Homepage (Chinese)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.scu.org.cn/home/home.asp">
Sichuan University Homepage (English)</weblink></entry>
</list>





</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</university>
</article>
