<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:06:33[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<technique  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105665146">
<know-how  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105616786">
<method  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105660268">
<header>
<title>Defatting</title>
<id>6154033</id>
<revision>
<id>233490164</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-22T07:10:05Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rada</username>
<id>289235</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Health</category>
<category>Chemical safety</category>
<category>Cooking techniques</category>
<category>Nutrition</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<b>Defatting</b> is a term which is used to describe the removal of fatty acids from an object.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Culinary definition </st>

<p>

From the perspective of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/2597318.xml">
culinary</link> science, the word defatting refers to various methods which are used to reduce the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
fat</link> content of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/80018.xml">
meal</link>.  This term can be used to categorize procedures that reduce the fat content of a food both after <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/5355.xml">
cooking</link>, and during the preparation of the meal.  Defatting is also often referred to as <b>fat trimming</b>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Benefits of defatting </st>
<p>

Defatting is often used by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/8460.xml">
diet</link>ers, particularly those following <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/1879534.xml">
Ornish Diet</link> or other low fat diets to reduce their fat consumption to induce weight loss.  The energy content of 1g of fat is 9 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/6423.xml">
calories</link>, while that of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/5932.xml">
carbohydrates</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
proteins</link> are 4 calories.  Hence, dieters often view decreasing fat consumption as an efficient way of losing weight without greatly sacrificing total volume of food.  Defatting during meal preparation is used to reduce the energy content of the food being prepared, and defatting on a prepared food is also often used in social situations where one may have to consume restaurant food which is rich in fat.</p>
<p>

Those people who wish to reduce their cholesterol level or fat intake, in particular people with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/513039.xml">
hypercholesterolemia</link> often use defatting to reduce their fat consumption.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Defatting of a meal after preparation </st>
<p>

Many different foods can be defatted after preparation. Some of these items are, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/52993.xml">
roasted</link> foods, oily foods which are solid, and liquid foods with floating oil. </p>
<p>

Roasted foods can often be defatted without decreasing the crispiness of the food item by simply blotting out the oil in the food item with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/2026564.xml">
tissue paper</link>.  For instance, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/10885.xml">
French fries</link> can be defatted by blotting out the fat with a piece of tissue paper.  The oil that is blotted on the tissue paper signifies the fat content that was reduced from the meal.  </p>
<p>

Other oily foods which may not necessarily be roasted, but are solid in nature may also be defatted by the same tissue paper blotting technique.  For instance, a slice of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/24768.xml">
pepperoni pizza</link> can be defatted by blotting out some of the fat from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/11749910.xml">
cheese</link> with a tissue paper.</p>
<p>

Foods which are liquid in nature and are floating with oil can be defatted by simply scooping out floating oil with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/46847.xml">
spoon</link>.  For example, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/19651298.xml">
soup</link> which is high in fat content can be defatted by scooping out the floating oil with a spoon and then discarding the oil.  In this case, the oil that was scooped out is the fat that was reduced from the meal.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Defatting of a meal during preparation </st>
<p>

Fat trimming of a meal can be done during preparation by a variety of methods.  The most common methods involving substituting food items or removal of naturally occurring fat and conservative addition of fat.</p>
<p>

Substituting fats is a method in which a certain ingredient is substituted by another ingredient.  A common way of doing this is substituting saturated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acids</link> with unsaturated fatty acids while cooking.  For instance, olive oil can be used instead of butter for seasoning salad.</p>
<p>

Food items are also substituted to reduce fat content.  For instance, instead of using eggs by using a whole egg, where the egg yolks are high in fat levels, egg whites can instead be used.  Alternatively, <link>
skimmed milk</link> or similar low fat products can be used as ingredients for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/5355.xml">
cooking</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Commercial defatting </st>
<p>

Many food manufacturing companies such as <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.weightwatchers.ca/index.aspx">
Weight Watchers</weblink> have been developed for people who wish to reduce their fat intake.  The customer need of defatting has also lead to the production of low fat products, eg., low fat cheese.</p>
<p>

Although there is a patent on a lipase inhibitor, there are no products which are commercially available which inhibit fat in food by addition of a compound to the food product, likely because of the development of drugs such as <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="114778436" confidence="0.8">
<drug wordnetid="103247620" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/402247.xml">
Orlistat</link></drug>
</agent>
</causal_agent>
</substance>
</physical_entity>
 which inhibit the absorption of fat instead.  Such a product is also not commercially available due to the likely abuse by people suffering from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/168536.xml">
Bulimia Nervosa</link>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Chemical definition </st>

<p>

Defatting is the term of a skin condition similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/2221241.xml">
Dermatitis</link> resulting from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/157293.xml">
chronic</link> exposure of human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/27978.xml">
skin</link> to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/1014.xml">
alcohol</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/92514.xml">
detergent</link>s, chemical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/37431.xml">
solvent</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/216189.xml">
motor oil</link> caused by the chemical dissolving of the oils (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/17940.xml">
lipids</link>) which constitute the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/7481.xml">
cell membrane</link>s. </p>
<p>

Defatting can be prevented by wearing appropriate protective clothing such as gloves, lab coats or aprons when dealing with defatting agents on a regular basis for a long time. </p>
<p>

It should also be noted that defatting increases the possibility of irritant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/692633.xml">
contact dermatitis</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ehso.com/msdsdefs.php">
Definitions of Terms Used in Material Safety Data Sheets</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.patentstorm.us/patents/5503831-description.html">
 Lipase inhibitor derived from a defatted rice germ</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://health.howstuffworks.com/cholesterol5.htm">
How Cholesterol Works</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.americanheart.org/presenter.jhtml?identifier=516">
Cook For Lower Cholesterol</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medicine.manchester.ac.uk/coeh/teachinglearning/resources/skin">
Occupational and Environmental Skin diseases</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</article>
