<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:25:17[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Key server (cryptographic)</title>
<id>616119</id>
<revision>
<id>239117093</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-17T21:43:02Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Danny</username>
<id>584</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Key management</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
computer security</link>, a <b>key server</b> is a computer &mdash; typically running special software &mdash; which provides cryptographic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/53039.xml">
key</link>s to users or other programs. The users' programs can be working on the same network as the key server or on another networked computer.<p>

The keys distributed by the key server are almost always provided as part of a cryptographically-protected <link>
identity certificate</link> containing not only the key but also 'entity' information about the owner of the key.  The certificate is usually in a standard format, such as the <link>
OpenPGP</link> public key format, the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/296352.xml">
X.509</link></advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 certificate format, or the <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/616418.xml">
PKCS</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 format.  Further, the key is almost always a public key for use with an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
asymmetric key</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link> algorithm.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

Key servers were developed as a result of the invention of <link>
public key cryptography</link>.
In public key cryptography an individual is able to generate a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
key pair</link> which 
included two related keys. One of the keys in the pair is meant to be kept private
while the other is meant to be distributed.  Public key cryptosystems are designed 
in a way such that the distribution of the public key of the key pair should not  
significantly weaken the security provided by encryption with the key pair. If an 
individual has the public key of a keypair, they are able to use that key to 
initiate secret communications with the holder of the matching secret key. The 
need to have the public key of a key pair in possession in order to start 
communication or verify signatures is a bootstrapping problem. Locating keys 
on the web or writing to the individual asking them to transmit their public 
keys can be time consuming.  Key servers act as central repositories to 
alleviate the need to individually transmit public keys.</p>
<p>

The first web-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/683446.xml">
PGP</link> keyserver was written for a thesis by Marc Horowitz,
while he was studying at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/19061.xml">
MIT</link>. Horowitz's keyserver was called the HKP Keyserver
after a web-based protocol it used to allow people to interact with the
keyserver. Users were able to upload, download, and search keys either through
the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/2701104.xml">
HTTP</link>-based HKP protocol on port 11371, or through web pages which ran CGI
scripts. Before the creation of the HKP Keyserver, keyservers relied on email
processing scripts for interaction.</p>
<p>

A separate key server, known as the <link>
PGP Certificate Server</link>, was developed by <link>
PGP, Inc.</link> and was used as the software (through version 2.5.x for the server) for the default key server in PGP through version 8.x (for the client software), keyserver.pgp.com. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/198684.xml">
Network Associates</link> was granted a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/23273.xml">
patent</link> co-authored by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<military_officer wordnetid="110317007" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/17832662.xml">
Jon Callas</link></military_officer>
</person>
 (United States Patent 6336186)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> on the key server concept. </p>
<p>

To replace the aging Certificate Server, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/18508.xml">
LDAP</link>-based key server was redesigned at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/198684.xml">
Network Associates</link> in part by <link>
Randy Harmon</link> and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/92210.xml">
Len Sassaman</link></research_worker>
</person>
, called <link>
 PGP Keyserver 7.0</link>. With the release of PGP 6.0, LDAP was the preferred key server interface for Network Associates’ PGP versions. This LDAP and LDAPS key server (which also spoke HKP for backwards compatibility, though the protocol was (arguably correctly) referred to as “HTTP” or “HTTPS”) also formed the basis for the PGP Administration tools for private key servers in corporate settings, along with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/48031.xml">
schema</link> for <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/2047621.xml">
Netscape Directory Server</link></software>
. It was later replaced by the new <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/2170520.xml">
PGP Corporation</link></company>
 Global Directory.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Public versus private keyservers </st>

<p>

The most important universally accessible key servers are those computers, located around the world, which store and provide <link>
OpenPGP</link> keys over the Internet for users of that cryptosystem. In this instance, the computers can be, and are, mostly run by individuals as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/154839.xml">
pro bono</link> service, facilitating the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/296356.xml">
web of trust</link> model PGP uses. There are also multiple proprietary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/194112.xml">
public key infrastructure</link> systems which maintain key servers for their users; only their users are likely to be aware of them at all.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Privacy concerns </st>

<p>

For many individuals, the purpose of using cryptography is to obtain a higher
level of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/25009.xml">
privacy</link> in personal interactions and relationships. It has been pointed
out that allowing a public key to be uploaded in a key server when using
decentralized web of trust based cryptographic systems, like PGP, may reveal a
good deal of information that an individual may wish to have kept private. Since
PGP relies on signatures on an individual's public key to determine the
authenticity of that key, potential relationships can be revealed by analyzing
the signers of a given key. In this way, models of entire social networks can be
developed.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Problems with keyservers </st>

<p>

The OpenPGP keyservers developed in the 1990s suffered from a few problems.  Once a public key has been uploaded, it is difficult to remove.  Some users stop using their public keys for various reasons, such as when they forget their pass phrase, or if their private key is compromised or lost.  In those cases, it was hard to delete a public key from the server, and even if it were deleted, someone else can upload a fresh copy of the same public key to the server.  This leads to an accumulation of old fossil public keys that never go away, a form of keyserver "plaque".  Another problem is that anyone can upload a bogus public key to the keyserver, bearing the name of a person who in fact does not own that key.  The keyserver had no way to check to see if the key was legitimate.</p>
<p>

To solve these problems, PGP Corp developed a new generation of key server, called the [https://keyserver.pgp.com/ PGP Global Directory].  This keyserver sent an email confirmation request to the putative key owner, asking that person to confirm that the key in question is his.  If he confirms it, the PGP Global Directory accepts the key.  This can be renewed periodically, to prevent the accumulation of keyserver plaque.  The result is a higher quality collection of public keys, and each key has been vetted by email with the key's apparent owner.</p>
<p>

These are some keyservers that are often used for looking up keys with "gpg --recv-key"</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 keyserver hkp://subkeys.pgp.net</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 keyserver hkp://pgp.mit.edu</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pat2pdf.org/patents/pat6336186.pdf">
United States Patent 6336186</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>




</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>


<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Crypto_key.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Cryptography&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/18508.xml">
Lightweight Directory Access Protocol</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mit.edu/afs/net.mit.edu/project/pks/thesis/paper/thesis.html">
Marc Horowitz's Thesis</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dmoz.org/Computers/Security/Products_and_Tools/Cryptography/PGP/Key_Servers//">
List of Key Servers</weblink> at the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<subsidiary_company wordnetid="108003935" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18949501.xml">
Open Directory Project</link></institution>
</subsidiary_company>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</property>
</undertaking>
</company>
</event>
</possession>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/pks/">
OpenPGP Public Key Server (PKS)</weblink> - an OpenPGP key server software package distributed under a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../111/18933111.xml">
BSD-style license</link> (with advertising clause). It has largely been supplanted by SKS.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://savannah.nongnu.org/projects/sks/">
Synchronizing Key Server (SKS)</weblink> - an OpenPGP key server software package distributed under the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GPL</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

[https://keyserver.pgp.com/ PGP Global Directory]</entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
