<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:46:33[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<sauce  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107829412">
<header>
<title>Mayonnaise</title>
<id>61933</id>
<revision>
<id>244642817</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T21:02:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>VoABot II</username>
<id>1879647</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Sauces of the mayonnaise family</category>
<category>Condiments</category>
<category>French cuisine</category>
<category>Sauces</category>
<category>Chilean cuisine</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/17404811.xml">
Mayonnaise (disambiguation)</link>.
<image width="150px" src="Les_ingrédients_d'une_mayonnaise.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Mayonnaise made in an electric food processor with an assortment of standard ingredients
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Mayonnaise</b> (sometime abbreviated to <b>mayo</b> in American English and other languages) is a thick <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/62155.xml">
condiment</link> made primarily from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/192331.xml">
vegetable oil</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/472293.xml">
egg yolk</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  Whitish-yellow in color, it is a stable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/10290.xml">
emulsion</link> formed from the oil and the yolks and is generally flavored with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/2723003.xml">
mustard</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/214288.xml">
lemon juice</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/32762.xml">
vinegar</link> and salt. Numerous other sauces can be created from it by adding additional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/52863.xml">
seasoning</link>s (see below).
</p>
<sec>
<st>
History and etymology</st>
<p>

One explanation of the origin of the name is that the idea was brought back to France from <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/74617.xml">
Mahon, Spain</link></urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, after <link>
Louis-François-Armand du Plessis de Richelieu</link>'s victory over the British at the city's port in 1756.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Later, <link>
Marie-Antoine Carême</link> made it lighter by blending the vegetable oil and egg yolks into an emulsion; his recipe then became famous throughout Europe. If this history is correct, <it>allioli</it> (the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/301349.xml">
Balearic</link></language>
 version of <link>
aïoli</link>) would seem to have been the inspiration. 
The name <it>mayonnaise</it> is generally said to have been derived either from <it>Mahon</it> (Mayonesa) (giving <it>mahonnaise</it>), or from the French word <it>manier</it> (meaning <it>to stir</it> or <it>to blend</it>, giving <it>magnonnaise</it>). </p>
<p>

The <it>Larousse Gastronomique 1961</it> suggests another explanation: "However logical Carême's justification for the exclusive use of the term <it>magnonaise</it> may seem, we are not by any means convinced that it should take the place of the usual form, <it>mayonnaise</it>. Mayonnaise, in our view, is a popular corruption of <it>moyeunaise</it>, derived from the very old French word <it>moyeu</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>, which means yolk of egg. For, when all is said, this sauce is nothing but an emulsion of egg yolks and oil."</p>
<p>

Since the name's real origin is unknown, several other explanations exist:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The sauce may have been christened <it>mayennaise</it> after Charles de Lorraine, duke of Mayenne, because he took the time to finish his meal of chicken with cold sauce before being defeated in the <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/10077481.xml">
Battle of Arques</link></conflict>
. Though, this suggestion was first made by the nineteenth-century culinary writer Pierre Lacam<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

According to the <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<wordbook wordnetid="106418693" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<dictionary wordnetid="106418901" confidence="0.8">
<reference_book wordnetid="106417598" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/22641.xml">
Oxford English Dictionary</link></publication>
</reference_book>
</dictionary>
</book>
</wordbook>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it>, <it>mayonnaise</it> made its English language debut in a cookbook of 1841.</p>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/18951309.xml">
Ambrose Bierce</link></writer>
</person>
 said in his <it>Devil's Dictionary</it> that mayonnaise is "One of the sauces which serve the French in place of a state religion."</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Making mayonnaise</st>

<p>

Mayonnaise can be made with an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/41371.xml">
electric mixer</link>, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/555505.xml">
electric blender</link>, or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/1001475.xml">
food processor</link>, or by hand with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/606369.xml">
whisk</link> or fork. Mayonnaise is made by slowly adding oil to an egg yolk, while whisking vigorously to disperse the oil. The oil and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/33306.xml">
water</link> in yolks form a base of the emulsion, while the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/525023.xml">
lecithin</link> from the yolks acts as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/10290.xml">
emulsifier</link> that stabilizes it. Additionally, a bit of a mustard may also be added to further stabilize the emulsion. Mustard contains small amounts of lecithin.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Traditional recipe</st>
<p>

The traditional French recipe is essentially the same as the basic one described above, but it uses top-quality olive oil and sometimes vinegar or lemon juice. Some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../068/1108068.xml">
nouvelle cuisine</link> recipes specify <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/746513.xml">
safflower</link> oil. It is considered essential to constantly beat the mayonnaise using a whisk while adding the olive oil a drop at a time, fully incorporating the oil before adding the next tablespoon.  Experienced cooks can judge when the mayonnaise is done by the emulsion's resistance to the beating action.  Mayonnaise made this way may taste too strong or sharp to people accustomed to commercial products.</p>
<p>

Overworking the olive oil can make mayonnaise bitter.   Therefore, it is common to use safflower oil to create the initial emulsion, then add olive oil, working it in with a wooden spoon rather than a whisk.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Vegan mayonnaise</st>
<p>

Several brands of soy-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/32587.xml">
vegan</link> mayonnaise substitutes are available, such as Nayonaise and Vegenaise. Vegan mayonnaise substitutes  can also safely be made at home.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Composition</st>
<p>

Homemade mayonnaise can approach 85% fat before the emulsion breaks down; commercial mayonnaises are more typically 70-80% fat. "Low fat" mayonnaise products contain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/27711.xml">
starch</link>es, cellulose gel, or other ingredients to simulate the texture of real mayonnaise.</p>
<p>

Some homemade recipes use the whole egg, including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/355802.xml">
white</link>.  It can also be made using solely egg whites, with no yolks at all, if it is done at high speed in a food processor.  The resulting texture appears to be the same, and—if seasoned, for example, with salt, pepper, mustard, lemon juice, vinegar, and a little paprika—the taste is similar to traditional mayonnaise made with egg yolks.</p>
<p>

Commercial producers either <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/23311.xml">
pasteurize</link> the yolks, freeze them and substitute water for most of their liquid, or use other emulsifiers.  For homemade mayonnaise it is recommended using the freshest eggs possible.  Some stores sell <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/23311.xml">
pasteurize</link>d eggs for home use.  The eggs can also be coddled in 170°F (77°C) water, after which the hot yolks, now slightly cooked, are removed from the whites.  Homemade mayonnaise will generally only keep under refrigeration for three to four days.</p>
<p>

<image location="left" width="170px" src="Mayonnaise_Jar_550x900.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A jar of mayonnaise
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Commercial mayonnaise, due to the addition of acids like vinegar or lemon juice, has a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/24530.xml">
pH</link> between 3.8 and 4.6, making it an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/656.xml">
acidic</link> food.  There is a misconception that foods like potato salad can make a person sick if left out in the sun, due to the mayonnaise spoiling.  This is false; the pH of mayonnaise prevents harmful <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/9028799.xml">
bacteria</link> from growing in it.  Left out of refrigeration, mayonnaise will develop an unappetizing taste and smell, due to other types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/9028799.xml">
bacteria</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/51469.xml">
molds</link> that can spoil it; but will not make one sick. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

Commercial mayonnaise contains calcium disodium <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/182451.xml">
EDTA</link> which manufacturers claim is added to protect quality.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> Oral exposures to EDTA have been noted to cause reproductive and developmental effects.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Use of mayonnaise</st>
<p>

Worldwide, mayonnaise is commonly served in a sandwich, or with salad such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/199795.xml">
potato salad</link> or canned tuna  ("tuna mayo" or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/263656.xml">
tuna salad</link>).  Regional uses are listed below:</p>

<ss1>
<st>
In the United States</st>
<p>

Commercial mayonnaise sold in jars originated in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/645042.xml">
New York City</link>, in Manhattan's <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<vicinity wordnetid="108641113" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<section wordnetid="108648322" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/327244.xml">
Upper West Side</link></section>
</geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</area>
</vicinity>
</region>
</site>
. In 1905, the first ready-made mayonnaise was sold at Richard Hellmann's delicatessen on Columbus Avenue, between 83rd and 84th Streets. In 1912, Mrs. Hellmann's mayonnaise was mass marketed and called Hellmann's Blue Ribbon Mayonnaise.</p>
<p>

At about the same time that Hellmann's Mayonnaise was thriving on the East Coast of the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, a California company, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/1493157.xml">
Best Foods</link>, introduced their own mayonnaise, which turned out to be very popular in the western United States.  Head-to-head competition between the two brands was averted when, in 1932, Best Foods bought out the Hellmann's brand.  By then both mayonnaises had such commanding market shares in their own half of the country that it was decided that both brands be preserved. </p>
<p>

In the Southeastern part of the United States, Mrs. Eugenia Duke of <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/134497.xml">
Greenville, South Carolina</link></city>
, founded the Duke Sandwich Company in 1917 to sell sandwiches to soldiers training at nearby Fort Sevier. Her homemade mayonnaise became so popular that her company began to focus exclusively on producing and selling the mayonnaise, eventually selling out to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/3494593.xml">
C.F. Sauer Company</link> of Richmond, Virginia, in 1929.  <substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<condiment wordnetid="107810907" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<flavorer wordnetid="107809368" confidence="0.8">
<ingredient wordnetid="107809096" confidence="0.8">
<foodstuff wordnetid="107566340" confidence="0.8">
<sauce wordnetid="107829412" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/4363054.xml">
Duke's Mayonnaise</link></sauce>
</foodstuff>
</ingredient>
</flavorer>
</food>
</condiment>
</substance>
, still made to the original recipe, remains a popular brand of mayonnaise in the Southeast, although it is not generally available in other markets.</p>
<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/10860689.xml">
Reily Foods Company</link></company>
 of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/53842.xml">
New Orleans, LA</link>, produces Blue Plate Mayonnaise, an extremely popular mayonnaise in the Southern United States. Formerly owned by Hunt-Wesson and manufactured in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/53842.xml">
New Orleans, LA</link>, Blue Plate Mayonnaise is now produced in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/135256.xml">
Knoxville, TN</link>.</p>
<p>

Professional athletes have used mayonnaise as a home remedy for aching joints and an ache blocker.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Europe</st>
<p>

In northern Europe, mayonnaise is often served with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/52982.xml">
deep-fried</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/23501.xml">
potatoes</link>, especially in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/21148.xml">
The Netherlands</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/3343.xml">
Belgium</link></country>
 and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
. It is also served with cold chicken or hard-boiled eggs in France, the UK, The Netherlands, Poland, Lithuania, and Ukraine.</p>
<p>

Guidelines issued in September 1991 by Europe's Federation of the Condiment Sauce Industries recommend that oil and liquid egg yolk levels in mayonnaise should be at least 70% and 5% respectively, although this is not legislated. Most available brands easily exceed this target. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Japan</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Mayonnaise_Kewpie_Japanese.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Japanese mayonnaise
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Japanese mayonnaise is typically made with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/5173107.xml">
apple cider vinegar</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/346047.xml">
rice vinegar</link> and a small amount of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/62289.xml">
MSG</link>, which gives it a different flavor profile from mayonnaise made from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/32762.xml">
distilled vinegar</link>. It is most often sold in soft plastic squeeze bottles. Its texture is thinner than most Western commercial mayonnaises (It's mayonnaise you jew).  A variety containing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/8028701.xml">
karashi</link> (Japanese mustard) is also common.</p>
<p>

Apart from salads, it is popular with dishes such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/147806.xml">
okonomiyaki</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/180075.xml">
takoyaki</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/526059.xml">
yakisoba</link>. It is sometimes served with cooked vegetables, or mixed with soy sauce or wasabi and used as dips. In the <link>
Tōkai region</link>, it is a frequent condiment on <it><dish wordnetid="107557434" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<solid wordnetid="115046900" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="107555863" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<noodle wordnetid="107699584" confidence="0.8">
<pasta wordnetid="107698915" confidence="0.8">
<nutriment wordnetid="107570720" confidence="0.8">
<soup wordnetid="107583197" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/37969.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Related+dishes%22])">
hiyashi chuka</link></soup>
</nutriment>
</pasta>
</noodle>
</food>
</food>
</solid>
</substance>
</dish>
</it> (cold noodle salad). Many fried seafood dishes are served with a side of mayonnaise for dipping. It is also not uncommon for Japanese to use mayonnaise in place of tomato sauce on pizza.</p>
<p>

Kewpie (Q.P.) is the most popular brand of Japanese mayonnaise, advertised with a <mascot wordnetid="110297234" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/227997.xml">
Kewpie doll</link></mascot>
 logo.</p>
<p>

People who are known to like mayonnaise are commonly called <it>mayoler</it> (マヨラー) by their friends.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Russia</st>
<p>

Mayonnaise is very popular in Russia where it is made with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/57622.xml">
sunflower</link> seed oil which gives it a very distinctive flavor. A 2004 study showed that Russia is the only market in Europe where more mayonnaise is sold than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/67922.xml">
ketchup</link> by volume. Leading brands are Calve (marketed by Unilever) and Sloboda (marketed by Efko). </p>
<p>

Furthermore, in many Russian speaking countries, one can find different commercial flavors of mayonnaise, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/22479.xml">
olive</link>, quail-egg, and lemon.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Chile</st>
<p>

Chile is the world's third major per capita consumer of mayonnaise and first in <environment wordnetid="113934596" confidence="0.8">
<grouping wordnetid="101012360" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<sphere wordnetid="114514039" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<situation wordnetid="113927383" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<categorization wordnetid="101012712" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/18524.xml">
Latin America</link></categorization>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</situation>
</act>
</sphere>
</state>
</event>
</grouping>
</environment>
. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Since mayonnaise became widely accessible in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/34557.xml">
1980s</link> Chileans have used it on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/16825369.xml">
loco</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/192368.xml">
hot dogs</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/10885.xml">
French fries</link>, and on boiled potatoes.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
As a base for other sauces</st>
<p>

Mayonnaise is the base for many other chilled sauces and <link>
salad dressing</link>s. For example:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><link>
Aïoli</link></b> is often made as an olive-oil mayonnaise with garlic.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/1330426.xml">
Rouille</link></b> is aïoli with added <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/53332.xml">
saffron</link>, red pepper or paprika.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/61972.xml">
Tartar sauce</link></b> is mayonnaise spiced with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18978668.xml">
pickled cucumber</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/51258.xml">
onion</link>.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/309317.xml">
Capers</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/1818836.xml">
olives</link>, and crushed hardboiled eggs are sometimes included. A simpler recipe calls for only pickle relish to be added to the mayonnaise.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Some types of <b><message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/481569.xml">
Russian dressing</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</b> (also known as Marie Rose sauce in Europe) combine mayonnaise with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/30916.xml">
tomato sauce</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/67922.xml">
ketchup</link>  and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/156754.xml">
yoghurt</link>  or heavy cream.  In <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/21139.xml">
North America</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, however, most homemade varieties and <it>all</it> commercial brands of Russian dressing use little or no mayonnaise as a base.  They are very dark red and sweet dressings made with vegetable oil, tomato paste, vinegar, sugar, and a variety of herbs and spices (often including mustard).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/481557.xml">
Thousand Island dressing</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</b> is a salmon-pink dressing that combines tomato sauce and/or tomato ketchup or ketchup-based chili sauce, minced sweet pickles or sweet pickle relish, assorted herbs and spices (usually including mustard), and sometimes including chopped hard-boiled egg—all thoroughly blended into a mayonnaise base.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/418269.xml">
Fry sauce</link></b> is a mixture of mayonnaise, ketchup or another red sauce (e.g., <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/31419.xml">
Tabasco sauce</link></company>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/105402.xml">
Buffalo wing</link> sauce, or one of many smokey <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../076/7391076.xml">
barbecue sauce</link>s popular in the Northwest states), spices, and sometimes a strong tasting salty liquid (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/33778.xml">
worcestershire</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/62153.xml">
soy sauce</link>) is added to balance out the sweeter red sauces. Commonly eaten on french fries in <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../716/31716.xml">
Utah</link></symbol>
,  <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/14607.xml">
Idaho</link></symbol>
, eastern <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/13015878.xml">
Washington</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 and rural <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/22198.xml">
Oregon</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/17404811.xml">
Mayonesa</link></b> is a lime-flavored mayonnaise, usually found in Mexican or Spanish grocers in North America.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<condiment wordnetid="107810907" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<flavorer wordnetid="107809368" confidence="0.8">
<ingredient wordnetid="107809096" confidence="0.8">
<foodstuff wordnetid="107566340" confidence="0.8">
<sauce wordnetid="107829412" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/1006214.xml">
Sauce rémoulade</link></sauce>
</foodstuff>
</ingredient>
</flavorer>
</food>
</condiment>
</substance>
</b>, in classic French cuisine is mayonnaise to which has been added mustard, gherkins, capers, parsley, chervil, tarragon, and possibly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/3215290.xml">
anchovy essence</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> An industrially made variety is popular in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/76972.xml">
Denmark</link></country>
 with french fries and fried fish. It is quite different from most of the remoulade sauces that are frequently found in Louisiana and generally do not have a mayonnaise base.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b><message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/425059.xml">
Ranch dressing</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</b> is made of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/235923.xml">
buttermilk</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/231473.xml">
sour cream</link>, mayonnaise, and minced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/453610.xml">
green onion</link>, along with other seasonings.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"Mayonnaise is an emulsion of oil droplets suspended in a base composed of egg yolks, lemon juice or vinegar, water, and often mustard and milk, which provide both flavor and stabilizing particles and carbohydrates." <it>On Food and Cooking,</it> <writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/1565001.xml">
Harold McGee</link></writer>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/1613023.xml">
Scribner</link>, New York, 2004.</entry>
<entry id="2">
David, E. (1960). "French Provincial Cooking" (1999 edition) p.120</entry>
<entry id="3">
A more usual definition of <it>moyeu,</it> from <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mallarme.net/mot79.html">
Mallarme.net</weblink>: "Partie centrale de la roue où s’emboîtent les rais, et par où passe l’essieu. "Mais de ce que les moyeux des roues de votre carrosse auront pris feu, s’ensuit-il que votre carrosse n’ait pas été fait expressément pour vous porter d’un lieu à un autre?" Voltaire, <it>Dictionnaire Philosophique</it>, "Causes finales."  Translation: "Central part of the wheel, where the spokes are housed, through which the axle passes." A fourteenthth-century surgeon, Guy de Chauliac, did use <it>moyeu</it> to mean yolk of the egg: "Oeufs sont tempérez : toutes fois l'aulbin tire à froideur, et le moyeu [le jaune]  à la chaleur, avec sédation." ("Eggs are tempered, for albumen tends to "cooling" and the yolk tends to "heating", in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/439185.xml">
Four humours</link> theory. The word <it>moyeu</it> would have been pronounced quite close to "mayo". </entry>
<entry id="4">
The page reference has not been identified; the passage appeared either in Lacam's <it>Mémorial historique et géographie de la pâtisserie</it> (privately printed, Paris 1908), in  his <it>Nouveau pâtissier glacier français et étranger</it> (1865) or his <it>Glacier classique et artistique en France et en Italie,</it> (1893).</entry>
<entry id="5">
Good Eats; Season four; <it>Mayo Clinic''</it></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://vegetarian.about.com/od/saucesdipsspreads/r/eggfreemayo.htm">
Egg-Free Vegan Mayonnaise Recipe</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5639903">
Happy Birthday, Dear Mayo - We Hold You Dear : NPR</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://old.cbbqa.org/recipes/Mayonnaise.html">
Hellmann's and Best Foods Mayonnaise -- overview and history</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Lanigan RS and Yamarik TA&#32;(2002).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=12396676&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus">
Final report on the safety assessment of EDTA, calcium disodium EDTA, diammonium EDTA, dipotassium EDTA, disodium EDTA, TEA-EDTA, tetrasodium EDTA, tripotassium EDTA, trisodium EDTA, HEDTA, and trisodium HEDTA</weblink>". <it>Int J Toxicol.</it>&#32;<b>21 Suppl 2</b>: 95–142. Retrieved on <link>
2008-01-28</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.foodanddrinkeurope.com/news/ng.asp?id=51737-mayonnaise-sales-hit">
Mayonnaise sales in Europe</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.latinamerican-markets.com/chile---consumo-de-mayonesa">
Chile - consumo de mayonesa (spanish)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
See, for example, <it><book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../552/18552.xml">
Larousse Gastronomique</link></book>
</it>, 2003, ISBN 0 600 60863 8, page 1054.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wikibooks-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wikibooks
</caption>
</image>

<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../006/329006.xml">
Wikibooks</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</property>
</undertaking>
</event>
</possession>
</work>
  has an article on
</p>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.creativecookingschool.com/ClassicalDishes.asp">
Creative Cooking School website:</weblink> offers six possible sources of <it>sauce mayonnaise</it>, including Pierre Lacam's suggestion.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sc-smn.jst.go.jp/8/bangumi.asp?i_series_code=F980601&amp;i_renban_code=002">
Science Channel's <it>The Making</it> Series: #2 Making of Mayonnaise</weblink> (video in <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/15606.xml">
Japanese</link></language>
)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5639903">
NPR's Report on the 250th Birthday of Mayonnaise and its history</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<vessel wordnetid="104531098" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<jar wordnetid="103593526" confidence="0.8">
<container wordnetid="103094503" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../907/4852907.xml">
Mayonnaise jar</link></material>
</part>
</container>
</jar>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</vessel>
</substance>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/2590592.xml">
Salad cream</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.8">
<trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/2294749.xml">
Miracle Whip</link></language_unit>
</database>
</part>
</wordnet>
</trade_name>
</name>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../067/1686067.xml">
Hellmann's and Best Foods</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<condiment wordnetid="107810907" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<flavorer wordnetid="107809368" confidence="0.8">
<ingredient wordnetid="107809096" confidence="0.8">
<foodstuff wordnetid="107566340" confidence="0.8">
<sauce wordnetid="107829412" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/17911283.xml">
Fritessaus</link></sauce>
</foodstuff>
</ingredient>
</flavorer>
</food>
</condiment>
</substance>
</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</sauce>
</article>
