<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:24:04[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<model  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="110324560">
<header>
<title>Sensitivity analysis</title>
<id>620083</id>
<revision>
<id>242981104</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-04T16:03:37Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>G716</username>
<id>697736</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Business terms</category>
<category>Scientific modeling</category>
<category>Process management</category>
<category>Statistical models</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Sensitivity analysis</b> (SA) is the study of how the variation (uncertainty) in the output of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/20590.xml">
mathematical model</link> can be apportioned, qualitatively or quantitatively, to different sources of variation in the input of a model <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>. <p>

In more general terms uncertainty and sensitivity analyses investigate the robustness of a study when the study includes some form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/20590.xml">
mathematical modelling</link>. While uncertainty analysis studies the overall <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/63778.xml">
uncertainty</link> in the conclusions of the study, sensitivity analysis tries to identify what source of uncertainty weights more on the study's conclusions. For example, several guidelines for modelling <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/crem/library/CREM%20Guidance%20Draft%2012_03.pdf">
  (see e.g. one from the US EPA)</weblink> or for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/17575646.xml">
impact assessment</link> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/governance/impact/docs/SEC2005_791_IA%20guidelines_annexes.pdf">
(see one from the European Commission)</weblink> prescribe sensitivity analysis as a tool to ensure the quality of the modelling/assessment.     </p>
<p>

The problem setting in sensitivity analysis has strong similarities with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/9541.xml">
Design of experiments</link>. In design of experiments  one studies the effect of some process or intervention (the 'treatment') on some objects (the 'experimental units'). In sensitivity analysis one looks at the effect of varying the inputs of a mathematical model on the output of the model itself. In both disciplines one strives to obtain information from the system with a minimum of physical or numerical experiments. </p>
<p>

In uncertainty and sensitivity analysis there is a crucial trade off between how scrupolous an analysist is in exploring the input <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/307808.xml">
assumptions</link> and how wide the resulting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/317465.xml">
inference</link> may be. The point is well illustrated by the econometrician Edward E. Leamer (1990)  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>: </p>
<p>

I have proposed a form of organized sensitivity analysis that I call ‘global sensitivity analysis’ in which a neighborhood of alternative assumptions is selected and the corresponding interval of inferences is identified. Conclusions are judged to be sturdy only if the neighborhood of assumptions is wide enough to be credible and the corresponding interval of inferences is narrow enough to be useful.</p>
<p>

Note Leamer’s emphasis is on the need for 'credibility' in the selection of assumptions. The easiest way to invalidate a model is to demonstrate it fragile with respect to the uncertainty in the assumptions or to show that its assumptions have not been taken 'wide enough'. The same concept is expressed by Jerome R. Ravetz, for whom bad modelling is when <it>uncertainties in inputs must be suppressed least outputs become indeterminate.</it><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  </p>
<p>

In modern econometrics the use of sensitivity analysis to anticipate criticism is the subject of one of the ten commandments of applied econometrics (from Kennedy, 2007<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> ):</p>
<p>

Thou shall confess in the presence of sensitivity. Corollary: Thou shall anticipate criticism [···] When reporting a sensitivity analysis, researchers should explain fully their specification search so that the readers can judge for themselves how the results may have been affected. This is basically an ‘honesty is the best policy’ approach, advocated by Leamer, (1978<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>).</p>
<p>

The use of mathematical modelling can be the subject of controversies, see Nassim Nicholas Taleb<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> in Economics, and Orrin H. Pilkey and Linda Pilkey Jarvis<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> in Environmental Sciences. As noted by the latter Authors, this increases the relevance of sensitivity analysis in today's modelling practice<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> 
.  </p>


<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>

<p>

Most mathematical problems met in social, economic or natural sciences entail the use of mathematical models, which are generally too complex for an easy appreciation of the relationship between input factors (what goes into the model) and output (the model’s dependent variables). Such an appreciation, i.e. the understanding of how the model behaves in response to changes in its inputs, is of fundamental importance to ensure a correct use of the models.  </p>
<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/20590.xml">
mathematical model</link> is defined by a series of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/9284.xml">
equations</link>, input factors, parameters, and variables aimed to characterize the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/4746766.xml">
process</link> being investigated. </p>
<p>

Input is subject to many sources of uncertainty including errors of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/19022.xml">
measurement</link>, absence of information and poor or partial understanding of the driving forces and mechanisms.  This uncertainty imposes a limit on our <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/2973525.xml">
confidence</link> in the response or output of the model. Further, models may have to cope with the natural intrinsic variability of the system, such as the occurrence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/292222.xml">
stochastic</link> events. </p>
<p>

Good modeling practice requires that the modeler provides an evaluation of the confidence in the model, possibly assessing the uncertainties associated with the modeling process and with the outcome of the model itself. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/63778.xml">
Uncertainty</link> and Sensitivity Analysis offer valid tools for characterizing the uncertainty associated with a model. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/13990608.xml">
Uncertainty analysis</link> (UA) quantifies the uncertainty in the outcome of a model. Sensitivity Analysis has the complementary role of ordering by importance the strength and relevance of the inputs in determining the variation in the output.</p>
<p>

In models involving many input variables sensitivity analysis is an essential ingredient of model building and quality assurance. National and international agencies involved in impact assessment studies have included sections devoted to sensitivity analysis in their guidelines. Examples are the <control wordnetid="105196375" confidence="0.8">
<authority wordnetid="105196582" confidence="0.8">
<power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/9974.xml">
European Commission</link></power>
</authority>
</control>
, the White House <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/44030.xml">
Office of Management and Budget</link>, the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/15030.xml">
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</link></organization>
 and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/58666.xml">
US Environmental Protection Agency</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methodology</st>
<p>

There are several possible procedures to perform uncertainty (UA) and sensitivity analysis (SA). Important classes of methods are: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Local methods, such as the simple derivative of the output  <math> Y </math> with respect to an input factor <math> X_i </math>:   <math>\left| \frac{\partial Y}{\partial X_i} \right |_{\textbf {x}^0 }</math>, where the subscript <math> \textbf {x}^0 </math> indicates that the derivative is taken at some fixed point in the space of the input (hence the 'local' in the name of the class). Adjoint modelling<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> and Automated Differentiation<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> are methods in this class.   </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/160361.xml">
sampling</link>-based method<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> A sampling-based sensitivity is one in which the model is executed repeatedly for combinations of values sampled from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/23543.xml">
distribution</link> (assumed known) of the input factors. Once the sample is generated, several strategies (including simple input-output scatterplots) can be used to derive sensitivity measures for the factors. </entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Scatter_plots_for_sensitivity_analysis_bis.jpg">
<caption>

 Sampling based sensitivity analysis by scatterplots. Y (vertical axis) is a function of four factors. The points in the four scatterplots are always the same though sorted differently, i.e. by Z1, Z2, Z3, Z4 in turn. Which factor among Z1, Z2, Z3, Z4 is most important in influencing Y? Note that the abscissa is different for each plot: (-5,+5) for Z1, (-8,+8) for Z2, (-10,+10) for Z3 and Z4. Clue: The most important factor is the one which imparts more 'shape' on Y.
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Methods based on emulators (e.g. Bayesian<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>). With these methods the value of the output  <math> Y </math>, or directly the value of the sensitvity measure of a factor <math> X_i </math>, is treated as a stochastic process and estimated from the available computer-generated data points. This is useful when the computer program which describes the model is expensive to run.     </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Screening methods. This is a particular instance of sampling based methods. The objective here is to estimate a few active factors in models with many factors<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Variance based methods<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>. Here the unconditional variance  <math> V(Y) </math> of  <math> Y </math> is decomposed into terms due to individual factors plus terms due to interaction among factors. Full variance decompositions are only meaningfull when the input factors are independent from one another<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 High Dimensional Model Representations (HDMR)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref>. The term is due to H. Rabitz<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> and include as a particular case the variance based methods. In HDMR the output <math> Y </math> is expresed as a linear combination of terms of increasing dimensionality.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Methods based on Monte Carlo filtering<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref>. These are also sampling-based and the objective here is to identify regions in the space of the input factors corresponding particular values (e.g. high or low) of the output.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Often (e.g. in sampling-based methods) UA and SA are performed jointly by executing the model repeatedly for combination of factor values sampled with some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/23543.xml">
probability distribution</link>. The following steps can be listed:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Specify the target <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/185427.xml">
function</link> of interest. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

It is easier to communicate the results of a sensitivity analysis when the target of interest has a direct relation to the problem tackled by the model.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Assign a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/43487.xml">
probability density function</link> to the selected factors. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

When this involves eliciting experts' opinion this is the most expensive and time consuming part of the analysis. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Generate a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/19008728.xml">
matrix</link> of inputs with that distribution(s) through an appropriate design. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 As in <link>
experimental design</link>, a good design for numerical experiments<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref> should give a maximum of effects with a minimum of computed points.    </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Evaluate the model and compute the distribution of the target function. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

This is the computer-time intensive step. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Select a method for assessing the influence or relative importance of each input factor on the target function.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

This depends upon he purpose of the analysis, e.g. model simplification, factor prioritization, uncertainty reduction, etc.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Sensitivity_scheme.jpg">
<caption>

 Ideal scheme of a possibly sampling-based sensitivity analysis. Uncertainty arising from different sources - errors in the data, parameter estimation procedure, alternative model structures - are propagated through the model for uncertainty analysis and their relative importance is quantified via sensitivity analysis.
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications</st>
<p>

Sensitivity Analysis can be used</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To simplify models </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To investigate the robustness of the model predictions </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 To play what-if analysis exploring the impact of varying input assumptions and scenarios </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 As an element of quality assurance (unexpected factors sensitivities may be associated to coding errors or misspecifications).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

It provides as well information on:  </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Factors that mostly contribute to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/41470.xml">
output</link> variability </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The region in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/27667.xml">
space</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/41264.xml">
input</link> factors for which the model output is either maximum or minimum or within pre-defined bounds (see Monte Carlo filtering above) </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/52033.xml">
Optimal</link> - or instability - regions within the space of factors for use in a subsequent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/47502.xml">
calibration</link> study </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/443083.xml">
Interaction</link> between factors</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Sensitivity Analysis is common in physics and chemistry<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref>, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/11162.xml">
financial</link> applications, risk analysis, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../324/29324.xml">
signal processing</link>, <link>
neural networks</link> and any area where models are developed. Sensitivity analysis can also be used in model-based  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.modeling.uga.edu/tauc/background_material/Washington-Main.pdf">
 policy assessment studies </weblink>. Sensitivity analysis can be used to assess the robustness of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://composite-indicators.jrc.ec.europa.eu/">
 composite indicators </weblink><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref>, also know as indices, such as the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://epi.yale.edu/Home">
Environmental Pressure Index</weblink>. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Errors </st>

<p>

In sensitivity analysis Type I error is assessing as important a non important factor, and Type II error assessing as non important an important factor. Type III error corresponds to analysing the wrong problem, e.g. via an incorrect specification of the input uncertainties. Possible pitfalls in sensitivity analysis are: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Unclear purpose of the analysis. Different statistical tests and measures are applied to the problem and different factors rankings are obtained. The test should instead be tailored to the purpose of the analysis, e.g. one uses Monte Carlo filtering if one is interested in which factors are most responsible for generating high/low values of the output. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Too many model outputs are considered. This may be acceptable for quality assurance of sub-models but should be avoided when presenting the results of the overall analysis.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Piecewise sensitivity. This is when one performs sensitivity analysis on one sub-model at a time. This approach is non conservative as it might overlook interactions among factors in different sub-models (Type II error).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Environmental </st>
<p>

Computer environmental models are increasingly used in a wide variety of  studies and applications.
For example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/164600.xml">
global climate model</link> are used for both short term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/73231.xml">
weather forecasts</link> and long term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/47512.xml">
climate change</link>.</p>
<p>

Moreover, computer models are increasingly used for environmental decision making at a local scale, for example for assessing the impact of a waste water treatment plant on a river flow, or for assessing the behavior and life length of bio-filters for contaminated waste water.</p>
<p>

In both cases sensitivity analysis may help understanding the contribution of the various sources of uncertainty to the model output uncertainty and system performance in general.
In these cases, depending on model complexity, different sampling strategies may be advisable and traditional sensitivity indexes have to be generalized to cover <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iemss.org/iemss2006/papers/s7/268_Fasso_0.pdf">
multivariate sensitivity analysis</weblink>,  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/612440.xml">
heteroskedastic</link> effects and correlated inputs.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Business </st>
<p>

In a decision problem, the analyst may want to identify cost drivers as well as other quantities for which we need to acquire better knowledge in order to make an informed decision. On the other hand, some quantities have no influence on the predictions, so that we can save resources at no loss in accuracy by relaxing some of the conditions. See .
Sensitivity analysis can help in a variety of other circumstances which can be handled by the settings illustrated below: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 to identify critical assumptions or compare alternative model structures</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 guide future data collections</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 detect important criteria</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 optimize the tolerance of manufactured parts in terms of the uncertainty in the parameters</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 optimize resources allocation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 model simplification or model lumping, etc.</entry>
</list>

However there are also some problems associated with sensitivity analysis in the business context:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Variables are often interdependent, which makes examining them each individually unrealistic, e.g.: changing one factor such as sales volume, will most likely affect other factors such as the selling price. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Often the assumptions upon which the analysis is based are made by using past experience/data which may not hold in the future. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Assigning a maximum and minimum (or optimistic and pessimistic) value is open to subjective interpretation. For instance one persons 'optimistic' forecast may be more conservative than that of another person performing a different part of the analysis. This sort of subjectivity can adversely affect the accuracy and overall objectivity of the analysis.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/102140.xml">
Perturbation analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/9645719.xml">
Robustification</link></entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Saltelli, A., Ratto, M., Andres, T., Campolongo, F., Cariboni, J., Gatelli, D. Saisana, M., and Tarantola, S., 2008, Global Sensitivity Analysis. The Primer, John Wiley &amp; Sons.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Leamer, E., (1990) Let's take the con out of econometrics, and Sensitivity analysis would help. In C. Granger (ed.), Modelling Economic Series. Oxford: Clarendon Press 1990.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Ravetz, J.R., 2007, No-Nonsense Guide to Science, New Internationalist Publications Ltd.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Kennedy, P. (2007). A guide to econometrics, Fifth edition. Blackwell Publishing.
</entry>
<entry id="5">
Leamer, E. (1978). Specification Searches: Ad Hoc Inferences with Nonexperimental Data. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, p. vi. </entry>
<entry id="6">
Taleb, N. N., (2007) The Black Swan: The Impact of the Highly Improbable, Random House.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Pilkey, O. H. and L. Pilkey-Jarvis (2007), Useless Arithmetic. Why Environmental Scientists Can't Predict the Future. New York: Columbia University Press.</entry>
<entry id="8">
Cacuci, Dan G.,  Sensitivity and Uncertainty Analysis: Theory, Volume I, Chapman &amp; Hall.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Cacuci, Dan G., Mihaela Ionescu-Bujor, Michael Navon, 2005, Sensitivity And Uncertainty Analysis: Applications to Large-Scale Systems (Volume II), Chapman &amp; Hall.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Grievank, A. (2000). Evaluating derivatives, Principles and techniques of algorithmic differentiation. SIAM publisher.</entry>
<entry id="11">
J.C. Helton, J.D. Johnson, C.J. Salaberry, and C.B. Storlie, 2006, Survey of sampling based methods for uncertainty and sensitivity analysis. Reliability Engineering and System Safety, 91:1175-1209.</entry>
<entry id="12">
Oakley, J. and A. O'Hagan (2004). Probabilistic sensitivity analysis of complex models: a Bayesian approach. J. Royal Stat. Soc. B 66, 751-769.</entry>
<entry id="13">
Morris, M. D. (1991). Factorial sampling plans for preliminary computational experiments. Technometrics, 33, 161–174.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Campolongo, F., J. Cariboni, and A. Saltelli (2007). An effective screening design for sensitivity analysis of large models. Environmental Modelling and Software, 22,
1509-1518.</entry>
<entry id="15">
Sobol’, I. (1990). Sensitivity estimates for nonlinear mathematical models. Matematicheskoe Modelirovanie 2, 112–118. in Russian, translated in English in Sobol’ , I. (1993). Sensitivity analysis for non-linear mathematical models. Mathematical Modeling &amp; Computational Experiment (Engl. Transl.), 1993, 1, 407–414. 
</entry>
<entry id="17">
Saltelli, A., K. Chan, and M. Scott (Eds.) (2000). Sensitivity Analysis. Wiley Series in Probability and Statistics. New York: John Wiley and Sons.
</entry>
<entry id="16">
Homma, T. and A. Saltelli (1996). Importance measures in global sensitivity analysis of nonlinear models. Reliability Engineering and System Safety, 52, 1–17.</entry>
<entry id="19">
Li, G., J. Hu, S.-W. Wang, P. Georgopoulos, J. Schoendorf, and H. Rabitz (2006). Random Sampling-High Dimensional Model Representation (RS-HDMR) and orthogonality of its different order component functions. Journal of Physical Chemistry A 110, 2474-2485.</entry>
<entry id="18">
Saltelli, A. and S. Tarantola (2002). On the relative importance of input factors in mathematical models: safety assessment for nuclear waste disposal. Journal of American Statistical Association, 97, 702–709.</entry>
<entry id="21">
Rabitz, H. (1989). System analysis at molecular scale. Science, 246, 221–226.</entry>
<entry id="20">
 Li, G., W. S. W., and R. H. (2002). Practical approaches to construct RS-HDMR component functions. Journal of Physical Chemistry 106, 8721{8733.</entry>
<entry id="23">
Saltelli, A., S. Tarantola, F. Campolongo, and M. Ratto (2004). Sensitivity Analysis in Practice: A Guide to Assessing Scientific Models. John Wiley and Sons.</entry>
<entry id="22">
Hornberger, G. and R. Spear (1981). An approach to the preliminary analysis of environmental systems. Journal of Environmental Management 7, 7-18.</entry>
<entry id="25">
Saltelli, A., M. Ratto, S. Tarantola and F. Campolongo (2005) Sensitivity Analysis for Chemical Models, Chemical Reviews, 105(7) pp 2811 – 2828.</entry>
<entry id="24">
Sacks, J., W. J. Welch, T. J. Mitchell, and H. P. Wynn (1989). Design and analysis of computer experiments. Statistical Science 4, 409-435.</entry>
<entry id="26">
Saisana M., Saltelli A., Tarantola S., 2005, Uncertainty and Sensitivity analysis techniques as tools for the quality assessment of composite indicators, Journal Royal  Statistical Society A, 168 (2), 307-323.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Bibliography</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fassò A. (2007) Statistical sensitivity analysis and water quality. In Wymer L. Ed, Statistical Framework for Water Quality Criteria and Monitoring. Wiley, New York.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fassò A., Esposito E., Porcu E., Reverberi A.P., Vegliò F. (2003) Statistical Sensitivity Analysis of Packed Column Reactors for Contaminated Wastewater. Environmetrics. Vol. 14, n.8, 743 - 759.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fassò A., Perri P.F. (2002) Sensitivity Analysis. In Abdel H. El-Shaarawi and Walter W. Piegorsch (eds) Encyclopedia of Environmetrics, Volume 4, pp 1968–1982, Wiley.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Saltelli, A., S. Tarantola, and K. Chan (1999). Quantitative model-independent method for global sensitivity analysis of model output. Technometrics 41(1), 39–56.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Santner, T. J.; Williams, B. J.; Notz, W.I. Design and Analysis of Computer Experiments; Springer-Verlag, 2003.</entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Special issues</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A special issue devoted to sensitivity analysis has been published in September 2008 on the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/121401979/issue">
International Journal of Chemical Kinetics</weblink>. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Another will appear in 2008 on  Reliability Engineering and System Safety (RESS). </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Both are selection of papers presented at the 2007 Conference of Sensitivity Analysis of Model Output (SAMO) held in Budapest in June. See <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://samo2007.chem.elte.hu/">
 SAMO 2007</weblink> for the slides of the presentations.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An earlier special issue on sensitivity analysis has been published in 2006 on the journal <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/journaldescription.cws_home/405908/description#description">
Reliability Engineering and System Safety (Volume 91, 2006)</weblink>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sensitivity-analysis.jrc.ec.europa.eu/">
A forum on sensitivity analysis</weblink> Main source - includes a tutorial and a bibliography.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nusap.net/">
The NUSAP web site</weblink> Discusses the use of pedigree for scientific information (including use of models).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simlab.jrc.ec.europa.eu/">
The SIMLAB software for sensitivity analysis: download it for free</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.princeton.edu/~hrabitz/">
Home page of Hershel A. Rabitz at Princeton.</weblink> Works on High Dimensional Model Representation (HDMR), used in sensitivity analysis.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://home.ubalt.edu/ntsbarsh/senanaly/SenAnaly.htm">
Sensitivity Analysis Index</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sensitivity.r-forge.r-project.org/">
The R software package "sensitivity"</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.lanl.gov/ccw/samo2004/">
SAMO 2004</weblink>, Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Sensitivity Analysis of Model Output, Santa Fe, New Mexico, March 8-11, 2004. Edited by Kenneth M. Hanson and François M. Hemez </entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</model>
</article>
