<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:19:31[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<scientist  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="110560637">
<psychologist  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="110488865">
<header>
<title>John Amsden Starkweather</title>
<id>6202931</id>
<revision>
<id>194033080</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-25T22:33:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ipeirotis</username>
<id>1139920</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>1925 births</category>
<category>2001 deaths</category>
<category>American psychologists</category>
<category>University of California, San Francisco faculty</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Scientist</name>
<parameters>

<image width="121px" src="Starkweather-John-Amsden.gif">
</image>
<citizenship>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States of America</link></citizenship>
<known_for>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/57399.xml">
PILOT</link> language</known_for>
<death_place>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/107733.xml">
San Rafael, California</link></village>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States of America</link></death_place>
<name>
John Amsden Starkweather</name>
<prizes>
Fellow of the <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/243062.xml">
American Association for the Advancement of Science</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
 , Fellow of the <association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/8485043.xml">
American College of Medical Informatics</link></association>
</prizes>
<death_date>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/20196.xml">
March 10</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link></death_date>
<birth_date>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/1794.xml">
August 30</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/34867.xml">
1925</link></birth_date>
<birth_place>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/8687.xml">
Detroit, Michigan</link></village>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States of America</link></birth_place>
<doctoral_students>
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/521432.xml">
Paul Ekman</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <link>
Rudolph Moos</link>, <link>
Donald Langsley</link>, <link>
Kay Blacker</link>, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/11573220.xml">
Gio Wiederhold</link></scientist>
</doctoral_students>
<alma_mater>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/34273.xml">
Yale</link>, B.A. in Art, 1950; <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/174216.xml">
Northwestern</link></ranking>
</university>
, Ph.D. in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/492271.xml">
Clinical Psychology</link>, 1955</alma_mater>
<field>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
Psychology</link></field>
<residence>
<county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/82017.xml">
Marin County, California</link></county>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States of America</link></residence>
<doctoral_advisor>
<link>
Carl Porter Duncan</link></doctoral_advisor>
<work_institutions>
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/31920.xml">
University of California, San Francisco</link></university>
</work_institutions>
</parameters>
</template>



<p>

<b>John Amsden Starkweather</b> (b. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/1794.xml">
August 30</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/34867.xml">
1925</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/8687.xml">
Detroit</link> - d. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/20196.xml">
March 10</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link> in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/107733.xml">
San Rafael, California</link></village>
) was a Professor of Medical Psychology at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/31920.xml">
University of California, San Francisco</link></university>
.  Starkweather was a clinical psychologist and a valued teacher by generations of clinical psychology interns and graduate students at <link>
UCSF</link>. He is most known as a "pioneer in the application of computer techniques to language processing." He was a pioneer in taking a psychologist's view of the emerging computer field and incorporating concepts as well as numbers. </p>

<sec>
<st>
Early years</st>
<p>

Starkweather's father was an engineer and his mother was a poet. Starkweather graduated from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/34273.xml">
Yale</link> in 1950 with a B.A. in Art and from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/174216.xml">
Northwestern</link></ranking>
</university>
 in 1955 with a Ph.D. in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/492271.xml">
Clinical Psychology</link>. He joined the faculty of the Department of Psychiatry at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/31920.xml">
University of California, San Francisco</link></university>
 in 1955, where he spent his entire career.  He married his wife, Jean, in 1952 while he was a graduate student at Northwestern. The Starkweathers had three sons, David, Timothy and Stephen.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Studies in speech</st>
<p>

Starkweather took an early interest in speech and language, and especially the expression of emotion in the voice. His dissertation, supervised by professor <link>
Carl Porter Duncan</link> at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/174216.xml">
Northwestern</link></ranking>
</university>
, was titled <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.stern.nyu.edu/~panos/tree/Starkweather-thesis.pdf">
Judgments of Content-Free Speech as Related to Some Aspects of Personality</weblink></it> and was the first to show that judges could distinguish reliably among different emotions from content-free speech, created by filtering out frequencies above 300 cycles. He went on to study spectral measures of voice and to show that such measures could track day-to-day changes in the degree of depression in hospitalized patients. However, he is best known for his contributions to computer science in relation to psychology, teaching, and medicine.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Contributions to computer science</st>
<p>

The 1950s were remarkable for the introduction of the stored-program computer. As Starkweather pursued his voice-quality research, he created a real-time pitch spectrum analyzer that could generate a 20-band pitch spectrum every two seconds from voice recordings. The quantitative analysis demands of such data plunged him into the use of the primitive computer resources available in the early 1960s.</p>
<p>

Starkweather began to realize that he might contribute to computer software development beyond simply being an informed research user. At that time most of the academic attention to computer software focused on quantitative analysis. For example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/37765.xml">
UCLA</link> was developing the Biomedical (BMD) Computer Programs, the first reliable and comprehensive statistical analysis package. Starkweather foresaw that psychology, education, and medicine would also need ways for computers to deal with language content. He first developed a programming language called COMPUTEST to allow students and teachers to access teaching materials and examinations by computer, even though the computer hardware needed to accomplish this at the time filled half of a classroom.</p>
<p>

As hardware became smaller, he developed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/57399.xml">
PILOT</link> language (Programmed Inquiry, Learning Or Teaching) that made it easy for non-programmers to write sequences of machine-administered teaching or testing using the time-share terminals in use in 1970, and then microcomputers when they became available a decade later. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/408290.xml">
National Library of Medicine</link> adopted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/57399.xml">
PILOT</link> as its primary computer language for the dissemination and exchange of computer-based instructional materials in the health sciences, and used it for instructing medical librarians in using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/240749.xml">
MEDLINE</link>. Starkweather chaired a working group for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/56938.xml">
Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers</link> from 1987-1991 that established the national standards for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/57399.xml">
PILOT</link>. The language is still in active use today. However, the introduction of microcomputers also attracted capital to a budding software industry, and this ended the early period when most non-business software was created in universities; Starkweather thereafter turned his energy to administration.</p>
<p>

In the 1960s, Starkweather was the logical person to develop a computer center for UCSF, which he led for 15 years until its operation was ready for a non-faculty administrator. In 1983, he became Academic Vice Chair of the Department of Psychiatry, and made major contributions to departmental planning and advising junior faculty regarding faculty advancement. Starkweather held this position until his retirement in 1993.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Contributions to UCSF</st>
<p>

UCSF is a health science campus with no undergraduate programs, and when Starkweather joined the faculty in 1955 there were no degree programs in psychology, although the Clinical Psychology Internship at the <link>
Langley Porter Psychiatric Institute</link> was already well known. Starkweather was one of the founders of the Psychology Ph.D. program established at UCSF in 1961 and he chaired the program in its early years. Under the leadership of George Stone, this program was later transformed into the first health psychology Ph.D. program in the country. Starkweather led the creation in 1971 of the UCSF Ph.D. program in Medical Information Sciences, and chaired that program for nine years.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Civic contributions</st>
<p>

Starkweather was also a civic leader in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/82017.xml">
Marin County</link> community where he lived. He served 12 years on his local school board and 20 years on the City of San Rafael Planning Commission. He used his gifts as a photographer and computer pioneer to help educational and conservation organizations, and worked with his wife Jean on projects to preserve Marin County open space. A longtime friend described him as "a founding father" of his local community, having built a home there in 1956 and immediately becoming involved in community affairs. "He was my partner and best friend," says Jean. "He was a wonderful person who did extraordinary things for the community." He volunteered in many programs, led a project to build a low-cost housing development, and worked with the Boy Scouts and the YMCA. San Rafael mayor Al Boro said that Starkweather "truly served his community, and everything he did, he did for the right reason." Boro called him "a gentle person-very bright, very articulate, and lots of fun."</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Honors and awards</st>
<p>

Among various honors for his academic work, Starkweather was elected a Fellow of the <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/243062.xml">
American Association for the Advancement of Science</link></group>
</society>
</social_group>
 "for contributions to medical information systems and the application of computers to instruction, inquiry, and learning," and Fellow of the <association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/8485043.xml">
American College of Medical Informatics</link></association>
 "for contributions to the field of medical information science." During his career, he served in many university-wide and campus-wide leadership roles, including Chair of the UCSF Academic Senate. Several of his students became leaders in their fields, including the psychologists <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/521432.xml">
Paul Ekman</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <link>
Rudolph Moos</link>, the psychiatrists <link>
Donald Langsley</link>, <link>
Kay Blacker</link>, and the computer scientist <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/11573220.xml">
Gio Wiederhold</link></scientist>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Death</st>
<p>

Starkweather died at the age of 75 after a long struggle with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/6302185.xml">
Parkinson's disease</link>.</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</psychologist>
</scientist>
</article>
