<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:25:51[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<idea  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105833840">
<concept  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105835747">
<category  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105838765">
<type  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105840188">
<kind  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105839024">
<header>
<title>Variable universal life insurance</title>
<id>633515</id>
<revision>
<id>241908174</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T01:13:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Taxman</username>
<id>18034</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with limited geographic scope</category>
<category>Types of insurance</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="46px" src="Globe_important.svg">
<caption>

Globe icon
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The examples and perspective in this article or section may not represent a  of the subject.
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Variable_universal_life_insurance&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> or discuss the issue on the .</col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Variable Universal Life Insurance</b> (often shortened to VUL) is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/383367.xml">
life insurance</link> that builds a cash value.  In a VUL, the cash value can be invested in a wide variety of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../828/4165828.xml">
separate account</link>s, similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/226597.xml">
mutual funds</link>, and the choice of which of the available separate accounts to use is entirely up to the contract owner.  The 'variable' component in the name refers to this ability to invest in separate accounts whose values vary--they vary because they are invested in stock and/or bond markets.   The 'universal' component in the name refers to the flexibility the owner has in making premium payments.  The premiums can vary from nothing in a given month up to maximums defined by the Internal Revenue Code for life insurance.  This flexibility is in contrast to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/2282039.xml">
whole life insurance</link> that has fixed premium payments that typically cannot be missed without lapsing the policy.  <p>

Variable universal life is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/527415.xml">
permanent life insurance</link>, because the death benefit will be paid if the insured dies any time as long as there is sufficient cash value to pay the costs of insurance in the policy.  With most if not all VUL's, unlike whole life, there is no <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../453/3291453.xml">
endowment</link> age (which for whole life is typically 100).  This is yet another key advantage of VUL over Whole Life.  With a typical whole life policy, the death benefit is limited to the face amount specified in the policy, and at endowment age, the face amount is all that is paid out.  Thus with either death or endowment, the insurance company keeps any cash value built up over the years.  With a VUL policy, the death benefit is the face amount <b>plus</b> the build up of any cash value that occurs (beyond any amount being used to fund the current cost of insurance.)</p>
<p>

If good choices for investments are made in the separate accounts, a much higher rate-of-return can occur than the low fixed rates-of-return typical for whole life.  The combination over the years of no endowment age, continually increasing death benefit and high rate-of-return in the separate accounts of a VUL policy could typically result in value to the owner or beneficiary which can be many times that of a whole life policy with the same amounts of money paid in as premiums.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Regulation of VUL Providers </st>

<p>

Because the separate accounts are <link>
securities</link>, the representative providing a VUL must be working in accordance with the securities regulations of the country or province in which he operates. And because they are life insurance policies,  VULs may only be sold by representatives who are properly licensed to sell life insurance in the areas in which they operate.  The insurance company providing the policy must also be licensed as an "insurer." </p>
<p>

This dual regulation helps protect consumers, who can look up the track record of offenses of any provider listed by the regulating SRO (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/3363446.xml">
Self Regulatory Organization</link>) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/664856.xml">
provincial securities commission</link>.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<b>United States</b>. VULs may only be sold in the United States by representatives who have a "producers" life insurance license in the state(s) in which he operates.  The insurance company providing the policy must also be licensed in the state(s) as an "insurer." Because the separate accounts are <link>
securities</link>, the representative must be working through a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/373060.xml">
broker/dealer</link> registered with the United States' SRO, the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/12481308.xml">
FINRA</link>) and himself be registered with FINRA.  (FINRA has an online database an investor can use to look up offenses and regulatory actions of any broker or broker/dealer.)  The fact of a representative's securities registration will show on his state insurance license as "Variable"  as in "qualified for Life and Variable Products."  (The exact wording could vary from state to state.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<b>Canada</b>. VUL's, as securities, may only be sold in Canada by representatives duly registered with their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/664856.xml">
provincial securities commission</link> to sell mutual funds.  And as VUL's are life insurance policies, providers must comply with the regulations of the Canadian Life and Health Insurance Association (CLHIA).  In Canada, there is no real differentiation between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/979677.xml">
universal life</link> and variable universal life.  The Canadian Securities Industry is also regulated by 2 self-regulatory organizations: the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/18847030.xml">
IIROC</link> {<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/18847030.xml">
Investment Industry Regulatory Organization of Canada</link>} and the MFDA (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/18720727.xml">
Mutual Fund Dealers Association</link>). The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/12805366.xml">
Canadian Securities Administrators</link> oversee these self-regulatory organizations and rely on them as front-line regulators of securities dealers and their representatives.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Uses </st>
<p>

Variable universal life insurance receives special tax advantages in the United States Internal Revenue Code.  The cash value in life insurance is able to earn investment returns without incurring current <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/50845.xml">
income tax</link> as long as it meets the definition of life insurance and the policy remains in force.  The tax free investment returns could be considered to be used to pay for the costs of insurance inside the policy.  See the 'Tax Benefits' section for more.</p>
<p>

In one theory of life insurance, needs based analysis, life insurance is only needed to the extent that assets left behind by a person will not be enough to meet the income and capital needs of his or her dependents.  In one form of variable universal life insurance, the cost of insurance purchased is based only on the difference between the death benefit and the cash value (defined as the net amount at risk from the perspective of the insurer).  Therefore, the greater the cash value accumulation, the lesser the net amount at risk, and the less insurance that is purchased.</p>
<p>

Another use of Variable Universal Life Insurance is among relatively wealthy persons who give money yearly to their children to put into VUL policies under the gift tax exemption. Very often persons in the United States with a net worth high enough that they will encounter the estate tax give money away to their children to protect that money being taxed. Often this is done within a VUL policy because this allows a tax deferral (for which no alternative would exist besides tuition money saved in an educational IRA or 529 plan), provides for permanent life insurance, and can usually be accessed tax-free by borrowing against the policy.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Contract Features</st>

<p>

By allowing the contract owner to choose the investments inside the policy the insured takes on the investment risk, and receives the greater potential return of the investments in return.  If the investment returns are very poor this could lead to a policy lapsing (ceasing to exist as a valid policy).  To avoid this, many insurers offer guaranteed death benefits up to a certain age as long as a given minimum premium is paid.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Premium Flexibility</st>

<p>

VUL policies have a great deal of flexibility in choosing how much premiums to pay for a given death benefit.  The minimum premium is primarily affected by the contract features offered by the insurer.  To maintain a death benefit guarantee, that specified premium level must be paid every month.  To keep the policy in force, typically no premium needs to be paid as long as there is enough cash value in the policy to pay that month's cost of insurance.  The maximum premium amounts are heavily influenced by the code for life insurance.  Internal Revenue Code section 7702 sets limits for how much cash value can be allowed and how much premium can be paid (both in a given year, and over certain periods of time) for a given death benefit.  The most efficient policy in terms of cash value growth would have the maximum premium paid for the minimum death benefit.  Then the costs of insurance would have the minimum negative effect on the growth of the cash value.  In the extreme would be a life insurance policy that had no life insurance component, and was entirely cash value.  If it received favorable tax treatment as a life insurance policy it would be the perfect <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/3325618.xml">
tax shelter</link>, pure investment returns and no insurance cost.  In fact when variable universal life policies first became available in 1986, contract owners were able to make very high investments into their policies and received extraordinary tax benefits.  In order to curb this practice, but still encourage life insurance purchase, the IRS developed guidelines regarding allowed premiums for a given death benefit.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Maximum Premiums</st>

<p>

The standard set was twofold: to define a maximum amount of cash value per death benefit and to define a maximum premium for a given death benefit.  If the maximum premium is exceeded the policy no longer qualifies for all of the benefits of a life insurance contract and is instead known as a <link>
modified endowment contract</link> or a MEC.  A MEC still receives tax free investment returns, and a tax free death benefit, but withdrawals of cash value in a MEC are on a '<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/4690937.xml">
LIFO</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
' basis, where earnings are withdrawn first and taxed as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/9337763.xml">
ordinary income</link>.  If the cash value in a contract exceeds the specified percentage of death benefit, the policy no longer qualifies as life insurance at all and all investment earnings become immediately taxable in the year the specified percentage is exceeded.  In order to avoid this, contracts define the death benefit to be the higher of the original death benefit or the amount needed to meet IRS guidelines.  The maximum cash value is determined to be a certain percentage of the death benefit.  The percentage ranges from 30% or so for young insured persons, declining to 0% for those reaching age 100.</p>
<p>

The maximum premiums are set by the IRS guidelines such that the premiums paid within a seven year period after a qualifying event (such as purchase or death benefit increase), grown at a 6% rate, and using the maximum guaranteed costs of insurance in the policy contract, would endow the policy at age 100 (ie the cash value would equal the death benefit).  More specific rules are adjusted for premiums that are not paid in equal amounts over a seven year period.  The entire maximum premium (greater than the 7 year premium) can be paid in one year and no more premiums can be paid unless the death benefit is increased.  If the 7 year level guideline premium is exceeded, then the policy becomes a MEC.</p>
<p>

To add more confusion the seven year MEC premium level cannot be paid in a VUL every year for 7 years, and still avoid MEC status.  The MEC premium level can only be paid in practice for about 4 years before additional premiums cannot be paid if non MEC status is desired.  There is another premium designed to be the maximum premium that can be paid every year a policy is in force.  This premium carries different names from different insurers, one calling it the guideline maximum premium.  This is the premium that often reaches the most efficient use of the policy.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Investment choices</st>

<p>

The number and type of choices available is dependent on the insurer, but some policies are available with a wide variety of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../828/4165828.xml">
separate account</link>s, also known as separate accounts.  Some insurers offer over 50 separate accounts with investment styles from very conservative guaranteed fixed accounts, to bond funds, to equity funds to highly aggressive sector funds.</p>
<p>

Separate accounts are organized as trusts to be managed for the benefit of the insureds, and are named because they are kept separate from the general account which is the other reserve assets of the insurer.  They are treated, and in all intents and purposes are, very much like mutual funds, but have slightly different regulatory requirements.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Tax advantages</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tax free investment earnings while a policy is in force </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

FIFO withdrawal status on principal paid into the contract</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tax free policy loans from non-MEC policies</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The death benefit is paid income tax free if premiums are paid with after tax money</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Taxes are the main reason those in higher tax brackets (25%+) would desire to use a VUL over any other accumulation strategy.  For someone in a 34% tax bracket (Federal &amp; State), the investment return on the separate accounts may average 10%, and at say age 75 the policy's death benefit would have an internal rate of return of 9%.  In order to get a 9% rate of return in an ordinary taxable account, in a 34% tax bracket, one must earn 13.64%. Another alternative is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/402261.xml">
Roth IRA</link>, because one would get the 10% tax free. But the limits on the Roth are low, and the Roth is normally unavailable to those in the 34% tax bracket.  These numbers assume expenses that may vary from company to company, and it is assumed that the VUL is funded with a minimum face value for the level of premium. The cash values would also be available to fund lifestyle or personally managed investments on a tax free basis in the form of refunds of premiums paid in and policy loans (which would be paid off on death by the death benefit.)</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Risks of Variable Universal Life</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cost of Insurance - The cost of insurance for VULs is generally based on term rates. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cash Outlay - The cash needed to effectively use a VUL is generally much higher than other types of insurance policies. If a policy does not have the right amount of funding, it may lapse.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Investment Risk - Because the sub accounts in the VUL may be invested in stocks and bonds, the insured now takes on the investment risk rather than the insurance company. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Complexity - The VUL is a complex product, and can easily be used (or sold) inappropriately because of this. Proper funding, investing, and planning are usually required in order for the VUL to work as expected.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
General Uses of Variable Universal Life</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Financial Protection - VULs can be used to protect a family in the case of a premature death. A VUL can be attractive for this need because it is a permanent policy, and, if funded correctly, will not lapse, unlike term insurance. This may give the insured more insurance flexibility in future years.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tax Advantages - Because of its tax-deferred feature, the VUL may offer an attractive tax advantage, especially to those in higher tax brackets. If highly funded (though still non-MEC), the tax advantages may even offset the cost of insurance. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Education Planning - The cash value of a VUL can be used to help fund children's education, as long as the policy is started very early. Also, putting money into a VUL can be used to help children qualify for federal financial aid, since the federal government does not consider the cash value when calculating EFC (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/11717343.xml">
Expected Family Contribution</link>). </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Retirement Planning - Because of its tax-free policy loan feature, the VUL can also be used as tax-advantaged income source in retirement, assuming retirement is not in the near future and the policy is not a modified endowment contract. Again, the policy must be properly funded for this strategy to work. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Estate Planning - Those with a large estate can sometimes use a VUL as part of their estate planning strategy to reduce or avoid estate taxes by setting up a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/6163599.xml">
life insurance trust</link> sometimes known as an ILIT.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Criticisms of Variable Universal Life</st>

<p>

Some general Criticisms</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

High Costs - VUL's tend to be more expensive than other types of insurance, including Whole Life, Term, and Universal Life (in that order).  The total cost of insurance in a VUL policy will be greater over its lifetime than a term policy and therefore more profitable to the insurer (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/2270738.xml">
Buy term and invest the difference</link>).  Tax savings however may more than compensate for the costs, assuming the individual has already taken advantage of Roth contributions.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Limited investment choices, confined to the (sometimes expensive) separate accounts that are run or set up by the insurance company. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Policy expenses may increase if the company has negative experience with mortality.  Usually there is a cap on those expenses.  It should not be assumed that the policy will continue to grow and stay robust, particularly if subjected to withdrawals and loans.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Many criticisms of VUL policies are not about the product in and of itself, but rather how it is sold by many insurance agents.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

VUL is more profitable to the insurance company and to the agent which creates a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/236850.xml">
conflict of interest</link> to sell it when term life insurance would be better for the customer.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Policy purchasers may not be fully aware of the investment risk and complexities involved.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

In order to emphasize the tax free savings aspect of VUL, many agents do not disclose the other tax free savings options open to people, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/402261.xml">
Roth IRA</link>s or section <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/676912.xml">
529 plan</link>s, which might be better. Also other tax advantaged savings options such as the 401(k) or other pre-tax retirement plans may be more appropriate in a given situation.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Some insurance companies or agents do not actively encourage the maximum efficient use of the policy by paying the greatest possible premium.  Thus cash values do not grow well and costs are maximized.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

While certain Universal Life insurance fees are scrupulously disclosed, there are some who claim that certain additional investment account management fees (MERs) are not fully disclosed in some VUL policy projections.  These additional fees can potentially cut the net yield of a VUL policy by a significant margin, compared to the identical investments held outside the VUL.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>
	 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://invest-faq.com/articles/ins-vul.html">
invest-faq article</weblink> on VUL</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://money.cnn.tv/2007/02/05/pf/expert/expert.moneymag/index.htm?postversion=2007020517">
Article</weblink> on the pitch and pitfalls of VUL</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aitraining.com/variableuniversallife.htm">
Variable Universal Life Contract Basics</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.clhia.ca/">
Canadian Life and Health Insurance Association Inc.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csa-acvm.ca/html_CSA/members.html">
List of Canadian provencial securities commissions</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.finra.org/InvestorInformation/InvestorProtection/ChecktheBackgroundofYourInvestmentProfessional/index.htm">
FINRA - look up a U.S. securities firm or broker in BrokerCheck</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</article>
