<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:20:32[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Wireless grid</title>
<id>6349878</id>
<revision>
<id>238396471</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-14T17:29:04Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mlaffs</username>
<id>5875630</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wireless networking</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Wireless grids</b> are wireless computer networks consisting of different types of electronic devices with the ability to share their resources with any other device in the network in an ad-hoc manner.
A definition of the wireless grid can be given as: "Ad-hoc, distributed resource-sharing networks between heterogeneous wireless devices"
The following key characteristics further clarify this concept:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

No centralized control </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Small, low powered devices </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Heterogeneous applications and interfaces </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

New types of resources like cameras, GPS trackers and sensors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dynamic and unstable users / resources</entry>
</list>
<p>

The technologies that make up the wireless grid can be divided into two main categories; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/6624928.xml">
ad-hoc network</link>ing and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/49373.xml">
grid computing</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
(Wireless) Ad-hoc networking</st>

<p>

In traditional networks, both wired and wireless, the connected devices, or nodes, depend on dedicated devices (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/3670866.xml">
edge device</link>s) such as routers and/or servers for facilitating the throughput of information from one node to the other. These 'routing nodes' have the ability to determine where information is coming from and where it is supposed to go. They give out names and addresses (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/14921.xml">
IP address</link>es) to each connected node and regulate the traffic between them. In wireless grids, such dedicated routing devices are not (always) available and the bandwidth that is permanently available to traditional networks has to be either 'borrowed' from an already existing network or publicly accessible bandwidth (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/249388.xml">
open spectrum</link>) has to be used.</p>
<p>

A group addressing this problem is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/142569.xml">
MANET</link> (Mobile Ad-Hoc Network).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Resource sharing</st>
<p>

One of the intended aspects of wireless grids is that it will facilitate the sharing of a wide variety of resources. These will include both technical as information resources. The former being bandwidth, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/25315.xml">
QoS</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/93483.xml">
web services</link>, but also computational power and data storage capacity. Information resources can include virtually any kind of data from databases and membership lists to pictures and directories.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/168704.xml">
Ad-hoc</link> resource sharing between mobile devices in the wireless grid require for the devices to agree on sharing/communication <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/83235.xml">
protocol</link>s without the existence of dedicated servers.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Coordination Systems</st>
<p>

Coordination Systems are the actual mechanisms that enable the sharing of resources between different devices. For different resources, devices use different coordination systems. Examples of such mechanisms are: <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/349873.xml">
SMB</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 or <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/51252.xml">
NFS</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 for sharing disk space and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/337011.xml">
distributed.net</link> client for sharing processor cycles.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Trust Establishment</st>
<p>

Before users are willing to share any resource, they demand a certain amount of trust between them and the users and/or systems they share resources with. The amount of trust required depends on the kind of information/resource that is to be shared. Sharing processor cycles requires less substantial trust then the sharing of personal information and commercial information can require another level of trust establishment altogether. There are systems currently in operation that can provide a certain amount of trust like the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/194112.xml">
public key infrastructure</link> that makes use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/223796.xml">
certificates</link>; now often used in web based email systems, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/16947.xml">
Kerberos</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Resource discovery</st>
<p>

Before any resource on a device in the grid can be utilized, those resources that are available must be discovered; all the devices that make up the grid and the resources they possess have to be identified. When a client enters the grid, such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/23304.xml">
PDA</link>, it has to be able to communicate to the other users that it is a PDA and it has a camera, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
GPS</link> capabilities, a telephone function and various office applications such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/30310.xml">
text editor</link>. Protocols like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/183365.xml">
UPnP</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../453/319453.xml">
ZeroConf</link> can detect a new node in the network when it enters. When detected, other users can send a query to the new device to find out what it has to offer. Commercial service providers can 'advertise' the resources they have to offer through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/2527345.xml">
IP multicast</link>s. Within large grids containing thousands of nodes, a kind of 'friend of a friend' mechanism can be used. 
There is a myriad of standards that include resource description protocols. Standards as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/15285.xml">
IETF</link>'s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../453/319453.xml">
ZeroConf</link>, Microsoft's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/183365.xml">
UPnP</link>, the Grid Resource Description Language (GRDL), the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/4030790.xml">
Web Services Description Language</link> (WSDL) for describing various specific web services and parts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/25315.xml">
QoS</link> that describe bandwidths all offer devices a way to describe and publish their specific resources and needs. There are also various different systems currently available that can gather these resource descriptions and structure them for other devices to use.
The OpenGrid Services Architecture (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/262630.xml">
OGSA</link>) uses a Web service-style IndexService. The Web services community has defined <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/158694.xml">
UDDI</link> which can makes a database of services that are available on the network, and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../828/217828.xml">
JXTA</link></software>
 uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../453/319453.xml">
ZeroConf</link> to identify resources in a network. However, the problem with using these in wireless grids is that no stable publisher of these descriptions may exist.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Resource description</st>
<p>

For any device to be able to use any resource, a way to identify and describe the resource has to be agreed on by all available devices. If, for instance, storage capacity is to be shared, it first has to be clear what the capacity of each device is and what the storage need is. As said, there are many techniques to describe certain resources but there is not one technique that is able to provide this service for all resources. The available techniques combined, however, cover most of what is needed.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Grid Computing</st>

<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/49373.xml">
Grid computing</link> came into existence as a manner of sharing heavy computational loads among multiple computers to be able to compute highly complex mathematical problems (a good real-world example being the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/309768.xml">
SETI@Home</link> project). However, it developed rapidly into a way of sharing virtually any resource that is available on any machine on the grid. Wired grids are now used to share not only computing power, but also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard disk</link> space, data, and applications. The grid topology is highly flexible and easily scalable, allowing users to join and leave the grid without the hassle of time and resource hungry identification procedures, having to adjust their devices or install additional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> on them. The goal of grid computing is described as "to provide flexible, secure and coordinated resource sharing among dynamic collections of individuals, institutions and resources" (McKnight, Howison, 2004).
It is intended to be a dynamic network without geographical, political, or cultural boundaries that offers real-time access to heterogeneous resources and still offer the same characteristics of the traditional distributed networks that are in use everywhere in our houses and offices. These characteristics being stability, scalability, and flexibility as the most important ones. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/1396931.xml">
Ian Foster</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 offers a checklist for recognizing a grid.
<indent level="1">

A grid allows:
</indent>
*Coordination of resources that are not subject to centralized control
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Use of standard, open, general-purpose protocols and interfaces</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Delivery of nontrivial qualities of service</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
The Wireless Grid</st>

<p>

One of the biggest limitations of the wired grid is that users are forced to be in a fixed location as the devices they use are to be hard wired to the grid at all times. This also has a negative influence on the flexibility and scalability of the grid; devices can only join the grid in locations where the possibility exists to physically connect the device to the grid (i.e. there is the need for a hub or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/40614.xml">
switch</link> to plug into).</p>
<p>

One description of the wireless grid is "an augmentation of a wired grid that facilitates the exchange of information and the interaction between heterogeneous wireless devices" (Argawal, Norman &amp; Gupta, 2004)</p>
<p>

Argawal, Norman &amp; Gupta (2004) identify three forces that drive the development of the wireless grid:</p>
<p>

<b>New user interaction modalities and form factors</b>
Applications that exist on current wired grids need to be adapted to fit the devices used in wireless grids. These devices are usually hand held and therefore the user interface devices (screens, keyboards (if any)) are significantly smaller and availability of additional input devices like a <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/7056.xml">
mouse</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 are limited. This means the traditional graphical interfaces found on PCs are not suitable.</p>
<p>

<b>Limited computing resources</b>
Wireless devices do not possess the computing power nor the storage capacity of full size devices like a PC or laptop. Therefore wireless applications need to have access to additional computing resources to be able to offer the same functionality that wired networks do.</p>
<p>

<b>Additional new supporting infrastructure elements</b>
In the case of an unforeseen event, there will be the need for major amounts of computational and communications bandwidths. An urban catastrophe, for example, would require a dynamic and adaptive wireless network to alert people within the population as well as those in the various coordination and aid services like the police, army, medical services, and government. Applications to provide for these bandwidths and 'instant' networks need to be addressed.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Wireless Grids infrastructure</st>

<p>

The infrastructure of the wireless grid consists of three basic levels:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/78300.xml">
physical layer</link> technologies and policies. The physical layer contains the spectrum on which the wireless devices can operate and communicate.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Network infrastructure</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/57183.xml">
Middleware</link> to provide communications between heterogeneous devices</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/3742.xml">
Bluetooth</link></system_of_measurement>
</machine>
</device>
</standard>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/14739.xml">
IEEE 802.11</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/912687.xml">
Mesh network</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/65776.xml">
Metcalfe's law</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/1014669.xml">
Overlay network</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/24107.xml">
P2P</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/29215.xml">
SOAP</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/63973.xml">
Wi-Fi</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.8">
<capitalist wordnetid="109609232" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<supplier wordnetid="110677271" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/273988.xml">
Wireless local loop</link></supplier>
</causal_agent>
</capitalist>
</businessperson>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<proposal wordnetid="107162194" confidence="0.8">
<recommendation wordnetid="106671637" confidence="0.8">
<advice wordnetid="106671484" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/296352.xml">
X.509</link></advice>
</recommendation>
</proposal>
</rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fcc.gov/">
FCC</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/">
IETF</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jürgen Falkner, Fraunhofer Institute for Industrial Engineering; JNF/842, 2004), <it>The Fraunhofer Resource Grid - making Grids usable''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lee W. McKnight, James Howison (2004). <it>Wireless Grids; Distributed Resource Sharing by Mobile, Nomadic, and Fixed Devices.''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Agarwal, Norman and Gupta (2004). <it>Wireless grids: approaches, architectures, and technical challenges.''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mcnight and Howison (2003). <it>Towards a sharing protocol for wireless grids''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sridhar Iyer (2000). <it>Routing in Mobile Ad Hoc Networks''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hwang &amp; Aravamudham. <it>Proxy-based middleware services for peer-to-peer computing in virtually clustered wireless grid networks''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wijngaert, v.d, Bouwman, Moerbeek and Kwiatkowska. <it>Would you Share? Predicting the Potential Use of a New Technology using Multilevel Linear Regression Analysis''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Uzunner and Davis. <it>Digital fingerprinting for distributed volume tracking: intellectual property protection in wireless grids''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
