<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:26:02[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>URL redirection</title>
<id>636686</id>
<revision>
<id>244144922</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T15:06:57Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>David.Monniaux</username>
<id>22449</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Black hat seo</category>
<category>Web design</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
<category>Articles to be merged&amp;#32;since December 2007</category>
<category>Spamming</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For URL redirection on Wikipedia, see .
"Short URL" redirects here. For information about short URLs on Wikipedia, see .
<b>URL redirection</b>, also called <b>URL forwarding</b>, <b>domain redirection</b> and <b>domain forwarding</b>, is a technique on the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
 for making a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/34063.xml">
web page</link> available under many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URLs</link>.
<sec>
<st>
 Purposes </st>
<p>

There are several reasons for a webmaster or developer to use redirection:</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Similar domain names </st>
<p>

A web browser user might mis-type a URL -- for example, "gooogle.com" and "googel.com". Organizations often register these "mis-spelled" domains and re-direct them to the "correct" location: google.com. For example: the addresses example.com and example.net could both redirect to a single domain, or web page, such as example.org. This technique is often used to "reserve" other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/31115.xml">
TLD</link>s with the same name, or make it easier for a true ".edu" or ".net" to redirect to a more recognizable ".com" domain.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Moving a site to a new domain </st>
<p>

Why redirect a web page? 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A web site might need to change its domain name.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An author might move his or her pages to a new domain.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Two web sites might merge.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

With URL redirects, incoming links to an outdated URL can be sent to the correct location. These links might be from other sites that have not realized that there is a change or from bookmarks/favorites that users have saved in their browsers.</p>
<p>

The same applies to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link>s. They often have the older/outdated domain names and links in their database and will send search users to these old URLs. By using a "moved permanently" redirect to the new URL, visitors will still end at the correct page.  Also, in the next search engine pass, the search engine should detect and use the newer URL.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Logging outgoing links </st>
<p>

The access logs of most web servers keep detailed information from where visitors came and how they browsed the hosted site.  They do not, however, log which links visitors left by.  This is because the visitor's browser has no need to communicate with the original server when the visitor clicks on an out-going link.</p>
<p>

This information can be captured in several ways.  One way involves URL redirection.  Instead of sending the visitor straight to the other site, links on the site can direct to a URL on the original website's domain that automatically redirects to the real target.  This added request will leave a trace in the server logs saying exactly which link was followed.  This technique is also used by some corporate websites to have a "warning" page that the content is off-site and not necessarily affiliated with the corporation.  This technique does bear the downside in the delay of an additional request to the original website's server. For websites that wish to display a "warning" page before automatically forwarding, the length of time the warning is displayed is an additional delay.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Short, meaningful, persistent aliases for long or changing URLs </st>
<p>

Currently, web engineers tend to pass descriptive attributes in the URL to represent data hierarchies, command structures, transaction paths and session information. This results in a URL that is aesthetically unpleasant and difficult to remember.  Sometimes the URL of a page changes even though the content stays the same.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Manipulating search engines </st>

<p>

Some years ago, redirect techniques were used to fool search engines.  For example, one page could show popular search terms to search engines but redirect the visitors to a different target page.  There are also cases where redirects have been used to "steal" the page rank of one popular page and use it for a different page, usually involving the 302 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/1514108.xml">
HTTP status code</link> of "moved temporarily." <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Search engine providers noticed the problem and took appropriate actions. Usually, sites that employ such techniques to manipulate search engines are punished automatically by reducing their ranking or by excluding them from the search index.</p>
<p>

As a result, today, such manipulations usually result in less rather than more site exposure.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Satire and criticism </st>

<p>

In the same way that a <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/286747.xml">
Google bomb</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
 can be used for satire and political criticism, a domain name that conveys one meaning can be redirected to any other web page, sometimes with malicious intent.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Manipulating visitors </st>

<p>

URL redirection is sometimes used as a part of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/428364.xml">
phishing</link> attacks that confuse visitors about which web site they are visiting.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Techniques </st>

<p>

There are several techniques to implement a redirect.  In many cases, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/1753130.xml">
Refresh meta tag</link> is the simplest one.  However, there exist several strong opinions discouraging this method.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Manual redirect </st>

<p>

The simplest technique is to ask the visitor to follow a link to the new page, usually using an HTML anchor as such:</p>
<p>

Please follow link!</p>
<p>

This method is often used as a fall-back for automatic methods — if the visitor's browser does not support the automatic redirect method, the visitor can still reach the target document by following the link.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 HTTP status codes 3xx </st>

<p>

In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/2701104.xml">
HTTP</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link> <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/630770.xml">
protocol</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 used by the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
, a <b>redirect</b> is a response with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/1514108.xml">
status code</link> beginning with <it>3</it> that induces a browser to go to another location.</p>
<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616.html">
HTTP standard</weblink> defines several <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec10.html#sec10.3">
status codes</weblink> for redirection:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 300 multiple choices (e.g. offer different languages)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 301 moved permanently</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 302 found (e.g. temporary redirect)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 303 see other (e.g. for results of cgi-scripts)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 307 temporary redirect</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

All of these status codes require that the URL of the redirect target is given in the Location: header of the HTTP response.  The 300 multiple choices will usually list all choices in the body of the message and show the default choice in the Location: header.</p>
<p>

Within the 3xx range, there are also some status codes that are quite different from the above redirects (they are not discussed here with their details):</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 304 not modified</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 305 use proxy</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This is a sample of a HTTP response that uses the 301 "moved permanently" redirect:</p>

<p>

HTTP/1.1 301 Moved Permanently
Location: http://www.example.org/
Content-Type: text/html
Content-Length: 174</p>


<p>

Moved</p>

<p>

Moved
This page has moved to http://www.example.org/.</p>




<ss2>
<st>
 Using server-side scripting for Redirection </st>

<p>

Often, web authors don't have sufficient permissions to produce these status codes: The HTTP header is generated by the web server program and not read from the file for that URL.  Even for CGI scripts, the web server usually generates the status code automatically and allows custom headers to be added by the script.  To produce HTTP status codes with cgi-scripts, one needs to enable non-parsed-headers.</p>
<p>

Sometimes, it is sufficient to print the "Location: 'url'" header line from a normal CGI script. Many web servers choose one of the 3xx status codes for such replies.</p>
<p>

Frameworks for server-side content generation typically require that HTTP headers be generated before response data.  As a result, the web programmer who is using such a scripting language to redirect the user's browser to another page must ensure that the redirect is the first or only part of the response.  In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/2883.xml">
ASP scripting</link> language, this can also be accomplished using the methods response.buffer=true and response.redirect "http://www.example.com".  Using <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<compiler wordnetid="109946957" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/24131.xml">
PHP</link></writer>
</language>
</causal_agent>
</compiler>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
, one can use header("Location: http://www.example.com");.</p>
<p>

According to the HTTP protocol, the Location header must contain an absolute <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/32146.xml">
URI</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. When redirecting from one page to another within the same site, it is a common mistake to use a relative URI. As a result most browsers tolerate relative URIs in the Location header, but some browsers display a warning to the end user.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Using .htaccess for Redirection </st>

<p>

When using the <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/2581.xml">
Apache</link></software>
 web server, directory-specific <record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<file wordnetid="106508816" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/554518.xml">
.htaccess</link></evidence>
</indication>
</file>
</record>
 files (as well as apache's main configuration files) can be used. For example, to redirect a single page:</p>
<p>

Redirect 301 /oldpage.html http://www.example.com/newpage.html</p>

<p>

To change domain names:</p>
<p>

RewriteEngine On</p>
<p>

RewriteCond %{HTTP_HOST} ^.*oldwebsite\.com$ [NC]
RewriteRule ^(.*)$ http://www.preferredwebsite.net$1 [R=301,L]</p>

<p>

Use of .htaccess for this purpose usually does not require administrative permissions, though it can be disabled.
When you have access to apache main config file (such as httpd.conf), it is best to avoid the use of .htaccess files.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Refresh Meta tag and HTTP refresh header </st>

<p>

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/21979.xml">
Netscape</link></company>
 introduced a feature to refresh the displayed page after a certain amount of time. This method is often called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/1753130.xml">
meta refresh</link>. It is possible to specify the URL of the new page, thus replacing one page after some time by another page: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3schools.com/tags/tag_meta.asp">
HTML  tag</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wp.netscape.com/assist/net_sites/pushpull.html">
An exploration of dynamic documents</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.security-protocols.com/programming-tutorials/CGI/ch14.htm">
Proprietary extensions</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A timeout of 0 seconds means an immediate redirect.</p>
<p>

This is an example of a simple HTML document that uses this technique:</p>




<p>

Please follow link!</p>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 This technique is usable by all web authors because the meta tag is contained inside the document itself.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The meta tag must be placed in the "head" section of the HTML file.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Note the strange syntax of the content field.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The number "0" in this example may be replaced by another number to achieve a delay of as many seconds.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Many users regard a delay of this kind as annoying unless there is a reason for it.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 This is a proprietary/non-standard extension by Netscape.  It is supported by most web browsers.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This is an example of achieving the same effect by issuing a HTTP refresh header:</p>

<p>

HTTP/1.1 200 ok
Refresh: 0; url=http://www.example.com/
Content-type: text/html
Content-length: 78</p>
<p>

Please follow link!</p>
<p>

This response is easier to generate by CGI programs because one does not need to change the default status code.
Here is a simple CGI program that effects this redirect:</p>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

!/usr/bin/perl</entry>
</list>

print "Refresh: 0; url=http://www.example.com/\r\n";
print "Content-type: text/html\r\n";
print "\r\n";
print "Please follow link!"</p>
<p>

Note: Usually, the HTTP server adds the status line and the Content-length header automatically.</p>
<p>

This method is considered by the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/33149.xml">
W3C</link></company>
 to be a poor method of redirection, since it does not communicate any information about either the original or new resource, to the browser (or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link>). The W3C's <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WAI-WEBCONTENT/#tech-no-periodic-refresh">
Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (7.4)</weblink> discourage the creation of auto-refreshing pages, since most web browsers do not allow the user to disable or control the refresh rate.  Some articles that they have written on the issue include <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WAI-WEBCONTENT/#gl-movement">
W3C Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (1.0): Ensure user control of time-sensitive content changes</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/QA/Tips/reback">
Use standard redirects: don't break the back button!</weblink></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 JavaScript redirects </st>
<p>

<programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/9845.xml">
JavaScript</link></programming_language>
 offers several ways to display a different page in the current browser window. Quite frequently, they are used for a redirect.  However, there are several reasons to prefer HTTP header or the refresh meta tag (whenever it is possible) over JavaScript redirects:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There are several reasons for some users to disable JavaScript:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Security considerations</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Some browsers don't support JavaScript</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 many crawlers (e.g. from search engines) don't execute JavaScript.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is no "standard" way of doing it: A search for "you are being redirected" will find that virtually each JavaScript redirect employs different methods.  This makes it difficult for Web client programmers to honor your redirect request without implementing all of JavaScript.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Frame redirects </st>

<p>

A slightly different effect can be achieved by creating a single HTML <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/274393.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Frames%22])">
frame</link> that contains the target page:</p>




<p>

Please follow link!</p>


<p>

One main difference to the above redirect methods is that for a frame redirect, the browser displays the URL of the frame document and not the URL of the target page in the URL bar.</p>
<p>

This technique is commonly called <it>cloaking</it>. This may be used so that the reader sees a more memorable URL or, with fraudulent intentions, to conceal a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/428364.xml">
phishing</link> site as part of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/8080436.xml">
website spoofing</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Redirect loops </st>

<p>

It is quite possible that one redirect leads to another redirect. For example, the URL http://www.wikipedia.com/wiki/URL_redirection (note the differences in the domain name) is first redirected to http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/URL_redirection and again redirected to the correct URL: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/URL_redirection. This is appropriate: the first redirection corrects the wrong domain name. The second redirection selects the correct language section. Finally, the browser displays the correct page.</p>
<p>

Sometimes, however, a mistake can cause the redirection to point back to the first page, leading to an infinite loop of redirects. Browsers usually break that loop after a few steps and display an error message instead.  </p>
<p>

The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec10.html#sec10.3">
HTTP standard</weblink> states: </p>
<p>

A client SHOULD detect infinite redirection loops, since such loops generate network traffic for each redirection.</p>
<p>

Previous versions of this specification recommended a maximum of five redirections; some clients may exist that implement such a fixed limitation.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Services </st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Mergefrom.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that  be  into this article or section. ()</col>
</row>
</table>


There exist services that can perform URL redirection on demand, with no need for technical work or access to the webserver your site is hosted on.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 URL redirection services </st>
<p>

URL redirection services exist to shorten long <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link>s
Hyperlinks involving URL redirection services are frequently used in spam messages directed at blogs and wikis.  Thus, one way to reduce spam is to reject all edits and comments containing hyperlinks to known URL redirection services; however, this will also remove legitimate edits and comments and may not be an effective method to reduce spam.</p>
<p>

Recently, URL redirection services have taken to using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/1610950.xml">
AJAX</link> as an efficient, user friendly method for creating shortened URLs.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 URL obfuscation services </st>
<p>

There exist redirection services for hiding the referrer using META refresh, such as Anonymity.com and Anonym.to.</p>
<p>

This is very easy to do with PHP, such as in this example.</p>
<p>

?php
/* This code is placed into the public domain */
/* Will redirect a URL */</p>
<p>

$u=htmlspecialchars($_GET['url']); // used to sanitise the code
?&amp;gt;</p>
<p>

Redirect
"&amp;gt;</p>


<p>

You should be able to be redirected to "&amp;gt;?php echo($u); ?&amp;gt;.</p>

<p>

This code can then be accessed by example,

http://example.org/redirect.php?url=http://www.google.com

If the input is not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/4996524.xml">
sanitized</link> (using htmlspecialchars()) someone could be supplied with a URL that executes some malicious JavaScript appearing to originate from the website hosting the PHP code.</p>
<p>

Further, the above example code may not work correctly with URLs containing variables, unless the input is first encoded, or code is added that loops across the $_GETs and pieces together the final URL.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/365511.xml">
Link rot</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pandia.com/sw-2004/40-hijack.html">
Google's serious hijack problem</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.loriswebs.com/hijacking_web_pages.html">
Stop 302 Redirects and Scrapers from Hijacking Web Page PR - Page Rank</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
R. Fielding, et al., Request for Comments: 2616, Hypertext Transfer Protocol &mdash; HTTP/1.1, published 1999-07, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec14.html#sec14.30">
|14.30 "Location"</weblink>, fetched 2008-10-07</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sfbay-infragard.org/Documents/phishing-sfectf-report.pdf">
Anti-Phishing Technology"</weblink>, Aaron Emigh, Radix Labs, 19 January 2005</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.ucdavis.edu/~hchen/paper/www07.pdf">
Paper on redirection spam (UC Davis)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/1.3/urlmapping.html">
Mapping URLs to Filesystem Locations</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dmoz.org/Computers/Internet/Web_Design_and_Development/Hosted_Components_and_Services/Redirects/">
 Listing of URL redirection services</weblink> at the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<subsidiary_company wordnetid="108003935" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18949501.xml">
Open Directory Project</link></institution>
</subsidiary_company>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</property>
</undertaking>
</company>
</event>
</possession>
</work>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.12scripts.com/demo/redirector/admin/">
 Demo of PHP GeoIP redirect script</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.coyol.net/12-09-2008/301-permanent-redirect-in-php.html">
 301 Permanent Redirect in PHP</weblink> Script example of how to properly use 301 redirect using PHP</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<practice wordnetid="100410247" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/28368.xml">
Spamming</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</practice>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link>
History</link>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/5200065.xml">
Network Abuse Clearinghouse</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/630770.xml">
Protocol</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
s</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<table style="width:100%;;;;" class="nowraplinks  navbox-subgroup" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;font-weight:normal;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/459847.xml">
E-mail</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.5em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/527353.xml">
Address munging</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/10748488.xml">
Bulk email software</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/4884478.xml">
Directory Harvest Attack</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/153977.xml">
DNSBL</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/1466663.xml">
Spambot</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/13497047.xml">
Pink contract</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding-left:0em;padding-right:0em;font-weight:normal;;" class="navbox-group">
Other</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.5em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/179958.xml">
Autodialer</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/2067563.xml">
Flyposting</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/712475.xml">
Junk fax</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/394592.xml">
Messaging</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/394616.xml">
Mobile phone</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/394596.xml">
Newsgroup</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/162180.xml">
Telemarketing</link>&nbsp;·  <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/1017252.xml">
VoIP</link></concept>
</idea>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/313737.xml">
Anti-spam</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/1626908.xml">
Disposable e-mail address</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/1497388.xml">
E-mail authentication</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../989/2064989.xml">
SORBS</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/1905427.xml">
SpamCop</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/1267954.xml">
Spamhaus</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/5718790.xml">
List poisoning</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/515929.xml">
Bayesian spam filtering</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/15252288.xml">
Policy block list</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/43651.xml">
Spamdexing</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/1789102.xml">
Keyword stuffing</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/286747.xml">
Google bomb</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·   <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/3152572.xml">
Scraper site</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/270213.xml">
Link farm</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/714684.xml">
Webring</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/418364.xml">
Cloaking</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/594839.xml">
Doorway page</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/636686.xml">
URL redirection</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../302/2501302.xml">
Spam blog</link>s&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/2791084.xml">
Sping</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/4803822.xml">
Forum spam</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/528830.xml">
Blog spam</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/4927965.xml">
Social networking spam</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/1376814.xml">
Referer spam</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/805626.xml">
Internet fraud</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/46526.xml">
Advance fee fraud</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/1093010.xml">
Lottery scam</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/17362858.xml">
Make Money Fast</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/12512849.xml">
Microcap stock fraud</link>&nbsp;·  <accomplishment wordnetid="100035189" confidence="0.8">
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<transgression wordnetid="100745005" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<crime wordnetid="100766234" confidence="0.8">
<wrongdoing wordnetid="100732746" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<feat wordnetid="100036762" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/428364.xml">
Phishing</link></activity>
</feat>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</wrongdoing>
</crime>
</event>
</transgression>
</occupation>
</accomplishment>
&nbsp;·  <accomplishment wordnetid="100035189" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<feat wordnetid="100036762" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/6002126.xml">
Vishing</link></feat>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</action>
</event>
</concept>
</idea>
</accomplishment>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
