<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:48:35[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Picture archiving and communication system</title>
<id>63860</id>
<revision>
<id>244281390</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T02:21:23Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jfdwolff</username>
<id>46555</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Medical imaging</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Pacs1.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

An image as stored on a picture archiving and communication system (PACS)
</caption>
</image>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Pacs2.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The same image following contrast adjustment, sharpening and measurement tags added by the system
</caption>
</image>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/234714.xml">
medical imaging</link>, <b>picture archiving and communication systems</b> (PACS) are computers or networks dedicated to the storage, retrieval, distribution and presentation of images. The medical images are stored in an independent format. The most common format for image storage is <link>
DICOM (Digital Imaging and Communications in Medicine)</link>.
<sec>
<st>
Types of images</st>
<p>

Most PACSs handle images from various medical imaging instruments, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/143357.xml">
ultrasound</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/19446.xml">
magnetic resonance</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/24032.xml">
PET</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/50982.xml">
computed tomography</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/197002.xml">
endoscopy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/262039.xml">
mammograms</link>, etc. (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/63864.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Application+areas%22])">
DICOM Application areas</link>).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Uses </st>
<p>

PACS has two main uses:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Hard copy replace: PACS replaces <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/41230.xml">
hard-copy</link> based means of managing medical images, such as film archives. With the decreasing price of digital storage, PACSs provide a growing cost and space advantage over film archives.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Remote access: It expands on the possibilities of conventional systems by providing capabilities of off-site viewing and reporting (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/8997.xml">
distance education</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/18507525.xml">
telediagnosis</link>). It enables practitioners in different physical locations to access the same information simultaneously for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/3012765.xml">
teleradiology</link>. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

PACS is offered by virtually all the major medical imaging equipment manufacturers, medical IT companies and many independent software companies.  </p>
<p>

One difficult area in PACS is interpreting the <link>
DICOM</link> image format. DICOM does not fully specify the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> tags stored with images to annotate and describe them, so vendors of medical imaging equipment have latitude to create DICOM-compliant files that differ in the meaning and representation of this metadata. A feature common to most PACS is to read the metadata from all the images into a central database, allowing the PACS user to retrieve all images with a common feature no matter the originating instrument. The differences between vendors' DICOM implementations make this a difficult task.
<image width="150px" src="Complete_body_medical_imaging.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A PACS can store volume data from exams and reconstruct 3D images
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Architecture</st>
<p>

Typically a PACS network consists of a central server that stores a database containing the images connected to one or more clients via a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/17739.xml">
LAN</link> or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/38140.xml">
WAN</link> which provide or utilize the images. </p>
<p>

More and more PACS include web-based interfaces to utilize the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> as their means of communication, usually via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/147130.xml">
VPN</link> (Virtual Private Network) or <link>
SSL</link> (Secure Sockets Layer). The software is loaded via <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/9845.xml">
JavaScript</link></programming_language>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/1165470.xml">
Java</link>. </p>
<p>

Definitions vary, but most claim that for a system to be truly web based, each individual image should have its own <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link>. </p>
<p>

Client workstations can use local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ago/Austin=2C_C$hicago.xml">
peripheral</link>s for scanning image films into the system, printing image films from the system and interactive display of digital images. PACS workstations offer means of manipulating the images (crop, rotate, zoom, brightness, contrast and others).</p>
<p>

Modern radiology equipment and modalities feed patient images directly to the PACS in digital form. For backwards compatibility, most hospital imaging departments and radiology practices employ a film digitizer.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Integration</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="CT_viewer_Chest_Keosys.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A chest image displayed via a PACS
</caption>
</image>

A full PACS should provide a single point of access for images and their associated data (i.e. it should support multiple modalities). It should also interface with existing hospital information systems: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/1075997.xml">
Hospital information system</link> (HIS) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/2156814.xml">
Radiology Information System</link> (RIS).</p>
<p>

Interfacing between multiple systems provides a more consistent and more reliable dataset:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Less risk of entering an incorrect patient ID for a study – modalities that support DICOM worklists can retrieve identifying patient information (patient name, patient number, accession number) for upcoming cases and present that to the technologist, preventing data entry errors during acquisition. Once the acquisition is complete, the PACS can compare the embedded image data with a list of scheduled studies from RIS, and can flag a warning if the image data does not match a scheduled study.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Data saved in the PACS can be tagged with unique patient identifiers (such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/48702.xml">
social security number</link> or NHS number) obtained from HIS. Providing a robust method of merging datasets from multiple hospitals, even where the different centers use different ID systems internally.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

An interface can also improve workflow patterns:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

When a study has been reported by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/152623.xml">
radiologist</link> the PACS can mark it as read. This avoids needless double-reading. The report can be attached to the images and be viewable via a single interface.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Improved use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/1693035.xml">
online storage</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/2305699.xml">
nearline storage</link> in the image archive. The PACS can obtain lists of appointments and admissions in advance, allowing images to be pre-fetched from nearline storage (for example, <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/991603.xml">
tape libraries</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../595/2367595.xml">
DVD jukeboxes</link>) onto online disk storage (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/54695.xml">
RAID array</link>).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Recognition of the importance of integration has led a number of suppliers to develop fully integrated RIS/PACS. These may offer a number of advanced features:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dictation of reports can be integrated into a single system. The recording is automatically sent to a transcriptionist's workstation for typing, but it can also be made available for access by physicians, avoiding typing delays for urgent results, or retained in case of typing error.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Provides a single tool for quality control and audit purposes. Rejected images can be tagged, allowing later analysis (as may be required under radiation protection legislation). Workloads and turn-around time can be reported automatically for management purposes.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
DICOM Viewers</st>

<p>

There are several DICOM Viewers available both free and proprietary. Some of the DICOM Viewers include: DICOM Works, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/1749085.xml">
Osirix</link>, SureVistaVision , UniPACS, Syngo Imaging, VRRender, <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/3793613.xml">
ImageJ</link></software>
 and MicroDicom. They are designed to directly connect with any PACS to provide extended viewing technology for the workstations.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

The principles of PACS were first discussed at meetings of radiologists in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/34756.xml">
1982</link>. Various people are credited with the coinage of the term <it>PACS</it>. Cardiovascular radiologist Dr Andre Duerinckx reported in 1983 that he had first used the term in 1981.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Dr Samuel Dwyer, though, credits Dr Judith M. Prewitt for introducing the term.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Dr Harold Glass, a medical physicist working in London in the early 1990s secured UK Government funding and managed the project over many years which transformed Hammersmith Hospital in London as the first filmless hospital in the United Kingdom.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Dr Glass passed away a few months after the project came live but is credited with being one of the pioneers of PACS.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Duerinckx AJ, Pisa EJ. Filmless Picture Archiving and Communication System (PACS) in Diagnostic Radiology. Proc SPIE 1982;318;9-18. Reprinted in IEEE Computer Society Proceedings of PACS'82, order No 388.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Samuel J. Dwyer III. A personalized view of the history of PACS in the USA. In: <it>Proceedings of the SPIE</it>, "Medical Imaging 2000: PACS Design and Evaluation: Engineering and Clinical Issues", edited by G. James Blaine and Eliot L. Siegel. 2000;3980:2-9.</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Bryan S, Weatherburn GC, Watkins JR, Buxton MJ&#32;(1999).&#32;"The benefits of hospital-wide picture archiving and communication systems: a survey of clinical users of radiology services". <it>Br J Radiol</it>&#32;<b>72</b>&#32;(857): 469–78. PMID 10505012.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/34197.xml">
X-ray</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
DICOM</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/50982.xml">
Computed axial tomography</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/774446.xml">
Telemedicine</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/1129641.xml">
Electronic health record</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (EHR)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/930653.xml">
Electronic medical record</link> (EMR)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rtstudents.com/pacs/free-dicom-viewers.htm">
Teleradiology, PACS and DICOM Software</weblink> List of free PACS and DICOM software available on the web</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.psychology.nottingham.ac.uk/staff/cr1/dicom.html">
DICOM info and a list of free tools</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imagingeconomics.com/library/200505-01.asp">
History of PACS</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ms-technology.com/medical-solutions/sure-vista-vision.html">
SureVistaVision</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
