<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:26:34[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<model  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="110324560">
<header>
<title>Economic model</title>
<id>638834</id>
<revision>
<id>240452598</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-23T15:01:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Acroterion</username>
<id>1839637</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Economics models</category>
<category>Articles with weasel words</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="Islm.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A diagram of the <curve wordnetid="113867641" confidence="0.8">
<line wordnetid="113863771" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/54057.xml">
IS/LM model</link></shape>
</line>
</curve>

</caption>
</image>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/9223.xml">
economics</link>, a <b>model</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/30746.xml">
theoretical</link> construct that represents economic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/4746766.xml">
processes</link> by a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/32818.xml">
variable</link>s and a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/3729225.xml">
logic</link>al and/or quantitative relationships between them. The economic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
model</link> is a simplified framework designed to illustrate complex processes, often but not always using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/20590.xml">
mathematical techniques</link>. Frequently, economic models use structural parameters. Structural parameters are underlying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/25065.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Statistics_and_Econometrics%22])">
parameters</link> in a model or class of models.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> A model may have various parameters and those parameters may change to create various properties.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Overview</st>
<p>

In general terms, economic models have two functions: first as a simplification of and abstraction from observed data, and second as a means of selection of data based on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/175308.xml">
paradigm</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/10390.xml">
econometric</link> study. </p>
<p>

<it>Simplification</it> is particularly important for economics given the enormous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/7363.xml">
complexity</link> of economic processes.  This complexity can be attributed to the diversity of factors that determine economic activity; these factors include: individual  and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/511556.xml">
cooperative</link> decision processes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/21675.xml">
resource</link> limitations, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/558685.xml">
environment</link>al and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/18963910.xml">
geographical</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/206360.xml">
constraint</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/294833.xml">
institution</link>al and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
legal</link> requirements and purely <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
random</link> fluctuations.  Economists therefore must make a reasoned choice of which variables and which relationships between these variables are relevant and which ways of analyzing and presenting this information are useful.</p>
<p>

<it>Selection</it> is important because the nature of an economic model will often determine what facts will be looked at, and how they will be compiled. For example <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/38286.xml">
inflation</link> is a general economic concept, but to measure inflation requires a model of behavior, so that an economist can differentiate between real changes in price, and changes in price which are to be attributed to inflation.</p>
<p>

In addition to their professional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/351220.xml">
academic</link> interest, the use of models include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../074/246074.xml">
Forecasting</link> economic activity in a  way in which conclusions are logically related to assumptions;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Proposing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/210522.xml">
economic policy</link> to modify future economic activity;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Presenting reasoned arguments to politically justify economic policy at the national level, to explain and influence <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/7485.xml">
company</link> strategy at the level of the firm,  or to provide intelligent advice for household economic decisions at the level of households.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/179824.xml">
Plan</link>ning and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/227616.xml">
allocation</link>, in the case of centrally <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/7843.xml">
planned</link> economies, and on a smaller scale in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/77547.xml">
logistics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/19881.xml">
management</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/39206.xml">
business</link>es.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/11162.xml">
finance</link> predictive models have been used since the 1980s for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/29678.xml">
trading</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/63121.xml">
investment</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/63088.xml">
speculation</link>), for example emerging market <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/60737.xml">
bonds</link> were often traded based on economic models predicting the growth of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/78449.xml">
developing nation</link> issuing them. Since the 1990s many long-term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/26404.xml">
risk management</link> models have incorporated economic relationships between simulated variables in an attempt to detect high-exposure future scenarios (often through a <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/56098.xml">
Monte Carlo method</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Obviously any kind of reasoning about anything uses representations by variables and logical relationships. A model however establishes an <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/13018310.xml">
argumentative framework</link></it> for applying logic and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link> that can be independently discussed and tested and that can be applied in various instances. Policies and arguments that rely on economic models have a clear basis for soundness, namely the validity of the supporting model.</p>
<p>

Economic models in current use do not pretend to be <it>theories of everything economic</it>; any such pretensions would immediately be thwarted by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../926/5926.xml">
computation</link>al infeasibility and the paucity of theories for most types of economic behavior.  Therefore conclusions drawn from models will be approximate representations of economic facts.  However, properly constructed models can remove extraneous information and isolate useful <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/336271.xml">
approximation</link>s of key relationships.  In this way more can be understood about the relationships in question than by trying to understand the entire economic process.</p>
<p>

The details of model construction vary with type of model and its application, but a generic process can be identified. Generally any modelling process has two steps: generating a model, then checking the model for accuracy (sometimes called diagnostics). The diagnostic step is important because a model is only useful to the extent that it accurately mirrors the relationships that it purports to describe. Creating and diagnosing a model is frequently an iterative process in which the model is modified (and hopefully improved) with each iteration of diagnosis and respecification. Once a satisfactory model is found, it should be double checked by applying it to a different data set.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Types of models </st>

<p>

Broadly speaking economic models are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/47895.xml">
stochastic</link> or non-stochastic; discrete or continuous choice.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Stochastic models</b> are formulated using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/47895.xml">
stochastic process</link>es. They model economically observable values over time. Most of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/10390.xml">
econometrics</link> is based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistics</link> to formulate and test <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/14281.xml">
hypotheses</link> about these processes or estimate parameters for them. A widely used class of econometric models popularized by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/188098.xml">
Tinbergen</link></scientist>
</person>
 and later <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/1417222.xml">
Wold</link> are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/764848.xml">
autoregressive</link> models, in which the stochastic process satisfies some relation between current and past values. Examples of these are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/764848.xml">
autoregressive moving average model</link>s and related ones such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/610752.xml">
autoregressive conditional heteroskedasticity</link> (ARCH) and <link>
GARCH</link> models for the modelling of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/612440.xml">
heteroskedasticity</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Non-stochastic mathematical models</b> may be purely qualitative (for example, models involved in some aspect of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/1745670.xml">
social choice</link> theory) or quantitative (involving rationalization of financial variables, for example with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/1264398.xml">
hyperbolic coordinates</link>, and/or specific forms of <mathematical_relation wordnetid="113783581" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<function wordnetid="113783816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/185427.xml">
functional relationships</link></function>
</concept>
</idea>
</mathematical_relation>
 between variables).  In some cases economic predictions of a model merely assert the direction of movement of economic variables, and so the functional relationships are used only in a qualitative sense: for example, if the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/211295.xml">
price</link> of an item increases, then the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/920978.xml">
demand</link> for that item will decrease.  For such models, economists often use two-dimensional graphs instead of functions.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Qualitative models</b> - Although almost all economic models involve some form of mathematical or quantitative analysis, qualitative models are occasionally used. One example is qualitative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/600500.xml">
scenario planning</link> in which possible future events are played out. Another example is non-numerical decision tree analysis. Qualitative models often suffer from lack of precision.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

At a more practical level, quantitative modelling is applied to many areas of economics and several methodologies have evolved more or less independently of each other. As a result, no overall model <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/30463.xml">
taxonomy</link> is naturally available.  We can nonetheless provide a few examples which illustrate some particularly relevant points of model construction.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/2593.xml">
accounting</link> model is one based on the premise that for every <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/1698417.xml">
credit</link> there is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/273279.xml">
debit</link>. More symbolically, an accounting model expresses some principle of conservation in the form</entry>
<entry level="2" type="indent">

 algebraic sum of inflows = sinks - sources</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

This principle is certainly true for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/8983183.xml">
money</link> and it is the basis for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/49808.xml">
national income</link> accounting.  Accounting models are true by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/7830.xml">
convention</link>, that is any <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/59861.xml">
experiment</link>al failure to confirm them,  would be attributed to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/58790.xml">
fraud</link>, arithmetic error or an extraneous  injection (or destruction) of cash which we would interpret as showing the experiment was conducted improperly. 
</indent>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Optimality and constrained optimization models - Other examples of quantitative models are based on principles such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/18487619.xml">
profit</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/45479.xml">
utility</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/45479.xml">
maximization</link>.  An example of such a model is given by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../519/751519.xml">
comparative statics</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/30297.xml">
tax</link>ation on the profit-maximizing firm. The profit of a firm is given by</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="2">

<math> \pi(x,t) = x p(x) - C(x) - t x \quad</math>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

where <math>p(x)</math> is the price that a product commands in the market if it is supplied at the rate <math>x</math>, <math>xp(x)</math> is the revenue obtained from selling the product, <math>C(x)</math> is the cost of bringing the product to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/3736784.xml">
market</link> at the rate <math>x</math>, and <math>t</math> is the tax that the firm must pay per unit of the product sold.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

The profit maximization assumption states that a firm will produce at the output rate <it>x</it> if that rate maximizes the firm's profit. Using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/50416.xml">
differential calculus</link> we can obtain conditions on <it>x</it> under which this holds. The first order maximization condition for <it>x</it> is
</indent>

<indent level="2">

<math> \frac{\partial  \pi(x,t)}{\partial x} =\frac{\partial  (x p(x) - C(x))}{\partial x} -t= 0 </math>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Regarding <it>x</it> is an implicitly defined function of <it>t</it> by this equation (see  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/581005.xml">
implicit function theorem</link>), one concludes that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/7921.xml">
derivative</link> of <it>x</it> with respect to <it>t</it> has the same sign as 
</indent>

<indent level="2">

<math> \frac{\partial^2  (x p(x) - C(x))}{\partial^2 x}={\partial^2\pi(x,t)\over \partial x^2},</math>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

which is negative if the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/742388.xml">
second order condition</link>s for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/298420.xml">
local maximum</link> are satisfied. 
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Thus the profit maximization model predicts something about the effect of taxation on output, namely that output decreases with increased taxation. If the predictions of the model fail, we conclude that the profit maximization hypothesis was false; this should lead to alternate theories of the firm, for example based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/70400.xml">
bounded rationality</link>.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

Borrowing a notion apparently first used in economics by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/216669.xml">
Paul Samuelson</link></scientist>
</person>
, this model of taxation and the predicted dependency of output on the tax rate, illustrates an <it>operationally meaningful theorem</it>; that is one which requires some economically meaningful assumption which is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/11283.xml">
falsifiable</link> under certain conditions.
</indent>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Aggregate models. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../820/18820.xml">
Macroeconomics</link> needs to deal with aggregate quantities such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/763707.xml">
output</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/1490155.xml">
price level</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/163115.xml">
interest rate</link> and so on. Now real output is actually a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/32533.xml">
vector</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/580039.xml">
goods</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/181586.xml">
service</link>s, such as cars, passenger airplanes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link>s, food items, secretarial services, home repair services etc. Similarly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/211295.xml">
price</link> is the vector of individual prices of goods and services. Models in which the vector nature of the quantities is maintained are used in practice, for example <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/408819.xml">
Leontief</link></scientist>
</person>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/1036651.xml">
input-output model</link>s are of this kind.  However, for the most part, these models are computationally much harder to deal with and harder to use as tools for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/371299.xml">
qualitative analysis</link>. For this reason, macroeconomic models usually lump together different variables into a single quantity such as <it>output</it> or <it>price</it>. Moreover, quantitative relationships between these aggregate variables are often parts of important macroeconomic theories.  This process of aggregation and functional dependency between various aggregates usually is interpreted statistically and validated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/10390.xml">
econometrics</link>. For instance, one ingredient of the <political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/17326.xml">
Keynesian model</link></political_orientation>
 is a functional relationship between consumption and national income: C = C(<it>Y</it>).  This relationship plays an important role in Keynesian analysis.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Pitfalls </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Restrictive, unrealistic assumptions </st>

<p>

Economic models can be such powerful tools in understanding some economic relationships, that it is easy to ignore their limitations. Take, for example, perfect-competition <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/227572.xml">
equilibrium</link> market models.  These models are based on perfect information, an identical product, and inability of individual agents to significantly affect total output or demand. When these assumptions are met, the resulting static equilibrium conditions will be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/45468.xml">
Pareto-optimal</link>.  One can interpret optimality as an ideal situation in which each agent can do no better.  When these assumptions fail, for instance under imperfect information or product differentiation, some contend that the model cannot be used to draw these conclusion. Others, such as <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/19640.xml">
Milton Friedman</link></scientist>
</person>
, contend that if the model is successful in prediction, then it is useful, even if the simplifying assumptions are not strictly true. He points out that all models, even in the physical sciences, are simplifications which ignore certain factors. For example, the model for acceleration of falling objects in Physics ignores air resistance, but is nevertheless useful in ballistics.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Model assumptions include not only those that can be expressed as predicates on model parameters but others with more qualitative or asymptotic form.  This basic concept is however surprisingly often ignored.  A common example is the application of <political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/17326.xml">
Keynesian economics</link></political_orientation>
 to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/12229.xml">
government</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/132645.xml">
fiscal policy</link>.  The simple Keynesian model postulates (among other things) that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/763707.xml">
output</link> is a function of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/353023.xml">
aggregate demand</link>.  Government spending is one component of aggregate demand, so Keynes' model is often applied to conclude that increasing government spending will have the same positive effect on output as private <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/63121.xml">
investment</link> (see the article by Paul Samuelson, <it>Simple Mathematics of Income Determination</it>).  This application of the model is correct in the short run, but the model does not take into account the results of this policy change, which may affect <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/168918.xml">
business cycle</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/146738.xml">
interest</link> and tax rates, private investment, and other factors which could in the long run either reduce or increase output as a result of the change in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/132645.xml">
fiscal policy</link>.  This example highlights one of the difficulties of applying economic models, which is correctly inferring short term and long term effects of economic policy.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Omitted details </st>



<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section contains </b>, vague phrasing that often accompanies  or  information. Such statements should be . 
<it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

A great danger inherent in the simplification required to fit the entire economy into a model is omitting critical elements. Some economists believe that making the model as simple as possible is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/752.xml">
art form</link>, but the details left out are often contentious. For instance:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Market models often exclude <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/61193.xml">
externalities</link> such as unpunished <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollution</link>. Such models are the basis for many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/1866009.xml">
environmentalist</link> attacks on mainstream <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/467180.xml">
economists</link>. It is said that if the social costs of externalities were included in the models their conclusions would be very different, and models are often accused of leaving out these terms because of economist's pro-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/11826.xml">
free market</link> bias.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In turn, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/47763.xml">
environmental economics</link> has been accused of omitting key financial considerations from its models. For example the returns to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/27743.xml">
solar power</link> investments are sometimes modelled without a <link>
discount factor</link>, so that the present <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/45479.xml">
utility</link> of solar energy delivered in a century's time is precisely equal to gas-power station energy today.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Financial models can be oversimplified by relying on historically unprecedented <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/3162.xml">
arbitrage</link>-free markets, probably underestimating the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/16848.xml">
chance of crises</link>, and under-pricing or under-planning for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/25617.xml">
risk</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Models of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/570984.xml">
consumption</link> either assume that humans are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/177052.xml">
immortal</link> or that teenagers plan their life around an optimal retirement supported by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/1539973.xml">
next generation</link>. (These conclusions are probably harmless, except possibly to the credibility of the modelling profession.)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Are economic models falsifiable? </st>

<p>

The sharp distinction between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/11283.xml">
falsifiable</link> economic models and those that are not is by no means a universally accepted one.  Indeed one can argue that the <it>ceteris paribus</it> (all else being equal) qualification that accompanies any claim in economics is nothing more than an all-purpose escape clause (See <it>N. de Marchi and M. Blaug</it>.)  The all else being equal claim allows holding all variables constant except the few that the model is attempting to reason about.  This allows the separation and clarification of the specific relationship.  However, in reality all else is never equal, so economic models are guaranteed to not be perfect.  The goal of the model is that the isolated and simplified relationship has some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/1983931.xml">
predictive power</link> that can be tested.  Ignoring the fact that the <it>ceteris paribus</it> assumption is being made is another big failure often made when a model is applied.  At the minimum an attempt must be made to look at the various factors that may not be equal and take those into account.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>

<p>

One of the major problems addressed by economic models has been understanding economic growth.  An early attempt to provide a technique to approach this came from the French <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/45440.xml">
physiocrat</link>ic school in the Eighteenth century.  Among these economists, <link>
François Quesnay</link> should be noted, particularly for his development and use of tables he called <it><link>
Tableaux économiques</link></it>.  These tables have in fact been interpreted in more modern terminology as a Leontiev model, see the Phillips reference below.</p>
<p>

All through the 18th century (that is, well before the founding of modern political economy, conventionally marked by Adam Smith's 1776 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/725991.xml">
Wealth of Nations</link>) simple probabilistic models were used to understand the economics of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/15176.xml">
insurance</link>. This was a natural extrapolation of the theory of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/11921.xml">
gambling</link>, and played an important role both in the development of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/23542.xml">
probability theory</link> itself and in the development of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/189373.xml">
actuarial science</link>. Many of the giants of 18th century <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link> contributed to this field. Around 1730, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/57327.xml">
De Moivre</link> addressed some of these problems in the 3rd edition of the <link>
Doctrine of Chances</link>. Even earlier (1709), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/1151030.xml">
Nicolas Bernoulli</link> studies problems related to savings and interest in the <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/17554277.xml">
Ars Conjectandi</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
. In 1730, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<analyst wordnetid="109790482" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/46784.xml">
Daniel Bernoulli</link></mathematician>
</writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</analyst>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
 studied "moral probability" in his book <link>
Mensura Sortis</link>, where he introduced what would today be called "logarithmic utility of money" and applied it to gambling and insurance problems, including a solution of the paradoxical <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<contradiction wordnetid="107206887" confidence="0.8">
<paradox wordnetid="106724559" confidence="0.8">
<falsehood wordnetid="106756407" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/466277.xml">
Saint Petersburg problem</link></falsehood>
</paradox>
</contradiction>
</message>
</statement>
. All of these developments were summarized by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/344783.xml">
Laplace</link> in his <link>
Analytical Theory of Probability</link> (1812). Clearly, by the time <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/8470.xml">
David Ricardo</link></person>
 came along he had a lot of well-established math to draw from.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Tests of macroeconomic predictions </st>

<p>

In the late 1980s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/334063.xml">
a research institute</link> compared the twelve top macroeconomic models available at the time. They asked the designers of these models what would happen to the economy under a variety of quantitatively specified shocks, and compared the diversity in the answers (allowing the models to control for all the variability in the real world; this was a test of model vs. model, not a test against the actual outcome). Although the designers were allowed to simplify the world and start from a stable, known baseline (e.g <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/19287594.xml">
NAIRU</link> unemployment) the various models gave dramatically different answers. For instance, in calculating the impact of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/297032.xml">
monetary</link> loosening on output some models estimated a 3% change in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/12594.xml">
GDP</link> after one year, and one gave almost no change, with the rest spread between.</p>
<p>

Partly as a result of such experiments, modern central bankers no longer have as much confidence that it is possible to 'fine-tune' the economy as they had in the 1960s and early 1970s. Modern policy makers tend to use a less activist approach, explicitly because they lack confidence that their models will actually predict where the economy is going, or the effect of any shock upon it. The new, more humble, approach sees danger in dramatic policy changes based on model predictions, because of several practical and theoretical limitations in current macroeconomic models; in addition to the theoretical pitfalls, (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/638834.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Pitfalls%22])">
listed above</link>) some problems specific to aggregate modelling are:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Limitations in model construction caused by difficulties in understanding the underlying mechanisms of the real economy. (Hence the profusion of separate models.)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The law of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/97517.xml">
Unintended consequence</link>s, on elements of the real economy not yet included in the model.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/1481533.xml">
time lag</link> in both receiving data and the reaction of economic variables to policy makers attempts to 'steer' them (mostly through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/297032.xml">
monetary</link> policy) in the direction that central bankers want them to move. <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/19640.xml">
Milton Friedman</link></scientist>
</person>
 has vigorously argued that these lags are so long and unpredictably variable that effective management of the macroeconomy is impossible.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The difficulty in correctly specifying all of the parameters (through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/10390.xml">
econometric</link> measurements) even if the structural model and data were perfect.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The fact that all the model's relationships and coefficients are stochastic, so that the error term becomes very large quickly, and the available snapshot of the input parameters is already out of date.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Modern economic models incorporate the reaction of the public &amp; market to the policy maker's actions (through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/11924.xml">
game theory</link>), and this feedback is included in modern models (following the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/65753.xml">
rational expectations</link> revolution and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/101175.xml">
Robert Lucas, Jr.</link></scientist>
</person>
's critique of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/362565.xml">
optimal control</link> concept of precise macroeconomic management). If the response to the decision maker's actions (and their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1494164.xml">
credibility</link>) must be included in the model then it becomes much harder to influence some of the variables simulated.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Comparison with models in other sciences </st>

<p>

The comparison of economic forecasting to weather forecasting using (much more sophisticated) simulations shows the present state of economic modelling in an unflattering light. Although <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/19904.xml">
meteorological</link> simulations are capable of only about two days reliability, this is all they claim to predict; the medium and long term macroeconomic models presently available often have similar predictive power to 1930s weather forecasters looking five days ahead.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/62903.xml">
Complex systems</link> specialist and mathematician <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/9470237.xml">
David Orrell</link></mathematician>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 wrote on this issue and explained that the weather, human health and economics use similar methods of prediction (mathematical models). Their systems - the atmosphere, the human body and the economy - also have similar levels of complexity. He found that forecasts fail because the models suffer from two problems : i- they cannot capture the full detail of the underlying system, so rely on approximate equations; ii- they are sensitive to small changes in the exact form of these equations. This is because complex systems like the economy or the climate consist of a delicate balance of opposing forces, so a slight imbalance in their representation has big effects. Thus, predictions of things like economic recessions are still highly inaccurate, despite the use of enormous models running on fast computers. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.postpythagorean.com/FAQ.html">
http://www.postpythagorean.com/FAQ.html</weblink></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 The effects of deterministic chaos on economic models </st>

<p>

Economic and meteorological simulations may share a fundamental limit to their predictive powers: <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/6295.xml">
chaos</link></concept>
</idea>
. Although the modern mathematical work on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/6295.xml">
chaotic systems</link> began in the 1970s the danger of chaos had been identified and defined in <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/466281.xml">
Econometrica</link></publication>
</periodical>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it> as early as 1958:
<indent level="1">

"Good theorising consists to a large extent in avoiding assumptions....(with the property that)....a small change in what is posited will seriously affect the conclusions." 
</indent>
:(<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<economist wordnetid="110043643" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/1253178.xml">
William Baumol</link></scholar>
</historian>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</economist>
</associate>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</social_scientist>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</peer>
, Econometrica, 26 <it>see</it>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iemss.org/iemss2004/pdf/keynotes/Keynote_OXLEY.pdf">
<it>Economics on the Edge of Chaos''</it></weblink>).</p>
<p>

It is straightforward to design an economic models susceptible to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/4024.xml">
butterfly effect</link>s of initial-condition sensitivity. See, for instance: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sp.uconn.edu/~ages/files/NL_Chaos_and_%20Macro%20-%20429%20Essay.pdf">
Review of chaotic models from 2003</weblink> </p>
<p>

However, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/10390.xml">
econometric</link> research program to identify which variables are chaotic (if any) has largely concluded that aggregate macroeconomic variables probably do not behave chaotically. This would mean that refinements to the models could ultimately produce reliable long-term forecasts. However the validity of this conclusion has generated two challenges: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In 2004 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/1916846.xml">
Philip Mirowski</link></scholar>
</historian>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</person>
</philosopher>
</physical_entity>
 challenged this view and those who hold it, saying that chaos in economics is suffering from a biased "crusade" against it by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/21634.xml">
neo-classical economics</link> in order to preserve their mathematical models.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The variables in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/11162.xml">
finance</link> may well be subject to chaos. Also in 2004, the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/32242.xml">
University of Canterbury</link></university>
 study <it>Economics on the Edge of Chaos</it> concludes that after noise is removed from <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<index wordnetid="106639674" confidence="0.8">
<fact wordnetid="106636259" confidence="0.8">
<stock_index wordnetid="106641924" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/170992.xml">
S&amp;P 500</link></stock_index>
</fact>
</index>
</information>
</message>
 returns, evidence of deterministic chaos <it>is</it> found.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

More recently, chaos (or the butterfly effect) has been identified as less significant than previously thought to explain prediction errors. Rather, the predictive power of economics and meteorology would mostly be limited by the models themselves and the nature of their underlying systems (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/638834.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Comparison+with+models+in+other+sciences%22])">
Comparison with models in other sciences</link> above).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 The critique of hubris in planning </st>

<p>

A key strand of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/11826.xml">
free market</link> economic thinking is that the market's "invisible hand" guides an economy to prosperity more efficiently than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/7843.xml">
central planning</link> using an economic model. One reason, emphasized by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/11646.xml">
Friedrich Hayek</link></philosopher>
</person>
, is the claim that many of the true forces shaping the economy can never be captured in a single plan. This is an argument which cannot be made through a conventional (mathematical) economic model, because it says that there are critical systemic-elements that will always be omitted from any top-down analysis of the economy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Examples of economic models</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/113515.xml">
Black-Scholes</link> option pricing model</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<motion wordnetid="100331950" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/1675534.xml">
Heckscher-Ohlin model</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</motion>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</action>
</change>
</event>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/15761387.xml">
International Futures</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <curve wordnetid="113867641" confidence="0.8">
<line wordnetid="113863771" confidence="0.8">
<shape wordnetid="100027807" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/54057.xml">
IS/LM model</link></shape>
</line>
</curve>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/76393.xml">
Participatory Economics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/17326.xml">
Keynesian</link></political_orientation>
 cross</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/408819.xml">
Leontief</link></scientist>
</person>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/1036651.xml">
input-output model</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/418604.xml">
World3</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/9223.xml">
Economics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/5016758.xml">
Economic methodology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/1420447.xml">
Computational Economics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/10941831.xml">
Agent-Based Computational Economics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/897740.xml">
Model (macroeconomics)</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/90075.xml">
List of economics topics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
List of economic models</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
List of financial models</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
List of statistical models</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
List of other socioeconomic models</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Moffatt, Mike. (2008) <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/38553.xml">
About.com</link></web_site>
 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://economics.about.com/od/economicsglossary/g/structuralp.htm">
Structural Parameters</weblink></it> Economics Glossary; Terms Beginning with S. Accessed June 19, 2008.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Moffatt, Mike. (2008) <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/38553.xml">
About.com</link></web_site>
 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://economics.about.com/od/economicsglossary/g/structure.htm">
Structure</weblink></it> Economics Glossary; Terms Beginning with S. Accessed June 19, 2008.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Milton Friedman, "The Methodology of Positive Economics," 1953.</entry>
<entry id="4"><p>

 <cite style="font-style:normal"><person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/11646.xml">
Hayek, Friedrich</link></philosopher>
</person>
&#32;(September, 1945).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/pss/1809376">
The Use of Knowledge in Society</weblink>". <it>American Economic Review</it>&#32;<b>35</b>&#32;(4): 519–530. Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-19</link>.</cite>&nbsp;

</p>
</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<economist wordnetid="110043643" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/1253178.xml">
William Baumol</link></scholar>
</historian>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</economist>
</associate>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</social_scientist>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</peer>
 and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<governor wordnetid="110140314" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/1229508.xml">
Alan Blinder</link></associate>
</scholar>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</colleague>
</governor>
</intellectual>
</leader>
</person>
</politician>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
, <it>Economics: Principles and Policy</it> 2 ed., Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc. 1982.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bruce Caldwell <it>Beyond Positivism</it>. Revised edition, Routledge, 1991.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 R. Frigg and S. Hartmann, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/models-science/">
Models in Science</weblink>. Entry in the <it>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</it>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 R. Holcombe, <it>Economic Models and Methodology</it>, Greenwood Press, 1989. Defines model by analogy with maps, an idea borrowed from Baumol and Blinder. Discusses deduction within models, and logical derivation of one model from another.  Chapter 9 compares the neoclassical school and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/1030.xml">
Austrian school</link>, in particular in relation to falsifiability.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/702199.xml">
Oskar Lange</link> <it>The Scope and Method of Economics</it>, Review of Economic Studies, 1945. One of the earliest studies on methodology of economics, analysing the postulate of rationality.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 N. B. de Marchi and M. Blaug., <it>Appraising Economic Theories</it>, Edward Elgar,  1991. A series of essays and papers analysing questions about how (and whether) models and theories in economics are empirically verified and the current status of positivism in economics.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<economist wordnetid="110043643" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/1535580.xml">
Michio Morishima</link></scholar>
</historian>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</alumnus>
</economist>
</associate>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</social_scientist>
</colleague>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</peer>
, <it>The Economic Theory of Modern Society</it>, Cambridge University Press, 1976. A thorough discussion of many quantitative models used in modern economic theory. Also a careful discussion of aggregation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/1203466.xml">
A.W. Phillips</link>, <it>The Tableau Économique of a Simple Leontiev Model</it>, Quarterly Journal of Economics, 69, 1955 pp 137-44.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/216669.xml">
Paul A. Samuelson</link>, <it><principle wordnetid="105913538" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<social_science wordnetid="106143154" confidence="0.8">
<knowledge_domain wordnetid="105999266" confidence="0.8">
<generalization wordnetid="105913275" confidence="0.8">
<economics wordnetid="106149484" confidence="0.8">
<discipline wordnetid="105996646" confidence="0.8">
<science wordnetid="105999797" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/6643997.xml">
Foundations of Economic Analysis</link></science>
</discipline>
</economics>
</generalization>
</knowledge_domain>
</social_science>
</idea>
</principle>
</it>, 1947, Enclarged ed., 1983, Harvard University Press.  This is a classic book carefully discussing comparative statics in microeconomics, though some dynamics is studied as well as some macroeconomic theory. This should not be confused with Samuelson's popular textbook.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Paul A. Samuelson, "The Simple Mathematics of Income Determination," in: <it>Income, Employment and Public Policy; essays in honor of Alvin Hansen</it>, W. W. Norton, 1948</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/188098.xml">
Jan Tinbergen</link></scientist>
</person>
, <it>Statistical Testing of Business Cycle Theories</it>, League of Nations, 1939</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Vivian Walsh (1987). "models and theory," , v. 3, pp.  482-83.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/454834.xml">
H. Wold</link>, <it>A Study in the Analysis of Stationary Time Series</it>, Almqvist and Wicksell, 1938</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 H.  Wold and L. Jureen, <it>Demand Analysis A Study in Econometrics</it>, 1953</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/9470237.xml">
David Orrell</link></mathematician>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <it>Apollo's Arrow : The Science of Prediction and the Future of Everything</it>, Harper Collins Canada, 2007</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sims.berkeley.edu/~hal/Papers/how.pdf">
H. Varian <it>How to build a model in your spare time''</it></weblink> The author makes several unexpected suggestions: Look for a model in the real world, not in journals.  Look at the literature later, not sooner.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Elmer G. Wiens: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.egwald.ca/macroeconomics/keynesian.php">
 Classical &amp; Keynesian AD-AS Model</weblink> - An on-line, interactive model of the Canadian Economy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  IFs Economic Sub-Model <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ifs.du.edu/ifs">
http://www.ifs.du.edu/ifs</weblink>:  Online Global Model</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</model>
</article>
