<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:16:45[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<leader  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109623038">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<header>
<title>Rand Wilson</title>
<id>6501351</id>
<revision>
<id>226642649</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-19T15:28:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ground Zero</username>
<id>232133</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Year of birth missing (living people)</category>
<category>American labor leaders</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Rand Wilson</b> has worked as a union organizer and labor communicator in the United States since the 1980s.<p>

Wilson started in the labor movement as a member of the Oil, Chemical and Atomic Workers Union (OCAW). While a member of Local 8-366, he led several organizing drives, was chief steward, and served on his local union's executive board.</p>
<p>

For most of the 1980s, Rand Wilson worked as an organizer for the <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/591645.xml">
Communications Workers of America</link></union>
. In 1989 he helped coordinate solidarity efforts in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/1645518.xml">
Massachusetts</link></country>
 during a successful three-month strike by 60,000 telephone workers against health care benefit cost shifting.</p>
<p>

The strike victory helped spur the formation of <link>
Massachusetts Jobs with Justice</link>. As the founding director in the early 1990s, Wilson spearheaded efforts in Massachusetts to support legislation for universal health care and against international trade deals like the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/22050.xml">
North American Free Trade Agreement</link></organization>
 (NAFTA) and the <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/33873.xml">
World Trade Organization</link></organization>
 (WTO).</p>
<p>

After returning to Boston, Rand Wilson served as Communications Director for <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/483275.xml">
Service Employees International Union</link></union>
 (SEIU) Local 285 (later renamed Local 2020 and now part of District 1199), assisting health care workers in dozens of nursing home and hospital contract campaigns. While working for SEIU, he helped revive the Jobs with Justice Health Care Action Committee - pushing for coordinated actions by union members to link their struggles against cost shifting with the broader movement for health care reform.</p>
<p>

In 2005 Wilson worked for the <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/178766.xml">
AFL-CIO</link></union>
's Office of Investment on a campaign to oppose the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/183895.xml">
Bush Administration's</link> plan to privatize <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/48728.xml">
Social Security</link>. Wilson organized actions across the country exposing the conflict of interest created by the financial services industry's support for privatizing Social Security while it managed trillions of dollars in worker's retirement assets.</p>
<p>

Wilson recently ran as the first (and only) candidate for a new Massachusetts Working Families Party where he received almost 20 percent of the vote for State Auditor in a successful bid to gain the party statewide ballot status.</p>
<p>

Rand Wilson has written and lectured widely about contract campaigns, strikes, health care reform, and strategies to build workers' political power. He is president of the Center for Labor Education and Research, and on the board of directors of the ICA Group, the Local Enterprise Assistance Fund (LEAF), and the Center for the Study of Public Policy.</p>
<p>

Currently, Wilson is organizing director at IUE-CWA Local 201, a union of <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/12730.xml">
General Electric</link></company>
 and other manufacturing workers in Lynn, Massachusetts. He lives in Somerville, Massachusetts.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.randwilson.org">
Wilson for Working Families</weblink> - Rand Wilson Campaign Web site</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.workingfamiliesparty.org/">
Working Families Party</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</causal_agent>
</leader>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
