<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:17:47[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<book  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="106410904">
<header>
<title>Network Analysis and Ethnographic Problems</title>
<id>6540763</id>
<revision>
<id>150688805</id>
<timestamp>2007-08-12T01:58:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bearcat</username>
<id>24902</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Sociology books</category>
<category>Political science books</category>
<category>Anthropology books</category>
<category>2004 books</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="200px" src="Fig10.2.jpg" type="frame">
<caption>

3-D Graphic of <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/6593988.xml">
Relinking Marriages</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 among Nomad Kin, color-coded by generations. Nodes are couples not individuals, so where downward lines meet it is a relative that is married. This is called relinking. The relinking structure and dynamic is a key to ethnographic understanding. Names of some of the lineage ancestors are shown at the top.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b><it>Network Analysis and Ethnographic Problems: Process Models of a Turkish Nomad Clan</it></b><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> is an anthropological and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/7363.xml">
complexity</link> science book by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/28854.xml">
social anthropologist</link>s <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/6044579.xml">
Douglas R. White</link></person>
</anthropologist>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/3993559.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Faculty%22])">
University of California, Irvine</link>, and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uni-koeln.de/phil-fak/voelkerkunde/alt/institut/johansen.htm">
Ulla Johansen</weblink> of the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/42754.xml">
University of Cologne</link></university>
. It is considered an important publication in anthropology<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> and the political science of Central Asia <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. </p>
<p>

The breakthrough is to code and portray the data of a longitudinal ethnography of a given people as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/37438.xml">
complex interactive system</link>, in this case from an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/2792751.xml">
ethnogenesis</link> in the late 18th century in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/11125639.xml">
Turkey</link> to the present date, based on the detailed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/12025.xml">
genealogies</link> and chronicles recorded in fieldwork carried out between 1956 and 2004 recorded by ethnographer <link>
Ulla Johansen</link>. The analysis of these data provides for an account of social dynamics relevant to many parts of the <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/19323.xml">
Middle East</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Synopsis </st>
<p>

The basis for the book is the complete <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/169269.xml">
genealogical network</link> for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/89908.xml">
nomad community</link>, its history, and its migrants and migrations. These form a relational web not just for description but for analysis of social dynamics. The picture that emerges is one of a complexly scalable social system that expands through reproduction, kinship alliances, and fissions, and overcomes internal conflicts and those with neighbors along routes of migration. These networks constitute a generative demographic engine for health, a potential for large sibling groups, and for extensive cooperation within and between these groups constructed through reciprocal ties of marriage. The book is lavishly illustrated with photos, network diagrams, and analytical tables showing how very simple principles of cohesion and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/185529.xml">
scalable</link> alliances between families are able to organize this social system through a series of shifting articulations at a variety of social and spatial levels. Thus continual reshuffling is capabable of moving, and does move individuals and groups in the society through a variety of transformations in relation to life problems, social problems, technological problems, and the transmission and enrichment of a highly complex cultural system. The book shows how these adjust dynamically to changing social conditions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Pedagogy </st>
<p>

This book makes major methodological, substantive, and theoretical advances for the disciplines of ethnography, social anthropology, and social history; and marks some new understandings of several of the many forms of social complexity. No previous work has been able to connect dynamical historic and social network analysis with changes that can be visualized and analyzed through time in terms of structure, interaction, and social change, using the actual concrete data of the ethnography, person by person, relation by relation, group by group, change by change. This is a level of integration hitherto never achieved in anthropology. It builds on a methodology for analysis of structural changes that was developed by the lead author. <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/6044579.xml">
Douglas R. White</link></person>
</anthropologist>
 had previously developed new concepts and measures for the study of social cohesion, starting first with cohesion in kinship ties (structural endogamy) and then progressing to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/6524226.xml">
structural cohesion</link> generally, which has since become one of the many major tools of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1039587.xml">
network analysis</link>. </p>
<p>

If the book combines complexity theory following lines of thought at the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/511751.xml">
Santa Fe Institute</link></association>
</institute>
 with a contribution to understanding of Middle Eastern social structure, it is through combining network visualization and analysis with the study of the dynamics of marriage choices. The book expands the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/735289.xml">
theory of social practice</link> to show how changes in the structure of a society's kinship network affect the development of social cohesion over time. By rigorously examining the genealogical networks of the Turkish nomad clan and associated clans that are studied, the authors explore how changes in network cohesion are indicative of key processes of social change. This approach alters in fundamental ways the anthropological concepts of social structure, organizational dynamics, social cohesion, marriage strategies, as well as the study of community politics within the dynamics of ongoing personal interaction.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0739118927">
Network Analysis and Ethnographic Problems: Process Models of a Turkish Nomad Clan</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lexingtonbooks.com/Catalog/SingleBook.shtml?command=Search&amp;db=^DB/CATALOG.db&amp;eqSKUdata=0739118927">
Lexington Books</weblink> 2006 paper 2004 hardback, <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/6044579.xml">
Douglas R. White</link></person>
</anthropologist>
 and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uni-koeln.de/phil-fak/voelkerkunde/alt/institut/johansen.htm">
Ulla C. Johansen</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://repositories.cdlib.org/imbs/socdyn/wp/wp5/">
Collaborative Long-Term Ethnography and Longitudinal Social Analysis of a Nomadic Clan In Southeastern Turkey</weblink>, 2002 Ulla Johansen and Douglas R. White, Chapter 4, pp. 81-99, in <it>Chronicling Cultures: Long-Term Field Research in Anthropology</it>, edited by Robert van Kemper and Anya Royce. AltaMira Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://repositories.cdlib.org/hcs/DRW2002A">
The Navigability of Strong Ties: Small Worlds, Tie Strength and Network Topology</weblink>, in Networks and Complexity Special Issue, <it>Complexity</it> 8(1):72-81. 2002. Douglas R. White and Michael Houseman.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References and footnotes </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 2006 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/238674.xml">
paperback</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/14919.xml">
ISBN</link> 0-7391-1892-7 and 2004 in hardcover</entry>
<entry id="2">
Reviewer <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/pw/Int.J.MiddleEastStud.38Wolfe2006Review.pdf">
Alvin Wolfe</weblink> writes it "...could be the most important book in anthropology in fifty years" </entry>
<entry id="3">
Amazon reviewer <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0739108964">
T. Martin Doyle</weblink> writes 'The White and Johansen approach to "network analysis" provides the framework for unparalleled examination of sub-national political behavior. This tool for nonlinear dynamic analysis encourages detailed assessment of highly decentralized self-organizing local governance structures otherwise unavailable through state level scrutiny. Those involved in the study of comparative politics will come to appreciate the meticulous findings exacted through use of this "network" construction. Additionally, examining the interaction of inter-governmental organizations, non-governmental organizations, or transnational advocacy networks with state government infrastructure becomes far more precise, compliments of White and Johansen.'</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/turks/TurkishNomadGallery.html">
Turkish Aydinli Nomads Study Photos</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/images/TurkishNomads/">
color figures from Network Analysis and Ethnographic Problems</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://intersci.ss.uci.edu/wiki/index.php/Network_Analysis_and_Ethnographic_Problems">
Book Contents</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/turks/NetworkAnalysisandEthnographicProblems-WikipediaFormatBookReview.mht">
http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/turks/NetworkAnalysisandEthnographicProblems-WikipediaFormatBookReview.mht</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</book>
</article>
