<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:28:35[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Roofnet</title>
<id>6542678</id>
<revision>
<id>240893337</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-25T13:20:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Tinucherian</username>
<id>1951636</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Articles to be expanded since February 2007</category>
<category>IEEE 802.11</category>
<category>All articles to be expanded</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Roofnet&amp;action=edit">
improve this article or section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(February 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Roofnet</b> is an experimental <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/14739.xml">
802.11</link>b/g <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/912687.xml">
mesh network</link> currently under development at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/434274.xml">
Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory</link> of the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/18879.xml">
Massachusetts Institute of Technology</link></university>
 (MIT). Part of the research project at MIT includes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/41320.xml">
link-level</link> measurements of 802.11, finding high-throughput routes in the face of lossy links, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/2321017.xml">
link adaptation</link>, and developing new protocols which take advantage of radio’s unique properties (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/12965568.xml">
ExOR</link>). The software developed for this project is available for free as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link>. 
<sec>
<st>
Routing Protocol</st>

<p>

The routing protocol is called SrcRR.  There are two broadcasts used with the protocol.  The first is periodic broadcasts used to determine a metric called ETX.  These public broadcasts measure the probability that a packet between two nodes in radio contact reaches its destination.  The second broadcast type is used to build up routing tables.  A node 0 will broadcast that it wants to find a route to D.  Then each node that receives the broadcast will add its id to the route and forward the packet on.  When node D receives a packet, it will reply back along the route that was found for that packet.  Then node 0 can use this information to determine the best route using the ETX metrics and the route information returned from its query.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Media Access and Forwarding</st>

<p>

One media access and forwarding protocol tested with RoofNet was <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/12965568.xml">
ExOR</link>.  ExOR simulates some advantages of multicasted data networks by using conventional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/14739.xml">
802.11</link> digital radios operated in broadcast modes.</p>
<p>

The source radio uses routing data to establish a list of radios that could help reach the destination radio.  The list is ordered so that radios closer to the destination are nearer to the head of the list.  The destination is at the head of the list.  The list is compactly stored in each packet.  </p>
<p>

Each packet also includes a list that shows the progress of each packet through the list of radios.  This list has one entry per packet.  Each entry is the number of radio that is closest to the destination and has retransmitted that packet.  The source inistially sets this list all to the source radio's number.</p>
<p>

Then, the source broadcasts a batch of packets.  </p>
<p>

Radios not on a packet's list discard the packet.  </p>
<p>

Radios on the list save the packet.  They update their list of radios transmitting each packet.  But they wait a calibrated time before they retransmit any packet. The time is less if they are closer to the destination.  The time is a probabilistic estimate of the time to retransmit the packets that will be retransmitted by radios closer to the destination.</p>
<p>

If a radio receives a packet transmitted from a radio that is closer to the destination, the farther radio throws away that packet, and never retransmits it. It also updates its list of packet progress.</p>
<p>

As they work backwards toward the source, the retransmissions propagate the batch of packets' progress information back to the source radio.</p>
<p>

At the end, a few packets of each batch sent by the source may never reach the destination.  It sends these on by the most reliable route, using conventional routing.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/8339721.xml">
B.A.T.M.A.N.</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/12327314.xml">
Meraki</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 - Company commercializing roofnet by producing hardware and software.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csail.mit.edu/index.php">
MIT Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory </weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pdos.csail.mit.edu/roofnet/doku.php">
MIT Roofnet project page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pdos.csail.mit.edu/roofnet/doku.php?id=design">
MIT Roofnet Design page</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
