<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:23:25[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Learnable Evolution Model</title>
<id>6548718</id>
<revision>
<id>170929613</id>
<timestamp>2007-11-12T09:07:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>JarlaxleArtemis</username>
<id>161122</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Learnable Evolution Model</b> (LEM) is a novel, non-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/8411.xml">
Darwinian</link> methodology for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/268020.xml">
evolutionary computation</link> that employs <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link> to guide the generation of new individuals (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/1556808.xml">
candidate problem solution</link>s). Unlike standard, Darwinian-type evolutionary computation methods that use random or semi-random operators for generating new individuals (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/555213.xml">
mutation</link>s and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/158005.xml">
recombination</link>s), LEM employs hypothesis generation and instantiation operators.<p>

The <link>
hypothesis generation</link> operator applies a machine learning program to induce descriptions that distinguish between high-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/187849.xml">
fitness</link> and low-fitness individuals in each consecutive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/22949.xml">
population</link>.  Such descriptions delineate areas in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/389707.xml">
search space</link> that most likely contain the desirable solutions. Subsequently the instantiation operator samples these areas to create new individuals.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Research Groups </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mli.gmu.edu">
Machine Learning and Inference Laboratory at George Mason University</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Selected References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wojtusiak, J. and Michalski, R.S., "The LEM3 Implementation of Learnable Evolution Model and Its Testing on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/5759.xml">
Complex Function</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/52033.xml">
Optimization</link> Problems," <it>Proceedings of Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference</it>, GECCO 2006, Seattle, WA, July 8-12, 2006. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wojtusiak, J., "Initial Study on Handling Constrained Optimization Problems in Learnable Evolution Model," <it>Proceedings of The Graduate Student Workshop at Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference</it>, GECCO 2006, Seattle, WA, July 8-12, 2006. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jourdan, L., Corne, D., Savic, D. and Walters, G., "Preliminary Investigation of the ‘Learnable Evolution Model’ for Faster/Better Multiobjective Water Systems Design," <it>Proceedings of The Third Int. Conference on Evolutionary Multi-Criterion Optimization</it>, EMO’05, 2005. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Domanski, P. A., Yashar, D., Kaufman, K. and Michalski, R. S., "An Optimized Design of Finned-Tube Evaporators Using the Learnable Evolution Model," <it>International Journal of Heating, Ventilating, Air-Conditioning and Refrigerating Research</it>, 10, 201-211, April, 2004. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kaufman K. and Michalski R.S., "Applying Learnable Evolution Model to Heat Exchanger Design," <it>Proceedings of the Seventeenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-2000) and Twelfth Annual Conference on Innovative Applications of Artificial Intelligence (IAAI-2000)</it>, Austin, TX, pp. 1014-1019, 2000. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cervone G., Michalski R.S., Kaufman K. A., "Experimental Validations of the Learnable Evolution Model," <it>2000 Congress on Evolutionary Computation</it>, San Diego CA, pp 1064-1071, July 2000. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Michalski R.S., "LEARNABLE EVOLUTION MODEL Evolutionary Processes Guided by Machine Learning," <it>Machine Learning</it> , 38, pp 9-40, 2000. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Michalski, R.S., "Learnable Evolution: Combining Symbolic and Evolutionary Learning," <it>Proceedings of the Fourth International Workshop on <link>
Multistrategy</link> Learning</it> (MSL'98), Desenzano del Garda, Italy, pp. 14-20, June 11-13, 1998.</entry>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
