<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:25:49[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108435388">
<group  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100031264">
<network  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108434259">
<header>
<title>Social-circles network model</title>
<id>6554098</id>
<revision>
<id>218127590</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-09T07:59:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Markles</username>
<id>195596</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Social networks</category>
<category>Networks</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The generative model of feedback networks <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> studied by <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/6044579.xml">
White</link></person>
</anthropologist>
, <link>
Kejžar</link>, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/3592142.xml">
Tsallis</link></scientist>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/2115447.xml">
Farmer</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
, or <b>social-circles network model</b>, defines a class of random graphs generated by simple processes that are common to edge formation and feedback loops in social circles. This class is distinct from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/1457254.xml">
small-world network</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/227155.xml">
scale-free network</link> models in <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1039587.xml">
network analysis</link></network>
</group>
</method>
</know-how>
</system>
</technique>
 but also captures many of the characteristics of real-world <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link>s. The implications of this type of model are carried further in Thurner, Kyriakopoulos and Tsallis, 2007, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;id=PLEEE8000076000003036111000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;gifs=yes">
Unified Model for Network Dynamics Exhibiting Nonextensive Statistics</weblink> Phys. Rev. E 76, 036111 (2007) (8 pages).
<sec>
<st>
 Highlights </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A feedback network is one where active nodes or agents send tokens or communications through their network to help locate potential partners for new ties.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 When a previously unconnected partner is located given constraints of distance a new tie is formed, creating a feedback loop.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Failing to locate a partner within the network, the active node engaged in partner selection recruits a new partner from outside the existing network and forms a tie.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Like many real-world networks, feedback networks modeled by this process evolve large networks with cohesive ties (social circles). In this way, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/8337525.xml">
small worlds</link> with cohesive subgroups and relatively short distances may be generated, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/227155.xml">
scale-free networks</link> may be generated, or a variety of other network topologies may be generated.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The generative feedback network model simulates these processes and their network outcomes as new nodes and edges are added to an initial network.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Only three parameters are used to govern network formation in this probabilistic generative model. These govern levels of node activity, distance decay in how soon network traversal fails to find a partner, and the extent to which local hubs are used in network traversal.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The model provides an explanation for how hubs are formed in networks, how well-traveled edges are formed, how cycles and <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/6524226.xml">
cohesion</link></network>
</group>
</system>
 are formed, and how other features of real-world networks may  result from different combinations of three basic network parameters.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Empirical network data can be fitted to the parameters of the general model.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Rationale </st>

<p>

A social-circles network models by a graph-generating process the formation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/6524226.xml">
cohesion</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/28244.xml">
dispersion</link> in connected networks as a function of acitvity and feedback. The process begins with a single node. The next events in the evolution of the network are that: (1) a node is chosen randomly (proportional to the number of current links of each node raised to power <it>alpha</it>) to emit a feedback token, (2) the token attempts to travel by a non-circular path through the current network by choosing its next neighbor randomly, proportional to the number of edges of the neighbor minus the node already traversed, raised to power <it>gamma</it>; (3) the token travels through the network until it reaches a random distance <it>d</it>,  proportional to 1 over <it>d</it> raised to a power <it>beta</it>, and  failing that, the source node that originated the token gains an edge to a node that is added to the network (dispersion of edges), but if the token succeeds in reaching a target at distance d, a new 'feedback' edge is added between the source and the target.</p>

<p>

The three parameters of the model are <it>alpha, beta, gamma.</it> The notion of 'feedback' in this model is very general and may involve intentionality on the part of source nodes as agents <it>looking for a partner</it> or simply nodes in a network emitting signals randomly that contain information that may enable the source and target to lock into a feedback relation, represented by the formation of a new edge. Whether searches or signals have the capacity to locate a target in an existing network is affected by the current size and topology of the network, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/6786225.xml">
distance decay</link> (<it>beta</it>) in traversal, and the intelligence (<it>gamma</it>) exhibited in the method of search. Failure to locate targets results in a generic substitution (new node and an edge connecting to it), like looking in the phone book for a doctor rather that asking for a referral.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The generative model </st>
<p>

At each step three stochastic processes are run. A node <it>i</it> is selected, a distance <it>d</it> (an imaginary number of steps to get to a searched node <it>j</it>) is chosen, and the search path of distance <it>d</it> is generated.
<indent level="1">

A node <it>i</it> is selected with a probability proportional to its degree
</indent>
::: <math>p_\alpha(i)=\frac{[deg(i)]^\alpha}{\sum_{m=1}^N [deg(m)]^\alpha}</math></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

A distance <it>d</it> is chosen with the probability
</indent>
::: <math>p_\beta(d)=\frac{d^{-\beta}}{\sum_{m=1}^\infty m^{-\beta}}</math>
<indent level="1">

where <it>d</it> represents the number of steps necessary to create a new cycle. If the number of steps cannot be concluded, a new node with a new edge is added.
</indent>

<indent level="1">

A search path of length <it>d</it> is generated. At a given moment a node <it>r</it> is a current node on the path. The next node is selected among the neighbors of <it>r</it> that were not yet visited. The probability of selecting a certain neighbor (say <it>l</it>) is proportional to their 'unused degree'. The 'unused degree', <it>u(l)</it>, is considered a degree of the node from which all the already visited neighbors are subtracted. The probability is given by
</indent>
::: <math>p_\gamma(l)=\frac {[1+u(l)^{\gamma}]} {\sum_{m=1}^N[1+u(m)^{\gamma}]}</math></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Results </st>

<p>

Social-circles network simulation with varying model parameters results in a variety of networks whose topology in terms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Density%22])">
network density</link>, <invariant wordnetid="105850432" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="105849040" confidence="0.8">
<feature wordnetid="105849789" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/1457636.xml">
clustering</link></feature>
</property>
</concept>
</idea>
</invariant>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/6524226.xml">
cohesion</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/2129782.xml">
degree distribution</link> varies in ways that resemble the variety of real-world networks. Study of the degree distributions and edge-traversal frequencies shows fit to the statistical distributions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/3573165.xml">
Tsallis entropy</link>, familiar to <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/3592142.xml">
nonextensive physics</link></scientist>
. This provides a baseline test of the model to real-world networks, one that contrasts with that of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/227155.xml">
scale-free network</link>, for which one baseline test is whether the degree distribution follows a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/24522.xml">
power law</link>.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/3573165.xml">
Tsallis entropy</link> distribution asymptotes to a power law for large degree but bends toward the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../906/45906.xml">
exponential distribution</link> in the lower part of the degree distribution.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Degree Distributions</st>

<p>

Parameters <math>\alpha, \beta, \gamma</math> in the social circles model are shown to generate networks with degree distributions that fit a general family of curves that combine power-law with exponential tendencies. The probability density function for degree <math>k</math> in this family, with parameters <math>\delta, \kappa, q </math>, and <math>p_0</math>, is given by:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>p(k)=p_0k^\delta e_q^{-k/\kappa}</math>   			
</indent>

where the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/4120642.xml">
<it>q</it>-exponential</link> function <math>e^{-x}_q</math> with parameter <math>q</math> is defined as</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>e^{-x}_q = (1+(1-q)x)^{1/(1-q)}   	(e_1^x = e^x) </math>
</indent>

The <it>q</it>-exponential function arises naturally as the solution of the equation <math>dk/dt=k^q</math>, which is <math>k=e^{-x}_q = [1+(1-q) a t]^{1/(1-q)}</math>. For the case where <math>q=1</math>, <math>k=e^{at}</math>. The function is related to the stationary solution of a nonlinear Fokker-Planck equation known as the <it>porous medium equation.</it> It describes correlated diffusion known as <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<equation wordnetid="106669864" confidence="0.8">
<mathematical_statement wordnetid="106732169" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/849543.xml">
Darcy's law</link></mathematical_statement>
</equation>
</message>
</statement>
, the scientific basis of fluid permeability used in the earth sciences. This is a constitutive equation that describes the flow of a fluid through a porous medium as formulated by Henry Darcy to describe results of experiments on the flow of water through beds of sand (see references [2,3,4]). In the density function, <math>p_0</math> coincides with <math>p(0)</math> if and only if <math>\delta=0</math>; <math>\kappa</math> is a characteristic degree. In a generalization of the water-flow analogy, the density function for degree would reflect a <it>q</it>-exponential component for which <it>q</it>=1 is omnidirectional flow, and as <it>q</it> increases there is initially a steep low-dimensional gradient that changes to flat and high dimensional as <it>q</it> grows to infinity. The other component corresponding to <math>p_0k^\delta</math> would reflect a characteristic magnitude of flow also affected by <it>q</it>. A loose analogy is to traders whose activities etch the routes of their commercial networks, amplified by gradient intensities and the heterogeneity of terrain.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Retrofitting</st>

<p>

The parameters <math>\delta,  \kappa,  q</math>, and <math>p_0</math> of the fitted models, which may also be applied to the degree distributions of empirical networks, were found to closely approximate 1-to-1 functions of the generating parameters, as given by the approximations
<indent level="1">

 <math>\delta = -1.5 \alpha  </math>
</indent>
: <math>q = 1+.64\alpha + 6\alpha\gamma(\beta-1)^2</math>
<indent level="1">

 <math>\kappa = 235\gamma(1-\alpha)(\beta-1)</math>
</indent>
: <math>p_0 = 2 + \alpha/4  - \beta  -1.3\gamma</math></p>
<p>

These allow approximate solutions for the generating parameters that fit observed empirical degree of networks:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>\alpha = - 2\delta/3</math>
</indent>
: <math>\beta = 3/2 + p_o/2 + q/9</math>
<indent level="1">

 <math>\gamma = 5|(q/k)-.5|^{1/2} + 5p0+ 11q/k</math>
</indent>

The last of these approximations (for <math>\gamma</math>) is the least accurate (more precise estimates may yet be found). The authors of the paper have provided a more exact optimal matching between the four parameters fitted from empirical degree distributions of actual networks (assuming they follow the <math>q</math>-exponential) in spreadsheet form.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  This makes the social circles model a prime candidate for accounting for the degree distributions of empirical networks in terms of a generative network model with the three parameters <math>\alpha, \beta, \gamma</math>: activity bias of agents, distance decay, and navigability of the network. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/140806.xml">
Maximum likelihood</link> estimates (MLE) of the four <math>\delta,  \kappa,  q</math>, and <math>p_0</math> parameters for empirical networks and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/2474821.xml">
goodness-of-fit</link> tests can establish the statistical relationship between model and data. Shalizi (2007) provides an <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cscs.umich.edu/~crshalizi/research/tsallis-MLE/">
MLE</weblink> procedure for the Pareto II or <it>q</it>-exponential parameter fitting.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Replication and extensions</st>
<p>

Kejžar in 2007 replicated these results by simulating feedback networks up to N=5000 nodes, extended the findings to:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Degree distributions for directed edges (indegree, outdetree). These were similar to those of the undirected model, especially for <math>\gamma=0</math> but differed toward higher q when <math>\gamma \rightarrow 1</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Densification. Growth of edges relative to nodes is initially linear, but soon changees to approximate a slightly superlinear power-law (for <math>\alpha=0, \beta=1.6,  \gamma=0.5, e\approx 0.08+n^{1.08}</math>, for example, where <it>e</it> are edge numbers and <it>n</it> numbers of node). Even with 1 billion nodes, however, this is scarcely more than an average degree of 5. Up to 6000 nodes, the average degree is less than two. For large degrees, however, the degree distribution approaches a power law with an exponent <math>1/(q-1) -\delta</math>. Densification is a natural consequence.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Average shortest paths. If <it>l</it> is the average shortest path and <it>n</it> the number of nodes, <it>l</it> shrinks with <it>n</it> if <math>\gamma=1</math> but rises if <math>\gamma=0</math> and a weighted sum of <math>\alpha, \gamma</math> determines the crossover (low <math>\alpha</math>, high <math>\gamma</math> has the most rapid shrinkage). In every case there tends to be a "shrinking limit" as <math>n \to \infty</math></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Variance of shortest paths. Most of the shortest paths between nodes approach the "shrinking limit."</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In short, the generative feedback model has realistic and nicely continuous characteristics, and these simulations show no evidence that the density function for degree <it>k</it> is not the correct function.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;id=PLEEE8000073000001016119000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;gifs=yes">
"Generative Model for Feedback Networks"</weblink> in <it>Physical Review E</it>, 016119 2006 (8 pages), <anthropologist wordnetid="109796323" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/6044579.xml">
Douglas R. White</link></person>
</anthropologist>
, <link>
Nataša Kejžar</link>, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/3592142.xml">
Constantino Tsallis</link></scientist>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<physicist wordnetid="110428004" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/2115447.xml">
J. Doyne Farmer</link></educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</physicist>
</physical_entity>
, [h3ttp://intersci.ss.uci.edu/wiki/index.php/Scott_D._White Scott D. White]. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.santafe.edu/research/publications/wpabstract/200508034|Final">
paper in pdf as SFI working paper</weblink>. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.europhysicsnews.com/us/html/EPNsommaire36.html">
Reviewed 2005 in Europhysicsnews 36(6):218-220</weblink> by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.europhysicsnews.com/full/36/article12.pdf">
Stefan Thurner</weblink>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/els/03784371/1995/00000222/00000001/art00211">
"Non-extensive statistical mechanics and generalized Fokker-Planck equation." 1995. A. R. Plastino and A. Plastino</weblink>. Physica A 222, 347-354</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;id=JMAPAQ000046000012123303000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;gifs=yes">
“Nonlinear diffusion equation, Tsallis formalism and exact solutions.’ 2005 P. C. Assis, Jr, L. R. da Silva, E. K. Lenzi, L. C. Malacarne, and R. S. Mendes</weblink> Journal of Mathematical Physics 46, 123303 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scitation.aip.org/getpdf/servlet/GetPDFServlet?filetype=pdf&amp;id=JMAPAQ000046000012123303000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;prog=normal">
pdf</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springerlink.com/content/90e0lbqhycnwleke/">
"Nonextensive statistical mechanics: A brief introduction", 2004. C. Tsallis and E. Brigatti.</weblink> Continuum Mechanics and Thermodynamics 16(3):223-235. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springerlink.com/content/90e0lbqhycnwleke/fulltext.pdf">
pdf</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

Nataša Kejžar. 2007. Evolution of Networks. Doctoral thesis. Department of Mathematics. University of Ljubljana.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/pub/paj/1250-0-2-0.paj">
Simulated data in a Pajek Network Project *.paj file for 1250 nodes paramaters 0-2-0</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/EBMsim/500-0-1d9-0x002.htm">
Walk-through of a network simulation, edge by edge with the same parameters</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.insna.org">
http://www.insna.org</weblink> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/7433852.xml">
INSNA</link> International Network for Social Network Analysis -- professional association of network analysts</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Cited by Wei, Wang, Qiuping, Nivanen, Lauret et al (2006-01-12) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.citebase.org/abstract?id=oai%3AarXiv.org%3Aphysics%2F0601091">
How to fit the degree distribution of the air network?</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="2">
Cited by de Meneses, Marcela, da Cunha, Sharon, and Soares et al (2006-01-12) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.citebase.org/abstract?id=oai%3AarXiv.org%3Acond-mat%2F0601273">
Preferential attachment scale-free growth model with random fitness</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
 White et al. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/0/parameter_values1.html">
Retrofitting the Generative Feedback Network (Social Circles) Models </weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
Shalizi, Cosma. 2007. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cscs.umich.edu/~crshalizi/research/tsallis-MLE/">
Maximum Likelihood Estimation for <it>q</it>-Exponential (Tsallis) Distributions.</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</network>
</group>
</system>
</article>
