<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:30:25[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Web traffic</title>
<id>665789</id>
<revision>
<id>244366355</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T13:26:16Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>BOTijo</username>
<id>3729068</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>World Wide Web</category>
<category>Computer network analysis</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="clear: right; margin-bottom: .5em; float: right; padding: .5em 0 .8em 1.4em; background: none; width: auto;" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>
__TOC__</col>
</row>
</table>

<b>Web traffic</b> is the amount of data sent and received by visitors to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/33898.xml">
web site</link>.  It is a large portion of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/856845.xml">
Internet traffic</link>.  This is determined by the number of visitors and the number of pages they visit.  Sites monitor the incoming and outgoing traffic to see which parts or pages of their site are popular and if there are any apparent trends, such as one specific page being viewed mostly by people in a particular country.  There are many ways to monitor this traffic and the gathered data is used to help structure sites, highlight security problems or indicate a potential lack of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/15612827.xml">
bandwidth</link> &mdash; not all web traffic is welcome.<p>

Some companies offer advertising schemes that, in return for increased web traffic (visitors), pay for screen space on the site.  Sites also often aim to increase their web traffic through inclusion on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link>s and through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/187946.xml">
Search engine optimization</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Measuring web traffic </st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="150px" src="WebTrafficGraph.gif">
<caption>

Example graph of <b>web traffic</b> at Wikipedia in December 2004
</caption>
</image>

Web traffic is measured to see the popularity of web sites and individual pages or sections within a site.</p>
<p>

Web traffic can be analysed by viewing the traffic statistics found in the web server log file, an automatically-generated list of all the pages served.  A <it>hit</it> is generated when any file is served.  The page itself is considered a file, but images are also files, thus a page with 5 images could generate 6 hits (the 5 images and the page itself).  A <it>page view</it> is generated when a visitor requests any page within the web site &ndash; a visitor will always generate at least one page view (the main page) but could generate many more.</p>
<p>

Tracking applications external to the web site can record traffic by inserting a small piece of <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/13191.xml">
HTML</link></format>
 code in every page of the web site.</p>
<p>

Web traffic is also sometimes measured by <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<analyzer wordnetid="102708711" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
packet sniffing</link></instrument>
</analyzer>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 and thus gaining random samples of traffic data from which to extrapolate information about web traffic as a whole across total <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link> usage.</p>
<p>

The following types of information are often collated when monitoring web traffic:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The number of visitors.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The average number of page views per visitor &ndash; a high number would indicate that the average visitors go deep inside the site, possibly because they like it or find it useful.  Conversely, it could indicate an inability to find desired information easily.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Average visit duration &ndash; the total length of a user's visit</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Average page duration &ndash; how long a page is viewed for</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Domain classes &ndash; all levels of the IP Addressing information required to deliver Webpages and content. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Busy times &ndash; the most popular viewing time of the site would show when would be the best time to do promotional campaigns and when would be the most ideal to perform maintenance</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Most requested pages &ndash; the most popular pages</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Most requested entry pages &ndash; the entry page is the first page viewed by a visitor and shows which are the pages most attracting visitors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Most requested exit pages &ndash; the most requested exit pages could help find bad pages, broken links or the exit pages may have a popular external link</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Top paths &ndash; a path is the sequence of pages viewed by visitors from entry to exit, with the top paths identifying the way most customers go through the site</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Referrers; The host can track the (apparent) source of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/49547.xml">
links</link> and determine which sites are generating the most traffic for a particular page.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Web sites like <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/264303.xml">
Alexa Internet</link></company>
 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://alexa.com">
http://alexa.com</weblink> produce traffic rankings and statistics based on those people who access the sites while using the Alexa toolbar.  The difficulty with this is that it's not looking at the complete traffic picture for a site.  Large sites usually hire the services of companies like Nielsen NetRatings <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nielsen-netratings.com/">
http://www.nielsen-netratings.com/</weblink>, but their reports are available only by subscription.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Controlling web traffic</st>
<p>

The amount of traffic seen by a web site is a measure of its popularity.  By analysing the statistics of visitors it is possible to see shortcomings of the site and look to improve those areas.  It is also possible to increase (or, in some cases decrease) the popularity of a site and the number of people that visit it.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Limiting access</st>
<p>

It is sometimes important to protect some parts of a site by password, allowing only authorized people to visit particular sections or pages.</p>
<p>

Some site administrators have chosen to block their page to specific traffic, such as by geographic location.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/519775.xml">
re-election campaign</link> site for <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
U.S.</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 <post wordnetid="108624385" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/24113.xml">
President</link></post>
 <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/3414021.xml">
George W. Bush</link></businessperson>
</person>
</president>
 (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.georgewbush.com">
GeorgeWBush.com</weblink>) was blocked to all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
internet</link> users outside of the U.S. on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/22333.xml">
25 October</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link> after a reported attack on the site.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

It is also possible to limit access to a web server both based on the number of connections and by the bandwidth expended by each connection. On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/2581.xml">
Apache HTTP server</link>s, this is accomplished by the <it>limitipconn</it> module and others.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Increase web site traffic</st>
<p>

Web traffic can be increased by placement of a site in <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<engine wordnetid="103287733" confidence="0.8">
<motor wordnetid="103789946" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engines</link></machine>
</device>
</motor>
</engine>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 and purchase of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/2861.xml">
advertising</link>, including bulk e-mail, <link>
pop-up ads</link>, and in-page advertisements. Web traffic can also be increased by purchasing non-internet based advertising.</p>
<p>

If a web page is not listed in the first pages of any search, the odds of someone finding it diminishes greatly (especially if there is other competition on the first page). Very few people go past the first page, and the percentage that go to subsequent pages is substantially lower.  Consequently, getting proper placement on search engines is as important as the web site itself. </p>
<p>

There are a number of other things you can do to increase your web traffic, including but not limited to building link popularity, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/714684.xml">
webrings</link>, offering free e-books or articles and classified advertisements.</p>
<p>

Of the above mentioned items, perhaps the easiest one to do is building link popularity. This can be accomplished by writing e-mails to sites similar to yours and asking if they would link to your site. The second way of increasing your web traffic is writing to e-zines or to free article sites. There are many sites which will accept your written material, the catch is that you are giving it away for free. The benefit, however, is that you get to include a link to your site in the article, meaning every time someone clicks on your link, it brings free traffic to your site. Pixel ads can bring traffic to your site but usually will not get you a targeted audience.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Organic traffic</st>
<p>

Web traffic which comes from unpaid listing at search engines or directories is commonly known as "organic" traffic.  Organic traffic can be generated or increased by including the web site in directories (such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo!</link></company>
 and <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<subsidiary_company wordnetid="108003935" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18949501.xml">
DMOZ</link></institution>
</subsidiary_company>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</property>
</undertaking>
</company>
</event>
</possession>
</work>
), search engines (such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/93521.xml">
Inktomi</link>), guides (such as yellow pages and restaurant guides) and award sites.</p>
<p>

In most cases the best way to increase web traffic is to register it with the major search engines. Just registering does not guarantee traffic,  as search engines work by "crawling" registered web sites.  These crawling programs (crawlers) are also known as "spiders" or "robots".  Crawlers start at the registered home page, and usually follow the hyperlinks it finds, to get to pages inside the web site (internal links).  Crawlers start gathering information about those pages and storing it and indexing it in the search engine database.  In every case, they index the page <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/32277.xml">
URL</link> and the page title.  In most cases they also index the web page header (meta tag) and a certain amount of the text of the page. Then, when a search engine user looks for a particular word or phrase, the search engine looks into the database and produces the results, usually sorted by relevance according to the search engine algorithms.</p>
<p>

Usually, the top organic result gets most of the clicks from web users.  According to some studies , the top result gets between 5% and 10% of the clicks.  Each subsequent result gets between 30% and 60% of the clicks of the previous one.  This indicates that it is important to appear in the top results.  There are some companies which specialize in search engine marketing.  However, it is becoming common for webmasters to get approached by "boiler-room" companies with no real knowledge of how to get results.  As opposed to pay-per-click, search engine marketing is usually paid monthly or annually, and most search engine companies cannot promise specific results for what is paid to them.</p>
<p>

Because of the huge amount of information available on the web, crawlers might take days, weeks or months to complete review and index all the pages they find.  Google, for example, as of the end of 2004 had indexed over eight billion pages.  Even having hundreds or thousands of servers working on the spidering of pages, a complete reindexing takes its time.  That is why some pages recently updated in certain web sites are not immediately found when doing searches on search engines.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Natural Traffic </st>

<p>

Natural website traffic is also in some cases attributed to the name of the website, particularly when the website uses a primary dictionary term as it's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/39878.xml">
domain name</link>. For instance many women instinctively know they can go to "Shoes.com"  and shop for shoes online. They do not need to go to a search engine to find that name into their browser. In the past many valuable names were simply undeveloped and you might see "under construction" or "free parking" listed, however today, many high profile <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/39878.xml">
domain names</link> are in use, and therefore increase the web surfer's belief they can go directly to a site based on its name. Another example is "Porn.com" which sold for 9.5 million dollars due to the ability to save on search engines and likelihood to attract visitors by name. Another example might be "BankRate.com" in which a bank rate might be found immediately. Other examples include cultural oddities such as "BavarianDancers.com." As all domains that represent a topic are likely registered, a visitor can find what they are looking for by typing in the topic.</p>
<p>

For that reason the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/39878.xml">
domain name</link> market is considered to be a very big factor in not only obtaining traffic, but especially in creating a name that is easily remembered.  eLoans, is easily recalled, as will be the new domain name purchased by CNN "iReport." It is possible that millions of people will log on to report news if that brand becomes a household name.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Paid advertising</st>
<p>

In return for a small payment many larger companies choose to advertise their sites on other popular sites.  This <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/1618177.xml">
e-marketing</link> usually takes the form of:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/34044.xml">
Banner advertising</link>: Banner impressions are sold by the thousands, and referred to as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/806538.xml">
Cost Per Impression</link> (CPM).  As of 2004, prices range from $1/CPM for a run-of-network to about $50/CPM or more for specialized targeted runs.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1027207.xml">
Pay per click</link>s: Advertisers "buy" keywords or keyphrases by bidding on them against other advertisers.  These Pay-per-click providers sell space on the respective search engines and sites with which they are aligned. Position is largely determined by a combination of the amount each advertiser is willing to pay and the click driving performance of the advertiser's creative - though advanced providers such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/1092923.xml">
Google</link></company>
 have started taking into account other factors such as the quality of the ad's destination and the ability of the site to satisfy visitors. Google sells paid advertisement through its <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/879962.xml">
AdWords</link></institution>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</company>
</event>
</work>
 and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/736238.xml">
AdSense</link></software>
 systems, which place sponsored links on search pages.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/44133.xml">
Overture</link>, now owned by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/188213.xml">
Yahoo!</link></company>
, is one of the most popular pay-per-click advertising venues.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

As users got used to seeing banners, some companies chose to make the advertisements more intrusive &ndash; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/466320.xml">
pop-up ad</link>s became particularly popular to attract attention.  However, most people consider pop-ups a nuisance and several software companies offer free pop-up blockers. Microsoft included a pop-up blocker in Service Pack 2 of <version wordnetid="107173585" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/33879.xml">
Windows XP</link></version>
.</p>

</ss2>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Traffic overload</st>
<p>

Too much web traffic can dramatically slow down or even prevent all access to a web site.  This is caused by more file requests going to the server than it can handle and may be an intentional attack on the site or simply caused by over-popularity.  Large scale web sites with numerous servers can often cope with the traffic required and it is more likely that smaller services are affected by traffic overload.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Denial of service attacks</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/39776.xml">
Denial-of-service attack</link>s (DoS attacks) have forced web sites to close after a malicious attack, flooding the site with more requests than it could cope with.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/18994196.xml">
Viruses</link> have also been used to co-ordinate large scale distributed denial-of-service attacks.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sudden popularity</st>
<p>

A sudden burst of publicity may accidentally cause a web traffic overload.  A news item in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/19641.xml">
media</link>, a quickly propagating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
email</link>, or a link from a popular site may cause such a boost in visitors (sometimes called <operation wordnetid="100955060" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/18933122.xml">
Slashdot effect</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</event>
</operation>
) that overwhelms the site.</p>
<p>

Web sites have been forced to close after an unexpected mass increase of traffic, particularly those run by an individual leasing the bandwidth from an ISP or hosting site.  Some sites backed by large companies running their own servers have also been caught out by the problems of overpopularity.  When first announced, the <link>
Vision of Britain Through Time</link> site, containing information taken from the 1901 <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
UK</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/6889.xml">
census</link>, was advertised on numerous television programmes and causing such interest that the site had to be taken offline until different arrangements were made to cope with the traffic.  The site was hosted by a project at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/64395.xml">
University of Edinburgh</link></university>
 and they had not foreseen the amount of bandwidth and the server load that would be required.  Ironically, by the time the site was able to cope with the traffic both the interest and the free advertisements of the site had greatly slowed, giving them excess capacity.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/187946.xml">
Search engine optimization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/264303.xml">
Alexa Internet</link></company>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Malacinski, Andrei; Dominick, Scott &amp; Hartrick, Tom (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/19346.xml">
1 March</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../551/34551.xml">
2001</link>). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/web/library/wa-mwt1/">
"Measuring Web traffic"</weblink> at <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/18622259.xml">
IBM</link></company>
 &ndash; retrieved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
1 January</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Machlis, Sharon (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/15798.xml">
17 June</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/35502.xml">
2002</link>). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.computerworld.com/managementtopics/ebusiness/story/0,10801,71989,00.html">
"Measuring Web Site Traffic"</weblink> at ComputerWorld.com &ndash; retrieved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/15787.xml">
1 January</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ward, Mark (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/19352.xml">
5 May</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thisdayonline.com/archive/2003/05/08/20030508e-b09.html">
"The Dangers of Having a Good Idea"</weblink> &ndash; A <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/2995343.stm">
BBC News</weblink> look at the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/484030.xml">
freelance</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/50100.xml">
journalist</link> Glenn Fleishman after his site was linked to from <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/285425.xml">
MacCentral</link></web_site>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</product>
</magazine>
</publication>
</medium>
</machine>
</press>
</print_media>
</creation>
</computer>
</work>
 &ndash; retrieved <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/15863.xml">
7 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link></entry>
</list>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Miller, Rich&#32;(<link>
2004-10-26</link>).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.netcraft.com/archives/2004/10/26/bush_campaign_web_site_rejects_nonus_visitors.html">
Bush Campaign Web Site Rejects Non-US Visitors</weblink>".&nbsp;
</entry>
</reflist>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alexa.com">
Alexa.com</weblink> &ndash; a website that tracks webtraffic.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boxesandarrows.com/archives/web_traffic_analytics_and_user_experience.php">
"Web Traffic Analytics and User Experience"</weblink> by Fran Diamond at boxesandarrows.com]</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wsiwebedge.com/building_an_online_presence.aspx">
Increase Web Traffic</weblink>, By Building an Online Presence - Article</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
