<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:30:40[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Oil paint</title>
<id>668958</id>
<revision>
<id>240929710</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-25T16:28:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ossmann</username>
<id>6395239</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Oils</category>
<category>Paints</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="250px" src="Jan_Vermeer_van_Delft_001.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<it>View of Delft</it> in oil paint, by <artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/43311.xml">
Johannes Vermeer</link></artist>
.
</caption>
</image>

<b>Oil paint</b> is a type of slow-drying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/23776.xml">
paint</link> consisting of small <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/49598.xml">
pigment</link> particles suspended in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/752713.xml">
drying oil</link>.  Oil paints have been used in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/9316.xml">
England</link></country>
 as early as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/34633.xml">
13th century</link> for simple decoration,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> but were not widely adopted for artistic purposes until the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/34567.xml">
15th century</link>.  The most common modern application of oil paint is domestic, where its hard-wearing properties and luminous colors make it desirable for both interior and exterior use.  Its slow-drying properties have recently been used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/7218055.xml">
paint-on-glass animation</link>.
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

The slow-drying properties of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
organic oils</link> were commonly known to early painters. However, the difficulty in acquiring and working the materials meant that they were rarely used. As public preference for realism increased, however, the quick-drying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/31053.xml">
tempera</link> paints became insufficient. <creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<art wordnetid="102743547" confidence="0.8">
<painting wordnetid="103876519" confidence="0.8">
<graphic_art wordnetid="103453809" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/3834277.xml">
Flemish artists</link></graphic_art>
</painting>
</art>
</artifact>
</creation>
 combined tempera and oil painting during the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../370/19554370.xml">
1400s</link>, but by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/19515597.xml">
1600s</link> easel painting in pure oils was common, using much the same techniques and materials found today.</p>
<p>

The oldest known extant oil paintings date from 650 A.D., found in 2008 in caves in Afghanistan's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/457220.xml">
Bamiyan Valley</link>, "using perhaps walnut and poppy seed drying oils."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Though the ancient Mediterranean civilizations of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/66540.xml">
Greece</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/521555.xml">
Rome</link>, and <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<empire wordnetid="108557482" confidence="0.8">
<domain wordnetid="108556491" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/874.xml">
Egypt</link></country>
</district>
</domain>
</empire>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 were familiar with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/192331.xml">
vegetable oils</link>, there is little evidence to indicate their use as <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/5145183.xml">
media</link></material>
</medium>
</part>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</substance>
 in painting. Indeed, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/295711.xml">
linseed oil</link> was long rejected as a medium because of its tendency to dry slowly, darken, and crack, unlike <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/60840.xml">
mastic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/58256.xml">
wax</link>. </p>
<p>

Greek writers such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/2685439.xml">
Aetius Amidenus</link> recorded recipes involving the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/752713.xml">
oils for drying</link>, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/1208431.xml">
walnut</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/1208398.xml">
poppy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/324632.xml">
hempseed</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/5576632.xml">
pine nut</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/172190.xml">
castor</link>, and linseed. When thickened, the oils became resinous and could be used as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/214645.xml">
varnish</link> to seal and protect paintings from water. Additionally, when yellow <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/49598.xml">
pigment</link> was added to oil, it could be spread over <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/3835508.xml">
tin foil</link> as a less expensive alternative to <link>
gold leaf</link>. Early Christian <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/419369.xml">
monks</link> maintained these records and used the techniques in their own artworks. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../835/1103835.xml">
Theophilus Presbyter</link>, a 12th century German monk, recommended linseed oil from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../335/3335.xml">
Baltic Sea</link> area, but advocated against the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link> due to its excessively long drying time. </p>
<p>

As early as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/34633.xml">
13th century</link>, oil was used to add details to tempera paintings. In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../625/34625.xml">
14th century</link>, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<painter wordnetid="110391653" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../806/1423806.xml">
Cennino Cennini</link></creator>
</artist>
</painter>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 presented a painting technique utilizing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/31053.xml">
tempera painting</link> covered by light layers of oil.</p>
<p>

The modern technique of oil painting was created circa <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/35204.xml">
1410</link> by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/46381.xml">
Jan van Eyck</link>. Though van Eyck was not the first artist to use oil paint, he was the first who is known to have produced a stable siccative oil mixture which could be used to bind <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/19053.xml">
mineral</link> pigments. Van Eyck’s mixture probably consisted of piled glass, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/1170793.xml">
calcined</link> bones, and mineral pigments boiled in linseed oil until reaching a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/18963754.xml">
viscous</link> state.</p>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<painter wordnetid="110391653" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/254609.xml">
Antonello da Messina</link></creator>
</artist>
</painter>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 later introduced another improvement to oil paint: he added <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/1939348.xml">
litharge</link>, or lead (II) oxide, to the mixture. The new mixture had a honey-like consistency and increased siccative properties. This medium was known as <it>oglio cotto</it>—"cooked oil."</p>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/18079.xml">
Leonardo da Vinci</link></artist>
</person>
 improved the technique even further by cooking the mixture at a low temperature and adding 5 to 10% <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/43536.xml">
beeswax</link>, which prevented dramatic darkening of the finished paint. <artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/140709.xml">
Giorgione</link></artist>
, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/154239.xml">
Titian</link></artist>
</person>
, and <artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/338821.xml">
Tintoretto</link></artist>
 each slightly altered this recipe for their own purposes.</p>
<p>

During his stay in Italy, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/102161.xml">
Rubens</link></artist>
</person>
 studied the Italian oil paint mixture. He later made his own improvement, using walnut oil warmed with litharge and adding mastic dissolved in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/151183.xml">
turpentine</link>.</p>
<p>

Since that time, experiments to improve paint and coatings have been conducted with other oils. Today, oils from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/8011852.xml">
bladderpod</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/61880.xml">
sandmat</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/2396376.xml">
ironweed</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/73348.xml">
calendula</link> plants are used to increase resistance or to decrease drying time.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Paint In Tubes</st>

<p>

The paint tube was invented in 1841 and artists were liberated from the studio. Artists no longer needed to grind each pigment by hand and carefully mix the binding oil in the proper proportions. Paints were made in bulk and sold in tin tubes with a cap. The cap could be replaced and the paints preserved for future use. The manufactured paints had a balanced consistency that the artist could thin with turpentine if he chose. Artists were no longer bound to the studio.  They could work outside in direct sunlight, misty fog, at dawn or twilight. Paint in tubes also changed the way artists applied paint to the canvas. Painting became much more spontaneous.  Artists were no longer obliged to paint in careful layers of thinned pigments and varnish, although they could use that time-tested method if they chose. With paint in tubes, a greater variety of techniques could be employed, such as blending the paint on the canvas and painting directly on the raw, ungessoed surface.  The effect of paint in tubes was so important that it contributed to the rise of the impressionist style. The artist Renoir said, “Without tubes of paint, there would have been no impressionism.” Thanks to the mobility that paint in tubes provided, artists could capture the light of a fleeting moment of the day, and the impressions that it provided.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Practical properties of oil paint </st>
<p>

Many artists today consider oil paint to be one of the fundamental art media; something that a student should learn to appreciate, because of its properties and use in previous, very popular artwork. Typical qualities of oil paint include a long "open time," which means that the paint does not dry quickly. Oil paints will not dry for up to several weeks, allowing the artist to work on a painting for several sessions. Oil paint also has a propensity to blend into surrounding paint allowing very subtle blending of colors. This medium also produced vivid color with a natural sheen and distinct contrast. Oil paints have a surface translucency similar to human skin, making it an ideal medium for portraits,</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Carrier </st>
<p>

Traditional oil paints require an oil that will gradually harden, forming a stable, impermeable film. Such oils are called siccative, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/752713.xml">
drying</link>, oils, and are characterized by high levels of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/1610513.xml">
polyunsaturated</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>s.  One common measure of the siccative property of oils is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/1786905.xml">
iodine number</link>, the number of grams of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/14750.xml">
iodine</link> one hundred grams of oil can absorb.  Oils with an iodine number greater than 130 are considered drying, those with an iodine number of 115-130 are semi-drying, and those with an iodine number of less than 115 are non-drying.  Linseed oil, the most prevalent vehicle for artists' oil paints, is a drying oil.</p>
<p>

When exposed to air, oils do not undergo the same <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/10303.xml">
evaporative</link> process that water does.  Instead, they <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/66313.xml">
oxidize</link> into a dry solid.  Depending upon the source, this process can be very slow, resulting in paints with an extended drying time.</p>
<p>

This earliest and still most commonly used vehicle is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/295711.xml">
linseed oil</link>, pressed from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/37694.xml">
seed</link> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/38869.xml">
flax</link> plant.  Modern processes use heat or steam in order to produce refined varieties of oil, which contain fewer impurities, but cold-pressed oils are still the favorite of many artists.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Other vegetable oils such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/324632.xml">
Hemp</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/1208398.xml">
poppy seed</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/1208431.xml">
walnut</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/2921902.xml">
sunflower</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/1208441.xml">
safflower</link>, and <link>
soybean oil</link>s may be used as alternatives to linseed oil for a variety of reasons. For example, safflower and poppy oils are paler than linseed oil and allow for more vibrant whites.</p>
<p>

Once the oil is extracted <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/578383.xml">
additive</link>s are sometimes used to improve its chemical properties.  In this way the paint can be made to dry more quickly if that is desired, or to have varying levels of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/425002.xml">
gloss</link>.  Modern oils paints can, therefore, have complex chemical structures; for example, affecting resistance to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/31990.xml">
UV</link> or giving a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/169546.xml">
suede</link> like appearance.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Non-oil carriers </st>
<p>

New carriers for paint were developed out of organic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/23001.xml">
polymer</link> technology in the twentieth century. In many cases, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/2838.xml">
acrylic paint</link>, a different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/2076473.xml">
binder</link> is substituted for oil. These new binders have different properties than oil paint, such as faster drying times and increased mechanical strength of the paint film. They require different (though overlapping) techniques and provide new possibilities that are not available to oil painters, such as the building of heavy texture and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/171211.xml">
impasto</link>, the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../195/18938195.xml">
collage</link>, and the sculpting of the paint surface. Contemporary thinking therefore recognizes the new materials as separate mediums. </p>
<p>

Some manufacturers, in an attempt to produce a medium that is oil-based but avoids toxic cleaners and thinners, have managed to produce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/983281.xml">
water miscible oil paint</link>s.  The vehicle for such paints is an oil with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/133176.xml">
surfactant</link> molecule chemically bonded to it which allows oil to mix with water in much the same way dish soap does, but with greater sophistication.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
How oil paint dries </st>

<p>

Unlike water-based paints, oils do not dry by evaporation.  The drying of oils is the result of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/66313.xml">
oxidative</link> reaction, chemically equivalent to slow, flameless <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/5638.xml">
combustion</link>.  In this process, a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/3189738.xml">
autoxidation</link>, oxygen attacks the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/13257.xml">
hydrocarbon</link> chain, touching off a series of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/369482.xml">
addition reaction</link>s.  As a result, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
oil</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/23001.xml">
polymer</link>izes, forming long, chain-like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/19555.xml">
molecule</link>s.  Following the autoxidation stage, the oil polymers cross-link: bonds form between neighboring molecules, resulting in a vast polymer network.  Over time, this network may undergo further change.  Certain <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/10911.xml">
functional group</link>s in the networks become <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/59611.xml">
ionized</link>, and the network transitions from a system held together by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/361038.xml">
nonpolar</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/6246.xml">
covalent bond</link>s to one governed by the ionic forces between these functional groups and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/19042.xml">
metal</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/18963787.xml">
ions</link> present in the pigment.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/192331.xml">
Vegetable oil</link>s consist of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/172732.xml">
glycerol</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/9675.xml">
esters</link> of fatty acids, long hydrocarbon chains with a terminal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/38850.xml">
carboxyl group</link>.  In oil autoxidation, oxygen attacks a hydrocarbon chain, often at the site of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/772827.xml">
allylic</link> hydrogen (a hydrogen on a carbon atom adjacent to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/6246.xml">
double bond</link>).  This produces a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/235028.xml">
free radical</link>, a substance with an unpaired <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/9476.xml">
electron</link> which makes  it highly reactive.  A series of  addition reactions ensues.  Each step produces additional free radicals, which then engage in further polymerization.   The process finally terminates  when free radicals collide, combining their unpaired electrons to form a new bond.  The polymerization stage occurs over a period of days to weeks, and renders the film dry to the touch.  However, chemical changes in the paint film continue.</p>
<p>

As time passes, the polymer chains begin to cross-link.  Adjacent molecules form covalent bonds, forming a molecular network  that extends throughout the painting.    In this network, known as the stationary phase, molecules are no longer free to slide past each other, or to move apart.  The result is a stable film which, while somewhat <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/268923.xml">
elastic</link>, does not flow or deform under the pull of gravity.  </p>
<p>

During the drying process, a number of compounds are produced that do not contribute to the polymer network.  These include unstable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/2296644.xml">
hydroperoxide</link>s (ROOH), the major by-product of the reaction of oxygen with unsaturated fatty acids.  The hydroperoxides quickly decompose, forming <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../906/5906.xml">
carbon dioxide</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/33306.xml">
water</link>, as well as a variety of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/37329.xml">
aldehyde</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/656.xml">
acid</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/13257.xml">
hydrocarbon</link>s.  Many of these <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/6782.xml">
compound</link>s are volatile, and in an un<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/49598.xml">
pigment</link>ed oil, they would be quickly lost to the environment.  However, in paints, such volatiles may react with lead, zinc, copper or iron compounds in the pigment, and remain in the paint film as coordination complexes or salts. A large number of free fatty acids are also produced during autoxidation, as most of the original ester bonds in the triglycerides undergo hydrolysis.  Some portion of the free fatty acids react with metals in the pigment, producing metal carboxylates.  Together, the various non-cross-linking substances associated with the polymer network constitute the mobile phases.  Unlike the molecules that are part of the network itself, they are capable of moving and diffusing within the film, and can be removed using heat or a solvent.  The mobile phase may play a role in plasticizing the paint film, preventing it from becoming too brittle.  </p>
<p>

One simple technique for monitoring the early stages of the drying process is to measure weight change in an oil film over time.  Initially, the film becomes heavier, as it absorbs large amounts of oxygen.  Then oxygen uptake ceases, and the weight of the film  declines as volatile compounds are lost to the environment. </p>
<p>

As the paint film ages, a further transition occurs. Carboxyl groups in the polymers of the stationary phase lose a hydrogen ion, becoming negatively charged, and form complexes with metal <link>
cation</link>s present in the pigment.  The original network, with its nonpolar, covalent bonds  is replaced by an ionomeric structure, held together by ionic interactions.  At present, the structure of these ionomeric networks is not well understood.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Pigment </st>
<p>

The color of oil paint derives from the small particles mixed with the carrier. Common pigment types include mineral salts such as white oxides: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/17747.xml">
lead</link>, now most often replaced by less toxic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/34420.xml">
zinc</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/30040.xml">
titanium</link>, and the red to yellow <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/5672.xml">
cadmium</link> pigments. Another class consists of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/561873.xml">
earth types</link>, e.g. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/29559.xml">
sienna</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/561853.xml">
umber</link>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/85029.xml">
Synthetic</link> pigments are also now available.  Natural pigments have the advantage of being well understood through centuries of use but synthetics have greatly increased the spectrum available, and many are tested well for their lightfastness.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Toxicity </st>
<p>
 
Many of the historical pigments were dangerous. Many toxic pigments, such as emerald green (copper(II)-acetoarsenite) and orpiment (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/897.xml">
arsenic</link> sulfide), to name only two, have fallen from use.  Some pigments still in use are toxic to some degree, however. Many of the reds and yellows are produced using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/5672.xml">
cadmium</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/426604.xml">
vermilion</link> red uses natural or synthetic mercuric sulfide or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/53464.xml">
cinnabar</link>.  Flake white and Cremnitz white are made with basic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/3533543.xml">
lead carbonate</link>. The cobalt colors, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/1182639.xml">
cobalt blue</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/1179005.xml">
cerulean blue</link>, are made with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ium/6th_millennium.xml">
cobalt</link> compounds.  Some varieties of cobalt violet are made with cobalt arsenate. Manufacturers advise that care should be taken when using paints with these pigments. They advise never to spray apply toxic paints.  Read the health warnings on the label.  Some artists choose to avoid toxic pigments entirely, while others find that the unique properties of the paints more than compensate for the small risks inherent in using them.</p>
<p>

Zinc white and titanium white may carry a California health label for lead content. Those paints contain far less lead than the lead whites. Some manufacturers put the text "California only" above the warning.</p>
<p>

Thinners such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/151183.xml">
turpentine</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/869868.xml">
white spirit</link> are flammable. Some of them, particularly the poor grades of turpentine, have a strong odor. Both turpentine and odorless mineral spirits can be harmful to the health if used inappropriately. Thinners made from D-limonene are thought by some to have some potential for risk.  The EPA has not made that determination, however. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/iris/subst/0682.htm">
http://www.epa.gov/iris/subst/0682.htm</weblink></p>
<p>

Generally speaking, these risks are minor if the materials are used as intended. Solvents can be made safer by painting in a well-ventilated area, and paint is likely only dangerous in the hands of small children. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Charles Eastlake, <it>Materials for a History of Oil Painting</it>, Longman, Longman, Brown, Green, and Longman, 1847.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dsc.discovery.com/news/2008/02/19/oldest-oil-painting.html">
"Oldest Oil Paintings Found in Afghanistan"</weblink>, Rosella Lorenzi, Discovery News. Feb. 19, 2008.</entry>
<entry id="3">
H. Gluck, "The Impermanences of Painting in Relation to Artists' Materials", <it>Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</it>, Volume CXII 1964</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<b>General</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mayer, Ralph. <it>The Artist's Handbook of Materials and Techniques</it> Viking Adult; 5th revised and updated edition, 1991. ISBN 0-670-83701-6</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>History</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cyberlipid.org/perox/oxid0011.htm">
History of Oil Paint</weblink>." <it>Cyberlipid Center</it>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.realcolorwheel.com/1mediums.htm#MEDIUMS,%20TURPENTINE%20AND%20OIL">
History of Painting Mediums</weblink>." <it>Real Color Wheel</it>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sanders-studios.com/instruction/tutorials/historyanddefinitions/historyofoils.html#anchorhistory">
A Brief History</weblink>." <it>Sanders-Studios.com</it>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.danielsmith.com/Learn/Articles/Evolution-of-Oil-Paint-Colors.asp">
The Evolution of Oil Color</weblink>." <it><name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<language_unit wordnetid="106284225" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/8565444.xml">
Daniel Smith Artists' Materials</link></institution>
</language_unit>
</part>
</trade_name>
</company>
</name>
</it>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Chemistry of Oil Paint</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

“Autoxidation.” McGraw Hill Encyclopedia. 8th ed. 1997.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.peggyflanders.com">
Flanders, Peggy J.</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.peggyflanders.com/Information/how_oils_dry.htm">
How Oils Dry</weblink>, 5 May 2006.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Friedman, Ann, et al., <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worldbookonline.com/wb/Article?id=ar410780">
Painting</weblink>,  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worldbookonline.com">
World Book online</weblink>, 46 Stetson St. #5 	Brookline, MA. 10 May,  2006. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cyberlipid.org/perox/oxid0011.htm">
History of Oil Paint</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cyberlipid.org">
CyberLipid.org</weblink>, 5 May 2006. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mecklenburg, Marion, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thepaintershandbook.org/forums/viewtopic.php?p=59&amp;sid=1af793cece44ccf8743ba531850d0cda">
Autoxidation of Oil</weblink>, 13 Jan 2006. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thepaintershandbook.org">
The Painter's Handbook</weblink>, Mark David Gottsegen.  11 June 2006.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

van den Berg, Jorit D.J., <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amolf.nl/research/biomacromolecular_mass_spectrometry/molart/highlights_www.pdf">
Mobile and Stationary Phases in Traditional Aged Oil Paint</weblink><message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link></format>
</language>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;(3.08&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/60727.xml">
MiB</link>), <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amolf.nl">
MOLART</weblink> 2002. 8 May 2006</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/22605.xml">
Oil painting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/752713.xml">
Drying oil</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/2876584.xml">
Semi-drying oil</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/31053.xml">
Egg tempera</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/2838.xml">
Acrylic paint</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../046/180046.xml">
Watercolor</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/16737680.xml">
Acrylic painting techniques</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
