<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:26:23[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network performance management</title>
<id>6798397</id>
<revision>
<id>217232167</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-05T04:33:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>BotMultichill</username>
<id>4080734</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Performance management</category>
<category>Network management</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Network performance management</b> is the discipline of optimizing how networks function, trying to deliver the lowest latency, highest capacity, and maximum reliability despite intermittent failures and limited bandwidth. While availability management is critical, infrastructure reliability has improved to the point at which 99.9% availability is not uncommon. Given these improvements in device availability, companies are focusing more attention on performance management. By measuring how networked applications perform under normal circumstances, understanding how performance is impacted by infrastructure and application changes, and isolating the sources of above-normal latency, IT organizations can ensure problems are resolved quickly, mitigate risk, and take measured steps to optimize application performance. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<sec>
<st>
 Reliable and unreliable networks </st>
<p>

Networks connect users or machines to one another using sets of well-defined protocols to govern how data is transmitted.  Depending on the type of network and the goals of the application, the protocols may be optimized for specific characteristics:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A best-effort network protocol tries to send data, but may lose some along the way to avoid congestion.  <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/15323.xml">
IP</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 and <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/31929.xml">
UDP</link></system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
 are popular examples of this. Often, this kind of protocol is used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/41291.xml">
isochronous</link> traffic such as voice over IP (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/75028.xml">
VOIP</link>).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A reliable network guarantees delivery of traffic, favoring correctness and completeness over speed.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/30538.xml">
TCP</link>, which is the basis for most Internet protocols including the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/13443.xml">
http</link> protocol over which web applications are delivered, is the most common example.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Factors affecting network performance </st>
<p>

Unfortunately, not all networks are the same.  As data is broken into component parts (often known frames, packets, or segments) for transmission, several factors can affect their delivery.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/19572286.xml">
Latency</link>: It can take a long time for a packet to be delivered across intervening networks.  In reliable protocols where a receiver acknowledges delivery of each chunk of data, it is possible to measure this as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/41672.xml">
round-trip time</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/2928109.xml">
Packet loss</link>: In some cases, intermediate devices in a network will lose packets.  This may be due to errors, to overloading of the intermediate network, or to intentional discarding of traffic in order to enforce a particular service level.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/2667590.xml">
Retransmission</link>: When packets are lost in a reliable network, they are retransmitted.  This incurs two delays: First, the delay from re-sending the data; and second, the delay resulting from waiting until the data is received in the correct order before forwarding it up the protocol stack.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/30932.xml">
Throughput</link>: The amount of traffic a network can carry is measured as throughput, usually in terms such as kilobits per second.  Throughput is analogous to the number of lanes on a highway, whereas latency is analogous to its speed limit.</entry>
</list>

These factors, and others (such as the performance of the network signaling on the end nodes, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/38808.xml">
compression</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link>, concurrency, and so on) all affect the effective performance of a network. In some cases, the network may not work at all; in others, it may be slow or unusable.  And because applications run over these networks, application performance suffers.  Various intelligent solutions are available to ensure that traffic over the network is effectively managed to optimize performance for all users. See <link>
Traffic Shaping</link></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The performance management discipline </st>

<p>

Network performance management consists of measuring, modeling, planning, and optimizing networks to ensure that they carry traffic with the speed, reliability, and capacity that is appropriate for the nature of the application and the cost constraints of the organization.
Different applications warrant different blends of capacity, latency, and reliability.  For example:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Streaming video or voice can be unreliable (brief moments of static) but need to have very low latency so that lags don't occur</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bulk file transfer or e-mail must be reliable and have high capacity, but doesn't need to be instantaneous</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Instant messaging doesn't consume much bandwidth, but should be fast and reliable</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Network performance management tasks and classes of tools </st>
<p>

Network managers perform many tasks; these include performance measurement, forensic analysis, capacity planning, and load-testing or load generation.  They also work closely with application developers and IT departments who rely on them to deliver underlying network services.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

For <it>performance measurement</it>, operators typically measure the performance of their networks at different levels.  They either using per-port metrics (how much traffic on port 80 flowed between a client and a server and how long did it take) or they rely on end-user metrics (how fast did the login page load for Bob.)  </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Per-port metrics are collected using flow-based monitoring and protocols such as <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/1206114.xml">
Netflow</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 (now standardized as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/4996273.xml">
IPFIX</link>) or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/11839689.xml">
RMON</link>. </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

End-user metrics are collected through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/320381.xml">
web logs</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/4639785.xml">
synthetic monitoring</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/6744108.xml">
real user monitoring</link>. An example is ART (application response time) which provides end to end statistics that measure <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/3411777.xml">
Quality of Experience</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

For <it>forensic analysis</it>, operators often rely on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
sniffer</link>s that break down the transactions by their protocols and can locate problems such as retransmissions or protocol negotiations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

For <it>capacity planning</it>, modeling tools such as <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/17119866.xml">
PacketTrap</link></company>
 pt360 NetFlow feature, <link>
SolarWinds</link> NetFlow Traffic Analyzer, or <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/15966661.xml">
OPNET</link></company>
 that project the impact of new applications or increased usage are invaluable.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

For <it>load generation</it> that helps to understand the breaking point, operators may use software or appliances that generate scripted traffic.  Some hosted service providers also offer pay-as-you-go traffic generation for sites that face the public Internet.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/3637561.xml">
Capacity management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/3074936.xml">
Capacity planning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/1577061.xml">
Network planning and design</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/1663751.xml">
Network monitoring</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../610/6615610.xml">
Performance engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../801/225801.xml">
Performance tuning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/27764.xml">
Systems engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/8940918.xml">
Computer Measurement Group</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~pb/640/perform.ppt">
Network Performance Measurement and Analysis</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web2.uwindsor.ca/courses/cs/aggarwal/HPGCGroup/Docs/npm.ppt">
Introduction to Network Performance Measurement</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://registration.fossconf.in/smedia/slides/Performance-Measurement-of-WLAN_FOSSConF_Vipin-M-V-03.02.pdf">
Performance Measurement in Wireless Communication Local Area Network</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkperformancedaily.com/2006/10/understanding_performance_mana.html">
Understanding Network Performance Management</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
