<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:34:58[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Single Source of Truth</title>
<id>6831362</id>
<revision>
<id>242270546</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T15:55:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Balis</username>
<id>700269</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Database normalization</category>
<category>Data modeling</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In Information Systems Design and theory, as instantiated at the <it>Enterprise Level</it>, <b>Single Source Of Truth</b> (SSOT) refers to the practice of structuring information models and associated schemata, such that every data element is stored exactly once and no more (e.g. in no more than a single row of a single table).  Any possible linkages to this data element (possibly in other areas of the relational schema or even in distant federated databases) are by reference only.  Thus, when any such data element is updated, this update propagates to the enterprise at large, without the possibility of a duplicate value somewhere in the distant enterprise not being updated (as there would be no duplicate values <it>to update</it>). Deployment of this architecture is becoming increasingly important in enterprise settings where incorrectly-linked duplicate or de-normalized data elements (a direct consequence of intentional or unintentional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/8561.xml">
denormalization</link> of any explicit data model) poses a risk for retrieval of outdated, and therefore, incorrect information.  A common example would be the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/1129641.xml">
electronic health record</link>, where it is imperative to accurately validate patient identity against a single referential repository, which serves as the SSOT.  Duplicate representations of data within the enterprise would be implemented by the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/459018.xml">
pointers</link> rather than duplicate database tables, rows or cells.  This ensures that data updates to elements in the authoritative location are comprehensively distributed to all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/1270246.xml">
federated database</link> constituencies in the larger overall enterprise architecture.<p>

SSOT systems provide data that are authentic, relevant and referable. </p>

<sec>
<st>
SSOT Categories</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Party SSOT</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Product SSOT</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Partner SSOT</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Geo SSOT</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Campaign SSOT</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Services SSOT</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
