<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:39:35[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<game  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100456199">
<header>
<title>Digital Pinball: Necronomicon</title>
<id>6864269</id>
<revision>
<id>173574457</id>
<timestamp>2007-11-24T23:05:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Paul foord</username>
<id>240061</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Pinball video games</category>
<category>1996 video games</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<b>Digital Pinball: Necronomicon</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/60508.xml">
Pinball</link> video game created for the <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/29035.xml">
Sega Saturn</link></system>
 by KaZe in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/34636.xml">
1996</link>. Only released in Japan, this high-res 2D game draws much of its graphical and audio inspiration from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/292910.xml">
metafictional</link> <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/21442.xml">
Necronomicon</link></it>. Most video pinball aficionado hold this title in high regard for its overall look and feel as well as its superior playability.</p>
<p>

<b>Necronomicon</b> is noteworthy for several reasons.  It's one of the few Saturn games to run in interlaced high-resolution.  This gives it a much more detailed view of the playfield, and is generally more visually appealing.  The physics are incredibly well realized, with accurate ball movements from every target and flipper.</p>
<p>

The sound is also exceptional, with a crisp rock soundtrack and a wealth of high-bitrate samples that put the Saturn's soundchip through its paces like few other games did.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Tables</st>

<p>

<it>Digital Pinball: Necronomicon</it> contains 3 separate playfields, or tables:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Arkham Asylum"</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Dreamlands"</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Cult of The Bloody Tongue"</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

All three tables are playable from the start menu. If a player chooses <it>Realms Mode</it> then he is required to play "Arkham Asylum" until he reaches sufficient progress to move on to the remaining two tables.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Other Info </st>
<p>

Kaze went on to produce several other pinball games, including Power Rangers Pinball for the Playstation, Akira Psychoball for the Playstation 2, and a series of  Java pins on the Japanese J-Phone/Vodafone network.
Kaze's main business now is web development.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Trivia</st>

<p>

<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../156/762156.xml">
John Petrucci</link></artist>
 guitarist for <musical_organization wordnetid="108246613" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/73066.xml">
Dream Theater</link></group>
</musical_organization>
 contributed music to the game's score by composing the prologue and epilogue FMV music. The ingame music however, was composed by Yusuke Takahama of Target Laboratories (http://www.target-ent.com/). John Petrucci is often incorrectly credited for the whole score, even though the introduction sequence of the game states that he only contributed two musical pieces.</p>
<p>

The game provided a password next to high scores, these could be used on the Kaze Co. website for an online submit system. Although the website is now down, renmants of it can be seen via the Wayback Machine (web.archive.org). The second table of the game (Cult of the Bloody Hand) is the only one with a maximized score counter of 999.999.999.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://kazenet.com/kaze/">
Kaze's Site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://evilboris.sonic-cult.net/necronomicon/">
fansite with complete game system, table, scoring &amp; map guides, as well as music lyrics and general information</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nfggames.com/games/necronomicon/">
NFG Games Review</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nfggames.com/games/necronomicon/Necronomicon_Guide.php?table=Cult&amp;page=map">
NFG Games Guide to Necronomicon</weblink> - includes table maps, scoring etc</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nfggames.com/games/prpinball/">
NFG Games Power Rangers Pinball Review</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</game>
</article>
