<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:36:20[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<action  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100037396">
<interaction  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100039021">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<header>
<title>Interspecific competition</title>
<id>6920233</id>
<revision>
<id>242142779</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T02:09:25Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Biological interactions</category>
<category>Competition</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Interspecific competition</b>, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/9630.xml">
ecology</link>, is a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/4715998.xml">
competition</link> in which individuals of <it>different</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/28023.xml">
species</link> vie for the same resource in an ecosystem (e.g. food or living space). The other form of competition is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/2717816.xml">
intraspecific competition</link>, which involves organisms of the same species.<p>

An example of interspecific competition, if a tree in a dense <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/11090.xml">
forest</link> grows taller than surrounding trees, it is able to absorb more of the incoming sunlight. However, less sunlight is then available for nearby trees that are shaded by the taller tree. An example among animals could be the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/45609.xml">
cheetah</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/36896.xml">
lion</link>s; since both species feed on the same prey, they are negatively impacted by the presence of the other because they will have less food. Also, lions sometimes steal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/57559.xml">
prey</link> items killed by cheetahs.</p>
<p>

Competition is only one of many interacting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/11708788.xml">
biotic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/1665285.xml">
abiotic</link> factors that affect community structure. Moreover, competition is not always a straightforward, direct interaction. Interspecific competition may occur when individuals of two separate species share a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/1473750.xml">
limiting resource</link> in the same area.  If the resource cannot support both populations, then lowered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/900798.xml">
fecundity</link>, growth, or survival may result in at least one species.  Interspecific competition has the potential to alter <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/22949.xml">
population</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/5695.xml">
communities</link> and the evolution of interacting species.  On an individual organism level, competition can occur as interference or exploitative competition.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Mechanisms</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Interference competition</st>

<p>

Interference competition involves direct interactions between individuals such as fighting over limiting resources.  This form of competition is typically, though not always, detrimental to both individuals and both species involved.  These interactions are usually asymmetric with one species having an advantage over the other resulting in greater loss by one competitor.  For example, large predators like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/6736.xml">
canids</link> have a significant size advantage over smaller predators such as foxes or weasels.  A violent interaction between two of these species would likely result in victory for the larger predator.  The stability of some mammalian carnivore populations is maintained through these conflicts over prey resources. 
An example of interference competition in which only one party is negatively affected is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/632030.xml">
allelopathy</link>, in which plants of one species release toxic chemicals that inhibit the germination and survival of other potential competitors.  Some animals utilize a similar strategy.  For example, algae in the feces of the common frog, <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/972584.xml">
Rana temporaria</link></it>, inhibit the tadpoles of the competing natterjack toad, <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/584196.xml">
Bufo calamita</link></it>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Exploitative competition</st>

<p>

Exploitative competition is a douche form of competition in which one species either reduces or more efficiently uses a douche resource and therefore depletes the availability of the resource for the other species.  A good example of exploitative competition is found in aphid species competing over the sap in plant phloem.  Each aphid species that feeds on host plant sap uses up some of the resource, leaving less for competing species.  In one study, <it>Fordinae geoica</it> was observed to out-compete <it>F. formicaria</it> to the extent that the latter species exhibited a reduction in survival by 84%.  
This type of competition can also be observed in forests where large trees dominate the canopy and thus allow little light to reach smaller competitors living below. These interactions have important implications for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/501466.xml">
population dynamics</link> and distribution of both species.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Consequences</st>

<p>

Many studies, including those cited previously, have shown major impacts on both individuals and populations from interspecific competition.  Documentation of these impacts has been found in species from every major branch of organism.  The effects of interspecific competition can also reach communities and can even influence the evolution of species as they adapt to avoid competition.  This evolution may result in the exclusion of a species in the habitat, niche separation, and local extinction.  The changes of these species over time can also change communities as other species must adapt.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Competitive exclusion</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/451120.xml">
competitive exclusion principle</link></it>
</indent>
The competitive exclusion principle states that two species that use the same resource in the same way in the same space and time cannot coexist and must diverge from each other over time in order for the two species to coexist.  One species will often exhibit an advantage in resource use.  This superior competitor will out-compete the other with more efficient use of the limiting resource.  As a result, the inferior competitor will suffer a decline in population over time.  It will be excluded from the area and replaced by the superior competitor.  
A well documented example of competitive exclusion was observed to occur between Dolly Varden charr (<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/1880489.xml">
Salvelinus malma</link></it>) and white spotted char (S. leucomaenis) in Japan.  Both of these species were morphologically similar but the former species was found primarily at higher elevations than the latter.  Although there was a zone of overlap, each species excluded the other from its dominant region by becoming better adapted to its habitat over time. In some such cases, each species gets displaced into an exclusive segment of the original habitat.  Because each species suffers from competition, natural selection favors the avoidance of competition in such a way.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Niche differentiation</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/4301692.xml">
Niche differentiation</link></it>
</indent>
Niche differentiation is a process by which competitive exclusion leads to differences with in resource use.  In the previous example, niche differentiation resulted in spatial displacement.  In other cases it may result in other changes that also avoid competition.  If competition avoidance is achievable, each species will occupy an edge of the niche and will become more specialized to that area thus minimizing competition.  This phenomenon often results in the separation of species over time as they become more specialized to their edge of the niche, called niche differentiation.  The species do not have to be in separate habitats however to avoid niche overlap.  Some species adapt regionally to utilizing different resources than they ordinarily would in order to avoid competition.  
There have been several well documented cases in  birds where species that are very similar change their habitat use where they overlap.  For example, they may consume different food resources or use different nesting habitat or materials.  On the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../118/171118.xml">
Galapagos Islands</link>, for example, finch species have been observed to change dietary specializations in just a few generations in order to utilize limited resources and minimize competition.
In some cases, third party species interfere to the detriment or benefit of the competing species.  In the laboratory study by Brockhurst et al in 2001, coexistence between two competing bacterial species was mediated by phage parasites. This type of interaction actually helped to maintain diversity in bacterial communities and has far reaching implications in medical research as well as ecology. Similar effects have been documented for many communities as a result of the action of a keystone predator that preys on a competitively superior species.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Local extinction</st>

<p>

Although local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/49417.xml">
extinction</link> of one or more competitors has been less documented than niche separation or competitive exclusion, it does occur.  In an experiment by Bengsson in 1989 involving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/50558.xml">
zooplankton</link> in artificial rock pools, local extinction rates were significantly higher in areas of interspecific competition.  In these cases, therefore, the negative effects are not only at the population level but also species richness of communities.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Impacts on communities</st>

<p>

As mentioned previously, interspecific competition has great impact on community composition and structure.  Niche separation of species, local extinction and competitive exclusion are only some of the possible effects.  In addition to these, interspecific competition can be the source of a cascade of affects that build on each other.  An example of such an effect is the introduction of an <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/67554.xml">
invasive species</link></issue>
 to the Northeastern United States, purple loostrife.  This plant when introduced to wetland communities often outcompetes much of the native flora and decreases species richness, food and shelter to many other species at higher trophic levels.  In this way, one species can influence the populations of many other species as well as through a myriad of other interactions. Because of the complicated web of interactions that make up every ecosystem and habitat, the results of interspecific competition are complex and site-specific.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Lotka-Volterra model</st>

<p>

The impacts of interspecific competition on populations have been formalized in a mathematical model called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/462534.xml">
Lotka-Volterra equation</link>, which creates a theoretical prediction of interactions. It combines the effects of each species on the other.  These effects are calculated separately for the first and second population respectively: </p>
<p>

dN1/dt=r1N1((K1-N1-α12N2)/K1)</p>
<p>

dN2/dt=r2N2((K2-N2-α21N1)/K2)</p>
<p>

In these formulae, N is the population size, t is time, K is the carrying capacity, r is the intrinsic rate of increase and α is the competition coefficient. The results show the effect that the other species has on the species being calculated.  The results can be graphed to show a trend and possible prediction for the future of the species.  One problem with this model is that certain assumptions must be made for the calculation to work.  These include the lack of migration and constancy of the carrying capacities and competition coefficients of both species.  The complex nature of ecology determines that these assumptions are rarely true in the field but the model provides a basis for improved understanding of these important concepts.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/1550259.xml">
Minimum viable population</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Solomon, E. P., Berg, L. R., &amp; Martin, D. W. (2002). <it>Biology, sixth edition</it>. (N. Rose, Ed.). Stamford, CT: Thomson Learning</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Begon, M., C.R. Townsend and J.L. Harper.  2006.  .  Blackwell Publishing, Malden, MA.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bengtsson, J. 1989.  Interspecific competition increases local extinction rate in a metapopulation system.  Nature 340, 713 – 715</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Brockhurst, M.A., A. Fenton, B. Roulston and P.B. Rainey.  2006.  The impact of phages on interspecific competition in experimental populations of bacteria.  BMC Ecology6:19.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Connell, J.H. 1961.  Factors on the distribution of the barnacle Chthamalus stellatus. Ecology 42,4. 710-723</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Giller, P. S. 1984. Community Structure and the Niche. Chapman &amp; Hall, London.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Holekamp, K.E.  2006.  Interspecific competition and anti-predator behavior.  National Science Foundation. http://www.nsf.gov/</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Inbar, M., A. Eshel and D. Wool. 1995. Interspecific competition among phloem-feeding insects mediated by induced host-plant sinks.  Ecology. 76.5: 1506-1515.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Shoener, T.W.  1983.  Field experiments on interspecific competition.  American Naturalist. 122: 240.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Taniguchi Y. and S. Nakano 2000. Condition-Specific Competition: Implications for the Altitudinal Distribution of Stream Fishes.  Ecology, 81. 7: 2027-2039</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Weiner, J. 1994.  The Beak of the Finch. Cambridge University Press, New York.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</interaction>
</action>
</event>
</article>
