<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:42:56[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<academician  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109759069">
<adult  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109605289">
<professional  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110480253">
<educator  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110045713">
<header>
<title>Valerie Frissen</title>
<id>6950325</id>
<revision>
<id>238593156</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-15T14:59:41Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>People from Limburg (Netherlands)</category>
<category>Dutch academics</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>1960 births</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

‘Valerie Frissen’ (born 1960, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/118546.xml">
Puth</link></village>
) holds the <link>
extraordinary professorship</link> in ‘ICT and Social Change’ at the Faculty of Philosophy at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/1568097.xml">
Erasmus University Rotterdam</link> were she belongs to the group of Professor Dr. <link>
Jos de Mul</link>. The chair is sponsored by the Dutch governmental research organization <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/2459773.xml">
TNO</link>, were Valerie Frissen is also head of the ICT &amp; Policy department of TNO Information and Communication Technology. She is also a member of the board of <link>
Het Expertise Centrum</link> (HEC) in The Hague.
<sec>
<st>
Scholar career</st>
<p>

Valerie graduated with a doctoral (master) degree in communication science from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/956504.xml">
Catholic University of Nijmegen</link> (now known as the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/956504.xml">
Radboud University Nijmegen</link></university>
 where she also obtained her PhD.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Publications</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brants, K., &amp; Frissen, V. (2000). Inclusion and exclusion in the Information Society. Final Deliverable to the European Media and Technology Everyday Life Network, 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (1992). Trapped in Electronic Cages? Gender and New Information Technologies in the Public and Private Domain: An Overview of Research. Media, Culture and Society, 14(1), 31–49.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (1994). The domestification of the telephone. Domestic technology and everyday life: Mutual shaping processes. Proceedings from COST A, 4, 28–30.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (1995). Gender is calling: Some reflections on past, present and future uses of the telephone. The gender–technology relation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (1996). Gender, ICTs and Everyday Life. Luxembourg: Office for Official Publications of the European Communities.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (1997). Gender, ITCs and Everyday Life: Mutual Shaping Processes: European Commission.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (2000). ICTs in the Rush Hour of Life. The Information Society, 16(1), 65-75.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (2000). Under Construction. Persoonlijke en culturele identiteit in het multimediatijdperk. Infodrome.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (2001). De schaduwdemocratie: ICT en maatschappelijke participatie: s. n.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V. (2004). De domesticatie van de digitale wereld: Erasmus Universteit.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V., &amp; de Mul, J. (2000). Under construction: persoonlijke en culturele identiteit in het multimediatijdperk: Infodrome.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V., &amp; Punie, Y. (1997). Never mind the gap: integrating qualitative and quantitative methods in ICT-User-Research: the case of busy households, paper presentado en el Sexto Workshop del grupo EMTEL: Barcelona.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V., &amp; Punie, Y. (2001). Present users, future homes–A theoretical perspective on acceptance and use of ICT in the home environment: TNO rapport STB-01-30a. Delft: TNO.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frissen, V., &amp; Zaat-Jones, J. (1999). ICT en arbeid in het dagelijks leven: Rathenau Instituut.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Servaes, J., &amp; Frissen, V. (1997). De interpretatieve benadering in de communicatiewetenschap: theorie, methodologie en case-studies: Acco.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Van Audenhove, L., Cammaerts, B., Frissen, V., Engels, L., &amp; Ponsioen, A. Transnational Civil Society in the Networked Society.</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</academician>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
