<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:40:25[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Participatory rural appraisal</title>
<id>7013377</id>
<revision>
<id>231462058</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-12T14:55:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>NE2</username>
<id>1757249</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
<category>Rural community development</category>
<category>Development</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Bartlett-Ranking_BGD(2004).jpg" type="frame">
<caption>

PRA ranking exercise being carried out by members of a Farmer Field School in Bangladesh, 2004
</caption>
</image>
<b>Participatory rural appraisal (PRA)</b> is an approach used by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/46539.xml">
non-governmental organizations</link> (NGOs) and other agencies involved in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/385745.xml">
international development</link>.  The approach aims to incorporate the knowledge and opinions of rural people in the planning and management of development projects and programmes. 
<sec>
<st>
 Origins of participatory rural appraisal </st>

<p>

The roots of PRA techniques can be traced to the activist adult education methods of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/618870.xml">
Paulo Freire</link></person>
 and the study clubs of the <commercial_enterprise wordnetid="108065093" confidence="0.8">
<cooperative wordnetid="101100877" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/11854437.xml">
Antigonish Movement</link></enterprise>
</cooperative>
</commercial_enterprise>
.  In this view, an actively involved and empowered local population is essential to successful rural community development.  Robert Chambers, a key exponent of PRA, argues that the approach owes much to "the Freirian theme, that poor and exploited people can and should be enabled to analyze their own reality."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.</p>
<p>

By the early 1980’s, there was growing dissatisfaction among development experts with both the reductionism of formal surveys, and the biases of typical field visits. In 1983, Robert Chambers, a Fellow at the Institute of Development Studies (UK), used the term <it>Rapid Rural Appraisal</it> to describe techniques that could bring about a 'reversal of learning' <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>. Two years later, the first international conference to share experiences relating to RRA was held in Thailand  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>. This was followed by a rapid growth in the development of methods that involved rural people in examining their own problems, setting their own goals, and monitoring their own achievements. By the mid 1990’s, the term RRA had been replaced by a number of other terms including ‘Participatory Rural Appraisal (PRA)’ and ‘Participatory Learning and Action’ (PLA).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Overview of PRA techniques </st>

<p>

Hundreds of participatory techniques and tools have been described in a variety of books and newsletters, or taught at training courses around the world. These techniques can be divided into four categories:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Group dynamics, e.g. learning contracts, role reversals, feedback sessions </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sampling, e.g. transect walks, wealth ranking, social mapping</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Interviewing, e.g. focus group discussions, semi-structured interviews, triangulation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Visualization e.g. venn diagrams, matrix scoring, timelines</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

To ensure that people are not excluded from participation, these techniques avoid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/32977.xml">
writing</link> wherever possible, relying instead on the tools of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/10417456.xml">
oral communication</link> like pictures, symbols, physical objects and group memory.  Efforts are made in many projects, however, to build a bridge to formal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/18456.xml">
literacy</link>; for example by teaching people how to sign their names or recognize their signatures.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 A 'new professionalism' for development </st>

<p>

A key idea that has accompanied the development of PRA techniques is that of a <it>new professionalism</it>. Robert Chambers has explained this as follows:</p>
<p>

“The central thrusts of the [new] paradigm … are decentralization and empowerment. Decentralization means that resources and discretion are devolved, turning back the inward and upward flows of resources and people. Empowerment means that people, especially poorer people, are enabled to take more control over their lives, and secure a better livelihood with ownership and control of productive assets as one key element. Decentralization and empowerment enable local people to exploit the diverse complexities of their own conditions, and to adapt to rapid change”.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>
<p>

To be an external agent of change within this discipline implies two-way learning.  Development agents learn to both appreciate and lever the power of oral culture and the transformations that are possible within it.  <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/1153843.xml">
Walter J. Ong</link></person>
 has argued that “many of the contrasts often made between ‘western’ and other views seem reducible to contrasts between deeply interiorized literacy and more or less residually oral states of consciousness.”<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The limits of PRA </st>

<p>

There are those who see limits to PRA. This is on a range of grounds - for example that it doesn't work, that it reveals the secrets of rural communities to be managed by development agencies,&#91;&#93; or that it is a tool of cooptation into neo-liberal development agendas. These were summarized in <b>Participation: The New Tyranny?</b> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/2819542.xml">
Participatory action research</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/7015182.xml">
Participatory technology development</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/585538.xml">
Participation (decision making)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/6409367.xml">
Farmer Field School</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/4155495.xml">
Community-led total sanitation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/4568259.xml">
Community-based participatory research</link> (CBPR)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/6472499.xml">
Asset-Based Community Development</link> (ABCD)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/10469004.xml">
Praxis intervention</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/10417456.xml">
Orality</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Robert Chambers.  <b>Whose Reality Counts? Putting the First Last</b> Intermediate Technology Publications, London, 1997, p. 106.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<b>Rural Development: Putting the Last First</b>, Robert Chambers, 1983, Longmans</entry>
<entry id="3">
<b>Proceedings of the 1985 International Conference on Rapid Rural Appraisal</b>, Khon Kaen University (Eds.), 1987, Rural Systems Research Project and Farming Systems Research Project, KKU, Thailand</entry>
<entry id="4">
<b>Challenging the Professions: Frontiers for Rural Development</b>, Robert Chambers, 1993, ITDG London</entry>
<entry id="5">
Walter J. Ong.  <it>Orality and Literacy</it>, p. 29.</entry>
<entry id="6">
<b>Participation: The New Tyranny?</b> Bill Cooke and Uma Kothari (eds), 2001, Zed London </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.childsurvival.com/connections/Chambers-AnalysisExperience.doc">
<b>Participatory Rural Appraisal (PRA): Analysis of Experience</b>, an article by Robert Chambers, 1994</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.worldbank.org/wbi/sourcebook/sba104.htm">
<b>Participatory Rural Appraisal</b>, from the World Bank Sourcebook on Participation</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/docrep/W3241E/w3241e09.htm">
<b>Rapid Rural Appraisal</b>, from the FAO manual on Market Research and Information Systems</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iied.org/NR/agbioliv/pla_notes/index.html">
<b>Participatory Learning and Action</b>, journal with many articles available for downloading, maintained by the International Institute for Environment and Development (IIED)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eldis.org/manuals/participation.htm">
<b>Participation Manuals and Toolkits</b>, an online collection, part of the ELDIS Gateway to Development Information</weblink>  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colostate.edu/Orgs/IISD/">
International Institute for Sustainable Development at Colorado State University</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/1/1c/Praxisintervention.pdf">
Praxis Intervention</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
