<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:34:14[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<occupation  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100582388">
<header>
<title>Speech and language pathology</title>
<id>7032057</id>
<revision>
<id>244270359</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T01:15:50Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DoubleBlue</username>
<id>220505</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Special education</category>
<category>Healthcare occupations</category>
<category>Medical terms</category>
<category>Speech and language pathology</category>
<category>Rehabilitation medicine</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Speech-language pathology</b> is the study of disorders that affect a person's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/2917649.xml">
speech</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/17524.xml">
language</link>, cognition, voice, swallowing (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/196920.xml">
dysphagia</link>) and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/1119701.xml">
rehabilitative</link> or corrective treatment of physical and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/106238.xml">
cognitive</link> deficits/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/148951.xml">
disorders</link> resulting in difficulty with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/5177.xml">
communication</link> and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/196983.xml">
swallowing</link>. Speech-language pathologists (SLPs) or Speech and Language Therapists (SLTs) address people's speech production, vocal production, swallowing difficulties and language needs through speech therapy in a variety of different contexts including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/28022.xml">
schools</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/18994221.xml">
hospitals</link>, and through private practice.<p>

Communication includes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/2917649.xml">
speech</link> (articulation, intonation, rate, intensity), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/17524.xml">
language</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/23247.xml">
phonology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/20646.xml">
morphology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/26860.xml">
syntax</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/44816.xml">
pragmatics</link>), both receptive and expressive language (including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/18581264.xml">
reading</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../977/32977.xml">
writing</link>), and non-verbal communication such as facial expression and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/403676.xml">
gesture</link>. Swallowing problems managed under speech therapy are problems in the oral, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/49375.xml">
laryngeal</link>, and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/62333.xml">
pharyngeal</link> stages of swallowing (not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/168506.xml">
oesophageal</link>).</p>
<p>

Depending on the nature and severity of the disorder, common treatments may range from physical strengthening <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/189037.xml">
exercise</link>s, instructive or repetitive practice and drilling, to the use of audio-visual aids and introduction of strategies to facilitate functional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../177/5177.xml">
communication</link>. Speech therapy may also include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/27699.xml">
sign language</link> and the use of picture symbols (Diehl 2003).  </p>
<p>

The practice is called:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Speech-language pathology</b> (SLP) in the United States and Canada</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Speech and language therapy</b> (SLT) in the United Kingdom, Ireland and South Africa</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Speech pathology</b> in Australia</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Speech-language therapy</b> in New Zealand</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Other terms in use include <b>speech therapy</b>, <b>logopaedics</b> and <b>phoniatrics</b>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Scope of practice </st>

<p>

The practice of speech-language pathology involves:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Providing prevention, screening, consultation, assessment and diagnosis, treatment, intervention, management, counseling, and follow-up services for disorders of: </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 speech (i.e., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/25037.xml">
phonation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/19942.xml">
articulation</link>, fluency, resonance, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/38481.xml">
voice</link> including aeromechanical components of respiration);</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 language (i.e., phonology, morphology, syntax, semantics, and pragmatic/social aspects of communication) including comprehension and expression in oral, written, graphic, and manual modalities; language processing; preliteracy and language-based literacy skills, including phonological awareness;</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 swallowing or other upper aerodigestive functions such as infant feeding and aeromechanical events (evaluation of esophageal function is for the purpose of referral to medical professionals);</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 cognitive aspects of communication (e.g., attention, memory, problem solving, executive functions).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 sensory awareness related to communication, swallowing, or other upper aerodigestive functions.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Establishing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/2106968.xml">
augmentative and alternative communication</link> (AAC) techniques and strategies including developing, selecting, and prescribing of such systems and devices (e.g., speech generating devices.)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Providing services to individuals with hearing loss and their families/caregivers (e.g.,auditory training; speechreading; speech and language intervention secondary to hearing loss; visual inspection and listening checks of amplification devices for the purpose of troubleshooting, including verification of appropriate battery voltage).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Screening hearing of individuals who can participate in conventional pure-tone air conduction methods, as well as screening for middle ear pathology through screening <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/2978488.xml">
tympanometry</link> for the purpose of referral of individuals for further evaluation and management.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Using instrumentation (e.g., <link>
videofluoroscopy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/997173.xml">
EMG</link>, <link>
nasendoscopy</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../454/1055454.xml">
stroboscopy</link>, computer technology) to observe, collect data, and measure parameters of communication and swallowing, or other upper aerodigestive functions in accordance with the principles of evidence-based practice.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Selecting, fitting, and establishing effective use of prosthetic/adaptive devices for communication, swallowing, or other upper aerodigestive functions (e.g., tracheoesophageal prostheses, speaking valves, <link>
electrolarynges</link>). This does not include sensory devices used by individuals with hearing loss or other auditory perceptual deficits.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Collaborating in the assessment of central auditory processing disorders and providing intervention where there is evidence of speech, language, and/or other cognitivecommunication disorders.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Educating and counseling individuals, families, co-workers, educators, and other persons in the community regarding acceptance, adaptation, and decision makes about communication, swallowing, or other upper aerodigestive concerns.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Advocating for individuals through community awareness, education, and training programs to promote and facilitate access to full participation in communication, including the elimination of societal barriers. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Collaborating with and providing referrals and information to audiologists, educators, and health professionals as individual needs dictate.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Addressing behaviors (e.g., perseverative or disruptive actions) and environments (e.g., seating, positioning for swallowing safety or attention, communication opportunities) that affect communication, swallowing, or other upper aerodigestive functions.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Providing services to modify or enhance <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/38481.xml">
communication performance</link> (e.g., accent modification, transgendered voice, care and improvement of the professional voice, personal/ professional communication effectiveness).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Recognizing the need to provide and appropriately accommodate diagnostic and treatment services to individuals from diverse cultural backgrounds and adjust treatment and assessment services according.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Professional roles </st>

<p>

Speech-language pathologists serve individuals, families, groups, and the general public through a broad range of professional activities. They:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Identify, define, and diagnose disorders of human communication and swallowing and assist in localization and diagnosis of diseases and conditions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Provide direct services using a variety of service delivery models to treat and/or address communication, swallowing, or other upper aerodigestive concerns.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Conduct research related to communication sciences and disorders, swallowing, or other upper aerodigestive functions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Educate, supervise, and mentor future speech-language pathologists.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Serve as case managers and service delivery coordinators.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Administer and manage clinical and academic programs.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Educate and provide in-service training to families, caregivers, and other professionals.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Participate in outcomes measurement activities and use data to guide clinical decision making and determine the effectiveness of services provided in accordance with the principles of evidence-based practice.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Train, supervise, and manage speech-language pathology assistants and other support personnel.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Promote healthy lifestyle practices for the prevention of communication, hearing, swallowing, or other upper aerodigestive disorders.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Education</st>
<p>

In the UK( United Kingdom) , SLTs undertake a three to four year degree course devoted entirely to the study of clinical language sciences and communicative disorders. This qualifies them to work in any of the three main clinical areas. The course, which varies according to university, includes intensive study of core theoretical components underpinning competence to practice [Clinical Phonetics], <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/17526.xml">
Linguistics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
Psychology</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
Medical science</link>, in addition to the study of a range of communicative disorders in children and adults. Students are also expected to become familiar with a range of policies, processes and procedures relevant to working in different contexts, including health and education. The course is very demanding, and is assessed via coursework, exams and clinical placement. Some universities require students to assess and diagnose an 'unseen client' prior to completing their degree course; all require the completion of a pilot study related to the field of Speech and Language Therapy. Throughout the course, students undertake a variety of clinical placements in which their ability to practise is continually assessed. All courses require students to complete a certain amount of hours of clinical placement, although the structure of placement differs from course to course.</p>
<p>

Upon qualifying SLT's enter the profession as a newly-qualified practitioner. The recommended career course is that they then achieve a number of competencies, which qualify them to work autonomously. The Royal College of Speech and Language Therapists, the professional body representing Speech and Language Therapists in the UK, provides a framework of competencies which therapists are expected to achieve within 12&ndash;18 months of beginning clinical practice. Access to supervision during this period varies from trust to trust, and each individual therapist is expected to provide documentary evidence of competencies achieved to a senior colleague (usually a manager) who determines whether a therapist meets the required criteria for admission to the 'full register'.</p>
<p>

Speech and Language Therapists in the UK are required by law to register with the Health Professions Council, a regulatory body governing a range of health professions. The Health Professions Council has the power to discipline members who do not meet the rigorous standards for effective and safe clinical practice, and may 'strike off' or deregister members who fail to maintain these standards.</p>
<p>

In the United States, Speech Language Pathology practice is regulated by the laws of the individual states. However, by 2006, the minimal requirements to be a certified SLP member of the American Speech-Language Hearing Association <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asha.org/">
http://www.asha.org/</weblink> were: a graduate degree in Speech-Language Pathology, which typically entails 2 years of post graduate work; a completed clinical fellowship year, which is generally employment for a year while supervised by a practicing SLP who is also ASHA certified; and passing the Praxis Series examination. The graduate degree work to acquire a Master's in Speech-Language Pathology is rigorous and demanding, requiring many hours of supervised clinical practica, and intensive didactic coursework in medical sciences, phonetics, linguistics, phonology, scientific methodology, and other subjects.</p>
<p>

Certification by ASHA is noted as carrying one's "C"s. (Certificate of Clinical Competence) It is noted after an SLP's name as: CCC-SLP.</p>
<p>

In Australia, Speech Pathologists either undertake a four year undergraduate degree, or a two year Masters degree to qualify. These dual pathways are considered by Speech Pathology Australia to produce equally prepared graduates. To be eligible for optional membership of Speech Pathology Australia, students must study in one of the accredited courses outlined on their website. Speech Pathology degrees in Australia vary in curriculum, but always include streams teaching anatomy and physiology, professional practice, communication and swallowing disorders, and often some elementary psychology and audiology. Most include no or minimal elective subjects. All degrees include a heavy clinical component, and many also include a research component in final year. Once graduated, students become fully qualified Speech Pathologists and are eligible for any Level 1 position, without the need for an internship or general examination. Registration is only required in the state of <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/59051.xml">
Queensland</link></group>
</colony>
</social_group>
</body>
, and membership of the professional organization is optional, although it is encouraged.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods of assessment</st>
<p>

There are separate standardized assessment tools administered for infants, school-aged children, adolescents and adults. Assessments primarily examine the form, content, understanding and use of language, as well as articulation, and phonology. Oral motor and swallowing assessments often require specialized training which includes the use of bedside examination tools and endoscopic/modified barium radiology procedures.</p>
<p>

Individuals may be referred to an SLP for the following:
Traumatic brain injury;
Stroke;
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/18914017.xml">
Alzheimer's disease</link> and dementia;
Cranial nerve damage;
Progressive neurological conditions (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/6302185.xml">
Parkinson</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/19375577.xml">
ALS</link>, etc);
Developmental delay;
Learning disability (speaking and listening);
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/25.xml">
Autism</link> Spectrum Disorders (including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../556/37556.xml">
Asperger Syndrome</link>);
Genetic disorders that adversely affect speech, language and/or cognitive development;
Injuries due to complications at birth;
Feeding and swallowing concerns;
Craniofacial anamolies that adversely affect speech, language and/or cognitive development; and
Augmentative Alternative Communication needs.</p>
<p>

There are myriad <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/16459564.xml">
Speech-Language Assessment</link> tools used for chidren and adults, depending on the area of need.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Patients/clients</st>

<p>

Speech and language therapists work with:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Babies with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/245407.xml">
feeding</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/196983.xml">
swallowing</link> difficulties</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Children with mild, moderate or severe:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/10970082.xml">
learning difficulties</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/56285.xml">
physical disabilities</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/1224162.xml">
language delay</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/1688561.xml">
specific language impairment</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

specific difficulties in producing sounds (including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/1586113.xml">
vocalic r</link> and lisps)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

hearing impairment</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/239890.xml">
cleft palate</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/28394.xml">
stammering</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/25.xml">
autism</link>/social interaction difficulties</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/8305.xml">
dyslexia</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link>
voice disorders</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Adults with eating and swallowing and/or communication problems following </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/625404.xml">
stroke</link> </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

head injury (Traumatic brain injury)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/6302185.xml">
Parkinson's disease</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/876.xml">
motor neuron disease</link> </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/50603.xml">
multiple sclerosis</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/47878.xml">
Huntington's disease</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/38390.xml">
dementia</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

cancer of the head, neck and throat (including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/922380.xml">
laryngectomy</link>)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

voice problems</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/990505.xml">
mental health</link> issues</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/10970082.xml">
learning difficulties</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/56285.xml">
physical disabilities</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/28394.xml">
stammering</link> (dysfluency)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

hearing impairment</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/611839.xml">
transsexual women</link> seeking <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/4775121.xml">
voice therapy</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

In the United States, the cost of speech therapy for a child younger than three years old is likely covered by the state early intervention (zero to three) program. </p>
<p>

In Britain, the majority of Speech and Language therapy is funded by the National Health Service (and increasingly, by partners in Education) meaning that initial assessment is available cost-free to all clients at the point of service, regardless of age or presenting problem. The large numbers of referrals contribute to high caseloads and long waiting lists, although this differs from area to area. To meet the needs of many of these clients, it has become necessary for many services to focus heavily on training and consultative models of service provision. The number of hours of direct therapy available to clients varies widely from trust to trust and most areas operate strict guidelines for prioritisation to meet the high clinical demand.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Place of work</st>

<p>

Speech and language therapists work in community health centres, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/18994221.xml">
hospital</link> wards and outpatient departments, mainstream and special <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/28022.xml">
school</link>s, further education <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/5689.xml">
college</link>s, day centers and in their clients' homes. Some now work in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/75358.xml">
court</link>rooms, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/19008450.xml">
prison</link>s and <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/2578676.xml">
young offenders' institutions</link></location>
</area>
</center>
</region>
.</p>
<p>

Some speech and language therapists who work independently will see children and adults in their own homes, and may offer appointments on a Saturday.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Colleagues</st>

<p>

SLTs/SLPs work closely with others involved with the client, for example difficulties with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/212818.xml">
eating</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/66254.xml">
drinking</link> may also involve an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/48726.xml">
occupational therapist</link>. Speech and language therapists also work closely with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/83441.xml">
parent</link>s and caregivers and other professionals, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/563683.xml">
audiologist</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/205075.xml">
teacher</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/55292.xml">
nurse</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/439999.xml">
dietitian</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/24022.xml">
physiotherapist</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/23315.xml">
doctor</link>s.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/2106968.xml">
Augmentative and alternative communication</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/872782.xml">
Esophageal speech</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/17884869.xml">
List of university speech-language pathology departments</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../619/185619.xml">
List of voice disorders</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/3063065.xml">
Oral myology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/25037.xml">
Phonation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<pathological_state wordnetid="114051917" confidence="0.8">
<disorder wordnetid="114052403" confidence="0.8">
<condition wordnetid="113920835" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<disability wordnetid="114548343" confidence="0.8">
<physical_condition wordnetid="114034177" confidence="0.8">
<unfitness wordnetid="114547369" confidence="0.8">
<ill_health wordnetid="114052046" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/1688561.xml">
Specific language impairment</link></ill_health>
</unfitness>
</physical_condition>
</disability>
</state>
</condition>
</disorder>
</pathological_state>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/28448.xml">
Speech processing</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asha.org">
American Speech-Language-Hearing Association</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aslpmalta.org">
Association of Speech Language Pathologists Malta</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.caslpa.ca/english/index.asp">
Canadian Association of Speech-Language Pathologists and Audiologists</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ishaindia.org">
Indian Speech and Hearing Association</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.rcslt.org/">
Royal College of Speech and Language Therapists.</weblink> (UK)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.saslha.co.za/">
South African Speech Language Hearing Association</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.speechpathologyaustralia.org.au">
Speech Pathology Australia</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/50643.xml">
Health science</link> &amp;gt; <occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/2603832.xml">
Allied health professions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/1742971.xml">
Athletic training</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/1050386.xml">
Audiology</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/7738.xml">
Chiropractic</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/8005.xml">
Dentistry</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/1560270.xml">
Dental hygiene</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/439999.xml">
Dietetics</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/76988.xml">
Electrocardiographic technicians</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/52975.xml">
Emergency medical services</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/590920.xml">
Hemodialysis technicians</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/43945.xml">
Massage therapy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/2243764.xml">
Medical assistant</link>s •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/202584.xml">
Medical physics</link> •
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/3770891.xml">
Medical technologist</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 •
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/3940866.xml">
Medical transcription</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 •
<occupation wordnetid="100582388" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/217662.xml">
Music therapy</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</occupation>
 •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/347838.xml">
Nuclear medicine technology</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
Nutrition</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/334037.xml">
Occupational therapy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/181226.xml">
Optometry</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/297350.xml">
Pharmacy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/234819.xml">
Phlebotomy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/2447242.xml">
Orthotics</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/72750.xml">
Prosthetics</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/24022.xml">
Physical therapy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/594086.xml">
Podiatry</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
Psychology</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/463734.xml">
Public health</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/26350.xml">
Radiation therapy</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/95807.xml">
Radiography</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/5399622.xml">
Radiologic technologist</link> •
<work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<treatment wordnetid="100658082" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<care wordnetid="100654885" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/48614.xml">
Respiratory therapy</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</care>
</event>
</treatment>
</work>
 •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/7032057.xml">
Speech and language pathology</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/146717.xml">
Social work</link> •
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/143357.xml">
Ultrasonography</link></p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</occupation>
</article>
