<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:40:17[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Rail inspection</title>
<id>7056262</id>
<revision>
<id>237200211</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-09T02:48:10Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Spencersutton</username>
<id>2260380</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Rail transport</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="An_Inspection_Car_on_the_Pennsylvania_Railroad.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<it>An Inspection Car on the <railway wordnetid="104048568" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<enterprise wordnetid="108056231" confidence="0.8">
<carrier wordnetid="108057633" confidence="0.8">
<business wordnetid="108061042" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/320965.xml">
Pennsylvania Railroad</link></institution>
</business>
</carrier>
</enterprise>
</company>
</railway>
</it>, an 1882 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/1119882.xml">
wood engraving</link> from <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/409207.xml">
Harper's Weekly</link></publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</press>
</creation>
</print_media>
</magazine>
</product>
</work>
''</it>
</caption>
</image>

<b>Rail inspection</b> is the practice of examining <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/321365.xml">
rail tracks</link> for flaws that could lead to catastrophic failures.  According to the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/1704678.xml">
Federal Railroad Administration</link> Office of Safety Analysis,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> track defects are the second leading cause of accidents on railways in the United States.  The leading cause of railway accidents is attributed to human error.  The contribution of poor management decisions to rail accidents caused by infrequent or inadequate rail inspection is significant but not reported by the FRA, only the NTSB.  Every year, North American railroads spend millions of dollars to inspect the rails for internal and external flaws.  <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/255047.xml">
Nondestructive testing</link></method>
</know-how>
 (NDT) methods are used as a preventative measures against track failures and possible derailment.  
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

<image width="300px" src="An_Inspection_Car_En_Route.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<it>An Inspection Car En Route</it>, 1891
</caption>
</image>

The first rail inspections were done visually.  Many sources cite that the need for better rail inspections came after a derailment at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/259945.xml">
Manchester, New York</link>, in 1911.  That particular accident resulted in the death of 29 people and injuries to 60 others.  The investigation of the accident revealed that the cause was a transverse fissure (a critical crack which lies perpendicular to the length of the rail) in the rail.  Further investigation in the late 1920s showed that this type of defect was quite common.  With increased rail traffic at higher speeds and with heavier axle loads today, critical crack sizes are shrinking and rail inspection is becoming more important.  In 1927, Dr. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/363829.xml">
Elmer Sperry</link> built a massive <link>
rail inspection car</link> under contract with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/1959998.xml">
American Railway Association</link>.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/148295.xml">
Magnetic induction</link> was the method used on the first rail inspection cars.  This was done by passing large amounts of magnetic field through the rail and detecting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/43590.xml">
flux</link> leakage with search coils.  Since then, many other inspection cars have traversed the rails in search of flaws.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Defects and location</st>
<p>

There are many effects that influence rail defects and rail failure.  These effects include bending and shear stresses, wheel/rail contact stresses, thermal stresses, residual stresses and dynamic effects.</p>
<p>

Defects due to contact stresses or rolling contact fatigue (RCF):
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

tongue lipping</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

head checking (gauge corner cracking)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

squats - which start as small surface breaking cracks</entry>
</list>

Other forms of surface and internal defects:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/155443.xml">
corrosion</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

inclusions</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

seams</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

shelling</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

transverse fisures</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

wheel burn</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

One effect that can cause crack propagation is the presence of water and other liquids.  When a fluid fills a small crack and a train passes over, the water becomes trapped in the void and can expand the crack tip.  Also, the trapped fluid could freeze and expand or initiate the corrosion process.</p>
<p>

Parts of a rail where defects can be found:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

head</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

web</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

foot</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

switchblades</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

welds</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

bolt holes</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A majority of the flaws found in rails are located in the head, however, flaws are also found in the web and foot.  This means that the entire rail needs to be inspected.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
NDT methods</st>
<p>

A list of methods used to detect flaws in rails:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../780/31780.xml">
Ultrasound</link> - the most popular method</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/465008.xml">
Eddy current</link> inspection - great for surface flaws &amp; near surface flaws</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Magnetic Particle Inspection</link> (MPI) - used for detailed manual inspection</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/95807.xml">
Radiography</link> - used on specific locations (often predetermined) such as bolt holes and where <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/3629158.xml">
thermite welding</link> was used</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/148295.xml">
Magnetic induction</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/3168401.xml">
Magnetic flux leakage</link> - earliest method used to locate unseen flaws in the railway industry</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/12389063.xml">
EMAT</link> Electromagnetic Acoustic Transducer</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Utilizing NDT methods</st>
<p>

The techniques mentioned above are utilized in a handful of different ways.  The probes and transducers can be utilized on a “walking stick”, on a hand pushed trolley, or in a hand held setup.  These devices are used when small sections of track are to be inspected or when a precise location is desired.  Many times these detail oriented inspection devices  follow up on indications made by a rail inspection cars or HiRail trucks.  Handheld inspection devices are very useful for this when the track is used heavily, because they can be removed relatively easy.  However, they are considered very slow and tedious, when there are thousands of miles of track that need inspection.  </p>
<p>

Rail <link>
inspection car</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/2627816.xml">
HiRail truck</link>s are the answer to today’s high mileage inspection needs.  The first rail inspection cars were created by Dr. Sperry.  Since then, many new models have rolled out.  These rail inspection cars are basically their own train with inspection equipment on board.  The probes and transducers are mounted on carriages located underneath the inspection car.  Modern day inspection cars now use multiple NDT methods.  Induction and ultrasound methods can be used in rail inspection cars and operate at testing speeds of more than 30&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/182283.xml">
mph</link> (48&nbsp;<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../755/662755.xml">
km/h</link>).  The next generation will go even faster.</p>
<p>

There are many manufacturers of road/rail inspection trucks, otherwise known as HiRail trucks.  These HiRail inspection cars are almost all ultrasonic testing exclusively, but there are some with the capability to perform multiple tests.  These trucks are loaded with high speed computers using advanced programs which recognize patterns and contain classification information.  The trucks are also equipped with storage space, tool cabinets, and workbenches.  A <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
GPS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 unit is used with the computer to mark new defects and locate previously marked defects.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/1704678.xml">
Federal Railroad Administration</link> (FRA) requires that any indications of defects need to be hand verified immediately.  The GPS system allows a follow up car to find precisely where the flaw was detected by the lead vehicle.  One advantage to the HiRail trucks is that they can work around regular rail traffic without shutting down or slowing down entire stretches of track.  However, because railroad management frequently orders HiRail trucks to be used to inspect tracks at speeds over 50 mph, tracks reported as having been inspected are, in fact, not inspected.  A NTSB report on the Amtrak derailment in Oregon in 2006 documented this fact.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The future of rail inspection</st>
<p>

With increased rail traffic carrying heavier loads at higher speeds, a quicker more efficient way of inspecting railways is needed. Lasers  inspect railway geometry, but one day they might be an utilized as a form of non-contact evaluation of the rail.  This most likely will be done with laser-optical transmitting transducers in ultrasonic testing.  Eliminating contact with the rail could one day allow high speed detection of flaws.  Another need for the future is a complete rail inspection system.  A step in this direction is deeper investigation of the rail by using low frequency eddy currents.  Other advancements could include neural network analysis of signals to improve defect detection and identification and longitudinal guided ultrasonics.  Improved rail quality, composition, and joining techniques could lead to better wear characteristics and a longer lifespan of the rail.  Some investigation into banitic steels looks promising.  A safe and portable means of filmless radiography could assist with onsite defect evaluation.  These are just a few advancements in the process of being developed for future use.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/1152365.xml">
maintenance of way</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/255047.xml">
nondestructive testing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/321365.xml">
rail tracks</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://safetydata.fra.dot.gov/officeofsafety/">
Federal Railroad Administration</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cannon, D. F., Edel, K.-O., Grassie, S. L. &amp; Sawley, K. “Rail defects: an overview.” <it>Fracture &amp; Fatigue of Engineering Material &amp; Structures</it>. vol. 26. no.10. pp. 865-886.  Oct. 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Eddy Current Inspection</it>.  GE Inspection Technologies Ltd. – Hocking.  April 5, 2005. http://www.hocking.com/applications/rail/.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Federal Railroad Administration, Office of Safety Analysis.  “Train Accidents by Type and Major Cause from Form: FRA F 6180.54. Jan.-Dec, 2004.”  April 6, 2005. http://safetydata.fra.dot.gov/officeofsafety/.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>G-Scan</it>.  “Practical Application”  Guided Ultrasonics (Rail) Ltd. April 6, 2005. http://www.guided-ultrasonics.com/rail/index.html.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Judge, Tom, engr. ed.  “Looking for flaws in all the right places.”  <it>Railway Age</it>. vol. 203. no.12. pp. 29-31.  Dec. 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Keefe, Kevin P.  “Track classifications - Classifying and inspecting railroad track.” <it>Trains Magazine</it>.  Sept. 10, 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

National Transportation Safety Board.  April 6, 2005.  www.ntsb.gov.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ndt-ed.org/AboutNDT/SelectedApplications/RailInspection/RailInspection.htm">
Rail Inspection</weblink></it>.  NDT Resource Center.  April 5, 2005.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.cater.fcpl.com.au</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.dapcondt.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.sperryrail.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.trak-tech.com</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.ensco.com/index.cfm?page=305</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.wavesinsolids.com/index11.html</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.tokimec.co.jp/rail/e/car.html</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://www.mermec.com</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
