<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:46:05[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<work  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100575741">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<service  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100577525">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Business Process Network</title>
<id>7068326</id>
<revision>
<id>222272048</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-28T13:02:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cydebot</username>
<id>1215485</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Supply chain management</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>Service-oriented (business computing)</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Process management</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from January 2008</category>
<category>Web services</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Business_Process_Network&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Business+Process+Network%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(January 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<b>Business process networks</b> (<b>BPN</b>), also referred to as <b>business service networks</b> or <b>business process hubs</b>, enable the efficient execution of multi-enterprise operational processes, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/186493.xml">
supply chain</link> planning and execution.</p>
<p>

To execute such processes, BPNs combine integration services with application services, often to support a particular industry or process, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../373/7794373.xml">
order management</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/77547.xml">
logistics</link> management, automated shipping and receiving, and others.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Why? </st>

<p>

Most organizations derive their primary value (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/247120.xml">
revenue</link>) and attain their goals outside of the 'four walls' of the enterprise-—by selling to consumers (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/3696159.xml">
B2C</link>) or to other businesses (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/1678261.xml">
B2B</link>)--thus the importance of efficiently enabling and managing processes that span multiple organizations.  This inherently includes supply chain management as well, and BPNs are gaining in popularity because of the changing nature of supply chains.  </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 The problems </st>

<p>

Today’s supply chains have become truly global.  Trends such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/10084075.xml">
global sourcing</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/529536.xml">
offshoring</link> to Asia, India and other low-cost production regions of the world continue to add complexity to effective trading partner management and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/27995.xml">
supply chain</link> visibility.</p>
<p>

At the same time, the transition to global sourcing will be challenging for most companies.  Few companies have the requisite strategies, infrastructure and extended process control to effectively make the transition to global sourcing.  </p>
<p>

The majority of supply managers continue to use a mix of e-mail, phone and fax to collaborate with offshore suppliers—-none of which are standardized nor easily integrated to enable informed business decisions and actions.</p>
<p>

Further, distant trading partners introduce new standards, new systems, multiple time zones, new processes and different levels of technological maturity into the supply chain.  </p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 How BPNs can help </st>

<p>

BPNs help reduce this complexity by providing a common framework for information exchange, visibility and collaboration.</p>
<p>

BPNs are also increasingly being used to enable and manage operational, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/1187175.xml">
business process outsourcing</link> (<b>BPO</b>) functions such as human resources, finance, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
information technology</link> (<b>IT</b>) and other ‘non-core’ (relative to each business) business functions, whereby the BPN facilitates collaboration and document movement between an organization and its outsourcing firm.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 How BPNs are implemented </st>

<p>

BPNs can be implemented using a host of technology platforms, including but not limited to traditional <information wordnetid="105816287" confidence="0.8">
<datum wordnetid="105816622" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/9790.xml">
EDI</link></datum>
</information>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/339215.xml">
value-added network</link>s (<b>VAN</b>s), industry exchanges, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/7003667.xml">
B2B Gateway</link>s, point to point integration brokers, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/147130.xml">
VPNs</link>, and other mechanisms that enable trading partners to connect electronically, collaborate and conduct business amongst each other. </p>
<p>

BPNs are being further accelerated by growth in Web services and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/666924.xml">
service-oriented architecture</link>s (<b>SOA</b>), technologies that simplify the integration of people, processes and systems.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Usage paradigms </st>

<p>

Business Process Networks are often managed using multi-tenant architectures to more rapidly enable seamless, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../970/2146970.xml">
many-to-many</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/2621383.xml">
one-to-many</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/285734.xml">
hub-spoke model</link>) connectivity between trading partners across the extended supply chain.</p>
<p>

Multi-tenant frameworks also ensure that all trading partners work from a single, shared set of applications and collaboration tools which are hosted by the network provider, mitigating integration barriers and hurdles from heterogeneous back-end IT infrastructures and systems across the trading community.  </p>
<p>

VANs and industry exchanges bring the added benefit of pre-connected trading partners, often ranging in the tens of thousands, that enable faster trading community implementation and lower overall cost to manage and maintain these connections.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/203249.xml">
Process management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/2910429.xml">
Supply network</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</article>
