<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:32:58[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<model  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110324560">
<assistant  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109815790">
<worker  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109632518">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<header>
<title>Quantum circuit</title>
<id>707404</id>
<revision>
<id>242381584</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T00:37:43Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Skippydo</username>
<id>4523461</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computational models</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing clarification</category>
<category>Quantum information science</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Ambox_?.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>All or part of this article may be .</b>
Please help . Suggestions may be on the . <it>(November 2007)</it></col>
</row>
</table>



<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/25274.xml">
quantum information theory</link>, a <b>quantum circuit</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
model</link> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/25220.xml">
quantum computation</link> in which a computation is a sequence of reversible transformations on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanical</link> analog of an <it>n</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/3364.xml">
bit</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/25996.xml">
register</link>. This analogous structure is referred to as an <it>n</it>-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/25284.xml">
qubit</link> register.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Reversible logic gates </st>

<p>

Ordinarily, in  a classical computer, the logic gates other than the NOT gate are not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1699635.xml">
reversible</link>. Thus, for instance, for an AND gate one cannot generally recover the two input bits from the output bit; the case <it>both</it> input bits are 1 is the exception.  However, as a first step in describing a quantum computing device it is instructive to observe that reversible gates are theoretically possible; moreover, these are actually of practical interest, since they do not increase <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/9891.xml">
entropy</link>. A reversible gate is a reversible function on  <it>n</it>-bit data that returns  <it>n</it>-bit data,  where an <it>n</it>-bit datum is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/27701.xml">
string</link> of bits <it>x</it>1,<it>x</it>2, ...,<it>xn</it>  of length  <it>n</it>.   The set of <it>n</it>-bit data is the space {0,1}<it>n</it>.  </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An <it>n</it>-bit reversible gate is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/3942.xml">
bijective</link> mapping <it>f</it> from the set {0,1}<it>n</it> of <it>n</it>-bit data to itself. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In fact we are only interested in maps <it>f</it> which are different from the identity, and for reasons of practical engineering we are only interested in gates for small values of <it>n</it>, e.g. <it>n</it>=1, <it>n</it>=2 or <it>n</it>=3.  These gates can be easily described by tables.  Examples of these logic gates which have been studied are the controlled NOT gate (also called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/3010688.xml">
CNOT</link> gate), the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/343286.xml">
Toffoli gate</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/1636691.xml">
Fredkin gate</link>.</p>
<p>

To consider quantum gates, we first need to specify the quantum replacement of an <it>n</it>-bit datum.</p>
<p>

The <it>quantized version</it> of classical <it>n</it>-bit space {0,1}<it>n</it> is </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>H_{\operatorname{QB}(n)}= \ell^2(\{0,1\}^n).</math>
</indent>

This is by definition the space of complex-valued functions on {0,1}<it>n</it> and is naturally an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/14856.xml">
inner product space</link>.   This space can also be regarded as consisting of linear superpositions of classical bit strings. </p>
<p>

Using Dirac <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/4542.xml">
ket</link> notation, if <it>x</it>1,<it>x</it>2, ...,<it>xn</it> is a classical bit string, then 
<indent level="1">

<math> | x_1, x_2, \cdots,x_n \rangle \quad </math>
</indent>
is an  <it>n</it>-qubit; these special <it>n</it>-qubits (of which there are 2<it>n</it>) are called <it>computational basis states</it>. All <it>n</it>-qubits are complex linear combinations of computational basis states.  Note that  <it>H</it>QB(<it>n</it>) has complex <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/8398.xml">
dimension</link> 2<it>n</it>.</p>
<p>

For a quantum computer we are also interested in reversible gates, but this time we are interested in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/225999.xml">
unitary</link> mappings, that is those that preserve the inner product on <it>H</it>QB(<it>n</it>). </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An <it>n</it>-qubit reversible gate is a unitary mapping <it>U</it> from the space  <it>H</it>QB(<it>n</it>) of qubits of size <it>n</it> onto itself. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Again we are only interested in unitary operators <it>U</it> which are different from the identity and we are only interested in gates for small values of <it>n</it>. In fact, reversible classical <it>n</it>-bit logic gates give rise to reversible <it>n</it>-bit quantum gates as follows:  to each reversible n-bit logic gate <it>f</it>  corresponds a quantum gate <it>Wf</it> defined as follows:
<indent level="1">

<math> W_f( | x_1, x_2, \cdots,x_n \rangle) = |f(x_1, x_2, \cdots, x_n) \rangle. </math>
</indent>
Of particular importance is the quantized 2 qubit CNOT gate <it>W</it>CNOT.  Of course there are many other, properly quantum gates.  For example, a relative phase shift is a 1 qubit gate given by multiplication by the unitary matrix:
<indent level="1">

<math> U_\theta =\begin{bmatrix} e^{i \theta} &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 1 \end{bmatrix}, </math>
</indent>
so 
<indent level="1">

<math> U_\theta | 0 \rangle = e^{i \theta}  | 0 \rangle \quad U_\theta | 1 \rangle = | 1 \rangle. </math>
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Reversible circuits </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/1539548.xml">
reversible computing</link></it>
</indent>

Again we consider first <it>reversible</it> classical computation.  Conceptually there is no difference between a reversible <it>n</it> bit  circuit and a reversible <it>n</it> bit logical gate: it is just an invertible function on the space of <it>n</it> bit data. However, as we mentioned in the previous section, for engineering reasons we would like to have a small number of reversible gates, that can be put together to assemble any reversible circuit. To explain this assembly process, suppose we have a reversible <it>n</it> bit gate <it>f</it> and  a reversible  <it>m</it> bit gate <it>g</it>.  Putting them together means producing a new circuit by connecting some set <it>k</it>  <it>n</it> of the outputs of <it>f</it> to some set of <it>k</it> inputs of <it>g</it> as in the figure below.  In that figure <it>n</it>=5, <it>k</it> =3 and <it>m</it> = 7. The resulting circuit is also reversible and operates on <it>n</it>+<it>m</it> -<it>k</it> bits.</p>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Reversible_circuit_composition.svg">
<caption>

Reversible circuit composition.svg
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<p>

We will refer to this scheme as a <it>classical assemblage</it>; (Remark: this concept corresponds to a technical definition in Kitaev's pioneering paper cited below.) In composing these reversible machines, it is important to insure that the intermediate machines are also reversible.  This condition assures that  <it>intermediate</it> garbage is not created (the net physical effect would be to increase entropy, which is one of the motivations for going through  this exercise). Now it is possible to show that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/343286.xml">
Toffoli gate</link> is a <link>
universal gate</link>. This means that given any reversible classical <it>n</it> bit circuit <it>h</it>, we can construct a classical assemblage of Toffoli gates in the above manner to produce an  <it>n</it>+<it>m</it> bit circuit <it>f</it> such that
<indent level="1">

<math> f(x_1, \ldots, x_n, \underbrace{0, \dots, 0}) = (y_1, \ldots, y_n, \underbrace{0, \ldots , 0})</math>
</indent>
where there are <it>m</it> underbraced zeroed inputs and 
<indent level="1">

<math> (y_1, \ldots, y_n) = h(x_1, \ldots, x_n) </math>
</indent>
Notice that at the end result has always a string of <it>m</it> zeros as the ancilla bits! No rubbish is ever produced, and so this computation is indeed one that, in a physical sense, generates no entropy.  This issue is carefully discussed in Kitaev's article.</p>
<p>

It follows immediately from this result that any function <it>f</it> (bijective or not) can be simulated by a circuit of Toffoli gates. Obviously, if the mapping fails to be injective, at some point in the simulation (for example as the last step) some garbage has to be produced.</p>
<p>

For quantum circuits a similar composition of qubit gates can be defined.  That is associated to any <it>classical assemblage</it> as above, we can produce a reversible quantum circuit when in place of <it>f</it> we have an <it>n</it> qubit gate <it>U</it> and in place of <it>g</it> we have an <it>m</it> qubit gate <it>W</it>. See illustration below:</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Q-circuit-comp.svg">
<caption>

Q-circuit-comp.svg
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<p>

The fact that connecting gates this way gives rise to a unitary mapping on <it>n</it>+<it>m</it> -<it>k</it> qubit space is an easy check, which should not concern the non-expert reader. It should also be noted that in a real quantum computer the physical connection between the gates is a major engineering challenge, since it is one of the places where decoherence may actually occur. </p>
<p>

There is also a universality theorem for sets of well known gates; such a universality theorem exists for instance, for the pair consisting of the single qubit phase gate <it>U</it>θ mentioned above for some reasonable value of θ together with the 2 qubit CNOT gate <it>W</it>CNOT). However the universality theorem is  somewhat weaker in the case of quantum computation, namely that any reversible <it>n</it> qubit circuit can be <it>approximated</it> arbitrarily well by circuits assembled from these two elementary gates. Note that there are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/32248.xml">
uncountably</link> many possible single qubit phase gates, one for every possible angle θ, so uncountably many of these gates cannot be represented by any finite circuit constructed from {<it>U</it>θ, <it>W</it>CNOT)}.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Quantum computations </st>

<p>

So far we have not shown how quantum circuits are used to perform computations.  Since many important numerical problems reduce to computing a unitary transformation <it>U</it> on a finite dimensional space (the celebrated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/8811.xml">
discrete Fourier transform</link> 
being a prime example) one might expect that some quantum circuit could be designed to carry out the transformation <it>U</it>. In principle, one needs only to prepare a <it>n</it> qubit state ψ as an appropriate superposition of computational basis states for the input and measure the output <it>U</it>ψ.  Unfortunately, there are two problems with this:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 One cannot measure the phase of ψ at any computational basis state so there is no way of reading out the complete answer. This is in the nature of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/573875.xml">
measurement in quantum mechanics</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is no way to efficiently prepare the input state ψ. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This does not prevent quantum circuits for the discrete Fourier transform from being used as intermediate steps in other quantum circuits, but the use is more subtle.  In fact quantum computations are <it>probabilistic</it>.</p>
<p>

We now provide a mathematical model for how quantum circuits can simulate
<it>probabilistic</it> but classical computations.  Consider an <it>r</it>-qubit circuit <it>U</it> with
register space <it>H</it>QB(<it>r</it>). <it>U</it> is thus a unitary map
<indent level="1">

<math>H_{\operatorname{QB}(r)} \rightarrow
H_{\operatorname{QB}(r)}.</math>
</indent>

In order to associate this circuit to a classical mapping on bitstrings, we specify</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An <it>input register</it> <it>X</it> = {0,1}<it>m</it> of <it>m</it> (classical) bits.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An <it>output register</it> <it>Y</it> = {0,1}<it>n</it> of <it>n</it> (classical) bits. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The contents <it>x</it> = <it>x</it>1, ..., <it>xm</it> of
the classical input register are used to initialize the qubit
register in some way.  Ideally, this would be done with the computational basis
state 
<indent level="1">

<math> |\vec{x},0\rangle= | x_1, x_2, \cdots, x_n, \underbrace{0, \dots, 0} \rangle </math> 
</indent>
where there are <it>r</it>-<it>m</it> underbraced zeroed inputs.  Nevertheless,
this perfect initialization is completely unrealistic.  Let us assume
therefore that the initialization is a mixed state given by some density operator <it>S</it> which is near the idealized input in some appropriate metric, e.g.
<indent level="1">

<math> \operatorname{Tr}\left(\big||\vec{x},0\rangle \langle \vec{x},0 | - S\big|\right) \leq \delta </math>
</indent>

Similarly, the output register space is related to the qubit register, by a <it>Y</it>
valued observable <it>A</it>. Note that observables in quantum mechanics are usually defined in
terms of <it>projection valued measures</it> on <b>R</b>; if the variable
happens to be discrete, the projection valued measure reduces to a
family {Eλ} indexed on some parameter λ
ranging over a countable set.  Similarly, a <it>Y</it> valued observable,
can be associated with a family of pairwise orthogonal projections
{E<it>y</it>} indexed by elements of <it>Y</it>.  such that
<indent level="1">

<math> I = \sum_{y \in Y} \operatorname{E}_y. </math>
</indent>

Given a mixed state <it>S</it>, there corresponds a probability measure on <it>Y</it>
given by 
<indent level="1">

<math> \operatorname{Pr}\{y\} = \operatorname{Tr}(S \operatorname{E}_y ) </math>
</indent>
</p>
<p>

The function <it>F</it>:<it>X</it> → <it>Y</it> is computed by a circuit
<it>U</it>:<it>H</it>QB(<it>r</it>) → <it>H</it>QB(<it>r</it>) to within ε if and only if
for all bitstrings <it>x</it> of length <it>m</it>
<indent level="1">

<math>\left\langle \vec{x},0 \big| U^* \operatorname{E}_{F(x)} U
\big|\vec{x},0 \right\rangle = \left\langle \operatorname{E}_{F(x)} U( |\vec{x},0\rangle) \big|  U( |\vec{x},0\rangle) \right\rangle \geq 1 - \epsilon</math>
</indent>
</p>
<p>

Now 
<indent level="1">

<math> \left| \operatorname{Tr} (S U^* \operatorname{E}_{F(x)} U) - \left\langle \vec{x},0 \big| U^* \operatorname{E}_{F(x)} U
\big|\vec{x},0 \right\rangle\right|\leq \operatorname{Tr} (\big||\vec{x},0\rangle \langle \vec{x},0 | - S\big|) \| U^* \operatorname{E}_{F(x)} U \| \leq \delta </math>
</indent>
so that
<indent level="1">

<math>\operatorname{Tr} (S U^* \operatorname{E}_{F(x)} U) \geq 1 - \epsilon - \delta</math>
</indent>

<b>Theorem</b>.  If  ε+ δ 1/2, then  the probability distribution 
<indent level="1">

<math> \operatorname{Pr}\{y\} = \operatorname{Tr} (S U^* \operatorname{E}_{y} U)</math>
</indent>
on <it>Y</it> can be used to determine <it>F</it>(<it>x</it>) with an arbitrarily  small probability of error by majority sampling, for a sufficiently large sample size.  Specifically, take <it>k</it> independent samples from the probability distribution Pr on <it>Y</it> and choose a value on which more than half of the samples agree. The probability that the value <it>F</it>(<it>x</it>) is sampled more than <it>k</it>/2 times is at least
<indent level="1">

<math> 1 - e^{- 2 \gamma^2 k} </math>
</indent>
where γ = 1/2 -ε - δ.  </p>
<p>

This follows by applying the <difference wordnetid="104748836" confidence="0.8">
<inequality wordnetid="104752221" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/741759.xml">
Chernoff bound</link></inequality>
</difference>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 E. Biham, G. Brassard, D. Kenigsberg, T. Mor, <it>Quantum Computing without Entanglement</it>, arXiv:quant-ph/0306182 v1, 2003.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 M. Freedman, A, Kitaev, M. Larsen and Z. Wang, <it>Topological Quantum Computation</it>, Bulletin of the AMS, 40:1,pp 31-38, 2002</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 M. Hirvensalo, <it>Quantum Computing</it>, Springer, 2001.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A. Kitaev, <it>Quantum Computations: Algorithms and Error Correction</it>, Russian Mathematical Surveys, 52:6, pp 1191-1249, 1997.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 M. Nielsen and I. Chuang, <it>Quantum Computation and Quantum Information</it>,  Cambridge University Press, 2000</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/25220.xml">
Quantum computing</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
General</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<unit_of_measurement wordnetid="113583724" confidence="0.8">
<definite_quantity wordnetid="113576101" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/25284.xml">
Qubit</link></definite_quantity>
</unit_of_measurement>
 • <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/25220.xml">
Quantum computer</link></group>
</collection>
</causal_agent>
</class>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/25274.xml">
Quantum information</link> • <paradigm wordnetid="113804375" confidence="0.8">
<linguistic_relation wordnetid="113797142" confidence="0.8">
<inflection wordnetid="113803782" confidence="0.8">
<grammatical_relation wordnetid="113796779" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/2137644.xml">
Quantum programming</link></grammatical_relation>
</inflection>
</linguistic_relation>
</paradigm>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../878/1911878.xml">
Quantum virtual machine</link> • <record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<chronology wordnetid="106503224" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<timeline wordnetid="106504965" confidence="0.8">
<written_record wordnetid="106502378" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/191911.xml">
Timeline of quantum computing</link></written_record>
</timeline>
</evidence>
</indication>
</chronology>
</record>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Quantum communication</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/1013550.xml">
Quantum channel</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/51910.xml">
Quantum cryptography</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/25280.xml">
Quantum teleportation</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/3423431.xml">
LOCC</link> • <link>
Entanglement distillation</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">

Quantum algorithms|Quantum algorithms</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/1136206.xml">
Universal quantum simulator</link> • <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/475310.xml">
Deutsch-Jozsa algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 • <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/58498.xml">
Grover's search</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 • <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/42674.xml">
Shor's factorization</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 • <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/11876741.xml">
Simon's Algorithm</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 • <class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../080/4080.xml">
(BQP)</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Quantum computing models</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/707404.xml">
Quantum circuit</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/888587.xml">
quantum gate</link>) • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/14240296.xml">
One-way quantum computer</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/14241236.xml">
cluster state</link>) • <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<theorem wordnetid="106752293" confidence="0.8">
<proposition wordnetid="106750804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/14436313.xml">
Adiabatic quantum computation</link></proposition>
</theorem>
</message>
</statement>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/185732.xml">
Decoherence</link>prevention</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/892803.xml">
Quantum error correction</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/4496518.xml">
Topological quantum computer</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<b>Physical implementations</b></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/658955.xml">
Quantum optics</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link>
Linear optics QC</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/16553854.xml">
Cavity QED</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/6393385.xml">
Ultracold atom</link>s</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/2095183.xml">
Trapped ion quantum computer</link> • <organ wordnetid="105297523" confidence="0.8">
<sense_organ wordnetid="105299178" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="109385911" confidence="0.8">
<eye wordnetid="105311054" confidence="0.8">
<body_part wordnetid="105220461" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/3800688.xml">
Optical lattice</link></body_part>
</eye>
</part>
</sense_organ>
</organ>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/19593829.xml">
Spin</link></concept>
</idea>
-based</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/5080727.xml">
Nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) quantum computing</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/537479.xml">
Kane QC</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/8481660.xml">
Loss-DiVincenzo (quantum dot) QC</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Other</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/1730328.xml">
Superconducting quantum computing</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/977983.xml">
Charge qubit</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/5260042.xml">
Flux qubit</link>) • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/14461309.xml">
Nitrogen-vacancy center</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
