<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:24:11[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Call centre</title>
<id>7243</id>
<revision>
<id>244162544</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T16:30:38Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Barek</username>
<id>1746167</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Telephony</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="200px" src="Callcentre.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A very large collections call center in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/109719.xml">
Lakeland, Florida</link></village>
.
</caption>
</image>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Telemarketoffice.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Call centre floor during shift.
</caption>
</image>

A <b>call centre</b> or <b>call center</b> (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/2053693.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22-re+.2F+-er%22])">
spelling differences</link>) is a centralized office used for the purpose of receiving and transmitting a large volume of requests by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/30003.xml">
telephone</link>.
A call centre is operated by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/4918223.xml">
company</link> to administer incoming product support or information inquiries from consumers. Outgoing calls for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/162180.xml">
telemarketing</link>, clientele, and debt collection are also made. In addition to a call centre, collective handling of <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/17845.xml">
letters</link></commodity>
</merchandise>
</artifact>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/10826.xml">
fax</link>es, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
e-mails</link> at one location is known as a <b>contact centre</b>.<p>

A call centre is often operated through an extensive open workspace for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/1555279.xml">
call centre agents</link>, with work stations that include a computer for each agent, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/30003.xml">
telephone</link> set/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/191884.xml">
headset</link> connected to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/59603.xml">
telecom switch</link>, and one or more supervisor stations. It can be independently operated or networked with additional centres, often linked to a corporate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/4122592.xml">
computer network</link>, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/20266.xml">
mainframes</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/48144.xml">
microcomputer</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/17739.xml">
LANs</link>. Increasingly, the voice and data pathways into the centre are linked through a set of new technologies called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/162190.xml">
computer telephony integration</link> (CTI).</p>
<p>

Most major businesses use call centres to interact with their customers.  Examples include utility companies, mail order catalogue firms, and customer support for computer hardware and software.  Some businesses even service internal functions through call centres.  Examples of this include help desks and sales support.</p>



<sec>
<st>
Call centre technology </st>
<p>

Call centre technology is subject to improvements and innovations. Some of these technologies include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/29468.xml">
speech recognition</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/42799.xml">
speech synthesis</link> software to allow computers to handle first level of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/638229.xml">
customer support</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/318439.xml">
text mining</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/21652.xml">
natural language processing</link> to allow better customer handling, agent training by automatic mining of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/805228.xml">
best practices</link> from past interactions, and many other technologies to improve agent productivity and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/3730788.xml">
customer satisfaction</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Automatic lead selection or lead stearing is also intended to improve efficiencies<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, both for inbound and outbound campaigns, whereby inbound calls are intended to quickly land with the appropriate agent to handle the task, whilst minimising wait times and long lists of irrelevant options for people calling in, as well as for outbound calls, where lead selection allows management to designate what type of leads go to which agent based on factors including skill, socio-economic factors and past performance and percentage likelihood of closing a sale per lead.
The concept of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/18900095.xml">
Universal Queue</link> standardises the processing of communications across multiple technologies such as fax, phone, and email.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Patents</st>

<p>

There are a large number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/23273.xml">
patent</link>s covering various aspects of call centre operation, automation, and technology.  One of the early inventors in this field, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<inventor wordnetid="110214637" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/9045054.xml">
Ronald A. Katz</link></creator>
</inventor>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, personally holds over 50 patents covering inventions related to toll free numbers, automated attendant, automated call distribution, voice response unit, computer telephone integration and speech recognition.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Call centre dynamics</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Eis_report2.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Typical report on the performance of an outbound call centre agent.
</caption>
</image>

Types of calls are often divided into <it>outbound</it> and <it>inbound</it>. Inbound calls are calls that are made by the consumer to obtain information, report a malfunction, or ask for help. These calls are substantially different from outbound calls, where agents place calls to potential customers mostly with intentions of selling or service to the individual. <it>(See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/162180.xml">
telemarketing</link>)</it>. It is possible to combine inbound and outbound campaigns,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> but it is not a common practice.</p>
<p>

Call centre staff are often organised into a multi-tier support system for a more efficient handling of calls. The first tier in such a model consists of operators, who direct inquiries to the appropriate department and provide general directory information. If a caller requires more assistance, the call is forwarded to the second tier, where most issues can be resolved. In some cases, there may be three or more tiers of support staff. If a caller requires more assistance, the caller is forwarded to the third tier of support; typically the third tier of support is formed by product engineers/developers or highly skilled technical support staff of the product. </p>
<p>

Call centres have their critics. Some critics argue that the work atmosphere in such an environment is de-humanising.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Others point to the low rates of pay and restrictive working practices of some employers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> There has been much controversy over such things as restricting the amount of time that an employee can spend in the toilet.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> Furthermore, call centres have been the subject of complaints by callers who find the staff often do not have enough skill or authority to resolve problems,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> while the dehumanised workers very often exhibit an attitude of apathy to even the most abusive customer.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

Owing to the highly technological nature of the operations in such offices, the close monitoring of staff activities is easy and widespread.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> This can be argued to be beneficial,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> to enable the company to better plan the workload and time of its employees. Some people have argued that such close monitoring breaches human rights to privacy.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Varieties of call centres</st>

<p>

Some variations of call centre models are listed below:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Remote Agents</it> – An alternative to housing all agents in a central facility is to use remote agents. These agents work from home and use internet technologies to connect.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Temporary Agents</it> – Temporary agents who are called upon if demand increases more rapidly than planned. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Virtual Call centres</it> – Virtual Call centres are created using many smaller centres in different locations and connecting them to one another. There are two methods used to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/925465.xml">
route</link> traffic around call centres: pre-delivery and post-delivery. Pre-delivery involves using an external switch to route the calls to the appropriate centre and post-delivery enables call centres to route a call they've received to another call centre.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Contact centres</it> – Deal with more media than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/41831.xml">
telephony</link> alone including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/9738.xml">
Email</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/1431240.xml">
Web Callback</link> and internet <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/40390.xml">
Chat</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Criticism &amp; performance of call centres </st>

<p>

Criticisms of call centres generally follow a number of common themes, from both callers and call centre staff. From callers, common criticisms include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Operators working from a script</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Non-expert operators (call screening)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Incompetent or untrained operators incapable of processing customers' requests effectively</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Overseas location, with language and accent problems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Automated queuing systems&mdash;this sometimes results in excessively long hold times</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Complaints that departments of companies do not engage in communication with one another</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deceit over location of call centre (such as allocating overseas workers false English names)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Requiring the caller to repeat the same information multiple times</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Common criticisms from staff include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Close scrutiny by management (e.g. frequent random call monitoring)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Low compensation (pay and bonuses)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Restrictive working practices (some operators are required to follow a pre-written script)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 High stress: a common problem associated with front-end jobs where employees deal directly with customers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Repetitive job task</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Poor working conditions (e.g. poor facilities, poor maintenance and cleaning, cramped working conditions, management interference, lack of privacy and noisy)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Impaired vision and hearing problems</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The net-net of these concerns is that call centers as a business process exhibit stratospheric levels of variability. The experience a customer gets and the results a company achieves on a given call are almost totally dependent on the quality of the agent answering that call.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> Call centers are beginning to address this by using technology to standardize the process all agents use.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> Anton and Phelps have provided a detailed HOWTO to conduct the performance evaluation of the business,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> whereas others are using various scientific technologies to do the jobs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> However more popular alternatives are using personality and skill based approaches.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> The various challenges encountered by call operators are discussed by several authors.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Unionization of call centers</st>
<p>

Unions in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/21139.xml">
North America</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 have made some effort to gain members from this sector,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref> including the <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/591645.xml">
Communications Workers of America</link></union>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
, the Call Centre Workers Union represents unionised workers; their activities form part of the Australian labor movement.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link>, Uni Global Union of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/26748.xml">
Switzerland</link></country>
 is involved in assisting unionization in this realm.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Standardization</st>
<p>

Currently, there are no universally bracketable international standards, other than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/147042.xml">
ISO 9000</link> series, available for the industry to follow up. However, there are some guidelines and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/3969853.xml">
standing operating procedure</link>s available on the internet.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mathematical theory</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/50578.xml">
Queuing theory</link> is a branch of mathematics in which <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/3151066.xml">
models of queuing</link> systems have been developed. A call center can be seen as a queuing network.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref> The models can be applied to answer queing questions for call centers.</p>
<p>

Call center operations have been supported by mathematical models beyond queuing, with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/43476.xml">
operations research</link>, which considers a wide range of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/52033.xml">
optimization problems</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/18299772.xml">
List of call centre companies</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<geographic_point wordnetid="108578706" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<workplace wordnetid="104602044" confidence="0.8">
<central wordnetid="102994858" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../749/40749.xml">
Automatic call distributor</link></central>
</workplace>
</location>
</geographic_point>
</point>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/3106770.xml">
Call center industry in the Philippines</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<distribution wordnetid="105729036" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/199028.xml">
Erlang distribution</link></distribution>
</arrangement>
</structure>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/7573262.xml">
Skills based routing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/250259.xml">
Queue management system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/7014943.xml">
Virtual queue</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
L Venkata Subramaniam&#32;(2008-02-01).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lvs004.googlepages.com/callcenters.pdf">
Call Centers of the Future</weblink>"&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link>)&#32;48-51.&#32;  i.t. magazine.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-29</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.patentstorm.us/patents/7035699/description.html">
US Patent 7035699 - Qualified and targeted lead selection and delivery system</weblink>".&#32;  Patent Storm&#32;(2006-04-25).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-29</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.findlaw.com/2004/Jun/9/133461.html">
Bednarek et al., "Katz Patent Reexamination: A Change in Momentum Favoring RAKTL Targets", ShawPittman, June 9, 2004</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
Freeman, Laura M&#59;&#32;Whitfield, Hilary C.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3700/is_199611/ai_n8743570">
Setting up for integrated inbound/outbound telemarketing</weblink>", <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/3069880.xml">
BNET</link></web_site>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eurofound.europa.eu/ewco/2005/04/SE0504NU02.htm">
Working conditions and health in Swedish call centres</weblink>".&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/2576527.xml">
European Foundation for the Improvement of Living and Working Conditions</link>&#32;(2005-04-28).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="6">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.payscale.com/research/US/Industry=Call_Center/Hourly_Rate">
Hourly Rate Survey Report for Industry: Call Center</weblink>".&#32;  <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/7805559.xml">
PayScale</link></company>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="7">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/lau/lacs/94-2.pdf">
Advice regarding call centre working practices</weblink>"&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link>).&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../308/361308.xml">
Health and Safety Executive</link>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="8">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hazards.org/toiletbreaks/index.htm">
Hazards 81 extended briefing: Toilet breaks: Give us a break!</weblink>".&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/10381331.xml">
Hazards</link>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="9">
Shaw, Russell&#32;(2006-01-30).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://blogs.zdnet.com/ip-telephony/?p=873">
Tone-deaf to customer complaints, Dell opens yet another call center in India</weblink>", <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/435858.xml">
ZDNet</link></web_site>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
Ahmed, Zubair&#32;(2006-02-22).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4738804.stm">
Abuse rattles Indian call centre staff</weblink>", <statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<announcement wordnetid="106746580" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106748466" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/1139893.xml">
BBC News</link></program>
</announcement>
</message>
</statement>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.callcentrehelper.com/call_centre_monitoring.htm">
Call Centre Monitoring</weblink>".&#32;<it>Management</it>.&#32;  callcentrehelper.com.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="12">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.callcentermagazine.com/shared/article/showArticle.jhtml?articleId=12803684">
The Call Center Answer Team reaches out to the industry for to crack a tough nut</weblink>".&#32;<it>Q&amp;A: How Many Calls Should I Monitor</it>.&#32;  callcentermagazine.com&#32;(2003-07-30).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="13">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acewh.dal.ca/eng/reports/moving6.pdf">
Who’s on the Line? Women in Call Centres Project</weblink>"&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/24077.xml">
PDF</link>).&#32;<it>Atlantic Centre of Excellence for Women's Health</it>.&#32;  <department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/216516.xml">
Health Canada</link></department>
.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-06-05</link>.</entry>
<entry id="14">
Fleming, J., Coffman, C., Harter, J. (2005) Manage Your Human Sigma, Harvard Business Review</entry>
<entry id="15">
Patel, S. (2008) How to win a no-sin situation. <it>In Queue</it>. http://www.nationalcallcenters.org/pubs/In_Queue/vol3no12.html#How_to_Win_a_No-Win_Situation</entry>
<entry id="17">
  <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Paprzycki, Marcin et al.&#32;(2004). Data Mining Approach for Analyzing Call Center Performance. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/b97304">
10.1007/b97304</weblink>. ISBN 9783540220077.</cite>&nbsp; </entry>
<entry id="16">
Anton, Jon;&#32;Dru Phelps.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://searchcrm.techtarget.com/searchCRM/downloads/HowToConducChapter2and9.pdf">
How to conduct a call center performance audit: A to Z</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="19">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Srinivasan, Raj et al.&#32;(2004).&#32;"Performance analysis of a call center with interactive voice response units". <it>TOP</it>&#32;<b>12</b>&#32;(1): 91 - 110.&#32;Springer Berlin. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2FBF02578926">
10.1007/BF02578926</weblink>. Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scholar.lib.vt.edu/theses/available/etd-04132003-184221/">
Evaluation of the Performance of customer service representatives in a call center using DEA/Network Model/Fussy Sets</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="21">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Stolletz, Raik; Stefan Helber&#32;(2004).&#32;"Performance analysis of an inbound call center with skills-based routing". <it>OR Spectrum</it>&#32;<b>26</b>&#32;(3): 331 - 352. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs00291-004-0161-y">
10.1007/s00291-004-0161-y</weblink>. Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
Skyrme, Pamela et al..&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://applyhrm.asp.radford.edu/Volume%2010/MS%2010_2_%20Abraham.pdf">
Using personality to predict outbound call center job performance</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="23">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Aguir, Salah et al.&#32;(2004).&#32;"The impact of retrials on call center performance". <it>OR Spectrum</it>&#32;<b>26</b>&#32;(3): 353 - 376. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs00291-004-0165-7">
10.1007/s00291-004-0165-7</weblink>. Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="22">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Witt, L. A. et al.&#32;(2004).&#32;"When Conscientiousness Isn’t Enough: Emotional Exhaustion and Performance Among Call Center Customer Service Representatives". <it>Journal of Management</it>&#32;<b>30</b>&#32;(1): 149 - 160. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.jm.2003.01.007">
10.1016/j.jm.2003.01.007</weblink>. Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="25">
Armony, Mor;&#32;Itay Gurvich.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gsb.stanford.edu/facseminars/pdfs/2006_12-08_Armony1.pdf">
When promotions meet operations: cross-selling and its effect on call-center performance</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="24">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Murthy, Nagesh N. et al.&#32;(2008).&#32;"The Impact of Simulation Training on Call Center Agent Performance: A Field-Based Investigation". <it>Mnagement Science</it>&#32;<b>54</b>&#32;(2): 384 - 399. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1287%2Fmnsc.1070.0818">
10.1287/mnsc.1070.0818</weblink>. Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="27">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">&#32;(2006) Paths to Union Renewal.&#32;Broadview Press. ISBN 1-55193-058-7.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="26">
Goldberg, L.S.;&#32;A.A. Grandey.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17638495">
Display rules versus display autonomy: emotion regulation, emotional exhaustion, and task performance in a call center simulation</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/15844.xml">
1 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="29">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://workers.labor.net.au/90/news22_call.html">
Call Centre Union Busters Get Wake-Up Call</weblink>".&#32;  Workers Online.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-08</link>.</entry>
<entry id="28">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uniglobalunion.org/UniTelecom.nsf/0/ADF36252C7AE907DC12574C900293C7A?OpenDocument">
AT&amp;T Mobility Workers Organize in Oklahoma City</weblink>".&#32;  Uni Global Union.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-09-27</link>.</entry>
<entry id="31">
Rochester Institute of Technology.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://finweb.rit.edu/buscont/docs/callcenterSOP.pdf">
Internal Call Center Standing Operating Procedures</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/15848.xml">
3 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="30">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uniglobalunion.org/uniindep.nsf/callcentres?openpage">
Uni Global Union's call center organizing campaigns</weblink>".&#32;  Uni Global Union.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-07-08</link>.</entry>
<entry id="34">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fic.wharton.upenn.edu/fic/papers/03/p0312.htmlStatistical">
Analysis of a Telephone Call Center: A Queueing-Science Perspective"
Lawrence Brown, Noah Gans, Avishai Mandelbaum, Anat Sakov, Haipeng Shen, Sergey Zeltyn and Linda Zhao, Novemer 2002 </weblink></entry>
<entry id="35">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.vu.nl/obp/callcenters/overview.pdf">
Queueing Models of Call Centers: An Introduction Ger Koole</weblink></entry>
<entry id="32">
Thinking problem management.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://thinkingproblemmanagement.blogspot.com/2007/10/documentation-techie-curse.html">
Documentation - the techie curse</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/15848.xml">
3 July</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>.</entry>
<entry id="33">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.vu.nl/~koole/ccmath/book.pdf">
Call Center Mathematics | A scientific method for understanding and improving contact centers by Ger Koole</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Kennedy I., <it>Call centres</it>, School of Electrical and Information Engineering, University of the Witwatersrand, 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Masi D.M.B., Fischer M.J., Harris C.M., <it>Numerical Analysis of Routing Rules for Call centres</it>, Telecommunications Review, 1998. http://www.noblis.org/Publications/TR98_8.doc</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 HSE Web site at <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/lau/lacs/94-2.htm">
www.hse.gov.uk/lau/lacs/94-2.htm</weblink> for guidelines about call centre working * practices.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fluss, Donna, "The Real-Time Contact centre", 2005 AMACOM</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
