<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:23:46[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Complexity</title>
<id>7363</id>
<revision>
<id>232895835</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-19T13:00:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>ClueBot</username>
<id>4928500</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Holism</category>
<category>Computational complexity theory</category>
<category>Abstraction</category>
<category>Transdisciplinarity</category>
<category>Complex systems theory</category>
<category>Systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/6532404.xml">
Complexity (disambiguation)</link>.
In general usage, <b>complexity</b> often tends to be used to characterize something with many parts in intricate arrangement. In science there are at this time a number of approaches to characterizing complexity, many of which are reflected in this article. <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/1451702.xml">
Seth Lloyd</link></scientist>
 of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/18879.xml">
M.I.T.</link> writes that he once gave a presentation which set out 32 definitions of complexity.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> <p>

Definitions are often tied to the concept of a ‘<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>’ – a set of parts or elements which have relationships among them differentiated from relationships with other elements outside the relational regime. Many definitions tend to postulate or assume that complexity expresses a condition of  numerous elements in a system and numerous forms of relationships among the elements. At the same time, what is complex and what is simple is relative and changes with time.</p>
<p>

Some definitions key on the question of the probability of encountering a given condition of a system once characteristics of the system are specified. Warren Weaver has posited that the complexity of a particular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link> is the degree of difficulty in predicting the properties of the system if the properties of the system’s parts are given.  In Weaver's view, complexity comes in two forms: disorganized complexity, and organized complexity.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> 
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/473287.xml">
Weaver’s</link></research_worker>
</mathematician>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 paper has influenced contemporary thinking about complexity.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

The approaches which embody concepts of systems, multiple elements, multiple relational regimes, and state spaces might be summarized as implying that complexity arises from the number of distinguishable relational regimes (and their associated state spaces) in a defined system. </p>
<p>

Some definitions relate to the algorithmic basis for the expression of a complex phenomenon or model or mathematical expression, as is later set out herein.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Disorganized complexity vs. organized complexity</st>
<p>

One of the problems in addressing complexity issues has been distinguishing conceptually between the large number of variances in relationships extant in random collections, and the sometimes large, but smaller, number of relationships between elements in systems where constraints (related to correlation of otherwise independent elements) simultaneously reduce the variations from element independence and create distinguishable regimes of more-uniform, or correlated, relationships, or interactions. </p>
<p>

Weaver perceived and addressed this problem, in at least a preliminary way, in drawing a distinction between 'disorganized complexity' and 'organized complexity'.</p>
<p>

In Weaver's view, disorganized complexity results from the particular system having a very large number of parts, say millions of parts, or many more.  Though the interactions of the parts in a 'disorganized complexity' situation can be seen as largely random, the properties of the system as a whole can be understood by using probability and statistical methods.  </p>
<p>

A prime example of disorganized complexity is a gas in a container, with the gas molecules as the parts.  Some would suggest that a system of disorganized complexity may be compared, for example, with the (relative) simplicity of the planetary orbits – the latter can be known by applying <link>
Newton’s laws of motion</link>, though this example involved highly correlated events.</p>
<p>

Organized complexity, in Weaver's view, resides in nothing else than the non-random, or correlated, interaction between the parts. These  non-random, or correlated, relationships create a differentiated structure which can, as a system, interact with other systems. The coordinated system manifests properties not carried by, or dictated by, individual parts.  The organized aspect of this form of complexity  vis a vis other systems than the subject system  can be said to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/37436.xml">
"emerge,"</link> without any “guiding hand.” </p>
<p>

The number of parts does not have to be very large for a particular system to have emergent properties.  A system of organized complexity may be understood in its properties (behavior among the properties) through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
modeling</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/43444.xml">
simulation</link>, particularly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/375416.xml">
modeling and simulation with computers</link>.  An example of organized complexity is a city neighborhood as a living mechanism, with the neighborhood people among the system’s parts.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources and factors of complexity</st>
<p>

The source of disorganized complexity is the large number of parts in the system of interest, and the lack of correlation between elements in the system.</p>
<p>

There is no consensus at present on general rules regarding the sources of organized complexity, though the lack of randomness implies correlations between elements. See e.g. Robert Ulanowicz's treatment of ecosystems. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Consistent with prior statements here, the number of parts (and types of parts) in the system and the number of relations between the parts would have to be non-trivial – however, there is no general rule to separate “trivial” from “non-trivial. </p>
<p>

Complexity of an object or system is a relative property. For instance, for many functions (problems), such a computational complexity as time of computation is smaller when multitape <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/30403.xml">
Turing machine</link></method>
</know-how>
</invention>
s are used than when <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/30403.xml">
Turing machine</link></method>
</know-how>
</invention>
s with one tape are used. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/544227.xml">
Random Access Machine</link>s allow one to even more decrease time complexity (Greenlaw and Hoover 1998: 226), while inductive Turing machines can decrease even the complexity class of a function, language or set (Burgin 2005). This shows that tools of activity can be an important factor of complexity.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Specific meanings of complexity </st>
<p>

In several scientific fields, "complexity" has a specific meaning :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/7543.xml">
computational complexity theory</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/4628222.xml">
amounts of resources</link> required for the execution of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s is studied. The most popular types of computational complexity are the time complexity of a problem equal to the number of steps that it takes to solve an instance of the problem as a function of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/89299.xml">
size of the input</link> (usually measured in bits), using the most efficient <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>, and the space complexity of a problem equal to the volume of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/5300.xml">
memory</link> used by the algorithm (e.g., cells of the tape) that it takes to solve an instance of the problem as a function of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/89299.xml">
size of the input</link> (usually measured in bits), using the most efficient <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>. This allows to classify computational problems by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/502426.xml">
complexity class</link> (such as <class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/658550.xml">
P</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
, <class wordnetid="107997703" confidence="0.8">
<collection wordnetid="107951464" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/21562.xml">
NP</link></group>
</collection>
</class>
 ... ). An axiomatic approach to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/7543.xml">
computational complexity</link> was developed by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/308357.xml">
Manuel Blum</link></scientist>
</person>
. It allows one to deduce many properties of concrete computational complexity measures, such as time complexity or space complexity, from properties of axiomatically defined measures.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/2829647.xml">
algorithmic information theory</link>, the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1635.xml">
Kolmogorov complexity</link></it> (also called <it>descriptive complexity</it>, <it>algorithmic complexity</it> or <it>algorithmic entropy</it>) of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/27701.xml">
string</link> is the length of the shortest binary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/5783.xml">
program</link> which outputs that string. Different kinds of Kolmogorov complexity are studied: the uniform complexity, prefix complexity, monotone complexity, time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity, and space-bounded Kolmogorov complexity. An axiomatic approach to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1635.xml">
Kolmogorov complexity</link> based on <maxim wordnetid="107152948" confidence="0.8">
<speech wordnetid="107109196" confidence="0.8">
<saying wordnetid="107151380" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/2392005.xml">
Blum axioms</link></auditory_communication>
</saying>
</speech>
</maxim>
 (Blum 1967) was introduced by Mark Burgin in the paper presented for publication by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/91161.xml">
Andrey Kolmogorov</link></scientist>
</person>
 (Burgin 1982). The axiomatic approach encompasses other approaches to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1635.xml">
Kolmogorov complexity</link>. It is possible to treat different kinds of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1635.xml">
Kolmogorov complexity</link> as particular cases of axiomatically defined generalized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/1635.xml">
Kolmogorov complexity</link>. Instead, of proving similar theorems, such as the basic invariance theorem, for each particular measure, it is possible to easily deduce all such results from one corresponding theorem proved in the axiomatic setting. This is a general advantage of the axiomatic approach in mathematics. The axiomatic approach to Kolmogorov complexity was further developed in the book (Burgin 2005) and applied to software metrics (Burgin and Debnath, 2003; Debnath and Burgin, 2003).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/315578.xml">
information processing</link>, complexity is a measure of the total number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/23626.xml">
properties</link> transmitted by an object and detected by an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/22649.xml">
observer</link>.  Such a collection of properties is often referred to as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/285512.xml">
state</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/773322.xml">
physical systems</link>, complexity is a measure of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/22934.xml">
probability</link> of the state vector of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>.  This should not be confused with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/302133.xml">
entropy</link>; it is a distinct mathematical measure, one in which two distinct states are never conflated and considered equal, as is done for the notion of entropy <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/28481.xml">
statistical mechanics</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/18831.xml">
mathematics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/513506.xml">
Krohn-Rhodes complexity</link> is an important topic in the study of finite <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/27799.xml">
semigroup</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/103356.xml">
automata</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

There are different specific forms of complexity: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In the sense of how complicated a problem is from the perspective of the person trying to solve it, limits of complexity are measured using a term from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/5961.xml">
cognitive psychology</link>, namely the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/435063.xml">
hrair limit</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Unruly complexity</link> denotes situations that do not have clearly defined boundaries, coherent internal dynamics, or simply mediated relations with their external context, as coined by Peter Taylor.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/1428810.xml">
Complex adaptive system</link> denotes systems which have some or all of the following attributes <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The number of parts (and types of parts) in the system and the number of relations between the parts is non-trivial – however, there is no general rule to separate “trivial” from “non-trivial;” </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The system has  memory or includes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/11545.xml">
feedback</link>;</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The system can adapt itself according to its history or feedback; </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The relations between the system and its environment are non-trivial or non-linear; and </entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The system can be influenced by, or can adapt itself to, its environment.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Study of complexity </st>
<p>

Complexity has always been a part of our environment, and therefore many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/26700.xml">
scientific</link> fields have dealt with complex systems and phenomena. Indeed, some would say that only what is somehow complex – what displays variation without being <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
random</link> – is worthy of interest.</p>
<p>

The use of the term complex is often confused with the term complicated. In today’s systems, this is the difference between myriad connecting "stovepipes" and effective "integrated" solutions. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> This means that complex is the opposite of independent, while complicated is the opposite of simple.</p>
<p>

While this has led some fields to come up with specific definitions of complexity, there is a more recent movement to regroup observations <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/15201.xml">
from different fields</link> to study complexity in itself, whether it appears in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/1056536.xml">
anthill</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/490620.xml">
human brain</link>s, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../328/52328.xml">
stock market</link>s. One such interndisciplinary group of fields is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../828/15046828.xml">
relational order theories</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Complexity topics </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Complex behaviour </st>
<p>

The behaviour of a complex system is often said to be due to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/37436.xml">
emergence</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../947/286947.xml">
self-organization</link>. <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/6295.xml">
Chaos theory</link></concept>
</idea>
 has investigated the sensitivity of systems to variations in initial conditions as one cause of complex behaviour. </p>
<p>

One of the main claims in <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/52469.xml">
Stephen Wolfram</link></scientist>
</person>
's book <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/93070.xml">
A New Kind of Science</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it> is that such behaviour can be generated by simple systems, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/491028.xml">
rule 110 cellular automaton</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Complex mechanisms </st>
<p>

Recent developments around <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/58656.xml">
artificial life</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../020/268020.xml">
evolutionary computation</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
genetic algorithm</link>s have led to an increasing emphasis on complexity and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/1428810.xml">
complex adaptive systems</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Complex simulations </st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/26781.xml">
social science</link>, the study on the emergence of macro-properties from the micro-properties, also known as macro-micro view in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/18717981.xml">
sociology</link>. The topic is commonly recognized as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/984629.xml">
social complexity</link> that is often related to the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/375416.xml">
computer simulation</link> in social science, i.e.: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/984692.xml">
computational sociology</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Complex systems </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/37438.xml">
Complex system</link></it>
</indent>
<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<branch wordnetid="108401248" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/29238.xml">
Systems theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</branch>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</process>
 has long been concerned with the study of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/37438.xml">
complex system</link>s (In recent times, <it>complexity theory</it> and <it>complex systems</it> have also been used as names of the field). These <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>s can be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biological</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/6639133.xml">
economic</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/29816.xml">
technological</link>, etc. Recently, complexity is a natural domain of interest of the real world socio-cognitive systems and emerging <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/346123.xml">
systemics</link> research. Complex systems tend to be high-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/8398.xml">
dimension</link>al,  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/146103.xml">
non-linear</link> and hard to model. In specific circumstances they may exhibit low dimensional behaviour.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Complexity in data </st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/14773.xml">
information theory</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/2829647.xml">
algorithmic information theory</link> is concerned with the complexity of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/27701.xml">
strings</link> of data. </p>
<p>

Complex strings are harder to compress.  While intuition tells us that this may depend on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../660/6660.xml">
codec</link> used to compress a string (a codec could be theoretically created in any arbitrary language, including one in which the very small command "X" could cause the computer to output a very complicated string like '18995316'"), any two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/30621.xml">
Turing-complete</link> languages can be implemented in each other, meaning that the length of two encodings in different languages will vary by at most the length of the "translation" language - which will end up being negligible for sufficiently large data strings.</p>
<p>

These algorithmic measures of complexity tend to assign high values to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/236932.xml">
random noise</link>. However, those studying complex systems would not consider <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
randomness</link> as complexity.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/15445.xml">
Information entropy</link> is also sometimes used in information theory as indicative of complexity.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Applications of complexity </st>
<p>
 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/7543.xml">
Computational complexity theory</link> is the study of the complexity of problems - that is, the difficulty of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/1467948.xml">
solving</link> them. Problems can be classified by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/502426.xml">
complexity class</link> according to the time it takes for an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> - usually a computer program - to solve them as a function of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/89299.xml">
problem size</link>. Some problems are difficult to solve, while others are easy. For example, some difficult problems need algorithms that take an exponential amount of time in terms of the size of the problem to solve. Take the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/31248.xml">
travelling salesman problem</link>, for example. It can be solved in time <math>O(n^2 2^n)</math> (where <it>n</it> is the size of the network to visit - let's say the number of cities the travelling salesman must visit exactly once). As the size of the network of cities grows, the time needed to find the route grows (more than) exponentially. </p>
<p>

Even though a problem may be computationally solvable in principle, in actual practice it may not be that simple.  These problems might require large amounts of time or an inordinate amount of space.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/7543.xml">
Computational complexity</link> may be approached from many different aspects. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/7543.xml">
Computational complexity</link> can be investigated on the basis of time, memory or other resources used to solve the problem.  Time and space are two of the most important and popular considerations when problems of complexity are analyzed.</p>
<p>

There exist a certain class of problems that although they are solvable in principle they require so much time or space that it is not practical to attempt to solve them. These problems are called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/7543.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Intractability%22])">
intractable</link>.</p>
<p>

There is another form of complexity called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/11911464.xml">
hierarchical complexity</link>. It is orthogonal to the forms of complexity discussed so far, which are called horizontal complexity</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/6295.xml">
Chaos theory</link></concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/6132.xml">
Complexity theory</link> (disambiguation page)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/8718538.xml">
Command and Control Research Program</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/11508558.xml">
Evolution of complexity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/317419.xml">
Game complexity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/1303219.xml">
Holism in science</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</field>
</region>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/330685.xml">
Interconnectedness</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/11911464.xml">
Model of hierarchical complexity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/36797.xml">
Occam's razor</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/6181775.xml">
Process architecture</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/2814347.xml">
Programming Complexity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<branch wordnetid="108401248" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../238/29238.xml">
Systems theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</branch>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../835/12261835.xml">
Variety (cybernetics)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../906/1014906.xml">
Cyclomatic complexity</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Lloyd, Seth, Programming the Universe, Knopf, 2006 </entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite id="CITEREFWeaver1948" style="font-style:normal">Weaver, Warren&#32;(1948),&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ceptualinstitute.com/genre/weaver/weaver-1947b.htm">
Science and Complexity</weblink>",&#32;<it>American Scientist</it>&#32;<b>36</b>:  536  (Retrieved on 2007-11-21.), </cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite id="Reference-Johnson-2001" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Johnson, Steven&#32;(2001). Emergence: the connected lives of ants, brains, cities, and software.&#32;New York:&#32;Scribner,&#32;p.46. ISBN 0-684-86875-X.</cite>&nbsp;.  
</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite id="Reference-Jacobs-1961" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Jacobs, Jane&#32;(1961). The Death and Life of Great American Cities.&#32;New York:&#32;Random House.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="5">
 Ulanowicz, Robert, "Ecology, the Ascendant Perspective", Columbia, 1997</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite id="Reference-Johnson-2007" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Johnson, Neil F.&#32;(2007). Two’s Company, Three is Complexity: A simple guide to the science of all sciences.&#32;Oxford:&#32;Oneworld. ISBN 978-1-85168-488-5.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="7">
(Lissack and Roos, 2000)</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Lewin-1992" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Lewin, Roger&#32;(1992). Complexity: Life at the Edge of Chaos.&#32;New York:&#32;Macmillan Publishing Co. ISBN 9780025704855.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Waldrop-1992" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Waldrop, M. Mitchell&#32;(1992). Complexity: The Emerging Science at the Edge of Order and Chaos.&#32;New York:&#32;Simon &amp; Schuster. ISBN 9780671767891.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Czerwinski-1997" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Czerwinski, Tom;&#32;David Alberts&#32;(1997). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dodccrp.org/files/Alberts_Complexity_Global.pdf">
Complexity, Global Politics, and National Security</weblink>.&#32;National Defense University. ISBN 9781579060466.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Czerwinski-1998" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Czerwinski, Tom&#32;(1998). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dodccrp.org/files/Czerwinski_Coping.pdf">
Coping with the Bounds: Speculations on Nonlinearity in Military Affairs</weblink>.&#32;CCRP. ISBN 9781414503158 (from Pavilion Press, 2004).</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Lissack-2000" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Lissack, Michael R.;&#32;Johan Roos&#32;(2000). The Next Common Sense, The e-Manager’s Guide to Mastering Complexity.&#32;Intercultural Press. ISBN 9781857882353.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Solé-2002" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Solé, R. V.;&#32;B. C. Goodwin&#32;(2002). Signs of Life: How Complexity Pervades Biology.&#32;Basic Books. ISBN 9780465019281.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Moffat-2003" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Moffat, James&#32;(2003). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dodccrp.org/files/Moffat_Complexity.pdf">
Complexity Theory and Network Centric Warfare</weblink>.&#32;CCRP. ISBN 9781893723115.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Smith-2006" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Smith, Edward&#32;(2006). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dodccrp.org/files/Smith_Complexity.pdf">
Complexity, Networking, and Effects Based Approaches to Operations</weblink>.&#32;CCRP. ISBN 9781893723184.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="CITEREF.5B.5BFrancis_Heylighen.7C_Heylighen.5D.5D2008" style="font-style:normal"><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/2291054.xml">
 Heylighen</link>, Francis&#32;(2008),&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pespmc1.vub.ac.be/Papers/ELIS-Complexity.pdf">
Complexity and Self-Organization</weblink>", in&#32;Bates, Marcia J.&#32;&amp;&#32;Maack, Mary Niles,&#32;<it>Encyclopedia of Library and Information Sciences</it>, CRC, ISBN 9780849397127</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Dombkins-2007" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Dombkins, D.H.&#32;(2007). [Complex Project Management].&#32;Booksurge. ISBN 9781419676901.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Greenlaw, N. and Hoover, H.J. <it>Fundamentals of the Theory of Computation</it>, Morgan Kauffman Publishers, San Francisco, 1998</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Blum, M. (1967) On the Size of Machines, <it>Information and Control</it>, v. 11, pp. 257-265 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Burgin, M. (1982) Generalized Kolmogorov complexity and duality in theory of computations, Notices of the Russian Academy of Sciences, v.25, No. 3, pp.19-23</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mark Burgin (2005), <it>Super-recursive algorithms</it>, Monographs in computer science, Springer.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Burgin, M. and Debnath, N. Hardship of Program Utilization and User-Friendly Software, in <it>Proceedings of the International Conference “Computer Applications in Industry and Engineering”</it>, Las Vegas, Nevada, 2003, pp. 314-317</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Debnath, N.C. and Burgin, M., (2003) Software Metrics from the Algorithmic Perspective, in <it>Proceedings of the ISCA 18th International Conference “Computers and their Applications”</it>, Honolulu, Hawaii, pp. 279-282</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.calresco.org/lucas/quantify.htm">
Quantifying Complexity Theory</weblink> - classification of complex systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cscs.umich.edu/~crshalizi/notebooks/complexity-measures.html">
Complexity Measures</weblink> - an article about the abundance of not-that-useful complexity measures.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/center/cac.html">
UC Four Campus Complexity Videoconferences</weblink> - Human Sciences and Complexity</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
