<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:55:51[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>MIRIAM</title>
<id>7420632</id>
<revision>
<id>237094959</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-08T17:00:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Perkeo</username>
<id>2341097</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Acronyms</category>
<category>Systems biology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="left" width="150px" src="MIRIAM_small_logo.png">
<caption>

logo of MIRIAM
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>MIRIAM</b> (Minimum Information Requested in the Annotation of biochemical Models)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, is an effort to standardize  the annotation and curation process of quantitative models of biological systems.</p>
<p>

The goal of the project, initiated by the BioModels.net<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> effort, is to produce a set of guidelines suitable for use with any structured format for computational models, as well as the software and services infrastructure, in order to allow different groups to collaborate on annotating and curating computational models in biology.</p>
<p>

<b>MIRIAM</b> is a registered project of the MIBBI (Minimum Information for Biological and Biomedical Investigations)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Standard </st>

<p>

<b>MIRIAM Standard</b> is composed of three parts: <it>reference correspondence</it>, <it>attribution annotation</it>, and <it>external resource annotation</it>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Reference correspondence</st>

<p>

The first part specifies that a model must be encoded in a public standardized machine-readable format, clearly related to a single reference description, and must reflect the biological processes listed in the reference description. All quantitative attributes have to be defined, including initial conditions, and the model must be able to reproduce reasonably well the results given in the reference description.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The model must be encoded in a public, standardized, machine-readable format (<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/4461797.xml">
SBML</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
, <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/1197057.xml">
CellML</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/12142270.xml">
GENESIS</link>, ...).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The model must comply with the standard in which it is encoded.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The model must be clearly related to a single reference description. If a model is composed from different parts, there should still be a description of the derived/combined model.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The encoded model structure must reflect the biological processes listed in the reference description.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The model must be instantiated in a simulation: all quantitative attributes have to be defined, including initial conditions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 When instantiated, the model must be able to reproduce all results given in the reference description within an epsilon (algorithms, round-up errors).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Attribution annotation</st>

<p>

The second part of the standard deals with the annotation of the model. A model has to provide the citation of the reference description, lists its creators, and be attached to some terms of distribution.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The model has to be named.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A citation of the reference description must be joined (complete citation, unique identifier, unambigous URL). The citation should permit to identify the authors of the model.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The name and contact of model creators must be joined.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The date and time of creation and last modification should be specified. An history is useful but not required.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The model should be linked to a precise statement about the terms of distribution. <b>MIRIAM</b> does not require "freedom of use" or "no cost".</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
External resource annotation</st>

<p>

Finally, each component of a model must be annotated to allow its unambiguous identification. This annotation is based on a set of standard <it>Unique Resource Identifiers</it> that describe a specific piece of knowledge.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The annotation must permit to unambiguously relate a piece of knowledge to a model constituent.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The referenced information should be described using a triplet {data type, identifier, qualifier}:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The data type should be written as a Unique Resource Identifier (URI).</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The identifier is analysed within the framework of the data type.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Data type and identifier can be combined in a single URI: urn:miriam:obo.go:GO%3A0006915, urn:miriam:uniprot:P62158, ...</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Qualifiers (optional) should refine the link between the model components and the piece of knowledge: "has a", "is version of", "is homolog to", etc.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In order to resolve this annotation, the community has to agree on a set of valid URIs and possesses ways of automating their treatment. <b>MIRIAM Resources</b> have been developed for this purpose: allowing the storage of the URIs of the data types and the resolution between them and the physical locations of the pieces of knowledge.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Uniform Resource Identifiers </st>

<p>

An important part of the standard consists in the controlled annotation of model components, based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/32146.xml">
Uniform Resource Identifiers</link>. For more information on the use of those URIs to annotate models, see the specification of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sbml.org/wiki/">
SBML Level 2 Version 2</weblink> (and above). In order to enable interoperability of this annotation, the community has to agree on a set of recognised data resources. <it>MIRIAM Database</it> (using <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/19545.xml">
MySQL</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
) is an online resource created to catalogue the data resources, their URIs and the corresponding physical URLs, whether these are controlled vocabularies or databases.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="MIRIAM_Resources_Enzyme_Nomenclature_entry.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Example of an entry stored in MIRIAM Resources
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Each entry contains a diverse set of details about the resource: official name and synonyms, root URIs (URL and URN forms), patterns of identifiers, documentation, etc. Each data resource can be associated with several physical locations. For instance:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 name: Gene Ontology</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 synonym: GO</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 pattern: GO:\d{7}$</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 URI: urn:miriam:obo.go</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Locations</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 location home: http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ego/</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 root URL: http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ego/DisplayGoTerm?selected=$1</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 location home: http://www.godatabase.org/cgi-bin/amigo/go.cgi</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 root URL: http://www.godatabase.org/cgi-bin/amigo/go.cgi?query=$1</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 [...]</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Note that MIRIAM URIs take a URN form. For instance the URI representing the enzyme classification is: urn:miriam:ec-code.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Resources </st>

<p>

A set of resources have been developed<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. They are freely available online from the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/2056296.xml">
European Bioinformatics Institute</link></association>
</institute>
 Website<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>, as well as the whole source code of the project on <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/52227.xml">
SourceForge.net</link></web_site>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>.</p>
<p>

The Website uses an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/200698.xml">
Apache Tomcat</link> server to provide an interface for the database. Users are able to perform queries such as retrieving valid physical locations (URLs) corresponding to a given URI (whether a generic data type or a precise piece of knowledge), retrieving all the information stored about a data type (such as its name, its synonyms, links to some documentation, etc.) and immediately get the results in a dynamic way, using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../950/1610950.xml">
AJAX</link>.</p>
<p>

Moreover, a programmatic access through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/93483.xml">
Web Services</link> (based on <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/1888026.xml">
Apache Axis</link></software>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/29215.xml">
SOAP</link> messages) is available. This <link>
API</link> permits not only to resolved model annotations, but also to generate the correct URIs based on resource name and accession numbers. For an easier use of these services, a <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
 library is also available.</p>
<p>

<b>MIRIAM Resources</b> is used by several worldwide projects, like BioModels Database<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>, SABIO-RK<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>, Virtual Cell<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref>, COPASI<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>, SBMLeditor<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>, ...</p>
<p>

Of course, everybody can contribute to the resources by adding new data types, via the online form provided.</p>
<p>

<b>MIRIAM Resources</b> are developed in the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/compneur-srv/">
Computational Neurobiology Group</weblink> at the European Bioinformatics Institute.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/7819348.xml">
Minimum Information Standards</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1363296.xml">
Computational systems biology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/6948407.xml">
BioModels Database</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/4461797.xml">
SBML</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/1197057.xml">
CellML</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Le Novère, N. <it>et al</it> (2005) Minimum information requested in the annotation of biochemical models (MIRIAM). <it>Nature Biotechnology</it> <b>23</b>:1509-1515. <b>PMID 16333295</b></entry>
<entry id="2">
http://www.biomodels.net/ BioModels.net Website</entry>
<entry id="3">
http://www.mibbi.org/ Minimum Information for Biological and Biomedical Investigations</entry>
<entry id="4">
Laibe, C., Le Novère, N. (2007) MIRIAM Resources: tools to generate and resolve robust cross-references in Systems Biology. <it>BMC Systems Biology</it> <b>1</b>:58. <b>PMID 18078503</b></entry>
<entry id="5">
http://www.ebi.ac.uk/miriam/ MIRIAM Resources Website</entry>
<entry id="6">
http://sourceforge.net/projects/miriam/ MIRIAM project on SourceForge.net</entry>
<entry id="7">
Le Novère, N. <it>et al</it> (2006) Biomodels database: a free, centralized database of curated, published, quantitative kinetic models of biochemical and cellular systems. <it>Nucleic Acids Research</it> <b>34</b>:D689-D691. <b>PMID 16381960</b></entry>
<entry id="8">
http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels/ BioModels Database Website</entry>
<entry id="9">
http://sabio.villa-bosch.de/ SABIO-Reaction Kinetics Database</entry>
<entry id="10">
http://www.nrcam.uchc.edu/login/login.html Virtual Cell modelling environment</entry>
<entry id="11">
http://www.copasi.org/ Complex Pathway Simulator</entry>
<entry id="12">
http://www.ebi.ac.uk/compneur-srv/SBMLeditor.html SBMLeditor</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
