<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:35:53[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<software  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106566077">
<application  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106570110">
<program  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106568978">
<written_communication  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106349220">
<writing  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106359877">
<code  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106355894">
<coding_system  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106353757">
<header>
<title>Content-based image retrieval</title>
<id>743971</id>
<revision>
<id>241031072</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-26T01:03:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ckatz</username>
<id>831038</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Artificial intelligence applications</category>
<category>Applications of computer vision</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Content-based image retrieval</b> (<b>CBIR</b>), also known as <b>query by image content</b> (<b>QBIC</b>) and <b>content-based visual information retrieval</b> (<b>CBVIR</b>) is the application of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/6596.xml">
computer vision</link> to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/346470.xml">
image retrieval</link> problem, that is, the problem of searching for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/503726.xml">
digital image</link>s in large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link>s. (see this survey<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> for a recent scientific overview of the CBIR field)<p>

"Content-based" means that the search will analyze the actual contents of the image.  The term 'content' in this context might refer to colors, shapes, textures, or any other information that can be derived from the image itself.  Without the ability to examine image content, searches must rely on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/18933632.xml">
metadata</link> such as captions or keywords, which may be laborious or expensive to produce.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

The term CBIR seems to have originated in 1992, when it was used by T. Kato to describe experiments into automatic retrieval of images from a database, based on the colors and shapes present. Since then, the term has been used to describe the process of retrieving desired images from a large collection on the basis of syntactical image features. The techniques, tools and algorithms that are used originate from fields such as statistics, pattern recognition, signal processing, and computer vision.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Technical progress </st>
<p>

There is a growing interest in CBIR because of the limitations inherent in metadata-based systems, as well as the large range of possible uses for efficient image retrieval. Textual information about images can be easily searched using existing technology, but requires humans to personally describe every image in the database. This is impractical for very large databases, or for images that are generated automatically, e.g. from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/87179.xml">
surveillance camera</link>s. It is also possible to miss images that use different synonyms in their descriptions. Systems based on categorizing images in semantic classes like "cat" as a subclass of "animal" avoid this problem but still face the same scaling issues.</p>
<p>

Potential uses for CBIR include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Art collections</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Photograph archives</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Retail catalogs</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Medical diagnosis</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Crime prevention</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The military</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Intellectual property</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Architectural and engineering design</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Geographical information and remote sensing systems</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 CBIR software systems and techniques</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Query techniques </st>
<p>

Different implementations of CBIR make use of different types of user queries.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Query by example </st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/2271084.xml">
Query by example</link> is a query technique that involves providing the CBIR system with an example image that it will then base its search upon.  The underlying search algorithms may vary depending on the application, but result images should all share common elements with the provided example.</p>
<p>

Options for providing example images to the system include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A preexisting image may be supplied by the user or chosen from a random set.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The user draws a rough approximation of the image they are looking for, for example with blobs of color or general shapes.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

This query technique removes the difficulties that can arise when trying to describe images with words.</p>
<p>

An example of a system that allows users to draw their search criteria can be found here:
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://labs.systemone.at/retrievr/">
http://labs.systemone.at/retrievr/</weblink></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Semantic retrieval </st>
<p>

The ideal CBIR system from a user perspective would involve what is referred to as <it>semantic</it> retrieval, where the user makes a request like "find pictures of dogs" or even "find pictures of Abraham Lincoln". This type of open-ended task is very difficult for computers to perform - pictures of chihuahuas and Great Danes look very different, and Lincoln may not always be facing the camera or in the same pose. Current CBIR systems therefore generally make use of lower-level features like texture, color, and shape, although some systems take advantage of very common higher-level features like faces (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/602401.xml">
facial recognition system</link>). Not every CBIR system is generic. Some systems are designed for a specific domain, e.g. shape matching can be used for finding parts inside a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/37315.xml">
CAD</link>-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/162289.xml">
CAM</link> database.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Other query methods </st>
<p>

Other query methods include browsing for example images, navigating customized/hierarchical categories, querying by image region (rather than the entire image), querying by multiple example images, querying by visual sketch, querying by direct specification of image features, and multimodal queries (e.g. combining touch, voice, etc.) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mayron.net/liam/pub/mayron_dissertation.pdf">
http://mayron.net/liam/pub/mayron_dissertation.pdf</weblink>. </p>
<p>

CBIR systems can also make use of <it>relevance feedback</it>, where the user progressively refines the search results by marking images in the results as "relevant", "not relevant", or "neutral" to the search query, then repeating the search with the new information.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Content comparison techniques </st>
<p>

The sections below describe common methods for extracting content from images so that they can be easily compared.  The methods outlined are not specific to any particular application domain.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Color </st>
<p>

Retrieving images based on color similarity is achieved by computing a color histogram for each image that identifies the proportion of pixels within an image holding specific values (that humans express as colors). Current research is attempting to segment color proportion by region and by spatial relationship among several color regions.Examining images based on the colors they contain is one of the most widely used techniques because it does not depend on image size or orientation.  Color searches will usually involve comparing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/474813.xml">
color histogram</link>s, though this is not the only technique in practice.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Texture </st>
<p>

Texture measures look for visual patterns in images and how they are spatially defined.  Textures are represented by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/877320.xml">
texels</link> which are then placed into a number of sets, depending on how many textures are detected in the image.  These sets not only define the texture, but also where in the image the texture is located.
Texture is a difficult concept to represent. The identification of specific textures in an image is achieved primarily by modeling texture as a two-dimensional gray level variation. The relative brightness of pairs of pixels is computed such that degree of contrast, regularity, coarseness and directionality may be estimated (Tamura, Mori &amp; Yamawaki, 1978). However, the problem is in identifying patterns of co-pixel variation and associating them with particular classes of textures such as ``silky<it>, or ``rough</it>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Shape </st>
<p>

Shape does not refer to the shape of an image but to the shape of a particular region that is being sought out.  Shapes will often be determined first applying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/505717.xml">
segmentation</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/331680.xml">
edge detection</link> to an image.  In some cases accurate shape detection will require human intervention because methods like segmentation are very difficult to completely automate.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Applications </st>
<p>

Some software producers are trying to push CBIR based applications into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/7144.xml">
filter</link>ing and law enforcement markets for the purpose of identifying and censoring images with skin-tones and shapes that could indicate the presence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/18841893.xml">
nudity</link>, with controversial results.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/7309022.xml">
Nearest neighbor search</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 CBIR software systems </st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Free &amp; Open Source </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imgseek.net/">
imgSeek</weblink> - opensource photo collection manager and viewer with content-based search and many other features. License: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GPL</link>. Windows, Linux and Mac OS versions available.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://server.imgseek.net">
imgSeek server</weblink> - Server side implementation of a content-based images database. Employs the same wavelet-based algorithms as the opensource <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/3190034.xml">
imgSeek</link> application.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/324408.xml">
GIFT</link> - <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/gift/">
The GNU Image Finding Tool</weblink> - an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../758/18938758.xml">
open source</link> query by example system. License: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/18938683.xml">
GPL</link>.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://viper.unige.ch/demo/">
Viper Demo</weblink> - an online demonstration of the GIFT</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://viper.infotech.monash.edu.au/~davids/cgi-bin/PerlMRMLClient/PerlMRMLClient.pl">
Perl MRML Client</weblink> - another GIFT demo, using a different client, and combining textual annotation with visual features</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mediaartnet.org/works/eye-vision-bot/">
EyeVisionBot</weblink> - An interface for eye-tracking based image search using the GIFT</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://thomas.deselaers.de/FIRE">
FIRE</weblink> another open source query by visual example CBIR system. Developed at RWTH Aachen University. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-i6.informatik.rwth-aachen.de/~deselaers/cgi_bin/fire.cgi">
FIRE online demo</weblink>, FIRE is a research system developed with extensibility in mind and can easily be combined with textual information retrieval systems.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.anaktisi.net">
img(Anaktisi)</weblink> This Web-Solution implements a new family of CBIR descriptors. These descriptors combine in one histogram color and texture information and are suitable for accurately retrieving images.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.semanticmetadata.net/">
Caliph &amp; Emir</weblink>: Creation and Retrieval of images based on MPEG-7 (GPL).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.img-rummager.com">
img(Rummager)</weblink>: Image retrieval Engine (Freeware Applicaton).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Closed Source </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.picporta.com">
picporta</weblink> - A picture management portal for organising pictures based on faces,content and other meta data.Site features automatic face based albums creation and searching.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tineye.com/">
TinEye</weblink> - A CBIR site for finding variations of web images.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pilevar.com/mfirs/">
MFIRS</weblink> Multi-Features Image Retrieval System, Abdol Hamid Pilevar </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://retin.ensea.fr">
RETIN</weblink> Interactive images retrieval system - CNRS - ETIS Lab., MIDI Team</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-list.cea.fr/fr/programmes/systemes_interactifs/labo_lic2m/piria/w3/pirianet.php">
PIRIA</weblink> CBIR tool developed at CEA-LIST, LIC2M (Multimedia Multilingual Knowledge Engineering Laboratory).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://amazon.ece.utexas.edu/~qasim/research.htm">
CIRES</weblink> developed by the University of Texas at Austin.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tiltomo.com">
Tiltomo : Image Visual Search Engine</weblink> CBIR (content based image retrieval) system uses advanced proprietary Subject, Color &amp; Texture recognition algorithms to analyze image composition.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-rocq.inria.fr/imedia/ikona.html">
IKONA</weblink> - Online demonstration - Generic CBIR system - INRIA - IMEDIA</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cortina.ch">
Cortina</weblink> - Content Based Image Retrieval for 3 Million Images. From UCSB.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://photo.beholdsearch.com/search.jsp">
Behold Image Search</weblink> - A search engine that uses image content analysis to index 1 million Flickr images with automatically generated tags.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://labs.systemone.at/retrievr/">
Retrievr</weblink> - search and explore in a selection of Flickr images by drawing a rough sketch or uploading an image.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://muvis.cs.tut.fi/">
MUVIS - MUVIS Image and Video Retrieval</weblink> CBIR System at TUT- Tampere University of Technology.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://persia.ee.columbia.edu:8008/">
WebSEEk</weblink>, 'A Content-Based Image and Video Search and Catalog Tool for the Web' at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/6310.xml">
Columbia University</link></ranking>
</university>
 using structured hierarchies and colour matching to search over 650,000 images and videos on the web.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ifp.uiuc.edu/~qitian/MARS.html">
Multimedia Analysis and Retrieval Systems</weblink> at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/384695.xml">
University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</link></university>
, using a combination of user feedback and salient points analysis:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ifp.uiuc.edu/~nakazato/CBIR/">
UIUC CBIR on the WEB</weblink> is a web-based demo.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ifp.uiuc.edu/~nakazato/grouper/">
ImageGrouper</weblink> is a related Java interface to a CBIR system which lets users select a group of images and use it as the basis of a query, or bulk-annotate the group.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 CBIR applied in museum and heritage contexts:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nies.liacs.nl:1860/">
LCPD: Leiden 19th-Century Portrait Database</weblink> - an online database of 19th century studio portraits searchable via CBIR and commonly referenced in the literature</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 The <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hermitage.ru/fcgi-bin/db2www/qbicSearch.mac/qbic?selLang=English">
QBIC Colour and Layout Searches</weblink> system on the website of the <museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/175403.xml">
Hermitage Museum</link></museum>
, St Petersburg. (Note that users also have the option of searching for images which are visually similar to ones retrieved using a text-based search.)</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sculpteurweb.org/">
Sculpteur</weblink> - CBIR and text searching applied to a database of objects from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/97275.xml">
Victoria and Albert Museum</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xcavator.net/">
xcavator</weblink> - an interactive image search portal integrated with large stock photography collections. Powered by technology developed by CogniSign.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://labs.ideeinc.com/visual/">
Piximilar</weblink> - a demonstration website on 3 million images. Developed by Idée Inc.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.picitup.com">
Picitup</weblink> - an image search engine, which indexes pictures from Yahoo, Flickr and Google's picasa. Includes similarity search, shape, color and visual rank.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imageclick.com/airs/sub/aboutAIRs_search.html">
AIRs</weblink> - Web based demo for coinmedialab's similar image search engine. Content Based Image Retrieval for 4 Million Images.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Uncategorized </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alipr.com/">
ALIPR automatic image tagging and searching</weblink> developed by Penn State University researchers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://wang.ist.psu.edu/IMAGE/">
SIMPLIcity, ALIP, and Story Picturing Enging online Demos</weblink> developed by Stanford and Penn State Universities</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.airliners.net">
airliners.net</weblink> searches more than one million images by the pixel content</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.artsugar.com">
artsugar.com</weblink> search engine for fine art</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://simba.informatik.uni-freiburg.de/">
SIMBA </weblink> - demo of the Search Images By Appearance system by the Albert-Ludwigs-Universität Freiburg (Germany) - Inst. for Pattern Recognition and Image Processing </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.robots.ox.ac.uk/~vgg/research/vgoogle/">
Video Google demo</weblink> - search movies for specific objects</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://octagon.viitala.eu">
Octagon</weblink> - Free Java based Content-Based Image Retrieval software.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cis.hut.fi/projects/cbir/">
PicSOM</weblink> CBIR tool, developed in the Laboratory of Computer and Information Science, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/60816.xml">
Helsinki University of Technology</link></university>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pixlogic.com/">
piXlogic</weblink> piXlogic offers a visual search engine that automatically analyzes,indexes, and searches the contents of images and video files with high levels of accuracy and speed.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.m4art.org">
Multimedia for Art ReTrieval (M4ART)</weblink> Online CBIR search engine prototype, offers query-by-example and text-based search.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Relevant research papers </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/2.410146">
Query by Image and Video Content: The QBIC System</weblink></it>, (Flickner, 1995)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.hmc.edu/~fleck/naked-people.ps.gz">
Finding Naked People</weblink></it>  (Fleck et al, 1996)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://spiedl.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;id=PSISDG003022000001000188000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;gifs=yes">
Virage Video Engine</weblink></it>, (Hampapur, 1997)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.svcl.ucsd.edu/publications/conference/1997/dcc97/dcc97.pdf">
Library-based Coding: a Representation for Efficient Video Compression and Retrieval</weblink></it>, (Vasconcelos &amp; Lippman, 1997)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-db.stanford.edu/~wangz/project/imscreen/JCC98/">
System for Screening Objectionable Images</weblink></it> (Wang et al., 1998)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jisc.ac.uk/uploaded_documents/jtap-039.doc">
Content-based Image Retrieval</weblink></it> (<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<administration wordnetid="108164585" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/3470813.xml">
JISC</link></administration>
</group>
</social_group>
</body>
 Technology Applications Programme Report 39) (Eakins &amp; Graham 1999)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.svcl.ucsd.edu/publications/conference/2000/cvpr00/cvpr00.pdf">
A Probabilistic Architecture for Content-based Image Retrieval</weblink></it>, (Vasconcelos &amp; Lippman, 2000)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.svcl.ucsd.edu/publications/conference/2000/icpr00/icpr00.pdf">
A Unifying View of Image Similarity</weblink></it>, (Vasconcelos &amp; Lippman, 2000)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.liacs.nl/home/mlew/comp2000.pdf">
Next Generation Web Searches for Visual Content</weblink></it>, (Lew, 2000)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.svcl.ucsd.edu/publications/conference/2001/cvpr01/cvpr01.pdf">
Image Indexing with Mixture Hierarchies</weblink></it>, (Vasconcelos, 2001)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-db.stanford.edu/~wangz/project/imsearch/SIMPLIcity/TPAMI/">
SIMPLIcity: Semantics-Sensitive Integrated Matching for Picture Libraries</weblink></it> (Wang, Li, and Wiederhold, 2001)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springerlink.com/index/10FL41074LE5699P.pdf">
FACERET: An Interactive Face Retrieval System Based on Self-Organizing Maps</weblink></it> (Ruiz-del-Solar et al, 2002)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-db.stanford.edu/~wangz/project/imsearch/ALIP/PAMI03/">
Automatic Linguistic Indexing of Pictures by a Statistical Modeling Approach</weblink></it> (Li and Wang, 2003)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/iel5/8769/27772/01238663.pdf">
Video google: A text retrieval approach to object matching in videos</weblink></it> (Sivic &amp; Zisserman, 2003)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.svcl.ucsd.edu/publications/journal/2004/sp04/sp04.pdf">
Minimum Probability of Error Image Retrieval</weblink></it> (Vasconcelos, 2004)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.svcl.ucsd.edu/publications/journal/2004/it04/it04.pdf">
On the Efficient Evaluation of Probabilistic Similarity Functions for Image Retrieval</weblink></it> (Vasconcelos, 2004)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nik.no/2004/bidrag/Hove.pdf">
Extending image retrieval systems with a thesaurus for shapes</weblink></it> (Hove, 2004)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www1.cs.columbia.edu/CAVE/NSF-ITR/research/publications/Berkeley/miller_cvpr_04.pdf">
Names and Faces in the News</weblink></it> (Berg et al, 2004)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1027650">
Cortina: a system for large-scale, content-based web image retrieval</weblink></it> (Quack et al, 2004)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ims.tuwien.ac.at/~hme/papers/ei2004-vir.pdf">
A new perspective on Visual Information Retrieval</weblink></it> (Eidenberger 2004)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irit.fr/~Gael.Jaffre/RECHERCHE/thesis.html">
Costume: A New Feature for Automatic Video Content Indexing</weblink></it> (Jaffre 2005) </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mi.eng.cam.ac.uk/~oa214/academic/publications/2005_CVPR_paper2.pdf">
Automatic Face Recognition for Film Character Retrieval in Feature-Length Films</weblink></it> (Arandjelovic &amp; Zisserman, 2005)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://grail.cs.washington.edu/projects/query/">
Algorithm on which Retrievr (Flickr search) and imgSeek is based on</weblink></it> (Jacobs, Finkelstein, Salesin)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://infolab.stanford.edu/~wangz/project/imsearch/review/JOUR/datta.pdf">
Image Retrieval: Ideas, Influences, and Trends of the New Age</weblink></it> (Datta et al., 2007)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://caim.uib.no/publications/NOKOBIT07_ljh.pdf">
 Evaluating Use of Interfaces for Visual Query Specification.</weblink></it> (Hove, 2007)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.svcl.ucsd.edu/publications/journal/2007/computer/computer07.pdf">
 From Pixels to Semantic Spaces: Advances in Content-Based Image Retrieval</weblink></it> (Vasconcelos, 2007)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.montefiore.ulg.ac.be/services/stochastic/pubs/2007/MGW07b/">
Content-based Image Retrieval by Indexing Random Subwindows with Randomized Trees</weblink></it> (Maree et al., 2007)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://infolab.stanford.edu/~wangz/project/imsearch/ALIP/PAMI08/">
Real-Time Computerized Annotation of Pictures</weblink></it> (Li and Wang, 2008)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Footnotes </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.liacs.nl/home/mlew/mir.survey16b.pdf">
<it>Content-based Multimedia Information Retrieval: State of the Art and Challenges''</it></weblink>, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../506/3328506.xml">
Michael Lew</link></writer>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
, et al., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/11586265.xml">
ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications, and Applications</link>, pp. 1-19, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Shapiro, Linda;&#32;George Stockman. Computer Vision. ISBN 0-13-030796-3.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Bird, C.L.; P.J. Elliott, Griffiths&#32;(1996).&#32;"User interfaces for content-based image retrieval".</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Rui, Yong; Thomas S. Huang, Shih-Fu Chang&#32;(1999).&#32;"Image Retrieval: Current Techniques, Promising Directions, and Open Issues".</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Datta, Ritendra; Dhiraj Joshi, Jia Li, James Z. Wang&#32;(2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://infolab.stanford.edu/~wangz/project/imsearch/review/JOUR/">
Image Retrieval: Ideas, Influences, and Trends of the New Age</weblink>". <it>ACM Computing Surveys</it>&#32;<b>40</b>: 1. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145%2F1348246.1348248">
10.1145/1348246.1348248</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
</article>
