<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:57:13[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Sivasankaran</title>
<id>7451799</id>
<revision>
<id>221510767</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-24T20:42:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Soleswaran</username>
<id>3450301</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Indian businesspeople</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="sivasankaran.jpg" type="frame">
<caption>

sivasankaran
</caption>
</image>

<b>C. Sivasankaran</b> is the chairman of the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/7451485.xml">
Sterling group</link></institution>
</company>
 operating out of India. The group has diversified businesses ranging from Cellular service to Coffee chains <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sig.co.in/KeyPeople.asp">
http://www.sig.co.in/KeyPeople.asp</weblink>.<p>

<b>The Sivasankaran story so far</b>  </p>
<p>

• 1995: Applied for Tamil Nadu telecom licence</p>
<p>

• 1997-98: Launched Aircel</p>
<p>

• March 1998: Incorporated Dishnet DSL, the country’s first DSL internet provider</p>
<p>

• Dec 2003: Bought 79% equity stake in RPG Cellular in Chennai for Rs 210 cr</p>
<p>

• February 2004: Agreed to sell 33% stake in TN Mercantile Bank to the Nadars for Rs 130 cr</p>
<p>

• March 2004: Sold the internet service division of DishnetDSL Limited to VSNL for Rs 270 cr </p>
<p>

• April 2004: Bought 65.4% equity stake Barista coffee chain from Turner Morrison for Rs 30 cr and the Tata group </p>
<p>

• August 2004: Dishnet Wireless bought Unified Access Service Licences for seven eastern circles at Rs 300 crore.</p>
<p>

• 2005: Entered health food business with Aiwo - a health food chain were low-calorie food cooked in olive oil </p>
<p>

• 2005: Bought out RPG Cellular Limited for Rs 208 cr and renamed it Aircel Cellular 
• Dec 2005: Sold 100% stake to Maxis and Reddy’s combine for $1.8b giving Maxis access to 628 million subscribers in India </p>
<p>

• Jan 5 2006: DTH television JV with Zee Telefilms Ltd (ZTL) .</p>
<p>

He is known for his mavericism and one of the few stylish entrepreuners in India thinking ahead of sunrise industries spreading his acumen elsewhere across the universe.  He pioneered the broadband and wifi technology in the sub-continent. </p>


<p>

C Sivasankaran specialises in buying, running and turning around unprofitable business and later exiting the business at a hefty profit. He started off with ventures in the telecom space and then expanded to a range of diverse business. His last acquisition was a Norwegian shipping company acquired in 2008. - Added by Manwhowenttomim</p>



<sec>
<st>
Link</st>
<p>

http://www.financialexpress.com/fe_archive_full_story.php?content_id=113712</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
