<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:36:39[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Philosophical Gourmet Report</title>
<id>752465</id>
<revision>
<id>217390844</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-05T20:46:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cleanup from section</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>Philosophical literature</category>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Articles to be expanded since June 2008</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>All articles to be expanded</category>
<category>Philosophy education</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that some of the information in this article's  be merged into other sections to achieve a . ()</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

The <b>Philosophical Gourmet Report</b> (also known as the <b>Leiter Report</b>) edited by Philosophy and Law professor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/3431371.xml">
Brian Leiter</link></scholar>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</person>
</philosopher>
</physical_entity>
  &mdash; in response to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/3095956.xml">
Gourman Report</link> &mdash;  is a ranking of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/13692155.xml">
philosophy</link> departments in the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English-speaking</link></language>
 world, based on a survey of philosophers who are nominated as evaluators by the Report's Advisory Board.  Its purpose is to provide guidance to prospective Ph.D students, particularly those students who intend to pursue a professional career in academic philosophy.</p>
<p>

As of December <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/35524.xml">
2004</link>, there are a total of 110 philosophy Ph.D programs in the U.S. alone. In its latest version (2006 - 2008) the Report ranks the top 50 programs in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, the top 15 in the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, the top five in <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
 and the top five in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/19630759.xml">
Australasia</link>.  The rankings are based primarily on perceived quality of the philosophical work of the faculty members.</p>
<p>

The Report was first compiled and distributed in 1989 and first appeared on the web in 1996; it has been distributed by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/4694268.xml">
Blackwell</link></institution>
</company>
 since 1997.  </p>

<sec>
<st>
Methods</st>
<p>

The report's rankings are based on an anonymous survey of faculty members of philosophy departments throughout the English-speaking world.  Respondents are asked to assign scores from one to five to lists of the faculty of each department (the name of the department is suppressed in the survey questionnaire.)  The results are compiled and sorted into an ordinal ranking which used to be subdivided into "peer groups," but no longer is.</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="36px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Philosophical_Gourmet_Report&amp;action=edit">
improve this section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Arguments for</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is currently no objective alternative to the survey.  Thus this is the most objective and useful source for students that is currently available.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Before the report, students largely relied on the opinions of their undergraduate faculty lecturers, without knowing how well informed, or biased the lecturers were in their opinions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 This attempts to shift the halo effect away from the prestige and reputation of the university, to more appropriately, the reputation of its philosophy department</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 If anyone would know about the quality, reputation and influence of the published academic works of various philosophy departments, it is most likely to be the senior, experienced and active academic philosophers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 This helps to combat unsubstantiated marketing language and claims, eg. 'This university has one of the top philosophy departments in the country'.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is most likely to be a strong correlation between strong research reputation and good Ph.D supervision practise by the respective staff.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The sample skew towards popular subjects is likely to have a strong correlation with employment prospects.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 This reinforces competitive pressure on departments to be more open, honest and transparent about the research records of their staff, relative strengths of their staff, number of supervising staff available, etc.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Report leads to an increased ability of Deans and other higher-ups in the university to see an immediate impact for money and effort spent on building a philosophy department. Some argue that this has increased cash flow to the discipline as a whole.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Arguments against</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 There is no necessary causal link in quality between research record and teaching practice, as the Report itself says.  In some cases, the research record is quite misleading, ie false positives or false negatives.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 It is extremely difficult for anyone to fairly and consistently assess the relative reputation of an individual academic, or an entire department, or a number of departments.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 An injustice is done to those departments which are not assessed and to those who narrowly miss out on the top 50/15/5 ranking on a statistically insignificant difference.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The scores are likely to reflect (consciously/unconsciously) the biases, interests, knowledge and specialisations of the evaluators.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The sample of evaluators is alleged to be skewed towards popular areas of philosophy - this is not necessarily an indicator of quality of research program.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The methodology of ranking in the "Breakdown by Specialties" is not the same as the methodology of overall rankings, and has been ably criticized by many for involving the subjective views of advisory boards made up of philosophers who are not peers, i.e., who are not specialists in the very area of specialization they are assessing.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Observations, concerns and/or other criticisms</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The survey intentionally acts as a market regulating mechanism of students and staff and recruitment practices.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Different survey methodologies can sometimes produce different results.  It is not clear that the method applied in this case, is the most appropriate or the most robust.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Because the score is an aggregate, the overall rankings are alleged to highly favor large research departments over smaller usually private schools with fewer faculty.  This is fine for graduate students who have no idea what they might want to study--which is often but by no means always the case &mdash; but for students who have a quite clear idea of what they want to do the Specialty Rankings are much more relevant.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Coursework students have mistakenly attempted to apply results to their own situations.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 This can be misleading as to the overall relative strength of a department, as departments with strong research records are omitted from the report if they do not have a Ph.D program.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Local vs Foreign differences are evident in the scores.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The composition of the consultative board is not proportionally representative of geography or area of specialisation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Report is alleged to be biased towards analytic programs.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Evolution since the first web report</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Addition of a consultative board who influence policy, ranking refinements, instructions to and nomination of evaluators.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Elimination of peer grouping universities based on median scores, as this could potentially mislead consumer choice as to the difference in relative merits of institutions.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Addition of specialised rankings (but not yet scores) of various areas of philosophy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Elimination of handicapping based on department size.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Addition of median scores, and local (for non-U.S.A. universities) mean and median scores.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Addition of some data on placement records and career prospects.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Addition of some advice on some individual areas of philosophy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Addition of number of staff evaluated at each department.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Addition of names and specialties of evaluators.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/448834.xml">
College and university rankings</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Reflections and advice for philosophy job seekers</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 http://aidan.mcglynn.googlepages.com/adviceforwannabephilosophers</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(February 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.philosophicalgourmet.com/">
The Philosophical Gourmet Report</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.csulb.edu/%7Ejvancamp/Female_Friendly.html">
Female Friendly Departments</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.geocities.com/Athens/1575/report.html">
A Ranking of U.S. Departments of Continental Philosophy</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.apa.udel.edu/apa/governance/statements/rankings.html">
The American Philosophical Association's statement on Rankings</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.spep.org/Statement%20on%20Ranking.html">
Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy statement on rankings</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.archive.org/web/20041127092842/http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu/~heck/aboutpgr/">
A Letter of Concern about the Philosophical Gourmet Report</weblink></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.utexas.edu/law/faculty/bleiter/open_letter.html">
Leiter's Reply</weblink></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pantheon.yale.edu/%7Ekd47/rankings.html">
Reply by various philosophers supporting Leiter</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pantheon.yale.edu/%7Ekd47/rankings.html">
Yale's Keith DeRose's position</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frege.brown.edu/heck/philosophy/aboutpgr.php">
Richard Heck updates and re-articulates his opposition to the Gourmet Report</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fleetwood.baylor.edu/certain_doubts/?p=635">
"Some Thoughts on How to Choose a Graduate Program in Philosophy," by Keith DeRose</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
