<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:56:19[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Network Instruments</title>
<id>7536672</id>
<revision>
<id>232311751</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-16T13:54:10Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Basement12</username>
<id>1477312</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Network Instruments</b> develops software and hardware solutions for analyzing and managing network and application performance, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
network analyzers</link>.  They were founded in 1994, and are headquartered in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/6097240.xml">
Minneapolis, Minnesota</link></village>
.<p>

The mainstay product of Network Instruments is its Observer family of network analyzers (including Observer, Observer Expert and Observer Suite). The Observer product family was built for real-time analysis, monitoring, and reporting of full-duplex network links in environments including local area networks (LAN), wireless, Fibre Channel, Wide Area Networks, gigabit Ethernet, and 10 GbE.</p>
<p>

Network Instruments gigabit hardware includes a full-duplex capture card that is designed and manufactured in-house. Designed for full-duplex analysis, it performs filtering and other processing on the card.</p>
<p>

Network Instruments also designs retrospective network analysis products, such as their GigaStor appliance, which records packets traversing the network for prolonged periods of time, for later use in network analysis, trending, and security forensics.</p>
<p>

Network Instruments products are built on a Unified Code Set known as NI-DNA (Distributed Network Analysis).</p>


<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.networkinstruments.com/">
Network Instruments</weblink></p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prolan.ru/observer/">
Network Instruments Official Distributor in Russia</weblink>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
