<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:01:03[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Z-80 SoftCard</title>
<id>7564233</id>
<revision>
<id>244609069</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T18:06:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Crea</username>
<id>200745</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Apple II family</category>
<category>Microsoft</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Z-80 SoftCard</b> was a plug-in card, supplied by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/19001.xml">
Microsoft</link></company>
 for use with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
Apple II</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18457137.xml">
personal computer</link>. It had a <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/64642.xml">
Zilog</link></company>
 <link>
Z80</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/5218.xml">
CPU</link> and was eventually renamed the <b>Microsoft SoftCard</b>.<p>

It enabled the Apple II to run the <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/45146.xml">
CP/M</link></O>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/22194.xml">
operating system</link>, developed by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/87367.xml">
Digital Research</link></company>
, which was at the time an industry standard operating system for running business software on small computers. </p>
<p>

This <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/45146.xml">
CP/M</link></O>
 capability conferred by the Z80 SoftCard transformed the Apple II into a viable platform for running a much broader range of business software applications than had been possible up on the Apple II until that point.</p>
<p>

The card was developed jointly between <celebrity wordnetid="109903153" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<interior_designer wordnetid="110210648" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<programmer wordnetid="110481268" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/202655.xml">
Tim Paterson</link></programmer>
</interior_designer>
</celebrity>
 of <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<electronics_company wordnetid="108003035" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/1499457.xml">
Seattle Computer Products</link></institution>
</electronics_company>
</company>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/587695.xml">
SCP</link> (who developed the initial prototypes) and a certain young <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/3747.xml">
Bill Gates</link></person>
 and <link>
Don Burdis</link> of Microsoft.</p>
<p>

It may perhaps be seen as ironic that Microsoft's 'road to success' began with their first ever hardware product.</p>
<p>

A copy of the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<tool wordnetid="104451818" confidence="0.8">
<implement wordnetid="103563967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/149766.xml">
Microsoft Basic</link></implement>
</tool>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 programming language was also included in the Softcard package (and the Basic license offering is likely to have played a significant part in Microsoft's initial motivation for their involvement in developing the SoftCard)</p>
<p>

It was first demonstrated publicly at the <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<meeting wordnetid="108307589" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<conference wordnetid="108308497" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/652988.xml">
West Coast Computer Faire</link></conference>
</group>
</gathering>
</meeting>
</social_group>
 in March 1980.</p>
<p>

An immediate 'blockbuster' success, there were an unprecedented 5,000 of these (at US$349 comparatively expensive) cards purchased in the initial three months, and the card sold extraordinarily well for several years.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 The influence of the SoftCard on IBM and DOS </st>

<p>

It may not be entirely unreasonable to claim that the Z80 SoftCard may have been perhaps the single most significant piece of computer hardware ever developed (certainly in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/48144.xml">
microcomputer</link> era) because it seems to be the only product which would have prompted <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../259/18622259.xml">
IBM</link></company>
 to consider Microsoft, who were at the time exclusively a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/23015.xml">
programming language</link> vendor which had never developed an operating system before, as a contender for providing an operating system for IBM's forthcoming <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/15032.xml">
IBM PC</link> when <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/87367.xml">
Digital Research</link></company>
 themselves did not offer CP/M to IBM for this purpose.</p>
<p>

The extent to which IBM's decision to approach Microsoft for the provision of the IBM PC operating system (a requirement which Microsoft did indeed eventually supply and which was called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/148169.xml">
PC-DOS</link>) might have been influenced by the Z80 SoftCard, remains tantalisingly undocumented, but as a persuasive case for this outcome, the SoftCard is unrivalled, simply because the feat of being able to run, by means of a surprisingly simple installation, the CPU of one type of computer inside a computer which was using a completely different CPU, running a completely different operating system, seemed at the time to be an extraordinary achievement.</p>
<p>

As a result of this 'impression of operating system mastery' which the Softcard conferred upon Microsoft (especially in the eyes of IBM) it would have seemed inconceivable to IBM that a firm that was capable of delivering such a remarkable achievement was not at least as capable of delivering a perfectly serviceable CP/M-like operating system which could be used for IBM's Personal Computer.</p>
<p>

Who, so the logic of the circumstances would seem to imply, would be expected to be more capable of delivering an operating system with 'CP/M capabilities' (i.e., suitability for running the majority of widely available business software applications) but running on a different CPU to the CPUs that CP/M ran on (CP/M ran on the <chip wordnetid="103020034" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<microprocessor wordnetid="103760310" confidence="0.8">
<conductor wordnetid="103088707" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<semiconductor_device wordnetid="104171831" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/15062.xml">
Intel 8080</link></semiconductor_device>
</device>
</conductor>
</microprocessor>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</chip>
 and the Zilog Z80 CPUs, whereas the IBM PC was going to use the <chip wordnetid="103020034" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<microprocessor wordnetid="103760310" confidence="0.8">
<conductor wordnetid="103088707" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<semiconductor_device wordnetid="104171831" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/15064.xml">
Intel 8088</link></semiconductor_device>
</device>
</conductor>
</microprocessor>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</chip>
 CPU)?</p>
<p>

Who would have seemed to IBM at the time to have been more capable of delivering 'the IBM PC's equivalent of CP/M' than the people who had already succeeded in getting CP/M to run on an Apple II?</p>
<p>

The Apple II was, after all a computer with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/20297.xml">
MOS Technology 6502</link> CPU, a CPU which was in many ways more different from the processors which ran CP/M than the new IBM's CPU would be from the Intel 8080 and the Zilog Z80.</p>
<p>

So from IBM's perspective, it is conceivable that IBM's requirements for what would become PC-DOS would potentially have seemed to IBM to have posed less of a development challenge to Microsoft than the Z80 SoftCard had done.</p>
<p>

This apparent 'ability to create exotic operating system hybrids' evidenced by the Z80 SoftCard, might have even made Microsoft seem to IBM to be even more suited to develop the new operating system than Digital Research, despite the fact that Digital Research had developed the industry standard <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/48144.xml">
microcomputer</link> operating system and Microsoft had never developed any operating systems.</p>
<p>

Strong confirmation of the Softcard's decisive influence over IBM's convictions concerning Microsoft's suitability for writing the IBM PC operating system can be found in the revelation by Digital Research founder <computer_scientist wordnetid="109951070" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/12740.xml">
Gary Kildall</link></person>
</computer_scientist>
's co-pilot and developer of <O wordnetid="106832680" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../780/87780.xml">
MP/M</link></O>
 <link>
Tom Rolander</link>.</p>
<p>

As a direct personal witness to these events, Rolander unequivocally challenges the impression given in the widely cited anecdote whereby 'IBM approached Kildall twice, IBM were snubbed by Kildall both times (Kildall was out flying his plane with Rolander) so IBM then approached Microsoft as a last resort and Microsoft gave them DOS'.</p>
<p>

Rolander claims that IBM in fact approached Microsoft <b>before</b> they approached Digital Research (IBM approached Microsoft specifically because of the existence of the Microsoft SoftCard) and that <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/3747.xml">
Bill Gates</link></person>
 of Microsoft responded to IBM's approach by <b>not offering a Microsoft solution</b> to IBM's operating system requirements but instead sending IBM to visit Kildall so that Digital Research could offer IBM a solution.</p>
<p>

Irrespective of the IBM perspective, many see the Softcard (and the associated project to develop it) as a critical and integral step in the development of DOS.</p>
<p>

This is primarily because, from a development point of view, both the Softcard and DOS initially involved the same individuals 'travelling on the same development path' in the journey from the 'pre-IBM' Intel (and Intel-compatible) microprocessor software support environment, to what followed in the IBM PC (and PC compatible) era.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The SoftCard legacy </st>

<p>

The extent to which the SoftCard bestowed perceived legitimacy upon the Apple II and upon Apple as a company is difficult to disentangle from the legendary struggle for 'business' credibility that Apple subsequently experienced with Apple II's successor the Apple <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/19006979.xml">
Macintosh</link>.</p>
<p>

In terms of helping Apple to  extricate themselves from the notorious 'toy' and 'unsuitable for serious use' initial characterisation of the Mac (which was exacerbated by the seemingly 'purely entertainment-oriented' impression which many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/12293.xml">
GUI</link>-detractors at the time gained from the game-like appearance of the Mac GUI, an attitude obviously long since rendered obsolete) the impact of operating system emulation (or rather non-availability, DOS emulation was not available on the Mac for its first three years) is extremely difficult to determine, and so it is equally problematic to make claims about whether the 'lesson of the SoftCard success' influenced any subsequent strategic decisions at Apple.</p>
<p>

The direct connection between the SoftCard and Microsoft's subsequent strategy decisions seems clouded by the extent to which IBM (and PC compatibility) rather than Apple became the next focus of Microsoft's development efforts.</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
