<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:01:06[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>FMRIB Software Library</title>
<id>7565579</id>
<revision>
<id>121368758</id>
<timestamp>2007-04-09T06:55:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cydebot</username>
<id>1215485</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Neuroimaging software</category>
<category>Neuroimaging</category>
<category>Medical imaging</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="FSL-GUIs.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Example FSL GUIs
</caption>
</image>
<p>

The <b>FMRIB Software Library</b> (FSL) is a software library containing image analysis and statistical tools for <link>
functional</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/19450.xml">
structural</link> and <link>
diffusion</link> MRI brain imaging data.</p>
<p>

FSL is available as both precompiled binaries and source code for Apple and PC (Linux and Windows) computers. It is freely available for non-commercial use.</p>


<sec>
<st>
FSL Functionality</st>



<p>

&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Functional MRI</p>
<p>

FEATModel-based FMRI analysis with straightforward but powerful GUI: data preprocessing (including slice timing correction, MCFLIRT motion correction and PRELUDE+FUGUE EPI unwarping);  FILM <link>
GLM</link> timeseries analysis with prewhitening; registration to structural and/or standard space images; and fully generalised mixed-effects group analysis using advanced <link>
Bayesian</link> techniques.</p>
<p>

MELODICModel-free FMRI analysis using Probabilistic <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<model wordnetid="110324560" confidence="0.8">
<assistant wordnetid="109815790" confidence="0.8">
<worker wordnetid="109632518" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Independent Component Analysis</link></causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 (PICA). MELODIC automatically estimates the number of interesting noise and signal sources in the data and because of the associated "noise model", is able to assign significances ("p-values") to the output spatial maps.</p>
<p>

FLOBSGeneration of optimal HRF basis functions and Bayesian activation estimation.</p>
<p>

SMMSpatial mixture modelling - alternative hypothesis testing using histogram mixture modelling with spatial regularisation of the voxel classification into activation and non-activation.</p>
<p>

&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Structural MRI</p>
<p>

BET /
BET2Brain Extraction Tool - segments brain from non-brain in structural and functional data, and models skull and scalp surfaces.</p>
<p>

SUSANNonlinear noise reduction. </p>
<p>

FASTFMRIB's Automated Segmentation Tool - brain segmentation (into different tissue types) and bias field correction.</p>
<p>

FLIRTFMRIB's Linear Image Registration Tool - linear inter- and intra-modal registration.</p>
<p>

FUGUEUnwarps geometric distortion in EPI images using B0 field maps.</p>
<p>

SIENAStructural brain change analysis, for estimating brain atrophy.</p>
<p>

&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Diffusion MRI</p>
<p>

FDTFMRIB's Diffusion Toolbox - tools for low-level diffusion parameter reconstruction and probabilistic tractography.</p>
<p>

TBSSTract-Based Spatial Statistics (part of FMRIB's Diffusion Toolbox) - voxelwise analysis of multi-subject diffusion data.</p>
<p>

&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Other tools</p>
<p>

InferenceVarious inference/thresholding tools, including: Randomise (permutation-based inference tool for nonparametric statistical thresholding), cluster (cluster-based thresholding using GRF theory for inference), FDR (false discovery rate inference) and Glm (a GUI for creating model design matrices).</p>
<p>

FSLViewInteractive display tool for 3D and 4D data.</p>
<p>

AVWUTILSMisc utils for converting and processing images.</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History and Development</st>
<p>

FSL is written mainly by members of the FMRIB Analysis Group, Oxford
University, UK. The first release of FSL was in 2000; there has been
approximately one major new release each year to date. The FMRIB
Analysis Group is primarily funded by the UK <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/2598108.xml">
EPSRC</link> and
<link>
MRC</link> Research Councils.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl">
FSL website</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/analysis">
FMRIB Analysis Group</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../074/2110074.xml">
AFNI</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/4479709.xml">
FreeSurfer</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/878481.xml">
SPM</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/3557219.xml">
Neuroimaging</link></entry>
</list>



</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
