<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:52:19[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<invention  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105633385">
<component  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105868954">
<engine  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103287733">
<device  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103183080">
<header>
<title>Electric motor</title>
<id>76086</id>
<revision>
<id>244313918</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T06:00:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Old Moonraker</username>
<id>233102</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles with dead external links</category>
<category>Alternative propulsion engines</category>
<category>Electric motors</category>
<category>British inventions</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Electromagnetic components</category>
<category>Articles with dead external links since March 2008</category>
<category>Energy conversion</category>
<category>Battery electric vehicle components</category>
<category>Electrical engineering</category>
<category>Magnetic propulsion devices</category>
<category>Nikola Tesla</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For other kinds of motors, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/58437.xml">
motor</link>.<p>

<image width="150px" src="Motors01CJC.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Electric motors
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

An <b>electric motor</b> uses <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/65895.xml">
electrical energy</link> to produce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/859234.xml">
mechanical energy</link>. The reverse process, that of using mechanical energy to produce electrical energy, is accomplished by a <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/82330.xml">
generator</link></invention>
 or dynamo.   <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/1081613.xml">
Traction motor</link></part>
</part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
s used on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/17717.xml">
locomotive</link>s and some electric and hybrid automobiles often perform both tasks if the vehicle is equipped with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/456930.xml">
dynamic brake</link>s. Electric motors are found in household appliances such as fans, refrigerators, washing machines, pool pumps, floor vacuums, and fan-forced ovens. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 History and development </st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Jedlik_electric_car_respelled.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

220px 
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The principle of conversion of electrical energy into mechanical energy by electromagnetic means was demonstrated by the British scientist <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/19727.xml">
Michael Faraday</link></scientist>
</person>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/34967.xml">
1821</link> and consisted of a free-hanging wire dipping into a pool of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/18617142.xml">
mercury</link>.
A permanent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/51079.xml">
magnet</link> was placed in the middle of the pool of mercury.
When a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/6207.xml">
current</link> was passed through the wire, the wire rotated around the magnet, showing that the current gave rise to a circular magnetic field around the wire. This motor is often demonstrated in school physics classes, but <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/70663.xml">
brine</link> (salt water) is sometimes used in place of the toxic mercury. This is the simplest form of a class of electric motors called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/2260743.xml">
homopolar motor</link>s. A later refinement is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/987792.xml">
Barlow's Wheel</link>. These were demonstration devices, unsuited to practical applications due to limited power.  </p>
<p>

The first real electric motor, using electromagnets for both stationary and rotating parts, was demonstrated by <link>
Ányos Jedlik</link> in 1828 <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/13275.xml">
Hungary</link></country>
, who later developed a motor powerful enough to propel a vehicle. </p>
<p>

The first <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/216794.xml">
commutator</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
-type direct-current electric motor capable of a practical application was invented by the British scientist <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/424676.xml">
William Sturgeon</link></scientist>
 in 1832. Following Sturgeon's work, a commutator-type direct-current electric motor made with the intention of commercial use was built by the American <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<pioneer wordnetid="110434725" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<inventor wordnetid="110214637" confidence="0.8">
<originator wordnetid="110383816" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/223492.xml">
Thomas Davenport</link></creator>
</originator>
</inventor>
</causal_agent>
</pioneer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and patented in 1837. Although several of these motors were built and used to operate equipment such as a printing press, due to the high cost of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/19174720.xml">
primary battery power</link>, the motors were commercially unsuccessful and Davenport went bankrupt. Several inventors followed Sturgeon in the development of DC motors but all encountered the same cost issues with primary battery power. No electricity distribution had been developed at the time. Like Sturgeon's motor, there was no practical commercial market for these motors. </p>
<p>

The modern DC motor was invented by accident in 1873, when <link>
Zénobe Gramme</link> connected the <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/82330.xml">
dynamo</link></invention>
 he had invented to a second similar unit, driving it as a motor. The <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<apparatus wordnetid="102727825" confidence="0.8">
<generator wordnetid="103434188" confidence="0.8">
<equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/5159962.xml">
Gramme machine</link></equipment>
</generator>
</apparatus>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 was the first electric motor that was successful in the industry.</p>
<p>

In 1888 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/21473.xml">
Nikola Tesla</link></scientist>
</person>
 invented the first practicable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/5578272.xml">
AC motor</link> and with it the polyphase power transmission system. Tesla continued his work on the AC motor in the years to follow at the Westinghouse company.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Categorization of electric motors </st>

<p>

The classic division of electric motors has been that of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/47713.xml">
Direct Current</link> (DC) types vs <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/42986.xml">
Alternating Current</link> (AC) types. This is more a <it>de facto</it> convention, rather than a rigid distinction. For example, many classic DC motors run on AC power, these motors being referred to as <link>
universal motor</link>s.</p>
<p>

The ongoing trend toward electronic control further muddles the distinction, as modern drivers have moved the commutator out of the motor shell. For this new breed of motor, driver circuits are relied upon to generate sinusoidal AC drive currents, or some approximation of. The two best examples are: the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/707787.xml">
brushless DC motor</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/170215.xml">
stepping motor</link>, both being poly-phase AC motors requiring external electronic control.</p>
<p>

Considering all rotating (or linear) electric motors require synchronism between a moving magnetic field and a moving current sheet for average torque production, there is a clearer distinction between an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/251075.xml">
asynchronous motor</link> and synchronous types. An asynchronous motor requires slip between the moving magnetic field and a winding set to induce current in the winding set by mutual inductance; the most ubiquitous example being the common AC <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/251075.xml">
induction motor</link> which must slip in order to generate torque. In the synchronous types, induction (or slip) is not a requisite for magnetic field or current production (eg. permanent magnet motors, synchronous <link>
brush-less wound-rotor doubly-fed electric machine</link>).</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Comparison of motor types </st>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<row>
<header>
Type</header>
<header>
Advantages</header>
<header>
Disadvantages</header>
<header>
Typical Application</header>
<header>
Typical Drive</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/1091113.xml">
AC Induction (Shaded Pole)</link></col>
<col>
Least expensive Long life high power</col>
<col>
Rotation slips from frequency Low starting torque</col>
<col>
Fans</col>
<col>
Uni/Poly-phase AC</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/251075.xml">
AC Induction (split-phase capacitor)</link></col>
<col>
High power high starting torque</col>
<col>
Rotation slips from frequency</col>
<col>
Appliances</col>
<col>
Uni/Poly-phase AC</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/487226.xml">
AC Synchronous</link></col>
<col>
Rotation in-sync with freq long-life (alternator)</col>
<col>
More expensive</col>
<col>
Clocks Audio turntables tape drives</col>
<col>
Uni/Poly-phase AC</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/170215.xml">
Stepper DC</link></col>
<col>
Precision positioning  High holding torque</col>
<col>
Slow speed  Requires a controller</col>
<col>
Positioning in printers and floppy drives</col>
<col>
Multiphase DC</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/707787.xml">
Brushless DC electric motor</link></col>
<col>
Long lifespan  low maintenance  High efficiency</col>
<col>
High initial cost  Requires a controller</col>
<col>
Hard drives CD/DVD players electric vehicles</col>
<col>
Multiphase DC</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/10004115.xml">
Brushed DC electric motor</link></col>
<col>
Low initial cost  Simple speed control (Dynamo)</col>
<col>
High maintenance (brushes)  Low lifespan</col>
<col>
Treadmill exercisers  automotive starters</col>
<col>
Direct (PWM)</col>
</row>
</table>
 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Torque capability of motor types </st>
<p>

When optimally designed for a given active current (i.e., torque current), voltage, pole-pair number, excitation frequency (i.e., synchronous speed), and core flux density, all categories of electric motors or generators will exhibit virtually the same maximum continuous shaft torque (i.e., operating torque) within a given physical size of electromagnetic core. Some applications require bursts of torque beyond the maximum operating torque, such as short bursts of torque to accelerate an electric vehicle from standstill. Always limited by magnetic core saturation or safe operating temperature rise and voltage, the capacity for torque bursts beyond the maximum operating torque differs significantly between categories of electric motors or generators.</p>
<p>

Note: Capacity for bursts of torque should not be confused with Field Weakening capability inherent in fully electromagnetic electric machines (Permanent Magnet (PM) electric machine are excluded). Field Weakening, which is not readily available with PM electric machines, allows an electric machine to operate beyond the designed frequency of excitation without electrical damage.</p>
<p>

Electric machines without a transformer circuit topology, such as Field-Wound (i.e., electromagnet) or Permanent Magnet (PM) Synchronous electric machines cannot realize bursts of torque higher than the maximum designed torque without saturating the magnetic core and rendering any increase in current (i.e., torque) as useless.  Furthermore, the permanent magnet assembly of PM synchronous electric machines can be irreparably damaged, if bursts of torque exceeding the maximum operating torque rating are attempted.</p>
<p>

Electric machines with a transformer circuit topology, such Induction (i.e., asynchronous) electric machines, Induction Doubly-Fed electric machines, and Induction or Synchronous Wound-Rotor Doubly-Fed (WRDF) electric machines, exhibit very high bursts of torque because the active current (i.e., Magneto-Motive-Force or the product of current and winding-turns) induced on either side of the transformer oppose each other and as a result, the active current contributes nothing to the transformer coupled magnetic core flux density, which would otherwise lead to core saturation. </p>
<p>

Electric machines that rely on Induction or Asynchronous principles short-circuit one port of the transformer circuit and as a result, the reactive impedance of the transformer circuit becomes dominant as slip increases, which limits the magnitude of active (i.e., real) current. Still, bursts of torque that are two to three times higher than the maximum design torque are realizable.</p>
<p>

The Synchronous WRDF electric machine is the only electric machine with a truly dual ported transformer circuit topology (i.e., both ports independently excited with no short-circuited port). The dual ported transformer circuit topology is known to be unstable and requires a multiphase slip-ring-brush assembly to propagate limited power to the rotor winding set. If a precision means were available to instantaneously control torque angle and slip for synchronous operation during motoring or generating while simultaneously providing brushless power to the rotor winding set (see <link>
Brushless wound-rotor doubly-fed electric machine</link>), the active current of the Synchronous WRDF electric machine would be independent of the reactive impedance of the transformer circuit and bursts of torque significantly higher than the maximum operating torque and far beyond the practical capability of any other type of electric machine would be realizable. Torque bursts greater than eight times operating torque have been calculated.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 DC motors </st>

<p>

A DC motor is designed to run on DC electric power. Two examples of pure DC designs are <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/19727.xml">
Michael Faraday</link></scientist>
</person>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/2260743.xml">
homopolar motor</link> (which is uncommon), and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/1489332.xml">
ball bearing motor</link>, which is (so far) a novelty. By far the most common DC motor types are the brushed and brushless types, which use internal and external commutation respectively to create an oscillating AC current from the DC source -- so they are not purely DC machines in a strict sense.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Brushed DC motors </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/10004115.xml">
Brushed DC electric motor</link></it>
</indent>
The classic DC motor design generates an oscillating current in a wound rotor with a split ring <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/216794.xml">
commutator</link>, and either a wound or permanent magnet stator. A rotor consists of a coil wound around a rotor which is then powered by any type of battery. </p>
<p>

Many of the limitations of the classic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/216794.xml">
commutator</link> DC motor are due to the need for brushes to press against the commutator. This creates <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/11062.xml">
friction</link>. At higher speeds, brushes have increasing difficulty in maintaining contact. Brushes may bounce off the irregularities in the commutator surface, creating sparks. This limits the maximum speed of the machine. The current density per unit area of the brushes limits the output of the motor. The imperfect electric contact also causes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/3966982.xml">
electrical noise</link>. Brushes eventually wear out and require replacement, and the commutator itself is subject to wear and maintenance. The commutator assembly on a large machine is a costly element, requiring precision assembly of many parts.
There are three types of DC motor: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 DC series motor</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 DC shunt motor</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 DC compound motor - these are also two types:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 cumulative compound </entry>
<entry level="2" type="number">

 differentially compounded</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Brushless DC motors </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/707787.xml">
Brushless DC electric motor</link></it>
</indent>
Some of the problems of the brushed DC motor are eliminated in the brushless design.  In this motor, the mechanical "rotating switch" or commutator/brushgear assembly is replaced by an external electronic switch synchronised to the rotor's position. Brushless motors are typically 85-90% efficient, whereas DC motors with brushgear are typically 75-80% efficient. </p>
<p>

Midway between ordinary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/47713.xml">
DC</link> motors and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/170215.xml">
stepper motor</link>s lies the realm of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/707787.xml">
brushless DC motor</link>. Built in a fashion very similar to stepper motors, these often use a permanent magnet <b>external</b> rotor, three phases of driving coils, one or more <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/242674.xml">
Hall effect sensor</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
s to sense the position of the rotor, and the associated drive electronics. The coils are activated, one phase after the other, by the drive electronics as cued by the signals from the Hall effect sensors. In effect, they act as three-phase synchronous motors containing their own <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/1845708.xml">
variable-frequency drive</link> electronics. A specialized class of brushless DC motor controllers utilize EMF feedback through the main phase connections instead of Hall effect sensors to determine position and velocity. These motors are used extensively in electric <conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/233091.xml">
radio-controlled</link></vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</conveyance>
 vehicles.  When configured with the magnets on the outside, these are referred to by modelists as <b>outrunner</b> motors. </p>
<p>

Brushless DC motors are commonly used where precise speed control is necessary, as in computer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/Species_8472.xml">
disk drive</link>s or in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/175445.xml">
video cassette recorder</link>s, the spindles within <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/6429.xml">
CD</link>, <recording wordnetid="104063868" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<sound_recording wordnetid="104262678" confidence="0.8">
<memory_device wordnetid="103744840" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<phonograph_record wordnetid="103924069" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/18959902.xml">
CD-ROM</link></medium>
</phonograph_record>
</device>
</memory_device>
</sound_recording>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</recording>
 (etc.) drives, and mechanisms within office products such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/12877572.xml">
fans</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/50677.xml">
laser printer</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/18935713.xml">
photocopier</link>s. They have several advantages over conventional motors:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Compared to AC fans using shaded-pole motors, they are very efficient, running much cooler than the equivalent AC motors. This cool operation leads to much-improved life of the fan's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/4127.xml">
bearing</link>s.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Without a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/216794.xml">
commutator</link> to wear out, the life of a DC brushless motor can be significantly longer compared to a DC motor using brushes and a commutator. Commutation also tends to cause a great deal of electrical and RF noise; without a commutator or brushes, a brushless motor may be used in electrically sensitive devices like audio equipment or computers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The same Hall effect sensors that provide the commutation can also provide a convenient <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/233487.xml">
tachometer</link> signal for closed-loop control (servo-controlled)  applications. In fans, the tachometer signal can be used to derive a "fan OK" signal.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The motor can be easily synchronized to an internal or external clock, leading to precise speed control.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brushless motors have no chance of sparking, unlike brushed motors, making them better suited to environments with volatile chemicals and fuels. Also, sparking generates ozone which can accumulate in poorly ventilated buildings risking harm to occupants' health.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Brushless motors are usually used in small equipment such as computers and are generally used to get rid of unwanted heat.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

They are also very quiet motors which is an advantage if being used in equipment that is affected by vibrations.</entry>
</list>

Modern DC brushless motors range in power from a fraction of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/38112.xml">
watt</link> to many kilowatts. Larger brushless motors up to about 100 kW rating are used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/279350.xml">
electric vehicle</link>s. They also find significant use in high-performance electric model aircraft.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Coreless or Ironless DC motors </st>
<p>

Nothing in the design of any of the motors described above requires that the iron (steel) portions of the rotor actually rotate; torque is exerted only on the windings of the electromagnets. Taking advantage of this fact is the <b>coreless or ironless DC motor</b>, a specialized form of a brush or brushless DC motor. Optimized for rapid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
acceleration</link>, these motors have a rotor that is constructed without any iron core. The rotor can take the form of a winding-filled cylinder inside the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/231303.xml">
stator</link> magnets, a basket surrounding the stator magnets, or a flat <it>pancake</it> (possibly formed on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/65910.xml">
printed wiring board</link>) running between upper and lower stator magnets. The windings are typically stabilized by being impregnated with Electrical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/211724.xml">
epoxy</link> potting systems. Filled epoxies that have moderate mixed viscosity and a long gel time. These systems are highlighted by low shrinkage and low exotherm. Typically UL 1446 recognized as a potting compound for use up to 180C (Class H)  UL File No. E 210549.</p>
<p>

Because the rotor is much lighter in weight (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/19048.xml">
mass</link>) than a conventional rotor formed from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/125293.xml">
copper</link> windings on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/27058.xml">
steel</link> laminations, the rotor can accelerate much more rapidly, often achieving a mechanical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../284/540284.xml">
time constant</link> under 1 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/36153.xml">
ms</link>. This is especially true if the windings use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/904.xml">
aluminum</link> rather than the heavier copper. But because there is no metal mass in the rotor to act as a heat sink, even small coreless motors must often be cooled by forced air.</p>
<p>

These motors were commonly used to drive the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/302083.xml">
capstan</link>(s) of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/20505.xml">
magnetic tape</link> drives and are still widely used in high-performance servo-controlled systems, like radio-controlled vehicles/aircraft, humanoid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/46673.xml">
robotic</link> systems, industrial automation, medical devices, etc.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Universal motors </st>
<p>

A variant of the wound field DC motor is the universal motor. The name derives from the fact that it may use AC or DC supply current, although in practice they are nearly always used with AC supplies. The principle is that in a wound field DC motor the current in both the field and the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/2152318.xml">
armature</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
 (and hence the resultant magnetic fields) will alternate (reverse polarity) at the same time, and hence the mechanical force generated is always in the same direction. In practice, the motor must be specially designed to cope with the AC current (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/41957.xml">
impedance</link> must be taken into account, as must the pulsating force), and the resultant motor is generally less efficient than an equivalent pure DC motor.</p>
<p>

Operating at normal power line frequencies, the maximum output of universal motors is limited and motors exceeding one kilowatt (about 1.3 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/14019.xml">
horsepower</link>) are rare. But universal motors also form the basis of the traditional railway <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/1081613.xml">
traction motor</link> in <link>
electric railways</link>. In this application, to keep their electrical efficiency high, they were operated from very low frequency AC supplies, with 25 and 16.7 hertz (Hz) operation being common. Because they are universal motors, locomotives using this design were also commonly capable of operating from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../963/338963.xml">
third rail</link> powered by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/47713.xml">
DC</link>.</p>
<p>

The advantage of the universal motor is that AC supplies may be used on motors which have the typical characteristics of DC motors, specifically high starting torque and very compact design if high running speeds are used. The negative aspect is the maintenance and short life problems caused by the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/216794.xml">
commutator</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
. As a result such motors are usually used in AC devices such as food mixers and power tools which are used only intermittently. Continuous speed control of a universal motor running on AC is easily obtained by use of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/181174.xml">
thyristor</link> circuit, while stepped speed control can be accomplished using multiple taps on the field coil. Household blenders that advertise many speeds frequently combine a field coil with several taps and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/Intel_8253.xml">
diode</link> that can be inserted in series with the motor (causing the motor to run on half-wave rectified AC).</p>
<p>

Universal motors generally run at high speeds, making them useful for appliances such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/555505.xml">
blenders</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/49105.xml">
vacuum cleaner</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/986413.xml">
hair dryer</link>s where high RPM operation is desirable.  They are also commonly used in portable power tools, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/205126.xml">
drills</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/89869.xml">
circular</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../906/133906.xml">
jig saws</link>, where the motor's characteristics work well. Many vacuum cleaner and <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<tool wordnetid="104451818" confidence="0.8">
<implement wordnetid="103563967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/567931.xml">
weed trimmer</link></implement>
</tool>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 motors exceed 10,000 RPM, while <hallmark wordnetid="104732543" confidence="0.8">
<characteristic wordnetid="104731497" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/1048336.xml">
Dremel</link></characteristic>
</hallmark>
 and other similar miniature grinders will often exceed 30,000 RPM.</p>
<p>

Motor damage may occur due to overspeeding (running at an RPM in excess of design limits) if the unit is operated with no significant load. On larger motors, sudden loss of load is to be avoided, and the possibility of such an occurrence is incorporated into the motor's protection and control schemes. In smaller applications, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/12877572.xml">
fan blade</link> attached to the shaft often acts as an artificial load to limit the motor speed to a safe value, as well as a means to circulate cooling airflow over the armature and field windings.</p>
<p>

With the very low cost of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/27709.xml">
semiconductor</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/60569.xml">
rectifier</link>s, some applications that would have previously used a universal motor now use a pure DC motor, sometimes with a permanent magnet field.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 AC motors </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/5578272.xml">
AC motor</link></it>
</indent>

In 1882, <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/21473.xml">
Nikola Tesla</link></scientist>
</person>
 identified the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/223352.xml">
rotating magnetic field</link> principle, and pioneered the use of a rotary field of force to operate machines. He exploited the principle to design a unique two-phase induction motor in 1883. In 1885, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../203/1644203.xml">
Galileo Ferraris</link></scientist>
 independently researched the concept. In 1888, Ferraris published his research in a paper to the Royal Academy of Sciences in Turin.  </p>
<p>

Introduction of Tesla's motor from 1888 onwards initiated what is sometimes referred to as the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/359626.xml">
Second Industrial Revolution</link></it>, making possible the efficient generation and long distance distribution of electrical energy using the alternating current transmission system, also of Tesla's invention (1888).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Before the invention of the rotating magnetic field, motors operated by continually passing a conductor through a stationary magnetic field (as in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/2260743.xml">
homopolar motor</link>s).</p>
<p>

Tesla had suggested that the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/216794.xml">
commutator</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
s from a machine could be removed and the device could operate on a rotary field of force. Professor Poeschel, his teacher, stated that would be akin to building a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/54077.xml">
perpetual motion machine</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Tesla would later attain <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?patentnumber=0416194">
U.S. Patent 0,416,194</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pat2pdf.org/pat2pdf/foo.pl?number=0416194">
&nbsp;</weblink>, <it>Electric Motor</it> (December 1889), which resembles the motor seen in many of Tesla's photos. This classic alternating current electro-magnetic motor was an <b>induction motor</b>. </p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/6003471.xml">
Michail Osipovich Dolivo-Dobrovolsky</link> later invented a three-phase "cage-rotor" in 1890. This type of motor is now used for the vast majority of commercial applications.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Components</st>
<p>

A typical AC motor consists of two parts:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 An outside stationary stator having coils supplied with AC current to produce a rotating magnetic field, and;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 An inside rotor attached to the output shaft that is given a torque by the rotating field.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Torque motors </st>

<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/30400.xml">
torque</link> motor (also known as a limited torque motor) is a specialized form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../075/251075.xml">
induction motor</link> which is capable of operating indefinitely while <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/7650988.xml">
stalled</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
, that is, with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../479/9797479.xml">
rotor</link> blocked from turning, without incurring damage. In this mode of operation, the motor will apply a steady torque to the load (hence the name).</p>
<p>

A common application of a torque motor would be the supply- and take-up <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/1150365.xml">
reel</link> motors in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/31109.xml">
tape drive</link>. In this application, driven from a low voltage, the characteristics of these motors allow a relatively-constant light tension to be applied to the tape whether or not the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/1952929.xml">
capstan</link> is feeding tape past the tape heads. Driven from a higher voltage, (and so delivering a higher torque), the torque motors can also achieve fast-forward and rewind operation without requiring any additional mechanics such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/82916.xml">
gear</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/6517.xml">
clutch</link>es. In the computer world, torque motors are used with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/300409.xml">
force feedback</link> steering wheels.</p>
<p>

Another common application is the control of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/4707019.xml">
throttle</link> of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/14796.xml">
internal combustion engine</link> in conjunction with an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/9663.xml">
electronic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/430361.xml">
governor</link>.  In this usage, the motor works against a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/316617.xml">
return spring</link> to move the throttle in accordance with the output of the governor.  The latter monitors engine speed by counting electrical pulses from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../070/362070.xml">
ignition system</link> or from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/1299353.xml">
magnetic pickup</link> and, depending on the speed, makes small adjustments to the amount of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/772.xml">
current</link> applied to the motor.  If the engine starts to slow down relative to the desired speed, the current will be increased, the motor will develop more torque, pulling against the return spring and opening the throttle.  Should the engine run too fast, the governor will reduce the current being applied to the motor, causing the return spring to pull back and close the throttle.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Slip ring </st>
<p>

The slip ring or wound rotor motor is an induction machine where the rotor comprises a set of coils that are terminated in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/759690.xml">
slip ring</link>s to which external impedances can be connected. The stator is the same as is used with a standard squirrel cage motor.</p>
<p>

By changing the impedance connected to the rotor circuit, the speed/current and speed/torque curves can be altered.</p>
<p>

The slip ring motor is used primarily to start a high inertia load or a load that requires a very high starting torque across the full speed range. By correctly selecting the resistors used in the secondary resistance or slip ring starter, the motor is able to produce maximum torque at a relatively low current from zero speed to full speed. A secondary use of the slip ring motor is to provide a means of speed control. Because the torque curve of the motor is effectively modified by the resistance connected to the rotor circuit, the speed of the motor can be altered. Increasing the value of resistance on the rotor circuit will move the speed of maximum torque down. If the resistance connected to the rotor is increased beyond the point where the maximum torque occurs at zero speed, the torque will be further reduced. </p>
<p>

When used with a load that has a torque curve that increases with speed, the motor will operate at the speed where the torque developed by the motor is equal to the load torque. Reducing the load will cause the motor to speed up, and increasing the load will cause the motor to slow down until the load and motor torque are equal. Operated in this manner, the slip losses are dissipated in the secondary resistors and can be very significant. The speed regulation is also very poor.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Stepper motors </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/170215.xml">
Stepper motor</link></it>	 
</indent>
Closely related in design to three-phase AC synchronous motors are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/170215.xml">
stepper motor</link>s, where an internal rotor containing permanent magnets or a large iron core with salient poles is controlled by a set of external magnets that are switched electronically. A stepper motor may also be thought of as a cross between a DC electric motor and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/179919.xml">
solenoid</link>. As each coil is energized in turn, the rotor aligns itself with the magnetic field produced by the energized field winding. Unlike a synchronous motor, in its application, the motor may not rotate continuously; instead, it "steps" from one position to the next as field windings are energized and de-energized in sequence. Depending on the sequence, the rotor may turn forwards or backwards.</p>
<p>

Simple stepper motor drivers entirely energize or entirely de-energize the field windings, leading the rotor to "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/170219.xml">
cog</link>" to a limited number of positions; more sophisticated drivers can proportionally control the power to the field windings, allowing the rotors to position between the cog points and thereby rotate extremely smoothly. Computer controlled stepper motors are one of the most versatile forms of positioning systems, particularly when part of a digital <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/325496.xml">
servo-controlled</link> system.</p>
<p>

Stepper motors can be rotated to a specific angle with ease, and hence stepper motors are used in pre-gigabyte era computer disk drives, where the precision they offered was adequate for the correct positioning of the read/write head of a hard disk drive. As drive density increased, the precision limitations of stepper motors made them obsolete for hard drives, thus newer hard disk drives use read/write head control systems based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../734/1273734.xml">
voice coil</link>s.</p>
<p>

Stepper motors were upscaled to be used in electric vehicles under the term SRM (switched reluctance machine).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Linear motors </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/44495.xml">
Linear motor</link></invention>
</it>	 
</indent>
A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../495/44495.xml">
linear motor</link> is essentially an electric motor that has been "unrolled" so that, instead of producing a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/30400.xml">
torque</link> (rotation), it produces a linear force along its length by setting up a traveling electromagnetic field.</p>
<p>

Linear motors are most commonly induction motors or stepper motors. You can find a linear motor in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../307/822307.xml">
maglev</link> (<conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<public_transport wordnetid="104019101" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<train wordnetid="104468005" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/172228.xml">
Transrapid</link></train>
</device>
</commodity>
</merchandise>
</public_transport>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</conveyance>
) train, where the train "flies" over the ground, and in many roller-coasters where the rapid motion of the motorless railcar is controlled by the rail.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Doubly-fed electric motor </st>
<p>

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<apparatus wordnetid="102727825" confidence="0.8">
<generator wordnetid="103434188" confidence="0.8">
<equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/7903176.xml">
<b>Doubly-fed electric motors</b></link></equipment>
</generator>
</apparatus>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 have two independent multiphase windings that actively participate in the energy conversion process with at least one of the winding sets electronically controlled for variable speed operation. Two is the most active multiphase winding sets possible without duplicating singly-fed or doubly-fed categories in the same package. As a result, doubly-fed electric motors are machines with an effective constant torque speed range that is twice synchronous speed for a given frequency of excitation. This is twice the constant torque speed range as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/7927161.xml">
singly-fed electric machine</link>s, which have only one active winding set. </p>
<p>

A doubly-fed motor allows for a smaller electronic converter but the cost of the rotor winding and slip rings may offset the saving in the power electronics components. Difficulties with controlling speed near synchronous speed limit applications.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Singly-fed electric motor </st>
<p>

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<apparatus wordnetid="102727825" confidence="0.8">
<generator wordnetid="103434188" confidence="0.8">
<equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/7927161.xml">
Singly-fed electric machine</link></equipment>
</generator>
</apparatus>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
s incorporate a single multiphase winding set that is connected to a power supply. Singly-fed electric machines may be either induction or synchronous. The active winding set can be electronically controlled. Induction machines develop starting torque at zero speed and can operate as standalone machines. Synchronous machines must have auxiliary means for startup, such as a starting induction squirrel-cage winding or an electronic controller. Singly-fed electric machines have an effective constant torque speed range up to synchronous speed for a given excitation frequency.</p>
<p>

The induction (asynchronous) motors (i.e., squirrel cage rotor or wound rotor), synchronous motors (i.e., field-excited, permanent magnet or brushless DC motors, reluctance motors, etc.), which are discussed on the this page, are examples of singly-fed motors. By far, singly-fed motors are the predominantly installed type of motors.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Nanotube nanomotor </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/1390297.xml">
Nanomotor</link></it>
</indent>

Researchers at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/31922.xml">
University of California, Berkeley</link></ranking>
</university>
, recently developed rotational bearings based upon multiwall carbon nanotubes. By attaching a gold plate (with dimensions of the order of 100nm) to the outer shell of a suspended multiwall carbon nanotube (like nested carbon cylinders), they are able to electrostatically rotate the outer shell relative to the inner core. These bearings are very robust; devices have been oscillated thousands of times with no indication of wear. These nanoelectromechanical systems (NEMS) are the next step in miniaturization that may find their way into commercial aspects in the future.  </p>
<p>

See also:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/2765047.xml">
Molecular motors</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/1581131.xml">
Electrostatic motor</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Materials </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Further information: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/19622.xml">
Materials science</link></it>
</indent>

There is an impending shortage of many rare raw materials used in the manufacture of hybrid and electric cars (Nishiyama 2007) (Cox 2008). For example, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/145440.xml">
rare earth element</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../102/8102.xml">
dysprosium</link> is required to fabricate many of the advanced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/76086.xml">
electric motors</link> used in hybrid cars (Cox 2008). However, over 95% of the world's rare earth elements are mined in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5042862.xml">
China</link> (Haxel et al. 2005), and domestic Chinese consumption is expected to consume China's entire supply by 2012 (Cox 2008).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Motor standards</st>
<p>

The following are major design and manufacturing standards covering electric motors:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/15144.xml">
International Electrotechnical Commission</link>: IEC 60034 Rotating Electrical Machines</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/273532.xml">
National Electrical Manufacturers Association</link> (USA): NEMA MG 1 Motors and Generators</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<classification wordnetid="105732756" confidence="0.8">
<basic_cognitive_process wordnetid="105701944" confidence="0.8">
<mark wordnetid="105737153" confidence="0.8">
<appraisal wordnetid="105733583" confidence="0.8">
<evaluation wordnetid="105736149" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/286312.xml">
Underwriters Laboratories</link></evaluation>
</appraisal>
</mark>
</basic_cognitive_process>
</classification>
</process>
 (USA): UL 1004 - Standard for Electric Motors</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Nuvola_apps_ksim.png">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Electronics&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Portal.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Energy&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

Motor control:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/638104.xml">
Motor controller</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/8145633.xml">
Motor Soft Starter</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/9420016.xml">
Direct on line starter</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/2769817.xml">
Adjustable-speed drive</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/2704993.xml">
Electronic speed control</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/1845708.xml">
Variable-frequency drive</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/996889.xml">
Thyristor drive</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/6167318.xml">
Torque and speed of a DC motor</link></entry>
</list>

Components:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/317905.xml">
Centrifugal switch</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/216794.xml">
Commutator (electric)</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/759690.xml">
Slip ring</link></entry>
</list>

Scientists and engineers:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Ottó Bláthy</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<electrical_engineer wordnetid="110049017" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/6451.xml">
Charles Proteus Steinmetz</link></mathematician>
</electrical_engineer>
</person>
 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/21473.xml">
Nikola Tesla</link></scientist>
</person>
 </entry>
</list>

Related subjects:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/9531.xml">
Electrical engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/58436.xml">
Timeline of motor and engine technology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<parameter wordnetid="105859071" confidence="0.8">
<constant wordnetid="105858936" confidence="0.8">
<quantity wordnetid="105855125" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/41568.xml">
Power factor</link></quantity>
</constant>
</parameter>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/261881.xml">
Polyphase system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/1081613.xml">
Traction motor</link></part>
</part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/76086.xml">
Electric motors</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Broad Motor Categories</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/487226.xml">
Synchronous motor</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/5578272.xml">
AC motor</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/759697.xml">
DC motor</link></col>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 0px 0px 2px;" rowspan="9">
<image width="70px" src="Motors01CJC.jpg">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Conventional
Electric Motors</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link>
 Induction</link> • <link>
 Brushed DC</link> • <link>
 Brushless DC</link> • <link>
 Stepper</link> • <link>
 Linear</link> • <link>
 Unipolar</link> • <link>
 Reluctance</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Novel Electric Motors</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link>
 Ball bearing</link> • <link>
 Homopolar</link> • <link>
 Piezoelectric</link> • <link>
 Ultrasonic</link> • <link>
 Electrostatic</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link>
 Motor
Controllers</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/2769817.xml">
Adjustable-speed drive</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
 • <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_equipment wordnetid="103278248" confidence="0.8">
<amplifier wordnetid="102705944" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/8032763.xml">
Amplidyne</link></amplifier>
</electronic_equipment>
</equipment>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/7107628.xml">
Direct Torque Control</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/9420016.xml">
Direct on line starter</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/2704993.xml">
Electronic speed control</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../303/11270303.xml">
Metadyne</link> • <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/638104.xml">
Motor controller</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
 • <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/1845708.xml">
Variable-frequency drive</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/13616862.xml">
Ward Leonard control</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
See also</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/987792.xml">
Barlow's Wheel</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/1390297.xml">
Nanomotor</link> • <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/1081613.xml">
Traction motor</link></part>
</part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
 • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/9487574.xml">
Lynch motor</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/3445130.xml">
Mendocino motor</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/4705609.xml">
Repulsion motor</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/1434994.xml">
Inchworm motor</link> • <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/11278410.xml">
Booster (electric power)</link> • <connection wordnetid="103091374" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/2684396.xml">
Brush (electric)</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</connection>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References and further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Citations</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://www.circuitcellar.com/ Motor Comparison, Circuit Cellar Magazine, July 2008, Issue 216, Bachiochi, p.78</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tfcbooks.com/tesla/system.htm">
http://www.tfcbooks.com/tesla/system.htm</weblink>&#91;&#93;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 "<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pbs.org/tesla/ll/ll_early.html">
Tesla's Early Years</weblink></it>". <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/1574304.xml">
PBS</link>. </entry>
<entry id="4">
 Cyril W. Lander, <it>Power Electronics 3rd Edition</it>, Mc Graw Hill International UK Limited, London 1993 ISBN 0-07-707714-8 Chapter 9-8 <it>Slip Ring Induction Motor Control </it></entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

General references</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Donald G. Fink and H. Wayne Beaty, <it>Standard Handbook for Electrical Engineers, Eleventh Edition</it>, McGraw-Hill, New York, 1978, ISBN 0-07-020974-X.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Edwin J. Houston and Arthur Kennelly, <it>Recent Types of Dynamo-Electric Machinery</it>, copyright American Technical Book Company 1897, published by P.F. Collier and Sons New York, 1902</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Kuphaldt-2000-2006" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Kuphaldt, Tony R.&#32;(2000-2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ibiblio.org/obp/electricCircuits/AC/AC_13.html">
Chapter 13 AC MOTORS</weblink>", Lessons In Electric Circuits &mdash; Volume II. Retrieved on <link>
2006-04-11</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aosmithmotors.com/pdf/brochures/bulletin3100/ACDC.PDF">
A.O.Smith: The AC's and DC's of Electric Motors</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-04-11</link>. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Resenblat &amp; Frienman DC and AC machinery</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Further reading </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Shanefield D. J., <it>Industrial Electronics for Engineers, Chemists, and Technicians,</it>   William Andrew Publishing, Norwich, NY, 2001.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fitzgerald/Kingsley/Kusko (Fitzgerald/Kingsley/Umans in later years), <it>Electric Machinery</it>, classic text for junior and senior electrical engineering students. Originally published in 1952, 6th edition published in 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Bedford-1964" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Bedford, B. D.;&#32;Hoft, R. G. et al&#32;(1964). Principles of Inverter Circuits.&#32;New York:&#32;John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc.. 0 471 06134 4.</cite>&nbsp; (Inverter circuits are used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/1845708.xml">
variable-frequency motor speed control</link>)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 B. R. Pelly, "Thyristor Phase-Controlled Converters and Cycloconverters: Operation, Control, and Performance" (New York: John Wiley, 1971).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 John N. Chiasson, <it>Modeling and High Performance Control of Electric Machines</it>, Wiley-IEEE Press, New York, 2005, ISBN 0-471-68449-X.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.howstuffworks.com/motor.htm">
How motors work</weblink> at <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/479125.xml">
HowStuffWorks</link></web_site>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sparkmuseum.com/MOTORS.HTM">
Electricity museum: early motors</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Video demonstration <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pkLyhUCIJW0">
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pkLyhUCIJW0</weblink> of an original 1887 domestic-use electric motor.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.specamotor.com/">
Brand-independent electric motor selection site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.phys.unsw.edu.au/~jw/HSCmotors.html">
Electric Motors and Generators</weblink>, explanations with animations from the University of New South Wales.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://kevinsbrady.net/motors.pdf">
The Numbers Game: A Primer on Single-Phase A.C. Electric Motor Horsepower Ratings</weblink>, Kevin S. Brady.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aseanexport.com/PDF/dc_motor_speed_controller.pdf">
Theory of DC motor speed control</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://motor.iea-4e.org/">
International Energy Agency (IEA) 4E Annex concerned with Energy Efficiency in Electric Motor Systems</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</device>
</engine>
</component>
</invention>
</article>
