<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:50:44[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Workflow</title>
<id>76656</id>
<revision>
<id>244632829</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T20:09:46Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bankbryan</username>
<id>3484992</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Management</category>
<category>All NPOV disputes</category>
<category>Workflow technology</category>
<category>Groupware</category>
<category>NPOV disputes from May 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>workflow</b> is a depiction of a sequence of operations, declared as work of a person, work of a simple or complex mechanism, work of a group of persons,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> work of an organization of staff, or machines. Workflow may be seen as any abstraction of real work, segregated in workshare, work split or whatever types of ordering. For control purposes, workflow may be a view on real work under a chosen aspect,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> thus serving as a virtual representation of actual work. <p>

A workflow is a model to represent real work for further assessment, e.g., for describing a reliably repeatable sequence of operations. More abstractly, a workflow is a  pattern of activity enabled by a systematic organization of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/10368228.xml">
resource</link>s, defined <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/19023436.xml">
roles</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/19048.xml">
mass</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/9649.xml">
energy</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/18985062.xml">
information</link> flows, into a <it>work process</it> that can be documented and learned.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Workflows are designed to achieve processing intents of some sort, such as physical transformation, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/181586.xml">
service</link> provision, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/315578.xml">
information processing</link>.</p>
<p>

Workflow concepts are closely related to other concepts used to describe organizational structure, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/3620743.xml">
silos</link>, functions, teams, projects, policies and hierarchies. Workflows may be viewed as one primitive building block of organizations. The relationships among these concepts are described later in this entry.</p>
<p>

The term <it>workflow</it> is used in computer programming to capture and develop human to machine interaction. Workflow software aims to provide end users with an easier way to orchestrate or describe complex processing of data in a visual form, much like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../453/527453.xml">
flow charts</link> but without the need to understand computers or programming.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Related concepts </st>

<p>

The concept of workflow is closely related to several other fields in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/43476.xml">
operations research</link> and other fields that study the nature of work, either quantitatively or qualitatively, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link> (in particular, the sub-discipline of AI planning) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/152626.xml">
ethnography</link>. The term <it>workflow</it> is more commonly used in  particular industries, such as printing, and professional domains, where it may have particular specialized meanings. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Processes: A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../766/4746766.xml">
process</link> is a more specific notion than workflow, and can apply to physical or biological processes, for instance. In the context of concepts surrounding work, a process may be distinguished from a workflow by the fact that it has well-defined inputs, outputs and purposes, while the notion of workflow may apply more generally to any systematic pattern of activity (such as all processes occurring in a machine shop).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Planning and scheduling: A plan is a description of the logically necessary, partially-ordered set of activities required to accomplish a specific goal given certain starting conditions. A plan, when augmented with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/277433.xml">
schedule</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/267428.xml">
resource allocation</link> calculations, completely defines a particular <it>instance</it> of systematic processing in pursuit of a goal. A workflow may be viewed as  an (often optimal or near-optimal) realization of the mechanisms required to repeatedly execute the same</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Flow control is a control concept applied to workflows to divert from static control concepts applied to stock, that simply managed the buffers of material or orders, to a more dynamic concept of control, that manages the flow speed and flow volumes in motion and in process. Such orientation to dynamic aspects is the basic foundation to prepare for more advanced job shop controls, as <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/218426.xml">
just-in-time</link></concept>
</idea>
 or just-in-sequence.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 In transit visibility is a monitoring concept that applies to transported material as well as to work in process or work in progress, i.e., workflows.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Historical development </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/607572.xml">
Organizational structure</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
</it>
</indent>

In the 1980s, the term <it>workflow</it> was first used in its modern form in the software industry by Filenet vice president David Siegel. The company called its business process automation software "Workflo".</p>
<p>

In 1995, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/68761.xml">
publishing industry</link> studied how traditional publishing processes could be re-engineered and streamlined into digital processes in order to reduce <link>
lagtime</link>, as well as substantial printing and shipping costs for delivering print copies of books and journals to warehouses and subscribers. The term <it><link>
electronic workflow</link></it> was used to describe the publishing process, from online delivery of digital manuscripts to the posting of content on the web for <link>
online access</link>.</p>
<p>

The development of the concept of workflow occurred over a series of loosely defined, overlapping, eras.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Pre-history</st>
<p>

Many historical projects, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/23704.xml">
pyramids</link> and cathedrals, required highly organized labor.  The idea that one can create <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/4095185.xml">
value</link> by studying the nature of work itself can be attributed to <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philosopher wordnetid="110423589" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/1814.xml">
Adam Smith</link></philosopher>
</person>
.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Beginnings in manufacturing</st>
<p>

The modern history of workflows can be traced to <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<management_consultant wordnetid="110289338" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/204995.xml">
F. W. Taylor</link></management_consultant>
</person>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../230/401230.xml">
H. Gantt</link></scientist>
</person>
. Together they launched the study of the deliberate, rational organization of work in the context of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/39388.xml">
manufacturing</link>. The types of workflow of concern to Taylor and his contemporaries primarily involved mass and energy flows. These were studied and improved using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/1682021.xml">
time and motion studies</link>. While the assembly line remains the most famous example of a workflow from this era, the early thinking around work was far more sophisticated than is commonly understood. The notion of <it>flow</it> was more than a sequential breakdown of processing. The common conceptual models of modern operations research, including flow shops, job shops and queuing systems<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> can be found in evolved forms in early 20th century industry.</p>
<p>

Information based workflows began to grow during this era, although the concept of an <it>information</it> flow lacked flexibility. A particularly influential figure was Melvil Dewey (inventor of the eponymous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../699/8699.xml">
Dewey Decimal System</link>), who was responsible for the development of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/1776297.xml">
hanging file folder</link>. This era is thus identified with the simplest notions of workflow optimization: throughput and resource utilization.</p>
<p>

The cultural impact of workflow optimization during this era can be understood through films such as Chaplin's classic <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/74962.xml">
Modern Times</link></movie>
.</it> These concepts did not stay confined to the shop floor. One magazine invited housewives to puzzle over the fastest way to toast three slices of bread on a one-side, two-slice grill. The book <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../535/196535.xml">
Cheaper by the Dozen</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it> introduced the emerging concepts to the context of family life.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Maturation and growth</st>
<p>

The invention of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/44365.xml">
typewriter</link> and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/18935713.xml">
copier</link> helped spread the study of the rational organization of labor from the manufacturing shop floor to the office. Filing systems and other sophisticated systems for managing physical information flows evolved. Two events provided a huge impetus to the development of formalized information workflows.  First, the field of optimization theory matured and developed mathematical optimization techniques.  Second, <military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
World War II</link></war>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</conflict>
</event>
</group_action>
</military_action>
 and the <deity wordnetid="109505418" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/594.xml">
Apollo</link></deity>
 program were unprecedented in their demands for the rational organization of work.</p>
<p>

The classic management tome <it>The Organization Man</it> culturally captured the nature of work in this era.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Quality era</st>
<p>

During the 1980s two aspects of workflow organization drew heavy criticism.  First, the methods pioneered by Taylor modeled humans as simple automatons.  The classical industrial-style organization of work was critiqued as being both dehumanizing and suboptimal in its use of the potential of human beings. <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<relationship wordnetid="113780719" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/163131.xml">
Maslow's hierarchy of needs</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</thinking>
</relationship>
</process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</examination>
</work>
, which describes human needs for self-actualization and creative engagement in work, became a popular tool in this critique.  This issue was acknowledged, but did not gain much traction otherwise.</p>
<p>

The second critique had to do with quality. Workflows optimized for a particular time became inflexible as work conditions changed. Quality, in both analytic and synthetic manifestations, transformed the nature of work through a variety of movements, ranging from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/143996.xml">
total quality management</link> to <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/222448.xml">
Six Sigma</link></method>
</know-how>
 to more qualitative notions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/1638840.xml">
business process reengineering</link> (Hammers and Champy, 1991). Under the influence of the quality movement, workflows became the subject of much scrutiny and optimization efforts. Acknowledgement of the dynamic and changing nature of the demands on workflows came in the form of recognition of the phenomena associated with critical paths and moving bottlenecks.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

The experiences with the quality movement made it clear that information flows are fundamentally different from the mass and energy flows which inspired the first forms of rational workflows. The low cost and adaptability of information flows were seen as enabling workflows that were at once highly rational in their organization and highly flexible, adaptable and responsive. These insights unleashed a whole range of information technology at workflows in manufacturing, services and pure information work. Flexible manufacturing systems, just-in-time inventory management, and other highly agile and adaptable systems of workflow are products of this era.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Virtual workflow era</st>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Unbalanced_scales.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  of this section is .</b> 
Please see the discussion on the . <it>(May 2008)</it>Please do not remove this message until the </col>
</row>
</table>


The Internet bust of the early years of the 21st century led to a period of caution towards ambitious conceptualizations of smart workflows. Today, a variety of actors in the economy are addressing more comprehensive models of work that are rational, flexible, take full advantage of globalized distributed work, and allow humans to use their full creative potential.  An interesting development in this area is the rise of the apparently anarchic organizations that have evolved in the open source software community.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Examples </st>

<p>

The following examples illustrate the variety of workflows seen in various contexts:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 In military planning, a "concept of operations" is a workflow that defines particular mission types</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 In machine shops, particularly  job shops and flow shops, the flow of a part through the various processing stations is a work flow</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Insurance claims processing is an example of an information-intensive, document-driven workflow</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Wikipedia editing is an example of a stochastic workflow</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The <book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/959928.xml">
Getting Things Done</link></book>
 system is a model of personal workflow management for information workers</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Features and phenomenology </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Modeling:  Workflow problems can be modeled and analyzed using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/12401.xml">
graph</link>-based formalisms like <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/225192.xml">
Petri net</link></language>
s.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Measurement: Many of the concepts used to measure scheduling systems in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/43476.xml">
operations research</link> are useful for measuring general workflows. These include throughput, processing time, and other <link>
regular metrics</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Specialized connotations: The term <it>workflow</it> has specialized connotations in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/15340.xml">
information technology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/71608.xml">
document management</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/226446.xml">
imaging</link>.  Since 1993, one trade consortium specifically focused on workflow management and the interoperability of workflow management systems has been the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/11438318.xml">
Workflow Management Coalition</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Scientific workflows: Found wide acceptance in the fields of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4214.xml">
bioinformatics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/575697.xml">
cheminformatics</link> in the early 2000s, where they successfully met the need for multiple interconnected tools, handling of multiple data formats and large data quantities. Also, the paradigm of scientific workflows was close to the well-established tradition of <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/23939.xml">
Perl</link></programming_language>
 scripting in life-science research organizations, so this adoption represented a natural step forward towards a more structured infrastructure setup.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Human-machine interaction: Several conceptualizations of <link>
mixed-initiative</link> workflows have been studied, particularly in the military, where automated agents play roles just as humans do. For innovative, adaptive, collaborative human work the techniques of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/2186768.xml">
human interaction management</link> are required.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Workflow improvement theories </st>

<p>

The key driver to gain benefit from the understanding of the workflow process in a business context is that the throughput of the workstream path is modelled in such a way as to evaluate the efficiency of the flow route through internal silos with a view to increasing discrete control of uniquely identified business attributes and rules and reducing potential low efficiency drivers. Evaluation of resources, both physical and human is essential to evaluate hand-off points and potential to create smoother transitions between tasks. Several workflow improvement theories have been proposed and implemented in the modern workplace. These include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/222448.xml">
Six Sigma</link></method>
</know-how>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/143996.xml">
Total Quality Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/1638840.xml">
Business process reengineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../074/2785074.xml">
Lean</link> systems</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

As a way of bridging the gap between the two, significant effort is being put into defining <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/3114382.xml">
workflow patterns</link></it> that can be used to compare and contrast different workflow engines across both of these domains.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Workflow components</st>
<p>

A workflow can usually be described using formal or informal flow diagramming techniques, showing directed flows between processing steps. Single processing steps or components of a workflow can basically be defined by three parameters:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/41264.xml">
input</link> description: the information, material and energy required to complete the step</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

transformation rules, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s, which may be carried out by associated human roles or machines, or a combination</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/41470.xml">
output</link> description: the information, material and energy produced by the step and provided as input to downstream steps.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Components can only be plugged together if the output of one previous (set of) component(s) is equal to the mandatory input requirements of the following component. Thus, the essential description of a component actually comprises only in- and output that are described fully in terms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/93817.xml">
data type</link>s and their meaning (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/29107.xml">
semantics</link>). The algorithms' or rules' description need only be included when there are several alternative ways to transform one type of input into one type of output – possibly with different accuracy, speed, etc.</p>
<p>

When the components are non-local services that are invoked remotely via a computer network, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/93483.xml">
Web service</link>s, additional descriptors (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/25315.xml">
QoS</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/40760.xml">
availability</link>) also must be considered.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Workflow applications</st>


<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/12286078.xml">
Workflow application</link></it>
</indent>
Many software systems exist to support workflows in particular domains. Such systems manage tasks such as automatic routing, partially automated processing and integration between different functional software applications and hardware systems that contribute to the value-addition process underlying the workflow.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/7705298.xml">
Bioinformatics workflow management systems</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/1155664.xml">
Business process automation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../335/142335.xml">
Business process management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1674621.xml">
Business process modeling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/5378877.xml">
Business-driven development</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/2028143.xml">
Computer-supported collaboration</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/1644982.xml">
Enterprise content management</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/6181775.xml">
Process architecture</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/16997543.xml">
Process-driven application</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../205/5604205.xml">
Smart contracts</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
See e.g., ISO 12052:2006, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iso.org">
http://www.iso.org</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
See e.g., ISO/TR 16044:2004, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iso.org">
http://www.iso.org</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
See e.g., on workflow patterns <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.workflowpatterns.com/documentation/documents/BPM-06-22.pdf">
http://www.workflowpatterns.com/documentation/documents/BPM-06-22.pdf</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
See e.g., workflow pattern analysis <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.informatik.uni-stuttgart.de/pub/library/medoc.ustuttgart_fi/STUD-2052/STUD-2052.pdf">
ftp://ftp.informatik.uni-stuttgart.de/pub/library/medoc.ustuttgart_fi/STUD-2052/STUD-2052.pdf</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
Taylor, 1919</entry>
<entry id="6">
Pinedo, 2001</entry>
<entry id="7">
Goldratt, E., 1996</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations .</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Layna Fischer (ed.): 2007 BPM and Workflow Handbook, Future Strategies Inc., ISBN-13: 978-0-9777527-1-3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Layna Fischer: <it>Workflow Handbook 2005</it>, Future Strategies, ISBN 0-9703509-8-8</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Layna Fischer: <it>Excellence in Practice, Volume V: Innovation and Excellence in Workflow and Business Process Management</it>, ISBN 0-9703509-5-3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Keith Harrison-Broninski. <it>Human Interactions: The Heart and Soul of Business Process Management</it>. ISBN 0-929652-44-4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Holly Yu: <it>Content and Work Flow Management for Library Websites: Case Studies</it>, Information Science Publishing, ISBN 1-59140-534-3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wil van der Aalst, Kees van Hee: <it>Workflow Management: Models, Methods, and Systems</it>, B&amp;T, ISBN 0-262-72046-9</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Marlon Dumas, Wil van der Aalst, Arthur ter Hofstede: <it>Process-Aware Information Systems</it>, Wiley, ISBN 0-471-66306-9</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Setrag Khoshafian, Marek Buckiewicz: <it>Introduction to Groupware, Workflow and Workgroup Computing</it>, John Wiley &amp; Sons, ISBN 0-471-02946-7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Rashid N. Kahn: <it>Understanding Workflow Automation: A Guide to Enhancing Customer Loyalty</it>, Prentice Hall, ISBN 0-13-061918-3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dan C. Marinescu: <it>Internet-Based Workflow Management: Towards a Semantic Web</it>, John Wiley &amp; Sons, ISBN 0-471-43962-2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Frank Leymann, Dieter Roller: <it>Production Workflow: Concepts and Techniques</it>, Prentice Hall, ISBN 0-13-021753-0</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Michael Jackson, Graham Twaddle: <it>Business Process Implementation: Building Workflow Systems</it>, Addison-Wesley, ISBN 0-201-17768-4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Alec Sharp, Patrick McDermott: <it>Workflow Modeling</it>, Artech House Publishers, ISBN 1-58053-021-4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Toni Hupp: <it>Designing Work Groups, Jobs, and Work Flow</it>, Pfeiffer &amp; Company, ISBN 0-7879-0063-X</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gary Poyssick, Steve Hannaford: <it>Workflow Reengineering</it>, Adobe, ISBN 1-56830-265-7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dave Chaffey: <it>Groupware, Workflow and Intranets: Reengineering the Enterprise with Collaborative Software</it>, Digital Press, ISBN 1-55558-184-6</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wolfgang Gruber: <it>Modeling and Transformation of Workflows With Temporal Constraints</it>, IOS Press, ISBN 1-58603-416-2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Andrzej Cichocki, Marek Rusinkiewicz, Darrell Woelk: <it>Workflow and Process Automation Concepts and Technology</it>, Kluwer Academic Publishers, ISBN 0-7923-8099-1</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Alan R. Simon, William Marion: <it>Workgroup Computing: Workflow, Groupware, and Messaging</it>, McGraw-Hill, ISBN 0-07-057628-9</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Penny Ann Dolin: <it>Exploring Digital Workflow</it>, Delmar Thomson Learning, ISBN 1-4018-9654-5</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gary Poyssick: <it>Managing Digital Workflow</it>, Prentice Hall, ISBN 0-13-010911-8</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Frank J. Romano: <it>PDF Printing &amp; Workflow</it>, Prentice Hall, ISBN 0-13-020837-X</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

James G. Kobielus: <it>Workflow Strategies</it>, Hungry Minds, ISBN 0-7645-3012-7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Alan Rickayzen, Jocelyn Dart, Carsten Brennecke: <it>Practical Workflow for SAP</it>, Galileo, ISBN 1-59229-006-X</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Alan Pelz-Sharpe, Angela Ashenden: <it>E-process: Workflow for the E-business</it>, Ovum, ISBN 1-902566-65-3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Stanislaw Wrycza: <it>Systems Development Methods for Databases, Enterprise Modeling, and Workflow Management</it>, Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers, ISBN 0-306-46299-0</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Database Support for Workflow Management</it>, Kluwer Academic Publishers, ISBN 0-7923-8414-8</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lri.fr/~mbl/cgi-bin/getpdf?Trends-CSCW/chap2.pdf">
Clarence A. Ellis: <it>Workflow technology''</it></weblink>, Computer Supported Co-operative Work, M. Beaudouin-Lafon (ed.), John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, UK, 1999, pp. 29-54</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Matthew Searle: <it>Developing With Oracle Workflow''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.workflowpatterns.com/">
Workflow patterns</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.informatik.uni-stuttgart.de/pub/library/medoc.ustuttgart_fi/STUD-2052/STUD-2052.pdf">
Pattern-based analysis of workflows</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/dellen97knowledge.html">
Knowledge Based Techniques to Increase the Flexibility of Workflow Management</weblink>" by Barbara Dellen, Frank Maurer, Gerhard Pews</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.theserverside.com/articles/article.tss?l=Workflow">
The State of Workflow</weblink> May 2004 article by Tom Baeyens</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wi-inf.uni-essen.de/FGFrank/ecomod/index.php?workflow=default&amp;&amp;lang=en">
Business Process Modelling vs. Workflow Management</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.informatik.uni-stuttgart.de/pub/library/medoc.ustuttgart_fi/DIP-2787/DIP-2787.pdf">
How to create workflows oriented on business goals</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wfmc.org/">
Workflow Management Coalition</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Maj. Dale Long, USAF&#32;(2000).&#32;"<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.chips.navy.mil/archives/00_apr/workflow.htm">
The Lazy Person's Guide to Workflow</weblink></it>"&#32;(HTML). &#32;CHIPS — the Department of the Navy Information Technology Magazine.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
