<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:03:49[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Order management system</title>
<id>7794373</id>
<revision>
<id>243511595</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T20:54:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>タチコマ robot</username>
<id>421426</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Software systems</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

An <b>order management system</b>, or <b>OMS</b>, is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
computer software</link> system used in a number of industries for order entry and processing.
<sec>
<st>
 Electronic commerce and catalogers </st>

<p>

A common use of order management software is by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/9611.xml">
electronic commerce</link> and catalog companies. This software facilitates the entering of an order, whether via a web-site shopping cart or a data entry system (for orders received via phone and mail). It typically captures <it>customer proprietary information</it> and <it>account level information</it>.  Credit verification or payment processing is done to check for validity and/or availability of funds. Once entered, valid orders are processed for warehouse fulfillment, such picking/packing/shipping.</p>
<p>

Orders can be received from businesses, consumers, or a mix of both, depending on the products.  Offers and pricing may be done via catalogs or web sites or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/406476.xml">
broadcast network</link> advertisements.</p>
<p>

An integrated order management system may encompass these modules:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Product Information (descriptions, attributes, locations, quantities)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Inventory Availability (ATP) and Sourcing</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Vendors, Purchasing, and Receiving</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Marketing (Catalogs, promotions, pricing)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Customers and Prospects</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Order Entry and Customer Service (including Returns and Refunds)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Financial Processing (credit cards, billing, payment on account)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Order Processing (selection, printing, picking, packing, shipping)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Data Analysis and Reporting</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Financials (Accounts Payable, Accounts Receivable, General Ledger)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Order Management requires multiple steps in a sequential process like Capture, Validation, Fraud Check, Payment Authorization, Sourcing, Backorder management, Pick, pack, ship and associated customer communications; it is common therefore for an order management system to have workflow capabilities as well.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Financial securities </st>

<p>

Another use for order management systems is as a software-based platform that facilitates and manages the order execution of <link>
securities</link>, typically through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/734281.xml">
FIX protocol</link>.</p>
<p>

The software allows firms to input orders to the system for routing to the pre-established destinations. It also allows firms to change, cancel and update orders. When an order is executed, the OMS must then update its database and send an execution report to the order's originating firm. An OMS should also allow firms access information on orders entered into the system, including detail on all open orders and on previously completed orders.</p>
<p>

Some management functions of an OMS might include: establishing and modifying order routing tables, entering and modifying dividend and stock split transactions, and processing and managing underwriting functionality. An OMS may offer direct market access (DMA). Typically only exchange members can connect directly to an exchange.</p>
<p>

An OMS encompasses five components: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 connectivity to a broker or market, typically using FIX messaging.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 trading blotter </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 post-trade support</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 compliance </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 portfolio modeling</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Order capture</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/8270105.xml">
Multi-channel order management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/7577325.xml">
Order fulfillment</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/5582851.xml">
Sales Order</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
