<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:56:27[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Random stimulus</title>
<id>7818227</id>
<revision>
<id>188440707</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-01T19:48:33Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Majeka</username>
<id>3367958</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category> Randomness</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>random stimulus</b> is any of a class of creativity techniques that explore randomization. Most of their names start with word "random"; random word, random heuristic, random picture, random sound, etc. In each random creativity technique the user is presented with a random stimulus and explores associations that has a potential to bring novel ideas. The power of random stimulus is that it can lead you to explore some useful associations that could never be explored intentionally.<p>

Random Word technique is the simplest technique of this class where a randomly picked word is used to generate new associations. By getting a random word and thinking how you can use it to solve your problem you are practically guaranteed to attack the problem from a different direction from that you would normally.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Low-tech implementations of the random word technique often use a pile of index cards and shuffling as a mechanism of randomization. For example, "The oblique strategies" created by Brian Eno and Peter Schmidt in 1975 is a set of 100 cards, each of which is a suggestion of a course of action or thinking to assist in creative situations, where standard logical solutions do not produce a desired result. High-tech implementations of these techniques use computers, random number generators, and availabiliy of internet resources to extend the potential of this technique. Simple random techniques are classified by modality of association (Verbal, Visual, Audial, Kinesthetic). Multi-modal techniques combine different modalities, e.g. random article, website, or video.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> 'Random article' link is an example of this kind of technique implemented by <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/323710.xml">
MediaWiki</link></software>
 software. The best tool to explore a random website creativity technique is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/759881.xml">
Stumbleupon</link>.</p>
<p>

The evolutionary-computation model of creativity <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> views random stimulus creativity techniques as mutation operators. Each such operator has some potential to bring a relatively small and beneficial change (innovation). Success of this process can be characterized by the innovation rate.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> In this context, it is the share of random stimuli that were useful among all presented. The innovation rate depends on the distribution from which the random stimuli are sampled. Improving innovation rate is an important research problem in human-based evolutionary computation.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Ray, 1989</entry>
<entry id="2">
Kosorukoff, 2000</entry>
<entry id="3">
Goldberg, 1989; Kosorukoff, 2000; Goldberg, 2002</entry>
<entry id="4">
Goldberg, 1989</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Goldberg, David (2002), <it>The design of innovation: Lessons from and for Competent Genetic Algorithms</it>, Springer</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Goldberg, David (1989), <it>Genetic Algorithms in Search, Optimization and Machine Learning</it>, Addison-Wesley</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hbga.org/hbga.html">
Kosorukoff, Alex (2000), <it>Human-based genetic algorithm''</it></weblink>, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Ray, Michael &amp; Myers, Rochelle (1989). <it>Creativity in business</it>, Doubleday, NY.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brainstorming.co.uk/tutorials/methodsofextraction.html">
Processes for extracting ideas from a stimulus</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brainstorming.co.uk/tutorials/randomwebsitetutorial.html">
How to use the Random Website technique</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://randomwebsite.com">
RandomWebsite</weblink> (2001)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stumbleupon.com">
StumbleUpon</weblink> (2001)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://mangle.ca">
Mangle.ca</weblink> (2002)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://thatrandomwebsite.com">
That Random Website</weblink> (2008)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://randomwebsite.net">
randomwebsite.net</weblink> (2005)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tools.blackhat-seo.com/strategies/">
Random strategies</weblink>, a website implementing the obligue strategies (Eno &amp; Schmidt, 1975)</entry>
</list>

</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
