<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:08:02[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Public sector knowledge management</title>
<id>7826344</id>
<revision>
<id>232905160</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-19T13:57:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>TexasAndroid</username>
<id>271376</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>UK-centric</category>
<category>Knowledge management</category>
<category>Information technology management</category>
<category>Articles with limited geographic scope</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Globe_important.svg">
<caption>

Globe icon
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section deals primarily with the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 and does not represent a  of the subject.
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Public_sector_knowledge_management&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> or discuss the issue on the .</col>
</row>
</table>


<sec>
<st>
 The British Standards Institution's view of the distinctiveness of public sector knowledge management</st>

<p>

British Standards (BSI) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bsi-global.com">
http://www.bsi-global.com</weblink> is the National Standards Body of the UK responsible for facilitating, drafting, publishing and marketing standards and related information products.  It has identified knowledge management, and in particular public sector knowledge management, as a key area of interest.</p>
<p>

According to the British Standards Institution, (British Standards Institution 2004 "Knowledge Management in the public sector") public sector knowledge management is growing in importance, requiring a distinctive understanding from traditional private sector approaches.  The BSI Report observed </p>
<p>

"The understanding and practice of Knowledge Management has been growing rapidly throughout the public sector over recent years.  Yet a constant comment from existing and nascent public sector KM practitioners has been that, until now, most of the analytical literature concerning Knowledge Management has sought to understand and explain it within a mainly private-sector context.  There has not been a single, easy-to-digest national study that objectively and specifically analysed the growth of KM in the public sector and thereby set out the evidence-based public sector context within which Knowledge Management can add value to the work of public servants. The British Standards Institution, through this Guide to Good Practice, has sought to plug this important gap". </p>
<p>

According to the BSI, it is a not uncommon trend for the public sector to lag behind the private sector in its adoption of new management theories or approaches.  Experience suggests that the jury is currently still out on public sector Knowledge Management. Some public sector practitioners believe that what is currently termed ‘knowledge management’ is actually what public servants have always done since time immemorial – objectively and collectively collating, analysing and deploying knowledge in an effort to inform, develop and enact the policies of the Government of the day.  Others believe that KM is a fad.</p>
<p>

The BSI Report suggests that whether it is recognized explicitly or not as being ‘Knowledge Management’, there are a range of knowledge and learning based activities going on around the public sector today which are delivering real innovation and demonstrating tangible benefits.</p>
<p>

The BSI Report also argues that, for the public sector, knowledge is a key component for providing services and developing policy, rather than a marketplace tool .  Knowledge shared in much of the public sector does not mean private sector competitive advantage diminished.  It is no surprise that many of the largest and most advanced examples in the United Kingdom of online ‘Sharing Best Practice’ are to be found amongst groups of public sector staff, often geographically or organizationally dispersed, but working in a common area (eg Local Authorities CPA <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/cpa/">
http://www.audit-commission.gov.uk/cpa/</weblink>, or Health Informatics <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informatics.nhs.uk/">
http://www.informatics.nhs.uk/</weblink>, or development of public sector standards, such as e-GIF and e-GMF <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.govtalk.gov.uk/schemasstandards/egif.asp">
http://www.govtalk.gov.uk/schemasstandards/egif.asp</weblink>).</p>
<p>

The BSI analysis rests on the argument that public sector organizations are clearly a major part of modern knowledge economies. They are also highly diverse in their governance structures, functions, personnel and outputs. We aim to respect this diversity in the report by acknowledging the different experiences of a wide range of organizations. At the same time, it is important to recognize that organizations in the public sector do experience a set of challenges in implementing KM that are not experienced by large swathes of private sector business.</p>
<p>

For example, according to the BSI:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The public sector cannot pick and choose its ‘customers’, ‘markets’ or areas of activity – it provides services to every citizen by right and obligation, not solely by choice or commercial strategy;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The public sector needs to co-operate internally and with a range of external but related organizations to meet complex policy goals – it cannot pick and choose its partners;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The majority of the explicit knowledge held within public sector organizations should be capable of being accessed by organizations and citizens through Freedom of Information – fully retrospectively in the UK from January 2005 for all information held by public organisations, not just that created after Jan 2005;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The evidence base for a particular policy or programme is constantly under the most intense scrutiny and challenge by policiticians, parliaments, stakeholders, citizens and the media to a degree and depth that is not always present in the private sector;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The development and implementation of policy is a highly public matter – often involving years of debate, consultation, policy analysis, policy development, design and enactment of legislation, and programme delivery and implementation – the majority of which is conducted in the glare of the public eye; </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The current drive for efficiency and ‘citizen centred’ services is putting an immense strain on already stretched public sector resources.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The size, range, complexity and centrality of the public sector knowledge challenge </st>

<p>

The BSI Report argues that knowledge lies at the very heart of what Government does, arguably in a way that is centrally more so than many private sector companies.  Not only is the relative importance of information and knowledge greater in the public sector, the sheer size and complexity of the public sector dwarfs most private sector companies. So the significance and distinctiveness of the challenge in the public sector, according to the BSI, is four-fold :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 size, </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 range,</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 complexity</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 centrality to the sector’s activity. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

To back its arguments about the size, range and complexity of the challenge, the BSI Report asks readers to consider the following facts:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Figures published in 2004 by the UK Cabinet Office show that, as of 1 April 2003, there were 512,000 (Full Time Equivalents) permanent Civil Servants <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/newsroom/news_releases/2004/040422_latest.asp">
http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/newsroom/news_releases/2004/040422_latest.asp</weblink>;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 This does not include the over 1 million people who work for the National Health Service, which if it were a private company would be the biggest company in Europe;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 This does not include the hundreds of thousands of public servants who work day-in, day-out in UK schools and universities, local government, the police force and emergency services; </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A recent copy of the UK Government's “List of Ministerial Responsibilities” ran to 108 pages, covering the work of 111 Government Ministers, Government Whips and Spokespersons in the House of Lords, 19 Ministerial Departments, 90 Executive Agencies, 9 Government Offices for the Regions and 21 Non-ministerial Departments; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/ministerial_responsibilities/downloads/index.asp">
http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/ministerial_responsibilities/downloads/index.asp</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Every month, over 647 gigabytes of e-mail is handled by the Government Secure Intranet, with over 12 million messages handled overall, 6 million of these messages are handled from the Internet. (only 7 years ago, it was virtually impossible to send an internal e-mail within Government); <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/csia/information_for_the_public_sector/">
http://www.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/csia/information_for_the_public_sector/</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 On average, The Stationery Office publishes 14,500 new titles per year for Her Majesty’s Government. There are 45,000 titles currently available from TSO stock, with a further 61,490 titles available on demand – the equivalent of 322 million pages <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tso.org.uk/">
http://www.tso.org.uk/</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 How the BSI believes the public sector provides a perfect 'fit' with traditional KM theory </st>

<p>

Looking at the centrality of knowledge to the public sector, the BSI believes we can consider 2 classic aspects of Knowledge Management theory</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The relationship between data, information and knowledge;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The inter-play between explicit and tacit knowledge.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The types of data that BSI identified that Government knowledge workers require and produce can be widespread and numerous.  It gives the following examples:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Official Statistical sets and publications produced by the Office for National Statistics;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Scientific data underpinning major policy positions;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Economic data assessing and analysing the state of the economy;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Departmental statistical systems, databases and knowledge repositories;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Financial, human resources and performance management information;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Project and delivery reporting data;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 local and regional data on the implementation and effects of national policies;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 external information from commercial, academic and international sources.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

According to BSI, that data begins to become information as it is contextualized and understood by policy makers and policy implementers in their day to day activities.  Examples cited by the BSI include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 within central government, policy option papers produced for discussion and debate of various policy options within policy units, across departments and at Ministerial and other Committee meetings;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 within local government, health or education, performance management information and analysis both as part of policy delivery and as part of external assessment</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 creation and responses to policy publications and proposals, such as Government Green Papers, White Papers and Policy and Delivery Frameworks; </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 speeches, statements, presentations, press release and articles that have been produced to publicly explain a particular policy or practice;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 	Regulatory Impact Statements and Explanatory Notes to Bills and Acts of Parliament explaining the intention and/or impact of items of primary and secondary legislation; </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 e-mail discussions, postings, downloads etc available on departmental Intranets and/or web sites.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

According to the BSI, the data and information becomes transformed into knowledge through the application of policy and administrative expertise and experience.  In other words, what a Knowledge Manager would recognize as the interplay of explicit and tacit knowledge.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Specific examples of public sector KM projects studied by the BSI Report</st>

<p>

The BSI Report includes case studies of the following public sector KM projects</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/7840362.xml">
The UK Government's Knowledge Network Programme</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The National College for School Leadership’s ‘Networked Learning Communities’ programme; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncsl.org.uk/networked/index.cfm">
http://www.ncsl.org.uk/networked/index.cfm</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Department of Health’s KM programme; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fujitsu.com/uk/casestudies/fs_uk-dept-of-health.html">
http://www.fujitsu.com/uk/casestudies/fs_uk-dept-of-health.html</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Countryside Agency’s ‘Learning Networks’ initiative</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frid, Randy, Frid Framework for Enterprise Knowledge Management: A Common Km Framework for the Government of Canada, IUniverse, ISBN 0-59530-699-3</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The ODPM New Deal for Communities’ stakeholder involvement programme;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The World Bank’s ‘Knowledge Bank’; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/WBI/0,,contentMDK:20212624~menuPK:575902~pagePK:209023~piPK:207535~theSitePK:213799,00.html">
http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/WBI/0,,contentMDK:20212624~menuPK:575902~pagePK:209023~piPK:207535~theSitePK:213799,00.html</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The Financial Ombudsman Service’s KM strategy.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 National Library for Health <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.library.nhs.uk/KnowledgeManagement/">
Knowledge Management Specialist Library</weblink> - collection of resources about knowledge management.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Improvement and Development Agency for local governement <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.idea.gov.uk/">
http://www.idea.gov.uk/</weblink> - </entry>
</list>
</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Community-driven knowledge management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/10115122.xml">
Community of practice</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/1706589.xml">
Competitive intelligence</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/1300192.xml">
Corporate memory</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/3829401.xml">
Cynefin</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/74677.xml">
e-learning</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/1644982.xml">
Enterprise content management</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/10136.xml">
Expert system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/243391.xml">
Knowledge</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/239497.xml">
Knowledge base</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/72896.xml">
Knowledge Management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/4000823.xml">
Knowledge management for development</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
KM bloggers</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/1299159.xml">
KM concepts</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 
Knowledge management journals|KM Journals</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Knowledge Elements</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/16920.xml">
Knowledge representation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/230647.xml">
Knowledge transfer</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/660850.xml">
Knowledge visualization</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/3013461.xml">
Meta-knowledge</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/15623038.xml">
Morphological analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../998/227998.xml">
Organizational learning</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/988751.xml">
Personal knowledge management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/7826344.xml">
Public sector knowledge management</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/334507.xml">
Procedural knowledge</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/3663653.xml">
Self service software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/29123.xml">
Semantic Web</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</service>
</event>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
Social network</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="100635850" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<survey wordnetid="100644503" confidence="0.8">
<investigation wordnetid="100633864" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/4709561.xml">
Skills management</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/233618.xml">
Tacit knowledge</link> &amp; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/2231743.xml">
Explicit knowledge</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/7840362.xml">
The UK Government's Knowledge Network Programme</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/1614337.xml">
Value network</link></network>
</group>
</system>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
