<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:09:05[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Query expansion</title>
<id>7872152</id>
<revision>
<id>215521457</id>
<timestamp>2008-05-28T15:54:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Firsfron</username>
<id>158443</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Information retrieval</category>
<category>Searching</category>
<category>Articles with specifically-marked weasel-worded phrases</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Query expansion</b> (QE) is the process of reformulating a seed query to improve retrieval performance in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
information retrieval</link> operations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
In the context of web <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
search engine</link>s, query expansion involves evaluating a user's input (what words were typed into the search query area, and sometimes other types of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/18985040.xml">
data</link>) and expanding the search query to match additional documents.  Query expansion involves techniques such as:<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Finding <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/67396.xml">
synonym</link>s of words, and searching for the synonyms as well</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Finding all the various <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/20646.xml">
morphological</link> forms of words by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/475964.xml">
stemming</link> each word in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/11525372.xml">
search query</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fixing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/1057428.xml">
spelling errors</link> and automatically searching for the corrected form or suggesting it in the results</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Re-weighting the terms in the original query</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Query expansion is a technology studied in the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link>, particularly within the realm of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/21652.xml">
natural language processing</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
information retrieval</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Precision and recall tradeoffs </st>

<p>

Search engines invoke query expansion to increase the quality of user search results.  It is assumed that users do not always formulate search queries using the best terms. Best in this case may be because the database does not contain the user entered terms.  </p>
<p>

By <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/475964.xml">
stemming</link> a user-entered term, more documents are matched, as the alternate word forms for a user entered term are matched as well, increasing the total <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../341/11705341.xml">
recall</link>. This comes at the expense of reducing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/12162988.xml">
precision</link>.  By expanding a search query to search for the synonyms of a user entered term, the recall is also increased at the expense of precision.  This is due to the nature of the equation of how precision is calculated, in that a larger recall implicitly causes a decrease in precision, given that factors of recall are part of the denominator. It is also inferred that a larger recall negatively impacts overall search result quality, given that many users do not want more results to comb through, regardless of the precision.</p>
<p>

The goal of query expansion in this regard is by increasing recall, precision can potentially increase (rather than decrease as mathematically equated), by including in the result set pages which are more relevant (of higher quality), or at least equally relevant. Pages which would not be included in the result set, which have the potential to be more relevant to the user's desired query, are included, and without query expansion would not have, regardless of relevance.  At the same time, many of the current commercial search engines use word frequency (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/2057290.xml">
Tf-idf</link>) to assist in ranking.  By ranking the occurrences of both the user entered words and synonyms and alternate morphological forms, documents with a higher density (high frequency and close proximity) tend to migrate higher up in the search results, leading to a higher quality of the search results near the top of the results, despite the larger recall.</p>
<p>

This tradeoff is one of the defining problems in query expansion, regarding whether it is worthwhile to perform given the questionable effects on precision and recall. Critics&#91;&#93; state one of the problems is that the dictionaries and thesauri, and the stemming algorithm, are driven by human bias and while this is implicitly handled by the query expansion algorithm, this explicitly affects the results in a non-automated manner (similar to how statisticians can 'lie' with statistics). Other critics&#91;&#93; point out potential for corporate influence on the dictionaries, promoting advertising of online web pages in the case of web search engines. </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/4059023.xml">
Search engine</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/7602386.xml">
Search engine indexing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/15271.xml">
Information retrieval</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/731640.xml">
Document retrieval</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/17526.xml">
Linguistics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/21652.xml">
Natural language processing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/475964.xml">
Stemming</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/20646.xml">
Morphology (linguistics)</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Software libraries </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lucene-qe.sourceforge.net/">
LucQE</weblink> - open-source, Java.  Provides a framework along with several implementations that allow to perform query expansion with the use of Apache <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/522923.xml">
Lucene</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 D. Abberley, D. Kirby, S. Renals, and T. Robinson, The THISL broadcast news  retrieval system. In <it>Proc. ESCA ETRW Workshop Accessing Information in Spoken Audio</it>, (Cambridge), pp. 14-19, 1999. Section on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/srenals/pubs/1999/esca99-thisl/node6.html">
Query Expansion </weblink> - concise, mathematical overview.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Y. Qiu and H.P. Frei. Concept Based Query Expansion. In <it>Proceedings of SIGIR-93, 16th ACM International Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval</it>, Pittsburgh, SIGIR Forum, ACM Press, June 1993. Available <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/qiu93concept.html">
here</weblink> - academic document on a specific method of query expansion</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Efthimis N. Efthimiadis. Query Expansion. In: Martha E. Williams (ed.), <it>Annual Review of Information Systems and Technology (ARIST)</it>, v31, pp 121-187, 1996. Available <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://faculty.washington.edu/efthimis/pubs/Pubs/qe-arist/QE-arist.html">
here</weblink> - an introduction for less-technical viewers.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Notes </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Vectomova, Olga; Wang, Ying&#32;(2006).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jis.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/32/4/324">
A study of the effect of term proximity on query expansion</weblink>"&#32;(Abstract). <it><link>
Journal of Information Science</link></it>&#32;<b>32</b>&#32;(4): 324&ndash;333. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177%2F0165551506065787">
10.1177/0165551506065787</weblink>. Retrieved on <link>
2006-12-09</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
