<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:40:50[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Nesting</title>
<id>791347</id>
<revision>
<id>219330115</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-14T18:36:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Btyner</username>
<id>185327</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Production and manufacturing</category>
<category>Automation</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about the manufacturing process.&#32;&#32;For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/17941813.xml">
Nesting (disambiguation)</link>.<p>

<b>Nesting</b> refers to the process of efficiently <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/39388.xml">
manufacturing</link> parts from flat <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../167/216167.xml">
raw material</link>.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Nesting_Rect.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Image 1: Simple rectangular nesting
</caption>
</image>
<image width="150px" src="Nesting_Rot.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Image 2: Improved Nesting with rotated parts
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Nesting_Opt.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Image 3: Minimizing waste by mixing different parts
</caption>
</image>

Companies manufacturing parts from flat raw material such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/1528221.xml">
sheet metal</link> use a variety of technologies to perform this task. The sheet metal nesting for flat sheets and nesting for coils are different algorithms. Material may be cut using off-line blanking dies, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/531911.xml">
lasers</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/1203787.xml">
plasma</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/1646693.xml">
punches</link>, <link>
shear blade</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/5431014.xml">
ultrasonic</link> knives and even <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/2366787.xml">
water jet cutter</link>s. </p>
<p>

In order to minimize the amount of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/1068262.xml">
scrap</link> raw material produced by this process, companies use nesting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link>. The software analyses the parts (shapes) to be produced at a particular time. </p>
<p>

Using proprietary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s, it then determines how to lay these parts out in such a way as to produce the required quantities of parts, while minimizing the amount of raw material wasted.</p>
<p>

A number of off the shelf nesting software address the optimization needs. While some cater to only rectangular nesting others also offer profile or shape nesting where the parts required can be any odd shape and not just rectangles. These irregular parts can be created using popular CAD tools. Most of the profile nesting software can read IGES or DXF profile files automatically, a few of them work with builtin convertors.</p>
<p>

An important consideration in shape nesting is to verify that the software in question actually performs true profile nesting and not just block nesting. In block nesting an imaginary rectangle is drawn around the shape and then the rectangles are laid side-by side which actually is not profile nesting. There still remains a scope for waste reduction</p>
<p>

Nesting software must take into account the limitations and features of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/365765.xml">
machining</link> technology in use, such as:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Machining cannot take place where the raw material is clamped into place;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Some machines can access only half of the material at a particular time; the machine automatically flips the sheet over to allow the remaining half to be accessed;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 When punching, the width of the punch tool must be considered;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Shearing may be permitted only in certain areas of the sheet due to limitations of the machinery;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A laser can cut parts at any rotation; a punch can only do so at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/76956.xml">
right angle</link>s;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Nesting software may also have to take into account material characteristics, such as:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Defects on material that must be discarded;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Different quality areas that must match corresponding quality levels required for different parts;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Direction contraints, that may come from a printed pattern or from fiber direction;</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Many machine manufacturers offer their own custom nesting software designed to offer ease of use and take full advantage of the features of their specific machines. </p>
<p>

If a fabricator operates machines from more than one vendor, they may prefer to use an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/4967015.xml">
off-the-shelf</link> nesting package from a third-party vendor. They then have the potential to run jobs on any available machine, and their staff should not have to learn several different software packages. </p>


</bdy>
</article>
