<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:07:10[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<protocol  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106665108">
<direction  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106786629">
<rule  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106652242">
<header>
<title>Mobile IPv6</title>
<id>7916685</id>
<revision>
<id>206689629</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-19T13:57:07Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>The Anomebot2</username>
<id>1979668</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>IPv6</category>
<category>Internet protocols</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(February 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Mobile IPv6</b> is a version of <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/1076132.xml">
Mobile IP</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 - a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/85024.xml">
network layer</link> IP standard used by electronic devices to exchange data across a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/43339.xml">
packet switched</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../067/15067.xml">
internetwork</link>. Mobile IPv6 allows an IPv6 node to be mobile—to arbitrarily change its location on an <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/15318.xml">
IPv6</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
 network—and still maintain existing connections. 
<sec>
<st>
Limitations of "fixed" IPv6</st>
<p>

When an IPv6 node changes its location, it might also change its link. When an IPv6 node changes its link, its IPv6 address might also change in order to maintain connectivity. There are mechanisms to allow for the change in addresses when moving to a different link, such as stateful and stateless address autoconfiguration for IPv6. However, when the address changes, the existing connections of the mobile node that are using the address assigned from the previously connected link cannot be maintained and are ungracefully terminated.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Benefits of Mobile IPv6</st>
<p>

The key benefit of Mobile IPv6 is that even though the mobile node changes locations and addresses, the existing connections through which the mobile node is communicating are maintained. To accomplish this, connections to mobile nodes are made with a specific address that is always assigned to the mobile node, and through which the mobile node is always reachable. Mobile IPv6 provides Transport layer connection survivability when a node moves from one link to another by performing address maintenance for mobile nodes at the Internet layer.
</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Changes from IPv6 to Mobile IPv6</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A set of mobility options to include in mobility messages</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A new Home Address option for the Destination Options header</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

A new Type 2 Routing header</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

New Internet Control Message Protocol for IPv6 (ICMPv6) messages to discover the set of home agents and to obtain the prefix of the home link</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Changes to router discovery messages and options and additional Neighbor Discovery options</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

The following Requests for Comment describe an intermediate status of standardization with IETF. Currently standardization is still in process (2007-11-17).</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3775.txt">
IETF RFC 3775 Mobility Support in IPv6</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3776.txt">
IETF RFC 3776 Using IPsec to Protect Mobile IPv6 Signaling Between Mobile Nodes and Home Agents</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

The complexity of the subject leads to a vast volume of resources. The following references just help to enter the scope of definitions involved.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ietf.org/html.charters/mext-charter.html">
Mobility Extensions for IPv6 (mext) IETF Working Group Web site</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hznet.de/ipv6/mipv6-intro.pdf">
Mobile IPv6 -- A short introduction</weblink> by Holger Zuleger</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
</article>
