<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:59:42[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>NETZ</title>
<id>7922042</id>
<revision>
<id>189351046</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-05T21:44:38Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Leaptad</username>
<id>3079561</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computer networking</category>
<category>Communication engineering</category>
<category>Computer network analysis</category>
<category>Network-related software</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>DEFT NETZ</b> (commonly known as <b>NETZ</b>) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../517/1446517.xml">
network simulation</link> environment encompassing a wide range of networking technologies. It is widely known among academicians and researchers for its versatility and the extremely friendly user interface. NETZ offers its users to carry simulations and understand the various design aspects related to modern and legacy networks. Network surivability features along with the most flexible <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/25750.xml">
routing</link> strategies and configurations are also incorporated in it. NETZ acquaints its users with advanced fields like buffer management, quality of service, network resource planning, traffic modeling, demand analysis and others. Network design and pre-release network analysis is an issue faced by network engineers repeatedly. <p>

One can configure the complete network through simple user interfaces, right from the used network nodes to the connections established between them. Using the libraries that come along with NETZ, user can run different traffic models, employ different routing protocols, or create networks that involve different technologies altogether. NETZ even makes network analysis simpler, efficient and more meaningful. The pre-define graph profiles helps to categorize metrics that the user want to assess. The distributed approach along with combinational network monitoring makes studies precise and accurate. Status reports, dynamic outputs, graphs and dynamic property monitors keep you aware of every network event. NETZ gives complete knowledge of each variable maintained at a network element, even with the non-intelligent components like the connections.</p>

</bdy>
</article>
