<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:51:32[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Topography</title>
<id>79239</id>
<revision>
<id>243285886</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T22:34:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SimonP</username>
<id>1591</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Geomorphology</category>
<category>Physical geography</category>
<category>Topography</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about Topography as the study of landforms at any scale.&#32;&#32;For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/8052542.xml">
Topography (disambiguation)</link>.
For discussion of land surfaces themselves, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/586839.xml">
Terrain</link>.
Not to be confused with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/29954.xml">
topology</link>.<p>

<image width="150px" src="Topographic_map_example.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A topographic map with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/650086.xml">
contour interval</link>s
</caption>
</image>

<b>Topography</b> (<it>topo-</it>,  "place", and <it>graphia</it>, "writing") is the study of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/9228.xml">
Earth</link>'s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/27865.xml">
surface</link> features or those of
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/22915.xml">
planet</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/53306.xml">
moons</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/791.xml">
asteroids</link>. </p>
<p>

In a broader sense, topography is concerned with local detail in general, including not only relief but also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/216226.xml">
vegetative</link> and human-made features, and even <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/13502171.xml">
local history</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/19159508.xml">
culture</link>. This meaning is less common in America, where topographic maps with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/1765158.xml">
elevation</link> contours have made "topography" synonymous with relief. The older sense of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/8096121.xml">
topography as the study of place</link> still has currency in Europe. </p>
<p>

For the purposes of this article, topography specifically involves the recording of relief or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/586839.xml">
terrain</link>, the three-dimensional quality of the surface, and the identification of specific <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/250515.xml">
landform</link>s. This is also known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/5155886.xml">
geomorphometry</link>. In modern usage, this involves generation of elevation data in electronic form. It is often considered to include the graphic representation of the landform on a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/19877.xml">
map</link> by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/7963618.xml">
variety of techniques</link>, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/650086.xml">
contour line</link>s, <link>
Hypsometric tints</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/7963618.xml">
relief shading</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Etymology</st>
<p>

The term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/79239.xml">
topography</link> originated in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/66540.xml">
ancient Greece</link> and continued in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/521555.xml">
ancient Rome</link>, as the detailed description of a place. The word comes from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/11925.xml">
Greek words</link> τόπος  (<it>topos</it>,  place) and γραφία (<it>graphia</it>, writing).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> In classical literature this refers to writing about a place or places, what is now largely called '<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../171/13502171.xml">
local history</link>'. In Britain and in Europe in general, the word topography is still sometimes used in its original sense<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>.</p>
<p>

Detailed military surveys in Britain (beginning in the late eighteenth century) were called <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<executive_agency wordnetid="108123696" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/19344100.xml">
Ordnance Survey</link></executive_agency>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
s, and this term was used into the 20th century as generic for topographic surveys and maps<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>. The earliest scientific surveys in France were called the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/98999.xml">
Cassini</link> maps after the family who produced them over four generations <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>. The term "topographic surveys" appears to be American in origin. The earliest detailed surveys in the United States were made by the “Topographical Bureau of the Army,” formed during the <conflict wordnetid="100958896" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/34059.xml">
War of 1812</link></conflict>
 <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. After the work of national mapping was assumed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/191640.xml">
U.S. Geological Survey</link> in 1878, the term topographical remained as a general term for detailed surveys and mapping programs, and has been adopted by most other nations as standard.</p>
<p>

In the 20th century, the term topography started to be used to describe surface description in other fields where <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/18937.xml">
mapping</link> in a broader sense is used, particularly in medical fields such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/21226.xml">
neurology</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Objectives</st>
<p>

The objective of topography is to determine the position of any feature or more generally any point in terms of both a horizontal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/81931.xml">
Coordinate system</link> such as latitude and longitude, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../211/59211.xml">
altitude</link>. Identifying (<link>
naming</link>) features and recognizing typical landform patterns are also part of the field.</p>
<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/60891.xml">
topographic study</link> may be made for a variety of reasons: military planning and geological exploration have been primary motivators to start survey programs, but detailed information about <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/586839.xml">
terrain</link> and surface features is essential for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../010/378010.xml">
planning</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/239038.xml">
construction</link> of any major <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ar)/5762_(H$ebrew_year).xml">
civil engineering</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/323158.xml">
public works</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/1091570.xml">
reclamation</link> projects.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Techniques of topography</st>
<p>

There are a variety of approaches to studying topograpy. Which method(s) to use depend on the scale and size of the area under study, its accessibility, and the quality of existing surveys. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Direct survey</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Vermessungspunkt.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A surveying point in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>

</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/60891.xml">
Surveying</link></it>
</indent>
Surveying helps determine accurately the terrestrial or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/3054853.xml">
three-dimensional space</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../217/268217.xml">
position</link> of points and the distances and angles between them using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/2741870.xml">
leveling instrument</link>s such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/248860.xml">
theodolite</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/2741870.xml">
dumpy level</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/889183.xml">
clinometer</link>s. </p>
<p>

Even though remote sensing has greatly speeded up the process of gathering information, and has allowed greater accuracy control over long distances, the direct survey still provides the basic control points and framework for all topographic work, whether manual or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
GIS</link>-based.</p>
<p>

In areas where there has been an extensive direct survey and mapping program (most of Europe and the Continental US, for example), the compiled data forms the basis of basic digital elevation datasets such as <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/410823.xml">
USGS DEM</link></format>
</information>
</message>
 data. This data must often be "cleaned" to eliminate discrepancies between surveys, but it still forms a valuable set of information for large-scale analysis.</p>
<p>

The original American topographic surveys (or the British "Ordnance" surveys) involved not only recording of relief, but identification of landmark features and vegetative land cover.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Remote sensing</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/228148.xml">
Remote sensing</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
</it>
</indent>
<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/228148.xml">
Remote sensing</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</program>
</application>
</software>
 is a general term for geodata collection at a distance from the subject area.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Aerial and satellite imagery</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/326279.xml">
Aerial photography</link></it>
</indent>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/1184557.xml">
Satellite imagery</link></it>
</indent>
Besides their role in photogrammetry, aerial and satellite imagery can be used to identify and delineate terrain features and more general land-cover features. Certainly they have become more and more a part of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/2794830.xml">
geovisualization</link>, whether <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/19877.xml">
maps</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
GIS</link> systems. False-color and non-visible <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/6478512.xml">
spectra</link> imaging can also help determine the lie of the land by delineating vegetation and other land-use information more clearly. Images can be in visible colours and in other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/6478512.xml">
spectra</link>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Photogrammetry</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/552840.xml">
Photogrammetry</link></it>
</indent>
Photogrammetry is a measurement technique for which the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/81931.xml">
co-ordinates</link> of the points in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../853/3054853.xml">
3D</link> of an object are determined by the measurements made in two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/23604.xml">
photographic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/71925.xml">
image</link>s (or more) taken starting from different positions, usually from different passes of an aerial photography flight. In this technique, the common points are identified on each image. A line of sight (or <organ wordnetid="105297523" confidence="0.8">
<sense_organ wordnetid="105299178" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="109385911" confidence="0.8">
<eye wordnetid="105311054" confidence="0.8">
<body_part wordnetid="105220461" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/3364761.xml">
ray</link></body_part>
</eye>
</part>
</sense_organ>
</organ>
) can be built from the camera location to the point on the object. It is the intersection of its rays (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/207174.xml">
triangulation</link>) which determines the relative three-dimensional position of the point. Known control points can be used to give these relative positions absolute values. More sophisticated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>s can exploit other information on the scene known a priori (for example, symmetries in certain cases allowing the rebuilding of three-dimensional co-ordinates starting from one only position of the camera).</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Radar and sonar</st>
<p>

Satellite <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/25676.xml">
radar</link> mapping is one of the major techniques of generating Digital Elevation Models (see below). Similar techniques are applied in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/965387.xml">
bathymetric</link> surveys using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/29438.xml">
sonar</link> to determine the terrain of the ocean floor. In recent years, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/41958.xml">
LIDAR</link> (<b>Li</b>ght <b>D</b>etection <b>a</b>nd <b>R</b>anging), a remote sensing technique using a laser instead of radio waves, has increasingly been employed for complex mapping needs such as charting canopies and monitoring glaciers.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Forms of topographic data</st>
<p>

Terrain is commonly modelled either using vector (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/2857072.xml">
triangulated irregular network</link> or TIN) or gridded (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/25742.xml">
Raster image</link>) mathematical models. In the most applications in environmental sciences, land surface is represented and modelled using gridded models. In civil engineering and entertainment businesses, the most representations of land surface employ some variant of TIN models. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/51531.xml">
geostatistics</link>, land surface is commonly modelled as a combination of the two signals - the smooth (spatially correlated) and the rough (noise) signal.</p>
<p>

In practice, surveyors first sample heights in an area, then use these to produce a Digital Surface Model (also known as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/78442.xml">
digital elevation model</link>). The DLSM can then be used to visualize terrain, drape remote sensing images, quantify ecological properties of a surface or extract land surface objects. Note that the contour data or any other sampled elevation datasets are not a DLSM. A DLSM implies that elevation is available continuously at each location in the study area, i.e. that the map represents a complete surface. Digital Land Surface Models should not be confused with Digital Surface Models, which can be surfaces of the canopy, buildings and similar objects. For example, in the case of  surface models produces using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/41958.xml">
LIDAR</link> technology, one can have several surfaces - starting from the top of the canopy to the actual solid earth. The difference between the two surface models can then be used to derive volumetric measures (height of trees etc). </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Raw survey data</st>
<p>

Topographic survey information is historically based upon the notes of surveyors. They may derive naming and cultural information from other local sources (for example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/72824.xml">
boundary</link> delineation may be derived from local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/2377056.xml">
cadastral</link> mapping. While of historical interest, these field notes inherently include errors and contradictions that later stages in map production resolve.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Remote sensing data</st>
<p>

As with field notes, remote sensing data (aerial and satellite photography, for example), is raw and uninterpreted. It may contain holes (due to cloud cover for example) or inconsistencies (due to the timing of specific image captures). Most modern topographic mapping includes a large component of remotely sensed data in its compilation process.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Topographic mapping</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/70713.xml">
Topographic map</link></it>
</indent>
<image location="right" width="155px" src="Europe_topography_map.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A map of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link> using <b>elevation modeling</b>
</caption>
</image>

In its contemporary definition, topographic mapping shows relief. In the United States, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/176584.xml">
USGS</link> topographic maps show relief using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/650086.xml">
contour lines</link>. The USGS calls maps based on topographic surveys, but without contours, "planimetric maps."</p>
<p>

These maps show not only the contours, but also any significant streams or other bodies of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../306/33306.xml">
water</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/11090.xml">
forest</link> cover, built-up areas or individual buildings (depending on scale), and other features and points of interest.</p>
<p>

While not officially "topographic" maps, the national surveys of other nations share many of the same features, and so they are often generally called "topographic maps."</p>
<p>

Existing topographic survey maps, because of their comprehensive and encyclopedic coverage, form the basis for much derived topographic work. Digital Elevation Models, for example, have often been created not from new remote sensing data but from existing paper topographic maps. Many government and private publishers use the artwork (especially the contour lines) from existing topographic map sheets as the basis for their own specialized or updated topographic maps<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

Topographic mapping should not be confused with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/657351.xml">
Geologic map</link>ping. The latter is concerned with underlying structures and processes to the surface, rather than with identifiable surface features.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Digital elevation modeling</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/78442.xml">
Digital elevation model</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</it>
</indent>
<image location="right" width="160px" src="Mtm-05277e_3d.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

3D rendering of a <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/78442.xml">
DEM</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 used for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/425344.xml">
topography of Mars</link>
</caption>
</image>

The digital elevation model (DEM) is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/208787.xml">
raster</link>-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/8276.xml">
digital</link> dataset of the topography (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/2021741.xml">
hypsometry</link> and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/965387.xml">
bathymetry</link>) of all or part of the Earth (or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/48510.xml">
telluric planet</link>). The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../665/23665.xml">
pixels</link> of the dataset are each assigned an elevation value, and a header portion of the dataset defines the area of coverage, the units each pixel covers, and the units of elevation (and the zero-point). DEMs may be derived from existing paper maps and survey data, or they may be generated from new satellite or other remotely-sensed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/25676.xml">
radar</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/29438.xml">
sonar</link> data.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Topological modeling</st>
<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/12398.xml">
geographic information system</link> (GIS) can recognize and analyze the spatial relationships that exist within digitally stored spatial data. These topological relationships allow complex spatial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3224795.xml">
modelling</link> and analysis to be performed. Topological relationships between geometric entities traditionally include adjacency (what adjoins what), containment (what encloses what), and proximity (how close something is to something else).
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 reconstitute a sight in synthesized images of the ground, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 determine a trajectory of overflight of the ground, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 calculate surfaces or volumes, </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 trace topographic profiles,</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Topography in other fields</st>
<p>

Topography has been applied to different science fields. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/21245.xml">
neuroscience</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/3557219.xml">
neuroimaging</link> discipline uses techniques such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../435/1165435.xml">
EEG topography</link> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/4173255.xml">
brain mapping</link>. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/56153.xml">
ophthalmology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/4584923.xml">
corneal topography</link> is used as a technique for mapping the surface curvature of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/311888.xml">
cornea</link>.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Gray1224.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Topography of thoracic and abdominal viscera.
</caption>
</image>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/13268.xml">
human anatomy</link>, topography is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/15297463.xml">
superficial human anatomy</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="65x28px" src="BlankMap-World.png">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Atlas&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/7294.xml">
Cartography</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/8096121.xml">
Topography as the study of place</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/78534.xml">
Geomorphology</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.michigan.gov/cgi/0,1607,7-158-14767-31893--F,00.html">
<it>What is topography?''</it></weblink> - Center for Geographic Information</entry>
<entry id="2">
Definition from WordNet Search - princeton.edu</entry>
<entry id="3">
Definition from Federal Citizen Information Center - pueblo.gsa.gov</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=topography">
Online Etymology Dictionary</weblink> - etymonline.com</entry>
<entry id="5">
For example, see the website of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.topsoc.org">
London Topographical Society</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
 Oxford English Dictionary "Ordnance Survey"</entry>
<entry id="7">
 http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartographie#Histoire#France </entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.topogs.org/History.htm">
Topographical Engineers - History and Personnel</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
 see for example the publications of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ngmapstore.com/jump.jsp?itemType=CATEGORY&amp;itemID=54">
National Geographic Trails Illustrated Maps</weblink> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/1404135.xml">
Delorme</link> products</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
