<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:00:18[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Audicom</title>
<id>7940030</id>
<revision>
<id>237675544</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-11T09:19:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>FlaBot</username>
<id>228773</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Audio engineering</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="Audicom5.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Solidyne's Audicom 5 running on Windows 98
</caption>
</image>

<b>Audicom</b> stands for: Audio en Computadora (Spanish).  Released in 1989, it was the world's first <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18457137.xml">
PC</link>-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/983002.xml">
broadcast automation</link> system to use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/18950025.xml">
audio data compression</link> technology based on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../448/24448.xml">
psychoacoustics</link>.<p>

The audio card was designed with standard CMOS logic ICs and used hardware to perform an audio data compression algorithm named ECAM,  based on the critical bands masking principle, a property of the human ear. Today the same principle is used in all the lossy audio bit compression systems, MP3 included. The audio card was designed for the old ISA slots of the PC and works using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/57717.xml">
direct memory access</link> to the host memory. The driver and the client application were developed by Gustavo Pesci<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>, while the hardware was designed by Ricardo Sidoti and Elio Demaria.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/983002.xml">
radio automation</link> system was launched in 1989 under the name Audicom. After 20 years, almost all the radio stations in the world are using some similar technology, now manufactured by a lot of companies around the world.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
History of Audicom's software versions</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="Audicom66.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Solidyne's Audicom 6.6 running on Windows XP
</caption>
</image>

Audicom (mid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/34640.xml">
1980</link>'s): first version, included a hardware compression audio card: ADX903</p>
<p>

Audicom II (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/34847.xml">
1989</link>): most popular version for DOS systems, exported to more than 30 countries. Introduced the concept of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/426504.xml">
Playlist</link> for computer systems, and created the concept of <link>
Live Assist</link>. When working in automatic mode, the music was selected from several directories with the /RANDOM command allowing the rotate styles along the day.</p>
<p>

Audicom III &amp; 4: not released, but developed internally. Audicom 4 was the first version intended to be a Windows version (for 16 bit Windows), but due to problems in the Win16 platform it was canceled in favor of a Win32 system (Audicom 5). The change (including staff change) caused a delay to the project of two years.</p>
<p>

Audicom 5 (Introduced at CAPER 96, commercially available at 1997): first Windows system available. There was two versions (both Win32 applications): ECAM and multimedia. The multimedia version included the option of an 'audio co-processor card' (a compressor-expanser for greater dynamic range with conventional sound cards). New ECAM cards allowd to perform the mixing on the same card. Multimedia version used two cards for mixing and 3 cards for mix and cue (which was pretty hard to install on a same PC). The Audicom 5 introduced a novel concept of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
Artificial intelligence</link> for selecting music called <link>
AutoDJ</link>, which allowed for '1 second precision' to meet the spots schedule on real time (the operator can add or remove titles and the autoDJ will meet the schedule without cut any music). Other novelty was the virtual locutor, which announces weather condition and time (based on a text to speech algorithm). A weather station was available as optional (SMT-100).</p>
<p>

Audicom 6 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/1478038.xml">
October 2000</link>): Only a multimedia version. It introduced a new play engine based on DirectX, allowing mixing on the same audio card. First broadcasting audio system to support <format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/19673.xml">
MP3</link></format>
, allowing cross-fade within two different MP3 files and CUE concurrently (all software decoding). The product was partnered with the PCI audio card <link>
SX46</link>.</p>
<p>

Audicom 7 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/88491.xml">
August 2002</link>): Included multiuser support, network ready, included autoEdit (automatic editing of MP3's files without recompressing), full MP3 mixing. Also was partnered with an advanced PCI audio card: <link>
DSP48</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 How the ECAM technology works </st>

<p>

When we start developing the perceptual coding technology for Audicom (the ECAM system),  the PCM coding was well known for its telephonic applications.   But our decision was to  use, instead of PCM linear coding,  a more complex  coding named Sigma Delta Adaptive Modulation. Since we  needed to  develop  a real system that can be manufactured with the late 1980  decade  technology, after considerable research, we decided to use a  Sigma Delta codec designed for speech coding in telephone applications. At that moment audio quality converters were not manufactured because it did not  have commercial application...   We change the clock rate and all external components to work   in wide bandwidth:  20 - 20.000 Hz.  We tested it at 96  Kbits/second and of course it does not sound well (this  was not a surprise  because was predicted by the Sigma Delta theory).</p>
<p>

At this stage we start   to use the band masking concept in a way different that  the proposed  for speech coding, because we were looking for audio quality at the full audio band. We use a crossover-like bank of  filters with four bands that follows the Ehmer curves <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>  We compress each band in a 2:1 ratio when record the sound. (2:1 means that  each 20 dB the signal changes,  the output only changes 10 dB). When reproduce,  we did a complementary expansion. </p>
<p>

To improve the audio quality we use a new Psychoacoustic concept developed by Oscar Bonello; the Burst Masking <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>  The burst masking theory deals with the concept of the “integration time” of the human ear.  If a a subject listen a burst of N milliseconds of the masking tone plus a second tone or noise, the masking threshold is dependent of the value N. When N is very high we get the Ehmer curves. For low values the masking increases. For example, if a masking curve (static) is applied to a pure tone of 1 kHz at 90dB SPL, it can be found that is possible to recognize a tone of 5 kHz, 65 dB below the tone of 1 kHz. But the masking theory shows that within a burst of 50 ms this value is reduced to 53 dB and for 5 ms to only 36 dB. .<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Modern  Systems for Radio Automation </st>
<p>

In 1983 Oscar Bonello a radio automation pioneer, and Engineering professor at the University of Buenos Aires and Fellow Member of the AES (USA) start researching about using the recently developed IBM PC computer. The problems that he faced were: 1) Create an audio PC card of good audio quality; 2) Create a bit compression algorithm; 3) Create the Automation software to be run from the PC.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

The audio card was designed with standard CMOS logic ICs and perform by hardware the ECAM bit compression algorithm based on the principle of Critical Bands Masking a property of the ear (see a brief History at MP3 ). Today the same principle as the one used by Bonello is used in all the lossy audio bit compression systems, included MP3. The audio card was designed for the old ISA slots of the PC and works using direct access to PC memory. The driver for this software was developed by Gustavo Pesci, a young software engineer, formerly a pupil of Bonello at University. The card hardware was designed for Ricardo Sidoti and Elio Demaria, both brilliant electronic engineers.</p>
<p>

The Radio Automation system was launched in 1987 under the name Audicom The software initially ran on DOS and was further changed by Sebastian Ledesma to Windows, using an Artificial Intelligence concept. Twenty years after the original Bonello invention, almost all the radio stations at the world use the same technology, now manufactured by various companies around the world. Mr Bonello refuses to apply for any type of invention patent. </p>
<p>

Modern systems typically run on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard disk</link>, where all of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/18839.xml">
music</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/932059.xml">
jingle</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/2861.xml">
advertisement</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/765178.xml">
voice track</link>s and other announcements are stored. These <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/7077.xml">
computer file</link>s may be either <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/8013.xml">
compressed</link> or uncompressed,  often with a minimal compression as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/40936.xml">
compromise</link>.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/1068736.xml">
Scheduling</link> was an important advance of these systems -- allowing for exact timing. Some systems use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/11866.xml">
GPS</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/27683.xml">
satellite</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/491851.xml">
receivers</link> to obtain exact <link>
atomic time</link>, for perfect <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../738/28738.xml">
synchronization</link> with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/45207.xml">
satellite-delivered</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/103661.xml">
programming</link>.</p>
<p>

Automation systems are now more <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/644528.xml">
interactive</link> than ever with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/8276.xml">
digital</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/193299.xml">
mixing console</link>s and can even <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../743/414743.xml">
record</link> from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/949960.xml">
telephone hybrid</link> to play back an edited <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/228569.xml">
conversation</link> with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/406703.xml">
telephone call</link>er.</p>
<p>

The simplest arrangements can even be done on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/5309.xml">
software</link> as basic as <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<player wordnetid="110439851" confidence="0.8">
<contestant wordnetid="109613191" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/76264.xml">
Winamp</link></causal_agent>
</contestant>
</player>
</person>
</physical_entity>
.</p>
<p>

There is also a trend in radio to use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../178/765178.xml">
voice-tracking</link> production techniques which make the live presenter in the studio, less critical in the overall broadcast; a great number of <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<format wordnetid="106636806" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/52301.xml">
Internet radio</link></format>
</information>
</message>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/3013559.xml">
variety hits</link> stations use automation software and voice-tracking to completely replace live on-air talent</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
PC Cards</st>
<p>

The Audicom cards are a family of PC audio cards developed by Solidyne. They were intended to the broadcasting market and some models included the Audicom broadcasting system. 
<image location="center" width="450px" src="ADX922_audio_card.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Solidyne's PC card model ADX922
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

In mid 80's Solidyne, a broadcast manufacturer company, started the project of recording audio in a PC to automate the spots emission (at that time done by cartridges). By that time, the hard disk were very expensive and extremely small (a PC hard drive allowed 10MBytes of storage), so the engineers knew that they needed to develop a system to reduce the required bits as much as possible in order to be successful. The result was the ECAM audio system, the first system was showed to the 'Secretaria de Ciencia y Tecnica de la Nacion de la Republica Argentina' in 1988.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

Models</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

ADX 903</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

ADX 922</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

ADX 925</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

ADX 925 Serie X</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

SX 48</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

SX 46</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

DSP 48</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gustavopesci.com">
Gustavo Pesci Bio</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lanacion.com.ar/Archivo/Nota.asp?nota_id=187775">
La historia del Audicom</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://books.google.com/books?id=zD9WAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=solidyne+audicom&amp;dq=solidyne+audicom&amp;pgis=1">
Audicom introduced at LAB</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
"Masking by Tones  Vs  Noise Bands",Richard Ehmer,  Journal  of Acoustical Society of America, September  1959  </entry>
<entry id="5">
 Oscar Bonello, Burst Masking, “Enmascaramiento por Rafaga”, EAA Symposium of Architectural Acoustics and Iberian Congress on Acoustics,  Madrid, Spain, October 2000,  ISBN 84-87985-03-3 </entry>
<entry id="6">
” Multiband audio processing and its influence on the coverage area of FM stereo transmission” Fig 7, Oscar Bonello, AES Journal<it>, New York, March 2007 </it></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aes.org/e-lib/browse.cfm?elib=2384">
New Improvements in Audio Signal Processing for AM Broadcasting by Bonello, Oscar</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aes.org/e-lib/browse.cfm?elib=6674">
PC-Controlled Psychoacoustic Audio Processor by Bonello, Oscar Juan</weblink></entry>
</reflist>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.solidynepro.com">
Solidyne</weblink> Company's web site.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
