<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:41:23[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Flexible spending account</title>
<id>798022</id>
<revision>
<id>244655702</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T22:12:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Sardanaphalus</username>
<id>427947</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Employment compensation</category>
<category>Taxation in the United States</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="float: right; border: 1px solid #8888aa; border-collapse:collapse; background: #fff8f7; padding: 5px; font-size: 85%; margin: 0 0 0 15px;width:240px" cellpadding="1">
<row>
<col style="background: #fcc; text-align: center; padding: 5px;">
 <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/1147240.xml">
Health care in the United States</link></b></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="padding: 5px 10px 5px 10px;">
<b>Government</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/215745.xml">
Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
 Medicare</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../794/55794.xml">
Medicaid</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/2996627.xml">
TRICARE</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
 Department of Veterans Affairs</link> (VA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/1707982.xml">
Indian Health Service</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/635422.xml">
State Children's Health Insurance Program</link> (SCHIP)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
 EMTALA</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../647/1149647.xml">
Federal Employees Health Benefits Program</link></entry>
</list>

----
<b><idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<type wordnetid="105840188" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/15343730.xml">
Private</link></kind>
</type>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/59097.xml">
Health maintenance organization</link> (HMO)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/1183870.xml">
Managed care</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/6691129.xml">
Medical underwriting</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/1184035.xml">
Preferred provider organization</link> (PPO)</entry>
</list>

----
<b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/7304558.xml">
Private consumer driven</link></b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/798022.xml">
Flexible spending account</link> (FSA)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/2988226.xml">
Health Reimbursement Account</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/797776.xml">
Health savings account</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/797848.xml">
Medical savings account</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/9154042.xml">
High Deductible Health Plan</link> (HDHP)</entry>
</list>

----
<b>Others</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/811714.xml">
Canadian and American health care systems compared</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/16463132.xml">
Health care reform in the United States</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../143/1043143.xml">
Single payer health care</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/17565113.xml">
Uninsured in the United States</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/570661.xml">
Universal health care</link></entry>
</list>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; border-top:1px solid #aaaaaa; text-align: center;"></col>
</row>
</table>

A <b>flexible spending arrangement</b> (FSA), or Flexible Spending Account, as they are commonly called, is one of a number of tax-advantaged financial accounts that can be set up through a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/8710924.xml">
cafeteria plan</link> of an employer in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
. An FSA allows an employee to set aside a portion of his or her earnings to pay for qualified expenses as established in the cafeteria plan, most commonly for medical expenses but often for dependent care or other expenses. Money deducted from an employee's pay into an FSA is not subject to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/438978.xml">
payroll tax</link>es, resulting in a substantial payroll tax savings. <p>

The most common FSA, the <b>medical expense FSA</b> (also <b>medical FSA</b> or <b>health FSA</b>), is similar to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/797776.xml">
health savings account</link> (HSA) or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/2988226.xml">
health reimbursement account</link> (HRA).  However, while HSAs and HRAs are almost exclusively used as components of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/7304558.xml">
consumer driven health care</link> plan, medical FSAs are commonly offered with more traditional health plans as well. An FSA may be utilized by paper claims or an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/8709858.xml">
FSA debit card</link> also known as a Flexcard.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Types of FSAs</st>
<p>

Most cafeteria plans offer two different flexible spending accounts; one is for qualified medical expenses and the other is for dependent care expenses.  A few cafeteria plans offer other types of FSAs, especially if the employer also offers an HSA.  Participation in one type of FSA does not affect participation in another type of FSA, but funds cannot be transferred from one FSA to another.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Medical expense FSA</st>
<p>

The most common type of FSA is used to pay for medical expenses not paid for by insurance; this usually means deductibles, copayments, and coinsurance for the employee's health plan, but may also include expenses not covered by the health plan, such as dental and vision expenses and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/192042.xml">
over-the-counter</link> drugs including a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/207040.xml">
first aid kit</link>.  A medical FSA cannot pay for health insurance premiums, cosmetic items, cosmetic surgery, controlled substances (in violation of federal law), or items that improve "general health".  All items must be intended to treat or prevent a specific medical condition; this can be as significant as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/44677.xml">
diabetes</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1771587.xml">
pregnancy</link>, or as trivial as skin cuts.  Generally, allowable items are the same as those allowable for the medical tax deduction, as outlined in <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irs.gov/publications/p502/index.html">
IRS publication 502</weblink>.</p>
<p>

The annual caps for a medical FSA varies by employer.  Unlike dependent care FSAs, there is no IRS cap on medical FSAs, but employers generally limit the annual amount each employee may contribute, in order to reduce the risk of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/798022.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Pre-funding%22])">
pre-funding</link>. Should the employee leave or be terminated and thus no longer pay in to the plan, the employer does not recapture their pre-funding from the employee's payroll deduction.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Dependent care FSA</st>
<p>

FSAs can also be established to pay for certain expenses to care for dependents that live with you while you are at work.  While this most commonly means <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/389615.xml">
child care</link>, it can also be used for adult day care for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/232585.xml">
senior citizen</link> dependents that live with you, such as parents.  It cannot be used for summer camps (other than "day camps") or for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/3118704.xml">
long term care</link> for parents that live elsewhere (such as in a nursing home).</p>
<p>

The dependent care FSA is federally capped at $5,000 per year.  While married spouses can each elect to have this amount deducted from their paycheck and applied to expenses, at tax time all withdrawals in excess of $5,000 are taxed.  Unmarried couples can each deduct and use $5,000.</p>
<p>

Unlike medical FSAs, dependent care FSAs cannot be "pre-funded"; employees can only receive reimbursement as funds are deposited into the FSA.  Also, although <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/8709858.xml">
FSA debit card</link>s can be used with dependent care FSAs, they are subject to restrictive IRS requirements that generally require employees to pay the first child-care bill of each year by other means, among other things.</p>
<p>

While medical FSAs almost always favor the taxpayer, dependent care FSAs are a more complicated matter because they are a tradeoff between pre-tax deductions and tax credits, not itemized deductions.  Enhancements to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/1515088.xml">
child tax credit</link>s in recent years have made them more attractive than dependent care FSAs for many taxpayers.</p>
<p>

If married, BOTH spouses must earn income in order for the Dependent Care FSA to work.  The only exception is if the non-earning spouse is disabled or a student.  If one spouse earns less than $5,000 then the benefit is limited to whatever that spouse earned.  Many plan coordinators do not warn of this limit.  This limitation can create a situation where the earning spouse sets up a Dependent Care FSA and dutifully sends in receipts to withdraw funds and then at tax time the FSA is effectively eliminated and all the work wasted.  See IRS Form 2441 Part III for details.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other FSAs</st>
<p>

Though not as common as the FSAs listed above, some employers have offered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/38534.xml">
adoption</link> assistance through an FSA.  Also, though medical FSAs cannot reimburse for health premiums, some small employers without a health plan have established FSAs to reimburse their employees for individual health premiums.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
FSA's coverage period</st>

<p>

An FSA's coverage period ends either at the time the "plan year" ends for your plan or at the time when your coverage under that plan ends.  Example: Loss of coverage due to a separation from the employer.  </p>
<p>

This means that if you are employed by a company from <b>January through June</b> and covered on their cafeteria benefits plan (including FSA) during that time, but do not <b>elect and pay for</b> continued coverage under that plan (i.e. COBRA).  Your coverage period is defined <b>only as January through June</b>, not January through December as one might think.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

All covered expenses must be incurred (or be dated) between January and June of that year.  </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods of withdrawal from FSAs</st>

<p>

In recent years, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/8709858.xml">
FSA debit card</link> was developed to eliminate "double-dipping" by allowing employees to access the FSA directly, as well as to simplify the substantiation requirement which required labor-intensive claims processing; the debit card also enhances the effect of "pre-funding" medical FSAs.  However, the substantiation requirement itself did not go away, and has even been expanded on by the IRS for the debit-card environment; therefore, withdrawal issues still remain for FSAs.</p>
<p>

According to Celent, as of May 2006, there were approximately 6 million debit cards in the market tied to an FSA account, representing 25% of the FSA participating community. Celent projects that FSA cards will increase FSA adoption rates. The average card participation rate was around 20% as of May 2006. By 2010, it is projected this rate will increase to 85%.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Plan year grace period</st>

<p>

In 2005, the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/15375.xml">
Internal Revenue Service</link></agency>
 authorized an optional 2½ month <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/2819414.xml">
grace period</link> that employers can use in their plans, allowing use of the funds for 2½ months after the end of the plan year.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Advantages and disadvantages of all FSAs</st>
<p>

An FSA allows money to be deducted from an employee's paycheck pre-tax and then spent on qualified expenses.</p>
<p>

For an example of potential tax savings associated with a flexible spending account, a person in the 28% Federal marginal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../124/768124.xml">
tax bracket</link> and an example 4% state tax (along with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/560096.xml">
FICA</link> taxes of typically 7.65%, for a total tax of almost 40%), could deduct $2,000 and put that money into an FSA for health care. This would result in almost $800 in tax savings.</p>

<p>

<b>Example 1: No FSA Account with Fixed Medical Expenses</b>
$NET_INCOME = $INCOME * (1 - $TAX_RATE) - $MEDICAL_EXPENSES
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Income = $50,000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tax Rate = 40%</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Medical Expenses = $2,000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Net Income = $28,000</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Example 2: Fixed Medical Expenses Reserved in an FSA Account</b>
$NET_INCOME = ($INCOME - $MEDICAL_EXPENSES)(1 - $TAX_RATE)
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Income = $50,000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tax Rate = 40%</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Medical Expenses = $2,000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Net Income = $28,800</b></entry>
</list>

There is a straight-line savings of $800, <b>IF</b> you spend everything in the FSA account <b>AND</b> you need everything you purchase.</p>
<p>

<b>Example 3: Minimum FSA Account Spending Threshold to Realize Savings</b>
$MEDICAL_EXPENSES * (1 - $TAX_RATE)
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tax Rate = 40%</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Medical Expenses = $2,000</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <b>Threshold = $1,200</b></entry>
</list>

As long as you spend at least this amount from an FSA account, every additional dollar spent improves your Net Income.</p>

<p>

If this example person had not utilized the FSA and instead itemized their deductions, they likely would not have been able to deduct this $2,000 expense because it would not have met the 7.5% of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/1477090.xml">
Adjusted Gross Income</link> threshold needed to be able to deduct it on their federal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/49674.xml">
tax return</link>.  Even if the expenses had met the 7.5% threshold, only the part in excess of 7.5% would count as an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/299563.xml">
itemized deduction</link>; and itemized deductions are only beneficial if they exceed the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/299624.xml">
standard deduction</link>, which is hard to meet unless you have home mortgage interest or large charitable contributions.  Finally, expenses for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/192042.xml">
over-the-counter</link> drugs cannot be deducted or counted towards the 7.5% threshold, but they can be paid for by the FSA.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Pre-funding</st>
<p>

One very important advantage of medical FSAs is that they are "pre-funded" by the employer:  If you set aside an amount per year in a medical FSA (as in the earlier example), the <b>entire</b> amount is available for your use immediately--either at the start of the plan year (commonly January 1) or after the first contribution to the FSA is received by the FSA vendor, depending on the plan--even though you only contribute to the FSA in small increments throughout the year (for example, 1/26 of the annual amount if you are paid biweekly).</p>
<p>

You do not continue to contribute to the plan upon termination of your employment. Thus, you could use the entire amount on day one of the plan year, terminate your employment on day two of the plan year, and contributions would have been none or negligible (e.g., perhaps 1/26 in the case of biweekly contributions).  The "free" money is not taxable. The reason for this is that the IRS views these plans for tax purposes as insurance policies. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Over-the-counter drugs &amp; medical items</st>
<p>

Another very powerful medical FSA feature that has been introduced in recent years is the ability to pay for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/192042.xml">
over-the-counter</link> (OTC) drugs and medical items. In addition to substantially expanding the range of "FSA-eligible" purchases, adding OTC items made it easier to "spend down" medical FSAs at year-end to avoid the dreaded "use it or lose it" rule.</p>
<p>

However, substantiation has again become an issue; generally, OTC purchases require either manual claims or, for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/8709858.xml">
FSA debit card</link>s, submission of receipts after the fact.  Most FSA providers require that receipts show the complete name of the item; the abbreviations on many store receipts are incomprehensible to many claims offices.  Also, some of the IRS rules on what is and isn't eligible have proven rather arcane in practice.  The recently-developed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/8713276.xml">
inventory information approval system</link> (IIAS), which separates eligible and ineligible items at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/220633.xml">
point-of-sale</link> and provides for automatic debit-card substantiation, should eliminate these issues and make medical FSAs very attractive for OTC purchases.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Use it or lose it</st>

<p>

One major drawback is that the money must be spent <b>within the coverage period</b> as defined by the benefits cafeteria plan coverage definition.  This coverage period is usually defined as the <b>period that you are covered</b> under the cafeteria plan during the "plan year". The "plan year" is commonly defined as the calendar year.  </p>
<p>

Any money that is left unspent at the end of the coverage period is forfeited back to the company; this is commonly known as the <b>"use it or lose it" rule</b>.  </p>
<p>

A second requirement is that all applications for refunds must be made by a date defined by the plan.  If funds are forfeited, this does not eliminate the requirement to pay taxes on these funds if such taxes are required.   For example, if a single person elects to withhold $5000 for child care expenses and gets married to a non-working spouse, the $5000 would become taxable.  If this person did not submit claims by the required date, the $5000 would be forfeited but taxes would still be owed on the amount.</p>
<p>

Also, the annual contribution amount must remain the same throughout the year unless certain qualifying events occur, such as the birth of a child or death of a spouse.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/8710924.xml">
Cafeteria plan</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/7304558.xml">
Consumer driven health care</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/7304558.xml">
Consumer driven health plan</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/8709858.xml">
FSA debit card</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../201/490201.xml">
Health insurance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/2988226.xml">
Health Reimbursement Account</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/797848.xml">
Medical savings account</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Footnotes</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<b>Internal Revenue Service Regulation 1.125-2</b>: Miscellaneous cafeteria plan questions and answers <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.indstate.edu/humres/docs/Section125-2.pdf">
http://www.indstate.edu/humres/docs/Section125-2.pdf</weblink>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <b>Celent Report</b>: According to figures published by Celent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/19674.xml">
15 May</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>. See also <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.celent.net/PressReleases/200605152/FSA.htm">
Flexible Spending Accounts, Flexible Cards</weblink>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
<b>IRS Publication 969</b>: Flexible Spending Arrangements (FSAs) - Distributions From an FSA <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irs.gov/publications/p969/ar02.html#d0e1788">
http://www.irs.gov/publications/p969/ar02.html#d0e1788</weblink> </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p969.pdf">
IRS Publication 969 (PDF)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irs.gov/publications/p969/index.html">
IRS Publication 969 (HTML)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p502.pdf">
IRS Publication 502, Medical and Dental Expenses (PDF)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irs.gov/irb/2003-38_IRB/ar08.html">
IRS Revenue Ruling 2003-102 (OTC items)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irs.gov/irb/2007-02_IRB/ar09.html">
Internal Revenue Bulletin:  2007-2  (Flex Debit cards)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.treas.gov/press/releases/reports/section125.pdf">
Internal Revenue Service Regulation 1.125-2 (Miscellaneous cafeteria plan questions and answers)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Most published information on FSAs is found on the websites of FSA vendors; two with which a major contributor to this article (and original author of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/8710924.xml">
cafeteria plan</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/8709858.xml">
FSA debit card</link> articles) is personally familiar with are:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tasconline.com/">
Total Administrative Services Corporation (TASC)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dpath.com/">
DataPath</weblink></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fbmc-benefits.com/">
Fringe Benefits Management Company (FBMC)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.benesyst.net/">
Benesyst</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irs.gov/publications/p502/index.html">
Official IRS site on Medical Expenses as a tax deduction</weblink> - Explains which medical expenses are covered and which are not.  (While this publication will generally also apply to the Medical Flex Spending benefit, some expenses listed in the publication are not eligible in the Medical Flex, including Long-Term care insurance, insurance premiums and expenses paid in the current year for services in prior years).  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rams.fremont2.k12.wy.us/districtoffice/DOMain/hsa_compare_chart.pdf">
Health Savings Accounts vs. Health Reimbursement Accounts vs. Medical Savings Accounts vs. Flexible Spending Accounts</weblink> - very helpful PDF chart comparing these, but has not been updated since 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ebri.org/pdf/publications/facts/0507fact-flexspend.pdf">
Fact Sheet</weblink> on FSAs from the Employee Benefit Research Institute (EBRI), May 2007</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
