<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:08:22[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<work  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100575741">
<examination  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100635850">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<survey  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100644503">
<investigation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100633864">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Site analysis</title>
<id>8025606</id>
<revision>
<id>242624316</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T23:59:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Urban studies and planning terminology</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from October 2008</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Site_analysis&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Site+analysis%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(October 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

Site Analysis is an inventory completed as a preparatory step to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/3453400.xml">
site planning</link>, a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/45346.xml">
urban planning</link> which involves research, analysis, and synthesis.  It primarily deals with basic data as it relates to a specific site.  The topic itself branches into the boundaries of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/903378.xml">
architecture</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/75286.xml">
landscape architecture</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/9251.xml">
engineering</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/9223.xml">
economics</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/45346.xml">
urban planning</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Site Analysis and Site Planning </st>
<p>

Site Analysis is an element in site planning and design.  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../948/1796948.xml">
Kevin A. Lynch</link></scholar>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</alumnus>
</theorist>
</communicator>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/53442.xml">
urban planner</link> developed an eight cycle step process of site design, in which the second step is site analysis, the focus of this section.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Site Design Process </st>
<p>

The site design process is divided up into three sections; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/25524.xml">
research</link> phase,  phase, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/330338.xml">
synthesis</link> phase.  These three phases are divided into the eight chronological steps in the design process.</p>
<p>

<b>Research Phase.</b>
The first step is defining the problem and its definition.  This is part of the research phase.  The site design and site planning process begins with the initial problem to be solved.  This is started by a client <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/19280537.xml">
contracting</link> a planner to work with a particular site.</p>
<p>

<b>Analysis Phase.</b>
The next step involves programming the site as well as site and user analysis, which is focused on in-depth below.  There are numerous site elements related to the analysis during this phase.  This is part of the analysis phase in site planning.  </p>
<p>

<b>Synthesis Phase.</b>
From the analysis, a program is developed, which is part of the synthesis phase.  The third step deals with <link>
schematic design</link> as well as a preliminary cost estimate for the site.  Step four involves more developed designs and a detailed cost estimate.  Step five is the <link>
construction documents</link> for the plan.  Bidding and contracting for the project follows as step six.  Construction then will take place as step seven.  The final step, step eight, in the site design process is occupation and management of the site.       </p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Site Analysis Elements  </st>
<p>

Numerous elements go into a given site analysis.  These elements include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/2393292.xml">
location</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/177193.xml">
neighborhood</link> context, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/1713225.xml">
site</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/56313.xml">
zoning</link>, legal elements, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/21830.xml">
natural</link> physical features, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/2839842.xml">
man-made</link> features, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/382210.xml">
circulation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/171136.xml">
utilities</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/236814.xml">
sensory</link>, human and cultural, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/5999.xml">
climate</link> components.  The following elements typically are considered in most sites: </p>
<p>

<b>Location.</b> 
The site should be related to major streets or landmarks previously existing.  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/326279.xml">
Aerial photographs</link> help in this assessment stage.  There should be documentation of distances and time from major places.  This should be completed by either driving or walking the distance first-hand. </p>
<p>

<b>Neighborhood Context.</b> 
Zoning of the neighborhood is important and information of this type can typically be found at the <link>
municipal planning department</link> of the site.  Numerous issues at this stage require direct observation.  Features of this sort include architectural patterns, street lighting, and condition of existing buildings.  This would also include the immediate surroundings of the site.The reaction of the surrounding buildings to wards the site and people moving around should be analysed.</p>
<p>

<b>Size and Zoning.</b> 
Site boundaries can be located by either verifying the dimensions physically or contacting the county tax assessor’s office.  Zoning classifications, set-backs, height restrictions, allowable site coverage, uses, and parking requirements are obtained by obtaining zoning classifications from a zoning map, which can be located from the city planning department. </p>
<p>

<b>Legal.</b> 
Typical legal information can be obtained from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/339764.xml">
deed</link> to the property.  The deed is held by the owner of the title insurance company.  In this deed is information such as the property description, present ownership, and the governmental jurisdiction the site is located in, and the city or county.  </p>
<p>

<b>Natural Physical Features.</b> 
Most of this information will be derived from the topographic features on the site.  A contour map of this magnitude can be located from the survey <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/38223.xml">
engineer</link>.  Drainage problems as well as existing natural features of trees, ground cover, ground texture, and soil conditions on the site should be directly observed.</p>
<p>

<b>Man Made Features.</b> 
Features located on the site such as buildings, walls, fences, patios, plazas, bus stop shelters should be noted.  The site and location of such features should be directly measured.  Documentation of existing <link>
historical districts</link> should be made, some of which may already have reports completed.  Locating this information can be done through the municipal planning department for the site.</p>
<p>

<b>Circulation.</b> 
The uses of streets, roads, alleys, sidewalks, and plazas are important in this inventory step.  It is not necessarily an analysis of these elements but more an analysis of what occurs on these circulation gateways.  </p>
<p>

<b>Utilities.</b>
Information for utilities concerning the site can be found through the utility departments and companies in the local area.  Generally this company has a print of the drawing of this information needed.  Information in this print includes the location of all utilities and their locations around or on the site itself.    </p>
<p>

<b>Sensory.</b>
Much of the sensory information collected will be done through first hand experience.  This type of information is obtained from sketching and photographs (sometimes aerial photographs).  Direct observation of other sensory elements of noise, odors, smoke, and pollutant areas must also be completed.  </p>
<p>

<b>Human and Cultural.</b> 
This information can be obtained through census statistics on the neighborhood.  Information regarding these statistics is available from the local municipal planning agency.  This information includes activities among people on the site and their relationships to these activities.    </p>
<p>

<b>Climate.</b> 
This information can be obtained through the local weather service.  Conditions such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/19009110.xml">
rainfall</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/28191.xml">
snowfall</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../812/52812.xml">
humidity</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../300/19572300.xml">
temperature</link> over months must be considered and analyzed.  The sun-path and vertical sun angles throughout an entire year are important to note. </p>
<p>

<it>-List taken from Site Analysis by Edward T. White</it></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gilpin, Alan. <it>Environmental Planning: a Condensed Encyclopedia</it>. Park Ridge, New Jersey: Noyes Publications, 1972. 271.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

LaGro, James A., Jr. "Site Analysis: A Contextual Approach to Sustainable Land Planning and Site Design", 2nd ed. Hoboken, New Jersey: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2008. 1-371.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

McBride, Steven B. "Site Planning and Design." The Web Book of Regional Science. 16 Nov. 2006 . </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Spreiregen, Paul D., and Beatriz De Paz. <it>Pre-Design</it>. Chicago, IL: Kaplan AEC Architecture, 2005. 1-382.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

White, Edward T. <it>Site Analysis: Diagramming Information for Architectural Design</it>. Tallahassee, Florida: Architectural Media Ltd., 2004. 1-158.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</investigation>
</survey>
</event>
</examination>
</work>
</article>
