<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:08:45[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Instituto Pedro Nunes</title>
<id>8039074</id>
<revision>
<id>225130777</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-12T01:12:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Camarinha</username>
<id>6817753</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Science and technology in Portugal</category>
<category>University of Coimbra</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Instituto Pedro Nunes</b> (<b>IPN</b>) is a non-profit private organization for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/118450.xml">
innovation</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/315952.xml">
technology transfer</link> based in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/378109.xml">
Coimbra</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/23033.xml">
Portugal</link></country>
. It is named after the Portuguese <painting wordnetid="103876519" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../568/34568.xml">
16th century</link></painting>
 mathematician and professor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<expert wordnetid="109617867" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<maker wordnetid="110284064" confidence="0.8">
<geographer wordnetid="110127555" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/227039.xml">
Pedro Nunes</link></creator>
</mathematician>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</geographer>
</maker>
</person>
</expert>
</physical_entity>
, who lived in the city of Coimbra and worked for the local university. 
<sec>
<st>
IPN profile</st>
<p>

Instituto Pedro Nunes is the technology transfer from the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/715164.xml">
University of Coimbra</link></university>
, being the main link between the University and  business sector. 
IPN work is made trough RTD in partnership with enterprises, specialized training and promotion and support to tech-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/63212.xml">
spin-off</link>s. IPN has its own technological infrastructures – six laboratories – besides accessing a network of researchers in the scientific and technological system, particularly from the University of Coimbra, mainly through the Faculty of Sciences and Technology. It also belongs to several national and international networks, including TII, EARTO, Incubator Forum and Proton (Gate2Growth). Some examples of successful technological companies born in the IPN include software company <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/18439933.xml">
Critical Software</link></company>
 and biotechnology company <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/8039116.xml">
Crioestaminal</link></institution>
</company>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
IPN laboratories and departments</st>
<p>

<b>LABPHARM</b> – Laboratory of Pharmaceutical Studies: LABPHARM covers the scientific areas of pharmacology, pharmaceutical chemistry, pharmaceutical technology and pharmacognosy. LABPHARM has for mission to provide better life quality trough scientific and technical pharmaceutical projects, working in collaboration with both public and private sector (pharmaceutical, chemical and food industry, among others).</p>
<p>

<b>LABGEO</b> – Laboratory of Geotechnique: LABGEO covers the scientific areas of Geotechnique and foundations. The main services area is consulting, engineering geology and soil mechanical characterization, based on the execution of research and field and laboratory tests. LABGEO aims to contribute to a general quality improvement on the construction of Geotechnical structures, trough applied research and services development in the area of Geotechnique.</p>
<p>

<b>LAS</b> - Laboratory of Automation and Systems: LAS develops its activities primarily in the following fields: wearable computing and instrumentation, robotics and industrial automation, image analysis, medical instrumentation and rational use of energy and support for sustainable development.</p>
<p>

<b>LEC</b> - Laboratory of Electroanalysis and Corrosion: LEC covers the areas of corrosion and of electroanalysis of trace metals or other pollutants in complex matrices, by detection in situ in real time, through continuous on-line monitoring, of inorganic or organic components of effluents or of environmental origin.</p>
<p>

<b>LED&amp;MAT</b> - Laboratory of Wear, Testing and Materials: LED&amp;MAT deals with the following areas: coatings for mechanical applications (wear and oxidation protection), recovery of inorganic waste, powder injection of ceramic materials, new metallic alloys, selection of materials,  failure analysis of in-service components, chemical analysis of solids, tribology, oxidation and corrosion, and non-destructive analysis of materials. This laboratory has also two unities: the UGRAN – Unity of Characterization and Certification of Granular Materials and the UMS – Unity for surface Modifications.</p>
<p>

<b>LIS</b> - Laboratory of Informatics and Systems: LIS includes all the fields of Information and Communication Technology, namely Information Systems, Communication Systems, Databases, Intelligent Systems, Industrial Informatics, Multimedia Systems, and Interactive Training Systems.</p>
<p>

<b>BUSINESS Incubator</b>: IPN promotes the creation of spin-off companies by giving support to innovative and technology-based ideas generated by its own laboratories, institutions of higher education, particularly the University of Coimbra, the private sector, and RTD projects in consortia with industry. The IPN’s environment allows to firms the development of knowledge in such areas as quality, management, and marketing; it also facilitates contacts with national and international markets.</p>
<p>

<b>Knowledge Valorisation and Innovation Department</b>: provides services to researchers, students and firms, as support to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../724/14724.xml">
intellectual property</link> protection and licensing, support to spin-offs creation, technology transfer and commercialization, and appliance and management of R&amp;D funded programmes.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/715164.xml">
University of Coimbra</link></university>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ipn.pt/">
Official site</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
