<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:10:31[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Documentalist</title>
<id>8099232</id>
<revision>
<id>219785280</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-16T21:30:19Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Broadbot</username>
<id>3410049</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Information science</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Documentalist</b> is a kind of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/250641.xml">
librarian</link>, trained in <link>
documentation (field)</link> and specializing in assisting researchers in their search for scientific and technical documentation. With the development of bibliographical databases such as MEDLINE, documentalists were professionals who searched such databases on the behalf of users. <p>

When the field of documentation changed its name to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/149354.xml">
information science</link>, the term information specialist often replaced the term documentalist.  </p>



<sec>
<st>
Literature</st>
<p>

Bowles, M. D. (1999). The information wars: Two cultures and the conflict in information retrieval, 1945-1999. In: M. E. Bowden, T. B. Hahn, &amp; R. V. Williams (Eds.), Proceedings of the 1998 Conference on the History and Heritage of Science Information Systems (pp. 156-166). Medford, NJ: Information Today, Inc. for the American Society for Information Science and the Chemical Heritage Foundation. Available: http://www.chemheritage.org/explore/ASIS_documents/ASIS98_Bowles.pdf</p>
<p>

Meadows, A. J. (1990). Theory in information science. Journal of Information science, 16, 59–63.</p>
<p>

Olsson, L. (1991). Bibliotekarieyrkets framtidida status. IN: Enmark, E. (Ed.). "Biblioteken och framtiden". Göteborg: Centrum för bibliotekforskning. </p>
<p>

Olsson, L. (1992). I&amp;D och profession - en fråga om teknik? Bidrag til 8:de Nordiska IoD, Helsingborg 19-21 maj, 1992. 10 sider. (I proceedings kun resumé på 1 side - manuskript udleveret på konferencen).</p>
<p>

Shera, J. (1960). School of Library Science annual report (1960–61). Cleveland, OH: Western Reserve University.</p>
<p>

Williams, R. V. (1998). The Documentation and Special Libraries Movement in the United States, 1910-1960. IN: Hahn, T. B. &amp; Buckland, M. (eds.): Historical Studies in Information Science. Medford, NJ: Information Today, Inc. (Pp. 173-180). </p>







</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
