<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:11:41[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<administrative_unit  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108077292">
<agency  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="108337324">
<header>
<title>Central Electricity Authority of India</title>
<id>8127717</id>
<revision>
<id>191557293</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-15T02:05:46Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Sardanaphalus</username>
<id>427947</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Energy in India</category>
<category>Government of India</category>
<category>Government agencies for energy (India)</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Central Electricity Authority of India</b> (CEA) is a statutory organisation constituted under section 3(1) of Electricity Supply Act 1948 ,which has been superseded by section 70(1) of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/2542486.xml">
Electricity Act 2003</link>.The CEA advises the Union Government on the matters relating to the National Electricity Policy &amp; formulates short-term and perspective plans for the development of electricity system.
<sec>
<st>
Functions</st>
<p>

Under the Electricity Act 2003, CEA prescribes the standards on matters such as construction of electrical plants,electric lines and connectivity to the grid,installation and operation of meters and safety and grid standards.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>The CEA is also responsible for concurrence of hydro power development schemes of central,state and private sectors taking into consideration the factors which will result in efficient development of the river and its tributaries for power generation,consistent with the requirement of drinking water,irrigation,navigation and flood control. 
The CEA plays a lead role in promoting the integrated operations of the regional power grids and the evolution of a National grid.The eastern,western and north-eastern grid have been integrated and are operating in a synchronous mode.The eastern grid is connected to the northern as well as southern grid through <link>
HVDC</link> back to back links.The western grid is also connected to the northern and southern grid through similar arrangements.The CEA facilitates exchange of power within the country from surplus to deficit regions and with the neighbouring countries for mutual benefits.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Advisory Role</st>
<p>

The CEA advises central government, state governments and regulatory commissions on all technical matters relating to generation,transmission and distribution of electricity. It also advises state governments,licensees or generating companies  on matters which shall enable them to operate and maintain the electricity system under their ownership or control in an improved manner and where necessary, in coordination with any other government, licensee or the generating company owning or having control of another electricity system.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book"> India Yearbook 2007.&#32;Publications Division,Ministry of Information &amp; Broadcasting,Govt. Of India,&#32;Pg. 259. ISBN 81-230-1423-6.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book"> India Yearbook 2007.&#32;Publications Division,Ministry of Information &amp; Broadcasting,Govt. Of India,&#32;Pg. 260. ISBN 81-230-1423-6.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cea.nic.in/">
Central Electricity Authority of India</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</agency>
</administrative_unit>
</article>
