<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:22:03[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Bose-Einstein condensation: a network theory approach</title>
<id>8337948</id>
<revision>
<id>238352665</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-14T13:02:09Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Terraxos</username>
<id>794371</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Applied and interdisciplinary physics</category>
<category>Miscellaneous articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Physics articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Graph theory</category>
<category>Condensed matter physics</category>
<category>Articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Pages needing expert attention</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from September 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is written like  and may require .</b>
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Bose-Einstein_condensation:_a_network_theory_approach&amp;action=edit">
help improve it</weblink> by rewriting it in an . <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.</b><p>

  may be able to help recruit one.
If a more appropriate  or 
portalexists, please adjust this template accordingly.</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="350px" src="Bec5555.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<b>Fig.1</b> Bose-Einstein Condensation at 400, 200, and 50 nano-Kelvins.The peaks show that as the temperature goes down, more and more atoms "condense" to the same energy level.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/22939.xml">
physics</link>, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/4474.xml">
Bose-Einstein condensate</link> is a state of matter that occurs in certain gases at very low temperatures. Any elementary particle, atom, or molecule, can be classified as one of two types: a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/18978718.xml">
Boson</link> or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/11529.xml">
Fermion</link>. For example, an electron is a Fermion, while a photon or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../256/13256.xml">
helium</link> atom is a Boson.  In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
Quantum mechanics</link>, the energy of a (bound) particle is limited to set of discrete values, called energy levels. An important characteristic of a Fermion is that it obeys the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/24669.xml">
Pauli exclusion principle</link></concept>
</idea>
, which states that no two Fermions may occupy the same energy level. Bosons, on the other hand, do not obey the exclusion principle, and any number can exist in the same energy level. As a result, at very low energies (or temperatures), a great majority of the Bosons in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/1064839.xml">
Bose gas</link> can be crowded into the lowest energy state, creating a Bose-Einstein condensate. </p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/766409.xml">
network theory</link>, a network is characterized by a set of nodes or vertices and a set of links between these nodes. This is a very general concept, and may be applied to many situations, such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
world wide web</link>, in which each page is a node in the network, and every link from that page to another page is a link in the network. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/358477.xml">
random graph</link> is a network which changes in time, with nodes and links appearing and disappearing randomly, but with certain definite probablilities. Again, one possible model is the internet, which also changes in time. In a particular type of random graph, called a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/8370929.xml">
fitness model</link>, the nodes and links have simple probabilities of appearing and disappearing. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

In the late 1990s, Ginestra Bianconi was a graduate student, working with Dr. <link>
Albert-László Barabási</link>, a noted network theorist<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  . At his request, she began investigating the fitness model, and realized that if each node in the network were thought of as an energy level, and each link as a particle, then a perfect analogy could be drawn between the mathematics of the network and the mathematics of a Bose gas. In particular, she found that under certain conditions, a single node could acquire most, if not all of the links in the network, resulting in the network analog of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/4474.xml">
Bose-Einstein condensate</link>. These results have implications for any real situation involving random graphs, including the world wide web, social networks, and financial markets.</p>

<sec>
<st>
The concept</st>
<p>

The result of the efforts of Bose and Einstein is the concept of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../839/1064839.xml">
Bose gas</link>, governed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/188935.xml">
Bose-Einstein statistics</link>, which describes the statistical distribution of identical particles with integer spin, now known as bosons (Such as the photon and helium-4). In Bose-Einstein statistics, the Pauli exclusion principle is not obeyed so that any number of identical bosons can be in the same state. Einstein speculated that cooling bosonic atoms to a very low temperature would cause them to fall (or "condense") into the lowest accessible quantum state, resulting in a new form of matter. This transition occurs below a critical temperature, which for a uniform three-dimensional Bose gas consisting of non-interacting particles with no apparent internal degrees of freedom is given by:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>T_c=\left(\frac{n}{\zeta(3/2)}\right)^{2/3}\frac{h^2}{2\pi m k_B}</math>
</indent>

where:</p>

<p>

<table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>
<math>T_c</math></col>
<col>
&nbsp;is&nbsp;</col>
<col>
the critical temperature,</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<math>n</math></col>

<col>
the particle density,</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<math>m</math></col>

<col>
the mass per boson,</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<math>h</math></col>

<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/19594213.xml">
Planck's constant</link>,</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<math>k_B</math></col>

<col>
 the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<constant wordnetid="105858936" confidence="0.8">
<quantity wordnetid="105855125" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/53702.xml">
Boltzmann constant</link></quantity>
</constant>
</concept>
</idea>
, and</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<math>\zeta</math></col>

<col>
 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/25809.xml">
Riemann zeta function</link>; <math>\zeta(3/2)</math>&nbsp;≈&nbsp;2.6124.</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History and measurement </st>

<p>

In the early 1920s <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/71777.xml">
Satyendra Nath Bose</link></scientist>
</person>
 was studying the new idea that light comes in little discrete packets, or quanta. Bose assumed certain rules for deciding when two photons should be counted up as either identical or different. We now call these rules <b>Bose statistics</b> (or sometimes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/188935.xml">
Bose-Einstein statistics</link>). Albert Einstein guessed that these same rules might apply to atoms. He worked out the theory for how atoms would behave in a gas if these new rules applied. What he found was that the equations said that generally there would not be much difference, except at very low temperatures. If the atoms were cold enough, something very unusual was supposed to happen. It was so strange he was not sure it was correct. Not all types of atoms actually follow the rules for Bose statistics. However, some atoms do, and for those Einstein's predictions were right. But even for those kinds of atoms, he did not realize the most important effects that his equations were predicting.  The effects come from the fact that, at very low temperatures, most of the atoms are in the same quantum level.  If you put an atom in any kind of container, even a mixing bowl, it also can only have certain particular energies. It cannot roll around in there with just any speed it wants. It has to choose from a particular set of allowed energies. They are so close together in energy that you never notice there are tiny steps. What Einstein's equations predicted was that at normal temperatures the atoms would be in many different levels. <b>However, at very low temperatures, a large fraction of the atoms would suddenly go crashing down into the very lowest energy level. It means that all the atoms are absolutely identical</b> (<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colorado.edu/physics/2000/applets/bec.html">
see how this happens</weblink>). There is no possible measurement that can tell them apart. The first such <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colorado.edu/news/nobel/wiemancornell/background.html">
Bose-Einstein Condensate</weblink> in alkali gases (<b>Fig.1</b>) was produced by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colorado.edu/news/nobel/wiemancornell/cornell.html">
Eric Cornell</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colorado.edu/news/nobel/wiemancornell/wieman.html">
Carl Wieman</weblink> in 1995 at the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.colorado.edu">
University of Colorado at Boulder</weblink> and independently by Wolfgang Ketterle of the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mit.edu">
Massachusettes Institute of Technology</weblink>. They were awarded the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/2001/">
Nobel Prize in Physics in 2001</weblink>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Connection with network theory</st>
<p>

The evolution of many complex systems, including the World Wide Web, business, and citation networks,
is encoded in the dynamic web describing the interactions between the system’s constituents. <b>Despite their irreversible and nonequilibrium nature these networks follow Bose statistics and can undergo Bose-Einstein condensation</b>. Addressing the dynamical properties of these nonequilibrium systems within the framework of equilibrium quantum gases predicts that the “first-mover-advantage,” “fit-get-rich(<b>FGR</b>),” and “winner-takes-all” phenomena observed in competitive systems are thermodynamically distinct phases of the underlying evolving networks<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.</p>



<p>

Starting from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/8370929.xml">
fitness model</link>, the mapping of a Bose gas to a network can be done by assigning an energy <b>∈i</b> to each node, determined by its fitness through the relation<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>\epsilon_i=-\frac{1}{\beta}\ln{\eta_i}</math>
</indent>

where <b>β=1/T</b> plays the role of inverse temperature. An edge between two nodes <b>i</b> and <b>j</b>, having energies <b>∈i</b> and <b>∈j</b> , corresponds to two noninteracting particles, one on each energy level (<b>Fig.2</b>). Adding a new node <b>l</b> to the network corresponds to adding a new energy level <b>∈l</b> and <b>2m</b> new particles to the system. Half of these particles are deposited on the level <b>∈l</b> (since all new edges start from the new node), while the other half are distributed between the energy levels of the end points of the new edges, the probability that a particle lands on level <b>i</b> being given by</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>\prod_i=\frac{e^{\beta\epsilon_i}k_i}{\sum e^{\beta\epsilon_i}k_i}.</math>
</indent>

The continuum theory predicts that the rate at which particles accumulate on energy level <b>∈i</b> is given by</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>\frac{\partial k_i(\epsilon_i,t,t_i)}{\partial t}=m\frac{e^{\beta\epsilon_i}k_i(\epsilon_i,t,t_i)}{Z_t}</math>
</indent>

where <b><math>k</math>i(∈i,t, ti)</b> is the occupation number of the level <b>i</b> and <b>Zt</b> is the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/312252.xml">
partition function</link></concept>
</idea>
, defined as </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>Z_t=\sum_j t e^{\beta\epsilon_i}k_j((\epsilon_i,t,t_i)).</math>
</indent>

The solution of this differential equation is </p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>k_i((\epsilon_i,t,t_i)=m\left(\frac{t}{t_i}\right)^{f(\epsilon_i)}</math>
</indent>

where the dynamic exponent <b>f(∈)</b> satisfies <b>f(∈)=e-β(∈-μ)</b>, <b>μ</b> plays the role of the chemical potential, satisfying the equation</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>\int deg(\epsilon)\frac{1}{e^{\beta(\epsilon-\mu)}-1}=1</math>
</indent>

and <b>deg(∈)</b> is the degeneracy of the energy level <b>∈</b>. In the <b>t → ∞</b> limit the occupation number, giving the number of particles with energy <b>∈</b>, follows the familiar Bose statistics</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>n(\epsilon)=\frac{1}{e^{\beta(\epsilon -\mu)}-1}.</math>
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
What all this means</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="350px" src="Bec2222.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

<b>Fig.3 </b>Numerical evidence for Bose-Einstein condensation
in a network model<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.
</caption>
</image>

<b>The mapping of a Bose gas predicts the existence of two distinct phases as a function of the energy distribution.</b> In the fit-get-rich phase, describing the case of uniform fitness, the fitter nodes acquire edges at a higher rate than older but less fit nodes. In the end the fittest node will have the most edges, but the richest node is not the absolute winner, since its share of the edges (i.e the ratio of its edges to the total number of edges in the system) reduces to zero in the limit of large system sizes (<b>Fig.2(b)</b>). The unexpected outcome of this mapping is the possibility of Bose-Einstein Condensation for <b><math>T&amp;lt;T</math>BE</b>, when the fittest node acquires a finite fraction of the edges and maintains this share of edges over time (<b>Fig.2(c)</b>). </p>
<p>

A representative <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/8370929.xml">
fitness distribution</link> <b>ρ(η)</b> that leads to a condensations</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

 <math>\rho(\eta)=(1-\eta)^{\lambda}</math>
</indent>

with <b>λ=1</b>
However, the existence of the Bose-Einstein Condensation or the fit-get-rich phase does not depend on the temperature or <b>β</b> of the system but depends only on the functional form of the fitness distribution <b>ρ(η)</b> of the system. In the end, the <b>β</b> falls out of all topologically important quantities. In fact it can be shown that Bose-Einstein Condensation exists in the fitness model even without mapping to a Bose gas<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. A similar gelation can be seen in models with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/8378158.xml">
superlinear preferential attachment</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>, however, it is not clear whether this is an accident or a deeper connection lies between this and the fitness model.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite id="Reference-Barabási-2002" style="font-style:normal" class="book"><link>
Barabási, Albert-László</link>&#32;(2002). Linked.&#32;Cambridge, MA:&#32;Perseus Publishing. ISBN 0-7382-0667-9.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
Bianconi, G.;  Barabási, A.-L. (2001). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://prola.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v86/i24/p5632_1">
Bose-Einstein Condensation in Complex Networks.</weblink>" <it><periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/649723.xml">
Phys. Rev. Lett.</link></periodical>
</it> <b>86</b>: 5632–35.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Albert, R.; Barabási, A.-L. (2002). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://prola.aps.org/abstract/RMP/v74/i1/p47_1">
Statistical mechanics of complex networks.</weblink>" <it><periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/3790957.xml">
Rev. Mod. Phys.</link></periodical>
</it> <b>74</b>: 47–97.</entry>
<entry id="4">
Dorogovtsev, S. N.; Mendes, J. F. F. (2001). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://prola.aps.org/abstract/PRE/v63/i5/e056125">
Scaling properties of scale-free evolving networks:  Continuous approach.</weblink> <it><periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/419663.xml">
Phys. Rev. E</link></periodical>
</it>
<b>63</b>: 056125.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Krapivsky, P. L.; Redner, S.; Leyvraz, F. (2000). "<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://prola.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v85/i21/p4629_1">
Connectivity of Growing Random Networks.</weblink>" <it><periodical wordnetid="106593296" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/649723.xml">
Phys. Rev.
Lett.</link></periodical>
</it> <b>85</b>: 4629–32.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
