<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:20:10[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Copying mechanism</title>
<id>8378440</id>
<revision>
<id>154279122</id>
<timestamp>2007-08-29T00:01:12Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Dlodge</username>
<id>488224</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing context</category>
<category>Graph theory</category>
<category>Wikipedia introduction cleanup</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The introduction to this article provides <b>insufficient context</b> for those unfamiliar with the subject.
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Copying_mechanism&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink> with a .</col>
</row>
</table>


A <b>copying mechanism</b> is a network growth mechanism of iterated duplication and mutation. There are several copying models based on it. The General Copying Model starts with a small initial graph and, at each time step, a new vertex and k outgoing edges are added. As a result of a stochastic selection, either k vertices are randomly selected as heads, or one vertex is randomly selected and k outgoing edges are ‘copied’ as heads of the new edges. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.  
<sec>
<st>
 Motivation </st>
<p>

Copying mechanism is motivated by the following intuition:</p>
<p>

(I) Some authors will note an interesting (but hitherto
unknown on the web) commonality between certain
pages, and will link to pages exhibiting this commonality. </p>
<p>

(II) Most authors, on the other hand, will be interested
in certain already-represented topics, and will collect
together links to pages about these topics.</p>
<p>

Those are the growth and preferential attachment properties of the networks.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Description </st>
<p>

For the simple case, nodes are never deleted. At each step we create a new node
with a single edge emanating from it. Let u be a page chosen
uniformly at random from the pages in existence before this
step.</p>
<p>

(I) With probability <math>p</math>, the only parameter of the model,
the new edge points to u. </p>
<p>

(II) With probability <math>1-p</math>,
the new edge points to the destination of u's (sole) out-link;
the new node attains its edge by copying. </p>
<p>

The second process increases the probability of high-degree nodes' receiving new incoming edges. In fact, since u is selected randomly, the probability that a webpage with degree <math>k</math>
will
receive a new hyperlink is proportional
with
<math>(1-p)k</math>, indicating that the copying mechanism effectively amounts to a
linear preferential attachment. Kumar et al. prove that the expectation of the incoming <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/2129782.xml">
degree distribution</link>
is <math>P(k_{in})=k^{-(2-p)/(1-p)}</math>,
thus <math>P(k)</math> follows a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/24522.xml">
power-law</link> with an exponent which varies between 2 (for
<math>p\rightarrow 0</math>) and <math>\infty</math> (for <math>p\rightarrow 1</math>).</p>
<p>

Above is the linear growth copying model. Since the web is currently growing exponentially,
there is the exponential growth copying model. At each step a new epoch of vertices arrives whose size is a constant
fraction of the current graph. Each of these vertices may
link only to vertices from previous epochs. </p>
<p>

The evolving models above are by no means complete. They
can be extended in several ways. First of all, the tails in our
models were either static, chosen uniformly from the new
vertices, or chosen from the existing vertices proportional
to their out-degrees. This process could be made more sophisticated
to account for the observed deviations of the
out-degree distribution from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/24522.xml">
power-law</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/23543.xml">
distribution</link>.
Similarly, the models can be extended to include death processes,
which cause vertices and edges to disappear as time
evolves. A number of other extensions are possible, but we
seek to determine the properties of this simple model, in order
to understand which extensions are necessary to capture
the complexity of the web.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Examples</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Undirected network models</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Protein interaction networks</st>
<p>

Vazquez proposed a growing graph based on duplication modeling protein interactions. At every time step a prototype is chosen randomly. With probability q edges of the prototype are copied. With probability p an edge to the prototype is created.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Proteome networks</st>

<p>

Sole proposed a growing graph initialized with a 5-ring substrate. At every time step a new node is added and a
prototype is chosen at random. The prototype's edges are copied with a probability δ. Furthermore, random nodes are connected to the newly introduced node with probability α= β/N, where δ and β are given parameters in (0,1) and N is the number of total nodes at the considered time step. (see fig. 1). <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Directed network models</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Biological networks</st>
<p>

Middendorf- Ziv (MZ) proposed a growing directed graph modeling biological network dynamics. A prototype is chosen at random and duplicated. The prototype or progenitor node has edges pruned with probability β and edges added with probability αR. V. Sole, R. Pastor-Satorras, E. Smith, T. B. Kepler, A model of large-scale proteome evolution, arXiv.org:cond-mat/0207311.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
WWW networks and citation networks</st>
<p>

Vazquez proposed a growth model based on a recursive 'copying' mechanism, continuing to 2nd nearest neighbors, 3rd nearest neighbors etc. The authors call it a 'random walk' mechanism.).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Growing network with copying (GNC)</st>
<p>

<image location="left" width="320px" src="GNC2.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

<b>Fig. 2:</b>  Illustration of the growing network with copying (GNC). The time order of the nodes is indicated. Initial links are solid and links to ancestor nodes are dashed. Later links partially obscure earlier links. The new node initially attaches to random target node 4, as well as to its ancestors, 1 and 3.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>

</caption>
</image>
 </p>
<p>

Krapivsky and Redner proposed a new growing network model, which grows by adding nodes one at a time. A newly introduced node randomly selects a target node and links to it, as well as to all ancestor nodes of the target node (Fig. 2). If the target node is the initial root node, no additional links are generated by the copying mechanism. If the newly introduced node were to always choose the root node as the target, a star graph would be generated. On the other hand, if the target node is always the most recent one in the network, all previous nodes are ancestors of the target and the copying mechanism would give a complete graph. Correspondingly, the total number of links <math>L_N</math>  in a network of N nodes can range from N−1 (star graph) to N(N−1)/2 (complete graph). Notice also that the number of outgoing links from each new node (the out-degree) can range between 1 and the current number of nodes. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
A. Kogias, Int. J. Web Engineering and Technology, Vol. 2, No. 1, 2005.</entry>
<entry id="2">
A. Vazquez, A. Flammini, A. Maritan, A. Vespignani, Modeling of protein interaction networks, arXiv:cond-mat/0108043.</entry>
<entry id="3">
R. V. Sole, R. Pastor-Satorras, E. Smith, T. B. Kepler, A model of large-scale proteome evolution, arXiv.org:cond-mat/0207311.</entry>
<entry id="4">
A. Vazquez, Knowing a network by walking on it: emergence of scaling, arXiv:cond-mat/0006132.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Krapivsky, P. L., and Redner, S., Network growth by copying, Phys. Rev. E 71 036118 (2005).</entry>
</reflist>
</p>
<p>

6. Kleinberg, J. M., R. Kumar, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, and A. Tomkins, 1999, Proceedings of the International Conference on Combinatorics and Computing.</p>
<p>

7. Kumar, R., P. Raghavan, S. Rajalopagan, D. Sivakumar, A. S. Tomkins and E. Upfal, 2000a, Proceedings of the 19th  Symposium on Principles of Database Systems.</p>
<p>

8. Kumar, R., P. Raghavan, S. Rajalopagan, D. Sivakumar, A. S. Tomkins and E. Upfal, 2000b, Proceedings of the 41st IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science.</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
