<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:23:06[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Social business</title>
<id>8383571</id>
<revision>
<id>237685525</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-11T10:55:29Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Olivier2point0</username>
<id>7415473</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Social enterprise</category>
<category>Sociology</category>
<category>Social economy</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>social business</b> is one which aims to be financially self-sufficient, if not profitable, in its pursuit of a social, ethical or environmental goal.  Examples of social businesses in the United Kingdom included <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ethicalproperty.co.uk/">
The Ethical Property Company</weblink>, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.divinechocolate.com/home/default.aspx">
Divine Chocolate</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fairfinance.org.uk/">
Fair Finance</weblink>.  A more famous example is the Bangladeshi <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/545529.xml">
Grameen Bank</link></institution>
</company>
, set up by Professor Dr. <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/548105.xml">
Muhammad Yunus</link></person>
 in 1976.  Dr. Yunus is a key proponent of the social business model, seeing it as a means to eradicate poverty and to influence the future of capitalism.  However, his definition specifies that profits cannot be distributed to investors and must instead be ploughed back into the business or the community it serves.  
<sec>
<st>
Definition</st>
<p>

Social businesses can be defined as follows:</p>
<p>

Social Businesses seek to profit from acts that generate social improvements and serve a broader human development purpose. A key attribute of social businesses is that an increase in revenue corresponds to an incremental social enhancement. The social mission will permeate the culture and structure of the organization and the dual bottom lines - social and economic will be in equal standing with the firm pursuing long term maximization of both.<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/35180.xml">
1</link></p>

<p>

In his book <it>Creating a World without Poverty - Social Business and the Future of Capitalism</it>, Professor Dr. <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/548105.xml">
Muhammad Yunus</link></person>
 defines what a social business is and what it is not. It boils down to the following requirements:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>social objectives:</b> it needs to have positive social objectives (help comes from the altruistic social services that the business provides to the poor): e.g. health, education, poverty, environment or climate urgency</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>community ownership:</b> it needs to be owned by the poor or disadvantaged (dividends and financial growth return to the poor where their fiscal situations are helped bringing them out of poverty): e.g. women, young people or long-term unemployed</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>non-profit distribution:</b> investors may not, after having had their investments paid back, take profits out of the enterprise.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A social business is driven to bring about change while pursuing profits. Although from a strictly capitalistic perspective it seems foolish to pursue a goal other than profit, social businesses aim to meet certain social and environmental goals. The Grameen bank is an example of a business that combines two of these business models into one; it offers social services and goods to the poor and in addition is owned by the poor. </p>
<p>

Others, including <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.catfund.com">
Catalyst Fund Management &amp; Research</weblink>, argue that there is no benefit in restricting a company's ability to distribute profit to investors and that this may in fact serve to reduce a business's access to much-needed capital.  Capital restrictions may then compromise the company's ability to achieve its social aims.</p>
<p>

Professor Dr. <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/548105.xml">
Muhammad Yunus</link></person>
 argues that capitalism is too narrowly defined. The concept of the individual as being solely focused on profit maximising ignores other aspects of life, religious, emotional, and political. Failures of this system to address vital needs, that are commonly regarded as market failures are actually conceptualisation failures, i.e. failures to capture the essence of a human being in economic theory.</p>
<p>

Professor Dr. <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/548105.xml">
Muhammad Yunus</link></person>
 postulates a new world of business in which profit-maximising enterprises and social-benefit-maximising enterprises coexist. In addition, a social business would operate much like a profit-maximizing business in that the company as a whole grows financially and gains profits. The only difference is that the company's shareholders and investors would be re-accumulating their initial investment as opposed to receiving dividends. He calls the latter social business enterprises.</p>
<p>

At this point it seems vital to distinguish between enterprises in the financial economy that make money out of money and companies in the real economy using money to deliver products and services.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Talk to walk </st>

<p>

In the first chapter of <it>Creating a World without Poverty - Social Business and the Future of Capitalism</it>, Professor Dr. <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/548105.xml">
Muhammad Yunus</link></person>
 puts forward his meeting with Franck Riboud, CEO of Group Danone, in 2005. Sharing ideas, they decided to launch a joint venture in Bangladesh : concrete execution of a social business, reducing poverty and bringing health through food to as many as possible. This project, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.danonecommunities.com/?page_id=145">
Grameen Danone Foods</weblink>, has set four objectives :
<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 To develop a product that has high nutritional value and is affordable for the poorest individuals</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 To improve the living conditions of the population : jobs, income level, enhancement of the social fabric</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 To protect the environment and conserve resources</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 To ensure a sustainable economic activity</entry>
</list>

<it>"Grameen Danone Foods is a unique opportunity to create a company with a strong social dimension, a business whose goal is not to maximize profits but to serve the interests of the population, yet without sustaining losses. This small-scale project may be the start of a whole new type of market that will change the economic foundations of the world."</it>
Professor Dr. <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/548105.xml">
Muhammad Yunus</link></person>
, President of the Grameen Group
It is the first project launched by <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.danonecommunities.com/">
danone.communities</weblink>, a dedicated fund to incubate and developp social businesses reducing poverty and bringing health through food.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Social Business Enterprises</st>
<p>

Social Business Enterprises (SBE) are based on the benefit maximisation principle. They are operated as a business enterprise with the objective to pass on all the benefits to the customer. SBEs are non-loss, non-dividend companies that compete with profit-maximising enterprises and other social business enterprises.</p>
<p>

Key ingredients to the success of the approach are education, institutions to make social businesses visible in the market place (a social stock market), rating agencies, appropriate impact assessment tools, indices to understand which social business enterprise is doing more and/or better than others so that social investors are correctly guided. The industry will need its Social Wall Street Journal and Social Financial Times.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mexican counter model</st>
<p>

Having been named as no. 22 of the world's greatest 30 entrepreneurs by <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/945157.xml">
Business Week</link></it>, Yunus is adamant about not making money off the poor. He has condemned the Mexican model of Carlos Danel and Carlos Labarthe of going public and profiting from microlending.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The "Two Carloses" countered that their bank better taps the "boundless pool of investor capital rather than the limited pool of donor money."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Alex Counts, the president of the Grameen Foundation, retorted that the poor clients were "generating the profits but they were excluded from them."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

Social objectives and financial rewards thus have to be considered for investors, managers and employees as well as the clients of an enterprise, especially if the enterprise deals with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/8983183.xml">
money</link> as its product.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/68754.xml">
market failures</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
micro_credit</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/2939161.xml">
social entrepreneur</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../161/2939161.xml">
social entrepreneurship</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/1690901.xml">
social enterprise</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/1744415.xml">
double bottom line</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/316929.xml">
triple bottom line</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/05/business/worldbusiness/05micro.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=1&amp;ei=5087&amp;em&amp;en=253b1304b9bc5c3f&amp;ex=1207540800&amp;oref=slogin">
Microfinance's Success Sets Off a Debate in Mexico</weblink>".&#32;  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/30680.xml">
New York Times</link>&#32;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
April 5</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/35825.xml">
2008</link>).</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.grameen-info.org/bank/socialbusinessentrepreneurs.htm">
Yunus, Muhammad, Social Business Entrepeneurs Are the Solution</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fleischer, Daniel (2001), thesis <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://peaceworks.com/inc/LSE_FINAL_THESIS.pdf">
Profit with a conscience, can business be good?</weblink> London School of Economics and Political Science </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Yunus, Muhammad (2008), <it>Creating a World Without Poverty: Social Business and the Future of Capitalism''</it></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.grameenfoundation.org">
Grameen Foundation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/2006/yunus-lecture-en.html">
Yunus Nobel Peace Prize lecture</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kW-4gJmXy5M">
Muhammad Yunus: Building Social Business Ventures Video at youtube.com</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://yunusphere.net">
YuNuSphere - Expanding Dr. Yunus' Sphere of Influence - Proposing "Usury-Free Banking" as "Social Business"</weblink> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.schwabfound.org">
Schwab Foundation</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ashoka.org">
Ashoka.org</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.danonecommunities.com/">
danone.communities</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nextbillion.net/">
Next Billion</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>






</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
