<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:26:16[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Complexity economics</title>
<id>8503698</id>
<revision>
<id>234994138</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-29T14:35:26Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mr3641</username>
<id>1032181</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Economic theories</category>
<category>Complex systems theory</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Complexity economics</b> is the application of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/62903.xml">
complexity science</link> to the problems of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../223/9223.xml">
economics</link>. It is one of the four C's of a new paradigm surfacing in the field of economics. The four C's are complexity, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/7615.xml">
chaos</link>, catastrophe and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/5904.xml">
cybernetics</link>. This new mode of economic thought rejects traditional assumptions that imply that the economy is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/402048.xml">
closed system</link> that eventually reaches an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/227572.xml">
equilibrium</link>. Instead, it views economies as open <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../810/1428810.xml">
complex adaptive systems</link> with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/790808.xml">
endogenous</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/9236.xml">
evolution</link>. Complex systems do not necessarily settle to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/37425.xml">
equilibrium</link> &mdash; even ideal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/47922.xml">
deterministic</link> models may exhibit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/7615.xml">
chaos</link>, which is distinct from both random (nondeterministic) and analytic behavior.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>
<sec>
<st>
 Introduction </st>
<p>

Complexity economics rejects many aspects of traditional economic theory. The mathematical models used by traditional economics were formulated in an analogy with early models of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/29952.xml">
thermodynamics</link>. These mathematical models of economics were substantially based on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/166404.xml">
first law of thermodynamics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/265823.xml">
equilibrium</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  Later, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/133017.xml">
second law of thermodynamics</link>, concerning the growing amount of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/9891.xml">
entropy</link> in any spontaneous physical process, was formulated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/175146.xml">
Rudolf Clausius</link>. Proponents of complexity economics claim that traditional economic models never adapted to the latter discovery and thus remain incomplete models of reality, and that mainstream economists are yet to introduce <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/15445.xml">
information entropy</link> to their models. Information entropy was developed in 1949 by <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/5693.xml">
C. Shannon</link></scientist>
 and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/473287.xml">
W. Weaver</link></research_worker>
</mathematician>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, based on <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/544255.xml">
Boltzmann's</link></scientist>
</person>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/4701125.xml">
statistical thermodynamics</link>, as "information uncertainty", associated with any probability distribution. Entropy has been used at least since 1988 to formulate the important concepts of organization and disorder, viewed as basic state parameters, in describing/simulating the evolution of complex systems (including economic systems).</p>
<p>

In the light of the new concepts introduced, economic systems shall no more be considered as "naturally" inclined to achieve equilibrium states. On the contrary, economic systems - like most complex and self-organized systems - are <it>intrinsically</it> evolutionary systems, which tend to develop, prevailingly toward levels of higher internal organization; though the possibility of involution processes - or even of catastrophic events - remains immanent. Traditional economic models have been constructed by allowing only a very small amount of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/176622.xml">
degrees of freedom</link>, in order to simplify models. For example, the relation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/31741.xml">
unemployment</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../286/38286.xml">
inflation</link> is traditionally considered to be a simple function with one degree of freedom, allowing for very little entropy.</p>
<p>

As to the practicability of theoretical instruments, there is also a crucial difference to allow for: traditional economics was conceived before computers had been invented. Computational simulations have made it possible to demonstrate macro-level rules using only micro-level behaviors without assuming idealized market actors. For example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/24562.xml">
Pareto's law</link> can be demonstrated to arise spontaneously.</p>
<p>

Complexity economics is built on foundations which draw inspiration from areas such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/177698.xml">
behavioral economics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/859910.xml">
institutional economics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../030/1030.xml">
Austrian economics</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/162791.xml">
evolutionary economics</link>. Complexity incorporates components from each of these areas of economic thought, though the complex perspective includes many more characteristics to describe a dynamic system such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/37436.xml">
emergence</link>, sensitive dependence on initial conditions, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/288278.xml">
red queen behavior</link>, and complex systems usually incorporate a selection mechanism as described by most general evolutionary models. There is no widely accepted specific definition for complexity as it pertains to economic systems. This is largely due to the fact that the field as a whole is still under construction.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Behavior of complex systems </st>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<economist wordnetid="110043643" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<social_scientist wordnetid="110619642" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Brian Arthur</link></associate>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</social_scientist>
</colleague>
</person>
</economist>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/13970008.xml">
Steven N. Durlauf</link>, and David A. Lane, of the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/511751.xml">
Santa Fe Institute</link></association>
</institute>
 define six features of complex systems that have presented significant trouble for traditional mathematics.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Dispersed Interaction</b> — What happens in the economy is determined by the interaction of many dispersed, possibly heterogeneous, agents acting in parallel. The action of any given agent depends upon the anticipated actions of a limited number of other agents and on the aggregate state these agents co-create.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>No Global Controller</b> — No global entity controls interactions. Instead, controls are provided by mechanisms of competition and coordination between agents. Economic actions are mediated by legal institutions, assigned roles, and shifting associations. Nor is there a universal competitor—a single agent that can exploit all opportunities in the economy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Cross-cutting Hierarchical Organization</b> — The economy has many levels of organization and interaction. Units at any given level behaviors, actions, strategies, products typically serve as "building blocks" for constructing units at the next higher level. The overall organization is more than hierarchical, with many sorts of tangling interactions (associations, channels of communication) across levels.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Continual Adaptation</b> — Behaviors, actions, strategies, and products are revised continually as the individual agents accumulate experience—the system constantly adapts.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Perpetual Novelty Niches</b> — These are continually created by new markets, new technologies, new behaviors, new institutions. The very act of filling a niche may provide new niches. The result is ongoing, perpetual novelty.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 <b>Out-of-Equilibrium Dynamics</b> — Because new niches, new potentials, new possibilities, are continually created, the economy operates far from any optimum or global equilibrium. Improvements are always possible and indeed occur regularly.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Comparison with traditional economics</st>
<p>

The table below illustrates the differences between the complexity perspective and classical economics. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../463/6164463.xml">
Eric Beinhocker</link></writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 proposes five concepts that distinguish complexity economics from traditional economics. The first five categories are Beinhocker's synthesis, the last four are from W. Brian Arthur as reprinted in David Colander's <it>The Complexity Vision</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<row>

<header>
Complexity Economics</header>
<header>
Traditional Economics</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Dynamic</col>
<col>
Open, dynamic, non-linear systems, far from equilibrium</col>
<col>
Closed, static, linear systems in equilibrium</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Agents</col>
<col>
Modelled individually; use inductive rules of thumb to make decisions; have incomplete information; are subject to errors and biases; learn to adapt over time; heterogeneous agents</col>
<col>
Modelled collectively; use complex deductive calculations to make decisions; have complete information; make no errors and have no biases; have no need for learning or adaptation (are already perfect), mostly homogeneous agents</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Networks</col>
<col>
Explicitly model bi-lateral interactions between individual agents; networks of relationships change over time</col>
<col>
Assume agents only interact indirectly through market mechanisms (e.g. auctions)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Emergence</col>
<col>
No distinction between micro/macro economics; macro patterns are emergent result of micro level behaviours and interactions.</col>
<col>
Micro-and macroeconomics remain separate disciplines</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Evolution</col>
<col>
The evolutionary process of differentiation, selection and amplification provides the system with novelty and is responsible for its growth in order and complexity</col>
<col>
No mechanism for endogenously creating novelty, or growth in order and complexity</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Technology</col>
<col>
Technology fluid, endogenous to the system</col>
<col>
Technology as given or selected on economic basis</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Preferences</col>
<col>
Formulation of preferences becomes central; individuals not necessarily selfish</col>
<col>
Preferences given; Individuals selfish</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Origins from Physical Sciences</col>
<col>
Based on Biology (structure, pattern, self-organized, life cycle)</col>
<col>
Based on 19th-century physics (equilibrium, stability, deterministic dynamics)</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
Elements</col>
<col>
Patterns and Possibilities</col>
<col>
Price and Quantity</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/1420447.xml">
Computational economics</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Beinhocker, Eric D. The Origin of Wealth: Evolution, Complexity, and the Radical Remaking of Economics. Boston, Massachusetts: Harvard Business School Press, 2006.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mckinsey.com/ideas/books/originofwealth/index.asp">
http://www.mckinsey.com/ideas/books/originofwealth/index.asp</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite id="CITEREFArthurDurlaufLane1997" style="font-style:normal"><link>
Arthur</link>; <link>
Durlauf, Steven</link>&#32;&amp;&#32;Lane, David A&#32;(1997),&#32;<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.santafe.edu/~wbarthur/Papers/ADLIntro.html">
"Introduction: Process and Emergence in the Economy"</weblink>,&#32;<it>The Economy as an Evolving Complex System II</it>, Reading, Mass.: Addison-Wesley</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Colander, David. The Complexity Vision: The Teaching of Economics. ISBN 1840642521.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.santafe.edu/">
Santa Fe Institute</weblink> Birthplace of complexity science</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.santafe.edu/research/publications/workingpapers/97-10-080.pdf">
What Should Policymakers Know About Economic Complexity (PDF)</weblink> Summary of key ideas in complexity economics</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
