<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:20:44[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Stock market prediction</title>
<id>8598331</id>
<revision>
<id>243239230</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T19:16:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CliffC</username>
<id>2208024</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Finance</category>
<category>Stock market</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Stock market prediction</b> is the act of trying to determine the future value of a company <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/19372783.xml">
stock</link> or other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/177773.xml">
financial instrument</link> traded on a <link>
financial exchange</link>. The successful prediction of a stock's future price could yield significant profit. Some believe that stock price movements are governed by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/2009882.xml">
random walk hypothesis</link> and thus are unpredictable. Others disagree and those with this viewpoint possess a myriad of methods and technologies which purportedly allow them to gain future price information.
<sec>
<st>
The random walk hypothesis</st>

<p>

When applied to a particular financial instrument, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/2009882.xml">
random walk hypothesis</link> states that the price of this instrument is governed by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/235451.xml">
random walk</link> and hence is unpredictable. If the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/2009882.xml">
random walk hypothesis</link> is false then there will exist some (potentially <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/146103.xml">
non-linear</link>) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/157057.xml">
correlation</link> between the instrument price and some other indicator(s) such as <link>
trading volume</link> or the previous day's instrument closing price. If this correlation can be determined then a potential profit can be made.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Prediction methods</st>

<p>

Prediction methodologies fall into three broad categories which can (and often do) overlap. They are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/11684.xml">
fundamental analysis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/112577.xml">
technical analysis</link> (charting) and technological methods. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Fundamental analysis</st>

<p>

Fundamental Analysts are concerned with the company that underlies the stock itself. They evaluate a company's past performance as well as the credibility of its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/2052683.xml">
accounts</link>. Many performance ratios are created that aid the fundamental analyst with assessing the validity of a stock, such as the <magnitude_relation wordnetid="113815152" confidence="0.8">
<ratio wordnetid="113819207" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../066/163066.xml">
P/E ratio</link></ratio>
</magnitude_relation>
. <celebrity wordnetid="109903153" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/211518.xml">
Warren Buffett</link></person>
</celebrity>
 is perhaps the most famous of all Fundamental Analysts.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Technical analysis</st>

<p>

Technical analysts or chartists are not concerned with any of the company's fundamentals. They seek to determine the future price of a stock based solely on the (potential) trends of the past price (a form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/406624.xml">
time series analysis</link>). Numerous patterns are employed such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/2649146.xml">
head and shoulders</link> or <link>
cup and saucer</link>. Alongside the patterns, statistical techniques are utilised such as the <link>
exponential moving average</link> (EMA).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Technological methods</st>

<p>

With the advent of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
digital computer</link>, stock market prediction has since moved into the technological realm. The most prominent technique involves the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
artificial neural networks</link> (ANNs). ANNs can be thought of as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/185427.xml">
mathematical function</link> approximators. Their value in stock market prediction is that if a (potentially non-linear) relationship exists then it is possible that it could be found with enough indicators, the correct network structure and a large enough dataset.</p>
<p>

The most common form of ANN in use for stock market prediction is the <link>
feed forward network</link> utilising the <link>
backward propagation of errors</link> algorithm to update the network weights. These networks are commonly referred to as <it><link>
back propagation networks</link></it>. Since NNs require training and have a large parameter space, it is useful to modify the network structure for optimal predictive ability. Recently this has involved pairing NNs with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
genetic algorithm</link>s, a method of finding optima in multi-dimension parameter spaces utilising the biological concepts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/9236.xml">
evolution</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/21147.xml">
natural selection</link>.
Moreover, some researchers have tried to extract meaningful indicators from the news flash and discussion rooms about a certain stock using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/42253.xml">
Data Mining</link> techniques. But the people can have different opinion about the same stock at the same time.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Validity</st>

<p>

There have been numerous academic studies on the validity of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/11684.xml">
fundamental analysis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/112577.xml">
technical analysis</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
Artificial Neural Network</link>s as stock market prediction methods. Some studies report success in all camps, on particular markets and with particular datasets. Others dispute the ability to even predict the stock market at all and adhere to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/2009882.xml">
random walk hypothesis</link>. In fact the theory of pricing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/9135.xml">
financial derivatives</link> relies on the random walk hypothesis (stock prices are usually modelled as random walks in derivative pricing models).</p>



</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Graham, B. <it>The Intelligent Investor</it> HarperCollins; Rev Ed edition, 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lo, A.W. and Mackinlay, A.C. <it>A Non-Random Walk Down Wall Street</it> 5th Ed. Princeton University Press, 2002.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Azoff, E.M. <it>Neural Network Time Series Forecasting of Financial Markets</it> John Wiley and Sons Ltd, 1994.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

StockMarketPrediction Blog at blogger</entry>
</list>


</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
