<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:28:22[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<intellectual  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109621545">
<alumnus  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109786338">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<scientist  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110560637">
<scholar  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110557854">
<header>
<title>T. V. S. R. Appa Rao</title>
<id>8603858</id>
<revision>
<id>217868225</id>
<timestamp>2008-06-08T01:57:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Cornell University alumni</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Year of birth missing (living people)</category>
<category>Indian scientists</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from June 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This biographical article or section is written .</b>
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=T._V._S._R._Appa_Rao&amp;action=edit">
help improve it</weblink> by revising it to be  and . <it>(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Dr.T.V.S.R._Appa_Rao.jpg" type="frame">
</image>

<b>T.V.S.R. Appa Rao</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/26997.xml">
scientist</link> from <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/14533.xml">
India</link></country>
. He is an Emeritus Scientist with over 40 years of experience in Research &amp; Development in the areas of structural analysis design, testing, and failure investigations including those due to natural hazards.  </p>
<p>

Appa Rao obtained his <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/188874.xml">
Bachelor's degree</link> with Honours in Civil Engineering from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/2519092.xml">
Andhra University</link></university>
 in 1962 and was a Gold Medalist of the university. He received his <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
Masters degree</link> in Structural Engineering from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/194710.xml">
University of Hawaii</link></university>
 and his <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/8775.xml">
Ph.D.</link></property>
</degree>
 degree from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/7954422.xml">
Cornell University</link></university>
 (<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
) in 1968. After a brief period of experience as a consultant in USA., he joined the Structural Engineering Research Centre(SERC), India, in 1969, and became its Director in 1995. He continued his research studies at SERC,as an Emeritus Scientist after his retirement in 2001.</p>
<p>

Appa Rao has made a number of research contributions in the areas of Computer-Aided Analysis and Design of Structures, development of Finite Element Methods,Stability of Steel Structures, Risk and Reliability Analysis of Structures, Damage Assessment and Vulnerability Analysis of Structures in Cyclone-prone areas. He has also research interests in Earthquake-resistant Design of Structures and Development of High Performance Concretes.</p>
<p>

Appa Rao has more than 125 research publications to his credit. He was awarded the Aerospace Engineering Division Gold medal by the Institution of Engineers(India) in December 1995 for the paper on 'Analysis for ship-water interaction effects. He received Vocational Excellence Award 1998 from Rotary Club of Madras Metro. He is the leaser of the teams which won the Engineering technology Prize (1999) and Engineering Technology Shield(2000) of CSIR. He was awarded the Indian Building Congress Medal in 2003 for his paper on Integration of Computer and IT applications.</p>
<p>

Appa Rao was a Visiting Associate professor at Cornell University, USA, during 1976-'77. He was on the Editorial Board of the international journal 'Engineering of Structures'. He was a Visiting Scholar at Standford University, USA. He visited USA, Germany, Canada, Bulgaria, Japan, DPR Korea, Malaysia and Thailand. Served as a member in several national committees of R&amp;D and served as a guide/examiner for Doctoral Research work at leading academic institutions.</p>
<p>

Appa Rao is a fellow of the Indian National Academy of Engineering and a Fellow of Institution of Engineers (India) and a member of a number of professional bodies.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Areas of Interest/experience </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Structural Engineering</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Research</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Education,Teaching</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Structural Analysis : Computer- aided, Finite Element Methods, experimental</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Design :    Computer Visualization, Computer software development</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Computer Applications</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Construction</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Information Technology applications</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Disaster Mitigation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Management</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Artificial Intelligence applications</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Science &amp; Technology development</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Human Development&amp;Spirituality</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Main Areas of Research Experience </st>
<p>

Finite element analysis of structures - linear, nonlinear and stability analysis : and strength/damage assessment of existing structures
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Computer-aided analysis and design of structures</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Development of computer software including Expert Systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Experimental Stress Analysis</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Information Technology Applications for Computer Integrated Design and Construction</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Academic  Honours and Awards </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gold Medalist for standing first in B.E. Degree Examination, Andhra  University</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Awarded East-West Center Fellowship for post-graduate studies at University of Hawaii, USA</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Post-Doctoral Research Fellow at Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y., USA (1967-68)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Visiting Associate Professor at Cornell University, USA  (1976-77)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Visiting Scholar at Stanford University, USA (Sept.1989)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Awarded the Aerospace Engineering Division Gold Medal by the Institution of Engineers (India) in December 1995 for the paper on "Analysis for ship-water interaction effects"</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Received Vocational Excellence Award 1998 from Rotary Club of Madras Metro</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Received ‘1999 CSIR Prize for Engineering Technology’ for contributions in the field of  computational technology and software development</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Received  CSIR Shield for ‘Engineering Technology’ for the Year 2000 in the area ofStructural Engineering</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Awarded  the  Indian Building Congress Medal  for the paper presented in Nov. 2003</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 List of Publications </st>
<p>

125 Research papers published in national and international journals and/or presented in national and international conferences.</p>
<p>

The list of the R&amp;D publications is given below:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Errera, S.J., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Beams and columns braced by thin-walled steel diaphragms', 8th Congress of the IABSE, held at New York, Sept. 1968</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Errera, S.J., and Fisher, G.P., 'Columns braced by girts and a diaphragm', ST5, ASCE, May 1969</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'An assumed stress hybrid finite element model for the analysis of axisymmetric thick-walled pressure vessel', presented at the First International Conference on Structural Mechanics in Reactor Technology, Berlin, West Germany, Sept. 1971</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Narayanan, R., Paul Joseph, G., and Ramachandran, V., 'The role of structural models in the design of prestressed concrete containments with particular reference to the Madras Atomic Power Project', presented at the Symposium on Nuclear Science and Engineering, held at Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Bombay, March 1973</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Behaviour of concrete nuclear containment structures up to ultimate failure with special reference to MAPP-1 containment', presented as an invited theme paper at the symposium on Structural Mechanics, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Bombay, March 1975</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Ramaswamy, G.S., Rajaraman, A., Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., and Khadakkar, A.G., 'Minimum weight design of parabolic dish antenna', presented at the Second International Conference on Space Structures, Surrey, England, Sept. 1975</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Errera, S.J. and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Design of I-shaped beams with diaphragm bracing', ST4, Journal of Structural Division, ASCE, April 1976</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Ramaswamy, G.S., Reddy, D.V., Chitale, S.L., Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., George, Z., Srinivasan, R.S., and Bobby, W., 'Design of hyperbolic paraboloid shell roof for a large auditorium', World Congress on Space Enclosures, Montreal, Canada, July 1976</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Errera,S.J. and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Design of I-shaped columns with diaphragm bracing', ST9, Journal of Structural Division, ASCE, September 1976</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Narayanan, R., Paul Joseph, G., and Khuddus, M.A., 'Structural model study of MAPP-1 containment', Proceedings of the Second Annual Engineering Mechanics Division Speciality Conference, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, North Carolina, USA, pp. 109-111, May 1977</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Rajagopalan, K., Selvaraj, S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'The torsional stiffness of a cylindrical tube with a reinforced cutout', presented at the International Conference on Computer Applications in Civil Engineering, held at University of Roorkee, India, Oc. 23-25, 1979</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Loganathan, K., and Gallagher, R.H., 'A discrete stiffener element for doubly-curved shells', presented at the International Conference on Computer-Applications in Civil Engineering, held at University of Roorkee, India, Oct. 23-25, 1979</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Khadakkar, A.G., Nagesh R. Iyer, and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Determination of the torsional stiffness of an azimuth tube with a stiffened opening by holographic inter-ferometry', Optics and Lasers in Engineering, pp.147-159, 1, 1980</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Jayarama Rao, G., Khadakkar, A.G., Narayanan, R., Ravi Sankar, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'An optical system to increase the sensitivity of moiré analysis of strains', Tenth Symposium on Optics, Indian Institute of Technology, Madras, India, Jan. 1982</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Jayarama Rao, G., Khadakkar, A.G., Narayanan, R., Ravi Sankar, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'An optical system to increase the sensitivity of moiré to analyse strains', Journal of Optics, Vol.11, No.3, July-Sept. 1982</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Khadakkar, A.G., Rao, G.J., Narayanan, T., Sambandam, T., Iyer, N.R., 'Assessment of structural behaviour of MAPP-1 containment from pressure test', Trans. 7th Intl. Conf. On Structural Mechanics in Reactor Technology, Chicago, Illinois, USA, 22-26 August 1983, pp. 125-130</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Khadakkar, A.G., Ravi Sankar, K., and Nagesh R. Iyer, 'Stiffened rectangular cantilever shell subjected to a corner load', Proc. Of Second International Conference on Computational Mechods and Experimental Measurements, On board Liner Queen Elizabeth-2’, June-July 1984</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gautam Sarabhai, Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Loganathan, K., Muralidharan, K., Sharma, P.C., Ramaswamy, G.S., 'Design and construction features of composite ferrocement shell roofs of optimum shape for the vocational workshop of the B.M. Institute, Ahmedabad, presented at the Second International Symposium on Ferrocement, Bangkok, Jan. 1985</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Loganathan, K., and Nagesh R. Iyer, 'Computer-aided analysis and design of ship structures', paper  presented at the Workshop on Engineering Software – Applications and Research (ENGSAR), Indian Institute of Technology, Kanpur, India, Jan. 1985</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Khadakkar, A.G., Ravi Sankar, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Three-dimensional photoelastic investigation of jaws of bridge superstructure', Jl. of Structural Engineering, Madras, Vol. 11, No. 4, Jan. 1985, pp 105-113</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Nagesh R. Iyer, Satish Chandra, and Pandian, N., 'Instability analysis of stiffened hyperboloidal shells', paper presented at the Second International Conference on Computer Aided Analysis and Design in Civil Engineering, University of Roorkee, India, Jan. – Feb. 1985</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Ravisankar, K., Narayanan, R., Jayarama Rao, G., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Residual Stresses in Indian Standard Rolled Steel I-Sections', Jl. of Structural Engg., India, Vol.12, No.1, April 1985, pp.21-27</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Pandian, N., Satish Chandra, and Nagesh R. Iyer, 'Performance of straight and curved finite elements for analysis of curved beams and arches' – Paper presented at the International Conference on Finite Elements on Computational Mechanics (FEICOM) held at the Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay, Dec. 1985</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Loganathan, K., and Nagesh R. Iyer, 'Computer-Aided analysis of ship hull structures' – Proc. Marine Symposium, Madras, Jan. 1986</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., and Venkateswarlu, B., 'Wind effects on industrial structures', Proc. Indo-US Workshop on Wind Disaster Mitigation, Madras, 17-21, Dec. 1985</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Structural behaviour of a prestressed conmcrete containment: Assessment from model and proof tests', paper presented at the Workshop on 'Structures for Nuclear Power Reactor Technology', held at IIT, Madras, during 25-28 February 1987</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Spatial stability of curved beams', in Journal of Structural Engineering (India), Vol. 14, No.4, Jan. 1988, pp. 121-127</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandian, N., Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., and Satish Chandra, 'Studies on performance of curved beam finite elements for analysis of thin arches', Computers &amp; Structures, Vol.31, No.6, 1989, pp. 997-1002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Suri Krishna Mohan and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R.a, 'Effect of column settlement on stress resultants in hyperboloid cooling towers', presented at Seminar on Finite Element Applications for Practical Problems and ASKA Users’ Conference, NAL, Bangalore, 28-29, Jan. 1988</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Stability of structures – Applications', Lecture notes in Engineering edited by J.N. Reddy, C.S. Krishnamurthy and K.N. Seetharamu, Springer-Verlag, July 1988, pp 491-524</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Khadakkar, A.G., Narayanan, R., Ravi Shankar, K. Iyer, N.R., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Free Vibrations of a Cylindrical Shell by holographics Interferometry', Journal of Sound &amp; Vibration (1988), 121(1), pp. 169,180</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer, Zachariah, K.Z., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Studies on free vibration of hyperboloic cooling tower shells', paper presented at International Symosium on 'Innovative Applications of Shells and Spatial Forms' held at Bangalore during 21-25, Nov. 1988</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Studies on stress concentrations at shell-column junctions of hyperboloid cooling towers, Computers &amp; Structures, Vol.34, No.2, 1990, pp 191-202</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Zachariah, K.Z., Nagesh R. Iyer, and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Modelling of ship hull structures for finite element analysis', paper presented at the International Conference on Engineering Software-89, IIT, Delhi, Dec. 1989</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Krishna Mohan Rao, S.V., Gopalakrishnan, S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Effect of tension stiffening on the nonlinear post-cracking behaviour of hyperboloid cooling towers', paper presented at the International Conference on Engineering Software-89, IIT, New Delhi, Dec. 1989</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Krishna Mohan Rao, S.V., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Inelastic analysis of windloaded cooling towers', paper presented at the National Seminar on Cooling Towers, NTPC, New Delhi, Jan. 1990</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandian N., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Instability analysis of natural draught cooling towers', paper presented at the National Seminar on Cooling Towers, NTPC, New Delhi, Jan. 1990</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer, Rajasankar, J., Zachariah, K.Z., Palani, G.S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Procedures for dynamic response analysis of ship hull structures subjected to propeller-induced excitations – A critical review', Proceedings of the National Seminar on ‘Marine Technology Perspective – 2000 A.D.’, Marine Engineers Division, Institution of Engineers (India), New Delhi, Feb. 1990</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Analysis and design of natural draught hyperboloid cooling towers – An assessment of the status and future trends', paper presented at the International Conference on Advances in Structural Testing, Analysis and Design, IISc, Bangalore, July-Aug. 1990</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandian, N., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Studies on effect of imperfection on stress resultants in hyperboloid cooling towers', Journal of Structural Engineering, Vol.16, No.2, 43-48, 1989</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Design of Ship Hull structures – An Overview of the Development', Advances in Steel structures, Tata McGraw-Hill Pub. Co., New Delhi, 357-377, 1990</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer, Rajasankar, J., Zachariah, K.Z., Palani, G.S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Procedures for dynamic response analysis of ship hull structures subjected to propeller-induced excitations', Journal of the Institution of Engineers (India), Marine Engg. Division, Vol.72, 13-22, 1991</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandian, N., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'A knowledge based expert system for the preliminary design of natural draught cooling towers', Journal of Structural Engineering, Vol.18, No.4, January 1992, pp 141-148</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer, Rajasankar, J., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Studies on added mass evaluation of ship-water interaction', Proceedings of the National Seminar on Offshore Structures, Visakhapatnam, C31-C39, 1992</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Palani, G.S., Nagesh R. Iyer and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'An efficient finite element model for static and vibration analysis of eccentrically stiffened plates/shells', Computers &amp; Structures, Vol.43, No.4, 651-661, 1992</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'A review of error analysis and adaptive refinement methodologies in finite element applications, Part-I: Error Analysis', Journal of Structural Engineering, Vol.19, No.2, 77-94, 1992</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'A review of error analysis and adaptive refinement methodologies in finite element applications, Part-II: Adaptive Refinements', Journal of Structural Engineering, Vol.19, No.3, 1992</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer, Rajasankar, J., Palani, G.S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'An efficient algorith for vibration analysis of submerged/floating structures', Journal of Structural Engineering, Vol.19, No.3, 1992</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Palani, G.S., Nagesh R. Iyer, and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'An efficient finite element model for static and vibration analysis of plate/shells with arbitrarily located eccentric stiffeners', Journal of Sound and Vibration, 163(3), 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Rajashankar, J., Nagesh R. Iyer, and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'A new 3-D finite element model to evaluate added mass for analysis of fluid-structure interaction problems', International Journal for Numerical Methods in Engineering, 36, pp 997-1012 (1993)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Ramanjaneyulu, K., Gopalakrishnan, S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Collapse loads of reinforced concrete cylindrical water tanks using limit analysis approach', Journal of Computers and Structures, Vol.48, No.2, 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer, Rajasankar, J., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Analysis of ship-water interaction effects', Proceedings of the 8th National Convention of Aerospace Engineers, IIT, Kharagpur, March 5-6, 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Krishna Mohan Rao, S.V., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Investigation of ultimate strength of reinforced concrete shells employing nonlinear finite element analysis – Case Studies', Proc. Of Int. Symp. On Innovative World of Concrete, Bangalore, Aug.30-Sep.3, 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandian, N., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Developments in the constitutive modeling of the reinforced concrete and their impact on the design of natural draft cooling towers', Proc. of National Seminar on Energy Structures, Madras, Feb.27-28, 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Krishna Mohan Rao, S.V., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Nonlinear analysis of RC hyperboloid cooling towers Part I' Material Model, Finite Element Model and Validation; Part II: Parametric study and results', Int. Jl. of Computers and Structures, Vol.49, No.6. pp 913-930, 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji Rao, K., Thomas, K.C., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Stochastic modeling of cyclones', Third Asia-Pacific Symposium on Wind Engineering, Hong Kong, Dec. 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Muralidharan, T.L., Durgaprasad, J., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Damage assessment and vulnerability analysis of structures subjected to cyclones', Third Asia Pacific Symposium on Wind Engineering, Hong Kong, Dec. 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Durgaprasad, J., Muralidharan, T.L., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Development of knowledge-based expert systems in structural engineering', Int. Computing Congress, Hyderabad, Dec. 1993</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, Nagesh R. Iyer, G.S. Palani and J. Rajasankar, 'Finite  Element Models for Vibration Analysis of Ship Hull  Structures for Propeller-Induced Excitations,' Proceedings  of the 5th International Marine Design Conference &amp; Summer Meeting of the German  Society of Naval Architects, Delft University  of  Technology, The Netherlands, May 1994, pp 235-249</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Advances and trends in finite element modeling for computer-aided structural analysis', paper presented at the National Symposium on Structural Mechanics – 1994, IIT, Kharagpur, Dec.8-10, 1994</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Nagesh R. Iyer, Zachariah, K.Z., and Rajasankar, J., 'Finite element modeling of ship hulls using interactive graphics', paper presented at NASAS-94, held at IIT, Kharagpur, Dec.8-10, 1994</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Rajasankar, J., Nagesh R. Iyer, and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'A boundary element formulation for exterior fluid-structure interaction problems', paper accepted for presentation at NASAS-94, held at IIT, Kharagpur, Dec.8-10, 1994</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji Rao, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Reliability analysis of frames subjected to extreme winds', 9th Int. Conference on Wind Engineering, New Delhi, Jan. 1995</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Muralidharan, T.L., Durgaprasad, J., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'A knowledge-based expert system for damage assessment and vulnerability analysis of structures subjected to cyclones', 9th Int. Conference on Wind Engineering, New Delhi, Jan. 1995</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Palani, G.S. Nagesh R.Iyer, Appa Rao, T.V.S.R 'Instability Analysis of Hyperboloidal Shells using the 9-Noded Lagrangian Plate/Shell Element', Proceedings of the Intl. Conf. on Stability of Structures, Allied Publishers Ltd., pp. 605-616, 1995</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao,T.V.S.R ' Knowledge Based Expert System for Damage assessment and Vulnerability Analysis of Structures subject to cyclones Proc. of Workshop on  Engineering of Structures for Mitigating Damage Due to Cyclones, Vol.22, No.1, Jan. '95, pp 1-10</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji  Rao,K., and T.V.S.R.Appa Rao, 'Reliability Analysis of  Frames Subjected to extreme winds',  9th Int'l Conf. in Wind Engineering, New Delhi Jan. 1995  pp 1182- 1194</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Murlidharan,  T.L.,  Durgaprasad,J., Appa  Rao,  T.V.S.R.,  'Knowledge Based  Expert System for Damage assessment and Vulnerability  Analysis of Structures subject  to cyclones', 9th Int'l Conf. in Wind Engineering, New Delhi Jan. 1995 pp 2176-2188</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, TVSR, Muralidharan, T.L., Balaji Rao, K. and Durgaprasad, J., 'Knowledge-based expert system for damage assessment and vulnerability analysis of structures subjected to cyclones', Journal of Structural Engineering (India), Vol.22, No.1, April 1995, pp.1-10.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer, J.Rajasankar and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Analysis for Ship-Water Interaction Effects ',  Jl. Of Aerospace Engg. Div., The Instit. of Engineers (India), 75, May 1995, pp. 1-5</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Arul Jayachandran S., Vaidyanathan C.V., and Appa Rao T.V.S.R., 'Collapse predictions of thin plates under compression', International Conference on Stability of Structures, ICSS-95, Coimbatore, June 1995, pp 561 – 574</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji Rao, K., and Appa Rao, TVSR, 'Reliability of reinforced concrete beams against first crack inflexure', Journal of Structural Engineering (India) , Vol.22, No.3, Oct, ‘95, pp.145-152</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Ramanjaneyulu, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Non-linear Finite Element Analysis of Wind Loaded Natural Draught Cooling Tower Shells' First National Conference on Computer Aided Structural Analysis and Design (NC-CASAD), Hyderabad, January, 1996, pp 166-173</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Ramanjaneyulu, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Nonlinear Finite Element Analysis of Reinforced Concrete Shell Structures', International Seminar on Civil Engineering Practices in Twenty-first Century, Roorkee, Feb., 1996, pp 170-179</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Durgaprasad, J, Muralidharan, T.L., and Appa Rao T.V.S.R., 'Application of artificial Neural networks for damage assessment in structural Engineering' Journal of StructuralEngineering (India), V.23, No.1, April 1996, pp 9-14</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Ramanjaneyulu, K., Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Studies on Inelastic Behaviour of Perfect and Imperfect Cooling Tower Shells', 4th International Symposium on Natural Draught Cooling Towers, held at Kaiserslautern, Germany, May 29-31, 1996, pp 173-181 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Ramanjaneyulu, K., Gopalakrishnan, S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Finite Element Analysis of a  Cooling Tower Shell with Openings for Flue-gas Ducts', 4th International Symposium on Natural Draught Cooling Towers, held at Kaiserslautern, Germany, May 29-31, 1996, pp 345-353</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Nonlinear Analysis of  Reinforced Concrete Shell Structures - Trends and Application in Design', National Seminar on Materials and Structures, Bangalore, 26th July 1996, I.1 - I.10</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji Rao, K and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Risk Analysis for Cyclone-Prone Regions and Industrial Structures', Proceedings of Asia-Pacific Symposium on Structural Reliability and its Applications, held at Tokyo, Japan, (during 12-14 November 1995), Proc. published 31st July 1996, pp. 204-211</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Ramanjaneyulu, K., Manjuprasad, M., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Design considerations and codal provisions for natural draught cooling towers', Proceedings of the national seminar on 'Industrial Structures', Madras, 23-24, December,  1996, pp. I.33-46</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Murlidharan, T. L., Durgaprasad, J., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Knowledge-based Expert System for Damage Assessment and Vulnerability Analysis of Structures Subjected to Cyclones', Journal of Wind Engineering and Industrial Aerodynamics, vol. 72, 1997, pp. 479-491</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Ramanjaneyulu, K., Manjuprasad, M., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Role of nonlinear finite element analysis in the design and assessment of strength of natural draught cooling tower shells', Proceedings of Structural Engineering Convention 1997, Madras, February 12-14, 1997, pp. 479-488</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Rajasankar J, Nagesh R Iyer, Appa Rao T V S R, 'Knowledge based design of offshore deck grillages', Proc., Structural Engineering Convention 1997, IIT, Madras, Feb 12-14,1997, pp.97-107. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Ramanjaneyulu, K., Gopalakrishnan, S., Manjuprasad, M., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Investigations on structural behaviour of cooling tower shells with openings for flue gas ducts', Proceedings of Structural Engineering Convention 1997, Madras, February 12-14, 1997, pp. 489-499</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R Iyer, Palani G S, Appa Rao T V S R, 'Modelling of steel plated local grillages for dynamic analysis', Proc. Conference on Ship and Ocean Technology, IIT Kharagpur, Mar 4-6, 1997, pp.131-137</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Manjuprasad, M., Gopalakrishnan, S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Nonlinear Dynamic Analysis of RC Cooling Tower Shell Subjected to Wind Load Using Layered Shell Elements', Proceedings of the National Seminar on Wind Effects on Structures, Ghaziabad, April 3-4, 1997, pp. 263-275</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nagesh R. Iyer, J. Rajasankar, G.S. Palani and T.V.S.R. Appa Rao 'An Efficient Procedure for Computation of Wet Modal Characteristics', Proceedings of the 7th NASAS on Recent Advances in Structural Dynamics and Aeroelasticity (Eds. S.A. Hussainy, B.K. Parida, V. Shankar and C.G. Shah), NAL, Bangalore, August 1997, Allied Publishers Ltd., pp. III-146 to III-153</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Durgaprasad, J., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R. 'Parameter Interdependencies for Development of a KBS for Risk Analysis', Journal of Computing in Civil Engineering, ASCE, vol. II, No. 4, Oct. 1997, pp. 224-230</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Thomas K.C, Balaji Rao, K and Appa Rao T.V.S.R, ' Reliability Analysis of Steel Roof Trusses subject to Wind Loads', Journal of the Institution of Engineers (India), Vol.78, Feb-98, pp.180-187</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Natural Disaster Mitigation – Roles of R&amp;D Industitutions and the Media', Seminar on Natural Disaster Prevention and the Media, Anna Institute of Management, Chennai, 14th Oct. 1998, pp 88-94</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji Rao, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Probabilistic analysis of design wind loads and reliability based design of structural components', Journal of Structural Engineering, SERC, Vol. 25, No.1, April 1998, pp 65-74</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Some recent advances in computational methods for structural analysis',  Key-note paper presented at the International Conference on Structural Engineering, Institution of Engineers (India), Sept. 25-27, 1999</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji Rao, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Cracking in reinforced concrete flexural members – A reliability model', Structural Engineering and Mechanics, An International Journal, Vol.7, No.3, March 1999, pp 303-318</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Manjuprasad, M., Gopalakrishnan, S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Nonlinear finite element analysis of RC shell structures subjected to dynamic loads using layered shell elements', Proc. International Conference on ‘Innovative World of Concrete-98’, held at Calcutta during 16-19, Nov, 1998, pp 7.47 – 7.54</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Muralidharan, T.L., Rao, K.B., Durgaprasad, J., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Handling uncertainties in knowledge-based modelling and acquisition for the development of a knowledge-based system', Computer-Aided Civil and Infrastructure Engineering (USA), Mar 1999, pp 141-154</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji Rao, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'A methodology for condition assessment of RC bridge girders with limited inspection data', The Bridge &amp; Structural Engineer, Ing-IABSE, Vol.29, No.4, December 1999, pp 13-26</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Lakshmanan, N., Shanmugasundaram, S., and Appa Rao, TVSR, 'Studies on structural response of chimneys and industrial structures using boundary layer wind tunnel', Specialist Conference on Industrialised Building Systems &amp; Structural Engineering, , WEC-99,  Kuala Lumpur,  Malaysia, July 1999</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Strategies for engineering of buildings and structures for cyclone disaster mitigation', TCDC Workshop on Natural Disaster Reduction – Policy Issues and Strategies, Dec.21-22, 1999, SERC, Madras</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., Nagesh R. Iyer, Rajasankar, J., and Palani, G.S., 'Dynamic response analysis of ship hull structures', Marine Technology, Vol.37, No.3, Summer 2000, pp 117-128</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Balaji Rao, K., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Probabilistic analysis of strength of steel imperfect columns', Journal of Structural Engineering, Vol.27, No.1, April 2000, pp 41-48</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Rajasankar, J., Nagesh R. Iyer, and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'A procedure to assemble only non-zero coefficients of global matrix in finite element analysis' – Technical Note – Computers and Structures, 77 (2000), 595-599</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Manjuprasad, M., Gopalakrishnan, S., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Non-linear dynamic response of a reinforced concrete secondary containment shell subjected to seismic load', Journal of Engineering Structures, 23(2001), 397-406</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Gopalakrishnan, S., Ramanjaneyulu, K., Manjuprasad, M., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Nonlinear behaviour of RC shell structures subjected to dynamic loads', Proceedings of the National Symposium on Advances in Structural Dynamics and Design, Jan. 9-11, 2001</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Arunachalalam, S., Govindaraju, S.P., Lakshmanan, N., and Appa Rao, T.V.S.R., 'Across-wind aerodynamic parameters of tall chimneys with circular cross-section – an empirical model', Engineering Structures, 23 (2001), 502-520</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Advances Towards Integration of Computer Applications and IT for Design and Construction of Structures - An Overview', Keynote Address, Proc. of SEC-2001, Recent Developments in Structural Engineering, IIT, Roorkee, October 2001</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Trends in Computer Applications and Use of Information Technology for Design, Construction and Maintenance of Infrastructural Facilities', Journal of Indian Buildings Congress, Vol.9, No.1, June, 2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Efficient Use of Computer for Design and Construction of Structures - An Overview of Problems &amp; Issues', Proceedings of the National Seminar on Recent Challenges in Civil Engineering (RCCE-2002), organized by Association of Consulting Civil Engineers (India), Hyderabad, June 22, 2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao, Review of the Book on 'Guidelines for the Use of Computers for Engineering Calculations', Published by the Institution of Structural Engineers, 11 Upper Belgrade Street, London SWIX, 8BH, 2002, pp 47, The Indian Concrete Journal, August 2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao &amp; V.Laxmi Narasaiah,  'Use of Computers and Information Technology by the Construction Industry in India - Assessment of Present Status and Needs', Project EMR-0141,Report No.01-03, SERC, Chennai, February 2003</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao &amp; V.Laxmi Narasaiah,  'Developments in Computer and Information Technology Applications towards Computer Integrated Construction (CIC)', Project EMR-0141, Report No.02-03, SERC, Chennai, June 2003</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Advances in the Use of Computers and IT for Design and Construction of RC Structures', Proceedings of the National Seminar on Innovative Technologies in Construction of Concrete Structures,  organized by Kavikulguru Institute of Technology &amp; Science, Ramtek, February 2003</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Modelling Issues for Finite Element Analysis' Proceedings of the Workshop: Finite Element Analysis and Design of Structures (FEADS), Dec. 2003,  SERC, Chennai. pp. 1-17.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao, and V.L.Narassaiah, 'Methods and Techniques for Integrating  Computer and Information Technology Applications Towards Computer integrated  Construction' Journal of Indian Building Congress, Volume X , No. 3, 2003, pp1-10.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao and V.Laxmi Narasaiah, 'Use of Computers and Information Technology by Construction Industry in India –An Assessment by Survey and Directions for Improvement', Communications, NICMAR Journal of Construction  Management, Volume XIX, April – June 2004 Number II, pp. 55-57.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  R.K.Arun, and T.V.S.R. Appa Rao, 'Methodology for Integrating Computer Aided  Design With Construction Scheduling', Journal of Structural of  Engineering, Vol.31, No.4,January.- March, 2005 , pp.281-288.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Development of Information Systems and Networking for Disaster Management - An Overview', Proceedings of the World Congress on Natural Disaster  Mitigation, New Delhi, Feb. 2004.pp. 325-336</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  M.B.Anoop, K.Balaji Rao, T.V.S.R.Apparao, and S.Gopalakrishnan, 'International  Standards for Durability of RC Structures: Part-I - A Critical Review', The Indian Concrete Journal, Vol.75, No.9, September 2001</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  M.B.Anoop, K.Balaji Rao, T.V.S.R.Apparao, and S.Gopalakrishnan, 'International Standards for Durability of RC Structures: Part- II –  Recommendations for IS 456: 2000', The Indian Concrete Journal, Vol.75, No.11,  November 2001</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Some Important Considerations and Application of Experimental Investigations for Design and Condition Assessment of Structural Components and  Systems', Invited Plenary Lecture Presented at the XI NASAS Conference, organized by NAL, Bangalore, 8-9 February 2002</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  B.Geetha, Nagesh R.Iyer and T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Multigrid Solver in Adaptive Finite Element Solution', Journal of Structural Engineering, Vol.No.29, No.4, January- March 2003, pp 239-243</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  M.B.Anoop, K.Balaji Rao, T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'A Methodology for Durability- Based Service Life Design of Reinforced Concrete Flexural Members', Magazine of  Concrete Research, Vol.55, No.3, June 2003, pp 289-303</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  K.Ramanjaneyulu, S.Gopalakrishnan and T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Seismic Response Analysis of Column supported Natural Draught Cooling Tower Shells', Proc. of The National Seminar on Design of Nuclear Power Plants, Feb. 2003,SERC, Chennai, pp 461-473</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  S..Gopalakrishnan, M.Manjuprasad and T.V.S.R.Apparao, 'Non-linear Finite Element Analysis of RC Secondary Containment Shell Subjected to Seismic Excitation', Proceedings of the National Seminar on Design of Nuclear Power Plants, Feb. 2003, SERC, Chennai, pp 41-52</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

  K.Balaji Rao &amp; T.V.S.R.Appa Rao, 'Stochastic modeling of crack width in reinforced concrete beams subjected to fatigue loading', Engineering Structures 26 (2004), pp 659-667</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 K.Balaji Rao, M.B.Anoop, N.Lakshmanan, S.Gopalakrishnan and T.V.S.R.Appa Rao, ‘Risk-based remaining life assessment of corrosion affected reinforced Concrete structural members', Journal of Structural Engineering, Vol.31, No.1,  April-June 2004, pp 51-64</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
