<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:30:50[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<symbol  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106806469">
<award  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106696483">
<signal  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106791372">
<header>
<title>Military decorations of Mexico</title>
<id>8678011</id>
<revision>
<id>196456325</id>
<timestamp>2008-03-07T03:37:10Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>DH85868993</username>
<id>2824367</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Military awards and decorations of Mexico</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="float:right; margin: 0 0 1em 1em; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaaaaa solid; border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 95%;" cellpadding="4" class="toc" border="1" cellspacing="0">
<caption>
<b><force wordnetid="108208016" confidence="0.8">
<military wordnetid="108199025" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/19229.xml">
Military of Mexico</link></military>
</force>
</b></caption>
<row>
<col colspan="2" align="center">
<table style="background:#f9f9f9; text-align:left;" cellpadding="2" border="0" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="125px" src="Seal_of_the_Government_of_Mexico.svg">
<caption>

centre
</caption>
</image>
</col>

</row>
<row>
<header style="background:#798050; font-size: 95%; border-top: 1px solid #aaaaaa; border-bottom: 1px solid #EEDD82; padding: 0 5px 0 5px;">
<b>Components</b></header>
</row>
<row>
<col style="background=#FFFFFF">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../920/1326920.xml">
Mexican Air Force</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
  <army wordnetid="108191230" confidence="0.8">
<force wordnetid="108208016" confidence="0.8">
<military_service wordnetid="108198137" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../082/2948082.xml">
Mexican Army</link></military_service>
</force>
</army>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
  <navy wordnetid="108191701" confidence="0.8">
<force wordnetid="108208016" confidence="0.8">
<military_service wordnetid="108198137" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/1225277.xml">
Mexican Navy</link></military_service>
</force>
</navy>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<header style="background:#798050; font-size: 95%; border-top: 1px solid #aaaaaa; border-bottom: 1px solid #EEDD82; padding: 0 5px 0 5px;">
<b>Ranks</b></header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/2554754.xml">
Air Force ranks and insignia</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/2554754.xml">
Army ranks and insignia</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../759/3361759.xml">
Navy ranks and insignia</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<header style="background:#798050; font-size: 95%; border-top: 1px solid #aaaaaa; border-bottom: 1px solid #EEDD82; padding: 0 5px 0 5px;">
<b>History</b></header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/3303790.xml">
Military History of Mexico</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<header style="background:#798050; font-size: 95%; border-top: 1px solid #aaaaaa; border-bottom: 1px solid #EEDD82; padding: 0 5px 0 5px;">
<b>Awards</b></header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<award wordnetid="106696483" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/8678011.xml">
Military decorations of Mexico</link></signal>
</award>
</symbol>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>

This is a <b>list of military decorations</b> awarded by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/3966054.xml">
United Mexican States</link> (<it>Estados Unidos Mexicanos</it>).
<ss1>
<st>
Medal of Valor</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Valor Heroico</it> is awarded to military personnel for exceptional acts of heroism at risk of their own life; it may be awarded in both war and peace.</p>
<p>

Description: Gilt-edged red-enameled "Lancer Cross" (equilateral cross whose arms resemble lance heads) resting on a gilt "star" of multiple rays (resembles a square with points at the cardinal points). Oval red central medallion has <it>1</it>, <it>2</it>, or <it>3</it> according to class, surrounded by a white band inscribed, <it>Valor Heroico</it> in gold. Suspended from a red and white ribbon according to class, with a gilt bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st class - solid red ribbon</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd class - five equal stripes, three red and two white</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 3rd class - white ribbon with medium width red edges</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
War Cross</st>
<p>

The <it>Cruz de Guerra</it> is awarded to military personnel in time of war or armed conflict for actions that do not merit an award of the Medal of Valor.</p>
<p>

Description: Red enameled gilt Maltese cross with "stepped" concave terminations; very large central medallion bears gilt head of <link>
Cuauhtémoc</link> in war helmet on red background, surrounded by gilt band inscribed, <it>Cruz de Guerra</it> above and class of medal below. Suspended from a red ribbon with a gilt bar at the top inscribed <it>Mexico</it>. Comes in three classes. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Medal of Military Merit</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Mérito Militar</it> is presented to members of the Army and Air Force for acts of exceptional merit that greatly benefits the Mexican Armed Forces.</p>
<p>

Description: Takes the form of an 8-pointed gilt or silver star of multiple rays, resting on a blue-enameled <link>
cross pattée</link> with slightly concave ends; central medallion has the Mexican eagle on a blue background, surrounded by a red band inscribed, <it>Mérito Militar</it> above <it>1a</it> or <it>2a</it> and <it>Clase</it>. Suspended from a blue and red ribbon according to class, with a gilt or silver bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st class - gilt star, worn directly on breast without ribbon</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd class - gilt star, blue ribbon with medium-wide red center stripe</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 3rd class - silver star, blue ribbon with 2 medium-wide red center stripes</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Medal of Naval Merit</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Mérito Naval</it> is the Naval equivalent of the Medal of Military Merit, conferred for exceptionally meritorious acts which benefit the Mexican Navy.</p>
<p>

Description: Gilt or silver 8-pointed star of multiple rays, with an anchor in the center in opposing metal color surrounded by a wreath of laurel and oak; inside the wreath is a blue ring inscribed, <it>Mérito Naval</it> in gold. Suspended from a white ribbon with blue stripes according to class.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st class - gilt star with silver anchor and wreath, blue ribbon with medium-wide white center stripe</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd class - silver star with gilt anchor and wreath, blue ribbon with three equally spaced narrow white stripes</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Medal of Naval Aviation Merit</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Mérito Aeronautico Naval</it> is the equivalent to the Medal of Naval Merit, given for exceptionally meritorious acts that benefit Mexican Naval Aviation.</p>
<p>

Description: Consists of a gilt or silver 5-pointed star with a red central medallion bearing a silver anchor with a gilt propeller along its shaft. The band surrounding center reads, <it>Mérito Aeronautico</it>. Suspended by a small gilt or silver replica of the Mexican eagle from an olive green ribbon with white stripes according to class.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st class - gilt star, solid olive green ribbon</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd class - silver star, olive green ribbon with equal-width white center stripe</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Medal of Technical Merit</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Mérito Técnico</it> is presented to Army or Air Force personnel who invent or develop useful materials, methods, or reforms that contribute greatly to national defense or the benefit of the armed forces.</p>
<p>

Description: Gilt or silver 8-pointed star of multiple rays, bearing large red central medallion with a faceted gilt 5-pointed star, surrounded by a white band inscribed, <it>Mérito Técnico Militar</it>. Surrounding this band is a silver wreath of laurel and oak. Suspended by a small replica of the Mexican eagle from a green and white ribbon according to class, with a gilt or silver bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st Class - gilt medal; light green ribbon with medium-wide white edges</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd Class - silver medal; ribbon has five equal stripes, three white and two light green</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Medal of Naval Technical Merit</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Mérito Técnico Naval</it> is equivalent to the Medal of Technical Merit, awarded to Naval personnel for the development of materials, methods, or reforms that contribute to national defense or the professional expertise of the Navy.</p>
<p>

Description: Consists of a gold or silver cross with pointed terminations and slightly curved arms, resting on pointed rays. Blue central medallion bears a silver anchor, surrounded by a red band inscribed, <it>Mérito Técnico Naval</it> in black. Suspended by a small replica of the Mexican eagle from a blue and white ribbon according to class.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st class - gold cross, blue ribbon</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd class - silver cross, blue ribbon with equal-width white center stripe</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Medal for Academic Merit</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Mérito Facultativo</it> is bestowed on students who achieve exceptional marks during their studies at the Military Academies. First class medals are given to those who achieve first-tier grades during all their years of study, and second class medals to those who post first and second tier marks. There is also the Medal for Naval Academic Merit.</p>
<p>

Description: Round medal with raised rim, bearing figure of the statute of the <belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<signal wordnetid="106791372" confidence="0.8">
<apparition wordnetid="109547111" confidence="0.8">
<emotion wordnetid="107480068" confidence="0.8">
<love wordnetid="107543288" confidence="0.8">
<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<statement wordnetid="106722453" confidence="0.8">
<description wordnetid="106724763" confidence="0.8">
<feeling wordnetid="100026192" confidence="0.8">
<spirit wordnetid="109545324" confidence="0.8">
<devotion wordnetid="107544491" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<word_picture wordnetid="107201804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/66440.xml">
Virgin Mary of Guadalupe</link></word_picture>
</spiritual_being>
</devotion>
</spirit>
</feeling>
</description>
</statement>
</message>
</love>
</emotion>
</apparition>
</signal>
</state>
</symbol>
</belief>
, with the Higher Military Academy in the background. Suspended from a green and white ribbon according to class, with a gilt or silver bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st class - gilt medal, moss green ribbon with medium width white center stripe</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd class - silver medal, ribbon has five equal stripes, three moss green and two white</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Medal for Teaching Merit</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Mérito Docente</it> recognizes instructors at Higher Military Schools who discharge their duties in an exemplary manner for at least three years.</p>
<p>

Description: Gilt 8-pointed star of multiple rays, with blue central medallion bearing head of Aztec chieftain Cuauhtémoc behind the head of the goddess <deity wordnetid="109505418" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/1182.xml">
Athena</link></deity>
, enclosed within a white band inscribed, <it>Recompensa al Saber y Asidua Aplicacion</it>. A green wreath of laurel surrounds the white band. Suspended from a ribbon with three equal stripes of red-green-red, with a gilt bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Long Service Medal</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración a la Perseverancia</it> is granted to military personnel for faithful, uninterrupted periods of military service.</p>
<p>

Description: Basic form is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/961313.xml">
Maltese cross</link> with two or three inner raised rims, resting on one or two circular wreaths of laurel, with a large round gilt central medallion bearing the number of years service surrounded by a white band inscribed <it>Perseverancia</it> above and the class of medal below. Suspended by a small replica of the Mexican eagle or a 5-pointed star from a ribbon colored according to class, with a gilt bar at top inscribed <it>Mexico</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Por la Patria (50 years service) - yellow enameled gilt cross, two laurel wreaths, diagonal red-white-green ribbon with the Mexican eagle as suspender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Institutional (45 years service) - red enameled gilt cross, two laurel wreaths, diagonal red-white-green ribbon with the Mexican eagle as suspender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Extraordinaria (40 years service) - white enameled gilt cross, two laurel wreaths, red ribbon with medium-narrow green-white center stripe, Mexican eagle as suspender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Especial (35 years service) - white enameled gilt cross, gilt laurel wreath, diagonal yellow above gray ribbon divided by narrow green-white-red stripes, Mexican eagle as suspender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st Class (30 years service) - gilt cross with blue rims, laurel wreath, white ribbon with diagonal green-white-red center stripes, Mexican eagle as suspender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd Class (25 years service) - red enameled cross, laurel wreath, ribbon of three equal green-white-red stripes with the Mexican eagle as suspender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 3rd Class (20 years service) - green enameled cross, laurel wreath, ribbon with five equal green-white-red-white-green stripes, 5-pointed star as a suspender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 4th Class (15 years service) - white enameled cross, laurel wreath, white ribbon with medium width green (left) and red edges, 5-pointed star as suspender</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 5th Class (10 years service) - red enameled cross, silver laurel wreath, halved green (left) and red (right) ribbon with 5-pointed star as suspender</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Military Sports Medal</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración al Merito Deportivo Militar</it> is given to military personnel who distinguish themselves while representing Mexico in either individual or team sports competitions.</p>
<p>

Description: Rectangular yellow alloy medal with circular emblem in center representing various sports, with inscription <it>Merito</it> above and <it>Deportivo</it> below. Suspended by a Mexican eagle resting in the flames of a torch from an orange and white ribbon according to class, with a gilt bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st Class - orange ribbon with medium width white edges</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd Class - white ribbon with five equal width stripes, three white and two orange</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 3rd Class - white ribbon with seven equal width stripes, four white and three orange</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 4th Class - white ribbon with nine equal width stripes, five white and four orange</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Distinguished Service Medal</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración a Servicios Distinguidos</it> is presented to Army and Air Force personnel who demonstrate initiative and dedication throughout the course of their military career.</p>
<p>

Description: Round gilt medal with outer rim formed by a wreath of laurel enclosing inner beaded, raised rim; center bears 10-rayed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../198/53198.xml">
Aztec</link> style "sun wheel" with <social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<society wordnetid="107966140" confidence="0.8">
<ethnic_group wordnetid="107967382" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<culture wordnetid="108287844" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/45522.xml">
Toltec</link></culture>
</group>
</ethnic_group>
</society>
</social_group>
 pyramid inside, above inscription <it>Servicios Distinguidos</it>. Suspended by a small Mexican eagle from a ribbon of three equal light blue-white-light blue stripes with a gilt bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Pacific Service Medal</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración por Servicio en el Lejano Oriente</it> recognizes military personnel, primarily members of the <link>
Mexican Expeditionary Air Force</link>, who fought against the Japanese in the Pacific during 1944-45.</p>
<p>

Description: Round medal with silver rim inscribed <it>Servicio en el Lejano Oriente</it> enclosing yellow enamel ring surrounding gilt central medallion bearing Aztec "sun god" emitting rays with three 5-pointed stars below and to sides. Gilt FAEM pilot's wing with pointed, enameled shield is mounted just above the center medallion, partially obscuring the top of the medallion and with wings breaking the edge of the medal. Suspended from a unique ribbon, half green (left) and half red with triangular white field inset at top; gilt attachment bar at top reads <it>Mexico</it>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Legion of Honor</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Legion_de_honor.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Legion of honor
</caption>
</image>

The <it>Condecoración de la Legión de Honor Mexicano</it> is awarded to officers inducted into the Mexican Legion of Honor as a result of their efforts and achievements.</p>
<p>

Description: Red enameled gilt Maltese cross with single blue inward pointing arrowhead inserted between the points of the terminations, with single sharp ray between each arm; the whole rests on a light blue oval with serrated edges. Hollow central oval bears gilt figure of warrior king Cuauhtémoc in feathered headdress surrounded by red band inscribed, <it>Legión de Honor</it> above a half-wreath of laurel. Suspended by a small gilt Mexican eagle from a light blue ribbon with medium-width yellow edges, with a gilt bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Retirees Medal</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración de Retiro</it> is presented to officers who retire after more than 45 years active service.</p>
<p>

Description: Vaguely cross shaped medal, each arm formed by three pointed rays (center ray longer than other two) with single, wide faceted ray between the arms (looks like pointed cross resting on an octagon). Central oval portrays hand above volcano within half-wreath of laurel, all on field of inscribed rays. Suspended from a sky-blue ribbon with equal width golden-yellow center stripe, with a gilt bar at top inscribed, <it>Mexico</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Banda - badge on sash for General Officers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Collar - badge on neck ribbon for Senior Officers</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Medalla - badge on chest ribbon for Officers</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Anti-Narcotics Campaign Medal of Merit</st>
<p>

The <it>Condecoración por Mérito en Campaña contra el Narcotráfico</it> recognizes military personnel and civilians for active participation in countering narcotics traffic.</p>
<p>

Description: Red-enameled gilt cross pattee with slightly widened terminations, with an 8-pointed star of multiple blunt rays in the center; the three major rays of each point are square-ended and extend more than the other rays. Green central medallion bears gilt map of Mexico, surrounded by white band inscribed, <it>Merito en Campana</it> above and <it>Narcotrafico</it> below. Suspended by a small replica of a Mexican eagle from a green and black ribbon according to class, with a gilt bar at top inscribed <it>Mexico</it>.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Orden - slightly larger cross, green ribbon with wide black center stripe and overlaid diagonal green-white-red central stripe</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 1st Class - cross suspended from green ribbon with wide black center stripe</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 2nd Class - cross suspended from ribbon with five equal green-black-green-black-green stripes</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 3rd Class - cross suspended from ribbon with three equal green-black-green stripes</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/2504569.xml">
Mexican Imperial Orders</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</bdy>
</signal>
</award>
</symbol>
</article>
