<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:36:22[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<know-how  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105616786">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<method  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105660268">
<header>
<title>Chou-Fasman method</title>
<id>8714796</id>
<revision>
<id>228173994</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-27T11:31:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>William Pembroke</username>
<id>1422260</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Protein methods</category>
<category>Bioinformatics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Chou-Fasman method</b> are an empirical technique for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/8833897.xml">
prediction</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/28691.xml">
secondary structure</link>s in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link>s, originally developed in the 1970s. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The method is based on analyses of the relative frequencies of each <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/1207.xml">
amino acid</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/3054.xml">
alpha helices</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../906/4906.xml">
beta sheet</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/5139050.xml">
turns</link> based on known <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
protein structure</link>s solved with <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/34151.xml">
X-ray crystallography</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
. From these frequencies a set of probability parameters were derived for the appearance of each amino acid in each secondary structure type, and these parameters are used to predict the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/22934.xml">
probability</link> that a given sequence of amino acids would form a helix, a beta strand, or a turn in a protein. The method is at most about 50-60% accurate in identifying correct secondary structures, which is significantly less accurate than the <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/8732281.xml">
GOR method</link></method>
</know-how>
 or modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link>-based techniques.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
<sec>
<st>
Amino acid propensities</st>
<p>

The original Chou-Fasman parameters found some strong tendencies among individual amino acids to prefer one type of secondary structure over others. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/63539.xml">
Alanine</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/63541.xml">
glutamate</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/63546.xml">
leucine</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/59364.xml">
methionine</link> were identified as helix formers, while <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/38811.xml">
proline</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../835/11835.xml">
glycine</link>, due to the unique conformational properties of their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/24446.xml">
peptide bond</link>s, commonly end a helix. The original Chou-Fasman parameters<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> were derived from a very small and non-representative sample of protein structures due to the small number of such structures that were known at the time of their original work. These original parameters have since been shown to be unreliable<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> and have been updated from a current dataset, along with modifications to the initial algorithm.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

The Chou-Fasman method takes into account only the probability that each individual amino acid will appear in a helix, strand, or turn. Unlike the more complex <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/8732281.xml">
GOR method</link></method>
</know-how>
, it does not reflect the conditional probabilities of an amino acid to form a particular secondary structure given that its neighbors already possess that structure. This lack of cooperativity increases its computational efficiency but decreases its accuracy, since the propensities of individual amino acids are often not strong enough to render a definitive prediction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Algorithm</st>
<p>

The Chou-Fasman method predicts helices and strands in a similar fashion, first searching linearly through the sequence for a "nucleation" region of high helix or strand probability and then extending the region until a subsequent four-residue window carries a probability of less than 1. As originally described, four out of any six contiguous amino acids were sufficient to nucleate helix, and three out of any contiguous five were sufficient for a sheet. The probability thresholds for helix and strand nucleations are constant but not necessarily equal; originally 1.03 was set as the helix cutoff and 1.00 for the strand cutoff. </p>
<p>

Turns are also evaluated in four-residue windows, but are calculated using a multi-step procedure because many turn regions contain amino acids that could also appear in helix or sheet regions. Four-residue turns also have their own characteristic amino acids; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/38811.xml">
proline</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../835/11835.xml">
glycine</link> are both common in turns. A turn is predicted only if the turn probability is greater than the helix or sheet probabilities <it>and</it> a probability value based on the positions of particular amino acids in the turn exceeds a predetermined threshold. The turn probability p(t) is determined as:
<indent level="1">

<math>
p(t) = p_{t}(j) \times p_{t}(j+1) \times p_{t}(j+2) \times p_{t}(j+3)
</math>
</indent>
where <it>j</it> is the position of the amino acid in the four-residue window. If p(t) exceeds an arbitrary cutoff value (originally 7.5e-3), the mean of the p(j)'s exceeds 1, and p(t) exceeds the alpha helix and beta sheet probabilities for that window, then a turn is predicted. If the first two conditions are met but the probability of a beta sheet p(b) exceeds p(t), then a sheet is predicted instead.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Chou PY, Fasman GD. (1974). Prediction of protein conformation. <it>Biochemistry.</it> 13(2):222-45.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Chou PY, Fasman GD. (1978). Empirical predictions of protein conformation. <it>Annu Rev Biochem</it> 47:251-76. </entry>
<entry id="3">
Chou PY, Fasman GD. (1978). Prediction of the secondary structure of proteins from their amino acid sequence. <it>Adv Enzymol Relat Areas Mol Biol.</it> 47:45-148. </entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Mount DM&#32;(2004). Bioinformatics: Sequence and Genome Analysis, 2,&#32;Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press. ISBN 0879697121.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
Chou PY, Fasman GD. (1974). Conformational parameters for amino acids in helical, beta-sheet, and random coil regions calculated from proteins. <it>Biochemistry</it> 13(2):211-22.</entry>
<entry id="6">
Kyngas J, Valjakka J. (1998). Unreliability of the Chou-Fasman parameters in predicting protein secondary structure. <it>Protein Eng</it> 11(5):345-8. PMID 9681866.</entry>
<entry id="7">
Chen H, Gu F, Huang Z. (2006). Improved Chou-Fasman method for protein secondary structure prediction. <it>BMC Bioinformatics</it> 7(Suppl 4):S14.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</method>
</entity>
</know-how>
</article>
