<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:33:50[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Life Quality Index</title>
<id>8742025</id>
<revision>
<id>223841364</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-06T02:37:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Denverjeffrey</username>
<id>1548749</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia references cleanup</category>
<category>Orphaned articles from October 2007</category>
<category>Index numbers</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Life_Quality_Index&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Life+Quality+Index%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(October 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The references used in this article may be clearer with a different or consistent style of <b>, , or </b>.</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

The <b>Life Quality Index</b> (LQI) is a compound <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/972079.xml">
social indicator</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/47789.xml">
human welfare</link> that reflects the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/18669.xml">
expected length of life</link> in good health and enhancement of the quality of life through access to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/15037.xml">
income</link>. The Life Quality Index combines two primary social indicators: the expectancy of healthy life at birth, E, and the <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<history wordnetid="106514093" confidence="0.8">
<record wordnetid="106647206" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<index wordnetid="106639674" confidence="0.8">
<fact wordnetid="106636259" confidence="0.8">
<indication wordnetid="106797169" confidence="0.8">
<evidence wordnetid="106643408" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/510501.xml">
real gross domestic product</link></evidence>
</indication>
</fact>
</index>
</information>
</record>
</history>
</message>
 per person, G, corrected for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/64489.xml">
purchasing power parity</link> as appropriate. Both are widely available and accurate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/26685.xml">
statistics</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Basic concept </st>

<p>

The three components of the Life Quality Index, G, E and K reflect three important human concerns: the creation of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/192617.xml">
wealth</link>, the duration of life in good health and the time available to enjoy life. The amount of life available to enjoy wealth acts as a multiplying factor upon the value of that wealth.  Conversely, the amount of income one has to enjoy that available lifetime acts as a multiplier on the expected duration of life.</p>
<p>

Unlike the United Nation’s <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/261460.xml">
Human Development Index</link> (HDI), the LQI is derived rigorously from the economics of human welfare. Like the HDI it can be used to rank nations in order of human welfare (development). However, more important and unlike the HDI it can also serve as an objective function to be used in setting national or corporate goals for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/26404.xml">
managing risk</link> and to guide effective allocation of society’s scarce resources for the mitigation of risks to life or health. The LQI is a summary indicator of net benefit to society for improving the overall public welfare by reducing risks to life in a cost-effective manner.</p>
<p>

In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/2593.xml">
accounting</link> and assessment of human development, we can view the role of individuals as the principal means, or contributors, to development as well as the ends. For example, the productivity of an individual contributes directly to the aggregate wealth creation in a society. However, the income so generated (to whomsoever it may accrue) increases the capacity of society to provide the necessary means such as the required <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/174521.xml">
infrastructure</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/18994221.xml">
hospital</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/28022.xml">
school</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/198725.xml">
clean water</link>, safe <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/25897.xml">
road</link>s and structures). The adequacy of the infrastructure in turn benefits the individual via access to quality health and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/558685.xml">
environment</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/9252.xml">
education</link> and means for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../508/19159508.xml">
cultural</link> expression and enrichment. The LQI enhances our decision-making capacity and helps brings into sharp focus the choices and trade-offs we have to make between extension of life and creation of productive wealth.</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Formulation </st>

<p>

The mathematical expression for the Life-Quality Index L is:</p>
<p>

<math>L = E^KG</math></p>
<p>

showing the LQI, L as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/1198904.xml">
power function</link> of E, the health-adjusted life expectancy (HALE) at birth and G, the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) per person. The parameter K is a constant based on <link>
time budget studies</link> available for many countries. K is approximately equal to 5.0 for developed nations (Rackwitz 2005, Pandey et al. 2006). </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Societal Capacity to Commit Resources (SCCR)</st>
<p>

The LQI has been used to determine an acceptable level of expenditure that can be justifiably incurred on behalf of the public interest in exchange for a small reduction in the risk of death that results in improved life-quality for all. This value can be considered as the <link>
Societal Capacity to Commit Resources</link> (SCCR) to <link>
sustainable risk reduction</link>. 
Suppose a portion of GDP, dG, is invested in implementing a program that has an impact on public risk, thus modifying the life expectancy by a small amount dE. There is a net benefit if there is a net increase in LQI, dL. This criterion can be derived from the definition of L as:</p>
<p>

<math>\frac{dL}{L} = K \frac{dE}{E} + \frac{dG}{G} &amp;gt; 0</math>                        </p>
<p>

from which the Societal Capacity to Commit Resources to sustainable risk reduction follows as:</p>
<p>

<math>SCCR = \max (\frac{dG}{dE}) = \frac{KG}{E}</math></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Application</st>

<p>

The Life Quality Index is a decision tool serving to promote human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/148127.xml">
development</link> through better allocation of society’s scarce resources by reducing wasteful efforts on inefficient risk-reduction and identifying efficient alternatives. </p>
<p>

Given that the Societal Capacity to Commit Resources (SCCR) is limited, the LQI is a powerful indicator of merit amongst competing but desirable goods, such as for example level of resources to be directed at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/10934212.xml">
air pollution</link> vs <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/312266.xml">
water pollution</link> vs low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/22934.xml">
probability</link>, high consequence risks in the distant future. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Using the Life Quality Index or SCCR  to Judge Risk </st>

<p>

Risks influence the LQI via the age- and sex-specific mortality, calculated by changes in an actuarial life table.  The safety benefit is the gain in health-adjusted life expectancy HALE, or life extension expected upon implementation of the program.  The cost impacts must also be evaluated, measured as the impact on the real gross domestic product per person (with refinements that could include correction for purchasing power parity for international comparisons). The net benefit of a program is measured, according to the SCCR, by the resultant increases in real gross domestic product per capita and life expectancy, weighted by K, eq.(3). 
The Life Quality Index may be thought of as refinement of monetary measures commonly used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/374583.xml">
cost-benefit analysis</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Net Benefit Criterion for Managing Risk </st>

<p>

The objective is to maximize life expectancy subject to society’s capacity to commit resources in light of existing or future constraints.   Reducing risk of death and disease translates into longer healthful lives.  The length of life extension in good health for a population can be reliably measured as the impact on the gain in life expectancy (dE).  Resources and monies (-dG) are required to achieve the gains, or increases, in life expectancy.  If the resources are wisely spent, then the gains in life expectancy will be sufficiently large that there is a net increase in the Life Quality Index (LQI).  In contrast, if inordinate sums are spent on activities that do not save lives or result in only meagre life extension then there is a net decrease in the LQI. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Life Quality Index as a Tool for Managing Risk </st>

<p>

Through case studies and worked examples, it has been shown how the Life Quality Index can be used to assist decision-makers in evaluating the effectiveness of regulations and activities aimed at reducing risk to life, health and the environment. The LQI is a versatile tool that can be used to assess a wide range of risk management problems. The examples of application of LQI include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the effectiveness of standards and regulations for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/723482.xml">
health and safety</link>;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 harmonization of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/537481.xml">
structural safety standards</link> and design goals;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 assessment of air pollution standards;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 efficiency of life-saving interventions and estimates of the societal willingness (or capacity) to commit resources for safety.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Development of the Life Quality Index </st>

<p>

The concept of the Life Quality Index was first initiated at the Institute for Risk Research<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irr-neram.ca/">
http://www.irr-neram.ca/</weblink>, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/73276.xml">
University of Waterloo</link></university>
, Waterloo, <district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/22218.xml">
Ontario</link></district>
, Canada in the early 1990s The two primary publications were:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Lind, N.C., Nathwani, J.S. and Siddal, E. (1992). Managing Risks in the Public Interest, Institute of Risk Research, University of Waterloo Press, Waterloo, ON, Canada and</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nathwani, J.S., Lind, N.C., and Pandey, M.D. (1997). Affordable Safety by Choice: The Life Quality Method. Institute for Risk Research, University of Waterloo Press,</entry>
</list>

Waterloo, ON, Canada, pp 230.</p>
<p>

The principal investigators involved in the development of the Life Quality Index have been Professors <link>
Niels Lind</link>, <link>
Jatin Nathwani</link> and <link>
Mahesh Pandey</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Allen, R.G.D. (1935). A note on the determinateness of the utility function. The Reviewof Economic Studies, 2(2), 155-158.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Beckerman, W. (1968). An Introduction to National Income Analysis. Weidenfeld and Nicolson, London, UK</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Hicks, J.R. (1939). Value and Capital. Clarendon Press, USA.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Hicks, J.R. (1939). The foundation of welfare economics. The Economic Journal, 49(196), 696-712. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Hicks, J.R. (1940). Valuation of social income. Economica, No. 26.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Hicks, J.R. (1958). The measurement of real income. Oxford Economics Paper.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Hicks, J.R. (1975). The scope and status of welfare economics. Oxford Economics Paper 27(3), 307-326.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Kubler, O. and Faber, M.H. (2005). LQI: On the correlation between life expectancy and the gross domestic product per capita. Proceedings of ICOSSAR 2005, Rome, Italy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Lind, N.C. (2002). Social and economic criteria of acceptable risk. Reliability Engineering and System Safety, 78(1), 21-26.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Lind, N.C. (2005). Turning Life into Life Expectancy: The Efficiency of Life-Saving Interventions. To Appear in Int. Journal of Risk Assessment and Management.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Maes, M.A., Pandey, M.D. and Nathwani, J.S. (2003). Harmonizing Structural Safety Levels with Life Quality Objectives. Canadian J. of Civil Engineering, 30(3), 500-510.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nathwani, J.S., Pandey, M.D. and Lind, N.C. A standard for determination of optimal safety in engineering practice. Proc. IFIP Conference, pp.1-8. May 23-25, Aalborg, Denmark, 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nathwani, J.S. (2004) Strategic Principles for Managing Risk, Keynote Lecture, Proceedings.of the 11th IFIP Conference Reliability and Optimization of Structural Systems, (eds.) Maes, M.A. and Huyse, L., 13-22.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Nathwani, J.S. and Narveson, J. (1995) “Three Principles for Managing Risk in the Public Interest,” Int J.Risk Analysis, vol. 15, No.6, pp 615-626, 1995.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Organization of Economic Development and Cooperation (OECD). www.oecd.org/statistics.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandey, M.D. and Nathwani, J.S. (2003). Life-Quality Index for the estimation of societal willingness-to-pay for safety. J. Structural Safety, 26(2), 181-199.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandey, M.D. and Nathwani, J.S. (2003). Canada Wide Standard for Particulate Matter and Ozone: Cost-Benefit Analysis using a Life-Quality Index. Int. J. Risk Analysis, 23(1), 55-67.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandey, M.D. and Nathwani, J.S. (2004). Discounting Models and the Life-Quality Index for the Estimation of Estimation of Societal Willingness-to-Pay for Safety. Proc. 11th IFIP Conference Reliability and Optimization of Structural Systems, (eds.) Maes, M.A. and Huyse, L., pp.87-94.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandey, M.D. Nathwani, J.S.and Lind, N.C. (2006). The Derivation and Calibration of the Life-Quality Index. from Economic Principles. J. Structural Safety, 28 (1-2), 341-360.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandey, M.D. and Nathwani, J.S. Foundational Principles of Welfare Economics Underlying the Life Quality Index for Efficient Risk Management, Int. J. Risk Assessment and Management, February 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Rabl, A., Nathwani, J., Pandey, M.D. and Hurley, F. (2003) Tools and Strategies for Improving Policy Responses to the Risk of Air Pollution, Int. Conf. Strategies for Clean Air and Health. 5-7 November, Rome, Italy.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandey, M.D. and Nathwani, J.S. A Reinterpretation of Life-Quality Index for Cost-Benefit Analysis of Safety Programs. Proc. Int. Conf. Application of Statistics and Probability in Civil Engineering (ICASP 03), Der Kiureghian A., Madanat, S. and Pestana, J.M. (eds.), Vol.1, 711-717. San Francisco, CA, July 6-9, 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Pandey, M.D. and Nathwani, J.S. (2003) A Conceptual Approach to the Estimation of Societal Willingness-to-Pay for Nuclear Safety Programs. Int. J. Nuclear Engineering and Design, 224(1), 65-77.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 M.D. Pandey and J.S. Nathwani. (1997) Measurement of Socio-economic inequality using the life quality index, Social Indicators Research, vol 39, 187-202.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 UNDP, United Nations Human Development Reports, 1991, 1993, 1995, 2000.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
