<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:26:30[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Nuclear structure</title>
<id>8752642</id>
<revision>
<id>222867420</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-01T14:29:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Soman</username>
<id>67221</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Particle physics</category>
<category>Nuclear physics</category>
<category>Quantum mechanics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="background:#f9f9f9; font-size:85%; line-height:110%; ">
<row>
<col>
 <image width="32x28px" src="Portal.svg">
</image>
</col>
<col style="padding:0 0.2em;">
 <b><it>
Physics&#32;portal</it></b></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<it>This page is an adapted translation of the corresponding  - As will be noted, there remain void paragraphs, as on the original. Competent Wikipedians are welcome to enrich it, and their contributions will be translated back to fr: </it></p>
<p>

Understanding the structure of the atomic nucleus is one of the central problems in nuclear physics. This article is written from a nuclear physics perspective; as such, it is suggested that a casual reader first read the main <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/21285.xml">
nuclear physics</link> article.
</p>
<sec>
<st>
The liquid drop model</st>

<p>

This is one of the first models of nuclear structure, proposed by Weiszäcker in 1935. It describes the nucleus as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../988/2684988.xml">
classical fluid</link> made up of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/21272.xml">
neutron</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/23317.xml">
proton</link>s , with an internal repulsive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/41092.xml">
electric force</link> proportional to the number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/23317.xml">
proton</link>s. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanical</link> nature of these particles appears via the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/24669.xml">
Pauli exclusion principle</link></concept>
</idea>
, which states that no two nucleons of the same kind can be at the same <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/279638.xml">
state</link>. Thus the fluid is actually what is known as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/170165.xml">
fermi fluid</link>. This simple model reproduces the main features of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/125769.xml">
binding energy</link> of nuclei.</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/1085343.xml">
liquid drop model</link>&nbsp;and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/1085343.xml">
Semi-empirical mass formula</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The Shell model</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/50609.xml">
Shell model</link></it>
</indent>
===Introduction to the shell concept===</p>
<p>

Systematic measurements of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/125769.xml">
binding energy</link> of atomic nuclei show systematic deviations with respect to those estimated from the liquid drop model. In particular, some nuclei having special values for their number of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/23317.xml">
proton</link>s and/or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/21272.xml">
neutron</link>s are much more bound than predicted by the liquid drop model. These nuclei are called simply/doubly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../633/546633.xml">
magic</link>. This observation led scientists to assume the existence of a shell structure of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/21961.xml">
nucleon</link>s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/23317.xml">
proton</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../272/21272.xml">
neutron</link>s) within the nucleus, like that of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/9475.xml">
electrons</link> within atoms.</p>
<p>

Indeed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/21961.xml">
nucleon</link>s are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum objects</link>. Strictly speaking, one should not speak of energies of individual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/21961.xml">
nucleon</link>s, because they are all correlated with each other. To be able to speak of a shell structure, one envisions first an average nucleus, within which nucleons propagate individually. Owing to their quantum character, they can have then only <it>discrete</it> values of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/59444.xml">
energy level</link>s. These levels are by no means uniformly distributed : some intervals of energy are crowded, but they are separated by almost empty gaps. A shell is such a set of levels separated from the other ones by a wide empty gap.</p>
<p>

The determination of the energy levels is done via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanics</link>, more precisely by diagonalization of the single-nucleon <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/14381.xml">
Hamiltonian</link>. Each level may be occupied by a nucleon, or empty. Some levels accommodate several different quantum states with the same energy : they are said to be <it>degenerate</it>. This occurs in particular if the average nucleus has some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/53741.xml">
symmetry</link>.</p>
<p>

The concept of shells allows one to understand why some nuclei are more bound than others. This is because two nucleons of the same kind cannot be in the same state (<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/24669.xml">
Pauli exclusion principle</link></concept>
</idea>
). So the lowest-energy state of the nucleus is one where nucleons fill all energy levels from the bottom up to some level. A nucleus with full shells is exceptionally stable, as will be explained.</p>
<p>

As with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/9476.xml">
electron</link>s in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/23053.xml">
periodic table</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/23317.xml">
proton</link>s in the outermost shell are relatively loosely bound to the nucleus if there are only few protons in that shell, because they are farthest from the center of the nucleus. Therefore nuclei which have a full outer proton shell will be more tightly bound and have a higher binding energy than other nuclei with a similar total number of protons. All this is also true for neutrons. The binding is said to be "magically" large.</p>
<p>

Furthermore, the energy needed to excite the nucleus (i.e. moving a nucleon to a higher, previously unoccupied level) is exceptionally high in such nuclei.
Whenever this level is the topmost of a shell, the only way to excite the nucleus is to raise one nucleon <it>across the gap</it>, thus spending a large energy. Otherwise, if the highest occupied energy level lies in the middle of a shell, much less energy is required to raise a nucleon to a higher state in the same shell.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Basic hypotheses</st>

<p>

The expression "shell model" is ambiguous in that it refers to two different eras in the state of the art. It was previously used to describe the existence of nucleon shells in the nucleus according to an approach closer to what is now called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../642/8752642.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Mean+field+theories%22])">
mean field theory</link>.
Nowadays, it refers to a set of techniques which help solving some variants of the nuclear <it>n</it>-body problem. We shall introduce these here.</p>
<p>

Several basic hypotheses are made in order to give a precise conceptual framework to the shell model :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The atomic nucleus is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum</link> <it>n</it>-body system.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The nucleus is not a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/26962.xml">
relativistic</link> object. The equation of motion giving the system <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/145343.xml">
wavefunction</link> (which contains the whole information about it in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/25202.xml">
quantum mechanics</link>) is the <link>
Schrödinger equation</link>.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/21961.xml">
nucleon</link>s interact only via a 2-body interaction. This limitation is in effect a practical consequence of the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/24669.xml">
Pauli exclusion principle</link></concept>
</idea>
 : the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/170097.xml">
mean free path</link> of a nucleon being large with respect to the nucleus size, the probability that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/1962679.xml">
three nucleons</link> interact simultaneously is considered as small enough to be negligible.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/21961.xml">
Nucleon</link>s are considered to be pointlike, without any structure, in this model, for the sake of simplicity.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Brief description of the formalism</st>

<p>

The general process used in the shell model calculations is the following. First a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/14381.xml">
Hamiltonian</link> for the nucleus is defined. As mentioned before, only 1- and 2-body terms are taken into account in this definition. The interaction is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../582/681582.xml">
effective theory</link> : it contains free parameters which have to be fitted with experimental data.</p>
<p>

The next step consists in defining a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/18420.xml">
basis</link> of single-particle states, i.e. a set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/145343.xml">
wavefunction</link>s describing all possible nucleon states. Most of the time, this basis is obtained via a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/475393.xml">
Hartree-Fock</link> computation. With this set of 1-particle states, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/481056.xml">
Slater determinant</link>s are built, that is, wavefunctions for <it>Z</it> proton variables or <it>N</it> neutron variables, which are antisymmetrized products of single-particle wavefunctions (antisymmetrized meaning that under exchange of variables for any pair of nucleons, the wavefunction only changes sign).</p>
<p>

In principle, the number of quantum states available for a single nucleon at a finite energy is finite, say <it>n</it>. The number of nucleons in the nucleus must be smaller than the number of available states, otherwise the nucleus cannot hold all of its nucleons. There are thus several ways to choose <it>Z</it> (or <it>N</it>) states among the <it>n</it> possible. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../170/5170.xml">
combinatorial mathematics</link>, the number of choices of <it>Z</it> objects among <it>n</it> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/4668.xml">
binomial coefficient</link> C<it>nZ</it> . If <it>n</it> is much larger than <it>Z</it> (or <it>N</it>), this increases roughly like <it>nZ</it>. Practically, this number becomes so large that every computation is impossible for <it>A</it>=<it>N</it>+<it>Z</it> larger than 8.</p>
<p>

To obviate this difficulty, the space of possible single-particle states is divided into a core and a
valence shell, by analogy with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/9475.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22valence+shell%22])">
chemistry</link>. The core is a set of single-particles which are assumed to be inactive, in the sense that they are the well bound lowest-energy states, and that there is no need to reexamine their situation. They do not appear in the Slater determinants, contrary to the states in the valence space, which is the space of all single-particle states <it>not in the core</it>, but possibly to be considered in the choice of the build of the (<it>Z</it>-) <it>N</it>-body wavefunction. The set of all possible Slater determinants in the valence space defines a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/18420.xml">
basis</link> for
(<it>Z</it>-) <it>N</it>-body states.</p>
<p>

The last step consists in computing the matrix of the Hamiltonian within this basis, and to diagonalize it. In spite of the reduction of the dimension of the basis owing to the fixation of the core, the matrices to be diagonalized reach easily dimensions of the order of 109, and demand specific diagonalization techniques.</p>
<p>

The shell model calculations give in general an excellent fit with experimental data. They depend however strongly on two main factors :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The way to divide the single-particle space into core and valence.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The effective nucleon-nucleon interaction.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Related problems</st>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Mean field theories</st>

<ss1>
<st>
The independent-particle model</st>

<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/21285.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22+Basic+properties+of+the+nuclear+force%22])">
interaction between nucleons</link>, which is a consequence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/27984.xml">
strong interaction</link>s, and binds the nucleons within the nucleus exhibits the peculiar behaviour to have a finite range : it vanishes when the distance among two nucleons becomes too large ; it is attractive at medium range, and repulsive at very small range. This last property correlates with the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/24669.xml">
Pauli exclusion principle</link></concept>
</idea>
 according to which two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/11529.xml">
fermion</link>s (nucleons are fermions) cannot be in the same quantum state. This results in a very large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/170097.xml">
mean free path</link> of a nucleon within the nucleus. This result, confirmed by particle scattering experiments, led to the elaboration of the independent-particle model.</p>
<p>

The main idea of this approach is that all looks as if a nucleon moves inside a certain potential well (which keeps it bound to the nucleus) independently from the other nucleons. In theory, this amounts to replacing a <it>N</it>-body problem (<it>N</it> particles interacting) by <it>N</it> single-body problems. This essential simplification of the problem is the cornerstone of mean field theories. These are also widely used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/1200.xml">
atomic physics</link>, where <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../476/9476.xml">
electron</link>s move in a mean field due to the central nucleus and the electron cloud itself.</p>
<p>

Although this hypothesis looks grossly simplifying, it led to big success, and mean field theories (we shall see that there exist several variants) are now a basic part of atomic nucleus theory. One should also notice that they are modular enough (in terms of programming theory), in that it is quite easy to introduce certain effects such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/50604.xml">
nucleon pairing</link>, or collective motions of the nucleon like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/39789.xml">
rotation</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/19427018.xml">
vibration</link>, adding "by hand" the corresponding energy terms in the formalism.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Nuclear potential and effective interaction</st>

<p>

A large part of the practical difficulties met in mean field theories is the definition (or calculation) of the <link>
potential</link> of the mean field itself. One can very roughly distinguish between two approaches :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <b>phenomenological</b> approach is a parameterization of the nuclear potential by an appropriate mathematical function. Historically, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/50609.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Deformed+harmonic+oscillator+approximated+model%22])">
this procedure</link> was applied with the greatest success by Sven Gösta Nilsson, who used as a potential a (deformed) <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/50719.xml">
harmonic oscillator</link> potential. The most recent parameterizations are based on more realistic functions, which account more accurately for scattering experiments, for example. In particular the form known as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../006/11357006.xml">
Woods Saxon potential</link> can be mentioned.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <b>self-consistent</b> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/475393.xml">
Hartree-Fock</link> approach aims to deduce mathematically the nuclear potential from the nucleon-nucleon interaction. This technique implies a resolution of the <link>
Schrödinger equation</link> in an iterative fashion, since the potential depends there upon the wavefunctions to be determined. The latter are written as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/481056.xml">
Slater determinant</link>s.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In the case of the Hartree-Fock approaches, the trouble is not to find the mathematical function which describes best the nuclear potential, but that which describes best the nucleon-nucleon interaction. Indeed, in contrast with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/1200.xml">
atomic physics</link> where the interaction is known (it is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/47719.xml">
Coulomb</link> interaction), the nucleon-nucleon interaction within the nucleus is not known analytically.</p>
<p>

There are two main reasons for this fact. First, the strong interaction acts essentially among the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/25179.xml">
quark</link>s forming the nucleons. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/27984.xml">
nucleon-nucleon interaction</link> in vacuum is a mere <it>consequence</it> of the quark-quark interaction. While the latter is well understood in the framework of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/47641.xml">
standard model</link> at high energies, it is much more complicated in low energies due to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/169188.xml">
color confinement</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/648008.xml">
asymptotic freedom</link>. Thus there is no fundamental theory allowing one to deduce the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/27984.xml">
nucleon-nucleon interaction</link> from the quark-quark interaction. Further, even if this problem were solved, there would remain a large difference between the ideal (and conceptually simpler) case of two nucleons interacting in vacuo, and that of these nucleons interacting in the nuclear matter. To go further, it was necessary to invent the concept of <link>
effective interaction</link>. The latter is basically a mathematical function with several arbitrary parameters, which are adjusted to agree with experimental data.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The self-consistent approaches of the Hartree-Fock type</st>

<p>

In the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/475393.xml">
Hartree-Fock</link> approach of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/428513.xml">
<it>n</it>-body problem</link>, the starting point is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/294202.xml">
Hamiltonian</link> containing <it>n</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/17327.xml">
kinetic energy</link> terms, and potential terms. As mentioned before, one of the mean field theory hypotheses is that only the 2-body interaction is to be taken into account. The potential term of the Hamiltonian represents all possible 2-body interactions in the set of <it>n</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/11529.xml">
fermion</link>s. It is the first hypothesis.</p>
<p>

The second step consists in assuming that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/145343.xml">
wavefunction</link> of the system can be written as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/481056.xml">
Slater determinant</link>. This statement is the mathematical translation of the independent-particle model. This is the second hypothesis.</p>
<p>

There remains now to determine the components of this Slater determinant, that is, the individual <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/145343.xml">
wavefunction</link>s of the nucleons. To this end, it is assumed that the total wavefunction (the Slater determinant) is such that the energy is minimum. This is the third hypothesis.</p>
<p>

Technically, it means that one must compute the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/19192.xml">
mean value</link> of the (known) 2-body <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/294202.xml">
Hamiltonian</link> on the (unknown) Slater determinant, and impose that its mathematical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/171882.xml">
variation</link> vanishes. This leads to a set of equations where the unknowns are the individual wavefunctions : the Hartree-Fock equations. Solving these equations gives the wavefunctions and individual energy levels of nucleons, and so the total energy of the nucleus and its wavefunction.</p>
<p>

This short account of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/475393.xml">
Hartree-Fock</link> method explains why it is called also the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../882/171882.xml">
variational</link> approach. At the beginning of the calculation, the total energy is a "function of the individual wavefunctions" (a so-called functional), and everything is then made in order to optimize the choice of these wavefunctions so that the functional has a minimum – hopefully absolute, and not only local. To be more precise, there should be mentioned that the energy is a functional of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/62844.xml">
density</link>, defined as the sum of the individual squared wavefunctions. Let us note also that the Hartree-Fock method is also used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/1200.xml">
atomic physics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/5387.xml">
condensed matter physics</link> as Density Functional Theory, DFT.</p>
<p>

The process of solving the Hartree-Fock equations can only be iterative, since these are in fact a <link>
Schrödinger equation</link> in which the potential depends on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/62844.xml">
density</link>, that is, precisely on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/145343.xml">
wavefunction</link>s to be determined. Practically, the algorithm is started with a set of individual grossly reasonable wavefunctions (in general the eigenfunctions of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../719/50719.xml">
harmonic oscillator</link>). These allow to compute the density, and therefrom the Hartree-Fock potential. Once this done, the Schrödinger equation is solved anew, and so on. The calculation stops – convergence is reached – when the difference among wavefunctions, or energy levels, for two successive iterations is less than a fixed value. Then the mean field potential is completely determined, and the Hartree-Fock equations become standard Schrödinger equations. The corresponding Hamiltonian is then called the Hartree-Fock Hamiltonian.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The relativistic mean field approaches</st>

<p>

Born first in the 1970’s with the works of <link>
D. Walecka</link> on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/27984.xml">
quantum hadrodynamics</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/26962.xml">
relativistic</link> models of the nucleus were sharpened up towards the end of the 1980’s by P. Ring and coworkers. The starting point of these approaches is the relativistic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/25267.xml">
quantum field theory</link>. In this context, the nucleon interactions occur via the exchange of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/192316.xml">
virtual particle</link>s called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/19870.xml">
meson</link>s. The idea is, in a first step, to build a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/198566.xml">
lagrangian</link> containing these interaction terms. Second, by an application of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/249438.xml">
least action principle</link>, one gets a set of equations of motion. The real particles (here the nucleons) obey the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/39407.xml">
Dirac equation</link>, whilst the virtual ones (here the mesons) obey the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/209627.xml">
Klein-Gordon equation</link>s.</p>
<p>

In view of the non-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/102140.xml">
perturbative</link> nature of strong interaction, and also of the fact that it is relatively badly known, the use of such an approach in the case of atomic nuclei requires drastic approximations. The main simplification consists in replacing in the equations all field terms (which are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../928/291928.xml">
operators</link> in the mathematical sense) by their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/19192.xml">
mean value</link> (which are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/185427.xml">
function</link>s). In this way, one gets a system of coupled integro-differential equations, which can be solved numerically, if not analytically.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Spontaneous breaking of symmetry in nuclear physics</st>

<p>

One of the focal points of all physics is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/53741.xml">
symmetry</link>. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/27984.xml">
nucleon-nucleon interaction</link> and all <link>
effective interaction</link>s used in practice have certain symmetries. They are invariant by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/204682.xml">
translation</link> (changing the frame of reference so that directions are not altered), by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/39789.xml">
rotation</link> (turning the frame of reference around some axis), or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../088/25088.xml">
parity</link> (changing the sense of axes) in the sense that the interaction does not change under any of these operations. Nevertheless, in the Hartree-Fock approach, solutions which are not invariant under such a symmetry can appear. One speaks then of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/297466.xml">
spontaneous symmetry breaking</link>.</p>
<p>

Qualitatively, these spontaneous symmetry breakings can be explained in the following way : in the mean field theory, the nucleus is described as a set of independent particles. Most additional correlations among nucleons which do not enter the mean field are neglected. They can appear however by a breaking of the symmetry of the mean field Hamiltonian, which is only approximate. If the density used to start the iterations of the Hartree-Fock process breaks certain symmetries, the final Hartree-Fock Hamiltonian may break these symmetries, if it is advantageous to keep these broken from the point of view of the total energy.</p>
<p>

It may also converge towards a symmetric solution. In any case, if the final solution breaks the symmetry, for example, the rotational symmetry, so that the nucleus appears not to be spherical, but elliptic, all configurations deduced from this deformed nucleus by a rotation are just as good solutions for the Hartree-Fock problem. The ground state of the nucleus is then <it>degenerate</it>.</p>
<p>

A similar phenomenon happens with the nuclear pairing, which violates the conservation of the number of baryons (see below).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Extensions of the mean field theories</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Nuclear pairing phenomenon</st>

<p>

Historically, the observation that the nuclei with an even number of nucleons are systematically more bound than those with an odd one led to propose the nuclear pairing hypothesis. The very simple idea is that each nucleon binds with another one to form a pair. When the nucleus has an even number of nucleons, each one of them finds a partner. To excite such a system, one must at least use such an energy as to break a pair. Conversely, in the case of odd number of nucleons, there exists a bachelor nucleon, which needs less energy to be excited.</p>
<p>

This phenomenon is closely analogous to that of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/26884.xml">
superconductivity</link> in solid state physics (at least the low-temperature superconductivity). The first theoretical description of nuclear pairing was proposed at the end of the 1950’s by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/23rd_century.xml">
Aage Bohr</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/396657.xml">
Ben Mottelson</link> (which led to their Nobel Prize in Physics in 1975). It was close to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/4403.xml">
BCS theory</link> of Bardeen, Cooper and Schrieffer, which accounts for metal superconductivity. Theoretically, the pairing phenomenon as described by the BCS theory combines with the mean field theory : nucleons are both subject to the mean field potential and to the pairing interaction, but these are independent.</p>
<p>

It is tempting to interpret the pairing interaction as a <b>residual interaction</b>. To build the mean field interaction, only some terms of the nucleon-nucleon interaction are taken into account. Everything else is qualified as <it>residual interaction</it>. The value of the mean field theory rests on the fact that the <it>residual interaction</it> is numerically much less than what is taken into account for the mean field. There should be however a link between them, since they proceed from the same <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/27984.xml">
nucleon-nucleon interaction</link>. This is not taken into account in the BCS theory. To circumvent this point, the <link>
Hartree-Fock-Bogolyubov</link> (HFB) approach has been developed, to include into a unified formalism the mean field, the pairing and their mutual links.</p>
<p>

Let us note finally that one big difference between superconductivity and nuclear pairing resides in the number of particles. In a metal, the number of free electrons is very large, compared to the number of nucleons in a nucleus. The BCS (and HFB) approach describes the system wavefunction as a superposition of components with different numbers of particles. In the case of a metal, this violation of the conservation of the number of particles is of no consequence, in view of the huge statistics. But in nuclear physics, this leads to a real problem. Specific techniques for restoring the number of particles have been developed, in the framework of the restoration of broken symmetries.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Description of collective motions of the nucleus</st>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
How to get "beyond" the mean field ?</st>



</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (French) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-phynu.cea.fr">
Service de Physique Nucléaire CEA/DAM, France</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (French) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.in2p3.fr">
Institut National de Physique Nucléaire et de Physique des Particules (In2p3), France</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (French) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ganil.fr">
Grand Accélérateur National d'Ions Lourds (GANIL), France</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (French) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cea.fr">
Commissariat à l'Energie Atomique (CEA), France</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (English) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gsi.de">
Gesellschaft für Schwerionenforschung (GSI), Allemagne</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (English) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jinr.dubna.su">
Joint Institute for Nuclear Research (JINR), Russie</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (English) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.anl.gov">
Argonne National Laboratory (ANL), États-Unis</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (French) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://public.web.cern.ch/public/Welcome-fr.html">
Centre Européen de Recherches Nucléaires, Suisse</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 (English) <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.riken.go.jp/engn/index.html">
Riken, Japon</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/21285.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22External+links%22])">
Nuclear physics#External links</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/21285.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22References%22])">
Nuclear physics#References</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
<ss1>
<st>
General audience</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 James M. Cork ; <it>Radioactivité &amp; physique nucléaire</it>, Dunod (1949).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Introductory texts</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Luc Valentin ; <it>Le monde subatomique - Des quarks aux centrales nucléaires</it>, Hermann (1986).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Luc Valentin ; <it>Noyaux et particules - Modèles et symétries</it>, Hermann (1997).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 David Halliday ; <it>Introduction à la physique nucléaire</it>, Dunod (1957).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fundamental texts</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Irving Kaplan; <it>Nuclear physics</it>, the Addison-Wesley Series in Nuclear Science &amp; Engineering, Addison-Wesley (1956).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A. Bohr &amp; B. Mottelson ; <it>Nuclear Structure</it>, 2 vol., Benjamin (1969-1975). Volume 1 : <it>Single Particle Motion</it> ; Volume 2 : <it>Nuclear Deformations</it>. Réédité par World Scientific Publishing Company (1998), ISBN 9810231970.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 P. Ring &amp; P. Schuck; <it>The nuclear many-body problem</it>, Springer Verlag (1980), ISBN 354021206X</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A. de Shalit &amp; H. Feshbach; <it>Theoretical Nuclear Physics</it>, 2 vol., John Wiley &amp; Sons (1974). Volume 1: <it>Nuclear Structure</it>; Volume 2: <it>Nuclear Reactions</it>, ISBN 0471203858</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 N. Cook; <it>Models of the Atomic Nucleus</it>, Springer Verlag (2006), ISBN 3540285695</entry>
</list>
</p>






</ss1>
</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
