<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:47:32[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Maltese cuisine</title>
<id>885371</id>
<revision>
<id>244413883</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T18:04:46Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Africa templates</category>
<category>Maltese cuisine</category>
<category>Middle East templates</category>
<category>Mediterranean cuisine</category>
<category>Europe arts and culture templates</category>
<category>Europe region templates</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b><country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/19137.xml">
Maltese</link></country>
 cuisine</b> is typically <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/1342098.xml">
Mediterranean</link>, based on fresh seasonal locally available <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/733668.xml">
produce</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/26866.xml">
seafood</link>, with some influence from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/3735620.xml">
Italian cuisine</link>, particularly <link>
Sicily and the south</link>. There are many unique and distinctive local dishes and the cuisine also embodies the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/1071756.xml">
gastronomic</link> legacies of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/39943.xml">
Malta's past</link>, including not only Italian, but <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/27669.xml">
Spanish</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/2053043.xml">
Moorish</link>, and more recently <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/7896915.xml">
British</link> influence.<p>

<image width="150px" src="Malta_grilled_klamari_2.JPG">
<caption>

 Grilled Calamari
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Maltese cuisine is still popular in households and restaurants in Malta, but influences from outside Malta's shores continue, though nowadays they come through travel and TV rather than foreign domination. Alongside Malta's traditional cuisine with its strong Southern Mediterranean character, there is today an eclectic mix of dishes drawn from other cuisines, not only Italian but also Asian, North American and Mexican for example. This article on Maltese cuisine however refers exclusively to the traditional dishes of Malta and Gozo, still widely prepared and enjoyed on the islands of Malta and Gozo, the second island, which boasts a number of dishes all of its own.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Dishes</st>
<p>

For such a small island of 10 miles by 20, the distinctive cuisine of Malta has a long and rich repertoire of dishes of which the best known are:</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Starters / Nibbles </st>



<ss2>
<st>
Żebbuġ Mimli (Stuffed Olives)</st>
<p>

Large green pitted olives filled with a piquant chopped anchovy,caper and breadcrumb mixture.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Fażola Bajda bit-tewm u it-tursin (Beans with parsley, garlic and olive oil)</st>
<p>

Large dried white beans previously soaked overnight simmered till cooked, dressed with finely minced garlic, chopped parsley and olive oil and served cold. Flaked canned tuna (<it>tonn taż-żejt</it>) or salt cured tuna (<it>tonn mielaħ</it>) black olives may be added.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Fritturi Tal-Qaqoċċ (Artichoke Fritters)</st>
<p>

Floured and fried artichoke hearts, previously poached with olive oil and garlic, dipped in a batter of flour mixed with parsley and salted anchovy or garlic and deep fried. Vegetable fritters are also made of slices of pumpkin, kohlrabi, zucchini, aubergine or long gourd (<it>qara' twil</it>) as well as with cauliflower florets and even wedges of Roma or curly endive lettuce. The vegetables are usually raw though they may have been previously parboiled.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Fritturi Tal-Makku (Whitebait Fritters)</st>
<p>

Fresh whitebait are dipped in a flour, chopped parsley and minced garlic mix and deep fried in small handfuls. Served with lemon wedges.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Bigilla (Bean paste or dip)</st>
<p>

<dish wordnetid="103206908" confidence="0.8">
<crockery wordnetid="103133538" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<article wordnetid="100022903" confidence="0.8">
<ware wordnetid="104550840" confidence="0.8">
<container wordnetid="103094503" confidence="0.8">
<tableware wordnetid="104381994" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../169/1595169.xml">
Bigilla</link></tableware>
</container>
</ware>
</article>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</crockery>
</dish>
 is a traditional bean paste. It is made with a type of dried <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/264501.xml">
broad beans</link> called <it>ful tal-Ġirba</it>, similar to those used for Egyptian <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/2243880.xml">
Ful Medames</link>,  which are soaked for 24 hours, rinsed, then boiled until they are very soft. The beans are subsequently mashed and mixed with salt, pepper, olive oil, crushed garlic and chopped parsley. Chili is optional. Usually served with <link>
 traditional Maltese ship's biscuits</link>  called <it>Galletti</it> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/885371.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22=C4=A6ob=C5=BCa+tal-Malti+(Maltese+bread)%22])">
Ħobża tal-Malti</link> drizzled with olive oil.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
"Angels on Horseback"</st>
<p>

In <link>
 British cuisine</link>, oysters  or (sometimes scallops) wrapped in bacon and grilled are called <link>
 "Angels on Horseback"</link> while <link>
"Devils on horseback"</link> are grilled bacon-wrapped prunes, two <link>
 savouries</link> now considered rather "retro" and 70s though originating in Victorian times. In Malta no one has ever stopped enjoying the local version adapted to what is locally available  and no Maltese cocktail buffet or catered wedding is complete without Maltese "Angels on Horseback" which consist of grilled, bacon-wrapped small pieces of liver.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Bebbux (Snails)</st>
<p>

Snails simmered in red wine, Lacto (a local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/19278603.xml">
ale</link>), and Kinnie (see Soft Drinks below) with mint, basil and marjoram. Often served with <it>Ajjoli</it> sauce or <it>Salsa Ħadra</it>, see below.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Soup (<it>Soppa</it>)</st>


<ss2>
<st>
Minestra (Thick vegetable soup)</st>
<p>

The start of many Maltese meals is soup. Traditionally minestra is a healthy, thick soup combining numerous fresh vegetables and one or more <link>
pulses</link>  like beans, chick peas and split  peas, accompanied by a hearty, slice of crusty Maltese bread, <it>ħobża</it>. This dish is eaten all year round, but usually preferable in winter as a healthy, warming dinner.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Kusksu (Broad Bean &amp; Pasta Soup)</st>
<p>

Another meal-in-a-soup, the essential ingredients are a form of small pasta beads called <it>kusksu</it>, which give it a particular texture, and fresh broad beans], cooked with onions and tomato paste. Some families also add another item (fresh peas or potatoes or gbejniet or small calamari) to the dish. The pasta is similar in shape to Sardinian <it>Fregula</it> but is not the same as North African <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/6745.xml">
couscous</link>, which in Tunisia is called <it>Kusksi</it> or sometimes <it>Kusksu</it>. For many this soup is associated with <vacation wordnetid="115137890" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/58009.xml">
Good Friday</link></vacation>
.  It is a spring favorite, since that is the time when broad beans are in season.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Soppa ta l-armla (Widow's soup)</st>
<p>

So named because of the tradition of neighbours donating products to poor widows living in their neighbourhood. This vegetable soup is a thinner version of <it>Minestra</it> ( see above), rounded off with fresh <it>ġbejniet</it> which melt into the hot soup. Usually raw eggs are added at the end and when they are just set, the soup is ready. A common variation makes the soup with just onions, lettuce, peas and carrots plus the traditional egg and cheese elements.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Aljotta (Fish soup)</st>
<p>

A rich fish <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/19651298.xml">
soup</link>, similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/502185.xml">
broth</link> in consistency, with plenty of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/50469.xml">
garlic</link>, herbs like mint or marjoram and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/9940234.xml">
tomato</link>es. usually contains rice, though variants may substitute fine long pasta or small pasta stars.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Kawlata (Pork and cabbage soup)</st>
<p>

Thick and chunky, almost a stew, of cabbage, potato and pork knuckle with Maltese sausage (see below) and sometimes also bacon. Traditionally served as two courses with the meats removed and served as second course but may be served as a comforting one pot cold weather meal</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Brodu (Clear broth)</st>
<p>

A broth similar to broths cooked in other countries. Can be vegetable broth or meat broth (beef or chicken or both) Stuffed vegetables or stuffed meat or chickens may be cooked in broth, also rice or pasta or small meatballs.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Pasta and rice</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Mqarrun il-Forn (Baked macaroni)</st>
<p>

A baked dish made with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/20229.xml">
macaroni</link>, bolognese style meat sauce, egg, and various other ingredients varying according to family tradition including chicken livers, hard boiled eggs, peas and bacon. The macaroni is usually topped with a layer of grated cheese or besciamella (béchamel) that will melt during the baking process and help to bind and set the pasta. </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ravjul (Malta Style <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/611752.xml">
ravioli</link>)</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Ravjul_w_Gbejna.JPG‎">
<caption>

 Gozo restaurant ravjul topped with grated Ġbejna 
</caption>
</image>

The ravjul (sing. <it>ravjula</it>) is typically filled with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/708679.xml">
ricotta</link> and fresh parsley and covered with a garlic scented fresh tomato sauce garnished with celery and basil.  This is served with freshly-grated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/304667.xml">
Parmesan</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../870/1338870.xml">
Romano cheese</link>. Alternatively spinach or  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/1513621.xml">
minced meat</link> is used as filling. In <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/205475.xml">
Gozo</link></village>
, Ravjul are filled with local Sheep's Cheese (<link>
Ġbejniet</link>). Traditionally <it>ravjul</it> portions are sized by the number of individual ravioli, and always counted in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/208154.xml">
dozen</link>s and half dozens. <it>Ravjul</it> can also be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/523770.xml">
caramelized</link> and served as a dessert.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ross il-Forn (Baked rice)</st>
<p>

<it>Ross il-forn</it> (or Baked Rice) is quite similar to <it>Mqarrun il-Forn</it> (Baked Macaroni). There is a version made with Maltese sausage (see below) that has <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/53332.xml">
saffron</link> as an additional ingredient. It is placed in the oven uncooked with 2 cups (200ml) of water for every cup of rice.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Timpana (Pastry-covered baked macaroni)</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Maltese_Timpana.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A slice of timapana.
</caption>
</image>

Baked <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/20229.xml">
macaroni</link> tossed in a tomato sauce containing a small amount of minced beef and sometimes hard-boiled eggs bound with a mix of raw egg and grated cheese. It can be thought of as a sort of macaroni meat pie as the pasta is encased in pastry or topped with a pastry "lid" and baked till the pastry is lgihtly golden.  The basic difference between <it>Timpana</it> and <it>Mqarrun il-Forn</it> is the addition of the pastry case or lid which makes Timpana the richer dish, more suited to festive occasions. There is also a less well known <b>Timpana tar-Ross</b>, where the pastry encloses rice mixed with chopped chicken livers braised with softened onions and garlic, broth mixed with tomato paste and saffron, grated cheese and eggs.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ghaġin bl-inċova (Pasta with Anchovy Sauce)</st>
<p>

Spaghetti dressed with a piquant sauce of tomato paste, salted anchovies and garlic is fried till crisp. Often a supper dish.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ghaġin  Grieg (Pasta "beads" with minced pork and cheese)</st>
<p>

A short local pasta that resembles Italian "ditali" is dressed with a sauce made of minced pork, diced bacon and sliced onions long simmered in chicken broth. The separately cooked pasta is tossed first in butter, then in the pork and bacon mixture and finally with lots of grated cheese. The cheese used to be British Cheddar but today it is more often Parmigiano-Reggano Reggiano. Why this should be called "Greek Pasta" - or by some "Turkish Pasta" or even "Greek Rice" - is a complete mystery!</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Meat</st>

<p>

The excellent local pork is probably the most universally eaten meat, followed by local rabbit, mainly imported beef and local chicken and turkey. Imported lamb and veal are also popular. Game birds like quail (<it>summien</it>), which are now farmed, turtle doves (<it>gamiem</it>) and wild pigeons (<it>bċieċen</it>) are also popular. Offal and organ meats like  pork liver and kidneys, tripe, brain, tongue, heart, stomach and tail also form part of the cuisine and are much loved by traditionalists and gourmets though not the squeamish. They are less popular today than in the past when the fine cuts of meat were not within everyone's reach. </p>

<ss2>
<st>
Braġjoli (Beef olives)</st>
<p>

A thin slice of beef rolled round a tasty filling of breadcrumbs, bacon, eggs and fresh herbs ("<it>beef olives</it>" in British English, "<it>braciole</it>" in Southern Italy or "<it>involtini</it>" in Northern Italy). The filling may also include a slice of cooked ham, hard boiled egg, grated cheese and a hint of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/323204.xml">
Curry powder</link>. Particularly tasty when slow braised in red wine or in tomato sauce.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Fenek (Rabbit)</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Malta_Rabbit_fried_with_wine_and_garlic.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Rabbit fried with wine and garlic
</caption>
</image>

Perhaps because the <order wordnetid="107168623" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<command wordnetid="107168131" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../399/84399.xml">
Knights of Malta</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</command>
</event>
</order>
 - who could eat rabbit any time they chose and enjoyed hunting them for sport - prohibited the islanders from eating rabbit with the one exception of<it> L'Imnarja</it>, the feast of Saints Peter and Paul held at the end of June, or maybe because most Maltese families kept rabbits as courtyard animals destined for the pot, rabbit is very popular and one of the most well known Maltese dishes, one of the few served in restaurants. The rabbit, often previously marinated, is lightly browned with garlic and herbs, then simmered for several hours, ideally in a terracotta casserole, in red wine or in a rich tomato sauce. Restaurants usually serve it with chips (the ubiquitous British legacy) and salad, though crusty local bread to soak up the rich sauces and a cooked green vegetable are more appropriate.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Laħam fuq il-fwar (Steamed Meat)</st>
<p>

Since many Maltese meals begin with soup this was a way for the frugal Maltese cook to utilise the heat from the soup pot. Thin slices of beef (most often) are placed on an oiled plate and layered with with the filling for <it>Braġjoli</it> (see above) or else with garlic, chopped herbs like marjoram and parsley, and breadcrumbs or cooked spinach. The meat and filling layers, which must not be too many, are covered with a second plate or with greaseproof paper and the meat is left to cook gently and slowly till tender. A very healthy cooking method also used for cooking liver, Maltese Sausage or thin pork chops, and also for simmering fish fillets over an <it>Aljotta</it>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Falda Mimlija (Stuffed Flank)</st>
<p>

Beef or more usually pork flank with a pocket cut into it. The pocket is filled with a mixture based on minced pork, grated cheese and parsley bound with egg. The stuffed meat may be steamed, poached in broth or baked on a bed of potatoes.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Laħam taż-żiemel (Horse or stallion meat)</st>
<p>

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="103081021" confidence="0.8">
<ingredient wordnetid="103570709" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="103892891" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/933515.xml">
Stallion meat</link></part>
</ingredient>
</component>
</commodity>
</merchandise>
</artifact>
 was fairly widely eaten in the past when available, usually steamed (see above) or fried with garlic or else simmered on top of the stove or in the oven in an onion and white wine sauce. As noted by the British Food Journalist <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<journalist wordnetid="110224578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/5067714.xml">
Matthew Fort</link></journalist>
</writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
   farmers and country folk simply could not afford to be too attached to their working farm animals. "In the frugal, unsentimental manner of agricultural communities, all the animals were looked on as a source of protein. Waste was not an option" <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Zalzett tal-Malti (Maltese sausage)</st>
<p>

Maltese sausage is typically made of pork, sea salt, black peppercorns, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/341640.xml">
coriander</link> seeds and parsley. Another version includes garlic. The plain version is dried whereas the one containing garlic is to be consumed fresh. It is short and thick in shape and can be eaten grilled, fried, stewed, steamed or even raw when freshly made. More recently a 'tal-barbikju' (lit. for the barbecuqe) variety has become popular. This variety is essentially the same as the original but with a much reduced salt content, and has a thinner skin. As its name implies, this variety is primarily targeted for cooking over a barbecue.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Fish</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Malta_Food_Rizzi.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Fresh Sea Urchin Roe, a prized delicacy, on toasted Gozo bread
</caption>
</image>

Fish is much eaten on the two islands and Maltese know from experience which fish is best baked, which poached, which grilled and which fried. Fish is often cooked and seasoned very simply but it may also be stuffed, stewed or made into pies. Many shellfish and crustaceans are also available and very popular.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Lampuka (Mahi Mahi or Dolphin Fish)</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/6541199.xml">
Lampuki</link> are perhaps Malta's favourite fish. Better known outside of Malta as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/211280.xml">
Mahi-mahi</link>, dorado, or dolphin fish, the Lampuka has fine, white flesh with only a few large bones, and is found in abundance in the seas between Sicily and Tunisia. </p>
<p>

It man be poached (<it>ghad-dobbu</it>) with rosemary and red wine; lightly pan-fried in olive oil and finished with garlic and vinegar or lemon juice and marjoram; it may be oven-baked in white wine and olive oil with tomatoes, onions, olives and capers or grilled and served with <link>
Zalza Pikkanti</link> or cut into small filleted pieces and deep fried; best of all for many of Maltese it may be made into a surprsing fish pie of many flavours with spinach or cauliflower, walnuts or chestnuts, capers, sultanas, hard-boiled eggs, herbs, and lemon zest, all enclosed in a shortcrust pastry.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Stuffat tal-Qarnit (Slow braised Octopus)</st>
<p>

Octopus, onions, tomato paste, olives, peas, bay leaves, walnuts and raisins slowly simmered in red wine. Many family variations exist: in one it is simmered in red wine, olives, tomatoes, black pepper and mint, in another with peas, tomatoes, lemon or orange zest, a bay leaf and a hint of curry powder. May be used as a sauce for pasta or served accompanied by Maltese bread.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Stuffat tal-Bakkaljaw (Salt Cod Stew)</st>
<p>

Previously soaked salt cod simmered with chunks of potatoes and diced carrots, as well as onions, garlic, tomatoes, salted anchovies, raisins and nutmeg. The recipe may be changed according to the availability of seasonal vegetables. A winter version has pumpkin chunks and cauliflower florets and black olives along with the potatoes, onions and tomatoes and bay leaf and thyme are used for flavouring.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><image width="150px" src="Malta_Octopus.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Octopus cooked in its own liquid with parsley, garlic and lemon
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Sawrell Mimli l-forn (Baked Stuffed Mackerel)</st>
<p>

Filled with a mixture of breadcrumbs, olives, salted anchovies and parsley and baked between layers of potatoes, onions and tomatoes sprinkled with salt and pepper, fresh marjoram leaves and olive oil.</p>


</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Klamari Mimili fl-inbid (Red wine braised stuffed calamari)</st>
<p>
 
The filling is made of breadcrumbs, parsley, garlic and capers with sometimes a slice of hard boiled egg in the middle. The filled calamari are then gently stewed in red wine with sultanas and nutmeg. Usually served with boiled potatoes dressed with olive oil and chopped parsley.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Braġjoli tat-tonn (Fresh tuna roll-ups)</st>
<p>

Thin slices of fresh tuna (or other large fish like <it>Aċċola</it> (amberjack), <it>Denċi</it> (a large pink sea bream), <it>Ċerna</it> (grouper) or <it>Pixxispad</it> (swordfish) are rolled around a filling of breadcrumbs, mint or marjoram, capers, olives, salted anchovy fillets and chopped hard boiled egg. The rolls are browned then briefly and very gently simmered in garlic scented olive oil deglazed with a little vinegar.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Pixxispad Mixwi Mħawwar(Grilled sword fish steaks with fresh herb topping)</st>
<p>

Thick swordfish steaks are grilled on gentle heat and when just done they are topped with a mixture of chopped fresh herbs, lemon zest, capers and olives and drizzled with olive oil. Grilled fish is usually served with a crisp fresh salad or else with <it>kapunata</it>.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Eggs and Cheese</st>


<ss2>
<st>
<link>
Ġbejniet</link> (<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/205475.xml">
Gozo</link></village>
 cheeselets)<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aboutmalta.com/gozo/folklore3.html">
http://aboutmalta.com/gozo/folklore3.html</weblink></st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Malta_Gbejniet.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Selection of fresh and cured Ġbejniet
</caption>
</image>

These are small, round cheeses, made from sheep or sometimes goat milk milk, often served as part of a light lunch, or as part of a hearty dinner. These cheeselets come in four  varieties, fresh (f<it>riski or tal-ilma</it>), sun dried (<it>moxxi</it>), salt cured (<it>maħsula</it>) or peppered (<it>tal-bżar</it>). The fresh variety have a smooth texture and a subtle, milky creamy flavour and are kept in their own whey in a similar manner to fresh <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/20632.xml">
Mozzarella</link>. The sundried variety have a more definite, nutty almost musky, taste, and are fairly hard, but can keep for a long time without refrigeration. The pepper cured variety are covered in crushed black pepper and cured, after which they may be stored in oil, ot sometimes pickled with the addition of vinegar. These last are the tastiest. and their sharp taste becomes more piquant the more they age. They also they develop a lovely crumbly texture. The dried varieties are traditionally served with Galletti an ancient local type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/368393.xml">
ship's biscuit</link> and a glass of robust red wine.</p>
<p>

<b>'Ġbejniet<it> are often referred to as a goat cheese, as indeed they originally were, though today these are almost always made from sheep milk. In the early 20th Century using unpasteurised milk led to an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/425881.xml">
Undulant Fever</link> epidemic in the Maltese islands . Undulant fever is also referred to as the Maltese Fever since the link between the illness and unpasteurised milk  was identified by the eminent Maltese doctor, archaeologist and scholar Sir <link>
 Temi Zammit</link>. Today thanks to a strict regime of certification of milk animals and widespread use of pasturisation the illness is completely eliminated from the islands and Ġbejniet are not only completely safe to eat, they are a widely used and much appreciated local speciality. Still most Maltese much prefer the tastier unpasteurised artisan-farmer prouced cheeselets to the mass produced vacuum-sealed version! See below: </it></b></p>
<p>

The widespread belief that<it> Ġbejniet</it> made from pasturised milk are less tasty than those made from unpasturised milk has never been corroborated by scientific evidence. Still, mass produced <it>Ġbejniet</it>, made exclusively from pasturised milk, tend to be less tasty than those produced by the cottage industry that makes use of certified but unpasturised milk.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Balbuljata or Barbuljata (Scrambled egg dish) </st>
<p>

Eggs scrambled with tomatoes, onions,fresh herbs, corned beef (another British legacy) and grated cheese. There are also versions using broad beans or gbejniet instead of the corned beef or simply omitting it. Traditionally the grated cheese was an imported peppercorn studded sharp <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/278505.xml">
Pecorino</link> known as <it>ġobon tal-bżar</it> or more recently a <link>
Cheddar cheese </link>, though <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/304667.xml">
Parmigiano Reggiano</link> is used these days.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Torta ta L-Irkotta (Fresh ricotta and parsley pie)</st>
<p>

Open faced or closed short crust pastry pie with local artisan sheep's milk ricotta, a sharp grated cheese and chopped fresh parsley bound with eggs.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Froġa bil-ful u l-ġbejniet friski (Eggs with fresh broad beans and fresh local cheeselets)</st>
<p>

The beaten eggs are mixed with shelled broad beans and mint and the finished omelette is topped with fresh <it>ġbejna</it> slices which melt on the omelette. </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Froġa tat-tarja or Tarja bil-bajd (Pasta "omelette" in Spanish <link>
 Tortilla</link> style)</st>
<p>

Angel's hair pasta cooked and tossed in cheese and butter, is mixed with eggs and shallow fried into a crisp coated two inch high savoury "cake".</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Froġa bil-laħam (Potato and meat "omelette")</st>
<p>

Made with mashed potato mixed with small pieces of finely chopped cooked beef and green fresh onion tops bound with eggs and grated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/6427.xml">
Cheddar</link> cheese. The thrifty Maltese way of making a tasty nutritious meal while making a little left over cooked meat go a long way.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Vegetables</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Vegetables_Malta.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Late summer cold vegetable dishes from Malta
</caption>
</image>

Vegetables are a mainstay of Maltese cuisine. Thye are used stuffed or made into stews or they may be made into soups, fritters and pies. </p>

<ss2>
<st>
Ful bit-tewm (Beans with mint and garlic)</st>
<p>

Dried broad beans are soaked overnight and then cooked with garlic and fresh or dried mint. Dressed with oil and vinegar this dish usually accompanies fish dishes.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Patata l-Forn (Maltese Style Baked Potatoes)</st>
<p>

Layers of medium thick potato rounds are placed on a bed of medium thick slces of onions, seasoned with salt, pepper and anis seeds or caraway or more rarely dried thyme (sagħtar), and almost covered in a half/half mixture of olive oil and water. Roast meats or game birds or meat stuffed vegetables like aubergine (see below) are usually cooked on top of these potatoes. The potatoes on top get a chewy dark skin while those submerged are meltingly tender - everyone has a preference for "uncovered" or "covered" baked potatoes</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Kapunata (Summer Vegetable Medley)</st>
<p>

A summer dish of pan braised tomatoes, capers, aubergines and green peppers, often served as a side dish for grilled or fried fish, or cold on its own as a savoury summer's lunch. Used also on pizza or pasta or on Maltese bread as a snack, or mixed with cold long grain rice and topped with canned tuna or hard-boiled eggs for summer rice salad. <it>Kapunata</it> is best home-made - traditionally large bowls of it were ever present in the fridge through the hot summer months.  A relative of Sicilian <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/7633637.xml">
caponata</link> which also includes celery, pine nuts and raisins and uses tomato paste instead of fresh tomatoes.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Haxix Mimli (Stuffed Vegetables)</st>
<p>

A rich chapter in Maltese cuisine. The fillings for cabbage leaves, small courgettes (zucchini or marrows), artichokes, the two varieities of gourds used in Malta (<it>qargħa twil</it> and <it>ċentinarja</it> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/1415333.xml">
chayote</link>), potatoes, onions, curly endive, tomatoes, aubergines (eggplants) and green bell peppers range from ricotta, herbs and cheese, to ground beef with bacon, cheese, and parsley, to rice with cheese, garlic and olives, to fresh or canned fish like <it>lampuki</it> or tuna and to breadcrumb based fillings with cheese, olives and/or capers and anchovy or garlic. These may constitute a one course meal. More below!</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Qargħa Bagħli Mimli (Stuffed round small marrows or long pale green gourds)</st>
<p>

Round pale green zucchini or courgettes, particularly delicious stuffed with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/574518.xml">
minced beef</link>, cheese and parsley or with ricotta and grated sharp cheese. The stuffed vegetable is subsequently baked or braised in tomato sauce or else cooked in chicken or meat broth. Sliced rounds may also be fried, and served hot or cold, or the marrows may be made into a creamy soup. They can also be made into fritters or fried vegetarian rissoles or patties. The long smooth skinned pale green gourd (<it>Qargħa Twil</it>) can be cooked in similar ways.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Brunġiel or Brinġiel Mimli (Baked Stuffed Aubergines)</st>
<p>

The aubergines are halved and some of the flesh scopped out leaving a shell. The pulp is cooked with ground beef, tomato paste, garlic  and onions and mixed when cool with egg and cheese. The shells are filled with this mix and topped with breadcrumbs mixed with grated cheese, dotted with butter and baked till crisp and crusty on top. May be baked alone but usually cooked on a bed of Maltese style baked potatoes as above.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ħass, ful u piżelli (Braised lettuce, fresh broad beans and peas)</st>
<p>

A spring dish of the above vegetables braised in olive oil with green onion or young leek tops. Nice paired up with juicy slices of the locally produced delicacy, cooked ham on the bone called <it>perżut tal-għadma</it>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Stuffat tal-Qargħa Ħamra (Pumpkin Stew)</st>
<p>

Sliced or diced orange flesh pumpkin cooked with onions, garlic, sultanas and mint, usually served with rice.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sauces</st>

<p>

The word <it>zalza</it> usually denotes a sauce meant for use as a dressing for pasta, thus <it>zalza tat-taddam</it> (tomato sauce), <it>tal-perżut</it> (with cooked ham on the bone), <it>tal-bringiel</it> (aubergine pasta sauce), <it>tal-klamari</it> (a pasta sauce with calamari), though each has many variations according to family traditions. 
Sauces in the generally understood sense are few, the following are very popular:</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Zalza Pikkanti (Bell pepper and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/309317.xml">
caper</link> sauce)</st>
<p>
 
Vinegar sharpened stewed bell peppers with tomato paste, garlic and mint or marjoram, sometimes also black or green olives, capers and softened onions, most often used with fish. </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Zalza tal-Kappar (Caper sauce)</st>
<p>
 
Capers, olives, parsley and mint, with or without stewed fresh tomatoes, onions and tomato paste. Good with grilled fish like swordfish steaks.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Zalza Ħadra (Green Sauce)</st>
<p>

Very green sauce of  parsley, fresh breadcrumbs, garlic and filleted salted anchovies with either vinegar or lemon juice</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ajjoli (Garlic Sauce)</st>
<p>

At least two versions exist. One is made by pounding softened  <link>
 Maltese Galletti</link>, with basil, mint, parsley, garlic, capers, olives and anchovy fillets and diluting with oil, the other is made by mixing chopped fresh tomato pulp with large amounts of garlic, parsley and fresh or dried mint and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link>. Most commonly used as dip or sauce for snails or to accompany shellfish or octopus.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sweet and Savoury Pastries</st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Malta_pie_qassata.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Home made Spinach and Pea Qassata with salted tuna, anchovies and herbs
</caption>
</image>

</p>
<ss2>
<st>
Imqaret (Deep fried diamond shaped pastry)</st>
<p>

Date-filled orange flower scented, deep-fried pastries which are served piping hot at home or from street vendors.  Look out for them at <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/2058058.xml">
City Gate, Valletta</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
. Some restaurants also offer them as desserts on their menu. Similar to Morrocan ("makroudh", which is the singular form of the name meaning "rhombus" or diamond shape).The <it>Maqrut</it> (plural <it>Imqaret</it>) was chosen as the Maltese representative for <link>
Café Europe</link> during the Austrian Presidency of the  <economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../317/9317.xml">
European Union</link></economy>
 in 2006.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Kannoli (Cheese or cream filled pastry)</st>
<p>

A tube-shaped confectionery of deep-fried crisp pastry filled with fresh <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/708679.xml">
ricotta</link> sweetened with pieces of chocolate and candied fruit.  Eaten as a treat any time of day, and also offered after dinner. The candied fruit included in this snack, is also often used in a delicious type of colourful <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/344611.xml">
nougat</link>. Very similar to Sicilian cannoli, not surprising since Malta was effectively part of Sicily from 1090 to 1530.</p>
<p>

Not the same as "Kannoli tal-Krema" where fresh whipped cream replaces the ricotta and puff or flaky pastry forms the tube. </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ftita Tar-Randan (Gozo deep fried pastry squares)</st>
<p>

Unconnected with the small loaf of the same name, these honey drizzled squares of crisp deep fried pastry where a  supper dish for the <fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<time wordnetid="115122231" confidence="0.8">
<festival wordnetid="115162388" confidence="0.8">
<day wordnetid="115123115" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/39726.xml">
Lent</link></day>
</festival>
</time>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
 or Randan period when animal fats and meat were not allowed and many people also avoided eggs and cheese.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Sfineġ (Deep fried pastry puffs)</st>
<p>

Once sold by street hawkers on cold rainy days, these squares of crisp pastry filled with small pieces of salt cod or anchovy, must be eaten hot. A similar dish called "Sfinja" (the Maltese singular is <it>sfinġa</it>) is found in Tunisia, but there the pastry circles are usually filled with egg or else left unfilled. A dish believed to have originated in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/2736.xml">
Andalucia</link>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../588/4258588.xml">
Pastizzi</link> (Ricotta or pea filled savoury pasties)</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Malta_Pastizzi.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

The two kinds of Pastizzi
</caption>
</image>

A popular snack for all Islanders, found at pastizzerias and most bars, pizzerias, and some restaurants and bakeries. Pastizzi are small, diamond-shaped or shell shaped packets of multi layered crips pastry stuffed with either fresh ricotta or with a mushy split pea mixture which is sometimes slightly spicy. The pastry used is similar to that of the Neapolitan sweet pastry <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/3366711.xml">
Sfogliatelle</link>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Qassatat (Round pastries with anchovy, ricotta or other fillings)</st>
<p>

Considered a "less messy" alternative to pastizzi because it is made with shortcrust pastry, traditionally filled with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/708679.xml">
ricotta</link>, peas, or spinach and anchovy. Alternative traditional fillings include pumpkin with rice and tuna or black olives, and <it>Ġbejniet</it> with fresh broad beans at Easter time.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Bread</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Ħobża tal-Malti (Maltese bread)</st>
<p>

A very crusty <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/189345.xml">
sourdough</link> bread loaf with a deliciously soft inside which is the mainstay of a meal. It is a snack in itself served with simple local produce like fresh tomatoes or kunserva (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/1073960.xml">
tomato paste</link>), and ġbejniet. This type of bread proves extremely popular: most households have a loaf delivered daily including Sundays, while tourists specifically request it wherever they eat. There is also a low rise, less crusty and more compact bread called <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://i23.photobucket.com/albums/b365/greenrover/ftira.jpg">
http://i23.photobucket.com/albums/b365/greenrover/ftira.jpg</weblink> <it>Ftira</it>. Maltese bread is best eaten fresh but cooled off, as it loses most of its taste and crunchiness within a day. Even so, some people prefer to eat when it is straight out of the oven.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ħobż biż-żejt u it-tadam (Malta's favourite sandwich)</st>
<p>

Two slices of crusty Maltese bread, or sometimes a very small whole loaf are rubbed generously with a juicy ripe (large, flat and multi-segmente) local tomato cut in half, then drenched in olive oil, seasoned with salt and Malta ground black pepper and filled with one or more of the following items: canned flaked tuna, thinly sliced fresh onion, olives,  basil, salted anchovy fillets, tiny Malta capers, fresh mint, sliced hard boiled egg, lettuce, small pickled vegetables, white beans, pickled onions. A truly memorably delicious and healthy meal in itself. Traditionally a portable lunch for shepherds and fishermen, it is today mainly eaten as on its own as a healthy snack, though restaurants may serve small pieces as a starter. Reminescent of Nice's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/5696381.xml">
Pan-bagnat</link> and of Catalan <link>
Pa amb tomàquet</link>. In winter tomato paste or sun  dried tomatoes, home made or shop bought, replace the fresh tomato rub.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Galletti (<link>
Ship's Biscuits</link>) </st>
<p>

Round hard dry white savoury biscuits <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medinaproject.net/malta/pages/poc.php?ID_AxisName=4&amp;ID_POC=292&amp;ID_Lang=1">
http://www.medinaproject.net/malta/pages/poc.php?ID_AxisName=4&amp;ID_POC=292&amp;ID_Lang=1</weblink>rarely home made today but available commercially in smaller and larger versions. Frequently accommpany pre-meal nibbles and dips like Bigilla. May be soaked to soften and used as a base for fish and vegetables or added to soups. Genoa and Naples have similar biscuits called "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/7633637.xml">
Gallette</link>".</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ftira (Another Maltese Bread) [http://www.medinaproject.net/malta/pages/poc.php?ID_POC=273&amp;ID_Lang=</st>
<p>
==
<image width="150px" src="Malta_ftira.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A fresh Ftira
</caption>
</image>

<it>Ftira</it> is a low rise, ring shaped, small and less crusty loaf. It is also delicious filled as for <it>Ħobż biż-Zejt</it>. In Gozo, ftira filled with sardines or anchovies was a typical supper snack during Lent fast days, when eating meat was not allowed.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ftira Għawdxija (<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/205475.xml">
Gozo</link></village>
 Ftira) </st>
<p>

Gozo bakeries cook the Ftira dough as a round flat bread which may be closed or open. The closed Gozo<it> ftira</it> enclosed a filling and was intended to serve as a workman's lunch. Toppings and fillings usually have potatoes and /or <it>ġbjeniet</it> for example:<it> ġbjeniet</it>, eggs and grated cheese; potatoes, tomato, anchovies and olive; or ricotta topped with slices of potato; or sliced potato, Maltese Sausage, <it>ġbjeniet</it> and rosemary. Among many others! <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medinaproject.net/malta/pages/poc.php?ID_AxisName=4&amp;ID_POC=274&amp;ID_Lang=1">
http://www.medinaproject.net/malta/pages/poc.php?ID_AxisName=4&amp;ID_POC=274&amp;ID_Lang=1</weblink></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sweets</st>


<ss2>
<st>
Torta tat-Tamal (Date and Cocoa Tart) </st>
<p>

Anise perfumed open <link>
 date</link> tart with cocoa, chopped walnuts, orange juice and orange zest</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Torta tal Marmorat (Almond, Candied fruit and Chocolate pie) </st>
<p>

Lattice topped or closed pie with a filling of ground almonds, chopped candied citrus peel and grated dark chocolate scented with cinnamon</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Sinizza (Ricotta and candied fruit sweet) </st>
<p>

Flaky pastry or sometimes sponge cake with a ricotta, candied peel and glacé cherry filling  rolled up like a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../683/1935683.xml">
swiss roll</link>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Figolla (Easter shaped pastry sweet)</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Heart_figolla.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A typical heart-shaped figolla.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

This dish is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/9325.xml">
Easter</link>-time favourite. It is a book-sized golden, icing-coated biscuit stuffed with a mixture of sweet ground almonds (called <it>intrita</it>). Found in various shapes. The most traditional shapes are those of a boy , a girl and a basket of eggs, which are ancient symbols of fertility, and those of a lamb and that of a fish, symbols of the Christian religion. Other common shapes are Hearts, Ducks and Mermaids, and more recently Cars, Rabbits (<tradition wordnetid="105809745" confidence="0.8">
<fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.8">
<imaginary_being wordnetid="109483738" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../125/47125.xml">
Easter Bunny</link></imaginary_being>
</fictional_character>
</tradition>
) and many more shapes that might appeal to children. </p>
<p>

Here is a good traditional <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thehealthyrecipes.com/figolli.php">
figolli recipe</weblink></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ħelwa tat-Tork (Turk's sweet)</st>
<p>

This is locally made <course wordnetid="107556970" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<nutriment wordnetid="107570720" confidence="0.8">
<dessert wordnetid="107609840" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/182802.xml">
Halva</link></dessert>
</nutriment>
</food>
</substance>
</course>
, made of ground sesame seeds and sugar and similar to the North African, Middle Eastern, Greek and Turkish varieties (hence the name). Traditionally containing crunchy whole almonds and some pistachios, an unfortunate modern version now also contains chocolate. </p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Kwareżimal (Lenten sweets)</st>
<p>

<it>Kwareżimal</it> is an almond biscuit scented with the zest of ornage, lemon and tangerine, scented with cinnamon and orange blossom water traditionally eaten during <fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<time wordnetid="115122231" confidence="0.8">
<festival wordnetid="115162388" confidence="0.8">
<day wordnetid="115123115" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/39726.xml">
Lent</link></day>
</festival>
</time>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
. The surface is drizzled with Malta honey and sprinkled with chopped pistachios. Similar sweets are also found in some areas of Sicily. </p>
<p>

Here is a good <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.thehealthyrecipes.com/kwarezimal.php">
Kwarezimal Recipe</weblink></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Pudina ta' l-Ħobż (Bread pudding)</st>
<p>

Sweet made from stale bread which is soaked in water overnight to re-moisten it, and then mixed with milk, cocoa, eggs sugar, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/546099.xml">
dried fruit</link> and nuts. Sometimes liqueurs such as anisette or sherry are added. Crunchy on top and  moist inside, it is commonly eaten all year round as a great way of using up bread. Traditionally it was made on Mondays so as not to waste the stale bread left over from the weekend</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Qagħaq ta' l-Għasel or tal-Qastanija (Treacle ring shaped pastries)</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="QaghaqtalGhasel.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Qagħaq ta' l-Għasel from <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/64646.xml">
Toronto</link></village>
's Malta Village
</caption>
</image>

Treacle rings made from a light pastry with a filling made of treacle, semolina, citurs zest, cinnamon and cloves. Those who kept bees made used the honey comb for the filling though the forgotten full name in Maltese - Qagħaq ta'l-Għasel -Iswed - makes it clear they were based on treacle not honey. Today often served in small pieces as an after-dinner accompaniment to coffee.  Originally a Christmas delicacy but you’ll find them in most confectioneries all year round.
<image location="right" width="150px" src="Qaghaq_tal-hmira.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Qaghaq tal-Hmira
</caption>
</image>
</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Prinjolata (Easter Pine Nut Sweet ) [http://www.medinaproject.net/malta/pages/poc.php?ID_POC=317&amp;ID_Lang=1</st>
<p>
==
A white dome or pyramid shaped <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/38483.xml">
Carnival</link> sweet of layered sponge fingers or sponge cake and a soft meringue, butter cream and pine nut mixture, decorated with glacè cherries, more nuts and dribbles of melted chocolate. Sometimes sliced almonds are used in place of the pine nuts for which the sweet is named (from Italian "pinoli".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Snacks</st>


<ss2>
<st>
Seeds and Nuts</st>
<p>

Salted savoury nibbles like dried pumpkin and melon seeds, crisp fried dried broad beans and dry roasted peanuts called <it>Karawett Inkaljat</it> are served to accompany a glass of wine or beer.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Karamelli tal-Ħarrub</st>
<p>

Artisan hard sqaure candies wrapped in greaseproof paper made from the fruit of the <link>
Carob</link>  tree. Traditionally sold by street hawkers, now mostly available only at village festas.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ciċri</st>
<p>

Street hawkers used to sell fresh green chickpeas still on their leafy branches as late as the early 1960s, alas the fresh legume is now hard to find on the islands.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Twistees</st>
<p>

Twistees <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.maltaproducts.com/food_and_consumables/malta_sweets/twistees.html"></weblink>are a popular Maltese baked crisp savoury snack popular since the 1960s/70s. They are produced in Malta and are made from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/36979.xml">
rice</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/10087528.xml">
corn</link> grits. </p>
<p>

Although the most popular flavour by far is "<it>Cheesy</it>" flavour, they are also available in chicken flavour, as well as in bacon flavour under the name of "Tastees" , the name chosen for the UK version. It was their popularity among British tourists who travel to Malta and the Maltese community in the UK which led to Twistees being successfully launched <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.maltamedia.com/artman2/publish/local/article_4784.shtml">
http://www.maltamedia.com/artman2/publish/local/article_4784.shtml</weblink> into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1048927.xml">
UK</link> market in 2008 as "Tastees" <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tastees.info"></weblink> . </p>
<p>

In September 2007 the manufacturers launched <it>Twistees Lite</it>, the new "<it>Low Fat - Low Salt</it>" version of Twistees.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.strand.com.mt/">
http://www.strand.com.mt/</weblink></p>
<p>

Australian <substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/2024123.xml">
Twisties</link></food>
</substance>
 are similar to Malta's Twistees.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Beverages</st>


<ss1>
<st>
Ġulepp tal-Ħarrub (<link>
Carob</link> Syrup)</st>
<p>

Considered to be very soothing for coughs and sore throats, this is also used drizzled on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/708679.xml">
ricotta</link>, ice cream or fresh fruit.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Imbuljuta (Chestnut and Cocoa Drink)</st>
<p>

Traditional homemade drink of sweetened pureed chestnuts with cocoa, tangerine zest, cinnamon and cloves, normally drunk hot but can also be served cold.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Ruġġata</st>
<p>

Long drink made by diluting concentrated almond "milk" or syrup with cold water, very refreshing in hot weather.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Flip</st>
<p>

Sugar, milk and raw egg, considered a very nourishing drink for a growing child.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Kafé biz-zokk</st>
<p>

Coffee scented with a piece of stick cinnamon. Other spices like cloves and anis seeds are used singly or together to flavour <it>Kafé Msajjar</it> or "cooked" coffee, which may also be perfumed with orange blossom water or chicory.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Soft Drinks</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Kinnie</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Kinnie.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A can and glass of Kinnie.
</caption>
</image>

<beverage wordnetid="107881800" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/511698.xml">
Kinnie</link></beverage>
 is a <link>
non-alcoholic</link>, mildy and pleasantly bitter soft drink that is very refreshing. Made from  a citrus fruit called Chino (pronounced Keen-oh) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/281028.xml">
aromatic herb</link>s, it is <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/5100543.xml">
caramel</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
 in colour.  Since 1984, a diet version (<it>Diet Kinnie</it>) has been available. In 1975, Kinnie was selected <it>beverage of the year</it> by the French organization <it>Comité International d'Action Gastronomique et Touristique</it>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Krest</st>
<p>

<beverage wordnetid="107881800" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/13132351.xml">
Krest</link></beverage>
 is a similar soft drink to Kinnie manufactured by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/914869.xml">
Coca Cola Company</link>. It was introduced in 1997 in regular and diet versions.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Swish</st>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/2019638.xml">
Swish</link> is a soft drink similar to Sprite and 7 up.It's taste is a little lighter that of sprite and 
7 up. A diet version was also released.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://maltavoyager.com/features.html">
Maltese recipes</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References  </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Darmanin, Francis. A Guide To Maltese Cooking.&#32;Malta:&#32;Jumbo Productions,&#32;14. ISBN 99909-79-00-6.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
Fort, Matthew <it>Eating Up Italy: Voyages on a Vespa</it> Harper Perennial, 2005, p253-254. ISBN 0-00-721481-2 </entry>
<entry id="3">
 Caruana Galizia, Anne and Helen <it>The Food and Cookery of Malta</it>, Pax Books, London, 2001</entry>
<entry id="4">
 Darmanin, Francis  <it>A Guide To Maltese Cooking.</it> Malta: Jumbo Productions, ISBN 99909-79-00-6.</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite id="Reference-Rizzo Naudi-2005" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Rizzo Naudi, John&#32;(2005). Brucellosis, The Malta Experience.&#32;Malta:&#32;Publishers Enterprises group (PEG) Ltd.. ISBN 99909-0-425-1.</cite>&nbsp;
</entry>
<entry id="6">
Vella, Marie <it> Cooking the Maltese Way</it>  2nd Edition  published in Valletta Malta by Cordina's Emporium</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wikibooks-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wikibooks
</caption>
</image>

Wikibooks'  has more about this subject:
</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/6656.xml">
Cuisine</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
Regional</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/1769393.xml">
Africa</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/294770.xml">
Asia</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/6672.xml">
Caribbean</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/524762.xml">
Europe</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/524651.xml">
Latin America</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/1342098.xml">
Mediterranean</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/887712.xml">
Middle East</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/1278184.xml">
North America</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/19525592.xml">
Oceania</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/2687330.xml">
South Asia</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
Styles</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/334079.xml">
Haute</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/13684751.xml">
Immigrant</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/11304.xml">
Fusion</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/360101.xml">
Fast food</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/10646.xml">
Food</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/36969.xml">
Bread</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/23871.xml">
Pasta</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/11749910.xml">
Cheese</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/36979.xml">
Rice</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../937/61937.xml">
Sauce</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/19651298.xml">
Soup</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/7976.xml">
Dessert</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/13296.xml">
Herb</link>s&nbsp;· <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/26897.xml">
Spice</link>s&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../760/44760.xml">
Confectionery</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
Technical</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/5355.xml">
Techniques</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/496929.xml">
Utensils</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../866/52866.xml">
Weights and measures</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
See also</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/49404.xml">
Kitchen</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../018/80018.xml">
Meal</link>&nbsp;·  </col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/524762.xml">
Cuisine of Europe</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/68253.xml">
Sovereign
states</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/333059.xml">
Albania</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Andorra</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/6582433.xml">
Armenia</link>1&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../319/592319.xml">
Austria</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/12835793.xml">
Azerbaijan</link>2&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/3587279.xml">
Belarus</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/211974.xml">
Belgium</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5668862.xml">
Bosnia and Herzegovina</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/1856141.xml">
Bulgaria</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/1485631.xml">
Croatia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/2582022.xml">
Cyprus</link>1&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../557/2807557.xml">
Czech Republic</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/488597.xml">
Denmark</link>4&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/12843748.xml">
Estonia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/215429.xml">
Finland</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/11002.xml">
France</link>4, 5, 6&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/10120183.xml">
Georgia</link>2&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../485/12485.xml">
Germany</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/12486.xml">
Greece</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../565/176565.xml">
Hungary</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/5642461.xml">
Iceland</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/918678.xml">
Republic of Ireland</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/3735620.xml">
Italy</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/4244845.xml">
Kazakhstan</link>3&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/1393340.xml">
Latvia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Liechtenstein</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/948976.xml">
Lithuania</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/9345617.xml">
Luxembourg</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/5066340.xml">
Republic of Macedonia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/885371.xml">
Malta</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/14163662.xml">
Moldova</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Monaco</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/4635280.xml">
Montenegro</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../733/918733.xml">
Netherlands</link>4&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/2215144.xml">
Norway</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/418713.xml">
Poland</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/918711.xml">
Portugal</link>6&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/1245931.xml">
Romania</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/644135.xml">
Russia</link>3&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/12844110.xml">
San Marino</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/2015602.xml">
Serbia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/1834468.xml">
Slovakia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/5408329.xml">
Slovenia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/27669.xml">
Spain</link>6&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/28490.xml">
Sweden</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/851627.xml">
Switzerland</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/31427.xml">
Turkey</link>3&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/995498.xml">
Ukraine</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/7896915.xml">
United Kingdom</link>&nbsp;(<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/77208.xml">
England</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/918678.xml">
Northern Ireland</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/6169255.xml">
Scotland</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../591/2185591.xml">
Wales</link>)</p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";padding:0.35em 1.0em; line-height:1.1em;;" class="navbox-group">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/214529.xml">
Dependencies</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
,
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../026/1636026.xml">
autonomies</link>,other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/6450815.xml">
territories</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<p>

<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/10120183.xml">
Abkhazia</link></it>&nbsp;2&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/10120183.xml">
Adjara</link>1&nbsp;· 
<link>
Adygea</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/2582022.xml">
Akrotiri and Dhekelia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Åland</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/918711.xml">
Azores</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Bashkortostan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Chechnya</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Chuvashia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/995498.xml">
Crimea</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Dagestan</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/488597.xml">
Faroe Islands</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Gagauzia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/13552894.xml">
Gibraltar</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/7896915.xml">
Guernsey</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Ingushetia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/2215144.xml">
Jan Mayen</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/7896915.xml">
Jersey</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Kabardino-Balkaria</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Kalmykia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Karachay-Cherkessia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Republic of Karelia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Komi Republic</link>&nbsp;· 
<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/2015602.xml">
Kosovo</link></it>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/918711.xml">
Madeira</link>7&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/7896915.xml">
Isle of Man</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Mari El</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Mordovia</link>&nbsp;· 
<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/6582433.xml">
Nagorno-Karabakh</link></it>1&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/12835793.xml">
Nakhchivan</link>1&nbsp;· 
<link>
North Ossetia-Alania</link>&nbsp;· 
<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../460/12844460.xml">
Northern Cyprus</link></it>1&nbsp;· 
<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/10120183.xml">
South Ossetia</link></it>&nbsp;2&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../144/2215144.xml">
Svalbard</link>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Tatarstan</link>&nbsp;· 
<it><link>
Transnistria</link></it>&nbsp;· 
<link>
Udmurtia</link>&nbsp;· 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/2015602.xml">
Vojvodina</link></p>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";padding:0.4em 0.2em 0.2em; line-height:1.4em; font-size:95%;" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<it>Italics</it> indicates an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../670/523670.xml">
unrecognised or partially recognised country</link>.&nbsp; 
1&nbsp;/ 7 Entirely in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/689.xml">
Asia</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
&nbsp;/ on the <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<sports_equipment wordnetid="104285146" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<home_plate wordnetid="103528901" confidence="0.8">
<base wordnetid="102797881" confidence="0.8">
<equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.8">
<baseball_equipment wordnetid="102799897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/521081.xml">
African Plate</link></baseball_equipment>
</equipment>
</base>
</home_plate>
</instrumentality>
</sports_equipment>
</artifact>
, but historically considered European.&nbsp; 2 Partially or entirely in Asia, depending on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/13973661.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Europe+and+Asia%22])">
border definitions</link>.&nbsp; 3 / 4 / 5 / 6 Has part of its territory in <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/689.xml">
Asia</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 / <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/21139.xml">
North America</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 / <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/26769.xml">
South America</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 / <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<see wordnetid="108586825" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/5334607.xml">
Africa</link></location>
</seat>
</see>
</area>
</center>
</region>
.</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/1342098.xml">
Cuisine of the</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../006/19006.xml">
Mediterranean</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/524762.xml">
Europe by state</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/333059.xml">
Albania</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/5668862.xml">
Bosnia and Herzegovina</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/1856141.xml">
Bulgaria</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/1485631.xml">
Croatia</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../022/2582022.xml">
Cyprus</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/13552894.xml">
Gibraltar</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../486/12486.xml">
Greece</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../620/3735620.xml">
Italy</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/5066340.xml">
Republic of Macedonia</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/885371.xml">
Malta</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/4635280.xml">
Montenegro</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/2015602.xml">
Serbia</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/5408329.xml">
Slovenia</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/27669.xml">
Spain</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/31427.xml">
Turkey</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/524762.xml">
Europe by culture</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/3777892.xml">
Andalusia</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/3789863.xml">
Balearics</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/71058.xml">
Catalonia</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/11002.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Corsica%22])">
Corsica</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/11002.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Roussillon+=E2=80=A2+Languedoc+=E2=80=A2+C=C3=A9vennes%22])">
Occitania</link>&nbsp;·  <link>
Sicily</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/3166349.xml">
Valencia</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../393/1769393.xml">
Africa by state</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/8559295.xml">
Egypt</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/3711181.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Food%22])">
Libya</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/19761.xml">
Morocco</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../659/14524659.xml">
Tunisia</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/294770.xml">
Middle East by state</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../433/6582433.xml">
Armenia</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/11447140.xml">
Israel</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../013/3548013.xml">
Lebanon</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/11146241.xml">
Palestine</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../682/11287682.xml">
Syria</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/294770.xml">
Middle East by culture</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;padding:0.25em 0; line-height:1.4em;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../043/2053043.xml">
Arab</link>&nbsp;·  <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<subject wordnetid="106599788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/9419058.xml">
Sephardic Jewish</link></subject>
</message>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>






</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
