<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:30:22[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>EcoCyc</title>
<id>8894085</id>
<revision>
<id>205940925</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-16T03:06:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Pkarp11</username>
<id>3236785</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Bioinformatics databases</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>EcoCyc</b> is a bioinformatics database for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/9028799.xml">
bacterium</link> <microorganism wordnetid="101326291" confidence="0.8">
<bacteria wordnetid="101348530" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/40114.xml">
Escherichia coli</link></bacteria>
</microorganism>
 K-12. The EcoCyc project performs literature-based curation of the <it>E. coli</it> genome, and of <it>E. coli</it> transcriptional regulation, transporters, and metabolic pathways.<p>

EcoCyc is a regularly updated electronic encyclopedia that contains written summaries of <it>E. coli</it> genes, distilled from more than 16,000 scientific articles. </p>
<p>

EcoCyc is also a computable description of the genome and cellular networks of <it>E. coli</it> that supports data mining and computational analyses.  </p>
<p>

Objects in the EcoCyc database describe each <it>E. coli</it> gene and gene product.  Database objects also describe molecular interactions, including metabolic pathways, transport events, and the regulation of gene expression.</p>
<p>

EcoCyc provides several genome-scale visualization tools to aid in the analysis
of omics data, such as by painting gene expression or metabolomics data onto
the full regulatory network of E. coli.</p>
<p>

EcoCyc can be accessed through the EcoCyc web site, as a set of downloadable files,
and in conjunction with the Pathway Tools software that can be installed locally
on Macintosh, PC/Windows, and PC/Linux computers.  The downloadable software
provides capabilities that go well beyond the web version of EcoCyc.</p>

<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ecocyc.org/">
EcoCyc</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.ai.sri.com/ptools/">
Pathway Tools</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
