<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:31:13[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Intelligent Collaboration Transparency</title>
<id>8923593</id>
<revision>
<id>224387910</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-08T17:07:49Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Mo-Al</username>
<id>214358</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Groupware</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Intelligent Collaboration Transparency</b> (ICT) is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/5472872.xml">
application sharing</link> framework for sharing familiar single-user tools (applications) for collaboration purposes without modifying their source code. At the user level, unmodified heterogeneous applications can be shared and interoperated. At the system level, the application sharing middleware is able to understand the behavior of the applications being shared. The main assumption underlying this work is that allowing collaborators to use familiar single-user tools for cooperative work can reduce development, deployment, and learning costs while improving individual and group productivity.
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

The project is led by Professor Du Li and started in 2001 at Texas A&amp;M university. Its first significant paper was published in the ACM <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/293991.xml">
CSCW</link> 2002 Conference. In the system prototype, heterogeneous single-user editors such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../287/20287.xml">
Microsoft Word</link></software>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/32478.xml">
GVim</link> were shared to edit the same document. As in early <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/5472872.xml">
application sharing</link> systems, generality of the technical approach was pursued at this stage. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/233488.xml">
machine learning</link> approach was explored to understand the editors' behavior such that window events can be translated between different editors for synchronization. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/8924002.xml">
Operational transformation</link> was used for optimistic concurrency control, which allows any user to edit any part of the shared document at any time. However, due to engineering difficulties in understanding application behavior from external, only a small subset of the original editor functionality is allowed.</p>
<p>

At a later stage (2004), a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/79673.xml">
diffing</link>-based approach was taken to specialize the framework in the domain of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/1518428.xml">
group editing</link>. The result was presented in an ACM <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/293991.xml">
CSCW</link> 2006 paper. The users are still allowed to edit a shared document concurrently with heterogeneous single-user editors without being constrained. A diff algorithm is called to derive edit scripts at each site. Concurrent edit scripts are merged on the fly to synchronize states of editors. As a result, users are not limited by editing commands that can be understood by the application sharing middleware. This implementation strategy significantly reduces engineering costs. In principle, any single-user editor can be shared with very little effort.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 A lightweight approach to transparent sharing of familiar single-user editors. Du Li and Jiajun Lu. ACM CSCW'06 Conference. Nov. 2006. Banff, Alberta, Canada.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Transparent Sharing and Interoperation of Heterogeneous Single-User Applications. Du Li and Rui Li. ACM CSCW'02 Conference. Nov 16-20, 2002. New Orleans, Louisiana, USA</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cocasoft.csdl.tamu.edu/~lidu/projects/ICT/">
Project website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
