<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:31:27[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<social_event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107288639">
<contest  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="107456188">
<game  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100456199">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<header>
<title>Sudden Attack</title>
<id>8933392</id>
<revision>
<id>243139559</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T09:28:46Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Wyatt Riot</username>
<id>935793</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Video games developed in Korea</category>
<category>Massively multiplayer online games</category>
<category>Articles for deletion</category>
<category>2005 video games</category>
<category>Windows games</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox VG</name>
<parameters>

<image width="200px" src="Suddenattacklogo.PNG">
</image>
<genre>
<genre wordnetid="105845332" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/11791.xml">
First-person shooter</link></kind>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</genre>
</genre>
<engine>
<software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/432891.xml">
Jupiter Game Engine</link></software>
</engine>
<designer>
GameHi</designer>
<platforms>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18457137.xml">
PC</link></platforms>
<requirements>
2 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/14121.xml">
GHz</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/5218.xml">
processor</link>, 512 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/19918.xml">
MB</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/25847.xml">
RAM</link>, 64MB <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/2646742.xml">
VRAM</link></requirements>
<publisher>
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/9624036.xml">
Netmarble</link></company>
 (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/18457137.xml">
PC</link>)</publisher>
<released>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/16179.xml">
July 21</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../984/35984.xml">
2005</link></released>
<input>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/18842281.xml">
Keyboard</link>, <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/7056.xml">
mouse</link></device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</input>
<title>
Sudden Attack</title>
<developer>
<image width="22x20px" src="Flag_of_South_Korea.svg">
<caption>

Flag of South Korea
</caption>
</image>
 GameHi</developer>
<modes>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../291/15079291.xml">
Multiplayer</link></modes>
<media>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/42295.xml">
Download</link></media>
<ratings>
15+ (no blood), 18+ (blood)</ratings>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-delete" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="border: none; padding: 0px; width: 1px;"></col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is being considered for deletion in accordance with Wikipedia's .</b>
Please share your thoughts on the matter at  on the  page.Feel free to edit the article, but the article <b>must not</b> be blanked, and this notice <b>must not</b> be removed, until the discussion is closed. For more information, particularly on merging or moving the article during the discussion, read the .
----<p>

<it>: 1. &#123;&#123;subst:afd&#125;&#125; &nbsp; 2. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Wikipedia:Articles_for_deletion/Sudden_Attack&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Template:Afd2+starter&amp;editintro=Template:Afd3+starter">
Preloaded debate</weblink> </it>OR<it> &#123;&#123;subst:afd2&#124;pg=Sudden Attack&#124;cat=&#124;text=&#125;&#125; &#126;&#126;&#126;&#126; (
AfD debates|categories) &nbsp; 3. &#123;&#123;subst:afd3&#124;pg=Sudden Attack&#125;&#125; (add to </it>'top<b> of <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Wikipedia:Articles_for_deletion/Log/2008_October_5&amp;action=edit">
 list</weblink>) &nbsp; 4. Please consider notifying the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Sudden_Attack&amp;action=history">
author(s)</weblink> by placing &#123;&#123;subst:adw&#124;Sudden Attack&#125;&#125; &#126;&#126;&#126;&#126; on their talk page(s).<it>
----
Unregistered users placing this tag on an article cannot complete the deletion nomination and should leave detailed reasons for deletion on . If the nomination is not completed and no message is left on the talkpage, this tag </it></b><it>may be removed</it>'.</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>




<p>

<b><it>Sudden Attack</it></b> (<W wordnetid="106833544" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../451/14451.xml">
Korean</link></W>
: 서든어택) is a free Korean <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../401/69401.xml">
first-person shooter</link> game developed by GameHi. Anyone 15 or older with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/27019.xml">
South Korean</link> citizenship registration number can create an account on <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../036/9624036.xml">
Netmarble</link></company>
 and play.</p>
<p>

=Story=</p>
<p>

In the year 2017 a SA policeman is guided to protect a laboratory. He then sees a top secret file about the United Great Force's nuclear attack on the general population scheduled for 2019. He then is spotted. All the SA soldiers confront him but he fights back and manages to escape. He told everyone and the evidence of it. Then a group of former SA soldiers calling themselves the Tanziriro Independence Force fight the SA at South Water Defense Port. Hearing about this, people started to join them. Now they have a large army fight for control before the SA launch the nuclear assault.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Gameplay</st>

<p>

There are two teams in the game, red and blue. Red is the Tanziriro Independence Force (Silent Fox corps) while blue is the United Great Force (SA Anti-terrorist Police) The weapon configuration is as follows: primary weapon, secondary weapon, knife, grenade, bomb defusal kit.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Clan Match</st>

<p>

In order for any player to create a clan, he or she must be at least 18 years of age, which is determined through the ID of the player and their social security number. Clan matches are held between Sudden Attack clans. They can range from a minimum of four team members to eight members. All clan matches take place in item retrieval or bomb/defuse maps.  Winning a clan match is determined by the number of rounds won; if both teams won 5 each, then the winner is determined by the team that planted/defused the bomb more. If that fails to break the tie, then the team with more kills wins, and if the kills are the same, it's a tie.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Game Modes</st>

<p>

There are currently four types of game modes: Team Deathmatch, Bomb/Defuse(mission), Item Retrieval (similar to capture/defend the flag), Property Defense (similar to king of the hill), and Submission. There can be up to 8 people on a team. The Team Deathmatch mode is red versus blue with the winning team decided by number of kills. The Bomb/Defuse mode is where the red team attempts to destroy a target with a timed bomb, while the blue team tries to prevent target from being destroyed. The Item Retrieval mode is when the red team attempts to prevent certain mission items from being taken by the blue team while blue team attempts to retrieve mission items and take to a safe area.  Both the Bomb/Defuse and the Item Retrieval type games can be ended by eliminating all opposing forces. The Property Defense mode is where either the red team or the blue team must be in possession of a property for a certain amount of time.
and Submission is when you are only allowed to use knife.
The number of rounds from the four types of game modes differ. Team Deathmatches have only one round in which players "fight to the death."  However, Item Retrieval and Bomb/Defuse games have short time limits and go anywhere from 3 to 9 rounds, depending on the room master's choice.
Also, all modes except knife match can have limited weapon options of Pistol Match (pistol and knife only) and Knife Match (knife only), which can be set by room master.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Lists of Maps (Sorted by Type, Then By Alphabet)</st>

<p>

Team Deathmatch
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Burning River - A long suspension bridge with an underground passage.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gateway - An Arabic-themed map with a marketplace and temple.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 G-Cube - A futuristic map that features a large low-gravity room.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 One Way - A long, dim street peppered with obstacles.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Power plant - A power plant with control rooms and a back storage area.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Royal Road - A two-floor shootout at the Royal Garden Hotel hall. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Shark Tail - A ice-locked ship with underwater and on-deck battle areas.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Submarine - An enclosed map with a submarine and three floors of fighting.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Warehouse - The smallest map, close quarters combat focused settings. Very quick and intense gameplay is executed.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Bomb/Defuse
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Airport - One of the largest maps in Sudden Attack, the red team must bomb either transport copter or a control tower. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 City Cat - A Japanese city theme map. Targets are white transport truck and large supply crate.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dragonroad - A map with a Chinese theme, the red team must bomb either of two sets of supply crates.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Emble Lab - A futuristic lab-styled map. The lab control room and equipment room are possible targets.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Frozen City - A large snowy city which has underground passages. Power generators are the possible targets.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Ocean Station - A sea-bound station, which features a red team helidrop into water. The targets are a control panel or a supply room.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Old Town - An old-European style town. The targets are two power generators.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Poseidon - An underwater mining base. The targets are the mining conveyor belt controls or a central control room. Name was most likely based on from the famous story of Poseidon, a ship sinking with a theme similar to Titanic.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Provence - Another old-European style town. The targets are a rocket launch site or a control panel.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The 3rd Supply Base - One of the most popular maps. The targets are two different supply sites. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 White Squall - Another European town. The targets are one of two generators.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Item Retrieval
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Club Night - A nightclub with back alleyways. The two items are located within the nightclub.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Golden Eye - A pagoda-like structure that houses two items to be retrieved. This map is probably named after the 007 movie, "Golden Eye". At the end of the movie, James Bond fights in a Japanese themed structure, similar to the one in the game.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Property Defense
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Aqua Bullet - A town river setting, where target is located in the middle of the map surrounded by water</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rush - An Europe base where there are critical energy source. Mission is to take over the energy source, which is at the middle of the map.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Stormville - An African city, the property to be captured is a radio tower, located in the middle of the map.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Submisson
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Mad Cage - A small arena inside a cage. Not allowed to use any ranged materials. Only allowed to use Knife. ( Allowed to use any type of knives )</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Monkey Garden- A mix of Property Defense and Knife Match. Once a person successfully captures the property, the person receives random pistol. (No alternate skin or beretta 93)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Level System</st>

<p>

Players earn experience for battles which they participate in. The ranking/level system is similar to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/2337229.xml">
Republic of Korea's military rank system</link>. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Trainee (Skull)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Private ~ Sergeant (1~4 Bars)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Staff Sergeant ~ Sergeant Major (1~3 Chevrons with Sublevels[Marks])</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Second Lieutenant ~ Captain (1~3 Diamonds with Sublevels [Hash marks])</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Major ~ Colonel (1~3 Flowers with Sublevels [Hash marks])</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Brigadier General ~ General of the Army (1~5 Stars) Note: These are the top/elite players, and their experience requirements differ as the top continually increase their stats.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

As players amass experience, levels are gained. Experience requirements for levels get successively larger. The amount of the points given are depend on what type of game is played (deathmatch, bomb/defusal, item retrieval, property defense, and submission) For deathmatch, players are given 10 points for killing an enemy, -2 points for getting killed. For bomb/defsual, players receive 10 points for killing an enemy, and are deducted 3 points for getting killed, 20 points is awarded to all players for winning a round (i.e. elimination the enemy team), and 50 points to whoever successfully plants a bomb. For item retrieval, the amount of points received and deducted is the same as bomb/defusal. The only different is that if red team wins a round, all players receive 35 points. If blue team wins a round (by eliminating enemy team) they all receive 25 points. Since the goal of the game is to retrieve items, and there are two total, each item retrieved gives the player 35 points. There is an option of destroying one of the items which results in a loss of 5 points for the player who destroyed the items, and each round won with items retrieved all players receive 35 points. For property defense, the amount of points received and deducted is the same as bomb/defusal and item retrieval. But, for winning the whole match, all players on the winning team receive 20 points. For submission, it is the same point system as property defense. Points and cash are the game currencies (look below), and experience is roughly given as double the amount of points earned.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Monetary System</st>

<p>

There are two types of currencies: cash and points. Cash is based on real money and can be charged in exchange for a monetary payment, cell phone billing or home phone billing as well. Points can be earned for playing games. Points and cash can be spent at the in-game shop. Points are used for buying weapons. Cash (which can be seen as a "premium user"-type feature) enables the purchase of in-game boosts (i.e. +10% points)and special bonus items, along with special team-specific outfits. Cash and points can also be earned through promotions such as corporate agreements between Netmarble and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/483481.xml">
SK Telecom</link></company>
 or <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/2589664.xml">
KTF</link></institution>
</company>
 where a user can add his/her cellular phone number to a call list (essentially an advertising scheme).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Weapons</st>

<p>

New users are given a weapon pack and 10000 points upon making an account. These starter packs contain weapons with 15 days worth of use.</p>
<p>

Weapons are bought on a time limit basis. For example, an M4A1 can be bought for 1400 points for one day use, 7000 points for a week of use, 28000 points for a month's use, and 70000 points for three month's use. If same weapon is purchased, number of days you have purchased are added to the weapon you already have.</p>
<p>

Note: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "(Standard)" Means that the labeled item is for unlimited use (i.e. default item).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "(Alternate Skin)" Means that the labeled item is an item that has a different appearance, but same statistics as its normal counterpart. These "Alternate Skin" items are slightly more expensive.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "(Lottery)" Means that the labeled item is available through a lottery 'mini-game' on the site that allows users to pay 7000 points and receive a weapon user selected for 1 day, 1 week, 1 month, 3 months, or 1 year. (Exception: SOCOM-K and M4A1 Devgru are only available by lottery)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 "(PC)" Means that the labeled item is only available to <name wordnetid="106333653" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/272350.xml">
PC bang</link></name>
 patrons.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../160/17160.xml">
Knives</link>: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Axe Knife</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../362/180362.xml">
Gurkha Knife</link></instrument>
</device>
</weapon>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/16889.xml">
Knife</link></instrument>
</device>
</weapon>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 (Standard)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/20261.xml">
Russian Machete</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tiger Stripe</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../966/9958966.xml">
Pistols</link>: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/506106.xml">
B.92FS</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/506106.xml">
B.92FS Black</link></weapon>
 (Alternate Skin) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/1285861.xml">
B.93R</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/876584.xml">
C.Anaconda</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/1401815.xml">
C.USP</link></weapon>
 (Standard)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/691737.xml">
D.Eagle</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/7975.xml">
Double Barrel</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/28491.xml">
Submachine Guns</link>: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../217/94217.xml">
AKS-74U</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../815/3427815.xml">
K1</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../297/14297.xml">
MP5</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/487339.xml">
P90</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/83239.xml">
SMG U101</link> (Standard)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/19690.xml">
Machine Gun</link>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/1863239.xml">
MG43</link></weapon>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/18950865.xml">
Assault Rifles</link>: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/1348.xml">
AK-47</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/1348.xml">
AK-47 Black</link></weapon>
 (Alternate Skin)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/236846.xml">
FAMAS F1</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/69892.xml">
GAL-1</link></weapon>
 (PC)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/698999.xml">
G36K</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/2680956.xml">
K2</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/19901.xml">
M16</link> (Standard)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/321957.xml">
M4A1 Carbine</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/321957.xml">
M4A1 CAMO</link> (Alternate Skin)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/321957.xml">
M4A1 Devgru</link> (Alternate Skin) (Lottery)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/1484559.xml">
SCAR</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/1484559.xml">
SCAR Sandstorm</link></weapon>
 (Alternate Skin)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/418418.xml">
Tavor</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
SIG 556</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/249896.xml">
UAR</link></weapon>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/26838.xml">
 Shot gun</link>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/1074215.xml">
ASG 12</link></weapon>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/479336.xml">
SG 870</link></weapon>
</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<link>
Sniper Rifle</link>:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/337494.xml">
Dragunov</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/6031546.xml">
MSG90</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/504626.xml">
Scout SR-69</link></weapon>
 (Standard)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/319543.xml">
SOCOM-K</link></weapon>
 (Lottery)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/7856579.xml">
TRG-21</link> </entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</article>
