<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:49:39[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<condiment  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107810907">
<ingredient  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="103570709">
<header>
<title>Sesame oil</title>
<id>905664</id>
<revision>
<id>240628844</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-24T06:54:07Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>PaulMSanders100</username>
<id>7927408</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Korean condiments</category>
<category>Chinese ingredients</category>
<category>Cooking oils</category>
<category>Vegetable oils</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="Sesame-oil.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A bottle of sesame Oil
</caption>
</image>

<b>Sesame oil</b> (also known as "gingelly oil" or "til oil") is an edible <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/192331.xml">
vegetable oil</link> derived from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/82420.xml">
sesame seed</link>s. Besides being used as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/422873.xml">
cooking oil</link> in <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<land wordnetid="109334396" confidence="0.8">
<peninsula wordnetid="109388848" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/678583.xml">
South India</link></peninsula>
</land>
</location>
</region>
, it is often used as a flavor enhancer in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../528/30528.xml">
Taiwanese</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/16793.xml">
Korean</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../741/28741.xml">
Southeast Asian</link> cuisine. 
<sec>
<st>
Composition</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Sa_white_sesame_seeds.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

White sesame seeds
</caption>
</image>

Sesame oil is composed of the following <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/10975.xml">
fatty acid</link>s:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<header>
Fatty acid</header>
<header>
Nomenclature</header>
<header>
Minimum</header>
<header>
Maximum</header>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../488/542488.xml">
Palmitic</link></col>
<col>
C16:0</col>
<col align="right">
7.0 %</col>
<col align="right">
12.0 %</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../025/3025025.xml">
Palmitoleic</link></col>
<col>
C16:1</col>
<col align="center">
trace</col>
<col align="right">
0.5 %</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/338511.xml">
Stearic</link></col>
<col>
C18:0</col>
<col align="right">
3.5 %</col>
<col align="right">
6.0 %</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/661100.xml">
Oleic</link></col>
<col>
C18:1</col>
<col align="right">
35.0 %</col>
<col align="right">
50.0 %</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/880497.xml">
Linoleic</link></col>
<col>
C18:2</col>
<col align="right">
35.0 %</col>
<col align="right">
50.0 %</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/4421561.xml">
Linolenic</link></col>
<col>
C18:3</col>
<col align="center">
trace</col>
<col align="right">
1.0 %</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/19245397.xml">
Eicosenoic</link></col>
<col>
C20:1</col>
<col align="center">
trace</col>
<col align="right">
1.0 %</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

Sesame seeds were one of the first crops processed for oil as well as one of the earliest condiments. In fact, the word ennai that means oil in Tamil has its roots in the Tamil words eL(எள்ளு) and nei(னெய்), which mean sesame and fat. </p>
<p>

Prior to 600 BC, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/266350.xml">
Assyrians</link> used sesame oil as a food, salve, and medication, primarily by the rich, as the difficulty of obtaining it made it expensive. Hindus use til oil in votive lamps, and consider the oil sacred. According to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/13677.xml">
Hindu</link> belief, lighting lamp filled with til oil in front of Lord <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/100239.xml">
Hanuman</link> removes obstacles and difficulties in life.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Nomenclature</st>
<p>

In the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/29919.xml">
Tamil language</link></language>
 of India, Sesame Oil is called "Nalla Ennai"(நல்லெண்ணெய்), which literal translation in English is "good oil". In the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/39202.xml">
Telugu language</link></language>
 of India, Sesame Oil is called "<it>Nuvvula Noone</it>" (<it>Nuvvulu</it> means sesame and <it>Noone</it> means cooking oil) or "<it>Manchi Noone</it>" (<it>Manchi</it> means good and <it>Noone</it> means cooking oil). In the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/37445.xml">
Kannada language</link></language>
 of India, Sesame Oil is called "yellenne" (from "yellu" for sesame). It is also called as Gingelly Oil in India.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Manufacture of sesame oil</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Manufacturing process</st>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="Korean_sesame_oil-Chamgireum-01.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Making sesame oil at Moran Market, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/967730.xml">
Seongnam</link></village>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/323103.xml">
Gyeonggi Province</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/27019.xml">
South Korea</link></country>
.
</caption>
</image>

The extraction of sesame oil from the sesame seed is not a completely automated process. In the fairy tale “<fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.8">
<imaginary_being wordnetid="109483738" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/927344.xml">
Ali Baba and the Forty Thieves</link></imaginary_being>
</fictional_character>
” the sesame fruit serves as a symbol for wealth. When the fruit capsule opens, it releases a real treasure - the sesame seeds. However, a great deal of manual work is necessary before this point is reached. That is why sesame is hardly ever cultivated in Western industrialised agricultural areas.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

The sesame seeds are protected by a capsule, which does not burst open until the seeds are completely ripe. The ripening time tends to vary. For this reason, the farmers cut plants by hand and place them together in upright position to carry on ripening for a few days. The seeds are only shaken out onto a cloth after all the capsules have opened. </p>
<p>

The discovery of an indehiscent (nonshattering) mutant by Langham in 1943 began the work towards development of a high yielding, shatter-resistant variety. Although researchers have made significant progress in sesame breeding, harvest losses due to shattering continue to limit domestic US production.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Sesame seed market</st>
<p>

As of 2007, sesame is being imported into the US at a price of US$0.43/lb. This relatively high price reflects a world-wide shortage. Though the market for sesame seed is strong, domestic US production awaits the development of high-yielding nonshattering varieties. It is advisable to establish a market before planting.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Varieties</st>
<p>

There are many variations in the colour of sesame oil: cold-pressed sesame oil is almost colourless, while Indian sesame oil (gingelly or til oil) is golden and Chinese sesame oil is commonly a dark brown colour. </p>
<p>

East Asian sesame oil derives its dark colour and flavour from toasted hulled sesame seeds.  Cold pressed sesame oil has less flavour than the toasted oil, since it is produced directly from raw, rather than toasted seeds.   </p>
<p>

Sesame oil is traded in any of the forms described above:  Cold-pressed sesame oil is available in Western health shops. In most Asian countries, different kinds of hot-pressed sesame oil are preferred.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Uses</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Cooking</st>
<p>

Sesame oil carries a premium relative to other cooking oils and is considered more stable than most vegetable oils due to antioxidants in the oil.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Sesame oil is least prone, among <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/422873.xml">
cooking oil</link>s, to turn rancid. This is because it has a very high boiling point. In effect, sesame oil retains its natural structure and does not break down even when heated to a very high temperature.</p>
<p>

Sesame oil is most popular in Asia, including the South Indian state of <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/29918.xml">
Tamil Nadu</link></city>
, where its widespread use is similar to that of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link> in the Mediterranean.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Body massage</st>
<p>

Sesame oil is reputed to penetrate the skin easily, and is used in India for oil massage.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Hair treatment</st>
<p>

Applying sesame oil to the hair is said to result in darker hair. It may be used for hair and scalp massage.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>
It is believed to reduce the heat of the body and thus helps in preventing hair loss</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Food manufacture</st>
<p>

Sesame oil is used in the manufacture of pickles.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> 
Refined sesame oil is used to make <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/193276.xml">
margarine</link> in Western countries.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Drug manufacture</st>
<p>

Sesame oil is used in the manufacture of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../674/236674.xml">
Ayurvedic</link> drugs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Worship</st>
<p>

Sesame or Til oil is used in brass or silver lamps kept in front of  gods and goddess of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/13677.xml">
Hindus</link>.  Sesame oil is used for performing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/189008.xml">
puja</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/13677.xml">
Hindu</link> temples.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Industrial uses</st>
<p>

In industry, sesame oil may be used as:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a solvent in injected drugs or intravenous drip solutions,</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 a cosmetics carrier oil,</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 coating stored grains to prevent weevil attacks.  The oil also has synergy with some insecticides.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Alternative medicine</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Vitamins and Minerals</st>
<p>

Sesame oil is a source of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/54104.xml">
vitamin E</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> Vitamin E is an anti-oxidant and has been correlated with lowering cholesterol levels.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> As with most plant based condiments, sesame oil contains magnesium, copper, calcium, iron, zinc and vitamin B6. Copper provides relief for rheumatoid arthritis. Magnesium supports vascular and respiratory health. Calcium helps prevent colon cancer, osteoporosis, migraine and PMS. Zinc promotes bone health.</p>
<p>

Besides being rich in Vitamin E, there is insufficient research on the medicinal properties of sesame oil. However, the following claims have been made.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Blood pressure</st>
<p>

Sesame oil has a high percentage of polyunsaturated fatty acids.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>
<p>

It is suggested that due to the presence of high levels of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/1610513.xml">
Polyunsaturated fat</link>ty acids in sesame oil, it may help to control blood pressure. It could be used in cooking in place of other edible oils and to help reduce high blood pressure and lower the amount of medication needed to control hypertension.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>
<p>

Sesame oil is unique in that it has one of the highest concentrations of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/681218.xml">
omega-6 fatty acids</link>. At the same time, the oil contains two natural-occurring preservatives, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../115/7410115.xml">
sesamol</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/17585052.xml">
sesamin</link>. Therefore, sesame oil is the only oil which has a high percentage of polyunsaturates and also keeps at room temperature. (Comparatively, olive oil also keeps at room temperature, but is predominately composed of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/3110439.xml">
omega-9</link> monounsaturated oil.)</p>
<p>

The effect of the oil on blood pressure may be due to polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA), and the compound sesamin – a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../262/1831262.xml">
lignan</link> present in sesame oil. There is evidence suggesting that both compounds reduce blood pressure in hypertensive rats. Sesame lignans also inhibit the synthesis and absorption of cholesterol in these rats.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Oil pulling</st>
<p>

Sesame oil is one of the few oils recommended for use in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../500/8556500.xml">
oil pulling</link>. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/2921902.xml">
sunflower oil</link> is the other oil recommended).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Stress and tension</st>
<p>

Various constituents present in the sesame oil have anti-oxidant and anti-depressant properties. Therefore proponents encourage its use to help fight senile changes and bring about a sense of well-being.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>
<p>

Adherents for its therapeutic use reports claims of feeling better than when not using it.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
General claims</st>
<p>

While not approved by the Food and Drug Administration (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/11632.xml">
FDA</link>), sesame oil is reputed to have a number of therapeutic uses.</p>
<p>

As with cure-all claims of other folk and therapeutic medicines, it is suggested that regular topical application and/or consumption of sesame oil should mitigate effects<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> of anxiety, nerve and bone disorders, poor circulation, lowered immunity and bowel problems. It is suggested such use would also relieve lethargy, fatigue and insomnia, while promoting strength and vitality, enhancing blood circulation. There are claims that its use has relaxing properties which eases pain and muscle spasm, such as sciatica, dysmenorrhoea, colic, backache and joint pain. There are claims similar to other therapeutic medicines, that its having antioxidants explains beliefs that it slows the aging process and promotes longevity.</p>
<p>

It is suggested that sesame oil, when consumed and/or topically applied, should relieve dryness both externally and internally. Sesame oil is sometimes recommended to alleviate the dryness associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/49611.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Symptoms_of_perimenopause=2C_the_menopause_transition_time%22])">
menopause</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> It is believed that its use "restores moisture to the skin, keeping it soft, flexible and young looking". It is suggested that it relieves "dryness of joints" and bowels, and eases symptoms of dryness such as irritating coughs, cracking joints and hard stools. Since "dryness of joints" is not a medically classifiable condition, it would be difficult to medically comprehend or verify these claims of panacea.</p>
<p>

Other uses include as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../526/168526.xml">
laxative</link>, as a remedy for toothaches and gum disease<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> and in the treatment of blurred vision, dizziness, and headaches.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> </p>
<p>

It is suggested that sesame oil could be used in the treatment of dry nose, reduction of cholestrol levels (due to presence of Lignans which are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/912933.xml">
phytoestrogens</link>), anti-bacterial effects, and even slowing down certain types of cancer(due to the anti-oxidant properties of the Lignans).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Adverse effects </st>
<p>

Sesame oil is not known to be harmful when taken in recommended dosages, though the long-term effects of taking sesame-derived remedies (in any amount) have not been investigated. Due to lack of sufficient medical study, sesame oil should be used with caution in children, women who are pregnant or breast-feeding, and people with liver or kidney disease.</p>
<p>

Because of its laxative effects, sesame oil should not be used by people who have diarrhea.</p>
<p>

No more than 10% of a person's total caloric intake should be derived from polyunsaturated fats such as those found in sesame oil, according to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/581673.xml">
American Heart Association</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref></p>
<p>

Oil massage should be avoided immediately after administering enemas, emetics or purgatives, during the first stages of fever or if suffering from indigestion.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref></p>
<p>

People who are allergic to Peanuts are likely to be more susceptible to Sesame allergy. Allergy to Peanuts is one of the most common allergies, and can lead to anaphylactic shock which can be fatal.  Persons allergic to Sesame seeds should be cautious about using Sesame oil.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.essentialoils.co.za/sesame-oil-analysis.htm">
Fatty acids found in sesame oil</weblink>".&#32;  Essential oils.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2006-10-07</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.asiafood.org/glossary_2.cfm?wordid=2814">
Glossary Term - Sesame Oil</weblink>".&#32;  Asia Source.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-01-08</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.graigfarm.co.uk/grocoils.htm#SESAME%20OIL">
Graig Farm Organics - What We Offer &amp;gt; Our Range &amp;gt; The Grocery &amp;gt; Organic Cold-pressed Oils</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hort.purdue.edu/newcrop/afcm/sesame.html">
Sesame</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.uni-graz.at/~katzer/engl/Sesa_ind.html">
Spice Pages: Sesame Seeds (Sesamum indicum)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jeffersoninstitute.org/pubs/sesame.shtml">
Growing Sesame: Production tips, economics, and more</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boloji.com/ayurveda/av011.htm">
Bliss at your Fingertips by Vasu Nargundkar</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boloji.com/ayurveda/av030.htm">
Hair and Scalp Massage by Shreelata Suresh</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pasumark.com/uses.html">
Template</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pasumark.com/uses.html">
Template</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pasumark.com/uses.html">
Template</weblink></entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://content.herbalgram.org/iherb/HealthyIngredients/default.asp?h=Sesame+Oil">
HerbalGram: The Journal of the American Botanical Council</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2004/07/26/earlyshow/health/main631719.shtml">
Cooking Oils That Are Good For You, From Sesame To Grapeseed What You Need To Know - CBS News</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.clinchem.org/cgi/content/full/44/8/1753">
Correlations between Cholesterol, Vitamin E, and Vitamin K1 in Serum: Paradoxical Relationships to Established Epidemiological Risk Factors for Cardiovascular Disease</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.treelight.com/health/nutrition/KimchiHealthy.html">
Kimchi Healthy</weblink></entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ayurveda.com/online%20resource/daily_routine.html">
The Daily Routine by Vasant Lad, MASc</weblink></entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2003-04/aha-soh042803.php">
Sesame oil helps reduce dose of blood pressure-lowering medicine</weblink></entry>
<entry id="19">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.positivehealth.com/article-view.php?articleid=1104">
The Therapeutic Value of Sesame Oil</weblink></entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ayurveda-herbs.com/31.htm">
Hair Loss Cure For Baldness Remedy Treatment Brahmi Oil Herbs</weblink></entry>
<entry id="21">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.idhayam.com/sesameoil/07.html">
Idhayam</weblink></entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_g2603/is_0006/ai_2603000655">
Sesame oil | Encyclopedia of Alternative Medicine | Find Articles at BNET.com</weblink></entry>
<entry id="23">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.youthingstrategies.com/med_refs.htm">
Youthing Strategies Medical References</weblink></entry>
<entry id="22">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hort.purdue.edu/newcrop/ncnu02/v5-153.html">
Food, Industrial, Nutraceutical, and Pharmaceutical Uses of Sesame Genetic Resources</weblink></entry>
<entry id="25">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.positivehealth.com/article-view.php?articleid=1104">
The Therapeutic Value of Sesame Oil</weblink></entry>
<entry id="24">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_g2603/is_0006/ai_2603000655/pg_2">
Sesame oil | Encyclopedia of Alternative Medicine | Find Articles at BNET.com</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";background:lightgreen;" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
Edible fats and oils</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:lightgreen;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/11042.xml">
Fat</link>s</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/63394.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Grease%22])">
Bacon grease</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/46183.xml">
Butter</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/14804879.xml">
Clarified butter</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/894218.xml">
Cocoa butter</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/2311636.xml">
Dripping</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/2579000.xml">
Duck fat</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/212394.xml">
Ghee</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/18621997.xml">
Lard</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../276/193276.xml">
Margarine</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/1995931.xml">
Niter kibbeh</link>&nbsp;• <compound wordnetid="114818238" confidence="0.8">
<merchandise wordnetid="103748886" confidence="0.8">
<fat wordnetid="114864360" confidence="0.8">
<macromolecule wordnetid="114944888" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<commodity wordnetid="103076708" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<lipid wordnetid="114938907" confidence="0.8">
<molecule wordnetid="114682133" confidence="0.8">
<organic_compound wordnetid="114727670" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/3058344.xml">
Salo</link></part>
</organic_compound>
</molecule>
</lipid>
</chemical>
</commodity>
</artifact>
</substance>
</material>
</macromolecule>
</fat>
</merchandise>
</compound>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/1093656.xml">
Schmaltz</link>&nbsp;• <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<compound wordnetid="114818238" confidence="0.8">
<fat wordnetid="114864360" confidence="0.8">
<macromolecule wordnetid="114944888" confidence="0.8">
<agent wordnetid="109190918" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<lipid wordnetid="114938907" confidence="0.8">
<molecule wordnetid="114682133" confidence="0.8">
<organic_compound wordnetid="114727670" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/1347993.xml">
Shea butter</link></part>
</organic_compound>
</molecule>
</lipid>
</causal_agent>
</chemical>
</substance>
</material>
</agent>
</macromolecule>
</fat>
</compound>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;• <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/5347581.xml">
Smen</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/177267.xml">
Suet</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/212396.xml">
Tallow</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/667154.xml">
Vegetable shortening</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";background:lightgreen;;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/4207510.xml">
Oils</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/1064.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Almond+oil%22])">
Almond oil</link>&nbsp;• <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/3820407.xml">
Argan oil</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../788/5864788.xml">
Avocado oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/86190.xml">
Canola oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/172190.xml">
Castor oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/239915.xml">
Coconut oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/1461753.xml">
Colza oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/2249452.xml">
Corn oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/613389.xml">
Cottonseed oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/413249.xml">
Grape seed oil</link>&nbsp;• <plant_part wordnetid="113086908" confidence="0.8">
<plant wordnetid="100017222" confidence="0.8">
<fruit wordnetid="113134947" confidence="0.8">
<tree wordnetid="113104059" confidence="0.8">
<vascular_plant wordnetid="113083586" confidence="0.8">
<edible_nut wordnetid="107737081" confidence="0.8">
<seed wordnetid="113135832" confidence="0.8">
<reproductive_structure wordnetid="111675842" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<woody_plant wordnetid="113103136" confidence="0.8">
<nut wordnetid="113136556" confidence="0.8">
<plant_organ wordnetid="113087625" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/484546.xml">
Hazelnut oil</link></plant_organ>
</nut>
</woody_plant>
</natural_object>
</reproductive_structure>
</seed>
</edible_nut>
</vascular_plant>
</tree>
</fruit>
</plant>
</plant_part>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/324632.xml">
Hemp oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/295711.xml">
Linseed oil (flaxseed oil)</link>&nbsp;• <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/4810999.xml">
Macadamia oil</link></material>
</part>
</chemical>
</substance>
&nbsp;• <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/12742305.xml">
Marula oil</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/746422.xml">
Mustard oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
Olive oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/57561.xml">
Palm oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/57561.xml">
Palm kernel oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/1195910.xml">
Peanut oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/5810563.xml">
Pecan oil</link>&nbsp;• <substance wordnetid="100020090" confidence="0.8">
<condiment wordnetid="107810907" confidence="0.8">
<food wordnetid="100021265" confidence="0.8">
<flavorer wordnetid="107809368" confidence="0.8">
<ingredient wordnetid="107809096" confidence="0.8">
<foodstuff wordnetid="107566340" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/4295731.xml">
Perilla oil</link></foodstuff>
</ingredient>
</flavorer>
</food>
</condiment>
</substance>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/5810617.xml">
Pistachio oil</link>&nbsp;• <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/1208398.xml">
Poppyseed oil</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;• <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/1550129.xml">
Pumpkin seed oil</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/219545.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Cultivation+and+uses%22])">
Rapeseed oil</link>&nbsp;• <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/2094823.xml">
Rice bran oil</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/1208441.xml">
Safflower oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/905664.xml">
Sesame oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../784/62784.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Oil%22])">
Soybean oil</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/2921902.xml">
Sunflower oil</link>&nbsp;• <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<information wordnetid="106634376" confidence="0.8">
<electronic_database wordnetid="106588511" confidence="0.8">
<lexical_database wordnetid="106638868" confidence="0.8">
<wordnet wordnetid="106639428" confidence="0.8">
<database wordnetid="106637824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../613/3025613.xml">
Tea seed oil</link></database>
</wordnet>
</lexical_database>
</electronic_database>
</information>
</message>
&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../431/1208431.xml">
Walnut oil</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style=";background:lightgreen;" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<b>See also:</b> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/4755911.xml">
List of vegetable oils</link>&nbsp;• <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/422873.xml">
Cooking oil</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</ingredient>
</condiment>
</article>
