<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:54:01[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Computer surveillance</title>
<id>91256</id>
<revision>
<id>243411052</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T12:09:59Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Crakkpot</username>
<id>2593843</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computer security</category>
<category>Cryptography</category>
<category>Surveillance</category>
<category>Computer forensics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Computer surveillance</b> is the act of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/87231.xml">
surveilling</link> people, generally their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computer</link> activity, possibly without their knowledge.<p>

Computers make excellent surveillance tools because they can be programmed (even surreptitiously) to record data without their owners' knowledge or consent. Most computers have connections to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../592/4122592.xml">
network</link>s, which can be exploited (through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/2471540.xml">
security cracking</link>) to gain access to any confidential data that may be stored on the computer. Additionally, if someone is able to install certain types of software on a system, they can turn it into an unsuspected  surveillance device.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Surveillance techniques</st>

<p>

<it><artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<analyzer wordnetid="102708711" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/59114.xml">
Packet sniffing</link></instrument>
</analyzer>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</it> is the monitoring of data traffic into and out of a computer or network.  In some networks, data transmissions are sent only to the machine they are intended for, while in others, transmissions are available to all connected nodes (eg, other computers), but are supposed to be processed only by the target computer. In the latter cases, it is possible to packet-sniff a computer by simply using another computer on the same network, without needing to place any software or equipment on the surveilled machine.</p>
<p>

A surveillance program installed on a computer can search the contents of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/13777.xml">
hard drive</link> for suspicious data, can monitor computer use, collect <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/24304.xml">
password</link>s, and even report back to its operator through the Internet connection. The most common are likely commercial <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/28951.xml">
spyware</link> designed to collect marketing data. But, such programs are not limited merely to data collection; they can also use more malicious tactics, such as removing or modifying the data. These last are often called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/19167679.xml">
virus</link>es, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/796442.xml">
logic bomb</link>s, and, generally, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/20901.xml">
malware</link>.</p>
<p>

Physical (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/5310.xml">
hardware</link>) surveillance devices ("bugs") are also possible. A relatively simple bug is a <operation wordnetid="100955060" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/57829.xml">
keystroke logger</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</event>
</operation>
 implanted in circuitry inside a standard  keyboard, perhaps broadcasting key stroke sequences for pickup elsewhere. More sophisticated (and more easily detected) devices with access to more information can also, in theory, be inserted into, or onto, the computer itself. The disadvantage of hardware devices is that placement and retrieval requires physical entry into the place where the computer is stored, and thus almost entirely restricted (legally) to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../378/2092378.xml">
law enforcement agencies</link> equipped with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/146745.xml">
search warrant</link>s, except in situations in which such warrants are not required or may be kept secret as, for instance, some official break-ins under the US <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/32191.xml">
Patriot Act</link> (sometimes termed <link>
sneak and peek</link>), or in the case of electronic communications, warrantless surveillance by such organizations as the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/21939.xml">
NSA</link></agency>
 (as has been authorized continuously against US citizens by President Bush since <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/177704.xml">
9/11</link>). In the US, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/26783.xml">
statute</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/5254.xml">
precedent</link> have also given employers very wide latitude to gather data about employee use of employer's computers.</p>
<p>

It has been shown that it is possible to surveil computers from a distance, with only commercially available equipment, by detecting  the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/25856.xml">
radiation</link> emitted by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/6014.xml">
CRT</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/7677.xml">
monitor</link>. And it has also been shown, by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/57314.xml">
Adi Shamir</link></scientist>
</person>
 et al, that even the high frequency <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../415/41415.xml">
noise</link> emitted by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/5218.xml">
CPU</link> includes information about the instructions being executed. More directly, IBM researchers have also found that, for most computer keyboards, each key emits a slightly different noise when pressed. The differences are individually identifiable under some conditions, and so it's possible to log key strokes without actually requiring logging software to run on the associated computer. Another method of surveilling computer use (key strokes, display images, etc) is video cameras, which are becoming small enough to be easily hidden from casual inspection in which case the surveillance can be surreptitious.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Installing surveillance software</st>

<p>

The simplest way to place surveillance software on a computer is to gain entry to the place where the computer is stored and install it from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/6429.xml">
compact disc</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/10891.xml">
floppy disk</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/400414.xml">
thumbdrive</link>.  This method shares a disadvantage with hardware devices in that it requires <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/13412142.xml">
physical access</link> to the computer.</p>
<p>

A more difficult method is to package the software as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/18994196.xml">
computer virus</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/30056.xml">
trojan horse</link>.  This tactic has the advantage of potentially subjecting multiple computers to surveillance.  However, if the virus is allowed to proliferate, it will become a target of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/268622.xml">
antivirus programs</link>, which will allow the software's removal from affected computers.</p>
<p>

Another method is to use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/2471540.xml">
security cracking</link> to gain access to the computer over a network. An attacker can then install surveillance software remotely. <generic wordnetid="107899976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/42116.xml">
Server</link></generic>
s and computers with permanent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/147184.xml">
broadband</link> connections are most vulnerable to this type of attack.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Protection against surveillance</st>

<p>

A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/1362296.xml">
firewall</link> is software (installed on a computer, or built into separate hardware) which controls network access to a computer, offering some protection against crackers and attempted installation of malware across the network, if properly configured. Unless it also controls outbound communication from the computer, this offers only very limited protection against surveillance even when otherwise properly configured and operating.</p>
<p>

An attractive surveillance target may face highly skilled attempts at physical entry to install software or hardware.  Thus, to be truly protected, such targets should be protected by measures such as reinforcing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/8637.xml">
door</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../400/49400.xml">
window</link>s and other potential entry points.  Password protection can also be effective at several levels, from the <generic wordnetid="107899976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/Form_4473.xml">
BIOS</link></generic>
 during <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/40909.xml">
booting</link>, at any of several points in the operating system (eg, at system log in time), or for applications such as database systems.</p>
<p>

Protection against remote surveillance of radiation emissions is more difficult. The <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 government's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/184781.xml">
TEMPEST</link> program is a standard of protection against eavesdropping of this nature.  Non-CRT displays (such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/17932.xml">
LCD</link>'s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/175859.xml">
plasma display</link>s) may be impossible to surveil in the same way. Some software (<link>
Soft TEMPEST</link>) has been designed to alter <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/64105.xml">
fonts</link> to minimize detectable radiation. The only certain measure, at other than exorbitant cost, is the purchase of a specially shielded monitor. In the extreme, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/151590.xml">
Faraday cage</link> techniques to prevent escape of electromagnetic radiation from equipment out of a physical volume (eg a room) is possible, though expensive.</p>
<p>

Cables can be a serious security problem. They carry signals (eg, to and from printing and display devices, modems, etc) from a computer to other devices, and from other devices (eg, keyboards, mice, scanners, modems, etc) to a computer. They also carry signals between computers (eg, network traffic, file transfers, security and control information, etc). Some cables can be remotely tapped without physical contact, some can be tapped with physical access to the cable, and so on. That cables are often installed in such a manner as to be invisible throughout much of their run (eg, in plenum spaces, within walls, between floors, etc), they are more vulnerable to physical tapping than is commonly appreciated. </p>
<p>

<link>
Fiber Optic</link> cables have the benefit over metallic ones in that unlike metals which transmit electrical signals which can be tapped and monitored while still being sent/received by the intended computers, it uses light which is far more difficult to monitor because it produces very few electromagnetic pulses, radiation, or noise, so remote tapping is nearly impossible. The only practical way to eavesdrop on a fiber optic cable is to physically tap it. This is difficult since, if the cable is cut open to install the tap, the signal is either lost or substantially degraded. (A good example of sensing a signal in a metallic cable is the use of a non-contact voltage tester through insulation. Even though the cable wire is inside plastic (or rubber, cloth, ...) and has now physical  connection to the tester, the tester can still read electrical signals and frequency carried by the cable. This cannot be done with fiber optic cables for which connections require careful mating of specially cut and polished fiber ends in special fittings, otherwise signals can't be detected. Even so, if the cable can be cut, attached to another computer with two network interface cards to monitor network packets. Furthermore, the higher bandwidth and packet refresh rate makes security systems more alert to delayed packets (theoretically, signals can be sent up to 1,079,252,849 km/h, the speed of light, if a completely empty cable were invented).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

Wireless connections between computers, or between computer components (eg, keyboards, mice, printers, modems, ...) are an even larger security problem. The signals are available over a wide area, and even in the best case (ie, proper cryptographic protection) are easy to intercept. In addition, many wireless installations are improperly configured at installation and remain so for long periods. This has inspired such things as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../721/216721.xml">
war driving</link> for open connections and Internet lists of insecure wireless access locations. Still worse in some sense, some wireless security protocols are fundamentally flawed, and so are insecure, even when 'properly' configured (eg, <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/422014.xml">
WEP</link></rule>
</direction>
</protocol>
</message>
, <computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/3742.xml">
Bluetooth</link></system_of_measurement>
</machine>
</device>
</standard>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
, ...). As new wireless standards are developed with greater range and higher speeds, the requirement for more secure protocols and proper configuration of them will increase.</p>
<p>

Other attack approaches are also available. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/667678.xml">
Side channel attacks</link> are possible and must be dealt with individually. For instance, hardware power monitoring can provide information about computer use, and power monitoring of the CPU itself can provide a good bit more. Filtering and conditioning of power lines can help (as with a continuous duty <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/41834.xml">
UPS</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
), as can physical isolation of hardware preventing installation of power monitoring devices for individual system components (eg, the CPU, disk drives, etc.).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Tracking software</st>

<p>

<b>Tracking software</b> is software which notes and logs actions made at a computer.</p>
<p>

For example, if a user checks his email, tracking software can make a record of the action. The same applies to chat, instant messages, Web sites visited, keystrokes typed, and so on.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Who uses tracking software?</st>
<p>

There are four principal groups who use tracking software: parents, employers, governments, and illegal users. Parents who want to be certain their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/128987.xml">
children</link> are not involved with inappropriate web activity, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/314993.xml">
employers</link> who decide to track activity on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../181/68181.xml">
workstations</link> owned or controlled by the business. Illegal tracking can be by criminals (acting on commission from other criminals, perhaps) or businesses wishing to collect usage patterns for marketing departments. Government use of tracking software or hardware is, as far as is known, largely confined to criminal investigations. In some countries, including the US, 'criminal activity' has been redefined to include surveillance of any citizen for terrorist connections or activities. Given the width of this redefinition, this is probably the largest and most comprehensive tracking activity in existence.</p>
<p>

Other users include schools and suspicious spouses.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Cookies</st>
<p>

A <link>
HTTP Cookie</link> is a <invention wordnetid="105633385" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/33139.xml">
World Wide Web</link></invention>
 browser mechanism to preserve <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/10931.xml">
machine state</link>, or interaction history, in Web interactions, since the core <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/2701104.xml">
HTTP</link> protocol was deliberately designed to be stateless. There is no restriction on the content of cookies stored on the HTTP client by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/33173.xml">
browser</link> and so, if configured to do so, cookies may store tracking information for later retrieval by a server computer or by tracking software. In this sense then, cookies can be used to facilitate tracking of user activities. 
Cookies are used by essentially all Internet merchants (eg, for cart tracking), and by most Web sites requiring registration or membership. In addition, they are used by most of the advertising click tracking companies such as DoubleClick.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Controversy </st>
<p>

Tracking software has been a source of controversy. While companies claim that their programs are used to protect children and enforce computer policies at workplaces, there has been strong criticism that this invades users' privacy, if for no other reason than that there is often no way to distinguish between one user of a computer and other users of the same machine. Some operating systems make no internal distinction between users, and others make such distinctions difficult for most user programs, including tracking software, to follow. Much tracking software doesn't even bother to try. Other critics say that these software programs, especially if they have keylogging capabilities, can be used for malicious or criminal purposes, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/180609.xml">
identity theft</link> and unauthorized access to other systems.</p>
<p>

Often, one side of a company's operations sells tracking software, while another side considers tracking software to be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/28951.xml">
spyware</link> and offer programs designed to detect or remove them. There are hundreds of vendors of computer monitoring software such as Retina-X Studios, who explicitly forbid the use of  monitoring software as spyware. Many companies also support detection of tracking software  by providing anti-spyware programs.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>




</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/184781.xml">
TEMPEST</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/20782.xml">
Magic Lantern</link> </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/1079134.xml">
Carnivore network surveillance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/5715.xml">
Cryptanalysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <operation wordnetid="100955060" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/57829.xml">
Keystroke logging</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</event>
</operation>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/667678.xml">
Side channel attack</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/11056386.xml">
Internet censorship</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/1970382.xml">
Remote administration tool</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/7674023.xml">
Employee monitoring software</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/12055260.xml">
ExploreAnywhere</link></institution>
</company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../951/28951.xml">
Spyware</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../056/30056.xml">
Trojan horse</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
http://www.corningcablesystems.com/web/college/fibertutorial.nsf/introfro#2</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.securitymagazine.com/CDA/Articles/Zalud_Report/e943cf6b474d8010VgnVCM100000f932a8c0____">
Fiber’s Turning Copper Green - Zalud Report - Security Magazine</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
