<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:45:58[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>History of Brampton, Ontario</title>
<id>9232086</id>
<revision>
<id>225035709</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-11T16:01:14Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Bearcat</username>
<id>24902</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>History of Brampton, Ontario</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing context</category>
<category>Wikipedia introduction cleanup</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The introduction to this article provides <b>insufficient context</b> for those unfamiliar with the subject.
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=History_of_Brampton%2C_Ontario&amp;action=edit">
improve the article</weblink> with a .</col>
</row>
</table>


<image location="right" width="250px" src="Perkins_bull.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

William Perkins Bull, 1934.
</caption>
</image>

Prior to 1834, the only building of consequence at the corner of Main and Queen streets, the recognized centre of Brampton, was William Buffy's tavern.  In fact, at the time, the area was referred to as "Buffy's Corners".  All real business in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<township wordnetid="108672199" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/7761122.xml">
Chinguacousy Township</link></urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</township>
</region>
 took place one mile distant at Martin Salisbury's tavern.  By 1934, John Elliott laid out the area in lots for sale, and applied the name "Brampton" to the area, which was soon adopted by others.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

In 1853, a small agricultural fair was set up by the then-new County Agricultural Society of the County of Peel, and was held at the corner of Main and Queen streets. Grains, produce, roots, and dairy products were up for sale, a precursor of today's Brampton Farmers' Market. Horses and cattle, along with other lesser livestock was sold at market. This agricultural fair eventually became the modern <diversion wordnetid="100426928" confidence="0.8">
<carnival wordnetid="100519333" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<show wordnetid="100520257" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<entertainment wordnetid="100429048" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/2314418.xml">
Brampton Fall Fair</link></activity>
</entertainment>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</show>
</event>
</carnival>
</diversion>
.  In that same year Brampton was incorporated as a village.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

A federal grant allowed the village to create its first public library in 1887, which included 360 volumes from the pre-existing Mechanic's Institute (est 1858). In 1907, the library successfully received a grant from steel magnate <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philanthropist wordnetid="110421956" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/1938.xml">
Andrew Carnegie</link></philanthropist>
</person>
 to build a new multi-person building, featuring a library. See <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/2314403.xml">
Brampton Library</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
.</p>
<p>

In 1884 a group of mechanics of the Haggert Foundry of Brampton formed what is now known as the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bramptonconcertband.com">
Brampton Concert Band</weblink>, one of Canada's oldest community concert bands.</p>
<p>

A group of regional farmers in Brampton had trouble getting insurance from city-based companies. After several meetings in Clairville Hall, it was decided that they should found the County of Peel Farmers Mutual Fire Insurance Company. In 1955, the company moved to its third and current location, 103 Queen Street West, and renamed itself Peel Mutual Insurance Company. It reigns as the longest running company in modern Brampton. Harmsworth Decorating Centre was established in 1890, as Harmsworth and Son, operated out of the family's house on Queen Street West. The store purchased its current location on September 1, 1904, after a fire destroyed their original store. Purchased for $1400, the 24 Main Street South location is the longest operating retail business in what is now Brampton.</p>
<p>

In 1922, when the town's population had reached 8,000, the Capitol Theatre was built in downtown Brampton. Its schedule consisted of primarily of vaudeville and silent movies.</p>
<p>

The Brampton Mall was built in 1960 on Main Street, near <link>
Peel Village</link>, marking the community's first mall.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Neighbouring Bramalea created</st>
<p>

Created as an innovative "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/143155.xml">
new town</link>", Bramalea was developed as a separate community, approximately 40 kilometres northwest of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../646/64646.xml">
Toronto</link>.</p>
<p>

Located in the former <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<township wordnetid="108672199" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../122/7761122.xml">
Chinguacousy Township</link></urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</township>
</region>
, it was Canada's first satellite community developed by one of the country's largest real estate developers, <it>Bramalea Limited</it>, formerly known as <it>Brampton Leasing</it>. The name "Bramalea" was created by the farmer William Sheard, who integrated the BRAM from Brampton, MAL from Malton (A neighbouring region), and the EA from his own farm; SunnymEAd Farms. He sold the land to Brampton Leasing developers and built one of Bramalea's first houses on Dixie road across from the former headquarters of Nortel. The community had an extensive Master Plan, which included provisions for a parkland trail system and a "downtown," which would include essential services and a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/235723.xml">
shopping centre</link>. The downtown area's centrepiece was the Civic Centre, which included the city hall and library. Directly across Team Canada Drive from the Civic Centre, Bramalea Limited built a shopping centre named <plaza wordnetid="103965456" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/584817.xml">
Bramalea City Centre</link></plaza>
. The two centrepieces were connected by a long underground tunnel, which has long since been closed due to safety issues. Other features included a police station, fire hall, bus terminal, and a collection of seniors' retirement homes.</p>
<p>

Each phase of the new city was built with progressing first letters of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/2551704.xml">
street name</link>s. Development started with the "A" section, with street names like Argyle, Avondale, and Aloma. Developer then created a "B" section, "C" section, and so forth. Children on the boundaries of these divisions would regularly compete in street hockey games, pitting, for example, the "D" section versus the "E" section.</p>
<p>

The community was also initially developed with a large number of recreational facilities, including tennis courts, playgrounds, hockey/lacrosse rinks and swimming pools. An extensive parkland trail and sidewalk system that connects the entire city, amplifying what Brampton already had in a smaller scale.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Region of Peel</st>
<p>

In 1974, the Ontario government decided to update <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../386/1092386.xml">
Peel County</link></county>
</location>
</region>
's structure. Along with amalgamating a series of villages into the City of Mississauga, the new City of Brampton was created out of the greater portion of the Townships of Chinguacousy and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/7762408.xml">
Toronto Gore</link>, including Bramalea and the other communities in those townships.  The province converted Peel County into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/328206.xml">
Regional Municipality of Peel</link>. Brampton retained its role as the administrative centre of Peel Region, which it already had as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../509/51509.xml">
county seat</link>. The regional council chamber, the <service wordnetid="100577525" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../697/1940697.xml">
Peel Regional Police</link></service>
 force, the public health department, and the region's only major museum, the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<depository wordnetid="103177349" confidence="0.8">
<museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/761382.xml">
Peel Heritage Complex</link></museum>
</depository>
</facility>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
, are all located in Brampton.</p>
<p>

This move was not met with open arms. Bramptonians feared urban sprawl would dissolve their town's personality, and Bramalea residents took pride in the built from scratch and organized structure that came with a new city. Many residents of the former community of Bramalea do not classify themselves as Brampton residents.</p>
<p>

In 1972, Bramalea created its civic centre. Two years after it was built, when Brampton and Bramalea merged, the new city's council chambers and other facilities were created in the building, moving from the town of Brampton's modest downtown locale. The library systems of Brampton and Bramalea became one, creating a system of four locations.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/328206.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22The+Region.27s+future%22])">
future of Peel Region</link> as encompassing all of Brampton, Mississauga, and Caledon, has been called into question by some. Mississauga council, led by Mayor <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<mayor wordnetid="110303814" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/160092.xml">
Hazel McCallion</link></mayor>
</person>
, voted in favour of becoming a single tier municipality and asked the provincial government to be separated from Peel Region, arguing that the city has outgrown the need for a regional layer of government and that Mississauga is now being held back by supporting Brampton and Caledon with its municipal taxes.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Development of Brampton as a city</st>
<p>

In the 1980s, the Capitol Theatre, then owned by <series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="107938773" confidence="0.8">
<chain wordnetid="108376250" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<ordering wordnetid="108456993" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/354994.xml">
Odeon</link></institution>
</group>
</ordering>
</company>
</chain>
</arrangement>
</series>
, closed its doors. The City bought the facility in 1981, under the spearhead of then-councillor Diane Sutter, turning the former movie house and vaudevillian stage into a theatre for the musical and performing arts. It was renamed the Heritage Theatre. In 1983, Toronto consultants Woods Gordon reported to the City that, rather than continue "pouring money" into the Heritage, a new 750-seat facility should be built. The 2005/06 season was designated as the theatre's "grand finale" season.</p>
<p>

The early 1990s brought a new city hall to Brampton's downtown. The facility was designed by local architects and constructed by Inzola Construction.</p>
<p>

The Brampton Fair Grounds were sold in 1992 to the City of Brampton, leading the Agricultural Society to relocate to Heart Lake Road and Old School Road in 1997.</p>
<p>

The Health Services Restructuring Commission (HSRC) decided in 1997 that <link>
Georgetown and District Memorial Hospital</link>, <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../580/4960580.xml">
Etobicoke General Hospital</link></hospital>
 and <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/4960540.xml">
Peel Memorial Hospital</link></hospital>
 amalgamate into the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<medical_building wordnetid="103739518" confidence="0.8">
<hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/4957278.xml">
William Osler Health Centre</link></hospital>
</medical_building>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
, becoming what now is the province's 6th largest hospital corporation. In early 2006, the Brampton campus of the William Osler Health Centre was renamed back to Peel Memorial Hospital, as residents continued to use the old name, a cause of much confusion.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Current events</st>

<p>

The <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<theater wordnetid="104417809" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/4092696.xml">
Rose Theatre</link></theater>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 (originally the Brampton Performing Arts Centre), billed as "a cultural and tourist destination that will attract significant new business to surrounding restaurants, shops and services," opened in September 2006. The City says that the facilities are expected to generate $2.7 million in economic activity the first year and grow to $19.8 million by the fifth year. This is predicted to attract more than 55,000 visitors annually who will spend about $275,000 on before and after-show entertainment, creating close to 300 permanent jobs. Despite the great promises, this project is the source of much cynicism among the community. Many have questioned the need for a larger facility, as the current Heritage Theatre rarely reaches capacity, and a great deal of residents don't meet the prime theatre going audience profile.</p>
<p>

A new hospital is being built in north Brampton, to supplement the <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/4960540.xml">
Peel Memorial Hospital</link></hospital>
.</p>
<p>

Brampton's 2003 Sesquicentennial celebrations were a booster to community spirit, restarting the tradition of a summer parade (with 100 floats), and creating other initiatives. To commemorate the Flowertown history, the City under Mayor Fennell reintroduced floral projects to the community, including more plantings around town, the restart of the Flowercity Parade in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/998383.xml">
2005</link>, and participation for the last few years in the Canada <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/1882403.xml">
Communities in Bloom</link> project.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Diversity embraced</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<festival wordnetid="115162388" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/3195639.xml">
Carabram</link></psychological_feature>
</festival>
</event>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
</it>
</indent>
<image location="right" width="150px" src="Apr_21_ontario_place_punjabi_virsa_miss_brampton.JPG" type="thumb">
</image>

With a growing multicultural population, the Peel Board of Education introduced evening <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/415406.xml">
English as a Second Language</link> (ESL) classes at high schools. Originally taught by volunteers, the classes eventually became daytime courses taught by paid instructors. In the 1980s, the public and Catholic board expanded its languages programs, offering night classes in 23 languages. These were introduced by the urging of parents who wanted their children to learn their ancestral heritage and language.</p>
<p>

Brampton also embraces its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/66936.xml">
Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender</link> community, with Mayor Susan Fennell proclaiming Gay Pride Day in 2004 and 2005, and a Gay Pride Week in 2006.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

<fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<festival wordnetid="115162388" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/3195639.xml">
Carabram</link></psychological_feature>
</festival>
</event>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
 was founded in 1982, after volunteers from different ethnic communities wanted to organize a festival celebrating diversity and cross-cultural friendship. With a name based on Toronto like-event, <link>
Caravan Festival of Cultures</link>, Carabram's first event included Italian, Scottish, Ukrainian, and West Indian pavilions. By 2003, forty-five-thousand visitors visited 18 pavilions. Canada itself had an anchor pavilion in the late-1980s, early-1990s, but ceased when it failed to get sponsorship.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Recent events</st>
<p>

The city's mascot is "Sassy the Sesqui Squirrel",<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> a character that replaced "Millie the Millennium Techno Bug", now the HACE mascot.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</ss1>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"Brampton's Beginning" in <it>Brampton's 100th Anniversary as an Incorporated Town: 1873-1973</it>, Brampton: The Corporation of the Town of Brampton and the Brampton Centennial Committee, 1973, originally published in Ross Cumming, ed., <it>Historical Atlas of Peel County</it>, n.p.: Walker and Miles, 1877.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Susan Fennell's <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prideeventspeel.com/Proclamation.html">
Proclamation of Gay Pride Week in Brampton</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
http://www.city.brampton.on.ca/review/fw2003/sesqui.shtml</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.artsbrampton.ca/hace/millie.htm">
HACE - Millie, the Techno Bug</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/160084.xml">
Brampton, Ontario</link></village>
</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Geography</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/16207532.xml">
410@Steeles Business Park</link>&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<vicinity wordnetid="108641113" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<section wordnetid="108648322" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/2797980.xml">
Claireville</link></section>
</location>
</area>
</vicinity>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <lake wordnetid="109328904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/5619053.xml">
Heart Lake</link></lake>
&nbsp;·  <lake wordnetid="109328904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/17046017.xml">
Loafers Lake</link></lake>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<vicinity wordnetid="108641113" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<section wordnetid="108648322" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/2035436.xml">
Mount Pleasant</link></section>
</location>
</area>
</vicinity>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<camp wordnetid="102945594" confidence="0.8">
<camp wordnetid="102944826" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<military_quarters wordnetid="103763727" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<housing wordnetid="103546340" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<living_quarters wordnetid="103679384" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../154/6784154.xml">
Camp Naivelt</link></living_quarters>
</geographical_area>
</tract>
</housing>
</location>
</military_quarters>
</artifact>
</camp>
</camp>
</structure>
</region>
</site>
&nbsp;·  <lake wordnetid="109328904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/7761684.xml">
Professor's Lake</link></lake>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../408/7762408.xml">
Toronto Gore Township</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Buildings and structures</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../461/17208461.xml">
A. Grenville and William Davis Courthouse</link>&nbsp;·  <plaza wordnetid="103965456" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/584817.xml">
Bramalea City Centre</link></plaza>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<library wordnetid="103660909" confidence="0.8">
<room wordnetid="104105893" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../403/2314403.xml">
Brampton Library</link></room>
</library>
</area>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/16183677.xml">
Brampton Soccer Centre</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<memorial wordnetid="103743902" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/6513219.xml">
Korean War Memorial Wall</link></memorial>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<depository wordnetid="103177349" confidence="0.8">
<museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/761382.xml">
Peel Heritage Complex</link></museum>
</depository>
</facility>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<scene wordnetid="108645963" confidence="0.8">
<venue wordnetid="108677628" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/1890150.xml">
Powerade Centre</link></venue>
</scene>
</location>
</area>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<theater wordnetid="104417809" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/4092696.xml">
Rose Theatre</link></theater>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<mercantile_establishment wordnetid="103748162" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<place_of_business wordnetid="103953020" confidence="0.8">
<establishment wordnetid="103297735" confidence="0.8">
<plaza wordnetid="103965456" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/2720803.xml">
Shoppers World Brampton</link></plaza>
</establishment>
</place_of_business>
</artifact>
</building>
</mercantile_establishment>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<mercantile_establishment wordnetid="103748162" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<place_of_business wordnetid="103953020" confidence="0.8">
<establishment wordnetid="103297735" confidence="0.8">
<plaza wordnetid="103965456" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../314/3774314.xml">
Trinity Common Mall</link></plaza>
</establishment>
</place_of_business>
</artifact>
</building>
</mercantile_establishment>
</structure>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Organization</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/209589.xml">
Brampton Arts Council</link>&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="102735688" confidence="0.8">
<enclosure wordnetid="103285912" confidence="0.8">
<chamber wordnetid="103003730" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/703456.xml">
Brampton Board of Trade</link></chamber>
</enclosure>
</area>
</artifact>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../085/160085.xml">
Visual Arts Brampton</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Events</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<diversion wordnetid="100426928" confidence="0.8">
<carnival wordnetid="100519333" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<show wordnetid="100520257" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<entertainment wordnetid="100429048" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/2314418.xml">
Brampton Fall Fair</link></activity>
</entertainment>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</show>
</event>
</carnival>
</diversion>
&nbsp;·  <fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<festival wordnetid="115162388" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/3195639.xml">
Carabram</link></psychological_feature>
</festival>
</event>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Politics</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<council wordnetid="108310949" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/3441658.xml">
Brampton City Council</link></council>
</administrative_unit>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/17693694.xml">
Brampton City Hall</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/17693183.xml">
Peel Centre</link></artifact>
</building>
</structure>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/17693132.xml">
Peel County Courthouse and Jail</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Media</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/454693.xml">
The Brampton Guardian</link></newspaper>
</publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</press>
</creation>
</print_media>
</product>
</work>
&nbsp;·  <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/4039299.xml">
The Bramptonian</link></publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
&nbsp;·  <radio_station wordnetid="104044119" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/164673.xml">
CFNY-FM</link></radio_station>
&nbsp;·  <radio_station wordnetid="104044119" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/3917465.xml">
CIAO</link></radio_station>
&nbsp;·  <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/4039253.xml">
The Brampton Times</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Education</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<school_district wordnetid="108587709" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../059/3568059.xml">
Peel District School Board</link></school_district>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<school_district wordnetid="108587709" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/1942265.xml">
Dufferin-Peel Catholic District School Board</link></institution>
</school_district>
</district>
</educational_institution>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</school>
</region>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Transportation</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/3493146.xml">
AcceleRide</link>&nbsp;·  <airport wordnetid="102692232" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/1678563.xml">
Brampton Airport</link></airport>
&nbsp;·  <theodolite wordnetid="104419073" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/1604128.xml">
Brampton Transit</link></theodolite>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
