<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:51:53[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Routing in the PSTN</title>
<id>925465</id>
<revision>
<id>223025334</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-02T06:31:03Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jim.henderson</username>
<id>2255048</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Teletraffic</category>
<category>Routing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In the context of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/468436.xml">
public switched telephone network</link>, <b>routing</b> is the process by which <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/30003.xml">
telephone calls</link> are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/25750.xml">
routed</link> around the telephone network. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../603/59603.xml">
Telephone exchange</link>s are connected together with <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<electrical_device wordnetid="103269401" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<circuit wordnetid="103033362" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../233/593233.xml">
trunks</link></circuit>
</device>
</electrical_device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
.  Each call that is to be routed contains a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../468/18790468.xml">
destination number</link> that has two parts, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/627405.xml">
prefix</link> which generally identifies the geographical location of the destination telephone, and a number unique within that prefix that determines the precise destination.<p>

The exchange uses pre-computed routing tables, which are generated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/37285.xml">
batch processing</link> at central locations based on the known <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/41413.xml">
topology of the network</link>, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../405/627405.xml">
numbering plan</link>, and analysis of <operation wordnetid="100955060" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<attack wordnetid="100972621" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/480015.xml">
traffic data</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</attack>
</event>
</operation>
.  These are then downloaded to telephone exchanges at intervals.  There may be several alternative routes to any given destination, and the exchange can select dynamically between these in the event of link failure or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/430522.xml">
congestion</link>.</p>
<p>

Because of the hierarchical nature of the numbering plan, and its geographical basis, most calls can be routed based only on their prefix.  Exceptions include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/41268.xml">
intelligent network</link> services with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/10408617.xml">
non-geographical numbers</link>, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/406726.xml">
 toll-free or freephone calling</link>.</p>
<p>

Routing in circuit-switched networks involves creating a path from one customer to another for the duration of each call. Routing decisions are an important part of this process as they determine which channels or circuits are used to connect the customers for the duration of the call. In a PSTN exchange, routing is typically performed using a routing table that contains the pre-defined routes for a connection. In such a system, alternative routes exist, which are specified in the routing tables [1].</p>
<p>

In determining routing plans, special attention is paid for example to ensure that two routes do not mutually overflow to each other, otherwise congestion will cause a destination to be completely blocked. </p>
<p>

According to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/826885.xml">
Braess' paradox</link>, the addition of a new, shorter, and lower cost route can lead to an increase overall congestion [1, 2]. The network planner must take this into account when designing routing paths.</p>
<p>

One approach to routing involves the use of Dynamic Alternative Routing (DAR) [1]. DAR makes use of the distributed nature of a telecommunications network and its inherent randomness to dynamically determine optimal routing paths. This method generates a distributed, random, parallel computing platform that minimises congestion across the network, and is able to adapt to take changing traffic patterns and demands into account [1].</p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

[1] Kelly F.P., <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.statslab.cam.ac.uk/~frank/CP/CPREAD/nr.html">
<it>Network Routing''</it></weblink>, Statistical Laboratory, University of Cambridge, 16 Mill Lane, Cambridge CB2 1SB, UK.</p>
<p>

[2] Wainwright M., <it>A Small Road Network</it>, Included in: Kennedy I., Teletraffic Lecture Notes, School of Electrical and Information Engineering, University of the Witwatersrand, 2003.
EQEQEQE</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
