<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:52:54[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Linda Harasim</title>
<id>9293733</id>
<revision>
<id>235837890</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-02T16:09:37Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Simon Fraser University faculty</category>
<category>Living people</category>
<category>Year of birth missing (living people)</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This biographical article or section is written .</b>
Please <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Linda_Harasim&amp;action=edit">
help improve it</weblink> by revising it to be  and . <it>(December 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


<p>

<b>Linda Harasim</b>  is a Professor of Communication, Faculty of Applied Sciences, at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/28525.xml">
Simon Fraser University</link></university>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/204848.xml">
Burnaby, British Columbia</link>. She holds a B.A. and M.A. from the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/242057.xml">
University of Alberta</link></university>
, and a <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/8775.xml">
Ph.D.</link></property>
</degree>
 in <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/17994.xml">
educational theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
 from the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/7955325.xml">
University of Toronto</link></university>
.</p>
<p>

She has been active for over a decade in researching educational applications of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/5652.xml">
computer networking</link>. She has designed, implemented, and evaluated networking applications in Canada, the U.S., and Latin America.  She is also leading the Virtual-U Project, one of the first networked multimedia learning systems in the world that is customized for course delivery and course enhancement at all levels of education.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Publications</st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Books </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, L., Hiltz, R., Teles, L., and Turoff, M. Learning Networks: A Field Guide to Teaching &amp; Learning Online. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1995.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. (Ed.). Global Networks: Computers and Communication. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1993.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. (Ed.). Online Education: Perspectives on a New Environment. New York: Praeger Publishers, 1990.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda and Johnson, E. Marcia. Educational applications of computer networks. Toronto: Ontario Ministry of Education Press, 1986.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Refereed Articles</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Shift Happens: Online Education as a New Paradigm in Learning,Internet and Higher Education: Special Issue. UK: Elsevier Science 3 (2000): 41-61.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Computer Networking for Education.In T. Husen, and T.N. Postlethwaite, (Eds.). The International Encyclopedia of Education, 2nd Edition. Oxford, U.K: Pergamon Press, 1994.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Riel, M. and Harasim, L. Research Perspectives on Network Learning Environments. Journal of Man-Machine Learning, 4(2&amp;3), 91-114, 1994.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Collaborating in Cyberspace: Using Computer Conferences as a Group Learning Environment. Interactive Learning Environments , 3 (2), 119-130, 1993.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda and Winkelmans, Tim. Computer-mediated scholarly collaboration: A case study of an international online workshop. Knowledge: Creation, Diffusion, Utilization, 11(4), 382-409, 1990.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Teaching and learning on-line: Issues in designing computer-mediated graduate courses. Canadian Journal of Educational Communications, 16(2), 1987.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. (Computer learning networks: Educational applications of computer conferencing. Journal of Distance Education, 1(1), 59-70, 1986.</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda and Johnson, E. Marcia. Computer conferencing and online education: Designing for the medium. Canadian Journal for Information Science, Winter, 1986.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Book Chapters </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Networlds: Networks as Social Space. In L. Harasim (Ed.) (1993). Global Networks: Computers and International Communication. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1993.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda (1993). Global Networks. In L. Harasim (Ed.) (1993). Global Networks: Computers and International Communication. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda and Smith, Dorothy. Making Connections, Thinking Change Together: Women Teachers and Computer Networks. In P. Bourne (Ed.) (1993). Feminism and Education. A Canadian Perspective , Volume 2. Toronto: OISE Press, 1993.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Foreword: Towards the Electronic University. In M. Paulsen's, From Bulletin Boards to Electronic Universities: Distance Education, Computer-Mediated Communication, and Online Education. ACSDE Research Monograph, Pennsylvania State University, 1992.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Online education: An environment for collaboration and intellectual amplification. In L. Harasim (Ed.) Online education: Perspectives on a new environment , (39-66). New York: Praeger Publishers, 1990.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Bibliography on educational CMC. In L. Harasim (Ed.) Online education: Perspectives on a new environment, (229-264) New York: Praeger Publishers, 1990.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harasim, Linda. Online education: A new domain. In R. Mason &amp; T.Kaye (Eds.) Mindweave: Computers, communications and distance education, (pp.50-62) Oxford: Pergamon Press, 1989.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Interviews </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Speaking Personally with Linda Harasim" by Greg Kearsley, published in <it>The American Journal of Distance Education</it>, Vol 7, No. 3, 1993.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://fas.sfu.ca/fas/GCMS2/bio.php?FirstName=Linda&amp;LastName=Harasim">
Faculty page</weblink> at Simon Fraser University</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
