<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:41:47[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Constrained clustering</title>
<id>9303553</id>
<revision>
<id>235107752</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-30T02:04:23Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>CmdrObot</username>
<id>1079367</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Cluster computing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link>, <b>constrained clustering</b> is a class of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/2829632.xml">
semi-supervised learning</link> algorithms. Typically, constrained clustering incorporates either a set of must-link constraints, cannot-link constraints, or both, with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/669675.xml">
Data clustering</link> algorithm. Both a must-link and a cannot-link constraint define a relationship between two data instances. A must-link constraint is used to specify that the two instances in the must-link relation should be associated with the same cluster. A cannot-link constraint is used to specify that the two instances in the cannot-link relation should <it>not</it> be associated with the same cluster. These sets of constraints acts as a guide for which a constrained clustering algorithm will attempt to find clusters in a data set which satisfy the specified must-link and cannot-link constraints. Some constrained clustering algorithms will abort if no such clustering exists which satisfies the specified constraints. Others will try to minimize the amount of constraint violation should it be impossible to find a clustering which satisfies the constraints.<p>

Examples of constrained clustering algorithms include:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 COP K-means</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 PCKmeans</entry>
</list>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.litech.org/~wkiri/Papers/wagstaff-kmeans-01.pdf">
Constrained K-means Clustering with Background Knowledge</weblink>. Wagstaﬀ, et al. Proceedings of the Eighteenth International Conference on Machine Learning, 2001, p. 577–584.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
