<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:42:32[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Information Search Process</title>
<id>9332933</id>
<revision>
<id>136819623</id>
<timestamp>2007-06-08T12:48:39Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Minghong</username>
<id>110454</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Information science</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Information Search Process</b> (ISP) is a six-stage process that information seekers go through when seeking information. ISP was first suggested by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/8236149.xml">
Carol Kuhlthau</link> in 1991. The six stages of ISP are as follows: Stage 1: Initiation, Stage 2: Selection, Stage 3: Exploration, Stage 4: Formulation, Stage 5: Collection, Stage 6: Presentation. 
<sec>
<st>
Stages</st>
<p>

During the first stage, <it>initiation</it>, the information seeker has a topic for which they need information. As they think more about the topic, they may discuss the topic with others and brainstorm the topic further. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>
<p>

In the second stage, <it>selection</it>, the individual begins to decide where to get the information needed. Some information retrieval may occur at this point. </p>
<p>

In the third stage, <it>exploration</it>, information on the topic is gathered. During this stage, new personal knowledge is created. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> </p>
<p>

During the fourth stage, <it>formulation</it>, the information seeker starts to evaluate the information that has been gathered. At this point, a focus begins to form and there is not as much confusion and uncertainty as in earlier stages. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Formulation is considered to be the most important stage of the process. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

During the fifth stage, <it>collection</it>, the information seeker knows what is needed to support the focus. At this point, the search is more effective because the focus is clear. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

In the sixth and final stage, <it>presentation</it>, the individual has completed the information search. Now the information seeker will summarize and report on the information that was found through the process.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Shannon, Donna. “Kuhlthau’s Information Search Process.” School Library Media Activities Monthly, Vol. 19, no. 2, October 2002: p. 19-23.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Isbell, Dennis and Lisa Kammerlocher. “Implementing Kuhlthau: A New Model for Library and Reference Instruction.” Reference Services Review, Fall/Winter 1998: p. 33-44.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Rubin, Richard E. Foundations of Library and Information Science. New York: Neal Schuman Publishers.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
