<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:43:15[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<statement  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106722453">
<message  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106598915">
<equation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106669864">
<mathematical_statement  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106732169">
<header>
<title>Constraint algorithm</title>
<id>9357898</id>
<revision>
<id>237652465</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-11T05:14:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jitse Niesen</username>
<id>14515</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computational physics</category>
<category>Molecular physics</category>
<category>Numerical differential equations</category>
<category>Molecular dynamics</category>
<category>Computational chemistry</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../559/19559.xml">
mechanics</link>, a <b>constraint algorithm</b> is a method for satisfying constraints for bodies that obey Newton's equations of motion.  There are three basic approaches to satisfying such constraints: choosing novel unconstrained coordinates ("internal coordinates"), introducing explicit constraint forces, and minimizing constraint forces implicitly by the technique of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/159974.xml">
Lagrange multipliers</link> or projection methods.<p>

Constraint algorithms are often applied to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/198608.xml">
molecular dynamics</link> simulations.  Although such simulations are sometimes carried out in internal coordinates that automatically satisfy the bond-length and bond-angle constraints, they may also be carried out with explicit or implicit constraint forces for the bond lengths and bond angles.  Explicit constraint forces typically shorten the time-step significantly, making the simulation less efficient computationally; in other words, more computer power is required to compute a trajectory of a given length.  Therefore, internal coordinates and implicit-force constraint solvers are generally preferred.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Mathematical background</st>

<p>

The motion of a set of <it>N</it> particles can be described by a set of second-order ordinary differential equations, Newton's second law, which can be written in matrix form</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>
\mathbf{M} \cdot \frac{d^{2}\mathbf{q}}{dt^{2}} = \mathbf{f} = -\frac{\partial V}{\partial \mathbf{q}}
</math>
</indent>

where <b>M</b> is a <it>mass matrix</it> and <b>q</b> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/32533.xml">
vector</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/473514.xml">
generalized coordinate</link>s that describe the particles' positions.  For example, the vector <b>q</b> may be a <it>3N</it> Cartesian coordinates of the particle positions <b>r</b><it>k</it>, where <it>k</it> runs from 1 to <it>N</it>; in the absence of constraints, <b>M</b> would be the <it>3N</it>x<it>3N</it> diagonal square matrix of the particle masses.  The vector <b>f</b> represents the generalized forces and the scalar <it>V</it>(<b>q</b>) represents the potential energy, both of which are functions of the generalized coordinates <b>q</b>.</p>
<p>

If <it>M</it> constraints are present, the coordinates must also satisfy <it>M</it> time-independent algebraic equations</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>
g_{j}(\mathbf{q}) = 0 
</math>
</indent>

where the index <it>j</it> runs from 1 to <it>M</it>.  For brevity, these functions <it>gi</it> are grouped into an <it>M</it>-dimensional vector <b>g</b>  below.  The task is to solve the combined set of differential-algebraic (DAE) equations, instead of just the ordinary differential equations (ODE) of Newton's second law.</p>
<p>

This problem was studied in detail by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/87793.xml">
Joseph Louis Lagrange</link></scientist>
</person>
, who laid out most of the methods for solving it.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  The simplest approach is to define new generalized coordinates that are unconstrained; this approach eliminates the algebraic equations and reduces the problem once again to solving an ordinary differential equation.  Such an approach is used, for example, in describing the motion of a rigid body; the position and orientation of a rigid body can be described by six independent, unconstrained coordinates, rather than describing the positions of the particles that make it up and the constraints among them that maintain their relative distances.  The drawback of this approach is that the equations may become unwieldy and complex; for example, the mass matrix <b>M</b> may become non-diagonal and depend on the generalized coordinates.  </p>
<p>

A second approach is to introduce explicit forces that work to maintain the constraint; for example, one could introduce strong spring forces that enforce the distances among mass points within a "rigid" body.  The two difficulties of this approach are that the constraints are not satisfied exactly, and the strong forces may require very short time-steps, making simulations inefficient computationally.</p>
<p>

A third approach is to use a method such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/159974.xml">
Lagrange multipliers</link> or projection to the constraint manifold to determine the coordinate adjustments necessary to satisfy the constraints.  Finally, there are various hybrid approaches in which different sets of constraints are satisfied by different methods, e.g., internal coordinates, explicit forces and implicit-force solutions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Internal coordinate methods</st>

<p>

The simplest approach to satisfying constraints in energy minimization and molecular dynamics is to represent the mechanical system in so-called <it>internal coordinates</it> corresponding to unconstrained independent degrees of freedom of the system.  For example, the dihedral angles of a protein are an independent set of coordinates that specify the positions of all the atoms without requiring any constraints.  The difficulty of such internal-coordinate approaches is twofold: the Newtonian equations of motion become much more complex and the internal coordinates may be difficult to define for cyclic systems of constraints, e.g., in ring puckering or when a protein has a disulfide bond.</p>
<p>

The original methods for efficient recursive energy minimization in internal coordinates were developed by Gō and coworkers.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> </p>
<p>

Efficient recursive, internal-coordinate constraint solvers were extended to molecular dynamics.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>  Analogous methods were applied later to other systems.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Lagrange multiplier-based methods</st>

<p>

In most <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/198608.xml">
molecular dynamics</link> simulation, constraints are enforced using the method of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/159974.xml">
Lagrange multipliers</link>. Given a set of <it>n</it> linear (holonomic) constraints at the time <it>t</it>,</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\sigma_k^{(t)} := \| \mathbf x_{k\alpha}^{(t)} - \mathbf x_{k\beta}^{(t)} \|_2^2 - d_k^2 = 0, \quad k=1 \dots n</math>
</indent>

where <math>\scriptstyle \mathbf x_{i\alpha}^{(t)}</math> and <math>\scriptstyle\mathbf x_{i\beta}^{(t)}</math> are the positions of the two particles involved in the <it>k</it>th constraint at the time <it>t</it> and <math>d_k</math> is the prescribed inter-particle distance.</p>
<p>

These constraint equations, are added to the potential energy function in the equations of motion, resulting in, for each of the <it>N</it> particles in the system</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\frac{\partial^2 \mathbf x_i^{(t)}}{\partial t^2} m_i = \frac{\partial}{\partial \mathbf x_i} \left[ V(\mathbf x_i^{(t)}) + \sum_{k=1}^n \lambda_k \sigma_k^{(t)} \right], \quad i=1 \dots N.</math>
</indent>

Adding the constraint equations to the potential does not change it, since all <math>\sigma_k^{(t)}</math> should, ideally, be zero.</p>
<p>

Integrating both sides of the equations of motion twice in time yields the constrained particle positions at the time <math>t + \Delta t</math></p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\mathbf x^{(t + \Delta t)}_i = \hat{\mathbf x}^{(t + \Delta t)}_i + \sum_{k=1}^n \lambda_k \frac{\partial\sigma_k^{(t)}}{\partial \mathbf x_i}\left(\Delta t\right)^2m_i^{-1}, \quad i=1 \dots N</math>
</indent>

where <math>\hat{\mathbf x}^{(t + \Delta t)}_i</math> is the unconstrained (or uncorrected) position of the <it>i</it>th particle after integrating the unconstrained equations of motion.</p>
<p>

To satisfy the constraints <math>\sigma_k^{(t + \Delta t)}</math> in the next timestep, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/159974.xml">
Lagrange multipliers</link> must be chosen such that</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\sigma_k^{(t + \Delta t)} := \left\| \mathbf x_{k\alpha}^{(t+\Delta t)} - \mathbf x_{k\beta}^{(t+\Delta t)}\right\|_2^2 - d_k^2 = 0.</math>
</indent>

This implies solving a system of <math>n</math> non-linear equations</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\sigma_j^{(t + \Delta t)} := \left\| \hat{\mathbf x}_{j\alpha}^{(t+\Delta t)} - \hat{\mathbf x}_{j\beta}^{(t+\Delta t)}  +    \sum_{k=1}^n \lambda_k \left[ \frac{\partial\sigma_k^{(t)}}{\partial \mathbf x_{j\alpha}}m_{j\alpha}^{-1} -  \frac{\partial\sigma_k^{(t)}}{\partial \mathbf x_{j\beta}}m_{j\beta}^{-1}\right] \right\|_2^2 - d_k^2 = 0, \quad j = 1 \dots n</math>
</indent>

simultaneously for the <math>n</math> unknown Lagrange multipliers <math>\lambda_k</math>.</p>
<p>

This system of <math>n</math> non-linear equations in <math>n</math> unknowns is best solved using <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/22145.xml">
Newton's method</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 where the solution vector <math>\underline{\lambda}</math> is updated using</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\underline{\lambda}^{(l+1)} \leftarrow \underline{\lambda}^{(l)} - \mathbf J_\sigma^{-1} \underline{\sigma}</math>
</indent>

where <math>\mathbf J_\sigma</math> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../351/195351.xml">
Jacobian</link> of the equations σ<it>k</it>:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\mathbf J = \left( \begin{array}{cccc}
    \frac{\partial\sigma_1}{\partial\lambda_1} &amp; \frac{\partial\sigma_1}{\partial\lambda_2} &amp; \dots &amp; \frac{\partial\sigma_1}{\partial\lambda_n} \\
    \frac{\partial\sigma_2}{\partial\lambda_1} &amp; \frac{\partial\sigma_2}{\partial\lambda_2} &amp; \dots &amp; \frac{\partial\sigma_2}{\partial\lambda_n} \\
    \vdots &amp; \vdots &amp; \ddots &amp; \vdots \\
    \frac{\partial\sigma_n}{\partial\lambda_1} &amp; \frac{\partial\sigma_n}{\partial\lambda_2} &amp; \dots &amp; \frac{\partial\sigma_n}{\partial\lambda_n} \end{array}\right).</math>
</indent>

Since not all particles are involved in all constraints, <math>\mathbf J_\sigma</math> is blockwise-diagonal and can be solved blockwise, i.e. molecule for molecule.</p>
<p>

Furthermore, instead of constantly updating the vector <math>\underline{\lambda}</math>, the iteration is started with <math>\underline{\lambda}^{(0)} = \mathbf 0</math>, resulting in simpler expressions for <math>\sigma_k^{(t)}</math> and <math>\frac{\partial \sigma_k^{(t)}}{\partial \lambda_j}</math>. After each iteration, the unconstrained particle positions are updated using</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\hat{\mathbf x}_i^{(t+\Delta t)} \leftarrow \hat{\mathbf x}_i^{(t+\Delta t)} + \sum_{k=1}^n \lambda_k^{(l)}\frac{\partial \sigma_k}{\partial \mathbf x_i}</math>.
</indent>

The vector is then reset to</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\underline{\lambda}^{(l)} = \mathbf 0.</math>
</indent>

This is repeated until the constraint equations <math>\sigma_k^{(t+\Delta t)}</math> are satisfied up to a prescribed tolerance.</p>
<p>

Although there are a number of algorithms to compute the Lagrange multipliers, they differ only in how they solve the system of equations, usually using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/7883127.xml">
Quasi-Newton methods</link>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
The SETTLE algorithm</st>
<p>

The SETTLE algorithm<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> solves the system of non-linear equations analytically for <math>n=3</math> constraints in constant time. Although it does not scale to larger numbers of constraints, it is very often used to constrain rigid water molecules, which are present in almost all biological simulations and are usually modelled using three constraints (e.g. SPC/E and TIP3P <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/8337703.xml">
water model</link>s).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The SHAKE algorithm</st>
<p>

The SHAKE algorithm was the first algorithm developed to satisfy bond geometry constraints during molecular dynamics simulations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

It solves the system of non-linear constraint equations using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/4046824.xml">
Gauss-Seidel method</link> to approximate the solution of the linear system of equations</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\lambda = -\mathbf J_\sigma^{-1} \underline{\sigma}</math>
</indent>

in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/22145.xml">
Newton iteration</link>. This amounts to assuming that <math>\mathbf J_\sigma</math> is diagonally dominant and solving the <math>k</math>th equation only for the <math>k</math> unknown. In practice, we compute</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

|
</indent>
|<math>\lambda_k</math>
|<math>\leftarrow</math>
|<math>\frac{\sigma_k^{(t)}}{\partial \sigma_k^{(t)}/\partial \lambda_k}</math>
|-
|<math>\mathbf x_{k\alpha}</math>
|<math>\leftarrow</math>
|<math>\mathbf x_{k\alpha} + \lambda_k \frac{\partial \sigma_k^{(t)}}{\partial \mathbf x_{k\alpha}}</math>
|-
|<math>\mathbf x_{k\beta}</math>
|<math>\leftarrow</math>
|<math>\mathbf x_{k\beta} + \lambda_k \frac{\partial \sigma_k^{(t)}}{\partial \mathbf x_{k\beta}}</math>
|}</p>
<p>

for all <math>k=1\dots n</math> iteratively until the constraint equations <math>\sigma_k^{(t+\Delta t)}</math> are solved to a given tolerance.</p>
<p>

Each iteration of the SHAKE algorithm costs <math>\mathcal O(n)</math> operations and the iterations themselves converge linearly.</p>
<p>

A noniterative form of SHAKE was developed later.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

Several variants of the SHAKE algorithm exist. Although they differ in how they compute or apply the constraints themselves, the constraints are still modelled using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/159974.xml">
Lagrange multipliers</link> which are computed using the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/4046824.xml">
Gauss-Seidel method</link>.</p>
<p>

The original SHAKE algorithm is limited to mechanical systems with a tree structure, i.e., no closed loops of constraints.  A later extension of the method, QSHAKE (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/51440.xml">
Quaternion</link> SHAKE) was developed to amend this.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>  It works satisfactorily for <it>rigid</it> loops such as aromatic ring systems but fails for flexible loops, such as when a protein has a disulfide bond.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>
<p>

Further extensions include RATTLE<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>, WIGGLE<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref> and MSHAKE<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>.
RATTLE works the same way as SHAKE, yet using the <link>
Velocity Verlet</link> time integration scheme. WIGGLE extends SHAKE and RATTLE by using an initial estimate for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/159974.xml">
Lagrange multipliers</link> <math>\lambda_k</math> based on the particle velocities. Finally, MSHAKE computes corrections on the constraint <it>forces</it>, achieving better convergence.</p>
<p>

A final modification is the P-SHAKE algorithm<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> for rigid or semi-rigid molecules. P-SHAKE computes and updates a pre-conditioner which is applied to the constraint gradients before the SHAKE iteration, causing the Jacobian <math>\mathbf J_\sigma</math> to become diagonal or strongly diagonally dominant. The thus de-coupled constraints converge much faster (quadratically as opposed to linearly) at a cost of <math>\mathcal O(n^2)</math>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The M-SHAKE algorithm</st>
<p>

The M-SHAKE algorithm<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref> solves the non-linear system of equations using <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846932" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<procedure wordnetid="101023820" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<algorithm wordnetid="105847438" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../145/22145.xml">
Newton's method</link></algorithm>
</activity>
</procedure>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</rule>
</event>
 directly. In each iteration, the linear system of equations</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\underline{\lambda} \leftarrow -\mathbf J_\sigma^{-1} \underline{\sigma}</math>
</indent>

is solved exactly using an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/6243993.xml">
LU decomposition</link>. Each iteration costs <math>\mathcal O(n^3)</math> operations, yet the solution converges <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/999701.xml">
quadratically</link>, requiring fewer iterations than SHAKE.</p>
<p>

This solution was first proposed in 1986 by Ciccotti and Ryckaert<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> under the title "the matrix method", yet differed in the solution of the linear system of equations. Ciccotti and Ryckaert suggest inverting the matrix <math>\mathbf J_\sigma</math> directly, yet doing so only once, in the fist iteration. The first iteration then costs <math>\mathcal O(n^3)</math> operations, whereas the following iterations cost only <math>\mathcal O(n^2)</math> operations (for the matrix-vector multiplication). This improvement comes at a cost though, since the Jacobian is no longer updated, convergence is only <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../701/999701.xml">
linear</link>, albeit at a much faster rate than for the SHAKE algorithm.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
The LINCS algorithm</st>

<p>

An alternative constraint method, LINCS (Linear Constraint Solver) was developed in 1997,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> but was based on earlier method, EEM,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> and a modification thereof.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref>  LINCS has been reported to be 3-4 times faster than SHAKE.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref></p>
<p>

LINCS applies <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../974/159974.xml">
Lagrange multipliers</link> to the constraint forces and solves for the multipliers by using a series expansion to approximate the inverse of the Jacobian <math>\mathbf J_\sigma</math>:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>(\mathbf I - \mathbf J_\sigma)^{-1} = \mathbf I + \mathbf J_\sigma + \mathbf J_\sigma^2 + \mathbf J_\sigma^3 + \dots</math>
</indent>

in each step of the Newton iteration. The inversion only works for matrices with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/2161429.xml">
Eigenvalues</link> smaller than 1, making the algorithm suitable only for molecules with low connectivity.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Hybrid methods</st>

<p>

Hybrid methods have also been introduced in which the constraints are divided into two groups; the constraints of the first group are solved using internal coordinates whereas those of the second group are solved using constraint forces, e.g., by a Lagrange multiplier or projection method.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref>  This approach was pioneered by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/87793.xml">
Lagrange</link></scientist>
</person>
,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> and result in <it>Lagrange equations of the mixed type</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../608/198608.xml">
Molecular dynamics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/12207850.xml">
Software for molecular mechanics modeling</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References and footnotes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite id="Reference-Laplace-1788" style="font-style:normal" class="book"><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/344783.xml">
Laplace, PS</link>&#32;(1788). Mécanique analytique.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Noguti T; Gō N&#32;(1983).&#32;"A Method of Rapid Calculation of a 2nd Derivative Matrix of Conformational Energy for Large Molecules". <it>Journal of the Physical Society of Japan</it>&#32;<b>52</b>: 3685–3690. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1143%2FJPSJ.52.3685">
10.1143/JPSJ.52.3685</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Abe, H; Braun W, Noguti T, Gō N&#32;(1984).&#32;"Rapid Calculation of 1st and 2nd Derivatives of Conformational Energy with respect to Dihedral Angles for Proteins: General Recurrent Equations". <it>Computers and Chemistry</it>&#32;<b>8</b>: 239–247. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2F0097-8485%2884%2985015-9">
10.1016/0097-8485(84)85015-9</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Bae, D-S; Haug EJ&#32;(1988).&#32;"A Recursive Formulation for Constrained Mechanical System Dynamics: Part I. Open Loop Systems". <it>Mechanics of Structures and Machines</it>&#32;<b>15</b>: 359–382.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Jain, A; Vaidehi N, Rodriguez G&#32;(1993).&#32;"A Fast Recursive Algorithm for Molecular Dynamics Simulation". <it>Journal of Computational Physics</it>&#32;<b>106</b>: 258–268.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Rice, LM; Brünger AT&#32;(1994).&#32;"Torsion Angle Dynamics: Reduced Variable Conformational Sampling Enhances Crystallographic Structure Refinement". <it>Proteins: Structure, Function, and Genetics</it>&#32;<b>19</b>: 277–290. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2Fprot.340190403">
10.1002/prot.340190403</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Mathiowetz, AM; Jain A, Karasawa N, Goddard III, WA&#32;(1994).&#32;"Protein Simulations Using Techniques Suitable for Very Large Systems: The Cell Multipole Method for Nonbond Interactions and the Newton-Euler Inverse Mass Operator Method for Internal Coordinate Dynamics". <it>Proteins: Structure, Function, and Genetics</it>&#32;<b>20</b>: 227–247. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2Fprot.340200304">
10.1002/prot.340200304</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Mazur, AK&#32;(1997).&#32;"Quasi-Hamiltonian Equations of Motion for Internal Coordinate Molecular Dynamics of Polymers". <it>Journal of Computational Chemistry</it>&#32;<b>18</b>: 1354–1364. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2F%28SICI%291096-987X%28199708%2918%3A111354%3A%3AAID-JCC3%3E3.0.CO%3B2-K">
10.1002/(SICI)1096-987X(199708)18:111354::AID-JCC3&amp;gt;3.0.CO;2-K</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Miyamoto, S; Kollman PA&#32;(1992).&#32;"SETTLE: An Analytical Version of the SHAKE and RATTLE Algorithm for Rigid Water Models". <it>Journal of Computational Chemistry</it>&#32;<b>13</b>: 952–962. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2Fjcc.540130805">
10.1002/jcc.540130805</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ryckaert, J-P; Ciccotti G, Berendsen HJC&#32;(1977).&#32;"Numerical Integration of the Cartesian Equations of Motion of a System with Constraints: Molecular Dynamics of n-Alkanes". <it>Journal of Computational Physics</it>&#32;<b>23</b>: 327–341. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2F0021-9991%2877%2990098-5">
10.1016/0021-9991(77)90098-5</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Yoneya, M; Berendsen HJC, Hirasawa K&#32;(1994).&#32;"A Noniterative Matrix Method for Constraint Molecular-Dynamics Simulations". <it>Molecular Simulations</it>&#32;<b>13</b>: 395–405. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080%2F08927029408022001">
10.1080/08927029408022001</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Forester, TR; Smith W&#32;(1998).&#32;"SHAKE, Rattle, and Roll: Efficient Constraint Algorithms for Linked Rigid Bodies". <it>Journal of Computational Chemistry</it>&#32;<b>19</b>: 102–111. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2F%28SICI%291096-987X%2819980115%2919%3A1102%3A%3AAID-JCC9%3E3.0.CO%3B2-T">
10.1002/(SICI)1096-987X(19980115)19:1102::AID-JCC9&amp;gt;3.0.CO;2-T</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">McBride, C; Wilson MR, Howard JAK&#32;(1998).&#32;"Molecular dynamics simulations of liquid crystal phases using atomistic potentials". <it>Molecular Physics</it>&#32;<b>93</b>: 955–964. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080%2F002689798168655">
10.1080/002689798168655</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Andersen, Hans C.&#32;(1983).&#32;"RATTLE: A "Velocity" Version of the SHAKE Algorithm for Molecular Dynamics Calculations". <it>Journal of Computational Physics</it>&#32;<b>52</b>: 24–34. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2F0021-9991%2883%2990014-1">
10.1016/0021-9991(83)90014-1</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Lee, Sang-Ho; Kim Palmo, Samuel Krimm&#32;(2005).&#32;"WIGGLE: A new constrained molecular dynamics algorithm in Cartesian coordinates". <it>Journal of Computational Physics</it>&#32;<b>210</b>: 171–182. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.jcp.2005.04.006">
10.1016/j.jcp.2005.04.006</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gonnet, Pedro&#32;(2007).&#32;"P-SHAKE: A quadratically convergent SHAKE in <math>\mathcal O(n^2)</math>". <it>Journal of Computational Physics</it>&#32;<b>220</b>: 740–750. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.jcp.2006.05.032">
10.1016/j.jcp.2006.05.032</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Lambrakos, S. G.; J. P. Boris, E. S. Oran, I. Chandrasekhar, M. Nagumo&#32;(1989).&#32;"A Modified SHAKE algorithm for Maintaining Rigid Bonds in Molecular Dynamics Simulations of Large Molecules". <it>Journal of Computational Physics</it>&#32;<b>85</b>: 473–486. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2F0021-9991%2889%2990160-5">
10.1016/0021-9991(89)90160-5</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="19">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ciccotti, G.; J. P. Ryckaert&#32;(1986).&#32;"Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Rigid Molecules". <it>Computer Physics Reports</it>&#32;<b>4</b>: 345–392. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2F0167-7977%2886%2990022-5">
10.1016/0167-7977(86)90022-5</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kräutler, Vincent; W. F. van Gunsteren, P. H. Hünenberger&#32;(2001).&#32;"A Fast SHAKE Algorithm to Solve Distance Constraint Equations for Small Molecules in Molecular Dynamics Simulations". <it>Journal of Computational Chemistry</it>&#32;<b>22</b>&#32;(5): 501–508. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2F1096-987X%2820010415%2922%3A5501%3A%3AAID-JCC1021%3E3.0.CO%3B2-V">
10.1002/1096-987X(20010415)22:5501::AID-JCC1021&amp;gt;3.0.CO;2-V</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="21">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Edberg, R; Evans DJ, Morriss GP&#32;(1986).&#32;"Constrained Molecular-Dynamics Simulations of Liquid Alkanes with a New Algorithm". <it>Journal of Chemical Physics</it>&#32;<b>84</b>: 6933–6939. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1063%2F1.450613">
10.1063/1.450613</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hess, B; Bekker H, Berendsen HJC, Fraaije JGEM&#32;(1997).&#32;"LINCS: A Linear Constraint Solver for Molecular Simulations". <it>Journal of Computational Chemistry</it>&#32;<b>18</b>: 1463–1472. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2F%28SICI%291096-987X%28199709%2918%3A121463%3A%3AAID-JCC4%3E3.0.CO%3B2-H">
10.1002/(SICI)1096-987X(199709)18:121463::AID-JCC4&amp;gt;3.0.CO;2-H</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="23">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Mazur, AK&#32;(1999).&#32;"Symplectic integration of closed chain rigid body dynamics with internal coordinate equations of motion". <it>Journal of Chemical Physics</it>&#32;<b>111</b>: 1407–1414. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1063%2F1.479399">
10.1063/1.479399</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="22">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Baranyai, A; Evans DJ&#32;(1990).&#32;"New Algorithm for Constrained Molecular-Dynamics Simulation of Liquid Benzene and Naphthalene". <it>Molecular Physics</it>&#32;<b>70</b>: 53–63. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080%2F00268979000100841">
10.1080/00268979000100841</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="25">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Rodriguez, G; Jain A, Kreutz-Delgado K&#32;(1991).&#32;"A Spatial Operator Algebra for Manipulator Modeling and Control". <it>The International Journal for Robotics Research</it>&#32;<b>10</b>: 371–381. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177%2F027836499101000406">
10.1177/027836499101000406</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="24">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Bae, D-S; Haug EJ&#32;(1988).&#32;"A Recursive Formulation for Constrained Mechanical System Dynamics: Part II. Closed Loop Systems". <it>Mechanics of Structures and Machines</it>&#32;<b>15</b>: 481–506.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="26">
 <cite id="Reference-Sommerfeld-1952" style="font-style:normal" class="book"><person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../639/213639.xml">
Sommerfeld, Arnold</link></scientist>
</person>
&#32;(1952). Lectures on Theoretical Physics, Vol. I: Mechanics.&#32;New York:&#32;Academic Press. ISBN-10 0126546703.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</mathematical_statement>
</equation>
</message>
</statement>
</article>
