<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:54:50[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<know-how  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105616786">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<method  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105660268">
<header>
<title>De novo protein structure prediction</title>
<id>9378673</id>
<revision>
<id>226948598</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-21T07:07:52Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>PrairePotatoe</username>
<id>3491057</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Protein structure</category>
<category>Protein methods</category>
<category>Bioinformatics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In computational biology, <b><it>de novo</it></b><b> protein structure prediction</b> is the task of estimating a protein's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/31032.xml">
tertiary structure</link> from its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/24511.xml">
sequence</link> alone.  The problem is very difficult and has occupied leading scientists for decades.  Research has focused in three areas: alternate lower-resolution representations of proteins, accurate energy functions, and efficient sampling methods.  At present, the most successful methods have a reasonable probability of predicting the fold of a small protein domain within 5 Angstroms.
This Structure Prediction algorithm uses the laws of Physics and Chemistry, to find the minimum energy conformation.<p>

De novo protein structure prediction methods attempt to predict tertiary structures from sequences based on general principles that govern protein folding energetics and/or statistical tendencies of conformational features that native structures acquire, without the use of explicit templates. A general paradigm for de novo prediction involves sampling the conformational space, guided by scoring functions and other sequence-dependent biases, such that a large set of candidate (“decoy”) structures are generated, and then selecting native-like conformations from those decoys using scoring functions as well as conformer clustering. High-resolution refinement is sometimes used as a final step to fine-tune native-like structures. There are two major classes of scoring functions. Physics-based functions are based on mathematical models describing aspects of the known physics of molecular interaction. Knowledge-based functions are formed with statistical models capturing aspects of the properties of native protein conformations.</p>
<p>

Ab initio- or de novo- protein modelling methods seek to build three-dimensional protein models "from scratch", i.e., based on physical principles rather than (directly) on previously solved structures. There are many possible procedures that either attempt to mimic protein folding or apply some stochastic method to search possible solutions (i.e., global optimization of a suitable energy function). These procedures tend to require vast computational resources, and have thus only been carried out for tiny proteins. To predict protein structure de novo for larger proteins will require better algorithms and larger computational resources like those afforded by either powerful supercomputers (such as Blue Gene or MDGRAPE-3) or distributed computing (such as Folding@home, the Human Proteome Folding Project and Rosetta@Home). Although these computational barriers are vast, the potential benefits of structural genomics (by predicted or experimental methods) make ab initio structure prediction an active research field.</p>



</bdy>
</method>
</entity>
</know-how>
</article>
