<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:52:48[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>SmarterChild</title>
<id>946226</id>
<revision>
<id>244541625</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T09:49:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ossmann</username>
<id>6395239</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Instant messaging</category>
<category>Chatterbots</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<b>SmarterChild</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/148349.xml">
chatterbot</link> available on the <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<client wordnetid="109985075" confidence="0.8">
<traveler wordnetid="109629752" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<case wordnetid="109898892" confidence="0.8">
<messenger wordnetid="110311021" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
AOL Instant Messenger</link></messenger>
</case>
</causal_agent>
</traveler>
</client>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/19011063.xml">
Windows Live Messenger</link></software>
 networks.  The entity is the property of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/8205445.xml">
Colloquis</link> (formerly ActiveBuddy), a company that develops IM based "Automated Service Agents". Colloquis was acquired by Microsoft on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/22530.xml">
October 12</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>.  SmarterChild is now part of the Microsoft <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/19011063.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22i=E2=80=99m+initiative%22])">
I'm Initiative</link></software>
.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Features</st>
<p>

Rather than mimicking human conversation (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/10235.xml">
ELIZA</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../447/405447.xml">
PARRY</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/3075657.xml">
A.L.I.C.E</link>),  Smarterchild translates everyday-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/17524.xml">
language</link> User input into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/8377.xml">
database</link> queries, initially giving the user access to licensed content, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/73231.xml">
weather forecasts</link>, news and stock quotes and also included basic information retrieval tools such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../253/9253.xml">
encyclopedia</link> entries, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/7931.xml">
dictionaries</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../593/7593.xml">
calculators</link> etc. ActiveBuddy then introduced features beyond simple information retrieval and chat, such as setting reminders, notebook, and sending messages about crushes to other users<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Partnership between SmarterChild and AOL</st>
<p>

Broadcasting messages over the instant messaging networks operated by America Online (AOL) (and to a lesser extent Yahoo and MSN Messenger) required some changes to those systems, as AOL had never envisioned one of its members needing to hold 250,000 simultaneous conversations. As a result, ActiveBuddy consulted with AOL, and AOL changed its infrastructure to enable the new technology. In exchange for this, AOL wanted access to the revenue generated by SmarterChild and the other agents now "living" on its network.</p>
<p>

Initially, ActiveBuddy wanted to sell advertisements within the content delivered via SmarterChild's conversations, using the context of the conversation as a means to deliver highly targeted messages. Because SmarterChild knew what types of conversations each user engaged in, ActiveBuddy would theoretically be able to send advertisements catered to their unique preferences. SmarterChild would also learn more about its users the more time it engaged in conversation, remembering information like birthdays, addresses, pets' names, favorite colors, etc. in the name of creating a more genuine artificial friend. Increased familiarity would, of course, also mean a better way to target advertising.</p>
<p>

AOL's involvement in the advertising sales process hampered ActiveBuddy's ability to see any real revenue from SmarterChild, as ActiveBuddy's sales team were forced to focus only on existing AOL advertisers. ActiveBuddy introduced features beyond simple information retrieval and chat, such as setting reminders, notebook, and sending messages about crushes to other users. In order to redefine the application, ActiveBuddy temporarily suspended the application in June 2002<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> (12 months after its initial release) with plans to relaunch it as a pay service<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>. The relaunch of SmarterChild in April 2003 was met with some reluctance, as millions of users had either moved onto other applications or did not see enough utility in the new applications to justify the $9.95 per year subscription fee<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>. With lagging numbers and little revenue from subscriptions, SmarterChild was reborn as a free service in April 2004. </p>
<p>

In subsequent years the audience for SmarterChild returned; as of November 2006, its buddy list featured more than 20 million unique names. SmarterChild remains extremely popular, and advertisements now appear in its messages. Microsoft's recent purchase of Colloquis will see SmarterChild become the centerpiece of the Windows Live Messenger initiative.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2006/Oct06/10-12ColloquisAcquisitionPR.mspx">
Microsoft Acquires Colloquis to Enhance User Interactions Online: Uses include customer self-service, enterprise information access, marketing and community outreach</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imessengr.com/2007/01/smarterchild-bot-for-aim-msn-icq.html">
SmarterChild - Bot for AIM, MSN, ICQ</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.com.com/Answer+service+too+popular+for+AIM/2100-1023_3-941062.html">
"Answer service too popular for AIM"</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.atnewyork.com/news/article.php/2176961/">
"SmarterChild Goes Premium"</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDF1F31F93AA15756C0A9659C8B63">
"At $10 a Year, Automated Buddy Loses Laughs"</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://smarterchild.colloquis.com/</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=smarterchild</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
