<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:57:08[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Tsui Ming-sum</title>
<id>9463905</id>
<revision>
<id>125480374</id>
<timestamp>2007-04-24T11:28:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Waacstats</username>
<id>1951353</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Academics</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Articles lacking reliable references from April 2007</category>
<category>All articles lacking sources</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section needs  that appear in reliable, third-party publications.</b>
s and sources affiliated with the subject of the article are generally not sufficient for a Wikipedia article. Please include more appropriate  from , or discuss the issue on the talk page. <it>(April 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>



<b>Dr. Ming-sum TSUI</b>, an associate professor in the Department of Applied Social Sciences at the <school wordnetid="108276720" confidence="0.8">
<nursing_school wordnetid="108283757" confidence="0.8">
<educational_institution wordnetid="108276342" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/268078.xml">
Hong Kong Polytechnic University</link></institution>
</educational_institution>
</nursing_school>
</school>
, has 25 years of experience in practising and teaching social work supervision. Before joining the Hong Kong Polytechnic University, he was Service Supervisor of Development and Health Services of Hong Kong Christian Service. Ming-sum set up the first community-based family service centre and the first counselling centre for psychotropic substance abusers in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../404/13404.xml">
Hong Kong</link></country>
. He also supervised a polyclinic and was responsible for program development, fund raising, program evaluation, and staff development of Hong Kong Christian Service — an NGO with 500 staff. <p>

Ming-sum received his MSW from <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/7954643.xml">
McGill University</link></university>
, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../681/7954681.xml">
Montreal</link></village>
, <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
. He is a member of the Academy of Certified Social Workers (ACSW), the first international member of Certified Social Work Managers (CSWM), a member of the Chartered Management Institute (MCMI), and a Certified ISO Auditor. Ming-sum earned his PhD at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/7955325.xml">
University of Toronto</link></university>
. His doctoral research was on the construction of a culturally sensitive model of social work supervision. </p>
<p>

The research interests of Ming-sum are related to social work supervision, human service management, human capital development, theory and practice of social work, and substance abuse. He has published 11 books, including <it>Social Work Supervision: Contexts and Concepts</it> (Sage, 2005) and <it>Social Work Supervision: Theories, Practice and Reflections</it> (co-authored with Dr. Wui-shing HO, published in Chinese), and 80 journal articles, book chapters, and research papers. He also serves as an editor and expert reviewer for 18 professional journals. </p>
<p>

Selected journal articles include: </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S. (1997).  The roots of social work supervision: An historical review.  <it>The Clinical Supervisor</it>, 15(2), 191-198.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S. (1997).  Empirical research on social work supervision: The state of the art (1970-1995).  <it>Journal of Social Service Research</it>, 23(2), 39-54.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S., &amp; Ho, W. S. (1997).  In search of a comprehensive model of social work supervision.  <it>The Clinical Supervisor</it>, 16(2), 181-205.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S. (1998). A job performance model of professional social workers. <it>Asia Pacific Journal of Social Work</it>, 8(2), 51-63. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S. (2000).  Harm reduction approach revisited: An international perspective. <it>International Social Work</it>, 43(2), 243-251.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S., &amp; Ho, W. S. (2000). Alcohol use and family violence: The relationship revisited. <it>Asia Pacific Journal of Social Work</it>, 10(2), 101-111.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S., Cheung, F.C. H., &amp; Gellis, Z. D. (2004). In search of an optimal model for board-executive relationships in voluntary human service organizations. <it>International Social Work</it>, 47(2), 169-186.   </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S., &amp; Cheung, F. C. H. (2004). Gone with the wind: The impacts of managerialism on human services. <it>The British Journal of Social Work</it>, 34, 437-442.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S. (2004). The supervisory relationship of Chinese social workers in Hong Kong. <it>The Clinical Supervisor</it>, 22(2), 99-120. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S. (2005). Supervision models in social work: From nature to culture. <it>Asian Journal of Counselling</it>, 11(1&amp;2), 1-49. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S. (2005). Functions of social work supervision in Hong Kong. <it>International Social Work</it>. 48(4), 485-493.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S., Ho, W. S., &amp; Lam, C. M. (2005). The use of supervisory authority in Chinese cultural context. <it>Administration in Social Work</it>. 29(4), 51-68. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsien, T. B. K., &amp; Tsui, M. S. (in press, 2006). A participative learning and teaching model: Partnership of student and teachers in practice teaching. <it>Social Work Education</it>. Vol. 25.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tsui, M. S. (in press). Hopes and dreams: Ideal supervision for social workers in Hong Kong. <it>Asia Pacific Journal of Social Work and Development</it>. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Chan, C., Tsui, M. S., Ho, W.S., Chan, M., &amp; Hong, J. (in press). Evaluation of WebCT social work education: Can the virtual learning environment enhance learning and teaching. <it>Journal of Teaching in Social Work</it>.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</bdy>
</article>
