<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:57:44[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<process  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105701363">
<thinking  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105770926">
<explanation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105793000">
<theory  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105989479">
<higher_cognitive_process  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105770664">
<header>
<title>Pluralism (political theory)</title>
<id>9484485</id>
<revision>
<id>242455859</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T08:59:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>JAnDbot</username>
<id>1725149</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Political science theories</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about a political theory called "pluralism".&#32;&#32;For the idea of "pluralism" in politics as acknowledgment of diversity, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/201537.xml">
Pluralism (political philosophy)</link>.&#32;&#32;For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/9482079.xml">
Pluralism</link>.&#32;&#32;
The <b>political theory of pluralism</b> holds that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/604028.xml">
political power</link> in society does not lie with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/232021.xml">
electorate</link>, nor with a small concentrated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/2222376.xml">
elite</link>, but is distributed between a wide number of groups. These groups may be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/17626.xml">
trade unions</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/961742.xml">
interest groups</link>, business organizations, and any of a multitude of formal and informal coalitions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> 
<sec>
<st>
Classical pluralism</st>

<p>

Classical pluralism is the belief that politics and decision making is located mostly in the governmental framework, but many non-governmental groups are using their resources to exert influence. The central question for classical pluralism is how power is distributed in western democracies. Groups of individuals try to maximize their interests. Lines of conflict are multiple and shifting. There may be inequalities but they tend to be distributed and even out. Any change under this view will be slow and incremental, as groups have different interests and may act as "veto groups" to destroy legislation that they do not agree with. The existence of diverse and competing interests is the basis for a <link>
democratic equilibrium</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>, and is crucial for the obtaining of goals by individuals. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/1081047.xml">
polyarchy</link> - a situation of open competition for electoral support within a significant part of the adult population - ensures competition of group interests. Pluralists stress civil rights, such as freedom of expression and organization, and an electoral system with at least two parties. On the other hand, since the participants in this process constitute only a tiny fraction of the populace, the public acts mainly as bystanders. This is not undesirable: political issues require continuous and expert attention, which the average citizen does not have.</p>
<p>

Important theorists of pluralism are <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/723243.xml">
Robert A. Dahl</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, who wrote the seminal pluralist work, <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../813/3446813.xml">
Who Governs?</link></it>, and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<sociologist wordnetid="110620758" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/2253929.xml">
Seymour Martin Lipset</link></sociologist>
</person>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Pluralist conception of power </st>

<p>

Pluralists emphasize that power is not a physical entity that individuals either have or do not have, but flows from a variety of different sources. Rather, people are powerful because they control various resources. Resources are assets that can be used to force others to do what one wants. Politicians become powerful because they command resources that people want or fear or respect. The list of possibilities is virtually endless: legal authority, money, prestige, skill, knowledge, charisma, legitimacy, free time, experience, celebrity, and public support.</p>
<p>

Pluralists also stress the differences between potential and actual power as it stands. Actual power means the ability to compel someone to do something; potential power refers to the possibility of turning resources into actual power. Cash, one of many resources, is only a stack of bills until it is put to work. Martin Luther King Jr., for example, was certainly not a rich person. But by using resources such as his forceful personality, organizational skills, and especially the legitimacy of his cause, he had a greater impact on American politics than most wealthy people. A particular resource like money cannot automatically be equated with power because the resource can be used skillfully or clumsily, fully or partially, or not at all.</p>
<p>

The pluralist approach to the study of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../028/604028.xml">
power</link>, states that nothing categorical about power can be assumed in any community. The question then is not who runs a community, but if any group in fact does.  To determine this, pluralists study specific outcomes.  The reason for this is that they believe human behavior is governed in large part by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/14909.xml">
inertia</link>.  That said, actual involvement in overt activity is a more valid marker of leadership than simply a reputation.  Pluralists also believe that there is no one particular issue or point in time at which any group must assert itself to stay true to its own expressed values, but rather that there are a variety of issues and points at which this is possible.  There are also costs involved in taking action at all—not only losing, but expenditure of time and effort. While a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/27763.xml">
structuralist</link> may argue that power distributions have a rather permanent nature, this <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../194/8458194.xml">
rationale</link> says that power may in fact be tied to issues, which vary widely in duration. Also, instead of focusing on actors within a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/8286675.xml">
system</link>, the emphasis is on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/130918.xml">
leadership</link> roles itself.  By studying these, it can be determined to what extent there is a power structure present in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/37235.xml">
society</link>.</p>
<p>

Three of the major tenets of the pluralist school are (1)resources and hence potential power are widely scattered throughout society; (2) at least some resources are available to nearly everyone; and (3) at any time the amount of potential power exceeds the amount of actual power. </p>
<p>

Finally, and perhaps most important, no one is all-powerful. An individual or group that is influential in one realm may be weak in another. Large military contractors certainly throw their weight around on defense matters, but how much sway do they have on agricultural or health policies? A measure of power, therefore, is its scope, or the range of areas where it is successfully applied. Pluralists believe that with few exceptions power holders usually have a relatively limited scope of influence.</p>
<p>

For all these reasons power cannot be taken for granted. One has to observe it empirically in order to know who really governs. The best way to do this, pluralists believe, is to examine a wide range of specific decisions, noting who took which side and who ultimately won and lost. Only by keeping score on a variety of controversies can one begin to identify actual power holders. Pluralism was associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/540715.xml">
behavioralism</link><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Partisan mutual adjustment</st>
<p>

Policy takes place in a crowded arena, and no group or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/713312.xml">
political faction</link> is powerful enough to dominate the others. Policy emerges as a compromise between the various interest groups. This brings along a specific rationale: each group adjusts its stance to take into consideration the others to promote stability, because even if a group loses out <it>this</it> time, this means it still retains the ability to fight another day.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Elite pluralism</st>

<p>

There were some objections to this model of pluralism. However, critics argue that groups need a high level of resources and the support of patrons to contend for influence. This observation formed the basis for elite pluralism. This modified pluralism account for elements of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/8130927.xml">
elite theory</link> and was advanced by writers such as <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../690/445690.xml">
Elmer Eric Schattschneider</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 who wrote that "The flaw in the pluralist heaven is that the heavenly chorus sings with a strong upper-class accent."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Neo-pluralism</st>
<p>

While Pluralism as a political theory of the state and policy formation gained its most traction during the 1950s and 1960s in America, some scholars argued that the theory was too simplistic (see Connolly (1969) <it>The Challenge to Pluralist Theory</it>) - leading to the formulation of neo-pluralism. Views differed about the division of power in democratic society. Although neo-pluralism  sees multiple pressure groups competing over political influence, the political agenda is biased towards corporate power.  Neo-pluralism no longer sees the state as an umpire mediating and adjudicating between the demands of different interest groups, but as a relatively  autonomous actor (with different departments) that forges and looks after its own (sectional) interests. Constitutional rules, that in pluralism are embedded in a supportive political culture, should be seen in the context of a diverse, and not necessarily supportive, political culture and a system of radically uneven economic sources. This diverse culture exists because of an uneven distribution of socioeconomic power. This creates possibilities for some groups - while limiting others - in their political options.  
In the international realm, order is distorted by powerful <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../299/239299.xml">
multinational</link> interests and dominant states, while in classical pluralism emphasis is put on stability by a framework of pluralist rules and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/11826.xml">
free market</link> society. </p>
<p>

There are two significant theoretical critiques on pluralism: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/7769.xml">
Corporatism</link> and <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../156/1865156.xml">
Neo-Marxism</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Charles Lindblom</st>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/3106890.xml">
Charles E. Lindblom</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, who is seen as positing a strong neo-pluralist argument, still attributed primacy to the competition between <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../742/961742.xml">
interest group</link>s in the policy process but recognized the disproportionate influence business interests have in the policy process. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Corporatism</st>
<p>

Classical pluralism was criticized as it did not seem to apply to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../782/33782.xml">
Westminster-style</link> democracies or the European context. This led to the development of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/7769.xml">
corporatist</link> theories. Corporatism is the idea that a few select interest groups are actually (often formally) involved in the policy formulation process, to the exclusion of the myriad other 'interest groups'. For example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/17626.xml">
trade union</link>s and major sectoral business associations are often consulted about (if not the drivers of) specific policies. </p>
<p>

These policies often concern tripartite relations between workers, employers and the state, with a coordinating role for the latter. The state constructs a framework in which it can address the political and economic issues with these organized and centralized groups. In this view, parliament and party politics lose influence in the policy forming process.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/8130927.xml">
Elite theory</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/606522.xml">
New institutionalism</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<paradigm wordnetid="113804375" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<linguistic_relation wordnetid="113797142" confidence="0.8">
<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<inflection wordnetid="113803782" confidence="0.8">
<motion wordnetid="100331950" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<grammatical_relation wordnetid="113796779" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../053/1904053.xml">
Marxism</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</grammatical_relation>
</psychological_feature>
</motion>
</inflection>
</act>
</action>
</event>
</thinking>
</process>
</linguistic_relation>
</theory>
</explanation>
</change>
</paradigm>
</political_orientation>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
State autonomy theory</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Overloaded Government</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../711/6052711.xml">
Legitimation Crisis</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Socialstudieshelp.com, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.socialstudieshelp.com/APGOV_pluralism.htm">
Pluralism</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
Held, David, Models of Democracy</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.socialstudieshelp.com/APGOV_pluralism.htm">
Pluralism</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
Schattschneider, E.E. 1960. <it>The Semi-Sovereign People</it>. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, p. 35.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Socialstudieshelp.com, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.socialstudieshelp.com/APGOV_pluralism.htm">
Pluralism</weblink>. Accessed 13 February, 2007. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Schattschneider, E.E. (1960) <it>The Semi-Sovereign People</it>. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<theorist wordnetid="110706812" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/14847704.xml">
Gad Barzilai</link></scientist>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</theorist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 (2003) <it>Communities and Law: Politics and Cultures of Legal Identities.</it> Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Polsby, Nelson W.  (1960) How to Study Community Power: The Pluralist Alternative. <it>The Journal of Politics,  (22)3</it>, 474-484</entry>
</list>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
</article>
