<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:46:31[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<header>
<title>Illinois Security Lab</title>
<id>9485191</id>
<revision>
<id>178495791</id>
<timestamp>2007-12-17T13:08:56Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Computer security organizations</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>Illinois Security Lab</b> is a research laboratory at the 
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/384695.xml">
University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</link> established in 2004 to support research and education in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../398/7398.xml">
computer</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../687/592687.xml">
network security</link>.  The lab is part of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/384695.xml">
UIUC</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
Computer Science</link> Department and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/5228765.xml">
Information Trust Institute</link>.  Its research projects concern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/3698136.xml">
critical infrastructure protection</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/261925.xml">
health care</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/41367.xml">
messaging</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/5652.xml">
networking</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/25009.xml">
privacy</link>.<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="ISL-Logo.png">
<caption>

Logo for the Illinois Security Lab
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Projects </st>

<ss1>
<st>
 Secure Control Systems </st>
<p>

Networked <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/275473.xml">
control systems</link> such as the electric <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/38824.xml">
power grid</link> use computers for tasks like protecting <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../189/1094189.xml">
substation</link>s against overloads (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/26590.xml">
protective relays</link>) and metering facilities (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../745/3895745.xml">
advanced meters</link>).  The lab developed the <it>attested meter</it>, a technology for security and privacy of advanced meters, and is working on security for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/2893444.xml">
building automation</link> systems and substation automation.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Assisted Living Security </st>
<p>

Advances in networking, distributed computing, and medical devices are combining with changes in the way health care is financed and the growing number of elderly people to produce strong prospects for the widespread use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/925356.xml">
assisted living</link>, a health care approach which can benefit from transferring medical information collected in homes or dedicated facilities to clinicians over data networks.  The lab explores security engineering of such systems through prototypes, field trials, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/161883.xml">
formal methods</link> based on an architecture that uses a partially-trusted <it>Assisted Living Service Provider (ALSP)</it> as a third party intermediary between assisted persons and clinicians.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Adaptive Messaging Policy (AMPol) </st>
<p>

Scalable distributed systems demand an ability to express and adapt to diverse policies of numerous distinct administrative domains.  The lab introduced technologies for messaging systems with adaptive <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/2842539.xml">
security policies</link> based on <it>WSEmail</it>, where Internet messaging is implemented as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/93483.xml">
web service</link>, and <it>Attribute-Based Messaging (ABM)</it>, where addressing is based on attributes of recipients.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Contessa Network Security </st>
<p>

Although there has been significant progress on the formal analysis of security for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/127859.xml">
integrity</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/353859.xml">
confidentiality</link>, there has been relatively less progress on treating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../776/39776.xml">
denial-of-service attack</link>.  The lab is exploring techniques for doing this based on the <it>shared channel model</it>, which envisions bandwidth as a limiting factor in attacks and focuses on host-based counter-measures such as <it>selective verification</it>, which exploits adversary bandwidth limitations to favor valid parties.  It is also developing new <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/161883.xml">
formal methods</link> for reasoning about dynamic configuration of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../130/147130.xml">
VPN</link>s.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Formal Privacy </st>
<p>

Many new information technologies have a profound impact on privacy.  Threats from these have provoked legislation and calls for deeper regulation.  The lab develops ways to treat privacy rules more formally, including better ways to reason using <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../883/161883.xml">
formal methods</link> about conformance and the implications of regulations, and about how to quantify and classify privacy attitudes to control the risks of new technologies.  Recent work showed how to formally encode <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/384064.xml">
HIPAA</link> consent regulations using <it>privacy APIs</it> so they can be analyzed with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/321157.xml">
model checking</link>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Unified Architecture for Large-Scale Attested Metering, Michael LeMay, George Gross, Carl A. Gunter, and Sanjam Garg. IEEE Hawaii International Conference On System Sciences (HICSS 07), Waikola, Hawaii, January 2007.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Residential energy monitoring and computerized surveillance via utility power flows, G. Hart. IEEE Technology and Society Magazine, pages 12–16, June 1989.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Securing the Drop-Box Architecture for Assisted Living, Michael J. May, Wook Shin, Carl A. Gunter, and Insup Lee. ACM Formal Methods in Security Engineering (FMSE '06), Alexandria, VA, November 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 I-Living: An Open System Architecture for Assisted Living, Qixin Wang, Wook Shin, Xue Liu, Zheng Zeng, Cham Oh, Bedoor K. Alshebli, Marco Caccamo, Carl A. Gunter, Elsa L. Gunter, Jennifer Hou, Karrie Karahalios, and Lui Sha. IEEE Systems, Man, and Cybernetics (SMC '06), Taipei, Taiwan, October 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 WSEmail: Secure Internet Messaging Based on Web Services, Kevin D. Lux, Michael J. May, Nayan L. Bhattad, and Carl A. Gunter. IEEE International Conference on Web Services (ICWS '05), Orlando, Florida, July 2005.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 AMPol: Adaptive Messaging Policy, Raja Afandi, Jianqing Zhang, Munawar Hafiz and Carl A. Gunter. IEEE European Conference on web Services (ECOWS '06), Zurich, Switzerland, December 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Identity based ecncryption from the Weil pairing, D. Boneh and M. Franklin. SIAM J. of Comp., 32(3):586-615, 2003.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Using Attribute-Based Access Control to Enable Attribute-Based Messaging, Rakesh Bobba, Omid Fatemieh, Fariba Khan, Carl A. Gunter, and Himanshu Khurana. IEEE Annual Computer Security Applications Conference (ACSAC '06) , Miami, FL, December 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Secure Role Based Messaging, David Chadwick, Graeme Lunt and Gansen Zhao Issrc. IFIP Conference on Communication and Multimedia (CMS '04), 2004.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DoS Protection for Reliably Authenticated Broadcast, Carl A. Gunter, Sanjeev Khanna, Kaijun Tan, and Santosh Venkatesh. ICSOC Network and Distributed Systems Security Symposium (NDSS '04), San Diego, CA, February 2004.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 DDoS Defense by Offense, Michael Walfish, Mythili Vutukuru, Hari Balakrishnan, David Karger, and Scott Shenker.  ACM SIGCOMM, Pisa, Italy, September 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Privacy APIs: Access Control Techniques to Analyze and Verify Legal Privacy Policies, Michael J. May, Carl A. Gunter, Insup Lee. IEEE Computer Security Foundations Workshop (CSFW 06), Venice, Italy, July 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Verified Interoperable Implementations of Security Protocols, Karthikeyan Bhargavan, Cedric Fournet, Andrew D. Gordon, Stephen Tse. IEEE Computer Security Foundations Workshop (CSFW 06), Venice, Italy, July 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Privacy Sensitive Location Information Systems in Smart Buildings, Jodie P. Boyer, Kaijun Tan and Carl A. Gunter. Springer Security in Pervasive Computing (SPC '06), LNCS, pages 149-164, York, UK, April 2006.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seclab.uiuc.edu">
Illinois Security Lab</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seclab.uiuc.edu/web/critical-infrastructure/attested-metering.html">
Attested Metering</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iti.uiuc.edu/tcip/index.html">
TCIP: Trustworthy Cyber Infrastructure for the Power Grid</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seclab.uiuc.edu/web/health-care/index.php">
Assisted Living Security</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lion.cs.uiuc.edu/assistedliving/">
UIUC Assisted Living Project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seclab.uiuc.edu/web/messaging/index.php">
Adaptive Messaging Policy</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://sels.ncsa.uiuc.edu">
SELS Secure Email List Services</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seclab.uiuc.edu/web/networking/index.php">
Contessa Network Security</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seclab.uiuc.edu/web/privacy/index.php">
Formal Privacy</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</organization>
</article>
