<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:54:13[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>CELTA</title>
<id>952323</id>
<revision>
<id>232110597</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-15T14:21:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jimp</username>
<id>275655</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>English-language education</category>
<category>Professional certification</category>
<category>Acronyms</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

For the Spanish football club, see <association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<club wordnetid="108227214" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../925/7613925.xml">
Celta de Vigo</link></club>
</association>
.
<p>

The <b>Certificate in English Language Teaching to Adults</b>, or <b>CELTA</b> (pronounced ), is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/6251.xml">
professional credential</link> held by many teachers of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/415406.xml">
English as a foreign language</link>.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

The CELTA is a common requirement for those entering the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/415406.xml">
English language teaching</link>. Because it is recognised internationally, it is a particularly popular credential among people who wish to travel and teach English around the world (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/1059235.xml">
TEFL</link> for an extended discussion of travel-teaching). However, it is also held by people who intend to teach only in the country where they trained, and do not intend to travel.</p>
<p>

The full-time CELTA course runs for four weeks; it can also be taken part-time over several months. CELTA courses are run by many different institutions, whereas the courses are validated and certificates are issued by the <division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../571/741571.xml">
University of Cambridge Local Examinations Syndicate</link></department>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
 (UCLES), a part of the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/31796.xml">
University of Cambridge</link></university>
.</p>
<p>

The CELTA is awarded upon passing the course, which includes at least six hours of supervised teaching practice to real English language students, at two different levels. The course grade is determined primarily by the performance of the teacher in this teaching practice; there are also a number of written assignments due throughout the course, which are graded on a pass/fail basis only. The grades awarded are pass, B and A. As of 2000, worldwide five percent of trainees withdrew before completing the course, three percent failed, 63% received a pass, 25% received a grade of B, and four percent received a grade of A.</p>
<p>

The full-time four-week course is very intensive, and students taking it must be prepared to dedicate all their waking hours to it for the duration. Even the part-time version of the course can take up more time than a full-time job for many students, especially those with no teaching background.</p>
<p>

Each year around 900 CELTA courses are run by around 280 centres, primarily language schools, in 54 countries, producing over 10,000 graduates.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Each course is audited by an external assessor.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Accreditation </st>
<p>

The CELTA is awarded by UCLES and accredited by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/292134.xml">
Qualifications and Curriculum Authority</link> for England, Wales and Northern Ireland.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

The current Cambridge CELTA replaced the RSA/Cambridge CELTA in 2001. In 1996, RSA/Cambridge CELTA replaced the RSA/Cambridge CTEFLA (the Certificate in Teaching English as a Foreign Language to Adults)—this was jointly administered by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/85748.xml">
Royal Society of Arts</link> (RSA) and UCLES. The RSA/Cambridge CTEFLA replaced the RSA Certificate in 1985.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Related credentials </st>
<p>

A less common qualification from UCLES is the CELTYL—the Certificate in English Language Teaching to Young Learners. Like the CELTA, it runs as a full-time course for four weeks. It is equal in status, having the same number of hours of instruction, teaching observation, and supervised teaching practice, but focuses on the teaching of children. Candidates who have already been awarded a CELTA can take a "YL extension course" in two weeks, which adds a qualification in teaching young learners to their existing qualification in teaching adults.</p>
<p>

UCLES also offers a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/346772.xml">
diploma</link> in ELT, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/3760381.xml">
DELTA</link>, which can be taken as a follow-up to the CELTA by those seeking further qualifications in the field.</p>
<p>

In order to meet the UK government's criteria for teachers of ESOL in the Learning and Skills Sector (that is, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/214737.xml">
adult education</link>) in England and Wales, holders of CELTA need to undertake an additional qualification, known as CELTA module 2.</p>
<p>

The CELTA and the <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/13016200.xml">
Trinity College</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/3760578.xml">
CertTESOL</link> are often considered to be roughly equivalent qualifications.</p>
<p>

A similar qualification is the CELT, a Certificate in English Language Traning. This is awarded by the Irish Department of Education and Sciences, the advisory Council of English Language Schools.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cambridgeesol.org/teaching/celta.htm">
Cambridge ESOL: Certificate in English Language Teaching to Adults</weblink></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.acels.ie">
Advisory Council of English Language Schools website</weblink></entry>
</list>



</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
