<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:54:16[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Semantic security</title>
<id>960585</id>
<revision>
<id>192426786</id>
<timestamp>2008-02-18T23:34:17Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Nakamura36</username>
<id>6463370</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Theory of cryptography</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Semantic security</b> is a widely-used definition for security in an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/24222.xml">
asymmetric key encryption algorithm</link>.  For a cryptosystem to be semantically secure, it must be infeasible for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../543/7543.xml">
computationally-bounded</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/5340837.xml">
adversary</link> to derive significant information about a message (plaintext) when given only its <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
ciphertext</link> and the corresponding public encryption key.  Semantic security considers only the case of a "passive" attacker, i.e., one who generates and observes ciphertexts using the public key and plaintexts of her choice.  Unlike other security definitions, semantic security does not consider the case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/103586.xml">
chosen ciphertext attack</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/533754.xml">
CCA</link>), where an attacker is able to request the decryption of chosen ciphertexts, and many semantically-secure encryption schemes are demonstrably insecure against chosen ciphertext attack.  Consequently, semantic security is now considered an insufficient condition for securing a general-purpose encryption scheme.<p>

The notion of semantic security was first put forward by Goldwasser and Micali in 1982.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  However, the definition they initially proposed offered no straightforward means to prove the security of practical cryptosystems.  Goldwasser/Micali subsequently demonstrated that semantic security is equivalent to the property of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/2187252.xml">
ciphertext indistinguishability</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  This equivalence allowed for security proofs of practical cryptosystems, and consequently the indistinguishability definition is used more commonly than the original definition of semantic security.</p>
<p>

Indistinguishability under <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../852/63852.xml">
Chosen Plaintext Attack</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../252/2187252.xml">
IND-CPA</link>) is commonly defined by the following <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/18723138.xml">
game</link>:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 A probabilistic polynomial time-bounded adversary is given a public key, which it may use to generate any number of ciphertexts (within polynomial bounds).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The adversary generates two equal-length messages <math>m_0</math> and <math>m_1</math>, and transmits them to a challenge oracle along with the public key.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 The challenge oracle selects one of the messages by flipping a fair coin, encrypts the message under the public key, and returns the resulting ciphertext <math>c</math> to the adversary.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The underlying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/506383.xml">
cryptosystem</link> is IND-CPA (and thus semantically secure under chosen plaintext attack) if the adversary cannot determine which of the two messages was chosen by the oracle, with probability significantly greater than <math>1/2</math> (the success rate of random guessing).  Variants of this definition define indistinguishability under <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/103586.xml">
chosen ciphertext attack</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/426533.xml">
adaptive chosen ciphertext attack</link> (<link>
IND-CCA</link>, <link>
IND-CCA2</link>).</p>
<p>

Because the adversary possesses the public encryption key in the above game, a semantically secure encryption scheme must by definition be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/1051442.xml">
probabilistic</link>, possessing a component of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/19196523.xml">
randomness</link>; if this were not the case, the adversary could simply compute the deterministic encryption of <math>m_0</math> and <math>m_1</math> and compare these encryptions with the returned ciphertext <math>c</math> to successfully guess the oracle's choice.</p>
<p>

Semantically secure encryption algorithms include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/2461162.xml">
Goldwasser-Micali</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/59458.xml">
El Gamal</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/480685.xml">
Paillier</link>.  These schemes are considered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/1182348.xml">
provably secure</link>, as their semantic security can be reduced to solving some hard mathematical problem (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/1198015.xml">
Decisional Diffie-Hellman</link> or the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/1183041.xml">
Quadratic Residuosity Problem</link>).  Other, non-semantically-secure algorithms such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/25385.xml">
RSA</link>, can be made semantically secure (under stronger assumptions) through the use of random encryption padding schemes such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../249/1579249.xml">
Optimal Asymmetric Encryption Padding</link> (OAEP).</p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>
  
<reflist>
<entry id="1">
S. Goldwasser and S. Micali, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=802212">
Probabilistic encryption &amp; how to play mental poker keeping secret all partial information</weblink>, Annual ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing, 1982.</entry>
<entry id="2">
S. Goldwasser and S. Micali, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0022-0000(84)90070-9">
Probabilistic encryption</weblink>. Journal of Computer and System Sciences, 28:270-299, 1984.</entry>
</reflist>

</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
