<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:58:17[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Genetic memory</title>
<id>9654867</id>
<revision>
<id>244342153</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T10:11:36Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Khoikhoi</username>
<id>657950</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Genetics</category>
<category>Parapsychology</category>
<category>Ethology</category>
<category>Evolution</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Genetic memory</b> describes a variety of processes in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biology</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
psychology</link> by which <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/12438.xml">
genetic material</link> confers a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../844/18844.xml">
memory</link> of an individual's or species' past history. It can refer to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/12385.xml">
genetic code</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
DNA</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/49033.xml">
epigenetic</link> changes to the genetic material, the inheritance of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/288316.xml">
instinct</link>, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/489089.xml">
racial memory</link> in psychology. The term is also used for a method of computer prediction.
<sec>
<st>
Biology</st>
<p>
 
In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biology</link>, memory is present if the state of a biological system depends on its past history in addition to present conditions. If this memory is recorded in the genetic material and stably inherited through cell division (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/20369.xml">
mitosis</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/18976.xml">
meiosis</link>), it is genetic.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Molecular biology</st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/19200.xml">
molecular biology</link>, genetic memory resides in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/12438.xml">
genetic material</link> of the cell and is expressed via the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/12385.xml">
genetic code</link> used to translate it into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The genetic code enables cells to decode the information needed to construct the protein molecules that make up living cells and therefore record and store a one-dimensional blueprint for all the parts that make up an organism. This blueprint or genetic memory in the form of species-specific collections of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/4250553.xml">
gene</link>s (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/12796.xml">
genotype</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../388/12388.xml">
genome</link>) is passed from cell to cell and from generation to generation in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
DNA</link> molecules. DNA therefore functions as a template for protein synthesis.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Genetic memory can be modified by <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/49033.xml">
epigenetic</link> memory</it>, a process by which changes in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/159266.xml">
gene expression</link> are passed on through mitosis or meiosis through factors other than DNA sequence.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Somatic memory</st>
<p>

<it>Somatic memory</it> is limited to the organism and not passed on to subsequent generations. However, its mechanism may involve mitotically stable genetic memory. The term applies for cellular memory, animals' memory, and plants' memory, as described in the following paragraphs.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
Cellular memory</st>
<p>

All cells in multicellular organisms are derived from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/981685.xml">
pluripotent</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/34441.xml">
zygote</link> and contain the same genetic material (with a few exceptions). However, they are capable of recording a history of their development within the organism leading to their specialized functions and limitations. Cells often employ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/49033.xml">
epigenetic</link> processes that affect DNA-protein interactions to record this <it>cellular memory</it> in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/20369.xml">
mitotically</link> stable changes of the genetic material without a change in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/7955.xml">
DNA</link> sequence itself. This is typically achieved via changes of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/6933.xml">
chromatin</link> structure.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Examples are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/89188.xml">
methylation</link> patterns of the DNA molecule itself and proteins involved in packaging DNA, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/14029.xml">
histone</link>s (also referred to as "histone code").<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
In animals</st>
<p>

A case of somatic genetic memory is the <it>immunological memory</it> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../060/1664060.xml">
adaptive immune response</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../856/36856.xml">
vertebrate</link>s. The immune system is capable of learning to recognize pathogens and keeping a memory of this learning process, which is the basis of the success of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/32473.xml">
vaccination</link>s. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/24th_century.xml">
Antibody</link> genes in B and T <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/298999.xml">
lymphocyte</link>s are assembled from separate gene segments, giving each lymphocyte a unique antibody coding sequence leading to the vast diversity of antibodies in the immune system. If stimulated by an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/1915.xml">
antigen</link> (e.g. following vaccination or an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/37220.xml">
infection</link> with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../358/24358.xml">
pathogen</link>), these antibodies are further fine-tuned via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../498/3113498.xml">
hypermutation</link>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/1144202.xml">
Memory B cell</link>s capable of producing these antibodies form the basis for acquired immunological memory.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Each individual therefore carries a unique genetic memory of its immune system's close encounters with pathogens. As a somatic memory, this is not passed on to the next generation.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
In plants</st>
<p>

Plants that undergo <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/151965.xml">
vernalization</link> (promotion of flowering by a prolonged exposure to cold temperatures) record a <it>genetic memory of winter</it> to gain the competence to flower. The process involves epigenetically recording the length of cold exposure through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/4292885.xml">
chromatin remodeling</link> which leads to mitotically stable changes in gene expression (the "winter code").<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> This releases the inhibition of flowering initiation and allows the plants to bloom with the correct timing at the onset of spring. As a somatic memory, this state is not passed on to subsequent generations but has to be acquired by each individual plant. The process of vernalization was falsely assumed to be a stably inherited genetic memory passed on to subsequent generations by the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/25391.xml">
Russia</link></country>
n geneticist <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/49185.xml">
Trofim Lysenko</link></scientist>
. Lysenko's claims of genetic memory and efforts to obtain or fabricate results in proof of it had disastrous effects for Russian genetics in the early 20th century (also see: <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../331/435331.xml">
Lysenkoism</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Inherited epigenetic memory</st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/12266.xml">
genetics</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/15235.xml">
genomic imprinting</link> or other patterns of inheritance that are not determined by DNA sequence alone can form an epigenetic memory that is passed on to subsequent generations through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../976/18976.xml">
meiosis</link>. In contrast, somatic genetic memories are passed on by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/20369.xml">
mitosis</link> and limited to the individual, but are not passed on to the offspring. Both processes include similar epigenetic mechanisms, e.g. involving histones and methylation patterns.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Microbial memory</st>
<p>

In microbes, genetic memory is present in the form of inversion of specific DNA sequences serving as a switch between alternative patterns of gene expression.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Evolution</st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/219268.xml">
population genetics</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/9236.xml">
evolution</link>, genetic memory represents the recorded history of adaptive changes in a species. Selection of organisms carrying genes coding for the best adapted proteins results in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/9236.xml">
evolution</link> of species. An example for such a genetic memory is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/3113497.xml">
innate immune response</link> that represents a recording of the history of common microbial and viral pathogens encountered throughout the evolutionary history of the species.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> In contrast to the somatic memory of the adaptive immune response, the innate immune response is present at birth and does not require the immune system to learn to recognize antigens.</p>
<p>

In the history of theories of evolution, the proposed genetic memory of an individual's experiences and environmental influences was a central part of <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../588/187588.xml">
Lamarckism</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
 to explain the inheritance of evolutionary changes.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Animal behavior</st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/9425.xml">
ethology</link>, genetic memory refers the inheritance of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/288316.xml">
instinct</link> in animals and humans.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Psychology</st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
psychology</link>, genetic memory is a memory present at birth that exists in the absence of sensory experience, and is incorporated into the genome over long spans of time.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>. It is based on the idea that common experiences of a species become incorporated into its genetic code, not by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../588/187588.xml">
Lamarckian</link> process that encodes specific memories but by a much vaguer tendency to encode a readiness to respond in certain ways to certain stimuli. It is invoked to explain the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/489089.xml">
racial memory</link> postulated by <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../031/42031.xml">
Carl Jung</link></scientist>
</person>
, and differentiated from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/8950930.xml">
cultural memory</link>, which is the retention of habits, customs, myths, and artifacts of social groups.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> The latter postdates genetic memory in the evolution of the human species, only coming into being with the development of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/17524.xml">
language</link>, and thus the possibility of the transmission of experience.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>

<ss1>
<st>
Genetic memory and language</st>
<p>

Language, in the modern view, is considered to be only a partial product of genetic memory. The fact that humans can have languages is a property of the nervous system that is present at birth, and thus phylogenetic in character. However, perception of the particular set of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../980/22980.xml">
phoneme</link>s specific to a native language only develops during <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/22469.xml">
ontogeny</link>. There is no genetic predisposition towards the phonemic makeup of any single language. Children in a particular country are not genetically predisposed to speak the languages of that country, adding further weight to the assertion that genetic memory is not Lamarckian.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Historical views</st>
<p>

In contrast to the modern view, in the 19th century biologists considered genetic memory to be a fusion of memory and heredity, and held it to be a Lamarckian mechanism. Ribot in 1881, for example, held that psychological and genetic memory were based upon a common mechanism, and that the former only differed from the latter in that it interacted with consciousness.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref>  Hering and <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<zoologist wordnetid="110806222" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/3255748.xml">
Semon</link></zoologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</biologist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 developed general theories of memory, the latter inventing the idea of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/727809.xml">
engram</link> and concomitant processes of <it>engraphy</it> and <it>ecphory</it>.  Semon divided memory into genetic memory and central nervous memory.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref></p>
<p>

This 19th century view is not wholly dead, albeit that it stands in stark contrast to the ideas of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../050/43050.xml">
neo-Darwinism</link>. Stuart Newman and Gerd B. Müller have contributed to the idea in the 21st century.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Parapsychology</st>
<p>

Some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/23754.xml">
parapsychologist</link>s have postulated that specific experience is encoded in genes, and proposed this as an explanation for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/2253499.xml">
past life regression</link>. However, parapsychologists generally dismiss this, on grounds that in those cases where past life regression has been considered, the subjects have no genetic link with the people whose lives they are considered to have regressed to; and that the idea is unsound as a mechanism for explaining how events could be recalled from past lives of people at points in those lives <it>after</it> they had had children. Parapsychologists generally agree with the biological view that genetic traits are dispositional &mdash; i.e that they merely encode a disposition to react in certain ways to environmental stimuli, and not actual memory or experience.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Computer science</st>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/5323.xml">
computer science</link>, genetic memory refers to an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/21523.xml">
artificial neural network</link> combination of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/40254.xml">
genetic algorithm</link> and the mathematical model of <link>
sparse distributed memory</link>. It can be used to predict weather patterns.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> Genetic memory and genetic algorithms have also gained an interest in the creation of artificial life.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<subject wordnetid="106599788" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/9554411.xml">
Genetic memory in fiction</link></subject>
</message>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Nirenberg M&#32;(1968).&#32;"Genetic memory". <it>JAMA</it>&#32;<b>206</b>&#32;(9): 1973–7. PMID 4880506.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../368/762368.xml">
Marshall Nirenberg</link> (1968): "The genetic code". <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1968/nirenberg-lecture.pdf">
Nobel Lecture</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hirose S&#32;(2007).&#32;"Crucial roles for chromatin dynamics in cellular memory". <it>J. Biochem.</it>&#32;<b>141</b>&#32;(5): 615–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fjb%2Fmvm092">
10.1093/jb/mvm092</weblink>. PMID 17416595.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Bird A&#32;(2002).&#32;"DNA methylation patterns and epigenetic memory". <it>Genes Dev.</it>&#32;<b>16</b>&#32;(1): 6–21. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101%2Fgad.947102">
10.1101/gad.947102</weblink>. PMID 11782440.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Turner BM&#32;(2002).&#32;"Cellular memory and the histone code". <it>Cell</it>&#32;<b>111</b>&#32;(3): 285–91. PMID 12419240.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Crotty S, Ahmed R&#32;(2004).&#32;"Immunological memory in humans". <it>Semin. Immunol.</it>&#32;<b>16</b>&#32;(3): 197–203. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.smim.2004.02.008">
10.1016/j.smim.2004.02.008</weblink>. PMID 15130504.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Sung S, Amasino RM&#32;(2006).&#32;"Molecular genetic studies of the memory of winter". <it>J. Exp. Bot.</it>&#32;<b>57</b>&#32;(13): 3369–77. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093%2Fjxb%2Ferl105">
10.1093/jxb/erl105</weblink>. PMID 16980591.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Amasino R&#32;(2004).&#32;"Vernalization, competence, and the epigenetic memory of winter". <it>Plant Cell</it>&#32;<b>16</b>&#32;(10): 2553–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105%2Ftpc.104.161070">
10.1105/tpc.104.161070</weblink>. PMID 15466409.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ooi SL, Henikoff S&#32;(2007).&#32;"Germline histone dynamics and epigenetics". <it>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</it>&#32;<b>19</b>&#32;(3): 257–65. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.ceb.2007.04.015">
10.1016/j.ceb.2007.04.015</weblink>. PMID 17467256.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gehring M, Henikoff S&#32;(2007).&#32;"DNA methylation dynamics in plant genomes". <it>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</it>&#32;<b>1769</b>&#32;(5-6): 276–86. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.bbaexp.2007.01.009">
10.1016/j.bbaexp.2007.01.009</weblink>. PMID 17341434.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Casadesús J, D'Ari R&#32;(2002).&#32;"Memory in bacteria and phage". <it>Bioessays</it>&#32;<b>24</b>&#32;(6): 512–8. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2Fbies.10102">
10.1002/bies.10102</weblink>. PMID 12111734.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Dempsey PW, Vaidya SA, Cheng G&#32;(2003).&#32;"The art of war: Innate and adaptive immune responses". <it>Cell. Mol. Life Sci.</it>&#32;<b>60</b>&#32;(12): 2604–21. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs00018-003-3180-y">
10.1007/s00018-003-3180-y</weblink>. PMID 14685686.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Rodolfo R. Llinas&#32;(2001). I of the Vortex: From Neurons to Self.&#32;MIT Press,&#32;190&ndash;191. ISBN 0262621630.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Allan Paivio&#32;(2006). Mind And Its Evolution: A Dual Coding Theoretical Approach.&#32;Routledge,&#32;240. ISBN 0805852603.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Mihai Nadin&#32;(1997). The Civilization of Illiteracy.&#32;Dresden University Press,&#32;103&ndash;104. ISBN 3931828387.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Timothy L. Strickler&#32;(1978). Functional Osteology and Myology of the Shoulder in the Chiroptera.&#32;Karger Publishers,&#32;325. ISBN 3805526458.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Louis D. Matzel&#32;(2002).&#32;"Learning Mutants",&#32;in Harold E. Pashler: Steven's Handbook of Experimental Psychology.&#32;John Wiley and Sons,&#32;201. ISBN 0471650161.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="19">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Robert F. Almeder&#32;(1992). Death and Personal Survival: The Evidence for Life After Death.&#32;Rowman &amp; Littlefield,&#32;28&ndash;29. ISBN 0822630168.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Brian Keith Hall, Roy Douglas Pearson, and Gerd B. Müller&#32;(2003). Environment, Development, and Evolution: Toward a Synthesis.&#32;MIT Press,&#32;17. ISBN 0262083191.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="21">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">John Donnelly&#32;(1994). Language, Metaphysics, and Death.&#32;Fordham Univ Press,&#32;356. ISBN 0823215628.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Susan J. Blackmore&#32;(1999). The Meme Machine.&#32;Oxford University Press,&#32;60. ISBN 019286212X.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="23">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Rocha LM, Hordijk W&#32;(2005).&#32;"Material representations: From the genetic code to the evolution of cellular automata". <it>Artificial Life</it>&#32;<b>11</b>: 189–214.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="22">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Rogers, David (ed. Touretzky, David S.)&#32;(1989). Advances in neural information processing systems: Weather prediction using a genetic memory.&#32;Los Altos, Calif:&#32;M. Kaufmann Publishers,&#32;455-464. ISBN 1-55860-100-7.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>

</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Further reading </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Alan Bullock and Oliver Stallybrass&#32;(1977).&#32;"Genetic memory".&#32;<it>The Harper Dictionary of Modern Thought</it>.&#32;&#32;Harper &amp; Row.&#32;258.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite style="font-style:normal">Raymond Joseph Corsini&#32;(1999).&#32;"Genetic memory".&#32;<it>The Dictionary of Psychology</it>.&#32;&#32;Psychology Press.&#32;410.&#32;ISBN 158391028X.</cite>&nbsp; &mdash; Note that the definition talks of "information based upon" learning and experience, rather than about learning and experience themselves.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
