<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:57:11[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>STRIDE (protein)</title>
<id>9660855</id>
<revision>
<id>110246329</id>
<timestamp>2007-02-23T04:18:41Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Opabinia regalis</username>
<id>1409745</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Protein structure</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../126/969126.xml">
protein structure</link>, <b>STRIDE</b> (<b>Str</b>uctural <b>ide</b>ntification) is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link> for the assignment of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/23634.xml">
protein</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/28691.xml">
secondary structure</link> elements given the atomic coordinates of the protein, as defined by <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/34151.xml">
X-ray crystallography</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/3654507.xml">
protein NMR</link>, or another protein structure determination method. In addition to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/13609.xml">
hydrogen bond</link> criteria used by the more common <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/8921202.xml">
DSSP</link> algorithm, the STRIDE assignment criteria also include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../046/338046.xml">
dihedral angle</link> potentials. As such, its criteria for defining individual secondary structures are more complex than those of DSSP. The STRIDE <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/582529.xml">
energy function</link> contains a hydrogen-bond term containing a <power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<influence wordnetid="105194151" confidence="0.8">
<force wordnetid="105194578" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/227686.xml">
Lennard-Jones-like</link></force>
</influence>
</power>
 8-6 distance-dependent potential and two angular dependence factors reflecting the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/12984700.xml">
planar</link>ity of the optimized hydrogen bond geometry. The criteria for individual secondary structural elements, which are divided into the same groups as those reported by DSSP, also contain statistical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../934/22934.xml">
probability</link> factors derived from empirical examinations of solved structures with visually assigned secondary structure elements extracted from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/102505.xml">
Protein Data Bank</link>.<p>

Although DSSP is the older method and continues to be the most commonly used, the original STRIDE definition reported it to give a more satisfactory structural assignment in at least 70% of cases. In particular, STRIDE was observed to correct for the propensity of DSSP to assign shorter secondary structures than would be assigned by an expert crystallographer, usually due to the minor local variations in structure that are most common near the termini of secondary structure elements.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Using a sliding-window method to smooth variations in assignment of single terminal residues, current implementations of STRIDE and DSSP are reported to agree in up to 95.4% of cases.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Both STRIDE and DSSP, among other common secondary structure assignment methods, are believed to underpredict <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/5198607.xml">
pi helices</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> </p>

<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Frishman D, Argos P. (1995). Knowledge-based protein secondary structure assignment. <it>Proteins</it> 23(4):566-79. PMID 8749853 </entry>
<entry id="2">
Martin J,   * Letellier G,  Marin A, Taly JF, de Brevern AG, Gibrat JF. (2005). Protein secondary structure assignment revisited: a detailed analysis of different assignment methods. <it>BMC Struct Biol</it> 5:17. PMID 16164759 </entry>
<entry id="3">
Fodje MN, Al-Karadaghi S. (2002). Occurrence, conformational features and amino acid propensities for the pi-helix. <it>Protein Eng</it> 15(5):353-8. PMID 12034854 </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://webclu.bio.wzw.tum.de/stride/">
STRIDE</weblink> - includes web interface, a print of the original STRIDE paper, and software documentation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/32/suppl_2/W500">
Paper on the original webserver implementation</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
