<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:55:32[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Mid-air retrieval</title>
<id>974604</id>
<revision>
<id>224078952</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-07T05:39:35Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Aviation terminology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Genesis_retrieval.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A helicopter with a long hook can catch a parachuting object in mid-air, as seen here in a practice run for the planned retrieval of Genesis.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Mid-air retrieval</b> is a technique used in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/45294.xml">
atmospheric reentry</link> when the reentering vehicle is incapable of a satisfactory unassisted landing. The vehicle is slowed by means of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/48339.xml">
parachute</link>s, and then a specially-equipped <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/849.xml">
aircraft</link> matches the vehicle's trajectory and catches it in mid-air.</p>
<p>

This is a risky technique, and so is only used when other forms of landing are infeasible. Successful mid-air retrieval requires correct operation of the retrieving aircraft, favourable atmospheric conditions, and successful execution of a tricky manoeuvre, in addition to correct operation of the vehicle itself.  Complicating matters, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../923/8286923.xml">
helicopter</link>s, which are the optimal aircraft for these operations due to their maneuverability, are particularly prone to mechanical breakdown. These risks can be mitigated somewhat: for example, multiple recovery aircraft can be used. The need for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../482/682482.xml">
human</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/66691.xml">
aviator</link>s to perform a manoeuvre which would normally be classed as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../087/212087.xml">
stunt</link> may in the future be avoided by advances in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/58900.xml">
unmanned aerial vehicle</link>s.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Uses </st>
<p>

The first successful mission use of mid-air recovery was on <link>
1960-08-19</link> when a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/1371521.xml">
C-119</link> recovered film from the Corona mission code-named <satellite wordnetid="104137444" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<equipment wordnetid="103294048" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../016/17868016.xml">
Discoverer 14</link></equipment>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</satellite>
. This was the first successful recovery of film from an orbiting satellite and the first aerial recovery of an object returning from Earth orbit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

Notable uses of the technique:</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The early-1960s era <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/191323.xml">
Corona</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</undertaking>
</event>
</work>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/53366.xml">
reconnaissance satellite</link> returned delicate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/47534.xml">
film</link> capsules to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/9228.xml">
Earth</link> that required mid-air retrieval by a <link>
JC-130 Hercules &amp; HC-130</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/3892712.xml">
airlift</link>er. These aircraft were manned by a crew of 10 personnel. Two pilots, one flight engineer Two telemetry operators, one winch operator and four riggers. The telemetry operators would acquire the location of the satellite and relay the info to the pilots. Once visually acquired the pilots would head on course to the satellite decending towards the pacific ocean. One could visually acquire the satellite and its parachute at an altitude of approximately 50,000 ft. The winch operator and the riggers would deploy the retrieving apparatus called the "Loop", which consisted of high quality nylon rope with a series of brass hooks spliced into the apparatus. The whole snatching operation by the pilots was done visually. The winch operator and the four riggers would deploy the loop. As the aircraft flew over the parachute you would feel a little uplifting of the aircraft. Once contact was made between the parachute and the loop the winch line would pay out and stop. The winch then was put into gear and the retrevial process commenced. Once on board, the aircraft flew back to Hickam Air Force Base, where they were stationed and offload the satellite or the canister onto a truck and then loaded immediately onto a running C-141 airlifter and then transported to a location, in Maryland, for analysis. The crews acquired these skills by practicing almost daily on practice missions, carried out with other aircraft dropping dummy bombs with chutes attached. The weights were 200 lb. in the early 70s and later to the conical parachute system which weighed in at 1,100 lb. To say the least, there were some very interesting activities that happened during practice. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The <accident wordnetid="107301336" confidence="0.8">
<happening wordnetid="107283608" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<probe wordnetid="105800611" confidence="0.8">
<process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<trouble wordnetid="107289014" confidence="0.8">
<mishap wordnetid="107314427" confidence="0.8">
<misfortune wordnetid="107304852" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<mission wordnetid="108403225" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<nongovernmental_organization wordnetid="108009834" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../407/187407.xml">
Genesis</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</psychological_feature>
</nongovernmental_organization>
</event>
</mission>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</misfortune>
</mishap>
</trouble>
</process>
</probe>
</problem_solving>
</happening>
</accident>
 mission returned a sample of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/28538.xml">
solar wind</link> that was so delicate that it would have been damaged by a parachute landing, so a mid-air retrieval using helicopters flown by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../849/53849.xml">
Hollywood</link> stunt pilots contracted by NASA was planned. Its parachutes failed to deploy, so mid-air retrieval was impossible and the capsule crashed.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

An early design for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/407982.xml">
SpaceShipOne</link> called for a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/27676.xml">
shuttlecock</link>-like shape that would have made it incapable of landing independently, necessitating mid-air retrieval. This was deemed too risky, and the final design made the spacecraft capable of independent horizontal landing while cleverly retaining the desired <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../819/2819.xml">
aerodynamic</link> qualities for the early part of reentry.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nssdc.gsfc.nasa.gov/nmc/spacecraftDisplay.do?id=1960-010A">
Discoverer 14 - NSSDC ID: 1960-010A</weblink>".&#32;  NASA.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
