<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:56:31[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<model  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110324560">
<assistant  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109815790">
<worker  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109632518">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<header>
<title>Agent-based model</title>
<id>985619</id>
<revision>
<id>241095322</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-26T10:05:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Scientific modeling</category>
<category>Computational models</category>
<category>Complex systems theory</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

An <b>agent-based model (ABM)</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/2815048.xml">
computational model</link> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/375416.xml">
simulating</link> the actions and interactions of autonomous individuals in a network, with a view to assessing their effects on the system as a whole. It combines elements of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/11924.xml">
game theory</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/62903.xml">
complex systems</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/37436.xml">
emergence</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/984692.xml">
computational sociology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/938833.xml">
multi agent systems</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/460689.xml">
evolutionary programming</link>. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../098/56098.xml">
Monte Carlo Method</link>s are used to introduce randomness.<p>

The models simulate the simultaneous operations of multiple agents, in an attempt to re-create and predict the actions of complex phenomena. The process is one of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/37436.xml">
emergence</link> from the lower (micro) level of systems to a higher (macro) level. The individual agents are presumed to be acting in what they perceive as their own interests, such as reproduction, economic benefit, or social status, and their knowledge is limited.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> ABM agents may experience "learning", adaptation, and reproduction.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

The idea of agent-based modeling was developed as a relatively simple concept in the late 1940s. Since it requires computation-intensive procedures, it did not become widespread until the 1990s.</p>
<p>

The history of the agent-based model can be traced back to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/500163.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Von+Neumann+probes%22])">
Von Neumann machine</link>, a theoretical machine capable of reproduction. The device <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/15942.xml">
von Neumann</link> proposed would follow precisely detailed instructions to fashion a copy of itself. The concept was then improved by von Neumann's friend <link>
Stanisław Ulam</link>, also a mathematician; Ulam suggested that the machine be built on paper, as a collection of cells on a grid. The idea intrigued von Neumann, who drew it up&mdash;creating the first of the devices later termed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../342/54342.xml">
cellular automata</link>. </p>
<p>

Another improvement was introduced by the mathematician <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/15807.xml">
John Conway</link></scientist>
</person>
. He constructed the well-known <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="105846054" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/37035.xml">
Game of Life</link></rule>
</concept>
</idea>
. Unlike  von Neumann's machine, Conway's Game of Life operated by tremendously simple rules in a virtual world in the form of a 2-dimensional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/381609.xml">
checkerboard</link>. </p>
<p>

The creation of agent-based models of social systems is often credited to the computer scientist <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/449965.xml">
Craig Reynolds</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
. He tried to model the reality of lively biological agents, known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/58656.xml">
artificial life</link>, a term coined by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../550/1122550.xml">
Christopher Langton</link></research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
. </p>
<p>

At the same time, during the 1980s, social scientists, mathematicians, operations researchers, and a scattering of people from other disciplines developed Computational and Mathematical Organization Theory (CMOT).  This field grew as a special interest group of The Institute of Management Sciences (TIMS) and its sister society, the Operations Research Society of America (ORSA).  Through the mid-1990s, the field focused on such issues as designing effective teams, understanding the communication required for organizational effectiveness, and the behavior of social networks.  With the appearance of SWARM in the mid-1990s and RePast in 2000, as well as some custom-designed code, CMOT -- later renamed Computational Analysis of Social and Organizational Systems (CASOS) -- incorporated more and more agent-based modeling.  Samuelson (2000) is a good brief overview of the early history, and Samuelson (2005) and Samuelson and Macal (2006) trace the more recent developments.  Bonabeau (2002) is a good survey of the potential of agent-based modeling as of the time that its modelling software became widely available.</p>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/people/faculty.php?detail=Carley,%20Kathleen%20M.&amp;ID=42">
Kathleen M. Carley</weblink> developed the first ABM, <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/projects/construct/index.php">
Construct</weblink> , to explore the co-evolution of social networks and culture.</p>
<p>

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<alumnus wordnetid="109786338" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../727/12547727.xml">
Joshua M. Epstein</link></scholar>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</alumnus>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 and Robert Axtell developed the first large-scale ABM, the <link>
Sugarscape</link>, to simulate and explore the role of social phenomenon such as seasonal migrations, pollution, sexual reproduction, combat, and transmission of disease and even culture.</p>
<p>

In the late 1990s, the merger of TIMS and ORSA to form INFORMS, and the move by INFORMS from two meetings each year to one, helped to spur the CMOT group to form a separate society, the North American Association for Computational Social and Organizational Sciences (NAACSOS).  <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/17363635.xml">
Kathleen Carley</link></scientist>
, of <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/48093.xml">
Carnegie Mellon University</link></university>
, was a major contributor, especially to models of social networks, obtaining <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/157427.xml">
National Science Foundation</link></agency>
 funding for the annual conference and serving as the first President of NAACSOS.  She was succeeded by David Sallach of the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/32127.xml">
University of Chicago</link></university>
 and <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/160773.xml">
Argonne National Laboratory</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</region>
</site>
, and then by Michael Prietula of <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/42730.xml">
Emory University</link></university>
.  At about the same time NAACSOS began, the European Social Simulation Association (ESSA) and the Pacific Asian Association for Agent-Based Approach in Social Systems Science (PAAA), counterparts of NAACSOS, were organized.  These organizations now collaborate internationally.  The First World Congress on Social Simulation was held under their joint sponsorship in Kyoto, Japan, in August 2006. The Second World Congress is scheduled to be held in the northern Virginia suburbs of Washington, D.C.,  in July 2008, with <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/12566.xml">
George Mason University</link></university>
 taking the lead role in local arrangements.</p>
<p>

More recently, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/17651946.xml">
Ron Sun</link></psychologist>
</research_worker>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 developed methods for basing agentbased simulation on models of human cognition, known as <link>
cognitive social simulation</link> (see Sun 2006).  Bill McKelvey, Suzanne Lohmann, Dario Nardi and others at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../765/37765.xml">
UCLA</link> have also made significant contributions in organizational behavior and decision-making.  Since 2001, UCLA has arranged a biennial conference at Lake Arrowhead, California, that has become another major gathering point for practitioners in this field.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Theory</st>
<p>

Most computational modeling research describes systems in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/1326107.xml">
equilibrium</link> or as moving between equilibria. Agent-based modeling, however, using simple rules, can result in far more complex and interesting behavior.</p>
<p>

The three ideas central to agent-based models are social agents as objects, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/37436.xml">
emergence</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/7363.xml">
complexity</link>.</p>
<p>

Agent-based models consist of dynamically interacting rule based agents. The systems within which they interact can create real world-like complexity.  
These agents are:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Intelligent and purposeful, but not so intelligent as to reach the cognitive closure implied by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../924/11924.xml">
game theory</link>. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/3479720.xml">
Situated</link> in space and time. They reside in networks and in lattice-like neighborhoods.  The location of the agents and their responsive and purposeful behavior are encoded in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/775.xml">
algorithm</link>ic form in computer programs. The modeling process is best described as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/14877.xml">
inductive</link>.  The modeler makes those assumptions thought most relevant to the situation at hand and  then watches phenomena emerge from the agents' interactions. Sometimes that result is an equilibrium.  Sometimes it is an emergent pattern.  Sometimes, however, it is an unintelligible mangle. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In some ways, agent-based models complement traditional analytic methods. Where analytic methods enable humans to characterize the equilibria of a system, agent-based models allow the possibility of generating those equilibria. This generative contribution may be the most mainstream of  the potential benefits of agent-based modeling.  Agent-based models can explain the emergence of higher order patterns -- network structures of terrorist organizations and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/14539.xml">
Internet</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/24522.xml">
power law distributions</link> in the sizes of traffic jams, wars, and stock market crashes, and social segregation that persists despite populations of tolerant people. Agent-based models also can be used to identify lever points, defined as moments in time in which interventions have extreme consequences, and to distinguish among types of path dependency.</p>
<p>

Rather than focusing on stable states, the models consider a system's robustness --  the ways that complex systems adapt to internal and external pressures so as to maintain their functionalities. The task of harnessing that complexity requires consideration of the agents themselves -- their diversity, connectedness, and level of interactions.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications</st>
<p>

Agent-based models have been used since the mid-1990s to solve a variety of business and technology problems. Examples of applications include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/5205119.xml">
supply chain optimization</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/77547.xml">
logistics</link>, modeling of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/754957.xml">
consumer behavior</link>, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../029/242029.xml">
word of mouth</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../726/325726.xml">
social network</link> effects, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/8501.xml">
distributed computing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/2840555.xml">
workforce management</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../105/2851105.xml">
portfolio management</link>. They have also been used to analyze <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/234226.xml">
traffic congestion</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> In these and other applications, the system of interest is simulated by capturing the behavior of individual agents and their interconnections. Agent-based modeling tools can be used to test how changes in individual behaviors will affect the system's emerging overall behavior.</p>
<p>

Other models have analyzed the spread of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/66981.xml">
epidemics</link>, the threat of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/4361.xml">
biowarfare</link>, the growth and decline of ancient civilizations, and biomedical applications including inflammation and the human <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/14958.xml">
immune system</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Methods</st>
<p>

A simple and accessible program for creating agent-based models is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/593757.xml">
NetLogo</link>. NetLogo was originally designed for educational purposes but now numbers many thousands of research users as well. Many colleges have used this as a tool to teach their students about agent-based modeling. A similar program, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../828/746828.xml">
StarLogo</link>, has also been released with similar functionality. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.swarm.org">
Swarm</weblink> was one of the first general purpose ABM systems. Swarm, developed by the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../471/13674471.xml">
Swarm Development Group</link></association>
</institute>
, uses the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../802/22802.xml">
Objective C</link> programming language, and is recommended for C programmers with little object-oriented programming experience. Swarm can also be implemented by <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/15881.xml">
Java</link></request>
</message>
 programmers, as can <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brook.edu/es/dynamics/models/ascape/">
Ascape</weblink>. Both <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cs.gmu.edu/~eclab/projects/mason/">
MASON</weblink> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/3867229.xml">
Repast</link> are widely used, and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ecolab.sourceforge.net">
EcoLab</weblink> is suitable for <programming_language wordnetid="106898352" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/72038.xml">
C++</link></programming_language>
 programmers. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cormas.cirad.fr">
Cormas</weblink> is another platform, focusing on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../675/21675.xml">
natural resources</link> management, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/8417961.xml">
rural development</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../630/9630.xml">
ecology</link> research, based on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../319/28319.xml">
SmallTalk</link> language. All the toolkits described previously are based on serial von-Neumann computer architectures. This limits the speed and scalability of these systems. A recent development is the use of data-parallel algorithms on Graphics Processing Units <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/390214.xml">
GPU</link>s for ABM simulation <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rudomin.cem.itesm.mx/~rudomin/shader-agents.htm">
http://rudomin.cem.itesm.mx/~rudomin/shader-agents.htm</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.me.mtu.edu/~rmdsouza/ABM_GPU.html">
http://www.me.mtu.edu/~rmdsouza/ABM_GPU.html</weblink>. The extreme memory bandwidth combined with the sheer number crunching power of multi-processor GPUs has enabled simulation of millions of agents at tens of frames per second.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<ss1>
<st>
In-line</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://policy.rutgers.edu/andrews/projects/abm/abmarticle.htm">
Agent-Based Models of Industrial Ecosystems</weblink>. <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/80135.xml">
Rutgers University</link></university>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/22542.xml">
October 6</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../163/36163.xml">
2003</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/cgi/content/full/99/suppl_3/7280">
Agent-based modeling: Methods and techniques for simulating human systems</weblink>. Proceedings of the <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<academy wordnetid="108279298" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../510/46510.xml">
National Academy of Sciences</link></academy>
</geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</region>
</site>
. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../676/19676.xml">
May 14</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/35502.xml">
2002</link>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.tfhrc.gov/advanc/agent.htm">
Application of Agent Technology to Traffic Simulation</weblink>. <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/58235.xml">
United States Department of Transportation</link></agency>
, May 15, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informs-sim.org/wsc06papers/008.pdf">
Tutorial on agent-based modeling and simulation part 2: how to model with agents</weblink>. Association for Computing Machinery, Winter Simulation Conference, 2006.</entry>
</reflist>

</p>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
General</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Axelrod, Robert, The Complexity of Cooperation: Agent-Based Models of Competition and Collaboration, Princeton University Press: Princeton, N.J., 1997.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bonabeau, Eric, Agent-based modeling: methods and techniques for simulating human systems. Proc. National Academy of Sciences 99(3): 7280-7287, 2002.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Carley, Kathleen M., Smart Agents and Organizations of the Future. In Handbook of New Media, edited by Leah Lievrouw &amp; Sonia Livingstone, Ch. 12 pp. 206-220, Thousand Oaks, CA, Sage. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/publications/Abstracts_All/SmartAgents_abstract.html">
http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/publications/Abstracts_All/SmartAgents_abstract.html</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Epstein, Joshua M. and Robert Axtell, Growing Artificial Societies: Social Science From the Bottom Up. MIT Press/Brookings Institution, 1996.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0262050536">
http://www.amazon.com/dp/0262050536</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Gilbert, Nigel, and Klaus Troitzsch, Simulation for the Social Scientist,  Open University Press, 1999; second edition, 2005.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Grimm, Volker, and Steven F. Railsback, Individual-based Modeling and Ecology, Princeton University Press, 2005.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Holland, John H., "Genetic Algorithms," Scientific American, 267:66-72, 1992. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Holland, John H., Hidden Order: How Adaptation Builds Complexity, Addison-Wesley:Reading, Mass., 1995.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 O'sullivan,D. and Haklay, M.Agent-based models and individualism: Is the world agent-based? Environment and Planning A32:1409-25,2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  Rudomin, B. Hernandez, E. Millan, Fragment shaders for agent animation using finite state machines, In Simulation Modelling Practice and Theory Journal, Volume 13, Issue 8 , Programmable Graphics Hardware November 2005, Pages 741-751 Elsevier, </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sallach, David, and Charles Macal, The simulation of social agents: an introduction, Special Issue of Social Science Computer Review 19(3):245–248, 2001.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Samuelson, Douglas A., “Designing Organizations,” OR/MS Today, December 2000.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Samuelson, Douglas A., “Agents of Change,” OR/MS Today, February 2005.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Samuelson, Douglas A. and Charles M. Macal, “Agent-Based Modeling Comes of Age,” OR/MS Today, August 2006.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sun, Ron, Cognition and Multi-Agent Interaction: From Cognitive Modeling to Social Simulation. Cambridge University Press, 2006.   http://www.cambridge.org/uk/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=0521839645</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Agent-based model development tools</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.altreva.com">
Adaptive Modeler</weblink> - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/16708680.xml">
Adaptive Modeler</link> creates agent-based models for price forecasting of financial markets.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.anylogic.com">
AnyLogic</weblink> - Modern and powerful simulation modeling tool, supports ABM + system dynamics + discrete event modeling</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ascape.sourceforge.net/">
ASCAPE</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.econ.iastate.edu/tesfatsi/acedemos.htm">
Computational Laboratories and Demonstration Software for Agent-Based Modeling</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cormas.cirad.fr/indexeng.htm">
Cormas</weblink> ABM platform dedicated to natural resources management, rural development and ecology</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.econ.iastate.edu/tesfatsi/acecode.htm">
General Software and Toolkits for Agent-Based Modeling</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.gmu.edu/~eclab/projects/mason/">
MASON</weblink> Fast discrete-event multiagent simulation library core in Java.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ccl.northwestern.edu/netlogo/">
NetLogo</weblink> Powerful ABM platform, excellent documentation and tutorials, easy to learn</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://repast.sourceforge.net/">
Repast</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.swarm.org/wiki/ABM_Resources#Software_Resources">
Swarm ABM Resources</weblink> - ABM modeling tools</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.teamseas.com">
System Effectiveness Analysis Simulation (SEAS)</weblink> - The US Air Force's Multi-Agent Theater Operations Simulation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.visualbots.com/index.htm">
VisualBots</weblink> - Multi-agent simulator in Microsoft Excel - Visual Basic syntax</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.me.mtu.edu/~rmdsouza/ABM_GPU.html">
GPU Agents</weblink> - Ultra-scalable, ultra-fast agent-based model simulator on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/390214.xml">
GPU</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/projects/construct/index.php">
Construct</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.icr.ethz.ch/research/growlab/">
GROWlab</weblink> - Freely available ABM toolkit of the International Conflict Research Group at the ETH Zurich</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../229/17974229.xml">
ABM Software Comparison</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://agent.cse.nd.edu/abmsearchengine.php">
ABM Search Engine</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/10941831.xml">
agent-based computational economics (ACE)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/58656.xml">
artificial life</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../636/985636.xml">
artificial society</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/404015.xml">
boids</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/37438.xml">
complex system</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/984692.xml">
computational sociology</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../898/5162898.xml">
dynamic network analysis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/37436.xml">
emergence</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/190837.xml">
evolutionary algorithm</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../021/90021.xml">
flocking</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<field wordnetid="108569998" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/1003441.xml">
Generative sciences</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</field>
</region>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/938833.xml">
Multi-agent system</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
simudyne</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/247365.xml">
simulated reality</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/984629.xml">
social complexity</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/387746.xml">
social simulation</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../106/430106.xml">
software agent</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<b>Articles/General Information</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.xjtek.com/file/142">
From System Dynamics and Discrete Event to Practical Agent-Based Modeling: Reasons, Techniques, Tools</weblink> Compares the three major methods in simulation modeling </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.econ.iastate.edu/tesfatsi/ace.htm">
Agents based computational economics</weblink> is the portal to the application of agents based models in computational economics and finance.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.teamseas.com">
System Effectiveness Analysis Simulation (SEAS)</weblink> - The US Air Force's Multi-Agent Theater Operations Simulation</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.coensys.com/agent_based_models.htm">
How to develop agent-based models using Anylogic</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.abmsystemsbiology.info">
Agent-Based Modeling for Systems Biology</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cmol.nbi.dk/models/">
Agent-based models of social networks, java applets.</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.econ.iastate.edu/tesfatsi/abmread.htm">
On-Line Guide for Newcomers to Agent-Based Modeling in the Social Sciences</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-unix.mcs.anl.gov/~leyffer/listn/slides-06/MacalNorth.pdf">
Introduction to Agent-based Modeling and Simulation</weblink>. <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.8">
<region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<tract wordnetid="108673395" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/160773.xml">
Argonne National Laboratory</link></geographical_area>
</tract>
</location>
</region>
</site>
, November 29, 2006.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 [http://www.abm-ecology.org Agent-based models in Ecology - Using computer models as theoretical tools to analyze complex ecological systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openabm.org/site/">
The Open Agent-Based Modeling Consortium</weblink> "To foster and improve the development, communication, and dissemination of agent-based models for research, practice, and education"</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.irisel.com/~jmgomez/IT/doctorate/taller_resumen2.htm">
Multiagent Information Systems</weblink> - Article on the convergence of SOA, BPM and Multi-Agent Technology in the domain of the Enterprise Information Systems. Jose Manuel Gomez Alvarez, Artificial Intelligence, Technical University of Madrid - 2006</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>People</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://socialcomplexity.gmu.edu/members.php">
Robert Axtell</weblink> - Dynamic modeling of social and economic systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brookings.edu/scholars/jepstein.htm">
Joshua M. Epstein</weblink> - Dynamic modeling of biological, social and economic systems</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://people.brandeis.edu/~blebaron">
Blake LeBaron</weblink> - leading researcher in the field of agents based models in finance. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.econ.iastate.edu/tesfatsi/">
Leigh Tesfatsion</weblink> - Agent-Based Computational Economics</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.humboldt.edu/~ecomodel/">
Steve Railsback</weblink> - Individual-/Agent-based Ecology</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/people/faculty.php?detail=Carley,%20Kathleen%20M.&amp;ID=42">
Kathleen Carley</weblink> - Dynamic Modeling of social and cultural systems, and social networks</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Organizations</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.santafe.edu">
Santa Fe Institute</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.swarm.org">
Swarm Development Group</weblink> ABM tools initially developed at Santa Fe Institute</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bandungfe.net">
The Web of Bandung Fe Institute</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ccl.northwestern.edu">
The Center for Connected Learning and Computer-Based Modeling</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.brookings.edu/es/dynamics/default.htm">
The Center on Social and Economic Dynamics at The Brookings Institution</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cscs.umich.edu/">
Center for the Study of Complex Systems at the University of Michigan</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://socialcomplexity.gmu.edu/">
The Social Complexity Center at George Mason University</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu">
Center for Computational Analysis of Social and Organizational Systems (CASOS) at Carnegie Mellon</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://csdc.asu.edu/">
Center for Social Dynamics &amp; Complexity (CSDC)</weblink> website, Arizona State University</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://csid.asu.edu/">
Center for the Study of Institutional Diversity (CSID)</weblink> website, Arizona State University</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Journals</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.springer.com/business/business+for+professionals/journal/10588">
Computational and Mathematical Organization Theory</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jasss.soc.surrey.ac.uk/JASSS.html">
Journal of Artificial Societies and Social Simulation</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Mailing Lists</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jiscmail.ac.uk/lists/simsoc.html">
SIMSOC</weblink> News and discussion about computer simulation in the social sciences</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</causal_agent>
</worker>
</assistant>
</model>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
